and gentlemen, and I welcome you to my GDC 2017 talk
about next level creature sound design.
And before I actually start, may I remind you
to just switch off your phones and maybe put them
into quiet mode or flight mode.
And I think we are ready to go.
So first of all, I want to give you an overview
about what I'm going to talk today.
So obviously it's about next level creature sound design.
And first of all, I'm going to give you an introduction
about myself, why am I kind of the right person
to talk about creature sound design in the first place.
I will give you some initial thoughts
about creature sound design,
because I've been doing this for about the last seven years.
I will also run you through pre-production,
the recording process, the design process,
and also briefly about implementation.
And yeah, so myself, my name's David Phillip,
and I'm a co-founder of Noiseworks Limited,
an audio outsourcing company in London.
And I'm also a Boom Library recordist and designer.
And I worked on a large amount of creature-heavy titles
in my past, so for example, Elder Scrolls Online,
most of you probably know.
Blade and Soul, which is an Asian game,
and Arcania is a German game,
again, a very creature-heavy title.
And over the last four years, or the last two years actually,
I was leading the Creature Sound Effects production
for Total War Warhammer, which I think many of you have played.
And it's, again, a very creature-heavy title.
And I'm very happy to share some insight out of that game
and out of the production with you tonight as well.
Right, so the initial thoughts, I
think that's quite important to ask yourself before you start
designing creature sounds.
So I think the first question I ask myself
is, what's my role as a creature sound designer?
And I think the best way to put it is to create sound for something alive,
where there's not really a reference in the real world,
so you can't just go out and have a look at what a creature sounds like.
That's pretty much impossible.
And that's a very creative process of making that make sense to the audience or the player.
The second question is, what makes a creature more difficult than other sound effects?
It's again a very difficult question in a way, but again, you know, there's no real life reference and that's definitely a tough aspect about the whole thing.
But we're also highly dependent on different layers, which, you know, they can be difficult to blend and, you know, we always have to aim for making a creature sound like one creature, not many at the same time.
And lastly, is there a difference between producing creatures for interactive and linear media?
I mean, obviously we're at GDC, so it's all about gaming, but
some of you might actually have to create creature sounds for FMVs or cutscenes and so on.
And I think the actual production, what we are going to focus on tonight, is actually not that different.
But we're going through that over the course of the next hour anyway.
So after these initial thoughts over the last few years,
I came up with, personally for me,
the three ingredients of great creature sound design,
like almost like a rule book for myself
to create the creature sound designs from.
So the first point, which always is very important for me,
is character.
So you probably ask yourself, what do you mean by character?
Because people come up to me, you know,
they give me feedback on a creature
and say they need much more character,
they don't have enough character.
And I, you know, initially I didn't really know
what they meant.
So character is about how does the creature act?
What's its characteristics, you know?
Is it aggressive?
Is it really stupid?
Is it highly intelligent?
And how do I perceive its emotions?
Or how does it react?
How does it make me feel as a player?
And that's everything on a vocal basis, obviously.
Then the next point, the next very important ingredient
is variation.
So firstly, variation in terms of your articulations.
So for example, attack sounds, death sounds,
pain sounds, idle sounds, all that.
But I think also variation in form of sounds we use.
So again, during the course of the next hour,
we're going to look at different recording techniques
to keep that variation always, you know,
to keep on top of that.
And then the last ingredient is perspective.
So, you know, quite a simple point really,
but it is really important to ask yourself,
where does the sound live in our game?
And in what space, you know, is it always indoors?
Is it outdoors?
Is it in a cave?
And so on.
Is it really close up or very far?
So do we have to, you know,
we have to take care of that as well.
And that all comes together in a term
which I think is very...
very important and I will use it, and I apologize in advance, I will use it a lot tonight, which is
believability. So that's our main aim as a creature sound designer, to make something
which I just mentioned before, which isn't real and which isn't in the real world, to make it
believable for the player and, you know, that results in immersion as well for the player.
So in the next video I'm going to show you a few examples of creature sounds which for me
stand for believability, they just work and they should get you pumped up for the next hour as
well. So let's have a listen to that.
So yeah, I don't know about you, but even the Godzilla roar
still gives me goosebumps actually,
just now it happened again.
So this is just a really good example
of believable creatures, you know,
that you can just feel the size,
you feel the aggression or the intelligence or whatever.
A lot of character and a lot of believability.
Right, so we can actually start on the actual process,
which we start with the pre-production.
And pre-production is actually
one of the most important aspects,
in my opinion, of creature sound design.
And I'm guilty myself of neglecting that process,
and because we always, as sound designers,
we kind of want to jump straight in there
and actually record a design.
So it is mostly overlooked and forgotten about,
but I do think it's very important,
because we always have to be aware of what we work on.
I talked about character before,
so that's one part, obviously,
but also what universe is it in,
and the characteristics and skills of the creatures
we're going to work on.
We also need to make ourselves aware of what material we want to use.
So creature sound designs, it stands and falls with the source we are using.
So we want to plan that as well.
One can't paint without colors, it's just, you know, we can't create great sounds without
great material in the first place.
And also I think at this point it's very important to mention that if you're freelance or with
a developer, it doesn't really matter.
Pre-production is always important.
Just that it probably is a bit easier to get the information you need when you're actually
employed by someone or in-house.
Let's look at the pre-production a bit of an advanced way
in terms of creature sound design.
So the first thing I would do is I would find out
the creature's origin, its special characteristics
and skills.
So I mentioned before, for example,
a creature can be highly intelligent,
it could be super stupid, it could be, you know,
Again, it could be very big, it could be very small,
and it could have special skills,
like for example, a dragon could have a fire breath.
I need to know about that.
And I need to search, look for the dialogue
between myself and the design team
to find out about the special characteristics
of a creature in the first place.
Then I want to know how does it produce sound in the first place.
Does it have a voice box?
Because I've dealt with creatures before who were actually ghostly and before actually
reading about this creature I wouldn't know how they would actually produce the sound.
And that's again something which dictates the way I'm working.
Is there a need for language?
that's a very uh tricky situation actually to be in and it happened to us in in Warhammer
because we are creatures who communicated with one another and that's you know I can't really
deal with that and with my attack sounds and my death sounds so that normally is very important
to know and would in our case would go to the dialogue team and they would deal with that
but again if you you know if you get to that information very late on in the process
you probably run out of time.
Size and their scale in relation to other creatures in game.
So this is also a very important one.
As you've seen before in the video,
you saw Khaleesi's dragon on her shoulder,
very small compared to Godzilla, which is obviously massive.
But if you just see a screenshot of the game,
you know, you see the dragon and you see Godzilla,
you probably wouldn't be able to tell the difference
between them in size.
And again, it's very important to check beforehand
because it's very difficult after you've created
a full set of creature sounds
to make the sounds very small or very big afterwards.
And all this will come together
and define the sonic character of your creatures.
And again, think about the three main ingredients,
characters, definitely one of the most important ones.
So if you, I hope you can see that.
I put like a few example notes together
of how I normally approach creature sound.
In this case, I called it random dragon.
You can see that on the top left there.
And for example, I put down,
I always do a little bit of a mind map.
So first of all, it's just for me,
but later on it's really useful to share this information
with my coworkers who might have to work on their creature
if it's not myself.
So in terms of the large dragon here,
the random dragon, sorry, it's a large size.
It's very aggressive, it's highly intelligent,
it's got a few skills like a fire breath,
a tail swing, and then...
Here's probably a good one, it's a mega scream which buffs my friendly units,
so I would already know that indicates that I would have to create that kind of scream later on as well.
And also put a note that it can attack from distance
with a fireball, so I probably have to think
from the very start about my distance as well
and what that brings to the table.
And then on the right here on the left page,
you can see how attack paints green
and how many variations I aim to do.
And that equals total amount of 42 sound effects
in this case, and this is a good indication.
I can put that on a timeline
and plan my time accordingly.
And on the right, I think that's a very, for myself, it's very important, is the potential
recordings I'm going to do, also the potential source I'm going to look at to just buy from
other libraries out there.
So, for example, I have the three types which we will hear later on more about, so humans,
animals, and non-literal recordings.
And when I think about a random dragon in this case,
I would think about, you know, I record myself
because I can do a crazy inward squeal,
which would be a great layer for this sound.
Or I can record Jack, who sounds like a pig, for example,
which can be very useful.
Then animals, I would, you know, look into pigs, horses,
donkeys, elephant, walrus, all that stuff,
which, you know, kind of has some kind of quality
I would look for in a dragon in this case.
And then also the non-literal stuff,
like dry, some metal, cellophane, door creaks.
Stuff which doesn't really necessarily have anything to do
with the dragon in the first place,
but I, because I've done this stuff before,
I can actually tell that might be really handy in the end
and add another bit of character to the creature.
Right, so we have, we just ran through
the pre-production aspect,
and we can finally look a bit into recording.
Obviously for, most of you will know
that different mics equals different results,
so I'm going to show you a few of the microphones
which I love using and which are really useful
for creature sound recording.
And I'm also going to talk about the literal approach of recording humans, which is, yeah,
very important.
Then we're also going to look into recording animals, and very importantly, we're going
to look at the non-literal approach, which is, in my opinion, the most interesting one.
So let's have a look at the microphones.
I'm going to show you a little bit of information and sound samples of the Sanken C100K, the
Sennheiser MKH series, and some contact mics as well.
So the Sankin C100K is, in my opinion, the most powerful weapon of a creature sound designer
and that's because it just picks up signals up to 100 kilohertz.
So it allows you, if you record in 192 sample rates, it just captures audio which is way
beyond the human hearing.
So...
What that allows us to do is if we pitch down audio with a normal mic, you know, you would lose all this information as long as you go one octave down, you would make the sound very muffled and therefore unusable for our creature sound design purposes.
But with the Sanken, and I really urge you to try it if you haven't done so before, you know, record yourself and pitch it down up to three octaves and it would still sound more or less crisp and really, really interesting.
A downside of the Sanken is that it's unfortunately an omnidirectional mic which makes it very
difficult to use outdoors.
But you know, it doesn't matter, you can still use it in the studio.
And outdoors you just have to do a bit more cleaning up afterwards and denoising and de-birding
and all that stuff.
And also a good tip for anyone who wants to record outdoors with a Sanken is that it stops
working below 10 degrees Celsius.
and so I don't want you guys to find out the way I did because it just stopped working. And how
you can get around that is either wait for a warmer day or you know, you know these pocket
warmers we have in the UK, once it gets really cold you just gaffer tape them to the mic and
that gets around that as well. So I do have some example sounds recorded with the Sankin C100K. I
think important for you guys to know is that it's uh the unpitched raw recording first and then the
processed and pitched sound after.
So the last example you heard of was actually one I created ages ago for Boom Library Creatures,
for the designed one.
And that just uses human sounds.
So you can see...
how powerful that Sanken is.
It really is breath-taking,
so you should definitely give it a go.
Second microphone we're going to look at
is the Sennheiser MKH series.
In my opinion, it's a great all-rounder.
It's probably the mics I use most in the field.
And yeah, it is a very popular choice
for recording in the field
because they, compared to the Sanken,
they just pick up half the,
they have half the frequency response of 50 kilohertz.
but it's actually still great for pitching purposes,
which you will hear in a minute.
And the positive aspect about the MKH series
that it's also available as cardioid
or super cardioid configuration.
Therefore, you can use it as MS,
which is probably 90% of the time what I'm doing.
So again, in terms of here,
a sample with the MKH 8014 mono
and the raw sound beforehand of myself
and then pitched and processed.
Mm-mmm.
Up.
Yes, so again I think you can see that it's still very much usable as a layer in a creature sound
and with the upside of, you know, being able to record in cardioid or supercardioid.
The next mics we're going to look at are contact mics.
So they are, compared to the Sanken and the Sennheiser
microphones, they are actually quite pricey.
They are, the Barker's Berry you can see here on the right,
it's actually not too pricey, normally very durable.
I think this one would be about $300, $350,
and it really is a great way to pick up different signals.
So what we would normally do is we would have either
the Sanken or the Sennheiser mic in about a distance
like this here, like you can see right here,
and then we would
We use a contact mic as a really, as a different source.
For example, I could put it on my throat
to create something completely different,
or I use it somewhere in the room,
you know, something which is resonating,
again, to pick up a different layer of interest,
and to be able to choose from that later on down the line.
So, what you have to keep in mind is,
it picks up very dry and isolated signals,
so whoever, you know, people in here
have used contact mics before,
they're obviously very clean sounding, very isolated,
don't really record much of the environment itself.
And what's, I think what also is important to keep in mind is there's a very big difference
between the budget and the high-end solutions. So the Barker's Berry has a massive frequency
response and it is really, a really good source and I've used other cheaper contact mic
solutions before which just don't give you the same, uh, fidelity. So let's also hear with
the Barker's Berry, let's listen to a few sound recordings with that.
So yeah, not necessarily something you would think that would make its way into a creature
sound in the end, but again, really, really interesting source and, you know, it might
work later on, we will see. Okay, so we have dealt with all the different mics I use on
a daily basis and, you know, the positives and the negatives aspects of that. Now let's
look what we are actually going to record with those mics.
So human recordings first of all,
they are very powerful sources,
you just heard with the samples.
Especially with the Sanken mic,
but also with the Sennheiser.
And a positive aspect about humans
is they usually perform on command
and they can be directed.
So there's obviously individuals who don't do that,
but we don't talk about them.
So normally they do what we tell them to do
and that's great.
And they can also,
they can normally be recorded in a controlled environment.
It keeps down the time we have to spend on cleaning up all the stuff we record and it's
just much more comfortable.
And unless you're high accuracy, it can be done quite cheaply.
So what we tended to do in our Warhammer production, we just sent around emails.
to the whole office and we asked can anyone do a really weird sound and ideally can you
do it in an attacking way, in a painful way and you know in an idling way and we got a
few responses and we recorded them all and again what I tried to tell you before is just
you know record as much source as you can possibly think of because it might come in
handy later on down the line.
Yeah, so there's obviously not just positives about human recordings, because after recording
loads of different human sounds, it can sound very similar once they're pitched and slowed
down.
So...
If I recorded all the people in the studio and later on,
I pitched them down two to three octaves
because I want to create some really deep sounding source
and it can sound a bit like a mess
and it's not really, again,
if we think about the three main ingredients,
variation is always key.
So we have to incorporate some different
recording techniques with the humans
to make them sound, to just make them stand out more.
Another downside is that humans complain about sore throats and hoarseness.
So ideally as a sound designer, I would like to keep it going until the vocal cords are
just non-existent anymore, but obviously most people don't like doing that.
And quite frankly said, it's not as much fun.
I can spend hours in the studio and record humans, but I do much prefer doing what this
guy on the right here is doing, and going outdoors and actually capturing animal recordings.
And animal recordings, they can be very rewarding as, like certain animals, they just produce
great and powerful sounds and they, you know, are conscious, reproduced by any humans.
And unfortunately, they are very difficult to achieve and most animals don't make noises
on command.
So...
So, yeah.
Anyone who, you know, a few people who went out there
and tried to record animals, normally when you point
your mic towards them, they're completely silent.
But as soon as you turn away, they would just start vocalize.
So that's obviously annoying, and it's also time consuming.
So you have to spend a lot of time in the field
recording animals to actually get what you're after.
And yeah, and obviously it's mostly outdoors
in an uncontrolled environment.
So it's, you know, it brings a lot of editing time with it,
a lot of cleaning up time, and so on.
But definitely sometime animal recordings
are absolutely necessary.
Again, in terms of variation, first of all,
which I have mentioned just a minute ago.
But also certain sounds, they can't be reproduced
by humans, or at least I don't know any.
So if you do know any, just refer them to me
because I would like to hear that.
For example, horses, bears, seals, vultures,
they just have some kind of, again, character to them,
which is very difficult for a human to do.
So the real thing is definitely best in this case.
Um, with animals they can be, animal recordings can be very pricey if agencies have to be
involved. So, due to the fact that it's a rare thing that a, an animal can, you know,
vocalize on command. There are some peop, there are some agencies in the UK who specialize
in, in advertising, you know, training animals for advertising and movie purposes. But they
do know it's a rare thing and they charge you for it accordingly, so.
That's obviously a downside.
And those recordings sometimes can also be dangerous.
So I always, you know, when recording wild cats
or stags in mating season,
it really is better to be on the other side of the cage
or have a very, very long boom pole at your disposal.
So just some tips for you guys in terms of animal recordings,
because I'm sure some of you have actually not done one before.
I think the first question you have to ask yourself before you go out in the field
is, where am I recording?
So again, with us in the UK, it's very
It's a very noisy environment, loads of fly path
and birds and motorways, it's really not ideal.
But you can obviously find spaces which are quiet enough
to record those animals.
So I would recommend to do a recce beforehand,
so just to go there and actually record the surroundings.
Again, this is an advantage that you just put that
in your archive and you can listen back to it later on.
Or you could also share it with your teammates
if you're not the one going on the recording
but other people are.
You have to make yourself aware of what are you recording.
You know, it's a difference of recording horses
to recording wildcats.
You just might want to have more mics
to record horses or less mics.
So definitely make yourself aware of what you are recording.
And also the question of how much do I think
I can get out of it is something you might be confronted
by your lead or by your financial director
because they want to know where you spent the money on.
And it's a very difficult question to answer,
but a tip for you.
to really get out most of your recordings is to actually talk to the people who
take care of the animals or who train the animals, because they would normally
know these little tricks. For example, before they get fed, they're
really vocal. Or, you know, if you turn away one of the
animals, then they start to get vocal. And all these tricks are really important
for you to actually get the sound you're after.
How dangerous is it going to be? Again, not really.
a good question I can help you with, just plan your insurance accordingly I guess.
And what equipment do I need? As you can see on the right, that's our current
Boom Library setup, which is obviously overpowered for most sessions, but
I tend to take more stuff
out with me than I actually need to just in case some animal bites my
windshield or bites my cable that I have a spare one in the car.
Right, so now we have dealt with the human recording aspect
and the animals, I actually want to do a bit
of a listening test with you guys.
So I'll show you two sounds.
And I want you to then lift your hand
and you tell me which file is made
just out of human sounds.
So that's sound number one.
I'll play you that again.
And sound number two.
Sound number three.
Sorry for that, I played them both together.
So who of you thinks that sound number one
was made just out of human sounds, please?
Lift your hand.
Okay, and what about sound number two?
Yeah, great, I have to disappoint you, unfortunately.
So sound number two was the one
which wasn't made just out of human sounds.
So sound number one, my good friend and colleague,
Byron Bullock made out of his own voice.
And I don't know if it speaks for him to sound like a boar or pig,
but it's still very impressive.
And sound number two was a giant we had in Total War Warhammer.
I vocalized that myself, but I had to, unfortunately,
use some walrus sounds for the guttural thing
because I just couldn't produce that sound.
So very interesting, again, to hear how we are fooled
by the believability of that sound,
especially that boar sound, sound number one.
Right, so now we're going to have a look at the non-literal approach.
So some of the best layers, in my opinion, for creature sounds,
they don't have to come from humans or animals.
So, for example, think about tire squeals, balloon stretches,
door creaks, dry ice and metal, high-pitched scrapes.
These are all sounds which can make a real difference
in creature sound design.
And a good advice I can give you is look for sounds and not for props.
And what I mean by that is...
You know, because I'm a bit of a sound nerd and I'm trying to, you know, I'm basically
going through my day with open ears and I have my recorder in my bag or a notepad where
if I hear something really weird and really interesting, I either take a note or record
it on the spot so I can later on, it doesn't necessarily have to be a Sanken or, you know,
the Sennheiser mic, but I can at least sketch that sound and I can come back to it later.
And that's really important because the non-literal approach is not something you just, you know,
get up in the morning and do, or if you can, then it's obviously great, but it's normally
not the case.
It can definitely add another layer of interest to the creature and make it sound different
to everything else, and again, all about character and variation and the believability as well.
So in this case, you could hear that's a non-literal recording of just some balloon scrapes.
I blew up a balloon and just, you know, just dragged my fingers on that.
And also, I combined that with a human scream.
So if we listen to that again, just listen to how the first sound is the human squeal,
and then it goes into that balloon and just sounds like nothing else.
And that's really what I'm after in terms of creature sound design.
Let's listen to that again quickly.
So the non-literal approach is creatively
definitely biggest challenge because we,
it just takes a lot of time to find the right props
and the right sounds.
But it is definitely the most rewarding
because if you can tell someone that he created
a great creature sound with just a balloon,
they'd probably be amazed.
And that's obviously what we want as sound designers.
We want the recognition of our other colleagues
because most people, most players wouldn't actually
know to tell the difference.
It's also very time consuming.
you know, again, because it's just a very time consuming process to find all these different
sounds.
And finding the right spots and props to record can be very difficult.
So again, my tip for all of you is to just listen out for stuff like that.
Like today in the morning I opened my hotel door and it sounded like, I think it's called
MOTU, the Godzilla movie, and yeah, so I recorded it and I'll come back to it later and hopefully
can use it in one of the future projects.
So the next video I'm going to show you is a combination of some of the non-literal recordings
we did for Total War Warhammer, also some of the animal recordings as well.
Unfortunately I have to say that the last cow sound didn't make it in the game.
But I'm still amazed that I can actually reproduce a cow sound.
So all my people in Austria are incredibly proud of me.
So now we actually went through the pre-production process,
the recording process, and finally we can actually,
what we always wanted to do, we can get stuck into design bit.
So this is the process where it all comes together.
And ideally after doing all these processes
and different recordings, we would know
what we want to try to achieve by now.
But sometimes it can still feel more like
throwing paint on a canvas and seeing what happens.
And this is absolutely fine because at this stage,
still now, it's still a lot of experimenting with sounds.
And I will also show you a video in a minute
where you can see the struggle of trying
to make these different layers work together.
And I think at this point I have to stress that the door
of your choice is actually not important.
So I hear loads of people telling me that Reaper sounds
more analog or Logic is super smooth and all that stuff,
but I can really say that you should stick to the tools
you're feeling comfortable with and also feel comfortable
with spending hours and hours on one kind of sound.
And unless you obviously have to collaborate with people
because then it obviously dictates what you have to use
and it makes it much easier to share projects and files
with your coworkers.
So just a basic, obviously a basic statement now.
Creature sound design consists of layers.
I think you got that by now.
Everything I showed you over the last half an hour,
there is, you know, hardly ever there will be one sound
which is enough.
So even though we create a great source material
with the Sanken, it still needs to be layered up
with different material to, you know,
to get to that character we always are after
and to get to that believable creature.
So the art of creature sound design
is to make all the different layers work together
and sound like a homogenous creature,
like one creature and not like many creatures.
And so we have to focus our attention on the tonal relation between the different layers.
And that's, I think in my opinion, that's the most important aspect of creature sound design.
It's not the plugins.
it is the source and the tonal relation to each other.
So let's have a look at a video I put together.
I'll try to show you the importance of, first of all,
how the pitch between the different layers works together.
I think it's important for you to know
that it's not intended to sound super crazy awesome
at the end, but I think you will get the message.
Just have a look at this video now.
you
So yeah, I think you can see the struggle here.
So the initial sound, I was actually happy to start with
the growl sound, where all the other layers are kind of
pitched to match that initial sound, but then I decided
in the end to add an intro sound, which I again really like,
but then it completely messed up the tonal relation
of my initial layer, so I had to pitch down
the initial layer.
And this is a very simple example of a very big problem,
you know, where you just have to
Still experiment with different layers, different source.
You find yourself deleting stuff, grabbing new stuff.
And again, it all comes down to the source and what you
recorded beforehand or what you bought library-wise to
really be able to choose from a large
amount of source material.
So I like to think that approaching those designs can be a bit like arranging music,
because of the whole pitching relationship.
So if you think of a guitar riff and the bass playing to it, then it could either sound
in tune, perfectly in tune and it harmonises, or it can sound out of tune and a bit bad
and just not really matching.
So pitch matching is the most important and plugins can't take that work off you.
So again, similar to the guitar example.
the creature sound like the high element, the hiss for example, and the bass element,
so the kind of body resonance, they have to match together.
Otherwise it will sound not believable and it will sound like many creatures rather than
one homogenous one.
So in my opinion, and I think that's quite important for the way I work, is that good
source can allow you to work with just volume and EQ.
Again, the example I just showed you is not really sounding that great, but you can still
tell that it could potentially be great, but there's actually nothing, no plugins are in
there.
This is just recordings I made and just pitch, volume, and I think in the example not even
EQ.
But, nevertheless, there's still plugins out there which are a must-have for every creature
sound designer and sound designer in general, and I want to show you some of those which
I use on a daily basis.
So first of all, it's Isotope by X.
Morph 2.
elastic pitch, the MAGICU, waves lower air,
and also crotas dehumanizer too.
So I think it's important to mention that,
you know, I could probably fill another talk.
at GDC about iZotope, about its functions and how it makes my life so much easier.
Just simply anyone who goes out in the field or who works in post-production probably has
used iZotope before and we just de-noise stuff, de-click stuff, you know, draw our birds from
recordings.
It really is a powerful tool everyone should have a look at if you haven't done so before.
Synaptic Morph 2. So this is a plugin which has been around for quite a while and somehow
it just completely went past me and I didn't know until just a few months or actually I
think a year ago. And what it basically does, just a simple explanation, it takes one spectral
characteristic of one sound and projects it to another. And I mean just, you know, saying
that actually sounds pretty cool for my purposes. So have a listen to that example I just put
something together for you.
So in this example I have a metal groan, a non-literal recording morphed with an elephant roar.
And I mean it's just amazing. Let's listen to it again. I actually want to hear it again.
And this is so, you know, again, another out of this world example which you wouldn't get
if you just record an elephant or metal groan, but put together, putting that time into just
experiment with different layers and with the help of this great tool here, really is
worth it.
So have a look at that as well.
Elastic Pitch, that's just a plugin I love using
for not just pitching stuff down,
but actually automating the pitch over time.
So what I'm also trying to do with my creatures,
I'm trying to automate pitch with movement.
So for example, if one of my creatures would die in game,
I try to get the asset to pitch down
when it's actually falling over,
almost make it sound like a final breath.
And this plugin does it in a really nice way.
It doesn't color the sound in any way,
and it also doesn't step the pitch,
which some other plugins do,
so that's a great one to look at as well.
The Magi-Q is actually something which most people don't know about.
I think that's kind of a little secret to share with you guys,
especially the orange 2.5 kHz knob and the air gain.
Because of the nature of our layers where we all pitch them down quite heavily,
sometimes even though we record with the Senken or the Sennheiser,
we lose some of the high fidelity.
And I find that if I used those two knobs here that I can just inject a bit of life back
into them, a bit of brilliance and a bit of sparkle. Which is, again, sounds like a very
basic thing but it actually does make a difference. So, again, if you have the chance,
download the demo and try it yourself. Waves Low Air, I don't think I have to say too much
about that. It's just a plug-in I've been using for years and it helps me with creating the
kind of bassiness and the bigness of a sound. And, again...
highly recommended to anyone, sound design in general, but also for creature sound designs.
And then Crotus Dehumanizer 2 which is, I think, is a great tool because I think version 1 was
already amazing, but for me it was the downside that it was a standalone plugin, I couldn't use
it in Pro Tools, my DAW of choice. So what they've done with Dehumanizer 2 is amazing because you have
I don't know how many hundred parameters there are in this plugin and it's also on a modular
basis so you can drag in whatever you want. And it's also fully automatable and uh you can
really lose yourself in again you know what I tried to to tell you guys today is just to
experiment and with this plugin you have uh yeah you have a lot to do if you want to just you
know experience all the functions. There's a lot of time to be spending that plugin and also
Crotus are here at GDC so have a look at at their booth if you wanna if you wanna know more
about their plugin.
So I've got another video for you.
This is actually a creature which made it
in the final release of Total War Warhammer.
It's a dragon ogre, a large dragon ogre.
And I tried to, I again captured my proto session here
and I'll show you every single layer.
You can see what it does and you can see
it sounds quite odd when you play it by themselves
but actually when they all play together,
at least in my opinion, they sound quite cool
and they sound pretty much believable.
Let's have a look at that.
Yeah, so you can see the layers by themselves don't sound like much,
and it just takes a lot of time for me to just pitch them all together,
and then, you know, the high elements would lose all their bass,
and with the bass layers I would try and emphasize their bass,
and then at the end I'd get to something like this, and I'm very happy,
but then I have to do five or six variations, and I'm again very sad.
So, um...
Yeah, I think that's a good example of how it's been broken down.
And, you know, this is actually an example where I used quite a lot of different layers
because I try sometimes to limit myself because obviously the less layers I use, the easier
it gets for me to actually get them work together.
Right, so after the pre-production part, the recording part, and also the design part, we do
have to look into implementation, which is the last part of the process, apart from the mix,
obviously. And I think it's so important these days that if the implementation is bad, even the
best sound can't save it. So it does make me very upset if I spend that much time on a sound.
you know, like weeks or maybe a week or two weeks,
and then in the end in the game,
it just doesn't sound the way I expect it to sound.
So we are dependent on great systems for sounds
to make them shine properly.
We really have to, you know,
this is very important that they actually do,
in Pro Tools or in your DAW, they sound great,
but as soon as they come in the game,
there's so many different factors,
and obviously the mix has to work around it,
and it's really important to get stuck into implementation.
So in my opinion, implementation is 50% the experience.
Again, it's completely useless to spend all this time
and all these processes if the implementation is bad.
But I also have to say there's countless possibilities
of implementing audio.
So anyone who worked in games before
knows that there's so many different things.
There's Wwise, there's FMOD, there's
so many different engines.
Every company works with different tools.
And therefore, I can't, unfortunately, just
show you everything about the.
about implementing creature sounds, but what I decided to do is actually to give you again
some tips which helped me in the past, especially when working on Total War Warhammer, a very
creature heavy game, you know, for you just to maybe gain some inspiration from.
So I think in terms of creature sound design, the hierarchy set up is incredibly important.
So again in terms of Warhammer, we had small, medium, large and extra large and huge creatures.
So again this is a hierarchy decision we had to make very early on in the process
because you know many people work on that game and we have to later on mix that stuff as well.
So it's very important to always keep that kind of hierarchy together,
almost like the layers of a creature sound design.
Because it does make it easier in the end
to make the large creature sounds bigger
than everything else and not to lose yourself
in the hierarchy in the end.
Another very interesting aspect,
which unfortunately I don't really have time
to get too much into today,
is the modular approach versus the one-shot approach.
So everything I've showed you today
was all based on one-shot.
So for example, I have an attack animation,
I make this attack sound.
and it would just, you know, I put a trigger point
into the animation, it would play in game and happy days.
But sometimes it can be necessary
that there's so many different animations,
a basic sound set of articulations,
like I showed you before of my random dragon example
with 42 sounds, would just not do it
because there's too many animations
and they would just not sync tightly to the animations.
So what we tried to do in some cases with Warhammer
and with other games as well is that we tried to,
for example, a scream.
we would divide them up in three parts,
like a start sound, a middle sound, and a stop sound,
which makes it, of course, that's great for variation purposes,
but anyone who has tried to blend them in-game before,
it's, again, quite tricky.
So you have to lay a problem in the first place,
and then you also have to blend between those three parts
in the game engine, which can be tricky.
But again, if you pull it off, it sounds amazing in-game
because you have the best amount of variation.
Distant versus close assets, I think that's a very basic thing to say.
It probably seems a bit stupid to talk about it, but I think it's incredibly important,
again, if we think about the three main ingredients of our perspective, that we always, as a rule,
and I don't know who set that rule, but whenever I start a creature sound design,
I start with a close-up, close to the camera kind of sound.
But sometimes it would actually be good to start with a distant sound before
and then work yourself, you know, towards the close sound.
And how we solved that in Wwise before is that we just had a closed sound,
we had a distant sound which was created after closed sound,
but sometimes had to lose some of the layers to actually make it sound distant.
So again, another problem we were facing.
And then we just blend them over distance and with in-game parameters like a cue or reverb.
Use of cone attenuation I think was something
which really changed the way we were mixing our games as well.
So you can imagine that like a cone coming out
of the creature's mouth.
And whenever it turns away from the camera,
the perspective would change accordingly.
And you can automate the EQ, not automate,
but the game engine would deal with the EQ settings,
like low pass and high pass and all that.
And it would just, again, work on the believability
of our game and work on the believability of our creature
sound.
Volume equals size, make use of it.
This is another really basic thing.
And you probably laugh about it if I tell you that,
you know, obviously large creatures should be
louder than small creatures.
But I don't know why it happens so much,
but if I look at a hierarchy,
small, medium, large creatures,
every starting point is actually zero dB
or minus 10 or whatever, but they're all equal.
And it's actually a good starting point to just, you know, do that gain staging
in a really simple way beforehand because it just really
makes the whole mixing process so much easier in the end.
And another thing, the sweetener layers, which is something we made use of heavily,
not just for creature sounds but also for other sound effects.
But for example, if we had big dragon sound, like the huge creatures, like the giants and the dragons.
we could actually, if they're very close to the camera,
we would play a sweetener sound on top of that,
something we created just for that effect
to add a proximity effect, which could be a stereo sound
or a quad sound even to really fill out that space
and to make that huge creature, which is already huge,
make even more huge, because that's what we want.
We want to make everything sound really loud and powerful.
So yeah, we are pretty much at the end of my presentation.
I'll just give you a summary of the most important aspects
what I've been talking about today.
Again, pre-production is key.
You definitely have to know what you're working on.
I think it's, again, very important to mention
that pre-production is important,
and it is worth it reading all the books
about the creatures, get to know their characteristics
and special skills, because it will pay off
in your recording process later on, and also in the design,
and you will always be in brief,
or most of the time anyway.
Be creative with the recording process, but sometimes the most simple approach can get
the most satisfying result, trial and error.
So again, with the recording process, it's all about recording as much as you can, you
know, really don't be scared to go out there and just record all day, edit it up, put it
in your library, and then later on you can choose from that stuff.
I can't stress enough how important it is to...
really, you know, have enough source to choose from. Because when I talk to, to some of you
guys beforehand, before this actual talk, the first question I've always, or I'm most of the
time being asked is, what plugins do you use? And again, I think my plugin and my plugin is
the source. And I think nobody can take that away from you if you really record as much as
possible.
Pitch matching EQ and volume, those three ingredients work with good source.
So again, this is in terms of the design process, obviously.
Stick with those three things for a start.
You know, match the pitch, EQ the elements you want to,
and then do the volume offsets, do some fades.
And I'm pretty sure it will get you far away.
And I think it's, you know, and afterwards you can use all the plugins in the world,
but just make sure that the first step is always pitch matching EQ and volume.
And I think most importantly, get stuck into implementation if you can.
If you're freelance, at least try to get involved.
So I'm now in a position where I'm freelance again.
And I do want to make sure that my sounds end up in the game as intended
and to sound as good as possible, obviously.
And if you're in-house, talk to the implementation team.
Sorry, get stuck into implementation.
Obviously in the in-house it's much easier
because you're actually on the spot
and you don't have to write as many emails
as I have to do normally.
And then finally, believability and character,
the most important aspects of creature sound design.
If you think about what we're trying to achieve with, you know, the whole creating games in the first place,
we want to create a universe for the player to get immersed in and, you know, to feel at home in a way.
And that's exactly what we're trying to do, what we're trying to achieve with our creature sounds as well.
To make them believable and, you know, to kind of define their character of something which isn't real in the real world,
but obviously real because designers designed it.
So it's all about believability and character.
So, yeah, thank you very much for your attention.
I think that's pretty much it.
Actually, if you could fill out the evaluation form,
that would be great, because we always like to get feedback
on the talks.
And I hope you enjoyed it, and obviously I'm
looking forward to answering all your questions now.
So I'm curious about your process for making variations.
So once you have the first variation,
do you tend to be able to just rely on modulating
those existing source assets?
Or do you have to bring in totally different assets
for the other variations?
Yeah, so that's actually a very good question and I can't believe I haven't covered that in my presentation, but it's a very good...
So again, when I was talking about the source, obviously, you know, what you normally do is you create...
So if I record myself screaming, for example, I would create several different variations of that.
in the first place. So then later on, and also all like modern libraries do that as well,
they provide one sound but they also provide you know eight different variations or six variations.
And then what I would do is as long as I get one sound to work in my in my session like an
an attack sound for example, I would then duplicate the whole thing and try and shift
everything so I use the next kind of variation of that. See if it works and then the whole
game starts again. It probably doesn't work so again I would replace layers but again
obviously because I already set some kind of style with the first variation.
then it gets more complicated.
But yeah, I would tend to do,
sorry, I would tend to duplicate the sounds
and try and just to change the files itself.
Okay.
And then see again if it works,
and if it doesn't work, then I have to restart.
So is it actually the opposite?
You leave the modulation and pitching more or less the same
and then.
Yeah, no, I mean, obviously, you know, the pitching can vary.
So that's in, um, oh yeah, I see what you mean.
No, yeah, I would leave it the same because you know, most of these sounds
would then work, but then if I play the second sound, if I play the second
variation, the pitch is again, shifting slightly, I then go back into the
different layers and try to match them together again.
And then for the third and fourth and fifth variation, it's exactly the same.
Awesome.
Well, thank you very much.
Hi, so I think I know the answer to this,
but I'm asking just in case.
You're pitching the layers to match them
so that they fit together, and then are you
then doing more expressive pitching on the master bus
to kind of pitch the whole thing up or down
if you wanna make it more expressive?
Yes, so I think that was, I think you're referring
to that example of the elastic pitch plugin.
Yeah, it really depends.
So as you said rightfully, I tried to pitch all the different layers together first of
all so that harmonizes and it sounds like believable.
And then yeah, exactly, on the master bus I could have like an elastic pitch plug-in
which affects all the layers at the same time.
And for example, when the creature falls over I just go like that, pitch it down or pitch
it up when it does a kind of raw sound effect to just add a bit of more like a point of
interest to it.
So that would happen on the master bus, yeah.
Thanks.
No worries.
Anyone else?
Perfect, I think we're done.
Thank you very much, guys.