Hi everybody. I'm Jason Roberts. I think I'm supposed to tell you to silence your devices,
please. My talk is called Gorogoa, the design of a cosmic acrostic. So who am I? I'm a
I should say a bit about my pedigree, which is mostly non-existent, at least prior to
this game.
I was a software engineer up until 2012, making non-entertainment software.
I was an artist in my spare time.
I liked to draw, mostly as making gifts for my mom, that kind of thing.
I started a couple of parser-based text games in the 90s that I never finished.
Apart from that, Gorgo is the first game I ever tried to make, and it released in December.
I don't want to spend a ton of time on this, but obvious question, why did it take so long?
It was in development for five-plus years, five years full-time.
I think the short answer is that you can't skip the learning process when making games.
The conventional wisdom is start with something simple, finish it, move on, do something slightly
more ambitious, finish that and move on.
And I think Gorgoa is not actually a counterexample to that.
I think that inexperience added years to the project.
I ended up throwing out a lot of prematurely polished work.
And I may even have learned more slowly because I think some lessons you can only learn by
finishing something and letting go of the protective delusions that allow you to get
through the project.
I released a demo of the game back in 2012 that has been bouncing around the internet
ever since.
And I sort of made it by instinct.
I didn't read any game design books or even understand that I was supposed to be thinking
about design.
And it looks more like a complete vision than it really is, that early demo.
I wound up with scenes, a bunch of, you know, that seemed,
I enjoyed making them, I enjoyed finishing art,
but those scenes were not really motivated
narratively or thematically.
And people could, you know,
people thought the demo was dreamlike,
but that only gets you so far.
When it came time to extend the game to full length,
I had to find a way to...
build in more story structure and stronger thematic through lines.
And, uh, so it's sort of like, I think an overall theme of this talk is about adapting
story and theme to mechanics and form, uh, even though maybe
Ideally it should be the other way around in the sense that you should know what story
you want to tell and then decide which mechanics express that story.
In practice I think it often goes the other way and that the process of discovering what
sort of story to tell, what sort of themes to address was both conscious and unconscious.
Back to the very early hazy origins of the game.
I don't remember the sequence of events exactly, but I know that I was trying to write a comic
at one point.
A few years before I started Gorgoa, I stalled about ten pages in.
The story already had problems, and those problems were sort of baked into art I'd already
done and finished pages.
And it was just too daunting a prospect to go back and redo those pages, which there's
a lesson in that.
I came to realize that it was composing the page that interested me more than telling
a sequential story.
This patchwork or mosaic of framed scenes is what I found compelling.
And I had to do something with it, even if it wasn't going to be a comic.
And so why, what is compelling about it?
I'm going to try and dig into that and explain it.
starting with this basic building block, which is a single framed image.
The fundamental building block of Gorgoa.
We I think, everything that we, with the exception of virtual reality, everything we consume,
all this media is inside a frame.
Whether it's the edge of the TV, the edge of the phone, edge of the movie screen.
But we're
We've learned to try and forget that the frame is there.
That's what we mean by immersion.
You forget the room you're in,
you forget the world you're in, yourself.
You kind of mentally project yourself
through the screen into the world on the other side
as sort of like virtual reality by sheer willpower.
But there's space outside the frame
and I think that's fertile territory for design,
as strange as that might sound.
And I think by working on a comic, you can't ignore the frame,
because your mind doesn't disappear inside any one frame for very long.
You have to pull all your consciousness back out and move on to the next frame.
So the frames become visible.
That's what got my attention, that's what got me started down this design path.
So Gorgoa starts with a single frame
and a big white empty space.
And I think when you do that,
the decision to leave empty space is clearly intentional.
And you can tell that somebody made the frame visible
for a reason.
The frame itself is part of the message.
But what is that message?
And I'm gonna look at what are the inherent properties
or what do I feel are the inherent properties
of the frame as an abstract concept?
Well, first, I think the frame, it's subtle,
but I think it has a poignancy to it.
If you imagine sitting in a room looking out the window,
whatever you see out there, you can't really be a part of it.
You can't reach it.
You can't touch it.
All you can do is send your mind out through the window.
And that has sort of a very sweet human sadness to it,
I think.
And some of that sadness is present
when you're playing a game or watching a movie also.
And as you shrink the frame down and make the space outside of it larger, then that
separation becomes, that we normally try to forget, becomes more clear.
And I think that creates a more wistful and sort of oblique relationship to whatever is
inside.
Also, a frame is a clue.
If I put a frame around something, I'm clearly trying to say something.
I'm sending a message.
It's guiding you to something.
and shrinking the focus concentrates significance.
A frame represents curation.
It isn't neutral.
It cares about what it contains.
It's making a choice about what to include
and what to exclude,
and it's excluding almost everything.
A frame is an act of affection.
You see things inside a frame often
because they're precious.
It's like a little jewel, like a box you built
for something that you care about deeply,
or like a halo.
Frame is mysterious.
Because you can see the space outside the frame,
your attention is drawn to the limits of what you can see.
And I think that naturally makes you wonder
what's beyond that boundary.
And also a frame is like a prison.
It's a box or a fence around whatever's inside.
And I think that creates an unconscious tension,
at least it does for me, because if you see a prison,
you wanna see an escape.
On some level, you wanna see the frame broken
or transcended.
So frames, at least in my mind, the way I think of it,
have all these qualities inherently.
And so the question becomes, you know,
how to tell a story that speaks to these properties,
that resonates with these inherent qualities.
And once we add interactivity,
and you know, interactivity in Gorgo is very simple.
You can just zoom in on parts of a scene,
but by zooming in, you're transferring
all the properties of the frame to whatever you zoom in on.
So you are making it a clue, you are lending it mystery,
you are imprisoning it, et cetera.
And so looking around in Gorgoa in this format
is a very forceful act.
Now once you start putting together multiple frames,
so sort of inching back towards the comic page,
It's sort of like you're now putting together a whole gallery exhibition,
multiple pictures on a wall.
And whenever you put multiple pictures together,
it's sort of like a montage in cinema.
Your brain fills up with heat lightning trying to make associations.
Why are these pictures together?
And your inner conspiracy theorist just starts
connecting red strings back and forth.
And if you have multiple interactive frames,
then every time you interact with a frame
to change what's inside of it,
you're recurating that exhibition.
And each one of those changes,
if one of four panels changes,
that sets off a whole new cascade of mental electricity
as your brain, again, tries to figure out
how these things are connected.
And that larger possibility of space of how the frames could be connected is sort
of what led me away from sequential storytelling
because that's only one axis of connection.
And maybe this search for connections between images
or fragments will turn out to be a narrative theme.
But the question remains, after everything I've said,
how to make that into a game.
I've got a set of panels.
I can interact with each panel.
And multiple panels, like I say, make
the promise of connections.
So we need them to interact with each other somehow.
One of my early ideas was some sort of card game.
Because once the comic panels are decoupled from the comic
page.
they sort of look like cards, they're little rectangles.
What if we can move them around,
stack them, play them on each other?
I don't have a mock-up of this, I never built it,
but if you can imagine a playing card
having an interactive scene inside,
like one of the panels in Gorgoa,
you enter that scene and by exploring it,
solving puzzles inside,
you change the picture on the card.
And thus you change the properties of the card.
So maybe you can turn two of diamonds
into five of hearts, something.
But that idea had some problems.
First, I don't know about card games.
I don't know how to make the rules interesting or fun.
I don't know how to relate that top level card game that you're playing to theme or
story and as soon as you make the scenes interactive then you're creating a world that feels like
it should have some narrative.
And besides, because you're changing the properties of the cards, you're cheating at whatever
the game is and that makes the whole thing pointless.
So how about something more like a card trick, something that feels like magic.
I want to keep...
I like the physicality of the cards and that's retained in the final game.
This sort of like subtle things like drop shadow and the papery sounds when you pick
things up and put them down because I think that that physicality makes it more magical
when they come to life and you can interact with them.
But the interactions between tiles should also feel magical and we don't need complex
rules for this top level game.
you don't need to know how to play cards to enjoy a card trick.
At some point I
sort of, I guess I mixed in the DNA of
a jigsaw puzzle. This is like what is
the most literal way in which two scenes can connect. That's connect
visually to form a single image.
And jigsaw puzzles are simple but compelling.
putting two pieces together, you know, that's exciting.
It's like reuniting two halves of a torn photograph
or something.
And this idea satisfies the promise I was talking about
earlier, resolve that tension that you wanna see things
escape from their frames.
It involves illusions, plays with subjectivity
and perspective, I love all that stuff.
And it satisfies this.
It relates to this old fantasy of, I think, of putting two pictures up on a wall, or seeing
two pictures on a wall, hanging side by side, and wanting them to kind of melt out of their
frames and join together.
And I had the same fantasy about two computer games running in windows side by side on a
computer screen, and that's sort of what gave rise to this game.
And the stacking variant of the puzzle mechanic
I see as the same thing, just in a different axis.
Maybe it's more like adding the last piece
to the center of a jigsaw puzzle in that case.
And I'll come back to talk about that mechanic
a little bit more later, but first I wanna go back
and trace another part of the design lineage of Gorogoa,
which is the classic adventure game.
And I think especially amongst designers,
those classic adventure game puzzles are often ridiculed
for having needless complexity.
The nouns and verbs and the mechanical language
are hidden and unclear, and they tend to fetishize,
go out of their way to include
counterintuitive uses for objects,
which makes it hard to reason and solve puzzles.
And many modern puzzle games separate puzzles
more cleanly from the world.
They have an unambiguous noun-verb set,
clear and consistent visual language.
I mean, think about test chambers in Portal
or the panels in The Witness.
But I grew up loving those adventure games
and I partly loved them for the very qualities
that some designers wanted to expunge.
And I think the core fantasy of those games, or part of that fantasy, was lost in that
process of modernization.
Because I think that fantasy is not just about inhabiting a clever character.
I think it's a fantasy about a world.
It's inhabiting a world full of hidden potential.
And those games love the exotic repurposing of ordinary objects
because that's about elevating, in my mind, that's about elevating the ordinary.
It requires us to look closely and carefully at everyday things for a second layer of meaning.
And some of that is lost when puzzles are too cleanly set apart from the world.
I also think that fantasy, unlike a lot of video game fantasies, maps, readily maps back
onto the real world.
It's something humans have always yearned to believe, I think, that there are these
secret compartments of meaning in the world around us that were put there by something
larger and invisible that's leaving us messages.
I, a friend of my mom's, who is a poet, honestly believed for much of his life that the reality
around us is a projection of the unconscious mind, like a very lucid dream.
And so he used a version of Freudian dream analysis on waking life,
which means he looked at objects and events around him,
interpreted them as coded symbols from his unconscious mind.
So when he arrived in a new part of the country,
he would start looking for clues.
He would look at a poster on the side of a building,
or the street signs at an intersection,
or a flyer on the ground.
And he would rearrange letters.
He would look for visual puns.
And he would follow these clues one by one,
and that until he figured out where he was supposed to live.
And obviously I have some logistical and metaphysical problems with that theory.
But I think we can all understand why someone might want to believe that.
The world is frightening and it's chaotic and it's a compelling notion
that something invisible is speaking to us.
Again, it's a deep-seated human compulsion to go looking for that hidden language
with which the cosmos is trying to guide us.
And I think, and again, I think that's obliquely connected to the core fantasy of adventure
games and it's certainly a core theme in Gorgoa, that search.
So I think of the core mechanic in Gorgoa as sort of like a visual acrostic.
An acrostic is, for example, a poem where the first letter of each line forms a vertical
word and unlike crossword puzzles, they're often hidden.
And I'm going to argue that on a cross that can be a spiritual or a metaphysical metaphor,
because it's an almost literal depiction of transcendent meaning.
If you look at only the expected form, reading horizontally, you're missing something essential.
The answer lies on an invisible axis.
You have to rotate your perception out of that axis to see a transverse vein of meaning.
And that's a powerful idea because it means that humble objects can be the intersection
point between those two dimensions, between the ordinary and the eternal or otherworldly.
And so that allows the sacred, if you will, to be accessible through the mundane without
being contained or constrained by the mundane.
So I think of this poet's view of the world
as being like a cosmic acrostic.
Poster on the wall is like a letter that's in two sentences.
It belongs to two different dimensions of meaning.
One dimension is to sell tobacco,
and the other dimension is to tell my mom's friend
where to go to look for the next clue.
So what do I mean by a visual acrostic?
Well, it means that elements in Gorgo
belong to two crossing axes of meaning,
and not just the obvious axes of the grid.
Here we have something that's a piece of a train map
on one axis, but on a different axis it's a ladder.
Here you have a figure in a window on one axis of meaning,
and on the other axis it's a profile on a coin.
Here's the edifice of a building in one dimension
and in the other dimension it is part of a Pachinko machine
for this falling rock puzzle.
So everything has a dual nature
and that was an essential principle of the design.
So like the scaffolding that you see here.
which is part of this falling rock sequence.
It's built to slow the rock down so the puzzle is easier to solve.
But it's also there to repair the building that it's on,
which has been damaged in a war.
So it has a place in the chronology of the game world.
The banners exist as visual clues
to help the player connect the tiles together.
But they're also there to advertise the opening of the museum.
And the same is true for other scenes in the same sequence.
You have ribbons that are wrapping sacred objects
in this basement.
And sometimes I will build scenes in the game
so that they allow me to include a lot of exotic,
varied objects in one place, like a museum
or a basement where religious artifacts are being stored.
So that's a bit of a cheat, but...
The point is that everything should seem,
everything should have that duality of meaning,
which means I had to work very hard
so that nothing in the world looks like
it's just there to be part of a puzzle.
And an effort is made to justify every puzzle element
and every scene within the story.
Because again, that acrostic,
that duality of meaning is essential thematically.
This same rock puzzle, which is the very last puzzle
I put in the game, so I'll talk about it a lot.
It's, and sorry there's no animation here,
but it's the only timing puzzle in the game,
and so it was controversial.
But it was added to address a specific issue
with the design.
And that's central tension in Gorgoa
is the balance between sort of discovery and challenge.
Because as I've said, this is thematically became partly
about searching for things that are inscrutable and astonishing
and otherworldly, which is partly
about escaping from predictable mechanical patterns.
Fantasy is about exploring beyond the limits
of what we understand, encountering
something large and mysterious.
But how can you solve puzzles without understanding?
And I had considered early on just taking the puzzles out.
Many people who loved Gorgoa don't
care that much about puzzles.
They just wanted the experience.
So should I allow players to just explore the world
and stumble across those surprising connections?
That might be truer to the fantasy
because those revelations should feel beyond comprehension.
And we want that feeling of a vast and strange universe.
But I, in the end, and admittedly partly because I like puzzles,
I decided to keep them.
I think some degree of challenge is appropriate to the theme
because in a sense this is something we want to be able to believe
about the real world and if it were possible to just stumble
across secret connections in the real world,
it would have happened by now.
And also I think those revelations gain substance
from the effort involved to uncover them.
We want to be required to look carefully or think differently.
And besides, connection to something greater should, I think instinctively we feel like
it should require some sort of a test.
And also puzzles impose pattern, and some pattern is essential.
I'm trying to create a sense of mystery, but mystery is really about, it's not about no
pattern, it's about a half-glimpsed pattern.
too little and you feel like there was nothing there to find and too much and the mystery
dissipates. So it's all about the right amount of disorientation. And that balance was crucial.
The surprise and delight of stumbling across something, challenge or test on the other
hand.
The way tiles fit together in the game
may be initially surprising and magical,
but at least later in the game,
puzzles are intended to require
an additional reasoning stage after that discovery stage.
I decided to limit the mechanical complexity. This train map you see here was going to be
part of a much more complex puzzle where there are multiple piles with multiple maps that
fit together and the train goes back and forth through this like headachy spaghetti of train
tracks. But I decided that that was too much pattern in a way, in a sense. Pendulum too
far in one direction.
But coming back to this rock puzzle, again,
sorry that's no animation, but I put it in the game
because it can't be solved accidentally, essentially.
Because it's a timing puzzle, you
have to understand how it works before you solve it.
And that is there as a reassurance.
I think the earliest puzzles in the game
are the most amenable to sort of accidental discovery.
And I felt that at this point in the game,
the player needed.
to be reassured that they could get a hold of something, figure out something, and that
there was some sense here.
And similar, another puzzle that comes right after it, this clock tower puzzle, as you're
setting the time on a clock, the position of the hands have enough permutations that
it makes it difficult to brute force.
And again, that is tipping the balance back towards some degree of reasoning.
The next chapter of the game has a series of these wheel puzzles.
You may partly stumble upon the means of turning the wheels, but then you, in theory, have
to think about their orientation.
And that repeated pattern allows players to make some simple deductions.
Okay, one last thing about this rock puzzle,
which is that you can't see it here,
but the way it works is rocks are knocked out
of this box periodically by explosions.
It's a city under bombardment.
And you solve the puzzle by waiting
for rocks to fall out of that box.
But why?
I mean, wouldn't it be easier to have the player
just click or tap on the box to generate a rock?
Well, the answer to that question,
I'm gonna take a deep dive on,
because it's a seemingly small design decision
that had a lot of implications.
Again, in theory, a high-level vision or aesthetic
should ripple downward to low-level mechanical decisions,
but I think in practice, the opposite happens a lot.
And it's...
a good idea, at least early in development, to allow that bottom-up disruption, because
that may nudge you towards the seed that crystallizes everything else.
So as I mentioned, the game is descended from adventure games, and the scene inside each
tile originally played like an adventure game, including, you know, it basically had mist
controls where you could not only move around but interact physically with objects.
You could open doors, push buttons, you know, turn levers, that kind of thing.
And that means, that made it possible to,
it was possible to implement puzzles within a single scene.
I, within a single panel.
So I could put a combination lock on this door here,
and maybe you have to search a nearby graveyard
and find one grave that's better tended than the others,
get the date off that, that's the combination.
Perfectly pleasant puzzle.
And.
that was nice because designing the puzzles where the two tiles connect is super hard.
And it was a nice safety net. I could pace the game out using these puzzles that are just
inside one scene.
But I decided that having those single tile puzzles was diluting the effect of the game. By
not using the core mechanic. The core mechanic is about connecting panels, tiles
together. So no single tile puzzles were allowed. I was going to take away my own design
safety net.
which I call the no touching rule.
So I'm completely gonna take away the player's ability
to physically interact with the world inside a tile.
And so the player can't bring about any change
in the game world except by combining two or more tiles.
And that, as a new designer,
that felt really virtuous and disciplined
and I was proud of myself for that one.
But there were some complications.
Like, if you look at this system here,
if you have the ability to interact,
you could click on that crank in the top tile
and crank the bucket up.
It rises from one tile to another.
Without that option,
the only way I can make this puzzle work
is by adding a counterweight to the other end of the rope.
The player can't put energy into the system,
so I have to build, essentially,
potential energy into the world.
But the problem is, or one potential problem is,
that as soon as these two tiles are connected,
the system moves, the bucket goes down,
the weight goes up, and that's a one-time,
one-way state transition.
It's really difficult in the design to reset that.
And it's prone to self-solving.
You connect two tiles and something moves
before you even realize what you're doing.
If, again, if the player had the ability
just to turn that crank at the top,
then it would at least require one extra interaction
after connecting the tiles
before this very, very simple puzzle could be solved.
And also, the player can then,
could crank the bucket up or down,
and that creates a much bigger, more robust state space
for the puzzle to exist in.
So this is a serious constraint on puzzle design.
and the crow puzzle at the beginning of the game
was driven by that decision.
There's no way for the player to knock that fruit loose,
to drop into the bowl, or to shake the branch.
So I had to create this crow,
which takes off from the branch,
and that was very expensive.
I had to do all that animation.
So this turns out to be a costly decision.
Here's another puzzle.
And a lot of puzzle design in Gorogoa consists of just sitting
around thinking what things look like other things.
A sun sort of looks like a gear if it's done in a stylized form.
Crenelated castle wall looks like a linear gear.
And they could fit together to make a rack and pinion assembly.
But it needs moving parts, so how does a player make it move?
Well, this one idea I had is to add a navigation button
that allows the player to move their camera to the right.
So, and if the camera moved to the right,
the wall subjectively moves to the left.
But the sun stays at the same position in the sky
because its parallax layer is at infinite distance.
So the relative movement of the two parallax layers
causes that gear to turn.
And I like that approach a lot.
It's sort of, I said that looking is supposed to be
a forceful act in Gorgoa,
and this is sort of having that effect.
But it's also sort of cheating,
because the player is changing the state of the world
using just one tile.
In a way, I've taken a navigation button
and turned it into a button
that operates a piece of machinery.
So is it really using the core mechanic?
I decided it wasn't.
So instead, I have a scene in the game
where the movement of the camera
is driven by the movement of the character.
Character is walking, the camera tracks the character
for cinematic reasons, essentially.
And so I get the same effect of camera movement.
But the difference is that the.
the character is literally driving the action now.
And that's much more thematically compelling.
I'm taking the efforts and energy of the character
and I'm literally hooking up a drive train to it.
And it works well with the themes of this chapter
in the game, which is about sort of the role
of repetitive and mechanical ritual in devotion.
So, you know, maybe the no touching rule
isn't such a liability after all.
Maybe it's leading me in interesting directions
I wouldn't have gone in otherwise.
And even more than that, because by taking away
the player's ability to physically interact with the world,
I've disembodied them.
And that turned out to liberate
my whole thinking about the game.
For example, a disembodied character
can just fly across space.
It doesn't require any physical explanation.
Nobody ever questions it
because there's no sense of physical presence in the world.
Disembodied player can enter a character's thoughts
or memories.
You can enter the world inside the China pattern on a plate.
that was really powerful.
And I don't know that maybe players would have accepted that
in addition to and still be able to turn cranks,
but not thinking of the player as embodied,
freed up my mind as a designer.
And at an even higher level,
limiting the player's interaction
makes the relationship between the player and the story
more oblique and mysterious.
And that leaves room for a wider range of interpretations
about what the interaction with the game means.
And notably, it allows the entire game to feel
as much like a mental process as a physical process.
Like maybe someone sorting through fragments
of experience or memory, looking for those connections.
And
Gorgo is often called dreamlike and some interpretations of what dreams are about have to do with that
process of sifting through these chunks of experience and trying to find patterns within
them.
And again, this connects to the properties of a frame, this idea of
the mental process of sorting through memories,
because the frame creates that same sort
of melancholy distance that you have,
the same relationship you have to memories.
There are scenes you can see and examine
and kind of turn over in your mind, but never re-enter.
So again, this is a relatively secondary or tertiary decision.
It didn't, this no touching rule,
that didn't seem to me like a, it seemed optional.
Like the game could have been built with or without
that decision.
But having made it one way, that rippled up
to not just to affect the game all the way
at the narrative and thematic level, ultimately.
So, speaking of narrative,
what kind of story does it make sense
to tell with these mechanics?
This is a question I asked very late in the process,
in a way, I had to kind of feel my way to this solution
as, you know, before I was able
to think about it consciously.
And since it's a puzzle game,
The basic question is how do you combine puzzle and narrative?
Well, there's a tried and true approach, which is puzzles as obstacles
for a protagonist in a typical dramatic narrative.
Story needs obstacles.
The protagonist needs to demonstrate cunning or perseverance.
So it works great.
It's classic for a reason.
But, Gorgo, it doesn't work that way at all.
it sort of turns that model inside out.
Instead of puzzles inside of a story,
it's a story suspended inside a puzzle.
The protagonist isn't solving puzzles.
The player is solving puzzles,
and from sort of an external god-like perspective,
and the player moves independently of the protagonist.
They just, the two sort of cross paths.
And at least to me, I mean, puzzles you solve in the game do facilitate character traversal,
but many of them, at least in my mind, are as much about discovering the story as advancing
the story.
So is any of this a good idea?
I could rip all the pages out of a great novel
and hide them around the city,
and the novel might be a delightful read,
and looking for the pages
might be a delightful scavenger hunt,
but are those two unrelated delights
that I've just stuck together?
And the story of the novel might suffer from pacing issues
as you find the pages out of order, et cetera.
So that steered me away from a traditional dramatic narrative,
because the emotional arc and act structure
would be too disrupted.
The chronology is all chopped up and scattered and folded back
on itself.
And I was drawn more towards something
like that is a like a parable that
suits the spiritual themes of the game
and what I'm trying to say.
A parable is instructive, it's an act of communication, typically there to give the teaching a lesson
of some kind.
It doesn't just exist to provide dramatic satisfaction.
You're not supposed to entirely lose yourself or forget that it's a story.
And that is, that's related again to the form of the game.
Like I say, a frame, by its nature, feels like a clue.
So it feels instructive,
it feels like an act of communication.
And because you are looking at the game world
through this shrunk down small window,
that allows you to keep at least one eye
on the exterior world.
And so you don't forget that you're being told a story
and you don't forget to ask why you're being told that story.
So I feel like the form of the game is putting the player
into the right posture to interact with a parable.
Parables are often puzzles in that they're,
you know, hidden in allegories.
They are a riddle that has to be unlocked.
Unlike the search for the novel pages, in this case that might be a virtue
because the act of solving the riddle is part
of the message of the parable.
I think every parable that requires this kind
of unlocking has a second, in addition
to whatever its specific lesson is, it has a second more general lesson
which is about how to look for meaning in the world,
to always look for that second layer.
So this is why I argue that it is acrostic in the sense that I mean.
At least if it's an allegorical parable.
It teaches us, exists to teach us that lesson of duality, of meaning.
And that just leaves the final question, a parable about what?
I, again, this, well, I don't want to reveal too much, but it is about the lifelong quest
for that.
hidden transcendent meaning.
So it sort of, it folds back on itself conceptually.
There is a dramatic narrative contained inside the game.
So it is, in a sense, it functions on two levels at once.
It is meant to be a story about a character,
but also it is meant to be structured and read as a fable.
Maybe one way of looking at it is it is an attempt
to look at a real life, at the pieces and fragments
of a real life, and retroactively impose
the structure of a parable, of a fable.
a parable, upon that life.
And you can make of that what you will.
Again, I don't know how well this worked.
The story of the game and how it comes across
is one of the things I'm most uncertain about in the end
product, I think.
Creating a sense of mystery was a core goal of the product.
I was inspired by.
I was particularly inspired by this puzzle book called Maze that I played when I was
a kid.
And I never solved it.
Which meant that the mystery of that unsolved book was something that I carried with me
my whole life.
And I wanted to recreate that feeling, but I couldn't do it by making an unsolvable
game.
So I had to find some other way to make mystery an inherent part of the experience.
The story in the game, I never went out of my way
to make it more obscure, but I also
allowed the inherent sort of obscurity
of the storytelling mechanism to function as an asset,
I think, or I hope.
And as for the story of the game,
I'll leave the rest up to your interpretation.
And that's it.
So thanks.
We have time for questions. If you have a question for Jason, please go to one of the
mics in the aisles and I'll start things off. So because the game is multi-platform, were
there any puzzles that you wanted to make that you couldn't because it has to be playable
with a mouse and a finger and a controller?
Well, the multi-platform decision was made relatively late.
Again, there's one timing puzzle in the game and that became an issue with the Switch because
just the operating the pointer with the control stick is just slightly more challenging.
And so we thought that puzzle might be a deal breaker.
It might need to be altered for the Switch, but in the end we decided it worked well enough.
Hi.
Whoa.
As a designer of some of those old school adventure games,
I really enjoyed this a lot.
I think you managed to kind of capture a lot of the feeling,
as you said, but with a very fresh approach.
One of the things that I thought that was inherent in
what you did that really solved a problem that we had
with the old and even some of the new school adventure games
is that you always want to have a degree of choices, but
not so many choices that you feel that you're just going
through 50 different locations trying 17 different objects
with each thing you can find in there.
And I found that the four panels.
were a perfect way to do that and that it never was able to get too complicated, even
though the depth of each panel meant that there were lots of other choices, but there
never was this sort of bewildering complexity. And I'm wondering if you experimented with
going to 3x3 or 4x4 or whether you just hit on that 2x2 as early on as the optimum.
Okay, so the question is about...
considering a three by three grid, et cetera,
and about the implications for not confusing the player.
And yes, that is a big reason why it's a two by two grid.
One, another reason is that the bigger the grid,
the smaller the tiles, or you have to add another layer
of zoom to zoom in on parts of the grid,
which is too complicated.
But yeah, it's clear from testing the game,
especially because scenes within tiles are very deep
in the sense that you can like dive.
through sort of multiple layers of reality.
And four tiles was clearly the absolute limit
of what people could keep track of.
And in fact, there are, the number of scenes
with four tiles in Gorgoa is actually limited
for that reason.
It's usually two or three to make it more comprehensible.
And one data point for you.
I thought that the story was intriguing,
but I appreciated the part that I got through the whole game
without ever thinking very hard about it
and just sort of experiencing it in that dreamlike way.
And I like the fact I kept waiting for some point
where you were going to penalize me for not having caught
some critical story piece.
So I appreciate the fact that that was optional.
You're welcome.
Hi there.
Thanks for a beautiful game and a really intriguing talk.
My question was just more from a practical perspective.
Playing the demo a few years ago, and then playing the
finished game, I picked up small elements from the demo
that had been rearranged.
I was just wondering how did you keep track of it all?
And sort of when you were...
I assume you must have...
There must have been a lot of rearranging of puzzles and orders of things.
And how do you keep it all in your head?
It just seems so...
So the question is about how I keep track of the various pieces of the game
and the design that I have to move around between iterations.
I...
It is...
It was mostly in my head and then the game itself becomes a document.
I did, so yeah, I thrown out a lot of work on the game,
and as I said, I put too much work into chunks of content
that didn't make sense,
or that were not justified thematically.
And when I cut something, I cut a whole puzzle out.
I always think, can I repurpose this?
Can I salvage it and stick it someplace else?
And occasionally, sort of, but...
most of the time didn't work and stuff that was cut just, I mean,
it might be able to take one little piece of the art and reuse it,
but so for the most part, stuff that was cut just went away.
So I didn't have to keep track of it. And, uh, yeah.
Hi.
I have a question about the...
You mentioned traditionally the emotional arc,
a story arc, is too disruptive for the game,
but a lot of happenings in the game is also unretractable.
You can't return to the previous state.
Why particularly this emotional arc
or story arc is too disruptive?
Can you explain?
Sorry, what was that last part?
Why the emotional arc, you think it is too disruptive,
so you intentionally took it out?
Well, so why do I think that the emotional arc of the game was disrupted by the format?
Because if I think of the story of the game as I see it as being like an act structure,
like a three-act structure, then...
several of the acts are happening in parallel as you play the game.
You're seeing two different threads from two different points in time
at the same time, often.
And again, you may not have even realized that,
and that's part of why that arc gets, that story arc gets disrupted.
time is mixing, different periods of time are mixing with each other throughout the
course of the game. And that, and usually when you want to tell a story, you want to
tell it in chronological order, unless you've got a very good reason not to. So, that's
why I felt like the traditional arc was, was challenging.
Hi, I just have a question about earlier you mentioned that those banners on the museum
were to kind of also, they serve the purpose of showing the player like where they can
connect with the other frames as well as the narrative implications.
I was just curious if you had like a hard and fast rule for every frame of this will
be an obvious clue for the player or if like how did you balance how much to hold their
hand and how much to let them kind of shuffle the pieces around to figure it out?
Right, thanks. How did I balance giving player guidance with kind of disguising puzzle elements
as part of the world? I guess playtesting is a big part of that and partly by feel,
but...
In that, again, so that puzzle with the falling rock
and the banners, that was one of the last puzzles.
And so I worked hard to find visual elements
that were both justified within the world,
but also really strong.
Because if you don't, that puzzle's complex enough
that if people don't get the connection pretty quickly,
they're gonna be frustrated.
So how is the balance achieved?
A lot of trial and error and seeing how people react to it.
Thank you.
Thank you for the talk.
How do you decide on the elements you're going to use?
That makes the puzzle seem very connected,
even though it is very,
like it jumps a lot.
Like it leaves the space,
and how can you decide this balance?
The balance between.
the balance between the theme and the elements you're using in different puzzles
and the transition, like the smooth transition between them?
Well, I mean, so the balance between...
Scene elements as puzzle, as mechanical pieces
and scene elements as, you know, story elements.
Again, that's largely a matter of trial and error.
As far as, I mean, you're talking about sort of the flow
through the game.
Okay, five minutes.
Yeah, well, one thing that flow from scene to scene
was very important to me.
I didn't ever want to.
have an edit or a cut.
So things flow from
one scene or moment in the game to another to
create a sensation of flow
and sort of calm movement through space.
Does that help?
And another question, how can you
put a high-level philosophical idea into a solid mechanic?
Well, I mean, like I say, I sort of worked.
So how do you put a high-level philosophical idea
into a concrete mechanic?
Yeah.
Like I say, I sort of worked backwards,
partly consciously and partly unconsciously,
from having built something.
I mean, I built the original demo
based on kind of a feeling.
And that feeling was driven by the formal and mechanical
properties of the game.
But then in order to make more of it,
I had to figure out what philosophically
the structure of the game was saying,
and then make the game about that.
So it was kind of the other way, start with the mechanic
and find the philosophy.
Thank you.
Hi.
Yeah, you clearly put in a ton of emotional and mental energy
into this entire experience.
And how do you continue persevering
in the face of discouragement and conflict and distress?
What keeps you going?
I guess, well, I mean, maybe because.
So what keeps me going on a long project?
Well, sometimes my productivity did falter sometimes.
Sometimes I did feel like giving up.
I think one important feature is that the game, the visual art part of the game, was
very nourishing to work on.
So making art is, for me, is pleasurable and it makes me, it has a short feedback loop
to make me feel good, feel good about myself.
Whereas game design is the opposite.
It's like broken for a long time.
So to some extent the game was the source of strength for me
during that part of my life.
So it was the thing I was most interested in doing
and working on.
So it wasn't the source.
I mean, occasionally it was a source of stress in my life.
But I think most of the time it was the escape from stress.
Cool, thank you.
I mean, you've spoken really elegantly about the balance
between the artistic and the mechanical sides of the game.
And I thank you so much for explaining so much
of how that's one thing.
But I'm really curious about the technical challenges.
You talk about art being a big motivating factor.
When you zoom in through a scene,
you have this line art style that needs to change to scale.
Did you ever draw a scene that you realized,
oh, I wanted to go a little further and throw away?
Tell a little bit more about the technical challenges.
Okay, there's a question about the tech of the game.
I always considered it simple, so that's why I didn't cover it much.
I mean, it uses parallax layers
in a very simple 3D space that the camera moves through.
But if you move from looking at an object from far away
and then you zoom in to look at it closely...
Often you're transitioning between two different objects,
two separate drawings of the same object.
So I zoom in on a clock tower,
I'm going from a small drawing of the clock tower
to a large drawing of the clock tower,
not scaling the same drawing.
I'd scale both drawings at once
and then crossfade from one to the other
and movement is blurry enough that you often don't see that.
And then that's about it mechanically,
at least for the inside of a tile.
Sure, did you ever find that you had to reorganize your workflow based on changes to how you
wanted the scenes to be composited?
Yeah, I mean the workflow was ironed out pretty early on, but yeah, I developed techniques
for how to sort of figure out the home position for an object and what it looks like from
that perspective and then...
and then quickly get to what the object looks like
from another perspective.
It's difficult to describe.
But yeah, there were approaches that I evolved over time
for dealing with that.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Last question.
This was an amazing talk.
I have a question about the dual nature of all of these things
when you were designing.
It seems like there would be a lot of dependency issues when you're iterating on your design.
And I'm wondering what maybe you learned was the greatest dependency?
So when you wanted to scrap a section and improve on it in some way, was it the art?
Was it the design progression?
So yes, everything in the game is dependent on everything else.
And what was the greatest sort of challenge or pain point?
Certainly art, because it was so expensive to produce,
and oftentimes like the, if you
connect two tiles together, the lighting has to match across,
all the colors and lights have to match across the tiles, and maybe one is an exterior
daytime scene, and one is an interior nighttime scene.
And...
if I need to change the puzzle for visual reasons,
that might force the time of day to change
in one of the two scenes,
so that pushes back onto the narrative.
That was a big challenge.
If I'm trying to make a puzzle and I think, oh, this puzzle
needs one more tile to have enough pieces to work,
then that means I have to create a whole life
cycle for that new tile.
I have to create a moment where it was born,
and all the scenes that are inside it, what those scenes
have to do with the story.
And then I have an extra tile around, which means I can't,
and I might.
take up a space that would otherwise be occupied by another tile. And so, just adding one more
piece to a puzzle if it's another tile is like a hugely costly decision that like ripples
forward and backward throughout the whole game.
Great. Thanks.
All right. That's going to wrap things up. Please make sure that you...