My name is Måns, and I'm Director of Monetization and Design at Rovio.
I need to stand close to this.
And I have also... Is this too loud?
I have also... Okay.
Hello. My name is Måns.
So, I was for many years the product lead of this game, Angry Birds 2.
And I have also been called on our biggest fan forums,
the guy who ruined Angry Birds.
Now this is a horrible thing to say about anyone.
This is not true.
But I am the guy who had to figure out how to do this, how
to basically turn one of the most popular premium games of
all time and turn it into a free-to-play game.
And things like that tend to piss people off sometimes.
But anyways, Angry Birds 2 is a nice game.
It's our biggest game to date and we really like it.
Today I wanted to talk about the mistakes because it's been a bit of a bumpy ride.
So it's been a lot of mistakes during the road.
I had a lot of mistakes. I had 30 once but I had to time it.
Let's go for top 3 mistakes.
Here they are.
Overfeeding the goldfish.
helicopter parenting and all work and no fun.
Mistake number one, overfeeding the goldfish.
This is not really one mistake.
It's more like 1,000 mistakes that all comes from the same
place, which would be me.
So the thing is, if we look at the total revenue of
Angry Birds 2, all the money that we make, and then we
split this money up by spend tier.
how much the players spend in the game.
So then we have the whales, of course, people that spend a lot of money, over more than
a thousand dollars, and they obviously make up for a really big portion of all the money
we get from this game.
And then we have dolphins, people that spend more than five hundred dollars.
Seals, this is I'm just making this shit up like that. I haven't been able to find any like
Terminology here, so don't use this
Whales is the only thing that exists as far as I know
The herrings people that spend more than ten dollars in the game, and then we have the goldfish up here
So the goldfish these are people that spend you know less than ten dollars in the game or zero
And me, myself, happen to be a goldfish.
In most games that I play, I spend less than $10,
or I spend nothing.
At least this was the case when I started
working with this game.
I'm more used to this now.
But anyways, I am a goldfish.
And this is a bit of a problem, because obviously, you can
see, we don't really make up that big portion of the
revenue, me and my goldfish.
mates. So even if there's a lot of us, like a lot, a lot, obviously most people are goldfish.
It's really a problem because if I spend, you know, if I don't watch myself really closely,
I'm going to end up spending 98% of all my time and energy catering for people that make
up for, you know, 2% of the revenue. These are not the guys that...
put food on the table for my kids. So this is a bit of a problem.
I used to be able to use my gut feeling
a lot. I was on TV before I used to write comedy sketches. I love watching comedy
sketches so
you know if I write a joke and it makes me giggle
chances are it's probably a pretty good joke and some other people will like it as well.
right? And then I got into gaming. I made this indie cute like indie puzzle games. Also all
about creating something that I like, assuming that other people would like it as well.
And still with, you know, in-game stuff, when I have time to do things like this in
Angry Birds 2, for example, still the same. I can use myself, but...
when it comes to system design, metagame design, or these kind of games, I am a goldfish. I can't
really use my gut feeling because these are goldfish guts and they are wrong, or at least
they are wrong in the sense that they will not really make the game grow the way that my
bosses wanted to do. So I need to not listen to my guts anymore and that's kind of hard.
So let's talk about phone booth stuffing for a while.
This is not a thing anymore.
I don't think that anyone in here has done this.
But phone booth stuffing was big in the 50s.
People were bored in the 50s.
So this is a thing where you try to cram as many people as
possible into one phone booth.
And the world record is 25.
So 25 grown-up people in one phone booth.
Yeah.
They didn't have smartphones and stuff.
Anyway, let's take this phone booth, and let's just make
some assumptions here.
Let's assume that these are perfectly
average American males.
In that case.
They should be about 181 centimeter tall, and they
should have a net worth of around 33k.
This is what Google is telling me, anyways.
Now, we're going to break the world record here today.
We're going to put two more guys into this phone booth.
And not any two guys.
We're going to put these two guys into the phone booth.
So this is obviously Jeff Bezos, the most, the richest man alive.
The CEO of Amazon.
And it's also Robert Wedlow, who is the tallest man to ever live.
So.
Let's put them in there and see.
We now have a new world record, 27.
This is amazing already.
But the averages are not really the same anymore.
So we need to update that.
So first, the height.
This is actually OK.
It went from 181 centimeter to 184.
We can live with this.
I mean, if I just grab a random dude from this phone booth,
chances are that he's going to be fairly close to 184, right?
Unless, of course, I happen to grab Robert.
But hopefully, fairly close.
So this is an average that tells something, at least.
Now, if we look at net worth, it's now $5.2 billion.
And this is more problematic because no one in this phone booth has anywhere near 5.2 billion dollars.
One guy has 27 times that and the other guys doesn't have anywhere near that of course.
So this average, I don't really know what to do with it.
If I grab any random guy...
they will never have anywhere close to 5.2 billion dollars.
And this, there are really two takeaways here.
So first off, obviously.
You know, the whales we have in the games, they screw up the data exactly the same way that Jeff Bezos
screwed up the nice data we had from this phone booth, and this is quite unintuitive for me as a
goldfish. When I think about an LTV of ten dollars for a game example, like
the average money we make from a player is $10. I tend to think that some people spend $10 but of
course no one will. Almost everyone will spend $0 and then some guys will spend a lot more.
So this doesn't really come naturally to me as a goldfish.
And also, of course, the other takeaway, and actually the more important one, I think, is that money is very unevenly distributed in this world, right?
So whenever I hear these stories, we have these in all games, right?
People, whales, super whales, spend more than $100,000 in one game.
That always feels weird or like I always get a bad feeling about that.
Like this guy has a problem, right?
But that's just because $100,000 is a lot of money for me.
If we're talking about Jeff Bezos guy here, $100,000 is nothing for this person, right?
I mean, he's probably spending that money when he just goes out to drink champagne with his friends.
So this is very hard for me to remember again as a goldfish.
And I end up, and I have ended up, spending so much time
trying to do this, trying to get people to make that first
purchase, trying to make people just spend a little bit more.
And this is really hard.
I mean, for this to make sense, I need people to spend
maybe three or four times the money they already spent.
That's a lot.
If I work with these guys instead, I only need them to spend 10% more every month or whatever,
and that will actually make a big difference. And also, of course, these are the Jeff Bezos of the
gaming world, so they probably have a lot more money. Let them pay for the development of the
game, and then a lot of other people will be able to play really nice games for free.
So in that aspect, I am a really, really nice guy, right?
So with that in mind, let's continue.
Mistake number two, I really need a drink, sorry.
Sorry, mistake number two, helicopter parenting.
So this is the start screen of Angry Birds 2
as it looked after launch.
And if you see that little button down in the corner,
this one, I remember hating this button so much.
I bitched so much about this button.
This was the review button.
Okay, so all the games, the review games
were supposed to have this button
and it was a button that would take you to,
you know, some.
central stuff like cross promotion to the other games and and Rovio news and
stuff like that and and I just hated this button I wanted to get rid of the
Rovio button because it was you know it was unclean I wanted a clean experience
I was super scared of distracting the players now let's have a look at the
start screen of Angry Birds 2 today
Now you can see that the ruby button is gone, so I did win the war against the corporate overlords.
But we have a lot of other distractions in there, so I counted the buttons today.
We have 25 buttons in the start screen.
So how did this happen?
When we were in pre-production, before we launched the game,
the other games, the other Slingshot games,
had more than 3 billion downloads already.
So that's a very, it's a big number, of course.
And obviously, we assumed that since we
have all these downloads, people know how to play these games.
This is easy, casual games.
3 billion, come on.
Right? And then we had the big launch. We launched Angular 2 in the end of July 2015.
And things actually didn't look that way.
So we weren't able to retain the players as well as we
thought we would.
And we also didn't make all the money that we
were supposed to.
So this was a problem.
And we started looking at the data, like what's going on
here, what's the problem?
And we made some discoveries.
So first off, people are really bad at throwing birds.
We didn't know that, but they are.
So I mean, do you remember this thing?
When you tap the screen and you do these abilities
with the birds, so this is a blue bird,
we'll split into three and they do this.
They have different abilities.
People don't do that.
And it's very hard. I mean, the game is supposed to be fun and easy and nice.
It's not fun and easy and nice if you don't do these things.
Then it's super hard.
So what we realized after launch was that we need to completely turn this game around
and make it into something else.
And the way we thought about it back then was, you know, let's refocus and make this game all about the characters instead, because people seem to like the birds a lot.
And I'm going to spoil this. I mean, this proved to be a very successful strategy. So this is the RPDAO of the game since launch, and it's been going up, I think, like, seven times.
Since then.
So the way we did this was basically, you know, we just started adding more depth to
the game.
We added an arena and daily challenges and hats and you know, just more and more and
more.
So many new features crammed the game with more stuff.
because people didn't seem to get enough.
We added new birds.
We even added a little Flappy Bird-inspired jetpack thing
with your little Tamagotchi hatchling some time ago.
Super popular.
People like it.
So the thing is, this all went really well.
We should of course have done this earlier. I mean, early on I was super scared. I always thought that, you know, we need to unlock all these features as late as possible.
I was so, so scared of, you know, just distracting these poor players too much and if I gave them too many features, too many options, they're just going to leave.
I've seen nothing of that.
So, if we, you know, instead of having this at launch, we would have had this.
We had, we just lost so much by launching a game that, you know, wasn't the game they wanted, wasn't the game they needed.
And this was all because that over-protective helicopter parenting thing.
I didn't think they were ready for something like this, but they really were.
Mistake number three, sorry I talk a lot because I'm now getting a bit nervous about time. Are we cool?
Okay, good.
All work and no fun.
Mistake number three.
So, do you know what this is? 6.78.
This is a D30 retention of Angry Birds 2.
It's not that great.
You really want it to be higher, or I would.
So, obviously when I can't sleep at night, I lie awake in my bed.
This is what I think about.
Why, why, why is it 6.78?
Why isn't it 10 or 20?
And I try to figure out what can I do to solve this.
And when I think about things like this, obviously I'm going
to get these kind of ideas.
Like we need a daily log-in calendar.
We need to give them better and better rewards for every
day they log in.
And if they log in 30 days in a row, we're going to give
them an epic X.
Right? Or, you know, we need to create a social clan system so they can chat with their friends
and, you know, create new clans and socialize. They don't want to do that on Facebook. They
want to do it here in our game. So, these are the things I'm going to end up thinking about
in my bed. And nothing wrong with these things. These are fine ideas. Will they fix retention?
No, or probably not.
So the problem is that these features, who are they really
catering for?
These features are for the fans, for these guys.
If you already like the game, if you already enjoy the game,
these are the kind of features that can give you a context
for enjoying it even more.
But are these guys really the problem?
Look at them, I mean they love the game, they're not going anywhere.
What I need to do is, you know, focus on the people that doesn't like the game and that
choose to leave the game.
It's not these guys.
So saying that people like the game, they just want some long term goals, to me it sounds
an awful lot like, you know, she's just dating that guy because he has a more expensive car
than I do.
It's what do I want to believe? It's not the truth. It's probably much nicer than I am and also he has a really nice car
So they don't want my epic axe because they don't like the game. They know they won't enjoy
Using the epic axe. It's just a game. They just want to kill some time
They just want to have some fun here or you know here
Over here, that's what they want.
So it took me a long time to understand this.
The first year after launch, I think
we maybe tested like hundreds of different variations
of the first chapters in the game.
What happens when you enter the game?
How do we keep players in the game?
And every possible variation of difficulty settings
of the levels and in which order we give you the chapters,
all these things we tested.
And of course, as always, it's quite easy to move the needle on some metrics.
It's very hard to move retention.
Obviously, I mean, we're not selling water in the desert here.
There's a lot of free entertainment around nowadays.
So if they don't like the game, they will leave most of the time.
But one year after launch, I got this email from the people
that make Angerous Pop, another game, a review game.
And they told us about how they had this new level design philosophy that made all the levels much more fun,
and how that actually improved their retention a lot.
And of course I was all like, fun? Is that a thing?
Because I've been thinking about all these other solutions for so long.
And I all of a sudden, OK, we need to test this, right?
So I told Oscar, lovely guy, this is a level designer,
and I told him, just create a fun group.
Make a test with more fun levels.
So he took the first 30 levels.
Fun is a relative term of course, but just tried to make them more fun.
And for the first time ever, we could actually see clear improvements of the retention.
So all the other tests, hundreds of tests, nothing.
And then we made the game fun.
This is one year after launch, so think about that.
A game like Angry Birds 2, I think we had 50 million downloads the first year.
These 50 million people could have had this more fun, better experience.
That would have made a big difference for us.
It took Oscar two days to create this group.
So this might be the biggest, or like, obvious biggest mistake of all, I think.
So...
Go to Beadaholique.com for all of your beading supply needs!
In conclusion, there's nothing wrong with me, you know, thinking about my epic access and trying to cater for the fans of the game, the people that really like it.
It's very good, but I tend to forget that it's just a game.
I started to think there is something else.
It's kind of like when I went here on the plane,
they have this little monitor on the plane.
And there was a QR code.
And it said, scan your phone to personalize your in-flight
experience.
And this is, you know, someone has had a meeting with someone and they've been talking about the in-flight experience.
I don't have an in-flight experience. It's just a necessary evil, right? I mean, it's horrible to sit there.
But this is how you start to think about things. I'm no better than these people because I do the same mistake with the games.
I think about the player journey or the player experience in the game.
I, um, sorry, this doesn't really work.
So as a conclusion, it's very important, I think, to remember
that it is a game.
It's nothing else.
Play the game every day.
For the first year, I kind of didn't.
And then I realized that.
And now I start playing the game every day.
So I have to remind myself, it's just a game.
Make it fun.
And that's it, actually.
That's it, thank you very much.