So this is a series of three micro talks
centered around a theme.
And that theme is how to run an indie studio
without a surprise hit.
I'm Christopher Langmuir.
I'm the creative director of An Enemy Hug Interactive.
And these are my fellow speakers.
This is Teresa Duranger.
She's the CEO of TumbleGates Games.
And this is Tanya Short.
She's the captain of Kit Fox Games.
And we don't have a lot of time, so I'm just
going to dive right into it, if my slides will advance,
which they aren't.
OK, cool.
All right, so what do our three studios have in common?
Why are we all in this panel together?
So what we are is we're all about the same size.
We're all about the same age.
We've been around about five years,
and we've all got 10-ish employees.
But most importantly, we don't have a runaway hit
that has founded the backbone of our company's budget and runway.
None of us have a product that has just moved a totally insane
number of units out of nowhere.
All of us are sort of very one foot in front of the other,
but we've still grown a lot over the last five years.
And I want to talk a little bit about how.
So I'll start with my micro talk,
which is about how to get client work
and balance it against original IP development.
So now I personally only have about seven minutes or so,
so if you're like watching this on the vault later,
set it to like half speed, but if you're here, sorry.
But seriously, my caveat is I don't actually have the answers.
Right?
I'm going to give you a whole bunch of things that
are about our experience and what I've learned,
but they're very contextual to us.
Like for example, our studio was founded in Canada.
Operating in different countries is different.
Different clients are different.
You and your team are going to be different than me
and my team.
Just because something worked for us
doesn't mean it's going to work for you.
That being said, if I could go back in time five years
and talk to myself before I started this studio,
there's a handful of things that I think
are pretty self-evident now that I'd love to tell me.
And I can't do that, but there might be like
future me's in the audience,
so I'm gonna say these things to you.
So a bit about Anemone Hug Interactive, my studio.
So like the rest of the shows, we've been in business
for about four years, and we've grown a lot
through that time period.
And through that whole time, from the first year
to the fifth, we've spent 50% of all hours company-wide
on internal IP development.
And that's a direct result of the fact
that we've done a lot of client work.
That's obviously really great, but what are other reasons
why you might wanna pursue this way of running a business?
Okay.
You can't hide from the business stuff.
Like you actually have to be serious about this.
Like you have to do,
like you actually have to incorporate
and you actually have to set up legal agreements
and you actually have to have real negotiations
and you have to do accounting and da da da da da.
Like if you're just hiding in a basement
for like a bunch of years working on your first game,
it can shelter you a lot from those business realities
that you're gonna really need to know how to do
once you've shipped a title.
And with that reliable income stream that is not from product,
you're going to be able to hire a lot more diverse team.
Overwhelmingly, the people with free time and capital
are English-speaking North American white men,
people that look like me and the other business partner who
is involved in this equation.
Many people can't work speculatively.
Some people need a stable job, no matter how talented
or driven they are.
If you can offer people real employment
while you're running your studio,
you're going to have access to a much larger pool of talent,
and it's going to make everything a lot easier.
So now, before you actually start your studio,
before you do anything at all,
there's just a few quick tips I'd like to give you.
First, these two things are really important
if you can do it.
One, have an entire year's worth of runway before you begin.
Even if you don't make a single dollar in the first year,
you should be okay.
Try and plan around this.
You might not need it for all 365 days,
but you'll be really grateful that you had it.
Two, if you are currently employed, get credit now.
This seems super evident to be in retrospect,
but it is way easier to get credit if you have a stable job
than if you are an unemployed person who owns a studio with no value.
Right? Try and do both of these first.
But third, and this is my most important takeaway from the entire talk.
is get a mentor, right?
My previous statements about, like,
I don't have the answers,
is because my advice to you is not contextual, right?
Like, you're gonna find someone
who's in the space you're in,
who's in the physical location is who's in,
who's doing the kind of stuff you wanna be doing,
who's bigger than you are.
Someone who's already gone through the growing pains
that you are hopefully going to go through.
That person will be able to give you much better advice
than anything in this talk I can give you.
If you remember only one thing from my talk,
let it be this one point.
So now we're getting into the part of the talk
that arguably everyone cares about.
And that's how do you actually get client work?
And I'm gonna begin with a spoiler.
All right, this is an age test.
Okay, it's not this spoiler either.
So what's the spoiler?
This one.
There's no magic wand.
There's no secret trick.
There's no directory of client work
that you can go onto online
that only me and a handful of people know about.
There's no list of potential clients.
There's no one trick that game devs hate.
There's nothing like that.
It's hard to get client work,
and it's hard to do client work.
Now, with that in mind,
how do you actually do it, even if it's hard?
So the first thing, and people hate this one,
is always be networking.
I hear a lot of people grumble about this,
and if you manage to succeed without doing this,
you are a unicorn,
and you probably don't need any of my advice.
You're gonna need clients,
you're gonna need employees,
you're gonna need friends,
you're gonna need allies,
you're gonna need publishers,
you're gonna need everything under the sun,
and you don't know what you're gonna need
before you need it.
These people are going to be your future clients,
they're gonna be your future partners,
they're gonna help you ship games,
they're gonna help you do work,
they're gonna give you money.
Networking puts you in contact with other people,
and people matter.
Grow your team.
Provide solutions, not labor.
What I mean by this is become a full service outfit.
Try and avoid single contributor contracts.
What you wanna be doing is you wanna be pitching things
like features, or ports, or full games.
You wanna be offering something
that there isn't an obvious substitution for.
Now, how do you get those ones?
Is you want to be climbing the ladder.
I know I just said go broad at the beginning
and network like literally all the time.
What we also want to be doing is your clients
are overwhelmingly going to be organizations
that are a little bit bigger than you.
Really big orgs, sometimes you'll get work for them,
but there's a ton of other people in the mix
to get those jobs.
And organizations and studios that are the exact
same size as you, you probably can't hire them.
So remember, they probably can't hire you.
There will be exceptions to this,
but generally speaking, always be trying to target
the people who are just a bit bigger than you.
And if you continue to grow year over year,
you're gonna be meeting new members
of those ladders of rungs.
So you're gonna wanna meet a whole bunch of people
one year and the next year, the group after that.
Also, don't always look for game studios.
Look for games adjacent clients, non-games clients.
The advantages of these are manifold.
Being a direct contractor means
you can command better rates,
there's not an obvious substitution to internal development,
and just everything's easier.
If you can get these kind of contracts to do,
you'll make your life a lot more straightforward.
This one also seems pretty obvious to me, but I haven't fought hard enough for it,
and it's really hurt us in the long run, is get attribution. You want to start from a point
where your game studio's name is at the very beginning of the game you're working along
with all of the other studios on it. You're not going to get that, but that's going to be the
point you want to start in negotiations and work your way back from them. Attribution lets other
people know what you've done, and that's really important for getting future work,
and we've been bad about that, and it's hurt us.
However, we've been really good about this one,
and I know this seems pretty obvious,
but you get so much out of this.
Deliver on time and deliver on budget.
Be involved in the project estimation and get good at it.
People are gonna tell other people that you're good at this
and this is completely invaluable in this industry.
Very few people are good at this
and it's gonna get you a lot of work.
Also, working on your own games,
it's really good at being good at this.
Like, knowing that you're gonna launch your own title
on a particular timeline is really gonna help you.
So how do you balance this against internal development?
Now, keep in mind that all of the other stuff I just said
is going to seriously burn you out creatively.
I personally struggle with this a lot.
Development on our games suffers from my focus on business
issues, and I'm not entirely clear on how I'm supposed
to compartmentalize those.
Just be aware that getting and delivering client work
is going to take a lot out of you
and is going to take a lot out of your focus
on a creative endeavor, like launching your first game.
Let me know how.
If you figure out how to solve this,
I still haven't figured this one out.
This lack of focus has really tangible impacts
on your internal development.
Don't assume that just because you have 50% of the time
that you're gonna make a game in half the time.
It's probably more like three times.
Working on something a lot gives you a lot of deep focus
and allows you to involve in deep collaboration
which really improves your productivity.
If you're like switching between different games
like clients games and your games,
you're not gonna be as effective.
If you have a timeline that says it's gonna come out
in a year, it's actually gonna be three.
Now, fair beans, I stole that from Gwen Frey's talk.
It's really good.
Three steps for finding a successful indie studio.
If you like what I'm saying, watch that one, too.
Now, to do this work, and this is pretty obvious
in any dev land, but you want to have people
who can wear a lot of hats.
Like, just because someone can do a bunch of things
on your game, you might need them to do stuff for clients
that have nothing to do with your game.
Maybe they have a graphic design acubent.
Maybe they have 2D animation skills,
but you're making a 3D game.
You're going to people who can wear a ton of hats
to make this work.
And last but not least, protect your team from sales thrash.
It's gonna be really tough, you're gonna be out there
trying to get new contracts.
Don't expose your team to all of this.
You're already stressed out about it,
you don't need your 3D modeler panicking
about whether or not you got that contract.
Be somewhat transparent so they understand
the health of the studio, but every single potential client
doesn't need to be your employee's problems.
Anyway, I'm running out of time, and I hope this was brief but helpful.
And it was really tough for us to do this, and I'm sure it's going to be tough for you.
So if you want any help, reach out to me on Twitter or talk to me after the talk.
I'd love to get a little bit more in the weeds on this, I just don't have the time.
Thank you so much.
All right.
I'm Teresa Derringer and I'm going to speak a little bit more towards the specifics of how to run a studio without a surprise hit
using hardware and IP partnerships.
So we've all heard about indie mega hit darlings,
the hotline Miamis, Fezzes, Bastions, and Braids,
but I would venture that at least some of the people
in this room are not working on the top five
grossing indie games.
However unflattering it is to address this subject,
it's worth being honest about.
The truth is that most indie games are not household names,
mine included.
So while it's really obvious what to do if you have a total hit, which is keep at it, awesome,
or if you have a total flop, you know, maybe do something else,
there's a question of what do you do if your game is somewhere in between?
And it's a really tough question, it's kind of embarrassing to ask,
and it's a question I've had to ask myself.
With my first indie game, Cannon Brawl,
it made about $400,000 in sales and about $130,000
in contest winnings.
It took two people three years to make, minus Steam's cut.
It was about $70,000 per person per year.
It's not nothing, but it's certainly not
time to buy a yacht.
So where do you go from here if your game is kind of like
somewhere in between?
After a big launch, it can be really tough to get going on the next thing or even know what that next thing is.
But that's the most important thing for you to be doing right at that moment.
So you just have to pick a direction.
And for me, with Cannon Brawl, we got started because it had won a contest.
So we found another contest and that was the Oculus VR Jam.
And don't worry, this talk is not going to be about contests.
But it can be helpful to identify one thing,
which is who has too much money and not enough video games?
Well, not VC.
For a lot of economic reasons, I can't get into a 10-minute talk.
Funding is not usually available to small, creative studios like ours.
Usually.
But there is an exception, and that is with speculative hardware.
So we saw with VR, there was a burst of new funding in the scene,
but we've seen it before with other kinds of hardware, like the PS Vita and OUYA.
And our team's been pretty bullish about this speculative hardware we've developed for Gear,
Vive, Rift, Tango, Starbreeze, even Ciftio. And while it can be really fulfilling to develop for
this exciting new medium, and you're jumping into a community that's really lovely, you're all
fingering it out together, and it feels like you're laying the tracks for the future, I would say
there are some practical reasons to run away. The SDKs are changing out from under you.
There are no standards.
But more importantly, there are no users.
So to give you a sense of my first game in VR,
this was called Bazaar.
And it made $6,000 total on Steam, at least.
That's gross revenue.
Gross being the operative word there.
So without money, at this point, I
would say never develop for speculative hardware,
except if there's money.
So if you have a new platform coming on the market,
especially one in an arms race between hardware manufacturers
or platform interests where they're pouring money into it
and they need content to show off the product,
there is going to be some VC funding for games content.
That's going to make it look good.
You're also going to see grants that are coming directly
from the platform stakeholders themselves,
like we've seen with the Oculus VR.
research grant for $250,000 recently.
In addition to that, you're gonna see other companies
that wanna expand their brands
into this new platform space, the new hotness.
So we saw airlines, TV shows approaching our company
to see if we could help them with that.
So if you've taken the risk of becoming an expert on a piece of hardware where there are relatively
few users, so relatively few developers, you're putting your name in a kind of small hat for
winning contracting bids. Bazaar had absolutely abysmal sales, but it put us on the map as a
studio capable of VR development.
And that's how we were able to get the funding to make Race for the Galaxy in VR from Oculus,
or to do the TAMP with Discovery Channel and do the app for their content on Rift and Gear.
Now you can't always know if that cat is going to,
the hat, not the cat, is going to exist.
You can take some educated guesses
and look and see who's pouring money into the platforms.
But I'd say the biggest way to mitigate your risk here
is to keep your projects to six months and less.
That way if the hat never shows up, you didn't risk it all.
So never develop for a speculative platform,
except if there's money, and also, except if there's IP.
So there's a common catch 22 if you're a studio interested in getting involved with IP work
is that nobody wants to risk their evergreen IP on an unknown developer. So it can be really
hard to get that first one going. But if you can approach an IP holder
With a platform that they're not getting their door knocked down on,
there's not as many competitors,
you can get your foot in the door and build a relationship with them.
And that's how we've gotten some really top-tier board game IPs at our company.
This is how we got Ascension.
They've already got a phone app,
but we were able to approach them with a VR app and get that going.
And once you have one IP, you can really
use this to swing from one to the next and the next,
especially for us with board games,
because many designers have designed more than one game.
Publishers have published more than one game.
So it really helps your flow.
So we started with Ascension VR.
Then we made Race for the Galaxy, Roll for the Galaxy.
And now we're on Shards of Infinity,
which is in beta this week, if anyone wants to give feedback
on that.
And these are all board games on the phone.
They all share the same set of features.
They're all in the same genre.
So board games have a really interesting property,
which is that they come with expansion packs.
And these are these delightful little chunks of work
that are super flexible on your schedule,
and they have a really predictable return.
We find 15% of our sales, our base game sales,
will reap back with our expansions.
Your superpower as an indie studio is you are a unit,
a team of people who work really well together,
especially on small projects.
So you can get a project done faster than a PM at a AAA company can even get the sign-off
on the headcount to do similar work.
So leverage that.
Move around your projects on your schedule so that if someone comes to you and they have
something that needs to get done yesterday, you just drop it and drop what you're doing
and you say, yes, we can do that.
And that's what expansions are really good for that.
But any small chunks of work will work for that.
Also, if funding gets delayed for a project,
then you can move those expansions up in your schedule.
So once you've found a genre, it's helpful to stick to it.
You can line up your next projects.
You can see once we started doing board game stuff
on the right, we started getting more and more projects
just flowing from one to the next.
The pink ones are the projects our studio has done.
Also, if you stick to a genre, you're
going to get a lot more return on investment for your tools.
So doing board game type of tools,
we have a lot of UI tools where we
can do a lot of transparency icons and careful attention
to draw order in 3D space.
You're going to get more value out
of that in your second, your third, and fourth title.
So you also, again, want to think about who has too much money and not enough video games.
Sometimes that's your players.
There's a big mistake I made with Cannon Brawl, which is it didn't have an existing genre when it came out.
There wasn't really a player base for a real-time artillery game.
So we had to do the work of not only building the game, but building a community for this kind of work.
Not the same thing with board games.
So you can just deliver something that the community is looking for, and it's a little easier.
Here's a picture of where our money comes from as a studio.
You can see we've moved from the longer project
to the shorter ones that are about six months.
And we make a lot of our money on direct sales,
but we still supplement that with grants,
work for hire, partnerships, and contests.
And Race for the Galaxy has been probably our top seller.
It's one of the top card games on iOS,
but we've also had plenty of failures.
The point of all this is that you as an indie studio
can do what you want, whether that's
working on a kooky piece of hardware
or working on a kooky game idea.
But if you don't win the lottery with that,
you're not out of the game.
You just have to balance out your workload
with some safer bets.
We have this idea of what it is to be indie,
to sometimes create this beautiful, glorious magnum opus
that takes seven years to produce, and that's very valid.
This is another way to be indie.
It's definitely not that.
This is being nimble, it's reacting to opportunities,
and staying alive to make those projects that you do love,
withstanding successes and failures.
Hello, I'm Tanya X. Short.
I'm the captain of Kit Fox Games.
And I'm here to present, I guess,
maybe a more traditional idea of what it is to be an indie
in that we still haven't managed to pay ourselves $70,000 a year.
That sounds great, but we are scrappily clawing our way up
every year, increasing our salary
through increasingly successful games, hopefully.
You might know us most through Boyfriend Dungeon.
We also last week announced we were
going to pair with Bay 12 Games to publish Dwarf Fortress.
And all of this does come back to a strategy
that we settled on about five, six years ago.
When we started, we weren't sure what we were doing.
We were just sort of working together
on trying to make a studio together that would survive,
that we could become better designers together.
Oh, the formatting's not great, but it's fine.
We want to make some of the best games in the world,
and in order to do that, we have to be happy,
and in order to be happy and make better and better games,
we have to survive.
And so,
When it all comes down to is every time we ship a game,
we're already in the middle of thinking
about what is the next one, and how do we
help the next one be better than the last one?
Not just better in terms of, I don't know,
review scores or sales or whatever,
but better in terms of how we make them
and how we feel proud of them.
So overall, we have made a lot of choices that
many would call maybe fiscally conservative, safer, less risky business practices.
Now Kickstarter doesn't really fit into any of those goals in theory. In theory, you know,
it obstructs your quality of life, it doesn't let you really practice your craft, and you can't
sustain a studio on it, that's for sure. But this actually does fit into our underlying strategy
of being opportunistic and by always trying to control our own destiny.
So what I mean by opportunistic is our very first game
transition is a really good example.
Our first game was Shattered Planet,
and it was a mobile and PC game.
And we were approaching beta, and the deadline
was coming up fast.
We were a bit behind.
It would end up getting delayed.
And our advisors who had helped fund
that initial seed of the game were getting very nervous.
But I heard about this cool new opportunity called
the Square Enix Collective.
And it was nothing at the time.
It was just a press release on Gamasutra.
But I cold emailed them, hey, can I pitch you something?
And they said, yeah, if you send me a good pitch in the next 48
hours.
So I actually set aside Shattered Planet.
Our advisors are freaking out.
What are you doing?
You need to focus on beta.
And instead I came up with the initial idea that would eventually become Moon Hunters.
And the reason I did that was because I needed the team to know that I believed in them more than just the success of one game.
That we were more than that. That we were multiple games. That we were going to survive.
And that we were going to have more beyond that no matter what happened to Shattered Planet.
There was going to be a continued Kit Fox.
So this sort of bleeds into the fact that we are very opportunistic about figuring out how our
next project is going to find funding and how it's going to help us survive even if it doesn't sell
very well, ends up with us maximally diversified, which absolutely impacts our strengths and
weaknesses as a studio. We're sort of maximally, like I said, we are maximally diversified. We've
been around almost six years now and we've released three major projects. We've announced three more,
two of which we're publishing, and we have another thing to announce actually.
You'll get a sneak preview of that at the experimental gameplay workshop on Friday,
if you stick around, but please don't announce it.
I don't know, it's supposed to be unannounced for another few months.
We'll see how that goes.
But the point is that we are now having two games simultaneously, side by side, in production,
our own IP for PC and console, despite the fact that none of our games have sold incredibly
well.
But it's because we've diversified
in terms of having the number of titles
and the variety of titles that we actually
started with a core, which we think of.
We can think of it in a few different ways.
Steam has been our core the whole time.
But system-driven role-playing games
is the core of what our audience expects from us.
And so we think all of our games have something in common
that appeals in that way.
So whether it's Dwarf Fortress or Moonhunters or Sword Boyfriends,
you're still going to have a good time with one of our games if you're into system-driven role-playing experiences.
And by having that core...
we can help move them from game to game more easily if our social media is all connected.
So rather than having a Moon Hunters Twitter and a Boyfriend Dungeon Discord, we just have a
Kitfox Twitter, we have a Kitfox Discord, and we have the wonderful Victoria Tran running that for
the last couple of years. It was driving me mad for the first four, and she does a way better job,
so I'm really glad we have her.
But the fact is that we've centralized it as a strategy,
because even though random gamer number five doesn't really
care about Kit Fox, there's no reason for them
to care about my brand, they're more
likely to move on with us to the next game
if they bond with us.
as a brand, but also they get to know us as people. So rather than getting really attached
to one game and one game's mechanics, which hopefully they also enjoy the game, they actually
attach to us and want us to succeed with our next game. And we have seen that as possible between
our Twitter and our Discord as they grow.
And all of that is possible because we've chosen to self-publish at every turn.
And again, this is one of those, if you can get away with it, absolutely try to do it,
because in the long term, we benefited so much from cutting our own salaries and doing
our own publishing and learning our own marketing.
All of our games can be found in one place on storefronts,
whether it's Steam or Itch or Nintendo,
you can go look at Kit Fox and see our games
and there's no other brands competing with us
for that airspace.
You know, Devolver isn't there,
saying this is a Devolver game,
which, you know, I respect them,
but I'm glad that when you go there,
there's no distractions,
that you can just see what are the Kit Fox games.
And speaking of fans being able to find us
and for us learning how to talk with them
and bond with them,
oh, no, that was incorrect.
We also sort of identified this chain of helping them grow to engage more and more deeply with
not just the game and the IP, but also just sort of bleed their own identity into being
bigger and bigger fans of us.
And a lot of them come in at the purchase step, of course.
But by helping figure out, like, how do we grow our fans to be super fans?
We spent a lot of energy, for example, having PAX boosts, even though we don't on paper
have any good reason for that.
We feel very deeply that that is part of our success over time.
So Kickstarter is part of that decision
to try to make better and better games,
because it helps us centralize our fans.
It helps us cement our brands.
And it helps us self-publish.
And so even though that money will never sustain us
in the long term, it does in the long term
serve all of those corporate sustainability functions.
I thought I would take a second to just actually be a little bit more transparent about our finances.
Diversification, you can see it on the two charts.
You have the development costs and the revenue of our games.
They're never quite the same.
There's a cancelled project in there that cost us money but actually maybe paid in some way,
and I'll talk about that in a second.
Early on, our payroll was our primary cost, absolutely.
But then the next year, so this is 2015, 2016,
you can see there.
And then the next year, because we had shipped
Moon Hunters and it did okay,
we had to start paying back loans and royalties.
This was all very complicated by the fact that we had income coming in from multiple titles as well,
so trying to calculate what was actually going on with our bookkeeping was more complicated,
but that's okay. Now, what I wanted to really note here was that we talk a lot about game sales,
and you probably got the hint from the people talking here previously, but that's the sexiest
money, but it's not the real money that a lot of us live on. For our first million dollars,
game sales were only 50% of that.
We had Kickstarter, we had some, well, did I call them investments? Yeah, we had investments,
and we had Kickstarter, and what is the, I can't even read, it's too small on my thing,
and Work for Hire, right. Yeah, we did some contract work that was very exciting,
and it helped us survive long enough to be able to use game sales as our primary motive.
Even last year, we did some Work for Hire that I can tell you about later.
So we haven't technically done all of these revenue sources,
but it's not that much of an exaggeration.
We get our money from everywhere we can,
and we stuff it into our bank vault.
And then at the end of the year, we look and see
if we can pay ourselves just a little bit more.
And maybe someday we'll reach industry average.
That'd be great.
And just as a side note, we did talk to a few of the other studios in Montreal,
and the top three, they did get their first million dollars from sales,
but the bottom three did not.
One did very well on Kickstarter some years ago.
One got most of theirs through government,
which I'm not sure if that's a grant or a loan or what's going on with the government, but yeah.
And then one had their first million dollars just straight from a publisher.
The point is there's no one right way,
but if you ask yourself what your goals are
for yourself, not only as a studio, but as a creator,
then you can see where your studio should be going
from here and how to get there.
But it matters what your goals are.
Different studios have different methods,
different constraints.
There's never one right way to run a company,
and anyone who claims otherwise
is trying to sell you something.
Thank you.