Welcome everyone to Developing Terranil, a strategy game about nature, not expansion.
Before we get started, just some introductions.
My name is Sam Alfred.
I'm the lead designer programmer on Terranil.
Being a programmer, this is probably more people than I talk to in a normal year.
I'm a bit nervous, but I think it'll be okay.
I work at a studio called Free Lives of dubious fame.
These are some of our other titles.
And we all live and work in the city of Cape Town in South Africa.
And as I'll explain, where TerraNull was conceived and developed ended up being quite important to its design.
And I just want to say that although I'm the one here giving the talk, TerraNull was developed by an amazing team of incredible people.
And I just drew the short straw.
So, hopefully most of you have at least seen some footage of Terranil, or it was supposed to be out by now, but game development being what it is, it's actually only coming out in six days.
So Terranil's a hybrid strategy, puzzle, relaxation game where you're taking a wasteland to this.
And in order to do that, you're using the
The normal verbs of the city builder genre, you're constructing buildings, you're constructing machines, but there are some differences.
Notably, and kind of what this talk is mostly about, Terrinal does not contain any of these things.
It's generally a mainstay of the strategy genre that exploitation of resources is just a core part of the game and that you need to chop down forests so you can build your houses or mine rocks to build up your castle.
Ternal doesn't have any of that.
It also has no land colonization, which is another common mainstay of the genre.
And it's not a game about unfettered expansion.
It's a very finite game where once you completely restore an ecosystem, you move on.
It's not a game you can play forever.
That's not to say these are inherently bad or wrong, but that's not the kind of game we wanted to make.
Just to go through the structure before we begin, what I'm going to be doing is I'm going to be telling the story of the game's development, and although presenting it in retrospect a lot seems obvious, the process was not always obvious, and at the risk of making a terrible pun, a lot of it grew organically.
Are we talking about what worked and what didn't in some of the lessons?
And in order to illustrate this, I'll go through some of the pillars of our design.
So let's start at the beginning.
Terranil started at Ludum Dare.
I can't say Ludum Dare with a straight face, so I say Ludum Dare.
And the theme of that jam was Start With Nothing.
The original prototype was a very literal interpretation of the theme.
It was a piece of wasteland with nothing on it.
And at the time I was playing a lot of Islanders, which if you haven't played it, you really should.
It's this incredible minimalist city builder.
But it's also really relaxing and doesn't have a lot of time pressure.
It's also not simulated.
So I wanted to make something with these city builder style mechanics.
but about nature.
And instead of building a city or a factory, you were building an ecosystem.
So just a warning, I'm about to show something really gross.
This was the original plan.
In my defense, it was a terrible camera.
It was 3 a.m.
local time.
I'd been jamming for 48 hours, and I never thought I'd have to show it at GDC.
I mostly just didn't want to lose it if I needed the whiteboard the next day.
And it is illegible, so I will explain it.
But before that, this was the result of the 48-hour jam.
Had six buildings, and you would build them, and your goal was to cover 50% of the landscape in greenery.
And this is how it worked.
So the beginning of a level, there were some rocks scattered around the map.
And on those rocks, you could build wind turbines, which would provide power.
And you could only construct turbines on rocks.
Power is important because it powers toxin scrubbers.
Toxin scrubbers would clean the wasteland and create fertile soil, which was a necessary step, before creating greenhouses, which would then allow greenery to grow on the fertile soil.
The greenery was both the thing that earned the currency and the goal of winning the game.
So you were trying to cover 50% of the map in greenery, but you're also using the currency to construct more buildings.
And I'll talk a little bit more on the currency later.
But there weren't enough rocks on the map to completely
reach the goal, so you needed a way to create more rocks.
And to do that, it was a rather complicated process of constructing an excavator, which would create straight riverbeds, and sometimes you would have to create more than one, and it ended up being this interesting spatial Tetris-y thing.
And then those riverbeds could be filled with water using a water pump, and the water would
create greenery on the riverbanks and also was used to power calcifiers which
are very hand wavy game magic ways of turning plants into rocks.
And then you could build more turbines on the rocks.
And so in this way, the rivers become like the veins of your operation.
You have to get water where you need power so you can construct turbines and so on.
And these were the results of that jam.
It did pretty well.
for us anyway, at our studio, when a jam game does really well, Ludum Dare, we generally think it warrants further exploration.
It's not necessarily a shoo-in for success, but it definitely means that we should be looking at it further.
But I want to draw your attention to a couple of things here, most notably the graphics result.
And so this original 48-hour prototype was full of program art, and I don't really think it
deserved first in graphics.
I have a theory about why I got that.
The idea is that players were just enjoying bringing life back to the barren wasteland.
Players really like coloring in books.
Players like turning something dirty into something clean.
You just have to look at something like Power Wash Simulator to see this happen.
And this can also be seen in the mood score a little bit.
But so it was quite promising.
We decided to develop it a bit further.
This was Terra Null then.
It was a tiny sapling.
And yes, the guy talking about the tree game is going to shoehorn a tree metaphor into his talk.
It's a building game.
It's about nature.
And we needed to figure out how to add to it.
The core loop was quite strong.
It was mechanically sound.
People were enjoying it.
And attempts to make it longer or
at all.
So to that effect, we decided, OK, what if we double down on the nature aspect?
And in order to do so, there are sort of three things we need to consider.
Nature's not homogenous.
It's varied and diverse.
It's full of cycles.
And South Africa, where we come from, has this incredible natural heritage.
This is a photograph from where we live.
This is like, I don't know, 30 minutes hike out of the city.
So on the first point, the original prototype had representations of water, soil, and greenery, and compare that to the complexity and diversity of flora in the world, to say nothing of animals and fauna, you know, you have
rivers with forests growing alongside them, which are full of biodiversity.
Wetlands are some of the most complex and important ecosystems on the planet, and even deserts are full of life that is specifically evolved to live there.
And so we were never going to capture all of the nuance and all of the complexity of the natural world in a video game, but we could do better than just greenery.
So biodiversity then would be the next goal that we wanted our players to achieve.
And this was kind of the first big lesson for us.
This idea that your players will care about whatever metrics you decide to track.
That is, we make biodiversity this goal of completing a level of Terra Null and
then players will begin to care about it.
No one at any point ever questioned why you used green money to build buildings, even though it made no sense.
You as a designer have the tools to tell your players what to care about.
So if you want to make players care about something other than gold or population or health points or territory ownership, all you've got to do is you've got to build it into the way to win your game.
On the second and third points, I need to take a brief biology tangent.
and talk about a floral kingdom of wildflowers that exists around Cape Town, where we're from, called Faneborse.
It's one of the biggest biodiversity hotspots in the world, and I want to talk about the protea flower specifically, which is the flower on the left.
Protea flower is the national flower of South Africa, and it is pyrophytic.
which means that it requires fire to germinate and protea flowers are super interesting where after they're pollinated they will actually close their petals and wait sometimes for years to be burned before opening and releasing their seeds and the reason they do this is so that all the grasses and the shrub beneath them is burned away and gives the seeds a better
chance with less competition to grow into new plants, and also the ash is nutritious.
And over the course of development, I would go on to discover that, or we would go on to discover that this kind of process of burning, whether it's human initiated or natural, actually exists in many ecosystems all over the world, but this was our example in South Africa.
So we found ourselves in a position where
We want to make biodiversity a core part of the game.
We can't break the existing loop.
And we have this great example of life and death on our doorstep.
And so we created another loop.
at the thing that you do after the initial reclamation phase.
So once you've reached a certain density of greenery and water, you would need to begin to diversify and improve the biodiversity of the landscape.
So to do that, the map would start with a couple of dead trees, and on those trees you would construct beehives.
And those beehives would create fynbos from the flowers, sorry, from the grasslands around them.
You could use a solar amplifier, which is a unnecessarily complex way of starting a fire, to then create a controlled burn, which would result in
ash and building husks.
You could then construct arboretums on the building husks, which would grow forests from the nutritious ash.
And then those forests were full of trees that you could use to build more beehives.
So that's how that loop worked.
At the same time, we were specializing the greenhouses into hydroponiums, which could create wetlands.
Hydroponiums could only be placed on low-lying ground near to rivers, and it would create wetlands.
And the other one is a biodome, and that was the opposite.
It would create arid plants, but it needed to be in a dry place, far from water.
And all of these things together became the goal of the second phase of a level of pteranodon.
You needed to improve the biodiversity.
And this had some significant implications for the design.
Most notably, it became again about balance, which was sort of
hand-in-hand with the idea of it being about nature, because nature is not about infinite growth.
It's ecosystems naturally find an equilibrium and balance.
And so the game is about balance.
If you use tiles for a wetland, implicitly you cannot grow a fynbos there.
Or your forest, if there's too much forest, that's almost as bad as having not enough.
Hand in hand with that is the idea that the game is finite.
To this day, we still receive requests from players to expand the map to be able to buy more territory and that's completely contrary to the design of the game because if you run out of
If you run out of land because you haven't created a good balance then you kind of ignored what the game is trying to tell you to do and if we let you then just buy more land so you could create the wetlands you missed out on kind of invalidates the philosophy.
This would become our core design pillar, that we are not doing a whole lot of the things that are normally done in strategy games.
So we need an alternative.
We need a place to look.
And we would turn to nature for inspiration over the coming months and years.
This is what a level of terrenal might have looked like at that point, and it looks good.
You've got your wetland and your fynbos and your forests, but there was a looming problem here.
And you get to see my fantastic editing skills.
Copy paste.
This might have been the result if we just added another layer of buildings.
The thing about making a game where you take actions by building things is building things is your main verb.
So we needed
to keep building the same game, we need to keep the verb the same, and you need to keep building.
But if you just kept building, then you would end up with something like this, where it's beginning to resemble a city or a factory or something like that, when really we wanted players to be focusing on the nature.
So we needed to keep the verbs the same, but we needed to not add more buildings.
So the kind of flash of inspiration came in the fact that Terranils never had a sell button.
Terranils never had a sell button because, like Islanders, it's an order of operations puzzle.
You have to build the toxin scrubbers before the greenhouses, otherwise it doesn't work.
It's not simulated per se.
That's why I call it sort of a half strategy, half hybrid puzzle game.
But if we created buildings that could remove buildings, then we would be keeping the verbs the same, but also not adding more buildings to the landscape.
And then once we made that connection, recycling became a natural extension of that idea.
Where does all the stuff go once you remove it?
So the final phase of a level in TerraNL is the recycling phase.
Recycle use these recycling beacons or recycling silos To recycle all of these buildings and then you would use You would use a loading port and Wally To to ship them to a rocket silo where they would get recycled into
a rocket of recycled parts, and then you would blast off and leave the landscape behind.
And it wasn't as mechanically deep as the previous two stages, and it was a little bit more of a victory lap, but that didn't really matter.
And it didn't really matter that there were no buildings left, because you ended up with something like this.
And that was great.
Players loved that.
You got to leave a paradise behind.
There's another mechanic involving weather that I haven't spoken about yet, but more on that later.
So we add recycling to our mechanics pillar, and this was the result.
At this stage, TerraNode was still a free prototype on itch.io.
That graph at the bottom is daily downloads.
The first spike you see in January 2021 was the biodiversity update and then the second spike around June is the recycling update and it was really resonating with people that were making YouTube videos and getting excited about it.
Still a free prototype.
Watching people play, watching YouTubers, reading comments, we realized that what really resonated with people was the overall experience.
It's the fantasy of cleaning up the wasteland.
The puzzle mechanics were good, they were fine, but without the experience they wouldn't have been sufficient.
I don't think anyone would have been playing the game if not for the feelings they were getting with the experience of cleaning up.
All of the pillars then became in support of this idea, this experience of restoring and healing a wasteland.
Right.
So the game was promising.
It warranted progressing beyond the prototype phase.
So we decided to...
adopt it as a real game rather than just a free prototype.
As I've said, we believe that it was the experience of playing Terrinal that was resonating with players, but we had these theories and we wanted to answer the questions.
We also had a large amount of tech debt because we were building from the Game Jam code base, which is never, ever a good idea.
And so naturally, we did what the most logical thing to do when you have a really promising game is we chucked it all out the window and started from scratch
Central to the experience of restoring and this experience of restoration was not just the design though.
I just want to make the point, and this is a design talk so I won't dwell on this for long, but the other disciplines were at least as important as the design and the mechanics.
At this stage, the design was ahead, sort of, because we knew what we needed to rebuild, but we were trying to figure out what a better art direction was, we were trying to figure out the music and the sound design.
And this was the most important lesson, really, that we learned making Terranil.
So, talk a bit about music and sound quickly.
Guy on the left there, his name is Maydan, he's our composer.
He's not actually a Freelives employee.
We used his free music in the prototype and it was so good that everyone kept asking us for the OST.
So we decided, you know, we've got to have this guy.
He had this
incredible natural piano that evoked wonderful emotion.
And at the same time we were working on a parallel ambience prototype, which is that picture on the right there, where, and this made it into the final game, the cursor internal acts like a microphone where there's spatial audio based on the current
vegetation around your mouse cursor, but also the buildings, so that moving your mouse cursor from ocean to beach to wetland to forest, you'll hear something different every time.
And so we have this physical instrument and physical sound coming into the game.
At the same time, we were pursuing some art experiments.
It was a beautiful game about nature, so we were like, everyone loves Ghibli, we love Ghibli, let's make it look like Ghibli.
These are some of those early experiments.
The one on the left there, you can see is very sort of anime inspired, and that had a big problem though, because with that kind of art direction,
backgrounds fade back and the foreground elements and the important elements that the player plays with are generally cel-shaded and they're much more noticeable and that's kind of the opposite of what we wanted for Terra Null is that the buildings ended up dominating when we wanted the nature to be at front and center.
And then on the right there you can see an early 3D prototype and that was cool.
That gave us a lot of confidence in the idea of moving away from pixel art because
Pixel art inherently, because of its nature, it's all jagged edges.
And this gave us softer shadows and softer curves everywhere.
And in that one, nature was balanced much better with the buildings.
So these are some more of the art experiments.
And on the right-hand side,
was a diorama we created to kind of test the waters of the new art style against our community.
And unfortunately, or perhaps fortunately, it got mixed responses.
People weren't so fond of it.
part of that was they missed the iconic wind turbines and the way we understood that was here's this real-world anchor that it's a fantasy but there's this real-world anchor that allows people to understand and relate to what's happening in the game and I also want to draw your attention to the
the bottom left of that image where you see some conveyor belts and concrete walls overgrown with greenery and we were busy trying to figure out the story of the world and what had happened and was it important and what we decided was it's not a game about everything that had gone wrong in the world and hitting our players over the head with
Oh, industry has ruined the planet and now it's up to you to fix it was kind of contrary to the philosophy and the feeling we were going for.
What had happened to the world was less important than what the player was going to be able to achieve.
And so in the end, we didn't have any of that stuff.
We just had these barren wastelands.
Around the same time, this was
When most of the global lockdowns were happening, we were beginning to see reports out of New Delhi that they could see mountains that had not been visible for 50 years.
We read this blog post by someone from Manila who played Terranil and was arguing that
Terranil worked, and this being the pixel art version of Terranil, because it embraced the fact that it's not the responsibility of individuals to restore the problems of industry.
It's the responsibility of industry to restore the problem of industry.
And industrial problems require industrial-sized solutions.
And that really sort of
made us think about the fact that we had these dinky Ghibli styled windmills and things when actually we needed to be embracing the fact that this is a hard problem and presenting it as needing sophisticated tools and resources was much better.
The other thing that was happening was we were realizing this game is
This game is a conduit for climate positivity.
People playing the game have often told us that it helps ease their climate anxiety.
It helps them feel agency that they can do something about the climate crisis, even though it's a fantasy and it's made up.
It gives you the idea that, hey, maybe we can do something about this.
And so those things go hand in hand with each other.
And so this is sort of where we settled in terms of art direction.
It ended up being more industrial, more painterly, less obviously Ghibli influenced, and more focused on the nature.
And we were beginning to see that there was a third pillar to our design, which was the idea of emotion in design, and that this wasn't necessarily something we started, set out to.
It's not necessarily something we set out to do, but realizing that the emotional aspect of the game was really important, at least as important as the mechanics, meant that it became the third pillar of our design.
And just because the design was mostly just copying what the prototype had already done doesn't mean there wasn't some innovation also happening in design land.
We added a rain mechanic.
where initially this was mechanically motivated because it's a strategy game and there's a lot of min-maxing.
You want to make sure that you get the best bang for buck.
You don't spend your resources restoring something
a small piece of wasteland.
And so what ended up happening is by towards the end of a level, players would have these horrible little holes in their landscape where there was still wasteland.
And so we created a rain mechanic and a climate mechanic where once you restored the local weather system, it would start raining and then it would fill in the gaps.
And as I said, it started as a mechanical thing, but it ended up being unexpectedly emotional.
It was almost like the game was saying to players, you've done enough.
Nature will take it from here.
And this was a little bit of a revelation that the design could also support moments of beauty and the features didn't all have to be mechanical in nature.
So, as I was saying, we restarted the game and we put it out on Steam Next Fest and it blew up.
It was way, way more
have way more traction than any of us expected.
When we put out the announcement trailer, all of us, including our publishers at Devolver, were like, what?
We got in touch with Netflix, and we started talking to them about, or they got in touch with us, actually.
And they started talking to us about doing a mobile version.
And watching people play the demo, the Steam Next Fest demo had about 100,000 plays in a week.
people were talking about the emotions and the feelings and not the mechanics.
So I want to read out one of these.
It was lovely to see the barren wasteland start to come back to life as I tended to the soil and the climate.
Then a storm rolled in and it started to rain, and I was a little overcome with emotion.
We started wanting to make a strategy game.
This was not the direction that we originally intended going, but we ended up trying to listen to what people were really enjoying.
In order to respond to the overwhelmingly much larger response than we anticipated, we decided we needed to go back to the drawing board and make the game a bit broader.
like
To go back to this idea of looking at nature for inspiration, we looked at the Koppen-Geiger climate classification system, which is the classification system of five broad categories and about 16 subcategories of biomes on Earth.
And we thought, wouldn't it be cool if we can make one level for each
broad category, and those being the temperate, tropical, polar, continental, and arid.
And you only see three here, because I've showed you one already, and the fifth one was cut because game dev.
And in the end we decided we were only going to have one level per region, which was a difficult decision to make, and I'm still not sure it was the right one.
We'll find out in six days.
But the idea there is people loved the nature aspect, people loved seeing new environments, and so we didn't want to overstay our welcome anywhere and make multiple levels in one region, because each region had brand new mechanics, brand new biomes, brand new animal species, brand new buildings.
And so I want to give you some examples of other ways we kind of followed the guiding star of using nature as inspiration when we were expanding the content.
So the first is to do with coral restoration projects.
This is a real life conservation technique where I'm sure many of you know that coral reefs all over the world are dying due to increases in sea water temperature and
There's coral bleaching due to acidification.
And in the restoration of coral reefs, what conservationists often do is they will create these like pools of seawater on land with steel frames immersed in the water.
And for some reason that maybe someone who knows the stuff better than I do could tell you, coral really likes growing on steel.
and in some places they even sink old World War I battleships to create artificial reefs as a result.
But using these steel frames you can take an existing coral, a piece of live existing coral, and through a process called microfracturing you can spread it out and then make it adhere to the frame.
and this increases the surface area of the coral and allows it to grow a lot faster.
And then once it's matured that entire frame can be dropped in the ocean and over time the coral will just grow over the original frame.
And so the way we codified this in a video game is we have this coral lab which is built
which is built on top of a greenhouse.
It's part of our phase two in the tropical region.
And what you do is there's a monorail system in the tropical level that you then use to transport this into the ocean.
On the top right, you can see that was our geothermal power plant.
And yes, I'm aware that geothermal power plants aren't really built on lava fields.
It was too good an image not to include.
We wanted to have other kinds of renewable energy in the game, and Geothermal Power presented this interesting scenario where lava
kind of behaves like water in the game but it's also a lot more tricky and can cause ash and fire and there's interesting mechanics around that.
And the third example at the bottom is kelp forest.
We also drew inspiration from real-life conservation techniques.
Kelp forests often lose their habitats to purple sea urchins.
Kelp needs to grow on a rock.
is
used to be populations of sea otters who naturally eat purple sea urchins, keeping those populations in check and meaning that kelp forests can continue to grow.
And then in turn, the sea otters live in the kelp forest, provide protection from predators, etc.
So in Terra Null, we have kelp forests that you can then create sea otters to live in the kelp forests.
And this is just a couple of other examples of looking at the natural world conservation techniques for inspiration of mechanics.
So we add regional diversity to the mechanics side.
Yeah, read ice level, I guess.
But I do want to talk a little bit about what didn't work because it wasn't all smooth sailing.
This was our most developed thing that we had to chuck out.
This was an attempt to create a loadout system and a meta game.
I feel like it's the
purview of every strategy game designer ever.
That game would be improved with a meta game, but anyway.
Loadout didn't work, and there are sort of three reasons why I think it didn't work.
The first is that loadouts work really well when you have lots of different things that do the same thing differently, i.e., you have lots of towers that all deal damage to creeps, but in different ways.
whereas in Terra Null you have lots of different things that do different things differently.
It didn't really make sense when everything was so specifically localized to give players the option to choose what they wanted because they would always just choose the same stuff.
Two, it was contrary to what was making the game good and what people were enjoying about the game.
I don't think I ever saw a comment or a tweet that said, geez, you know what, this game could need a metagame.
Yeah.
And three, we had no time.
We had quite a stringent externally imposed deadline.
Deadlines have a way of sharpening your priorities and as such this just kept getting pushed to the bottom of the list and it kept getting smaller and smaller and eventually we decided to do a level select thing instead.
There were some mechanics that worked just about well enough.
They're still a bit icky, but whatever.
This is our first powers and then abilities iteration.
We realized quite late in development that we had to add a second verb to the game that, as wonderful and elegant as it would have been to only have the one verb of building buildings to influence the game state,
We needed some buildings to be able to do a second action.
And it felt ugly.
It felt like at the end of the game there are only a handful of buildings that have this mechanic.
But it was kind of necessary.
In the end, mechanics just needed to be good enough to support the experience.
With the experience being the most important thing, we put the bullet and made something a bit ugly.
This is our appreciate mode.
This was added right at the end of development.
What happens here is, once you finish a level, you get the opportunity to appreciate it.
This is both to appreciate nature, but also to appreciate your hard work, and it has these close-ups and these far-outs.
And we never would have bothered with a feature like this if we weren't listening to the game, because it's not a gameplay mechanic.
It's a feature to allow people to enjoy more what they're already enjoying.
So it's like this slow nature documentary style of thing.
So that would be the final point on our emotional pillars, this idea of relaxation and appreciation, to appreciate
what you have done.
On the flip side, it was really important for the game to be a bit challenging, that you're restoring a barren wasteland.
You're trying to bring life back to a place where life hasn't lived for I don't know how long.
If it didn't feel difficult, it wouldn't feel earned.
If we just gave players a paintbrush and said, you can paint whatever you want, you can just place these flowers over here,
wouldn't have had the same emotional resonance.
So this balance between the relaxing elements and the challenge elements of Terranol actually became one of the most difficult parts of the design.
And balancing those things against each other, yeah, I hope we got it right.
So this is the final picture of the design.
We have the mechanics on the left, nature in the middle, and emotions on the right.
So, to sum up, these are the main takeaways for us.
Genre rules exist for a reason.
If you're going to decide to not follow the established rules of a genre, you better have something to replace them, because even though we had this idea of following nature and looking to nature for inspiration to replace what we were losing from ignoring all the normal rules of strategy games,
Oftentimes we just felt like we were completely without a rudder.
We didn't know what to do.
They're just trying to figure it out so even then They're there for a reason and you need to have a really good reason to ignore them and If you do you need to find something to replace them You have you could
And we have probably alienated quite a lot of the strategy game audience as a result.
People who like playing games where you build the same city for many hundreds of hours will probably, well, I don't know, maybe they'll like Terrinal, but it's very different to what they might expect.
But hopefully, by not adhering too closely to the rules of the genre, we can also begin to cultivate a new audience.
And finally, and I've been saying this throughout the talk, everything in the game should be in service of the experience.
Nothing is above the experience, whether that be mechanics and design, or art direction, or audio.
More lessons.
As I said in the beginning, players care about the resources you track.
If you tell them something is important, they will care about it.
There's no reason you have to have population as the resource you track.
You can have a different resource you track, and players will care about it.
Players like coloring in books.
They like filling in gaps.
They like making things dirty clean.
making things dead alive.
And finally, suboptimal design, like our ability system, which still feels pretty dirty to me, is okay if it supports the experience.
Because nothing is above the experience, it's okay to make those concessions.
And I'm slightly short on time, but that is what I have for you.
Thank you for an amazing presentation.
This is eye-opening, like insanely smart with a mouse cursor, like tracking the sounds.
My mind is blown.
I have a question that maybe goes a little bit beyond your talk, but I think it's also quite fitting to your lessons.
Do you think in order to be able to pull this off in the real world, we need to change the currency that we're tracking?
And so you asked if we want to pull this off in the real world, we have to change the currency we're tracking.
Yes.
Thank you.
So I have a less profound question.
Thank you again for your talk.
I can't believe I haven't heard of this game until today because I am currently in still very game jam rudderless level prototyping stages of a similar idea.
where instead of starting with a city builder and turning it into a nature game, I'm starting with Minecraft and turning it into a nature game.
Right.
And I'm encountering a lot of these same problems that you've been saying about feeling rudderless and feeling like there's a lot of discussion to be had about, like, avoiding the comfortable mechanics of your genre.
Like, how much do you have to concede to the idea of, like, you're still building buildings.
but they're in the service of this larger goal.
Yes.
And I guess my question is sort of how do you navigate that internal or social experience of deciding when to concede to comfortable game mechanics and when you really want to force the experience and what is too comfortable and what is too far in the other direction
Right, so you're basically asking how to find the line between what genre norms do you accept and what do you not.
Do I put a furnace in my game is sort of the summary of my question.
Right, do you put a furnace in your game.
Well, our feeling anyway is that you can't change everything, right?
The innovation happens when there is some familiarity for people to latch on to.
But then, once you have that familiarity, you can then begin to challenge things.
So, do you put a furnace in your game?
I'll have to maybe think about that.
I would say that
Pick a pillar, whether it's controls, mechanics, whatever, and make that familiar, and then try to change something else.
But also, what we discovered with Terra Null is we did a lot of testing it in the real world.
When we had it on itch.io, it was free, and we just saw what people were enjoying.
So that also is a valuable way of gaining more data.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks so much.
It was a really interesting talk, and I'm so excited to play the final build of the game.
I wonder if you could talk a little bit more about your process of translating research into mechanics.
I was really intrigued by some of the little scientific details that you were talking about, and I'm curious how you came upon those and how you worked with that data, I guess, in conversation with your design process.
Sure, sure.
So in order to translate some real-world techniques into mechanics, we generally, as I said, we started with wanting multiple regions to the game.
And what we would do is when we got a new region, we would try and do some research about what grows there, what lives there.
Is there anything weird and interesting and unique about it?
Is there some weird process we've never heard of that we can then turn into a mechanic?
And in some cases that there was, and in other cases we had to come up with stuff.
But it was mainly just because we had this idea of we want to try and represent the real world, we could just
look and research that particular region and then see what we can find.
Yeah, that's really interesting.
Thank you.
Cool.
Anyone else?
Well, thank you.