All right.
Hello.
Hi.
My name is Mullen Leo.
I work for ILMxLAB as director of content and platform strategy.
First of all, I'm supposed to make a couple of requests that electronic devices are turned
off or to silent, and that at the end of the talk you fill out the survey.
If you like it.
If you don't like it, then don't.
So we're excited to be part of the new GDC vision track, which
kind of invites contributors to sort of gaze
into the crystal ball and make predictions about the future.
And then those will be put in the GDC vault.
And then years from now, people can look at it and laugh at how
we were wrong about everything.
So making predictions is particularly hard, I think,
about things like VR and AR and mixed reality,
because there's still so much in their infancy
that it's really hard to speculate on how they will
affect our lives in the future.
Astronomer and author Clifford Stoll famously wrote,
Discount the fawning techno-verbal about virtual communities.
Computers and networks isolate us from one another.
This non-place lures us to surrender our time on Earth.
A poor substitute it is, this virtual reality.
He wrote that in 1995 in a now notorious Newsweek article
on why the Internet will never take off.
It actually took courage for him to put something like that in writing,
and he's been mocked for it ever since.
So I'm counting on two things today,
that it'll take at least a few years for you to figure out that I'm wrong about everything.
And secondly, I didn't put anything in writing, I just put a bunch of pictures on here.
So speaking of the Internet, early visions of shared VR communities and worlds like the
1992 novel Snow Crash, which introduced the term metaverse, were certainly influenced
by impressions of the Internet at the time.
And oddly, in spite of the vast technological advances
and social changes over the last 25 years,
the pop culture predictions for what VR will be in the future
haven't really changed much.
So from the metaverse in Snow Crash to, you know, the oasis in the upcoming Ready Player
One film, there's really a common theme here of the future of VR, sort of as a walled-off
substitute world that we escape into while outside the real world sort of descends into
a dystopian nightmare.
Maybe one reason why this prediction hasn't really changed much
is because we tend to consider VR in isolation.
But when you look at truly transformative shifts in technology and culture,
they often don't stem from a single technological advancement,
but from the clash of multiple, at first seemingly unrelated,
breakthroughs that then combine into a catalyst for change.
So, for example, it's easy to think that our current world
is a product of the Internet age.
But that's too simplistic.
The internet certainly played a big part in it,
but our popular culture was built
on the confluence of many different technical
developments.
Take something as simple as a video chat filter.
The technology required to make something like this possible
is much more than just the internet.
There's portable computing, high speed wireless connectivity,
miniaturized cameras, multi-touch screens,
real-time rendering, face recognition, feature tracking,
and many more.
So to look at VR in isolation when making future predictions
is too reductive as well.
At ILMxLAB, virtual reality experiences
are a big part of what we create.
But we chose to call our mission something broader,
immersive entertainment, because we
believe that storytelling and world building that places you
at the center, that lets you step inside the story
and become part of the world, will
develop into many different experiences
in different places, virtual, real, and everywhere
in between.
Two core concepts of the original metaverse idea
are a persistent social world and persistent avatars.
So in most fiction about VR, the only way
to access a virtual world and to have agency in it as an avatar
is through a headset.
Right now in games, many people enjoy building up an avatar over hundreds or even thousands
of hours, in some cases, with all its stats and possessions.
But being in VR commands 100% of your attention, and many of us can only afford to completely
tune out the real world for a couple of hours a day at the most.
So to start with, why not instead engage that same virtual world in different ways throughout the day?
So if you're really into that space wizarding world, then on the way home you could on your cell phone have an AR geolocation experience where you collect some ingredients.
Then at home on the couch with your tablet you use those ingredients to craft some potions or acquire new spells.
With a game controller on your TV, you can fly your wizard spaceship
through an asteroid field to the Wizarding Championship,
and then for the really intense wizard duels, you jump into VR
and use your newly learned spells.
The virtual world and your identity in it remain the same,
but the way you interact with that virtual world is flexible enough
to adjust to your desired depth of engagement from moment to moment.
There are non-VR games that have already explored this to some success.
But these experiences don't have to be exclusively digital either.
You could go to a themed hotel or escape room or even a theme park
and be recognized as your persistent avatar
with its unique history and traits
and participate in storylines that connect across these.
And a themed location or theme park
offers a level of immersion that you can't create at home,
even in VR.
You can have face-to-face social interactions
with your family or friends, walk
among elaborate physical sets, actors in costumes,
sensational practical effects, thrill rides.
And in the future, those location-based experiences
could even be enhanced by mixed reality glasses
to add magical and impossible elements into an already
elaborate fantasy world.
If you want, you could participate in this out-of-home adventure as your avatar,
and when you return home, your storyline continues in the digital world.
The stories you experienced in the physical world
could become part of that same ongoing biography.
Our homes are changing too.
As IoT connectivity is catching on,
cloud and edge computing will empower everyday objects
with more information and abilities.
The individual object doesn't have to be complex or expensive.
A smart speaker isn't very smart on its own.
It can't do speech recognition, natural language processing,
speech synthesis without the cloud server that
does the computational heavy lifting.
But when connected, that little speaker
not only has much of the knowledge of the internet
at its disposal, it knows who you are,
what music and podcasts you like,
what time you should leave for the airport.
Those same devices can become access points for persistent virtual worlds as well.
And I think especially toys will follow this trend pretty soon.
You can have a toy droid that understands what you say, answers intelligently, and knows
you and your avatar, all without requiring expensive on-board electronics.
Because its brain is actually in the cloud.
This could even be a character that exists seamlessly
both as a physical toy in the real world
and as a digital character in the virtual world
and remembers your shared activities in both.
Mixed reality glasses will take this one step further,
allowing fully digital characters
to cross between the real and virtual worlds.
MR characters and physical smart toys
could even interact with one another.
Streaming television, real-time rendering, and speech synthesis
could allow for linear content to be personalized on the fly
so that an episode of your favorite show
features a cameo of your personal droid
or even references the latest adventures you had in VR.
Outside the home, self-driving cars
may well become an entertainment hub and platform.
What better time to dive into a virtual world
than when you're trapped in a metal box
that you don't even have to steer anymore?
So moments of sort of tedium and isolation
could actually become opportunities for entertainment
and social interaction.
In a matter of years, not decades, the same 3D models that are necessary for self-driving
cars and autonomous drones to navigate our cities could actually provide the foundation
for taking mixed reality out into the street.
You could allow to build a whole fictional world that exists layered on top of the real
one.
Real AI characters and even friends' avatars could join you in everyday life.
There might be big AR social events where people gather together for a spectacle seen
through mixed reality glasses, like a multiplayer MR narrative, which throughout the week sent
participants all over the city for their individual adventures, only to bring them together in
the same square for the big finale on the weekend.
All of that may feel quite far away.
And there are definitely technical hurdles
to overcome which are not only beyond our studio,
but even beyond our industry to solve on our own.
So there's backend architecture.
It's 2018.
You can't avoid it.
There's backend architecture.
There's improved sensing and mapping, fast connectivity,
plausible AI characters, and so on.
And without a doubt, by the time we get there,
the ideas I just presented will seem quaint and outdated,
and new ideas and imagination that we haven't even
dreamed up yet will emerge.
I think it's also important to briefly mention
social responsibility.
This is not just about the obvious dangers of technology
that allows people to live in different realities,
because to an extent, that's already happening right now.
But I think there's also just a more basic dimension to that.
There's lots of tangible, useful applications
of these technologies that I mentioned for education,
health care, civil engineering, and so on.
But what I've been talking about is just entertainment.
And as much as I like the idea of filling the real world
with magical virtual things,
we can't also solve some of the most basic societal problems,
then I don't think we've really earned the right
to use technology to make reality look nicer than it is
or cover up problems we'd rather not think about.
You can imagine that you'd end up in a black mirror version
of where you're walking down the street with your virtual pets
past the homeless tents on the sidewalk.
And I don't think we want to really end up there.
So anyway, that future may be a ways away.
But I think the tools to begin mixing
real and virtual worlds are already
available to everyone right now.
And I'm not just talking about ARKit and ARCore.
Last year when I moved back to San Francisco, I had to furnish an empty apartment.
And so the first thing I did, just for fun really, was to make a rough 3D model of the
flat and I just took a couple of dozen snapshots and fed them through photogrammetry software.
And then I blocked out the furniture arrangement with a few cubes based on the measurements
from the furniture store website.
And then I put on my VR headset, and I stood in my real living room,
and at the same time in my virtual living room,
just to see how that layout would feel.
And all that was required for that was really a point-and-shoot camera,
a laptop, and a consumer VR headset.
At the moment, we're still restricted by cables and sensors,
but within a hardware generation or two,
untethered, inside-out tracking headsets might free us up from that.
And I'm actually looking forward to just making different skins
for my apartment so I can then freely walk around
in the VR spaces.
Initially, this probably has to be done manually.
But I think very quickly, there will
be tools, games, and experiences that procedurally match up
walls and objects of the right size
between fictional and real world, both for VR and MR.
So your armchair could become a captain's chair in a spaceship,
your coffee table a control console,
and your wall a window to space.
Eventually, it's not just your living room you could map and skin.
Take a few coolers or trash bins out into your backyard, scan the environment and props
with your phone or headset, and skin them like the fictional world of your choice.
Then invite a few of your friends over with their untethered headsets, and now you're
together running and dodging behind cover, both in the real world and in the fictional
version of it, having a story adventure, playing sci-fi VR or MR paintball, or fighting side
by side against waves of AI enemies.
Network this with the backyard of a friend in another city, and in the virtual world,
her and your backyard become the same place.
Her friends in her backyard, your friends in yours,
moving freely, hanging out, playing games
in physical and virtual spaces simultaneously.
The relationship between physical world and virtual worlds
may turn out to be very fluid.
One virtual space may connect to multiple real places,
and a single real location can have many virtual layers
to choose from.
It actually seems unlikely that we will converge on a single metaverse
when we can choose from many worlds or even customize our own.
So, as technology advances, the digital and the real world
don't have to remain two separate places.
The metaverse doesn't have to stay trapped inside a headset.
It can end up being all around us.
We're going to move on to the panel discussion now.
And recently ILMxLAB and The Void,
using Epic's Unreal Engine, created Star Wars Secrets
of the Empire, an experience that
is a first step in exploring what
future immersive multiplayer content that
mixes physical and virtual worlds can be.
So while I play the trailer, please welcome to the stage
Camille Cellucci, head of production at The Void.
Judah Graham, Senior Producer at Epic Games,
and our moderator for this discussion, David Collins,
Sound Mixer and Editor at Skywalker Sound.
This is Von Bonner.
I have an assignment for you.
The Rebellion needs you, and we don't have much time.
You must work together.
You must not fail.
In disguise, your team's mission is to recover Imperial intelligence critical to our survival.
You're with me. The rest of you, get on that skiff. Do your best to act Imperial.
Looks like you'll have to fight your way out.
What is that?
This could be a threat to our entire existence.
Morning everyone.
Thank you so much for joining us this morning.
And thank you very much, Mon, for that fascinating talk.
That was really fantastic.
Give her a round of applause for that.
Thank you.
It's very exciting, and thank you for joining us here at GDC today.
I am very excited to host this conversation with Mo and Camille and Judah.
You just saw the trailer for Star Wars Secrets of the Empire.
Just curious, how many of you have experienced, first of all, how many of you heard of Secrets
of the Empire in the Void?
And how many of you have experienced Secrets of the Empire?
OK, great.
Great, great, great.
Well, before we get started, I want
to tell you a little bit about who I am and why I'm up here.
So I am a sound editor, re-recording mixer
at Skywalker Sound with a long history
of working in interactive.
I was at LucasArts for over a decade, PlayStation,
and in digital health at Akili Interactive Labs.
So I'm here because I am so passionate about this.
I experienced it recently at the Glendale Galleria, which
just opened.
Yeah.
My wife and I went through it together, and I was just totally blown away.
Even having worked on it a little bit, I voiced some Stormtrooper characters in the experience,
but it did not prepare me for sort of the hyper-reality of the experience.
I wanted to start just by having you introduce yourselves to everyone here in the audience.
Sure, well I'm Camille Salucci and I have a fairly long background in visual effects.
I feel like I was born at Industrial Light & Magic and got some good legs there and went
out and ended up being a couple of the big credits would be I was the visual effects
producer on Titanic.
I've done about 35 films, more recently The Walk that Robert Zemeckis directed and was
The line producer on The Little Prince, for those of you who had a chance to see it on Netflix.
So I come from that background of animation and visual effects.
More recently, I learned about... I wanted to work in VR and sort of transition my career.
And literally two years ago, I paid a full price ticket, sitting at GDC, learning as much as I can,
and wondering if someday maybe I would have enough knowledge to sit on a panel.
I'm not sure about the formal, but I guess I'm here.
So, anyway, and then I was at Google Spotlight Stories,
for those of you who know about their VR storytelling,
and I've produced a couple of things there before The Void came
and asked me to join them as head of production,
which is just, I'm just in the month and a half or so since I've been there.
Very cool.
So, I'm Judah Graham.
I'm a senior producer at Epic Games.
I was with ILMxLAB for...
Several years. My background is mainly in games.
I've spent, I don't know, the last 20 years in games,
working at Red Storm back in Raleigh,
and then I decided to come out and work with Activision for a good bit.
Did Call of Duty, and then after Call of Duty, I...
I was so fascinated when I put my first headset on and saw the potential of VR.
So it made a natural fit for me to go work with Vicky and the crew at ILMxLAB for a while.
When we got the opportunity to go down and kind of check out The Void, it was a brand
new platform at the time.
It was one of those kind of transformative moments where you just walk through it and
you thought, oh my gosh, this is where the future of...
of VR and entertainment is, it's the hyper aspect of it that I think really kind of pulls you in.
And so once we had the opportunity to work on that, it was just fantastic.
I mean, it's kind of, it's definitely on that forward thinking, you know,
future of where this entertainment can go.
You mentioned hyperreality just now.
I mentioned it as well.
Can you just talk a little bit, for those that don't know,
about what hyperreality is at The Void,
when you talk about that?
Sure.
So the idea being that
To start with, first of all, I want to acknowledge one thing,
and that was Curtis Hickman was supposed to be here today
on the panel.
And some of you might have come to see Curtis.
And unfortunately, rarely do we have so much rain in San
Francisco that flights can't get in.
But he couldn't get here.
So Judah graciously joined us, which is fantastic.
Thank you, Kelly.
And he knows a lot more about the producing of this, for sure.
But in terms of hyperreality, as some of you might know, Curtis is a magician, and his
idea is always about being able to suspend disbelief and do whatever we can to create
an illusion that your brain believes.
And so a VR headset on its own is pretty incredible,
but when you add things like physical location,
walls you can physically touch,
heat that you feel on Mustafar,
or wind that you feel,
or mist, or rumbles in the floor,
it really goes a long way towards making it an experience that is...
Completely, hopefully, convincing for the brain to say, I am here.
And so hyperreality takes it to that next level from sort of virtual reality in the headset
to a full sensory experience for people to enjoy.
The one-to-one is so powerful when you experience that.
I mean, your brain is telling you what you're seeing,
and then you're experiencing with all of your other senses.
I'm just blown away by it.
And Judy, can you talk a little bit about your work with Epic
and working together to bring that to life?
So Epic, obviously, has one of the best platforms.
And its true interest is really in helping
to stay on the cutting edge and help partner
with companies like ILM, XLAB.
I think for a big part of what the VOID project in terms of the challenges that we faced in
development from ILMxLAB, there's a lot of firsts that had to go into this.
So first time for putting a headset on and tracking people through a VR space but being
driven by motion capture as well.
So you have multiplayer along with...
The avatar is being driven in a virtual space untethered.
So all of those things that were kind of first,
I think it made a lot of sense for Epic Games
to kind of dive in and really see what types of things
could potentially add tech back to the engine
for the long term.
So since this was really one of those, like,
It was just a challenge I think on all aspects of trying to handle the amount of data that
we had to process.
So from Epic just kind of being able to step in and give some consulting and some advice
walked us through the process for animation and then rigging characters and doing blend
states and it just became a natural fit.
Not to mention, you know, building a virtual space that is one-to-one with a physical space
that you walk through that creates just such an immersive platform.
I mean, I experienced fear, I experienced, you know, exhilaration, joy, I was physically
touching things, you know, grabbing, solving puzzles, going through everything.
I mean, that really does seem like a monumental leap forward in VR.
Yeah, and I'll just jump in.
I think one of the things that I love most about The Void
is that there is that level of the one-to-one
where things really match up.
But then there's another level of illusion and magic
that sits on top of that.
My brother was a very intelligent person.
He works in medical research and has a PhD.
He went to see their previous experience, the Ghostbusters
one in New York.
And afterwards, I talked to him.
And I said, oh, yeah, I did the same thing in a warehouse in
LA, and he said, how could you do that in a warehouse?
It has to be at least like four stories for
the elevator, right?
And I basically had to tell him, like, you were never in an elevator.
You know?
And that's really...
For me, that highlighted the magic of this kind of VR, that it can create memories that
feel as real as real experiences that you've had.
Because the blend is totally seamless.
I mean, I mentioned I went through the experience
with my wife, and I was just like,
at one point, you have to cross this chasm,
and you're convinced it's real,
because you're getting all of the sensory information
plus visuals, and I'm just like, yeah,
and I'm holding her hand as we're walking through,
two stormtroopers holding hands, it's totally normal,
on this imperial outpost, no big deal,
they don't know we're spies.
But yeah, you really are crossing the chasm there
with the one-to-one, in a way.
You know, one traditional tool that storytellers have had for immersive entertainment is control
over camera.
And when I went through it, I was really struck by how not only is it obviously in VR, it's
completely 3D, but you're telling a story, an immersive story.
But not only do you not have control of the camera,
therefore, what I'm looking at, what I'm focused on,
but it's a group of people all focused on different things.
How do you see that, what some might see initially
as a disadvantage, how do you see that as an advantage
to this kind of hyperreality and as a creative tool?
That's a really good question.
I think,
Social aspects of VR is one of the things that's kind of lagged through VR basically coming into the spotlight and mainstream.
But I think being able to give, I mean, one of the really cool things about the Voids platform.
is that you can drive individual experiences as much as you can the social and group aspect of the experience.
So where you have, you can have full conversations because you're mic'd up and you're talking to the person next to you,
you're seeing them, you know how to navigate around them, but at the same time you...
As developers for VR, we can send individual experiences,
whether it's auditory or, because you're not truly
in the exact same space, you can send visual differences.
So I could be looking at one thing that's
completely different than, say, Camille or you.
And then driving different social aspects of that, too.
So you can part ways and then come back and have.
Like, group effort, team driven experiences where you're, you know, one group on one side
is actually solving one problem that converges and then you get back together and meet a
common goal.
So it's like, I think the void having that untethered aspect I think is just a.
A good driver for social.
I think also on what you're saying about sort of turning that to your advantage.
One thing I think for these kinds of immersive storytelling experiences
is that as sort of the storytellers have to have a little bit like looser grip on it.
You can't, you know, in a movie you control literally everything what people look at.
But what the nice thing about...
This medium is that you create more of a narrative framework.
But the experience that every person going through it has
is still their personal experience.
You know, people do different things.
They go different places.
They look at different things.
And that's sort of how people experience the real world
as well, right?
And so I think what, and that's certainly true
as sort of we progress to like, you know,
bigger social VR worlds.
I think.
We can't really necessarily control the narrative,
and shouldn't try to control the narrative down to the last detail,
but create basically stories and story frameworks
that leave enough room for individuals to have their own story in that.
Yeah, I would say one of the things that, a term that I learned actually from Vicky,
is we aren't, you know, it's been looked at for a long time about storytelling.
And what we're really moving into in this new world is it's more about story living.
You know, we are creating spaces and worlds where people have a chance to...
live out their own stories and create their own stories within a framework that we design.
So it's got some complexity to it because there's definitely a narrative that we want
people to experience, but we want to give them enough freedom to experience it in a
personal way.
And in that way, our hope is, especially with the social aspect, which we're really
We love to have that part of it, because we think it's a critical part in VR in the future,
is allowing people to have that experience with each other and carry memories.
So in essence, we're really making memories is what I like to think about.
And I think that that is successful even with this,
because when you have people coming out of the void
experience, they start actually telling their own stories
of what happened.
They're going like, oh, and then he shot at this guy,
and I was doing this thing.
And so they had their own story within that framework.
Well, let's talk about that framework and get into that a little bit, because the framework,
you're still having to build it and kind of anticipate what the boundaries are, you know,
and create, in certain cases, maybe the illusion of choice versus actual choice, you know,
creating set pieces or arenas or something.
And obviously storytelling, film, books, there isn't choice.
It's a guided narrative.
Do you see that going away and breaking down completely?
Or is that illusion of choice always
going to be a part of even something
as open as a group experience in immersive VR?
I'd say from my perspective, I think that you're, to have, one of the things that I
think people enjoy is being part of a world that has been created and been curated by
someone.
And so, certainly from our perspective, or I should say from my perspective, I'm still
learning everything about the full void perspective being a bit new there.
But what I can say is that I think that curated experience,
creating those worlds, is important.
And so giving people and trying to think about what the choice is.
One of the terrific things we have with AVOID is we get data from our users now
in a real way, in a significant way.
We actually have people lining up to take surveys, which is sort of unheard of.
Usually you're begging people to take the survey, like at GDC.
I'm going to fill out your surveys.
But often at the Void, because people want to express what
happened, they want somewhere to share it, somewhere to
talk about it.
And I've even seen people who don't know each other come out
being close, talking as if they were really good friends,
and they didn't know each other when they walked in.
So, but I think if it's just left where there's no curation,
from my perspective, it's kind of a little bit on the
choose your own adventure level, where that might take
off for a bit, but I think it often comes back to a curated
experience.
Interesting. And now in terms of world building, say, versus a content play, right?
Choose your own adventure. I mean that to me thinks about branching story paths,
which means you have to build all of these different story paths.
Do you see, how do you see that balance moving forward then,
in terms of the world building being the appeal,
or actually having customized stories for everyone that goes through,
or some limited version of that?
Anyone, any thoughts on that?
I think we're still so early in exploring that, and I think that there's definitely
really interesting developments that can happen in that field over the next ten years or so,
let's say.
One thing, I think it's impossible to create the kind of depth of experiences,
both story and worldwide, that could support something like the metaverse idea.
From a content creator perspective, you can't write hundreds of hours of branching narratives.
So I think...
We have to figure out things like letting users participate
in a meaningful way without breaking the fiction.
So user-generated content becoming part of that.
And procedural content.
And so procedural world building, I think,
is something that is really exciting.
And you look at something like No Man's Sky that not only
created this enormous universe, but created it
with a six-gigabyte footprint.
And so.
I think if we can, for example, figure out how to describe Mustafar in a procedural way,
then you can say, okay, I need a hundred more square miles of Mustafar,
and you can do that in an efficient way.
And it's much more experimental, but I think there's even interesting work starting to happen on
procedural narratives, on story engines, on creating systems that can create narrative situations.
And so I think if we can sort of push that further, then there's an opportunity there to build worlds
that are really complex, that can sustain themselves, where you don't, as a story creator,
have to create thousands and thousands of hours of content.
That's really interesting.
And one of the things you brought up in your talk, too, was this sort of cross-platform
idea of feeding that customizable content.
Any thoughts that you can give us about a future vision you may have for that?
How people will experience that via cross-platform and then go into an immersive experience?
Are you talking about cross-platform being multiple platforms, whether it's your phone?
Your phone, exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, we've...
When we started working on The Void and trying to come up with a really good design and something that would be engaging for the masses,
one of the things that's really challenging is, well, especially from a games background,
we all know what drives gaming and what drives storytelling and how to compel a player or a user going through the experience.
How to pull them along through.
choice and design and layout.
I think one of the things that was really tough with this is we kept trying to pull
back and simplify because there's an education process.
We would do some user tests and people would put the headset on and they get lost.
They didn't know what to do.
It was the sensory overload of this new world, this new experience.
For the first time, it became very difficult for them to just kind of, oh, what do I do?
Can I touch?
Oh, I can touch this.
And then they have to turn around and sit down and kind of then, oh, they were missing
dialogue if we had dialogue that was too complex.
So I think there's a phase of both, it's part of the adoption process, but there's a phase
of getting people comfortable in that environment and making sure that they're...
enjoying it and can function with it.
And then automatically the next step for them is more complex choice or diverging storylines.
I think at that point they could go into different directions.
As this matures, and what's exciting about the Void platform and what Epic Games is doing
long term by supporting these types of hyper-reality platforms or cutting edge platforms is by
doing that and supporting that, we're learning how fast this adoption is happening and staying
on the cutting edge.
These features can be used by the masses, and as a whole, I believe those all contribute back to the main goal, which is how this progresses in the future.
One of the things, just real quick, on cross-platform that we're excited about and we're actively
talking about, so it's future but I don't think it's 20 years in the future, but one
of the things you'll start seeing for sure is the interrelated content across platforms.
So talking with an AR experience that you might have on your phone, that for someone
who's really into that world.
There will be connections and tangents.
We're working across various companies to find the ways where those things connect.
Or you might have, you know, you might experience something at the void, but then have an opportunity
to go deeper into that world at home with your own VR headset.
So really working on how can we connect.
Well, having someone who is only going to do the one experience, have that be complete
enough for them, but someone who is interested in going across experiences or is a real fan
of that work, making it rewarding for them to see interconnections and have a deeper
and richer experience.
And I think it's important, again, not to think about sort of...
These virtual worlds are something that only exists in a VR headset.
You can very easily imagine asymmetrical experiences,
especially right now, I think a lot of people that are developing for VR
are struggling with the size of the market.
If you look at stuff like VRChat that took off a lot,
the reason why it became so popular is because...
You didn't have to be in a VR headset to participate.
At any point in time, a large number of the people in VRChat
are actually just on a desktop watching other people that have headsets.
And so you could easily imagine designing experiences where, you know...
If you want to be a Jedi and have a lightsaber, you're in VR,
but if you just want to run around with a blaster,
you can do that with a game controller.
And those people being in the same world
and still having those interactions,
some people in VR, some people outside of VR.
That's interesting, too, to think about cross-platform
versus the idea of the newness of the experience
every time someone walks into, say, Secrets of the Empire
versus looking forward.
Because do you see cross-platform maybe
as even a training tool to...
to experience these worlds that you're building.
For example, I had no idea where I was going,
and that was part of the illusion and part of the experience,
was the unveiling of the world.
But I could see maybe with cross-platform,
knowing exactly where I'm going,
If I step into it because I'm already so invested,
is that something that you're thinking about in the future?
Or how does that work possibly as a training tool for showing up?
I think you're absolutely right.
And as Judah said, especially at the moment,
people are not used to VR.
And so trying to tell them a complex story in VR
can be really overwhelming.
It's really hard to drive a complicated narrative.
I think audiences will mature and be able to take on more of that,
but if you can basically set up a storyline outside of that location-based VR experience
and people already know what it's about,
then that can complement those more visceral location-based VR experiences.
And in particular, if you then can have a persistent character
that goes across those things, so you're already
not only invested in the world, but you're
invested sort of in your role in the world,
and you play that character both at home
and in a location-based experience,
I think it would be interesting.
If I can just step in there.
And in Tim's keynote yesterday, he
was talking about how the adoption of cross-platform,
the way we're able to.
Fortnite is pioneering some of this, especially on the various platforms.
So cross-play between all of these various platforms, I think that is a real breakthrough
that will then just add more adoption into this type of space.
So if somebody is...
If you go to the void and you...
You go through the experience and there's something that you can take away from that
and it's on your mobile phone and it drives the engagement.
You're configuring whatever, your blaster or your lightsaber or something else and then
you're the social aspect of that.
Now I'm sharing it with you.
We're texting pictures back and forth or we're in the same...
I don't know if there's a subset platform from the void, but it's the takeaways that
drives the engagement.
And then you're going back into maybe you're at home on your PSVR and you put your headset
on and you're able to configure your character that way as well.
So I think all of those technologies kind of converging together in a way that drives
better cross-platform support for the individual experience.
is, in the long term, I think it's just going to help the void and those types of hyperreality
experiences mature a lot faster.
One of the things I was just going to say is we have some interesting statistics so
far from The Void.
And it's basically, as I said, people are lining up for surveys, and we found that 25
percent have no experience at all with VR.
It's the first time they've even heard about it.
They didn't know what it was in any form.
Another 25% have very little experience, like they might have heard about it, but they might not have experienced it.
Then 31% have some experience, and that some experience often is cardboard, or they walk by,
you know, one of the Best Buy demos, or an airport demo, or something like that. And then
19% have a lot of experience.
So in some ways, for me, the numbers in terms of people
being exposed to it were a little higher than I had
originally anticipated.
I thought it might be like 80% didn't know anything and
maybe 20% and it broke down further.
So I think more and more people, I mean it's
It's blooming faster than we might have anticipated,
but we still have a ways to go.
And I think The Void is a great way that's
allowing people to enter this world for the first time
and hopefully then take it on broader experiences.
Well, I will tell you, from my experience, going to the mall to basically go to this
new opening at Glendale Galleria reminded me of when I was eight years old and couldn't
wait to get to the Gold Mine, which was an arcade that I used to go to and just obsessed
over because that's where the magic was, that's where the new cutting edge was, the technology.
I had that same experience as a grown man going to Secrets of the Empire, and I couldn't
wait to go back.
and see everything that I missed, because I knew there was so much.
And all I could think of was stop...
I couldn't stop myself from obsessively thinking about where it's going to go,
what's next, and everything that I suddenly had to look forward to
that I didn't even know I had to look forward to.
I could sit here and ask you guys questions all morning,
but we have a room full of people that I'm sure have their own questions,
so I wanted to open it up to the room for questions.
We have time to answer if any of you have questions for our panelists.
There's a mic here and a mic right there.
While someone's walking up, I'm going to give you guys one
statistic that has been fascinating for us and not
necessarily what we expected.
We opened in the Westfield, London, and that mall.
And we thought we were going to get a lot of foot traffic
from the mall, which we are getting for sure.
But let me see.
71.6% of the people coming to the Westfield Mall, London,
it's their first time going to that mall.
And the reason they came is because of the void.
Wow.
Yeah, I've done both the Ghostbusters in New York experience and did the Anaheim one at
Downtown Disney when that opened up for Star Wars.
So both amazing and love the hyper-reality with the various effects.
I guess the question is, I want to do more.
So is there like a sequel coming out?
Or I don't know if you can say anything, but I guess I can continue to do Secrets of the
Empire again and again and again.
But just curious, like, what's next?
Well, we haven't announced our slate yet, but we will be
announcing the slate.
And there's definitely more to come, for sure.
And there are more locations to come in lots of places.
So you won't necessarily have to go to New York, only New
York or Los Angeles.
Hopefully, there'll be something
closer for you as well.
I just want to say great work, got a chance to go through the experience in Orlando.
You know, really fantastic.
A lot of great milestones being overcome, so great job.
But I'm curious about, first it was the Ghostbusters and now it's Star Wars.
What challenges do you see of authoring theme worlds outside of established and well-known theme worlds?
Well, you know, this is a journey that we're all on together.
We're all experienced.
Nobody knows.
We just keep putting our feet out there and experiencing.
We are going to be, and I can't announce the title,
but I can say we are going to be introducing an original IP
into the marketplace in the next few months.
And as we do that, it's going to be a lot of learning.
What is it like to introduce an original piece of IP that
doesn't have a $100 million ad campaign behind it, where
we're trying to get people to know about it?
And we're still a startup, so we don't have $100 million to
put into advertising.
So stay tuned.
We're all learning together, and we'll find out, because
we're going to be introducing that.
That's the next piece that will be coming out.
Hey, this sounds awesome.
I haven't experienced it myself, but I'm a chief engineer and it sounds like something
even I would pay for, so that sounds great.
I'm curious about, right now it sounds like it's very niche and kind of a high-end experience,
very customized.
It seems to me like we have the tools and capabilities where it could theoretically
trickle down where someone with moderate computer experience would be able to do something like what Noel was talking about,
take a picture of your house and then build an experience in your own home,
like a fun house or a haunted house where people could come in.
I'm just curious what your guys' thoughts are on the path to that,
how long would that take and some tools that might be in place to start doing that on our own.
I think that will happen fairly quickly.
I mean, I think that if you really
wanted to do that just with a tethered headset,
you could do that now.
It's just the length of your cable
will sort of limit how far you can walk.
But I think as you get into untethered VR headsets,
and certainly also like mixed reality headsets
meant for the home, I think that'll happen very quickly.
They rely on effectively inside-out tracking SLAM algorithms
that create a point cloud of things around you.
It becomes a question of whether that's exposed to you necessarily immediately or not.
But even if it's not, I think you'll...
You'll have the tools, I mean, in particular people in this industry have the tools very
quickly to make a map of the real environment and then in a game engine build a world that
matches that and just calibrate your position to that.
And I think you'll very quickly be able to sort of experiment with that.
And if those types of headsets become successful, I think, in particular like mixed reality
headsets.
very, very quickly have to rely on the idea of having
a map of the world around you.
You want to be able to put a virtual object on a table,
so it has to know there's a table there.
And so I think we're talking a matter of two, three years
where you'll be able to do some of these things.
And the tool set too, for Epic Games, anybody can go download Unreal Engine.
It doesn't take much computer power to actually run the engine itself.
There's a lot of construction tools in there.
You can build some of these experiences.
I think the one key piece that you would need to actually just look at VR, it would be the
headset whether it's Oculus or Vive or something along those lines.
My kids are doing it at home.
They're building their room and then being able to dress it up the way that they want to.
So it's not too far that you'll be able to have objects and placement and multiplayers.
I think user-generated content is such a big part of culture now.
I think naturally the market will drive experiences that allow people to participate in the world creation, in the storytelling.
Thanks. One other thing that struck me was when you're talking about the memories that people were having of these things that you know are virtual,
is have you looked into educational experiences where you could really bring someone into some historical events
and really have it strike a student that would stick with them much better than just reading the book?
Yes, it's absolutely. Educational is definitely on our roadmap.
Some of the stuff you guys are doing is super, super cool.
One thing I'm really curious about is how often do you guys have repeat, like, visitors
to some of your centers?
Is that a common thing?
We do have repeat and we are learning more about our repeat.
You know, most recently in Glendale, we've only been open since Friday and we already
have a 10% repeat rate, which is surprising for us.
So people are coming back and we hope they do.
Have those kind of people kind of mentioned what brings them back?
I think a lot of it is people experience something and then they want to experience it with other
friends or they want to bring their brother or they want to bring their sister or, you
know, I went through with my 83-year-old mom who held on to me the whole time and...
Stormtroopers holding hands.
Again.
Yep.
It's happening.
Go ahead.
Sorry, I didn't mean to interrupt you.
No, so I was just going to say, and the first thing she wanted to do was, okay, now that
I've been so overwhelmed, I want to do it again now to start to find other things.
So I think it's both those.
But go ahead, Judah, you have some more.
I just think the medium is so transformative, and it's not something that you can watch
a commercial or a TV show or see an ad, and you just don't understand it when you see
it on a flat screen.
So it's not until you put the headset on and you actually go into it.
And especially with the void because it's tactile so you're touching things you're smelling the the ash in the air
I think that is when people put that on it's it's so
In your face groundbreaking you can't help but say I've got to try this again
It was that the way I really remembered it like
from yesterday.
But I think also as audiences become more sophisticated,
that first wow effect, that'll over the next couple of years
I think will start wearing off.
You can't rely on that anymore being the thing that
makes it amazing.
And so I think as we design future experiences,
we really have to think about that.
What makes it rewarding to come back?
How can we make sure that when you come back,
you actually have a different experience that
is just as rewarding?
Yeah, absolutely.
No, we've got to continue to raise the bar each step of the way.
I look at visual effects, for example, even looking at things like the original Star Wars
or looking at Titanic or any of these groundbreaking films.
When you look back at them, the general audience now can see, like, oh, that doesn't look real
anymore.
But when they first saw it, it looks real.
And we're going to have the same thing in VR.
Hi. Huge Star Wars fan. Been seeing David around for a year, so it's cool to see you here.
One of my questions is, so one of the issues here is footprint, right?
The amount of space that it takes to do these experiences and how customized those things are.
Have you considered just kind of fooling the user into going back through certain areas and reskinning them
or even reskinning the entire experience for other kind of IP, you know?
Like being able to reuse the space in ways that could...
We've absolutely I mean part the only thing that makes it possible to scale which you know one of the things about the void is it's also a place where we're starting to see a business model that might that makes sense or hopefully will make sense and so so the only way to do that is to scale a business and the only way to scale a business in real terms is to start to come to some sort of standardization so
The footprint of the void, you know, is now basically the layout of our, what we call our stages, is basically solidified.
And now what we're doing is exactly what you suggest, and you're right on the right track,
is how do we re-skin our experiences and make them unique and exciting every time.
It's the balance between how do we do that and also make something scalable that makes sense in a business world.
Yeah, the challenge of reusing without having it feel...
feel like it's being used. Yes, exactly.
Thanks.
If I can say one thing there too, because with Secrets of the Empire,
I don't have you. Have you done the experience or gone through it?
So it kills me because I just moved from Orlando to New York
and I moved to New York after they opened the Orlando experience.
So I got to do the Ghostbusters one.
I have not been able to do the Star Wars one.
So it's good that you were able to do the Ghostbusters one because it kind of helps
get an idea.
Raising the bar, one of the things that we really tried to do on this, we wanted to lengthen
the experience.
It was going from 8 or so minutes to like 11 or 12 minutes.
So we had to reuse the space, the physical space, the actual stage itself, two or three
times.
So we get...
I don't know if I'm giving away too much here, so stop me.
But four groups of four going through the experience at any given time,
having their own original experience,
as you wrap around and come back and you have the, uh...
Spoiler alert.
Have the end battle...
at the very end, I'll just leave it at that.
You're actually going through a space that you were just in
five minutes prior to on a skiff going into the vault.
So we're reusing and trying to lengthen the experience.
And in the most basic sense, you know,
it's even doing that in Ghostbusters where you're in a hallway,
you get into an elevator, you go up five floors, you get back out.
You're still in the same hallway.
I peaked, so.
It just, yeah, I mean the parallel to game design, I mean level designers have to do this as well.
You know, reuse, clever reuse of space, reuse of assets, but you have no idea.
Just really, really fast and...
Oh, actually we have more people. Oh, let's ask more.
There's a, that scene near the end where there's a certain villain character that appears which...
It gave me palpitations while I was doing that.
I'm starting to relive that now.
It becomes a very strong memory more than, say, watching it in a film.
So what you're saying to the fact that this imprints in your memory more
out of actually experiencing it than watching it on a film is totally true.
Also the fact that smell is introduced really helps transport you there too.
How do you figure out which smells, or are there certain smells that are more attuned to it?
I smell burnt stuff in that.
Was that all of them, or were there more?
Did I miss anything?
Oh, and the other thing that affects repeatability is points, like having a score.
For Ghostbusters, there was a score.
Was there a score for Star Wars?
Because I would definitely do it again,
because I think I totally messed up the first time.
We intentionally did not want to do that,
because we wanted to keep this more of a story
type of experience.
So we intentionally kept the scoring in any.
Anything that would kind of lend towards more gamified type
of experience, we kind of pulled back on that.
However, we've had enough, and Judah doesn't know this yet
because he's over, he's in Africa,
but we've had so much request, that very question
that we are, while it's not necessarily a game,
like a game score exactly, and how many hits,
and where are the hits, and different points,
there is something that's going to be introduced
that has that.
A component like that coming in the next couple months.
We have 30 seconds left, so last question here.
And then I understand you are going to be available for
questions afterwards.
Yeah, we'll go to wherever the wrap up area is.
So just a quick question.
So it's a great work to bring all the physical feelings into
the experience, like the touch and the heat and rain, those
things, have you thinking about bringing real world
experience into this experience?
Like your cell phone?
Go to the link on the left-hand side when you get the demo.
Please.
And that was Frazer.
And that's you.
So it would take a little, it would take a few minute.
So and that is how we got to where we are today.
And on that note I'm going to take the floor and hand it back to my questions to the panel
and Chris to conclude.
So you can put your question in emergency management, and I ask you to please do that.
Thank you so much.
I know you had to do some in headset, and some other types of people being able to bring
the experience with them, so that technology is being worked on now.
Thank you all very much for coming.
Please give a round of applause to our panelists.
Thanks.
And thanks to our test participants every week.
Okay next question.
Thank you and have a great day.