All right, that thing works, okay.
We'll get started.
Hello everyone, welcome to this presentation
that is not about Zelda, I'm sorry.
really. Thank you all guys for being here. I know there's a lot of exciting stuff on the side and
I really appreciate that you come to my talk. Before I begin, I was told to remind you to
please switch your phones to silent mode and please don't forget to rate the session at the
end. That really helps us a lot.
All right, so today I will talk about a small game that I've been making for almost 7 years now
that is called Transformice.
Before I begin, let me introduce you to it with this short video for those who don't know it.
here. So that is Transformice. So Transformice is about now 75
million icons created. Almost 2 million active players a month.
1.5 million Facebook fans. No, we didn't buy any. And the game
is now translated into 20 languages. And that is how the
team looked like by the end of the last year.
So how did it get there?
In 2010, my friend Jean-Baptiste and I
were full-time employed at a French video game company.
Him as a programmer and me as a graphic designer.
We weren't very satisfied with our day jobs
and we wanted to make a small game on our free time.
Jean-Baptiste had a history of creating
small browser games for fun
and he asked for my help in order to create a new one
with better graphics.
It all came from a silly life experience.
I was sleeping at a friend's house and some rodents kept scratching against the wall all
through the night.
And I imagined them climbing on the top of each other in order to get, in order to overcome
obstacles and reach a potential cheese.
I proposed the idea to John Batiste,
where the players would be mice that transform themselves
into planks and crates in order to help the other players.
And he liked the idea instantly,
and that's how the name Transform Mice was born.
We realized pretty early on the prototype that when you were too few players, everybody would
turn into a plank and nothing really happened. This wasn't very fun, so instead of
transforming players, we gave them, we gave the ability to summon physical objects to one
mouse at a time, the almighty shaman mouse, obviously. But the name Transformice stuck
because we liked it and it had no results on Google.
In about three weeks, we had, thanks to reusing some bricks
of code that Jean-Baptiste made earlier,
we had a working prototype, like that.
We launched the game on May the 1st of 2010,
and we posted the link to a small French video game forum.
The first week was a great success.
We had a couple hundred players
and they were completely addicted.
We quickly added an account system
to keep track of all the cheese you gathered
and we started to add hats for your mouse to wear
that you could buy against the cheese you gathered.
But then a couple weeks later, a huge forum called Something Awful, they found out about this.
And the game wasn't even translated in English, but they didn't care.
And a massive amount of players, they were yelling,
omelette du fromage everywhere in our little server.
And it was completely melting, and the game was unreachable for weeks.
That was a perfect moment for the press to write about us and make our server die a little more.
We got featured by Kotaku, Paper Shroudgun, IndieGames.com, PC Gamer and other websites.
The game was completely free at the time and we were paying for the servers out of our own pockets.
This really wasn't a viable solution because we needed to
rent a lot more servers to cope with the demand and so we
needed to earn money really fast. We didn't have time to
set up anything complicated to earn money so we went for the
fastest solution. We set up an advertising banner under the
game because this is a browser game and we opened a PayPal
account to receive donations from the players.
Thankfully it worked. The advertising banner generated approximately $50 a day for
about 80,000 unique visitors a day. This made around $11,000 by the end of 2010. The
donations were less effective and they only generated about $3,000 in two year stops.
A little spoiler, but this is going to end badly.
and this went on for months where every single minute of our free time was taken by the game.
We took days off from our jobs to work on it and sleepless nights to fix the bugs, the
crashing servers, deal with community management and add more hats obviously. At this point
we knew we had to make a choice. Resign and create our own company to take care of the game
or kill it entirely because we didn't have enough free time to take care of it.
It wasn't an obvious choice because we had comfortable positions at all the jobs and
even if the game started to generate some income, we didn't know if it would be enough
to sustain the two of us and the servers.
That's how we started to dive into the joys of the French administration.
We realized the amount of paperwork and knowledge it took to create a company.
And thankfully we benefited from a special program in the north of France that allowed us to
get mentoring and cheap offices. Yay! That really saved our lives. That's how one year after the
game was released we finally resigned from our jobs to create our own studio. Yay! I
initially drew the slide like that but really inside it was more like this.
It was a real scary leap of faith,
and I was super scared to let go of my day job.
But we resigned anyway, and two days later,
we were entering our new offices,
and we started working on the game full-time immediately.
Because we went full time on the game,
we doubled the number of active players
in less than six months from 100,000 to 200,000 players a day
because we decided to translate the game in every language.
We saw we had players in.
We had a very exotic player distribution.
More than 50% of our overall audience came from Brazil,
then United States, Turkey, France,
overall Latin America, Russia.
Another huge factor of the success then was the seasonal
events that we made in the game where the players could
drop some thematic hats and have some gameplay twist
and the players really loved them.
They became a huge part of our strategy
all through the game's life.
The advertising model was performing really great.
We jumped to $300 a day, generating more than
$100,000 for 2011.
So we made some calculations and we realized
we could hire one more person to work on the game.
We didn't hesitate one moment and we recruited
our most passionate moderator in-game
to be our community manager,
so she could answer the thousands of emails
we were getting every week
and manage the in-game moderators.
Everything was going great,
and we were very happy about it,
but the joy didn't last long.
On December of 2011,
we got banned from Google Adsense.
We really took a hit at this moment.
Since Google pays with a 60 day roll,
the sudden ban of our account meant
that more than $14,000 of click never got paid.
We were left with three salaries
and about 30 servers to pay for
and our main source of income had simply disappeared.
Numbers weren't adding up anymore.
So Jean-Baptiste and I stopped paying ourselves
for a few months in order to be able to pay for the servers
and the salary of our community manager
while working to solve this out.
Suddenly, our whole domain was blacklisted
without any warning or email
and not a single form available to inquire to Google.
Literally, there is absolutely no way to get in touch
with the Google Adsense staff.
your only chance is a user driven forum where people usually don't know much more than you
about what's going on. It's only by tremendous luck that we got out of this. A friend of ours
happened to go to the same school as one of the Google employees and a couple of emails
later she managed to get us banned.
It's only then that we learned why the banning occurred.
When you read Google AdSense policies,
I mean, we do read them, right?
For different clicks and web pages away,
there's a little, little paragraph that says this.
Distance between ads and flash games.
The Google bots detected that our banner was less than 150 pixels away from a flash game and
they banned us automatically. No warning, no explanation. So small advice, when you sign
something, always read the small print and do not underestimate the power of networking.
So we re-installed the AdSense banner by February 2012,
but with 150 pixel, most of our audience
with low-end computers and small screen resolutions
weren't able to see it anymore.
So the numbers didn't add up,
and we were still pretty bitter
about how it had been handled.
So we decided not to rely on advertisement anymore,
and we were getting to go free-to-play.
We took six months to develop this with extreme caution
because it was a real shift for us.
We were very afraid, will the players hate us
for asking for money?
Will they stay in the game?
It was really hard for us to come up with price points
because how much were we comfortable letting people
pay within our browser-based cute little mice flash game?
We wanted extremely fair and ethic monetization,
making only cosmetics available and very low prices.
I completely redrew the 200 hats that we had at this moment
so the players could completely customize
every color of each item.
And the new currency would be strawberries,
opposed to the soft currency that was cheese.
At this point, we were still pretty bitter about Google
and we did something very stupid.
We decided to remove the ad banners completely
prior to the launch of the free-to-play version.
We thought that players would hate us less if we showed them that we removed this source of
income and so they wouldn't think we were sellouts. And retrospectively it was a very bad
idea. We finally released the free to play version on June 14th of 2012 and it went quite well.
The players response was truly astounding.
They were so enthusiastic to be able to support
the game they love and have a full color.
The first month generated more than $250,000.
We were completely astonished.
After six months of not paying ourselves,
sleepless nights, thinking how we failed
only a few months after founding a company,
this was a real emotional rollercoaster.
Between June and December of 2012, micro transaction generated $1,070,000 with peaks that
you see on every content, every new content, seasonal updates with more hats to buy. It was
at the end of this year that we broke our all-time concurrent record with more than
86,000 users online at the same time.
And for 2012, it was 1 million euros.
We quickly hired eight more people,
developers, community managers,
chief financial officer, interns,
and with about three million active players
and 40 servers to handle,
we thought it was a good team scale
and it would allow us to sleep a bit better.
We also moved into bigger and more expensive offices by the end of 2012. 2013 started
slowly on the money side because we hired so many people we were more often than not
close to the break even. This can also be explained by the fact that we ran a huge winter
event in December 2012 and we gave away a ton of content like hats, title, cheese, even
hot currency for free.
This was a huge mistake on our part because players can only wear that many hats at a time
and it slowed down our sales for several months.
As you can see, it became even more concerning
around November that we decided to reactivate
the advertising banner next to the game,
but this time vertical instead of horizontal.
We saw that it wasn't disturbing our players at all,
and it did perform a lot better than before.
So looking back, a year and a half of ads
even performing badly was still more than $100,000,
and we were really, really stupid to get rid of it.
2013 was also the first time the number of players
was decreasing and we lost roughly 15%
of our active user base while our overall income
was 920,000 euros.
January, February being usually slow month. Then we took one of our biggest decisions, not
to give any free hats during seasonal events anymore and sell them instead against cheese or
strawberries. We finally realized that we were basically giving too many things for free
during events and while it was very appreciated, it was really dangerous in the long term
because we had nothing to sell basically.
The decision was quite unpopular. We gave out badges and titles instead of hats but players
felt that they didn't have anything worthy to fight for anymore. Some players were happy
about it because they didn't want to play all through the evening to get the nice valentine
hat but mostly people felt that we had become sellouts.
Eventually they calmed down and slowly but surely,
you can see, all sales went up
and we were above break even a lot more frequently.
And while the number of players decreased again
by 15% in 2013, we were monetizing a lot better.
So in the whole, 2014 generated around $1 million
in sales and advertisement, and after paying
for charges and taxes, our benefit was $40,000.
In the beginning of 2015, thanks to networking again,
we managed to get accepted into Steam directly.
We launched the game on January 30 and it was a bit chaotic at launch. We wanted to launch on
a Friday afternoon so we could sit on the popular new releases all weekend long. Everybody
does that. And we had everything prepared but as we pushed the button at 4 p.m.
French time, there was something missing. Like that. This button. It wasn't here. Oops.
turns out it was a bug on steam's end because the game was free. It didn't have a set price. So
the system didn't display the button that usually says buy this game. Because 4 p.m.
french time was 7 a.m. bell time. We didn't get help immediately and the game could not be
downloaded for more than two hours.
but it got better eventually and since we put some incentive in the steam version for all
players to download it, a little badge so they could download the steam version, we were
able to sit in the popular new releases for quite some time.
Launching on Steam also allowed us to get some nice press reviews,
a thing that we didn't get for the previous five years.
All the press the game ever got prior to the Steam launch
was the full article that launched in 2010.
And releasing on Steam was like a new launch for the game
with YouTubers making videos about it
and the press writing nice articles.
It brought us a lot of credibility.
People acknowledged it as a real...
video game, you know, not just a flash toy that you play for five minutes. I'm not allowed to
share numbers here, but at the end of 2015, we got a massive amount of charge back through
steam. Since we never had any problem with paypal or mobile partner, we weren't prepared
for the amount of fraud the fake credit card can generate.
Suddenly, all players were,
they were generating,
there's an opportunity to get free strawberries
with a simple method, and it spread like wildfire
so, so very quickly.
For a moment, we were the single game
with the most fraud of all Steam.
This is not a record I'm very proud of.
We had a huge amount of, we had to add a huge amount
of rules and checks in order to stop the disease
and we banned over 7,000 accounts,
including a lot of almost dedicated players in the process.
This was immensely unpopular,
but we really had no choice here.
Overall, I can tell you those numbers.
We had over 2.5 million icons created through Steam,
and 16% of those played for more than an hour,
which is superior to the browser version.
So we are very satisfied with Steam,
as today it makes a good part of our revenue.
For 2015, our income was roughly 1.2 million euros
for a benefit of 50,000.
For 2016, we decided to go all in in Transformice.
We wanted to favor a mechanism that all our players love,
the seasonal events.
We wrote and planned 52 events,
one for each week of the year
that would cycle the next year round.
And for the good part of the first trimester,
it seemed like a great idea.
We never had a first three months so good
in all of Transformice's history.
Players engagement was high, monetization was good,
it's everything we wanted, right?
Actually, not really.
I'll make a small digression here,
but I think this is a common trap with free-to-play games.
We made those little events,
and they weren't very complicated to complete
because they were so short.
So we gave them some great rewards for them.
But if you look back a little,
they were like small Skinner boxes
where you did a silly thing
that was hardly related to the game,
and you got a great reward at the end.
Of course, such a mechanic makes your stats look good.
You have a great retention rate,
good concurrent user picks,
but ultimately the players get highly frustrated
because if they miss an event because they weren't there,
or if the newest event doesn't have as many good rewards
as the previous one,
and overall they only do the small, silly thing
in order to get the rewards,
and then they quit the game until the next event.
why would they keep playing as the rewards are not so good after you completed the event? It
felt like an old cranky deli reward system where you log in only to collect the rewards and you
cannot miss a single day because it's going to break your streak and frankly it was shit. That
was not what the players were here for. We had a solid game play and we were driving players
out of this game play with that.
So by the end of March 2016, we decided to stop making
one event per week.
We wanted to focus more on the original gameplay.
We did longer events.
We added new currencies for other game modes
so the players would get an incentive
to play the actual game in its entirety.
We also started refactoring a lot of code
so we could focus on more core features
like the ability for someone to change their username,
opening the authentication system
so we could accept the API from other websites.
And the Steam launch convinced us to invest
in order to get the game on as many portal as we can,
like Congregate and more games.
games of 10, and so on.
This will bring us a nice additional stream of users
allowing us to reach out, out of the word of mouth
strategy that we currently only have.
So it's time for the what went right and wrong.
What went right, physics.
Back in 2010, there was a thing for physics flash games
like Fantastic Contraption, Quop and stuff.
They were all very fun and solo,
but none of them included a multiplayer twist.
People love to mess with the physics,
but it's becoming hilarious in multiplayer.
Real-time multiplayer, of course.
2010 was a great year for Facebook games,
but they were all asynchronous,
and a real-time multiplayer game
that could still be played in your browser
was a great alternative at this time,
and one of the only ones.
Accessibility, the game is Flash, the game weighs less than one mega and can be played on all computers thanks to the Flash player.
It has a guest mode so you don't have to create an account, the registration doesn't ask you for an email, and all of this make it very frictionless and made it spread like wildfire.
And such low specs also allow us to reach more developing countries which leads us to the next point, localization.
We translated the game very early to Brazilian, Russian,
Spanish, Polish, Turkish, and so on.
And this helped us a lot because some countries
don't have as many games as we do.
And even if some countries don't monetize as good,
it doesn't matter because it only makes more players
in your game.
And this is the most important parameter
in multiplayer game and free-to-play games.
More the players, the funnier and more competitive
your game gets and the further it reaches.
We asked all players to help us with the translation
and they were more than happy to do it.
Graphics, don't want to be too self-congratulatory here
because I made the graphics,
but the shoes of cute little mice getting cruelly killed
turned out to be a good part of our success.
Never underestimate cute.
players feedback. Many players kept yelling on your forums that we never listen to them.
But we actually do a lot. And we did so very early on the development of the game. We
iterate a lot based on the players feedback. And 20% of the workforce is dedicated to
community management today.
And two people team, Jean-Baptiste and I
are very complimentary and we maxed the different skills
while minimizing the number of persons involved
and that allowed us to develop and iterate very fast.
Now where we're wrong, two people team.
Of course there's a downside to being only two people when you have to manage a multi-player,
multi-million player MMO. I mean, we missed a lot of opportunities because we weren't able to
cope up with the initial rush and the bugs and stuff.
Retrospectively, our adsense ban transformed into a good thing. But at the moment it
certainly wasn't. And it put a lot of physical stress on us. We have been careless with how we
generated money. And when your business model only relies on one single source of income, you
better make sure you know exactly what you're doing.
Never try anything shady and think you'll get away with it
easier either because this is the best way to screw everything up.
Hiring to fast end management.
When the free-to-play took off,
we were so relieved that we could finally scale the team
up to more reasonable standard
that we didn't pay as much attention
to the hiring as we should have.
We grew from three to 10 in less than eight months
and we weren't prepared for it.
We made some mistakes and some tensions arose,
and suddenly, employee's management had become a thing
without us realizing.
We always try to provide the best working conditions
to our workers, but we shrug it off,
project management entirely,
relying on everyone to find stuff to do on their own
without setting proper goals.
And this is something we're getting better at lately, but it took us a very long time
and very painful experience to realize how important that was.
disregard mobile, we were so busy with the PC version,
we never took a mobile app seriously,
especially knowing that our game was flash
and it was best used with a keyboard and mouse.
And so we made a couple tries with Adobe Air on Android,
but we never invested enough for it to be meaningful
and that's probably a missed opportunity here.
Monetization, we had no idea what we were doing.
When we decided to go free to play,
we didn't pay much attention to what others did around us.
To us, you could only do free to play in two ways,
the fair League of Legend way,
and the horrible Farmville way.
And we were so stressed out that the players would hate us
that we went for the most fair we could.
But that also meant underselling our products.
And once they are set,
it's always easier to go down on your prices,
but you cannot raise them after.
We didn't do homework and we had no idea about RPU,
break even, all that kind of jiggly business thing.
We are very, very grateful for the free to play model
because the game wouldn't exist without it.
But it was just a ton of work we weren't prepared for
and if you want to do this, get prepared.
Now what, very quickly, we've been working for two years now
on our biggest production after Transformers
that we called Deniz.
It's a massively multiplayer survival game
with zombies, loot, crafting,
but everything cooperative and not player versus player.
Think of Project Zomboid meets Don't Starve
in a massively multiplayer setting.
The game is currently in a private alpha state and we hope to release an open beta for the first half of 2017.
Sorry, the syllabus is here.
Believe it or not, but that's Flash too.
Now what?
Every time I say that all game is Flash, I get the mandatory response like, but Mel,
haven't you heard? Flash is dying. And yeah, I'm quite aware of that, trust me. Today, yes,
there is a trend in the major web browser companies where they are slowly but surely
removing the user Flash player plug-in into the systems.
But the Flash content is still overwhelmingly present
on the web, so most of them are also working
on replacement like Google, for example,
has an ongoing project integrating Flash directly
inside Chrome that is called Paper API.
And some Mozilla programmers are trying
to implement Paper API to Firefox.
So there are workarounds.
We think that for a long period of time,
Flash will be disabled in browser,
but can still be activated manually with a single button,
which is okay for us.
Even if there's a total block one day,
we developed a standalone version that you can install
and we can advertise it on the website.
So that would definitely cause a huge drop in acquisition
but the game won't die because of flash obsolescence.
About our place in the industry, it's a bit unconventional.
We have a project that allows us to live
for more than six years now,
but we are still what you can call a one game studio, really,
because all of our other games
failed to generate significant revenue,
and Transformice is still 99% of our income.
Overall, I feel there are more and more triple I studios
with very professional production,
and also there are more and more of a one man game
with hobbyists that already have a day job
and do a game on their free time.
And there's less and less of studios in the middle, I feel.
Thanks to Transformice, we are closer to the triple I side
of the spectrum in terms of budget and production,
but
That means we are competing with very professional teams
and all games need to be quite ambitious
and this is a bit stressful.
But whatever happens, we will keep making multiplayer games
because we love it and we really believe
that playing together is the funniest thing ever.
Thank you.
I was reminded to please rate the session at the end
and I will be in the wrap-up room.
I don't know if we have time for some questions.
Do we?
We don't?
No?
All right, I will be in the wrap-up room
right by the hall.
Thank you everyone.