Hi, so just a few things before we get started.
Please remember to fill out your evaluation forms
at the end of this session and other sessions you attend.
It's really helpful for speakers to improve
and learn about their speaking.
And if you have cell phones,
just make sure they're on silent.
And we'll most likely be using the wrap-up room.
I know my talk is going on pretty long, so.
I don't know if we'll get to any questions,
but there'll be a wrap-up room after this,
so you guys can just come in.
We can continue the discussion.
All right.
So, hi, my name's Julia Karanditar,
and I'm a game designer at Untamed.
My talk is called History Shaping Design,
Inequality and Player Behavior.
Before we get started though, I do have a few disclaimers.
So this is a series of talks I've given
called History Shaping Design.
And usually I look at game systems from the past
and try to understand their context,
the time period that they were made in their culture
in order to understand those relationships
and the design decisions made around that game.
And again, like what we can learn as designers now
about our own time period and our own.
culture and how it's, you know, influencing our designs.
But this time I'm sort of focusing more on recent events, so this is not so much about
looking at the past or comparing the past.
And in particular I'm looking at unequal systems and how they shape people's behavior.
And I'll be comparing game systems and economic systems, both of which are very complex and
very different.
And also for this talk, I'm going over and covering
a lot of different psychology studies.
But psychology research tends to be very muddy
because they're trying to analyze
the complexity of human nature.
And there's lots of variables.
And so variables are hard to isolate and analyze.
So just take some of the conclusions
with a grain of salt. This is not a very hard or fast
science.
This is something that's sometimes very hard to predict.
Also, just due to time, I'm not going to go into too much of the studies that I've included,
but I am going to reference them on my slides so you can look them up and read more information
on your own time if you're interested.
Also, I'm using a lot of economic data and cultural references coming out of the U.S.
in particular.
Part of this is because I live in the U.S., so I'm most comfortable talking about, you
know, the country that I grew up in.
But I also believe that the US does have sort of an accelerated pace of particularly income
and wealth inequality that seems to be going faster than other developed countries, so
it makes for an interesting test case.
Alright, so we evolved two forms of thinking, one logical and energy heavy that we use sparingly,
and one fast and effortless that we use a lot.
Heuristics is the understanding of how our fast brains work
and how it explains some of the seemingly illogical ways
we process information, make decisions,
and navigate complex systems.
Now, as game designers, we use tricks and tools
to help our fast brain understand our games.
An example is the use of visual elements
that draw players to certain places in our world,
giving them a sense of direction without forcing them
through a series of instructions.
They sort of already kind of.
you know, an interesting thing catches their eye
and they want to gravitate to that thing.
We don't need to tell them where to go necessarily.
Heuristics in economics is called behavioral economics
and economic designers and marketers
can use similar tools to control
how we think about purchasing things.
In this example, I'm giving a list price,
which is usually at a higher price point
than people would usually buy that item at,
but it gives the illusion of a really great discount
off of that item.
So one of the ways this is achieved is through something
called priming or framing.
Priming or framing describes the fact that we are always
making comparisons.
And we tend to use the most recent things we were thinking
about or information in our immediate environment to
influence our choices and actions, even if they are
seemingly unrelated and even if we're not even aware we're
doing so.
So for example, if I were to show you a picture of a dust
pan and then asked you to fill in the blank, most people will
jump to the word soap, sort of connecting the dust
pan to cleaning.
This might be, you know, I might have triggered a different outcome if I had changed up the image.
Now, priming is used in a lot of UI, UX, and game design, right?
By using players' ingrained knowledge of how the world works,
designers can quickly communicate how elements should behave,
and sort of, you know, using that knowledge,
we can prevent players from feeling frustrated,
because they sort of understand right away how something would look.
For example, like I will probably know,
jumping on something with spikes is not a good idea,
but jumping on something that looks soft and mushroomy
is probably fine.
Apart from just using visual elements,
planning levels so players are kind of equipped
with the right tools or in the right frame of mind
before ramping up on a challenge
or offering a series of more difficult puzzles.
can help them understand what they need to know next easily,
and again, minimizing frustration.
So in this example, this is Zelda Breath of the Wild,
and in this room there were lots of buried treasures,
and usually when players come across those buried treasures,
they know they need to use the magnet tool
in order to unearth them,
but the magnet tool also just happens to be the tool
you need to use to unlock the secret door
and move on to the next series of challenges.
So priming here is the use of the buried treasures
to get players to be equipping with the right tool.
in order to move on to more difficult actions.
Now this effect of priming can also show
some seemingly illogical purchasing behaviors
that we might have.
So for example, if there was a discount
on a new flat screen TV,
maybe there's $100 off of a flat screen TV,
this might make people think
that this is a really good deal,
good enough to maybe drive across town
and go to that particular store that has that deal,
or maybe to wait in a long line
in order to get that coupon.
or that limited time offer in order to secure that savings.
However, when presented with the sale of a new car,
most people won't apply the same amount of time
to save that $100.
Now, traditionally in economics, this is sort of weird
because economists are like, we're logical beings
and we should sort of apply the same effort
to save that $100.
It shouldn't matter if it comes from a flat screen TV
or if it comes from a brand new car.
But we do have different behaviors, right?
We're not as motivated.
And why is this?
Well, it's because we're being primed by the actual purchase
price of the item.
It feels really good to save $100 off of something that's
only a few hundred dollars, because the relationship is
much bigger.
It seems like a much bigger discount versus something
that's a few thousand dollars.
So Dan Gilbert, a psychologist from Harvard, said, this is
why a lot of people will spend a lot of time and effort
cutting.
two dollar coupons off of four dollar toothpaste,
but they don't spend the same amount of effort
looking through fees in their retirement funds.
Now, according to this USA Today chart,
the difference between 1% and 2%
of like an active managed fee
and your retirement fund over the course of like 30 years
is the difference between 200 and $300,000.
So it's really significant.
But because it's abstract and 1% and 2% just
don't seem like they should be that different,
people kind of glaze over it and they
don't exert the same amount of energy
saving something that is much more significant.
Priming can also change how we perceive the people around us,
especially those who have less or more than us
and how much inequality we're willing to put up with.
According to this study done,
they looked at how people's framing changes
when confronted with different people.
So for example, if I were thinking of a series of choices,
it could be something as mundane
as going to the grocery store
and figuring out what things I'm gonna buy
at the grocery store.
And I were to come across somebody asking for money,
I'm much more likely to frame that interaction
in terms of a series of choices.
So what did this person do
to land themselves in this situation?
That would be different if I were thinking beforehand about a series of chance events.
Maybe somebody I knew got into a car accident,
or maybe somebody I knew won a scratch-off ticket for like a couple hundred bucks.
Then I were to pass that same person,
I'm more likely to think of that person in terms of chance events.
So like what kind of bad luck did that person
have that they're now in this situation where they're asking for money.
And this is important because it can change our behavior.
I'm much more likely to give to a person
where I'm thinking about the events that
may be outside of that person's control that
led them into this situation.
And the reason for this is if we see something that is unfair,
we try to explain it in our mind.
And if we can't do that, that can cause some discomfort
or it can cause us to try to rectify that difference.
Another aspect of priming or framing is something called the stereotype threat or boost.
Now this is if someone associates with a group that has either a positive or negative stereotype,
they might reflect that outcome on the results of an action that are related to that stereotype.
So this is a study done by the World Bank where they took people from a high caste group
in India and a low caste group of India, they gave them logic puzzles to solve and when
solved individually there's no distinction between the two groups.
You couldn't tell who was who, their performance was completely identical.
However, when they put the people together
to solve the puzzles in front of each other,
and it was obvious who belonged to what caste,
the differences started to diverge,
with the higher caste group performing slightly better
than the lower caste group.
Now, the researchers were trying to think
about why that could happen.
And they sort of concluded that if a person is associated
with a group that has a positive stereotype,
this might give them just enough confidence in the action
to kind of boost their performance slightly.
people who identify with groups with a negative stereotype might have the stress in disproving
that stereotype, particularly when they feel like they're interacting with people who might
hold those beliefs.
you know, in their mind, you know, having to be twice as good or twice as smart to kind
of overcome that perceived stereotype.
And even the mental space of paying attention to those negative stereotypes might be enough
to impact that person's performance compared to a person who just wouldn't even be thinking
about it because their identity affords them the privilege of assuming those stereotypes
don't apply to them, right?
They just, they wouldn't even be thinking about it.
Now, again, psychology research is very muddy,
and there has been different studies
that show various amounts of this effect.
And there has actually been studies that show the opposite,
which is that the pressure of having to overcome
that negative stereotype is going to motivate people
to work hard enough and that will actually
boost their performance,
making them perform slightly better.
But I brought this up because when I was reading
these studies, I was thinking about all the times
that I was, as a player, confronted with various
difficulty selections before I even get to a puzzle.
And I'm wondering if that can somehow prime me to,
you know,
change my performance slightly.
If I select easy, for example,
is that gonna give me enough confidence
that I'll assume that I'll be able to solve those puzzles
or overcome those challenges?
Or will it impact my performance negatively
because maybe I won't be as activated
or I won't be as challenged
if I think that they're gonna be easy?
So some priming takeaways.
We're always making comparisons.
We use the most recent and immediate or well-known data
available to shape our choices and thoughts,
and perceptions can perpetuate.
Okay, so loss aversion is another bias
that can explain some of the behavioral changes
that happen in unequal systems.
So this is the bias that makes the loss of something
twice as painful as the gain of the same thing.
As shown in this graph,
this is called a loss aversion curve.
As you can see, the curve is steeper
when the losses are negative.
versus the gains.
So in games, loss aversion is used in lots of different ways
for making players feel motivated,
feeling a sense of loss when playing,
and amplifying punishments or bad situations.
Now, Jeff Engelstein had a great GDC talk last year
where he talked in depth about loss aversion
and in particular board game design.
But I'll be giving two examples
of how he used loss aversion differently
in the games he's worked on.
So this one is called The Expanse.
And here, currency and victory points are the same unit.
So in order to set an action or plan a strategy,
players are actually consuming their winning points.
So this makes players slow down and pay attention
to the actions that they're going to be doing in this game
to make sure that they're going to compensate for that loss
of points that they have to spend on.
This is in contrast to his pit crew game.
Here he wanted to encourage players to take risks
and also this game is team based,
so teams are kind of competing against each other.
So here it was important for the losses
when penalty points were triggered by players
to not feel so bad.
So instead of a team's car moving back a step
when a penalty point is triggered, everyone else moves up.
Now again, and logically it shouldn't matter, right?
It's the same as if you move back one or everyone else moves up,
but it feels different to players.
And because it feels different to players, it doesn't feel so bad.
Therefore, you know, there's not so much of a sense of loss
when those points are triggered,
and the teams will kind of stick together
because there won't be so much infighting if somebody triggers a point
because there won't be necessarily that same impact of loss.
Another place loss aversion can be found is in branching narratives.
Because of the limitations of tech and content, most branching narratives need to funnel at
some point.
However, players can be very aware of the loss of their choice space in narrative outcomes.
They can imagine their characters going in one direction or following a certain sort
of storyline in their head and if it like starts to diverge into another area, they
can be, they can really notice that and that can feel very impactful to them.
Inventory systems are also where loss aversion can happen, right?
How much I'll value something I have in my possession than picking something else up
unless it's, you know, obvious that the thing I'm going to pick up is better
or the thing that I have is damaged in some way.
And inventories also show this another aspect of loss aversion.
Losses need to be proportional in order to have an effect.
If I have 10 units of wood and I have 15 units in my inventory,
I'm going to really think about that transaction and weigh it.
Is it going to be worthy for me to spend that 10 units of wood?
However, if I have 500 units of wood,
I'm not probably going to pay the same amount of attention.
I might not even think about spending 10 units of wood.
So there's many reasons that drive inventory hoarding,
but this aspect of loss aversion is one of them.
Now, many free-to-play games use loss aversion
as a player hook.
The most common example is the use of lives,
or moves, or time in order to continue playing
and preventing the loss of progress.
And daily combo bonuses also use loss aversion
to motivate players to log in every day.
Now interestingly enough,
even though the person hasn't actually logged in
for the fifth day to get that really awesome reward,
because they're being promised that by missing out,
it's the same thing as if they had had that thing
and now are losing it, right?
Because they're thinking about how cool it would be
to have it, it's sort of in their mental space
that they already have it, and then missing out
means that they've somehow lost it.
So, failed expectation of future gains is the same thing as losing them.
It's the same effect.
Another aspect of loss aversion is that many losses are more painful than a single big loss,
even if the big loss is more in absolute terms than the sum of all the small losses.
And all of these explanations of loss aversion can maybe explain why the game Monopoly can
have such a painful losing experience for players.
It sort of uses all these different types of loss aversion really well, kind of compounding
it to being this like really unpleasant experience, right?
You're constantly losing little bits every turn.
As you start the game, you have a certain amount of resources,
but those resources start to dwindle over time
as you slowly become more and more broke,
making each little loss more and more amplified.
And then just thinking about how painful
it is to flip over cards, right?
There's all these little actions you
do to sort of add insult to injury when you're
losing money in this game.
So loss aversion also affects all different types of economics.
We tend to hold on to a stock for too long if we feel like it's losing value.
Instead of relying on the fundamentals behind the company,
in terms of like their profit or loss margin, or how healthy that company is,
instead we try to hold on to a stock hoping that it will rebound to prevent that loss.
And what will usually happen is we'll hold on to it for longer and longer,
it will lose more and more value and we'll sell it at an even greater loss.
There's a reverse effect of this.
We might be too scared to buy stocks at all
because we'll think that they'll lose value.
So we'll take that money
and maybe shove it under our mattress.
But the problem with that is like that money in 10 years
isn't gonna buy the same amount just due to inflation.
But because we don't think about that in those terms,
right, it's not like we're actually losing money
coming out of our mattress.
We won't think about inflation and its effects on it.
And therefore, we might be too conservative
in our strategies for investing in the long term.
We also tend to overvalue assets we have.
So if we're putting a house on the market
or we're trying to sell something that we have.
We're framing that thing or that transaction in terms of losing that house or losing that
thing that we're putting on the market instead of the money we're going to get for that thing.
And so there's usually a mismatch between the price somebody is willing to buy for it
versus our desire or our tendency to be scared of losing that object.
And actually we're not alone in this. So monkeys have the same loss aversion that humans do
Researchers were able to teach monkeys a currency system and the monkeys could use their coin to buy from various different
researchers and one of the options they could do is buy
from a researcher that would offer one fruit and then give another fruit for a total of two fruits for one monkey coin.
Or buy from a researcher who would offer three fruits and then take one fruit away for a total of two fruits for one monkey coin.
Logically, again, it's the same thing. You're getting two fruits for one coin,
but monkeys really did not like seeing that fruit being taken away, so they avoided buying from that researcher.
All right, so what does this mean with a society
with like growing income inequality, right?
We talked about how loss aversion affects game systems
and how loss aversion can affect economics,
but what about in society?
Well, so I think maybe some of the different aspects
of loss aversion might sound familiar,
particularly the expectation of future gains not being met.
So, right, if you're thinking that you're gonna do better
than your parents maybe, or if you have like a certain set
standard of living that might be in your mind and somehow.
you're not making it or maybe your children aren't making it,
that can trigger that kind of loss aversion.
And this can show up in well-being and health standards.
So this is a study where researchers looked at
thousands of households in the UK and Germany,
and they tried to analyze or control
for all different types of variables.
But what they found was that the same loss aversion curve
shows up in terms of income.
So when somebody loses a certain amount of income,
the impact for well-being is negative
by twice the amount as that same gain in income.
And well-being here is characterized by different mental and physical health outcomes.
So this is pretty big because a lot of times economists will explain like,
oh, you know, when there's a hollowing out of the middle,
yes, you have people falling behind, but you also have people going up,
and that's really good, right?
But the problem with that thinking
is that you have like a 2 to 1 ratio, right?
If somebody goes up, that's great,
but it's not compensating for the damage done by somebody
falling out into the bottom.
Another interesting aspect of this study was showing how incomes or jobs that have very
fluctuating amounts of revenue or income to an individual has the same sort of damaging
effect than someone who has a more stable steady stream of income.
Even if maybe that person in that variable, like freelance job, makes more in absolute
terms, they can still have a more negative impact.
just because we're always making comparisons and if we like have a lot of variable of income
the differences between the really good times and maybe the okay times is going to
have that negative effect.
All right so some loss aversion takeaways. A loss is twice as painful as the joy of gaining the same
thing. Losses need to be proportional in order to have an effect. Many small losses are more
painful than one big loss and
And unrealized feature gain is the same thing as losing that gain.
All right, so hindsight bias.
This bias makes us want to point to reasons for something that just happened, right?
Things that just happened, they seem to be really predictable or inevitable
and we'll claim that we knew all along that they would happen.
One of the reasons for hindsight bias is that the world is filled with so much messy data
that it's really hard to understand why complex things happen.
So our fast brains try to make that easier for us by pointing to a few different things
that could lead to an outcome so that we can learn from it and then
use it in the future. The problem is we tend to oversimplify the reasons. We usually don't
account for luck or randomness and sometimes we get those reasons wrong. If we have strong
assumptions or intuitions before that thing happens and then we point to those assumptions
or intuitions that could lead us astray.
So hindsight bias is stronger when the event
is negative or unfavorable.
Here's a site from Trader HQ where they're like,
oh, the five indicators that foretold the 2008 crash,
right, this is a really complex sort of black swan event
that was very complex and involved global markets
and deflationary housing prices and all this stuff.
But you can see that it's really easy after the fact
to sort of point to a few things and be like,
oh, see, we could have totally known it would happen
by just looking at these things.
We can see hindsight bias play out when someone or something is successful,
sort of attributing steps or actions taken, and again, town playing randomness or luck.
I think we've all seen talks or articles about like the five things you need to know
to be successful on X platform.
The problem again with this tendency is that it reinforces priming of choices.
And as I mentioned earlier, that can, you know,
perpetuate the increasing amount of inequality we're willing to put up with, right?
It sort of overblows.
actions taken. Now, in particular, the U.S. has a sort of culture-stressing
mitocracy, right? There's this sort of image of like the self-made man or
rags-to-riches kind of mythos that goes with being in the U.S. and this can make
policies around minimizing inequality harder because there's an assumption
that if anyone can become wealthy they can, you know,
anyone could become wealthy if they just apply themselves right now this isn't to say that
like the choices we make aren't important or that successful people didn't work really
really hard to earn their success but it can make us forget things like luck and inheritance
it also compounds and ignores systemic discrimination against minorities and women that go hand
in hand with income inequality particularly in the US.
So this is a screenshot from Pew Charitable Trusts
where they looked at intergenerational mobility.
So how likely a child born in one quintile
will move to the other as an adult.
And as we can see, there is mobility, right?
And there's a color for every column on this.
chart, but there's also stickiness, right? 43% of people born in the bottom are going to stay
there as adults and 40% of people born in the top are going to stay there. So that doesn't look like
a, you know, system of pure mitocracy and, you know, this focus on choices and strategy
and actions kind of downplays this reality.
So another interesting aspect of hindsight bias is how strong the effect can have on
seemingly unchangeable views and value systems.
So this study is a study that looks at choice blindness.
Choice blindness is when making a choice we might not be 100% sure of our decision when
we make it, but after we make it we sort of look retroactively with this understanding
of assurance.
Like we always knew all along that we wanted to make that choice and that's the choice
we made.
So in this study participants would rate charged policy questions, questions like how far are against you
for the government looking over your emails to prevent terror attacks, questions like that.
So they would rate those questions and then afterward the researchers would collect the results.
They actually swapped out the questions,
so they taped over a new set of questions that would change some of the policy questions and kind of flip them in reverse.
and then they would hand them back to the participants
and they ask the participants to explain their choices.
And almost 70% of the participants
failed to notice all the changes,
ending up arguing against their original position
on at least one occasion.
So this strong tendency to assume choices
made were done for a reason
might be what's so powerful behind the use of games
to make effective tutorial systems, right?
By collapsing the choice space provided to players to ensure
that they either get it right away or fail fast and then
succeed, players can feel like the decisions they made were
because they wanted to and knew all along what the
outcomes would be.
This makes learning more impactful and players more
likely to retain the information than if they were
just told or shown what to do.
And this is an example of Plants vs. Zombies tutorial
system where the choice space is greatly reduced so people
can understand pea shooters.
Hindsight bias, though, can be really challenging for designers.
It can lead players to groupthink.
If one strategy was successful and another not so, players might question the person
who had the faulty strategy because they should have known all along that it wouldn't work.
It could lead to players repeating the same tested strategy, so if something works but
maybe it's not optimal, it's really hard to get users to challenge that.
They'll just keep making that same strategy over and over again.
Now, there's no solution to completely eliminate hindsight bias in its totality,
but there are ways to reduce it.
So, some of those are to consider alternate explanations
or opening one's mind to different perspectives.
So I think games that use kill or death cams do this
to prevent the players from feeling discouraged
in games with lots of instant kills.
You know, being shown how much luck or randomness
was involved in a player's death
can prevent this idea of like,
oh, I keep dying all the time.
I'm just not very good at this game.
Right, instead they can see how much luck was involved
and instead be like, oh, I wanna play again
because maybe next time I'll be lucky
and I'll survive longer.
So hindsight bias takeaways.
Hindsight bias can increase confidence but decrease rational thinking.
It can be stronger when there are negative impacts or a perceived limited set of explanations.
And having people think about other possible outcomes or effects can minimize the bias.
Okay, so last place aversion.
This bias I actually didn't know about
until I started researching for this talk.
But I think many of us have probably experienced this,
particularly when we're going to check out
at the grocery store and we're confronted
with a series of long lines.
Maybe we're at the end of one line and then we realize maybe there's, you know, this line is moving faster.
So we move to this line and then maybe we move to another line because that seems to be moving faster.
And then we realized if we just stayed put, we'd probably be further along.
So there is research to back this up.
When people know that they're at the end of a line, they're twice as likely to swap queues
and four times as likely to exit that queue altogether
than if they know that just somebody else is behind them in queue.
Right. So as soon as somebody steps in line behind you, that kind of...
that fear is minimized in terms of needing to swap queues.
Last place aversion shows up in various economic situations.
So here's a chart from a study showing
how likely people are for supporting an increase
in minimum wage policies broken down by income.
And the people who are the least likely to support minimum wage
policies are actually those people making
just above minimum wage.
So the idea of like if it's increased, then all of a sudden now I'm kind of in the same group making minimum wage,
that doesn't feel as nice to me, even though maybe it could benefit people on the lower end of the earning spectrum.
So in games, you know, there's not too many game systems
that consistently trigger last place aversion,
at least that I've studied.
But I mean, I think that it shows up in various situations,
especially for things like leaderboards
and endgame ranking systems, right?
You're always trying to make sure you're not coming
in last place.
There are systems that kind of collapse the extremes
of the leaderboards if there are a lot of people.
And
I think the addition of AI players in competitive games
can also kind of inflate
the rank between the human players, right? This can amplify
the pressure to need to, you know, make sure you're not coming in last,
maybe more so than competitive games without those AI players.
And ranking leads us back to, again, thinking about unequal systems.
Now, most game systems, they're unequal, right?
This drives competition, engagement, challenge, and suspense.
You know, if game systems were equal, like, no one would win.
Even co-op games are, you know, players playing against a system, right?
There needs to be a challenge to overcome.
There needs to be some sort of...
unequalness in order to engage players.
And when there's not, there's not a lot of motivation or it just doesn't
feel as challenging or interesting.
So this is the Landlord's Game. This was
one of the original...
versions of monopoly and Lizzie McGee when she made this she wanted to compare
a very like you know hard capitalist system against a more egalitarian system
so she had two rule sets and the second rule set was like showing the merits of
a more equal world but it lacks the appeal of the competitive first system
right like nobody really enjoyed playing the game where you go around the board
and you redistribute wealth to everyone else.
So people took that first rule system and kind of iterated on it and sort of
made it into this sort of unbalanced game system that we know today as
Monopoly. Now an unbalanced game system has the same sort of problems, right? It
no longer provides a challenge to the winner and losers might feel like they
have no control, prompting frustration and a sense of helplessness. So you know
most games we try to limit this by rubber banding.
Now sometimes rubber banding is social.
This usually happens when rank is obvious
and there's a clear ending like in Sari or Munchkin.
Almost always someone at some point
will gang up on the winner
when they have the agency to target other players
like knocking players home in Sari
or attacking players in Munchkin.
Sometimes the game systems can reward the players who fall behind.
Probably the most common example is Mario Kart, right?
If someone's falling behind, they get better boosts
that they can then set up against people in the lead.
But the problem with this is that the game...
system can feel like it's kind of putting its thumb on the scales
and this can make the system feel unfair to players
and if it done too much it can also make the
you know unexpected last minute wins that just feel unrealistic
and this ends up dulling you know a winner's sense of accomplishment when they win
or raises suspicion when they lose
So, games that end up turning what we're banning into an explicit and clear game mechanic
often become more palatable to players just because it's really obvious and clear that
it's there and who can use it and when it can be triggered.
And this is especially true in systems with AI players, right, because people are always
sort of assuming AI players are cheating anyway.
So again, being as clear as possible with these kind of mechanics is important.
So a great example is the robber in Catan.
And another great thing about this is that it also forces players to use it, right?
If you roll a seven, you have to use it.
And this can remove some of the social pressure that players might have,
whether or not to punish somebody else.
So, you know, this is all good, but what about an economy?
When Michael Norton and Dan Ariely surveyed people in the U.S.,
they asked people what they thought their ideal distribution of wealth would be.
What would create a system that would again motivate people to work really hard
and innovate stuff, but also wouldn't be so unbalanced as to create some negative feedback loops?
And surprisingly, across ideology, wealth, education,
and other factors, more or less, this
is the amount of distribution people wanted.
Again, surprisingly to me, I had assumed
that people who are more conservative
would want a lot of income inequality.
People who are more liberal would maybe want more equality.
But actually, it's around the same amount.
They then asked what they, you know,
those people, what they thought the actual distribution was.
And again, across differences, people reported similar answers.
This is what they think the distribution is.
And this was the actual distribution of wealth in the US, again, from 2010,
so about eight years ago.
So what does this mean for an economy, right?
Again, like when things are unbalanced, they have negative impacts.
Part of what could drive an economy when you have such inequality
is that you have a lot of companies with a lot of capital,
and this can drive things like mergers and acquisitions.
So instead of coming up with really cool products
and innovative systems, if a company has a lot of money,
you just sort of buy out other smaller companies, right?
And this can suppress research and development spending
and can suppress different types of innovation.
Also, when there's a lot of unbalance
between labor and capital,
you can actually have people
disengage from the labor force, right?
If they think that if they're going to be working a lot
and they're just not going to be able to earn like a living
wage, that might not drive them to earn an extra degree
or try to go into different types of work
because they might not think it's worth the effort.
Now, again, this is US distribution,
but inequality is growing for other countries as well.
So it's just another thing to think about.
And, you know, like leaderboard ranking in games,
as an economy grows more unequal, status is emphasized.
So, here's a study where researchers wanted
to know what the difference is in search terms through Google
for people who live in a more equal state like Colorado,
compared to a highly unequal state
like Louisiana or New York.
And they found that about 70% of those differences had to do
with positional items, things like searching
for luxury brands, sneakers, jewelry, handbags,
those kind of things.
And another study from MIT wanted to see
if they could find out the impact on US savings rate
going to things called trickle-down consumption.
As the economy becomes more unequal,
there's more pressure to spend on goods
to sort of keep up with the Joneses, right?
And they found that about between two to 3%
of the savings rate was lost to this increased consumption.
Now, for those who might not know,
Americans are not very good savers.
We save around 5%, so two to 3% is quite significant.
So, you know, a lot of personal finance people are always like,
why do people spend so much money on these, you know, positional items, right?
It doesn't make any sense.
You should, you know, save that money and that'll help you build up an emergency fund
or try to get you out of financial trouble.
But I think people who have that assumption,
they're not in the mindset of having to defend
perceived stereotypes against them, right?
Particularly in the US,
wealth can signal positive attributes, right?
We have this sort of subconscious culture
that if we see somebody that's successful,
we assume that that person's worked hard
or is smart or is innovative, right?
And if you don't display that wealth,
you might think people might not think
that you work that hard or that you're that smart.
So there's pressure to offset that with positional items.
And this is another way that inequality can perpetuate.
So inequality promotes the need to show
outward signs of status, leading to increased consumption
and decreased savings.
So this is a study Michael Norton
and Catherine DeSels conducted,
where they tried to look at five years of flight data
to see if they could find ways to predict the chances
of a flight having to land because of air rage.
Now, air age is when there's a dispute on the flight so severe enough that they actually
have to land, like not at their destination, but wherever the nearest airport is.
So these events are very rare, but they found that planes designed where people have to
pass through first class were twice as likely to experience air age than planes where first
class is either above the cabin or where people enter within the middle.
You know, there's some problems with this study, mostly because, you know, again, sample
sizes and other things, but I bring this up because designers, they weren't trying to
cause any disturbance within their passengers, right?
It sort of set up this way as an upsell.
And I wonder if we might be creating the same unintended consequences
when we advertise something really cool that can be bought in our game.
Now, there is a best practice of trying to introduce players slowly
to different types of in-game purchases,
but there are lots of games that have weekly specials
where the first thing you see is this really cool thing,
or open stores where a new player could go to
and see an in-game purchase for a lot of money.
And I wonder if this might be causing a similar tension.
in our player group because they can maybe think,
oh, I can just buy a lot of money,
or maybe this game is kind of rigged
toward people who have money to get these really cool things.
So Paul Pift, he's a researcher at Berkeley, and he wanted to find out how people react
to other people around them when they experience fluctuating status changes.
So in this study, he had people come into a lab where they played a rigged game of Monopoly.
So a coin toss would determine who was the rich player and who was the poor player.
The rich player got twice the starting money, the poor player only got to roll one die,
and was only...
able to pass Go with $100 instead of $200.
So it was clearly rigged.
However, within 15 to 20 minutes of playing the game,
the behavior of the two people started to diverge.
The poor person was more hunched over and quieter.
The rich person took up more space.
They started to pound their piece on the board
with more force as the game progressed.
And most interestingly, at the end of the game,
players were given a questionnaire,
and one of the questions was what they thought
led to their win or loss.
And rich players were much more likely to mention
a series of choices or purchases they made early on
as the reason for their success.
Very few would mention the coin flip,
which is of course the real reason why they won.
Charity is another thing that changes as a person's status changes.
So while the wealthy give more in absolute terms,
if you look at contribution rates compared to income, they give less,
with the bottom quintile giving about 10% of their total income
versus the top quintile giving between 2 and 4%.
Now, some of this is explained by large numbers, right?
If you're writing $500,000 checks, that just feels like a huge amount of money,
but if you're making several million, it doesn't actually end up being a lot.
If you're making less than $20,000 a year,
20 bucks here and 100 bucks there can add up really quickly
to a bigger percentage of your income.
But the people at the Chronicle of Philanthropy,
which puts out studies about charity trends,
they point to a different factor.
They think that as someone becomes more wealthy,
they tend to look at their safety net in terms of assets.
So if you have a savings account
and then you get into a bind,
you can draw down on that savings, right,
to kind of tide you over.
But if you don't have a savings account,
you're much more likely to invest in the connections
with the people around you, right?
If you give 20 bucks to your neighbor
and then you have car trouble,
maybe your neighbor will give you a ride to work.
So this tendency to focus on social connections
versus assets can create an empathy gap
among wealthier individuals.
This can also be amplified, again,
by other cultural tendencies, particularly in the US.
to think that wealthier people are smarter or more skilled
than others of less means, right?
So wealthier individuals can be primed
not to pay attention to the others,
you know, other people around them,
or at least not think about their input quite as much.
So in another study that Paul Piff conducted,
he wanted to see if a car status could predict
whether or not it would notice and stop
for a pedestrian trying to cross the road.
and he was able to see a correlation again with the car status.
A higher status car is least likely to stop for a pedestrian.
So higher status people are less dependent on others.
This leads to cooperation and observation of the people around them.
And this could be important for game designers as well, right?
If one of your players is
acquiring a lot of power, a lot of resources, and you're, you know, they're
relying on a team, you can have this sort of mismatch of
behavior. However, you know, just like other kinds of priming, this empathy gap
is made, again, because of information around people, right? What's in their
immediate space? If they're focused on not as much on social connections, then
they're just sort of in this mindset. And Paul Pift actually found that
you know, just priming people or being reminded of the benefits of cooperation,
community, and compassion were enough to remove this empathy gap, right?
Just sort of reminding people how important their team members are were enough to be
like, oh yeah, my team members are important. I should pay attention to them.
Um, so, uh, effects of status takeaways.
The more unequal a system is, the stronger the desire to show and compete for status.
As people climb up in status, they rely less on social group for help.
And closing the empathy gap caused by status can be done with a reminder of the importance of community and teamwork.
Alright, so what about income inequality in games?
Well, now there's a lot of pressure to find different revenue streams, right, in our games.
And one way is to add in-game purchases.
Now, lots of casual games were early experimenting grounds with various in-game purchase ideas.
One of the most common standards to come out was this two-currency system, right?
Hard currency, which you pay for actual money, and soft currency earned while playing the game.
This allows the games to offer really cool items for sale to get additional revenue,
but also gives a chance for people who might not have that money.
the shot at buying or accessing those same really cool items.
But to make sure that the hard currency is more valuable,
players usually need to sink a lot of time into the game in order to earn those items.
I think one of the problems that's starting to emerge is in-game purchases move to many other types of games.
and genres is that this focus on earning currency can change how players perceive the game.
Chris Hecker had a really great 2010 GDC talk called Achievements Considered Harmful, where
he talked about how extrinsic motivations can undermine people's natural desire to want
to explore and experience challenges.
by shifting the focus of a game system
and playing that game system because it's fun
or because it's challenging to having the player think
about how many things they need to do
to earn X number of currencies
so they can get this really cool item
that they saw in the store,
can switch how they frame that game from fun to work.
Now, this is probably really hard to discover
because players' engagement is probably just the same
or maybe even more so if they're thinking about
having to earn stuff in order to get cool things
that they want.
And removing this currency system might induce that feeling of unfairness,
that sort of air rage or that rage that, you know, can present itself
when you're trying to upsell and people don't have access.
So if those items can only be purchased, right, that could be problematic.
So it's a really hard challenge, but I do think it's something we're thinking about
as we're implementing these currency systems in many different games.
Adding multiple currencies can easily obscure the value of items, right,
making it hard to calculate how something is worth.
So if a player thinks that an item is worth X amount,
and then they use it and they feel like there's a mismatch,
they could regret that purchase, right?
They might regret that.
And even more important is not changing the value of things already in existence.
Again, going back to all the different types of loss aversion,
if a player spends time or money or effort buying or customizing something,
they put a lot of value into it.
They have a strong value association with it.
And any kind of change that happens that can, you know,
diminish that sense of value can upset players, right?
So it's really important to think about if there is a challenge that needs to be made
because, you know, we as game designers are always constantly using player feedback in
order to adjust our systems.
Trying to give as much time as possible for people to process that change is really important.
And then taking even a further step back, thinking about
you know, what does this mean for all of us as designers?
You know, we're working on balancing unequal systems
and understanding how people's behavior
in those systems can change as they grow more powerful
or as they obtain more or less status in a system
is really important so that we can craft those systems
we want our players to feel and to have.
But we're also in an interesting point in time.
For most of us in the US and maybe other developed countries,
I think inequality is starting to shape some of the changes
in our civic and social life.
And trying to understand these current events
in light of some of this research,
this is, yes, me trying to be affected by hindsight bias,
right, I'm trying to understand this complex thing.
But I think it might drive us to ask, are the things we're developing, are they reflecting
this shift that's happening?
Will historians years from now kind of analyze the game systems that you guys are making
and maybe point to some of these changes?
For example,
Eric Zimmerman and Naomi Clark gave a 2011 GDC talk
where they identified a new genre called fantasy of labor games.
These are games based on grinding where the main mechanic is time.
And unlike skill games, fantasy of labor games have little learned skill.
Right. The appeal of these games is that any player can just jump in
and move up the ranks if they invest enough time into these games.
Right. A classic example is probably Farmville.
you plant a seed and then come back 15 minutes later and you get money for your pumpkins.
But historians might point to the fact that these games rose to prominence when productivity
was decoupled from earnings, meaning as people made more and more things, their wages sort of
stayed the same, they kind of flatlined. And these games might have been so popular because they
provided this sort of escapist world reinforcing this myth of the harder you work, the more you earn.
a world looking less likely than the ones players were actually living in.
Another important aspect I think we all need to pay attention to is the data sets we're
using in building.
Many of these data sets are preserving systems of inequality, not because they were designed
to necessarily, but because they rely on data that reflects biases we humans have built
in over the years.
An example is using credit scores in the US
to determine who can get hired, who can start a business,
who could buy a home.
And these systems are perpetuating
racial and gender discrimination.
And even something as seemingly innocent
as facial recognition software can have these biases built in,
as shown by the research done by Joy Boulamani.
So, and even further step back, you know, usually my talks end with like, okay, now
that we've learned about history, you know, how can we be more aware about making sure
we're crafting experiences that we want our players to have?
But I'm sort of kind of flipping it back now on you guys because, you know, there's, you
guys are very, very smart and we're all trained to sort of look at.
balancing a game system, and now balancing an economy is completely different,
but I do think that maybe you guys have some fresh ideas and proposals,
and maybe thinking about how to share that data with people
who can actually influence things that will make
the growing unequalness and unbalancedness that we see in our economies
maybe less so. So, can game designers
save the world?
So thank you. That was a lot to unpack. Um,
I just want to spend a couple of time.
moments thanking people.
So, Sorin Johnson was my mentor.
Jeff Engelsten, who has Ludosity podcast, which is amazing.
And Project Horseshoe, if you guys worked
and contributed on that, awesome, you guys are amazing.
If you don't know what Project Horseshoe is,
it's basically a game jam where designers
write up white papers around different design problems,
and they have amazing resources, so you should check it out.
Thanks everyone.
I don't know how much time we have for questions.
Oh, here's some additional readings
if you are interested in income inequality.
I did a lot of research and a lot of reading,
and so here's some books you'll want.
All right, thanks guys.
Thank you.
Wow, five minutes, geez, all right, I must have talked fast.
Can I ask a question?
Yeah.
OK, cool.
So I guess this is not a question of maybe
if you had an observation on it.
So I've been really researching a lot of collectible games,
especially collectible card games.
And some of the collectible card games,
in terms of play mechanics, players
tend to dumb down their play for other players
in order for them to like.
you know, even the playing field.
So were there any studies or sort of moments in those studies
where they saw like their research like turn and be like,
this is unfair, or this is bad?
because there are a lot of games in the sphere that I'm researching that they just let that
behavior happen and it is dependent by play group and it really like affects the whole format as a
whole so I just wondered if there was any. Yeah I was looking at so when I was trying to find games
that have or cause like a last place aversion I was like drawn to
Left 4 Dead, or I'm sorry,
the Dead of Winter board game.
Because, like, that game is just so interesting
because it's like, you know, you have people
whose job it is to tank that game,
but also because of how it's structured.
So, like, you have the goal,
and then you have your own goal.
If your own goal isn't met,
then there's some drive to tank the game
without that being, like, your goal.
But, and so that's sort of, I mean it's not last place aversion, but it's kind of
like this idea that like if I can't have it all, then no one can kind of thing
that maybe the designers were thinking about, but was interesting. But in my
studies in particular, most of it was just again on like social relationships
in terms of finance, so I didn't really see too much of that. Yeah, I don't know,
but definitely it's interesting to think about, because you definitely see that a
lot in games.
So my question is, to what extent have you seen in studies or research in this,
that different play styles that arise from socioeconomic strata?
Because it was interesting, like, particularly in terms of the status stuff you talked about,
and I wondered whether you see that carry over into actual gameplay styles from players.
I think that there are definitely examples where that, like,
the relationship of people with a lot of status
or a lot of power are not necessarily as cooperative
with other people of lesser means.
And I think different, I mean, I don't know.
I don't really have, I guess, that much knowledge
that I can just pull out of my head about gameplay examples,
but I'm sure it shows up in those kind of situations.
Have you ever encountered any developers' gaming last place
aversion by, for example, say, when you're in a queue
to get into a server, instead of showing how many spots away
you are from getting in, showing how many people are behind you
and all the people who are worse off than you,
into any sort of?
I haven't in games but the research for the Last Place Aversion looked at
queues for telecommunications so when you're in line for someone if somehow
you instead they can focus on like how many people are you are out of how many
people then that makes people like stay in line or on the phone longer if they
know that they're like other people in the queue behind them that was what the
the studies were looking at
I don't really know, again, how in depth that would work for games, but maybe it's something
worth considering.
Hi.
So given the delta of utility in a game where one person wins and everybody else loses,
obviously, the net...
penis, I don't know what the word for that is, is like seriously negative.
Do you have any thoughts on designing games where,
even though maybe they're still like a winner,
because yeah, it's fun to win,
people don't necessarily feel that sense of negativity
in the same way or like it balances out a bit more?
I mean, I think that when it's balanced
so that people feel like they almost won
or they could have won or they were close to winning,
definitely helps.
And then you have like, I mean, it's the same with co-op.
Like if you're beating the system in pandemic
and you get only so far and then the game destroys you,
that just doesn't feel very good.
But if you get pretty far and you feel like you could have.
maybe won that, or if you only did a few things,
you could have passed it or maybe beat it,
then you have that sense of happiness,
or at least engagement in terms of the,
like, next time I go in it,
I can totally beat this kind of sense.
Yeah.
The MSs tend to feel better to players, you think?
Yeah. Yeah, okay.
Yeah, definitely. That's great.
And I think that's part of the thing
that I was trying to talk about, the balancing, right?
You don't want, it's so unequal where one person
just blows everybody else out of the water,
because then it's like...
Well, you know, it's also for entertainment too.
If you're watching a soccer match and it's like 10 to zero,
it's no longer fun to watch the soccer match.
There's nothing engaging about it.
Thank you very much.
All right, well, thank you guys.