this is all true. Even that long list of
post-nominals are actually legit
movement certifications that I hold.
We'll talk about that later. Yes I'm also
a technical artist at Facebook. Yes
Facebook hires technical artists. If any
of you guys are technical artists looking
for work please come talk to me. And
before we dive in let's do a little bit
of housekeeping. So we're actually going to do
our very first movement exercise. So I
want you to take one of your shoulders
depending on which side of the
room you're at, and I want you to turn it
so it's pointed.
roughly at one of those beautiful green turquoise-ish shirts in the back.
So there we go. Yeah. Okay.
Now, whichever shoulder is pointed at those guys—
No, no, no, stay in that position. Hold that position.
Okay, so whichever shoulder is pointed at those guys,
I want you to take your hand, I want you to stretch that arm out
all the way through the finger.
Get a nice point at whichever shoulder, whichever beautiful green shirt you're pointing at.
Now, I want you guys to repeat after me.
You.
Come on, you guys, with feeling.
awesome. Yes, thank you CAs. You guys are awesome. You guys, in fact, give them a round
of applause. So like I said, I've been, I've been speaking here a long time and this conference
would not go off the way it does without those guys. I mean, they're here before we're here.
They're here after we're here. They do, they, they, they basically do all the, all the micro
dirty jobs and make sure that GDC is an awesome conference.
So, you know, and help them out you guys.
If they, you know, if they ask you to do something, you know,
they're not trying to assert their dominance.
They're not trying to get you to respect their authority.
They're just trying to make sure the conference runs smoothly.
So, and on the flip side, you know, if some of, some of our students,
they're all volunteers, if they come up to you and have questions about the
industry or, you know, they want to ask, you know, spend some time with you,
like, you know, give them your ear for a bit, you know, like, you know,
help them out.
And another way you can do that, and I don't have a slide for this,
but you guys have probably read it.
is follow the code of conduct.
GDC has a pretty simple, non-intrusive code of conduct.
And it's got a couple points.
Like I said, I don't have it here.
But I think we could sum it up best
in the words of one of the preeminent philosophers
of at least my generation and one
of my favorite movie characters, Dalton from Roadhouse, who
said, anybody?
Yes, oh my god, be nice.
Thank you.
You're my people.
We can do this.
Oh, I'm so excited.
OK, I'm double happy now.
And another way to be nice and.
make this your conference and keep it your conference.
And you guys are going to get tired of hearing this.
You're going to hear this the next three days,
but please fill out your evaluation forms.
And this is a serious thing, you guys.
And I know it kind of sucks.
I mean, I went to like one session yesterday
and already my inbox is like,
hey, fill out this, hey, fill out this.
But we really do value that feedback.
I mean, that's what kind of makes this conference
you guys' conference, you know?
I mean, all the organizers for all the disciplines
and all the tracks read all the feedback.
and it really does help kind of decide what you guys want.
I mean, if you guys like this, who knows?
Maybe next year we'll do a full on, I don't know,
like full on workout.
I'll get my buddies on it to roll some gear down here
and we'll swing maces for an hour.
I don't know, we'll do something like that.
But, and me personally, I'm actually really interested
in what you guys have to say too,
because this presentation in this incarnation,
I've never actually done for, I guess,
a general population fitness audience.
Like I've done it as kind of a,
like a full on day long workshop.
But usually it's been for other coaches,
gyms, trainer in sessions.
But I want to kind of take this out
to a more general population.
So you guys are kind of like my beta testers.
So I mean anything that you guys
from your specific perspective think is useful,
like anything you like,
if there's something you wish you had gotten out of this,
if there's something you wish I'd talked about more,
something I talked about less,
if you think my jokes are terrible,
they are, they're not gonna get better.
I mean if you don't like my shirt,
which I would actually take kind of personally,
because I think this is like.
This actually passes for fitness industry presentation formal.
I mean, I match.
I'm wearing, I guess, partial synthetics
with no swoosh or animal or stripes on the side.
I mean, I'm doing all right.
Can you believe I dressed myself this morning?
I did.
But that's another thing.
I laugh too much at my own bad jokes and deprecating comments.
So you can write that down, too.
But I've been hearing that for 13 years.
So I guess that just means I need to write better jokes,
right?
Teachable moment.
Yes.
All right.
And lastly, one of my favorite quotes
from one of my favorite.
I don't know what you call him anymore, Joe Rogan.
Be the hero of your own story.
What that means is for the time that we spend here,
we are going to be in a,
I'm looking at this more as a personal training session
than a seminar, and we are gonna actually do some moving,
but one of the hallmarks of a good personal training session
that we see at the Yoneda Academy,
which is kind of my alma mater for personal training,
is training is largely experiential.
A training session is a story,
and you guys, the clients, are the heroes of that story.
So I wanna make sure that.
everything we talk about like somehow comes back to you.
That means if you have a question,
go ahead and jump up in the middle of the presentation
and ask it.
I mean, I've kept the practicum and the theorem
like kind of purposely short,
like we'll probably be out of here in about 45 minutes
so you guys, so we can have kind of
that real time conversation.
Okay, so let's go ahead and start that story,
but with the boring part that is talking about me.
So yeah, it's actually,
I don't think it's a horribly boring story, but.
But it's really interesting to me
when I kind of look back at sort of my path up through,
from like fitness enthusiast to fitness pro
to now fitness education lecturer,
because it's kind of inextricably linked
to sort of my time in the games and tech industry.
And actually there's some cool artifacts.
Like Ross, there you are.
So that guy right there, Ross Patel from,
where are you at now, BioWare Austin?
So Ross and I were at Crystal Dynamics together
years and years together,
and he was actually one of my first personal training clients
and training partners.
And one day, if we ever are in the same town,
we'll probably train together again.
And good talk at TABC, by the way.
You made your old man proud.
Thank you.
Ross is also somebody that I mentored in tech.
I knew Ross before he was a tech artist, and so I mentored him.
So he's actually been kind of with me through this whole path.
So thank you for coming, sir.
But the other cool thing was just that a lot of these companies
have really good fitness programs.
They have really good gyms.
And that's actually kind of how we all got together.
We were all at the gym.
And I kind of realized that, oh, it's actually really fun
to train people.
It's actually really fun to research this.
And since I was kind of in software engineer, developer,
kind of nerd mode, take that how you will, I apologize,
I really did like kind of the research side.
I mean, putting together programs for training
is a lot like putting together programs for writing code
programs.
I mean, because you have to debug.
You have to try things at work.
You have to take things that kind of already exist
and maybe rearrange them.
And so.
So it was kind of a natural fit and now that I've actually gotten into what we call movement coaching,
it's even more so because movement, you know, and what makes good movement and how we use good movement to kind of,
like I said, we're here to really turn back the hands of time, you know, to make sure that, you know, if you have movement conditions or pain,
we're trying to get you out of that, is even more of a puzzle because even though we all have, you know,
I mean, able-bodied people, we all have a spine, a neck, two shoulders, two elbows, you know, all these wonderful things we have.
Everybody is subject to different things.
We hold tensions differently based on how we do things.
So figuring out what's right for you
is just like trying to chase down that bug
or trying to figure out exactly what shade of blue
that one picture should be
that's throwing off the whole image.
So let's see, was it Intel I was at?
So I was at Intel, yeah, about three or four years ago.
And I was kind of climbing that hill
up to that age that shall not be spoken.
And I was kind of thinking to myself, well, you know,
somehow I made it this far being relatively unencumbered.
So I wonder what I do with all my free time.
And of course, I thought back to spending time
with guys like my buddy Ross and all these other great people
that I've trained with at a bunch of other gyms.
I thought, you know, that was really fun.
I should try and do that for real.
And so again, thankfully, because a lot
of these companies have very flexible schedules
and pay very well, I was able to kind of get
onto a real fitness education path, which kind of led me
to where I am today.
And so again, these are some of the certifications I have.
Viking ninja, that's like the coolest thing ever, right?
And so, and these are all the,
what these all have in common is,
they're actually not strength
and conditioning certifications.
They're actually more along the lines of physical therapy,
rehab, prehab, correctives.
And that's actually what I bill myself as.
I'm actually a movement coach and corrective specialist.
And it's really interesting.
The way I got into all this was,
is everybody here familiar with Rigging Dojo
or some of you guys heard of Rigging Dojo at all?
Yeah, a couple of you guys.
So Brad Clark, I found out, he's a really good friend of mine.
And he lives out in Austin where the Onnit Academy is.
And I'd kind of seen Onnit's ads come up on Facebook.
And at the time, it's Joe Rogan with the gorilla kettlebell
looking all hard.
And at the time, I thought they were a clothing company,
which is funny because they'll actually tell you
they are if you ask them.
But he sent me a podcast from them.
So of course, me being the obsessive impulsive that I am,
binge watched all their podcasts, thought this is great.
And so I come to Seattle to DJ a show and just by sheer coincidence on I was doing a one of their I think it's actually their first sort of vacations that weekend so I dropped in got certified said wow this is great and three years later I'm here and I love all this stuff and I'm really excited to actually talk to you guys about it and speaking of you guys.
Let's talk about that so.
The interesting thing about the tech industry that I've noticed as kind of a sort of outsider,
not outsider, is there's been this really interesting progression of what training programs
people have.
I don't know if you guys have noticed this, but everywhere I've worked, everybody kind
of does a similar training program.
For example, when I was at Bungie back in 2007, everybody there was into boxing fitness
or MMA.
It probably had to do with the fact that.
We're in the 434 building at Kirkland, which
is right up the street from AMC Pankration, which
if you're a UFC fan, that's where
Mighty Mouse does his camps, which is kind of awesome.
And when I was at, let's see, when I was at 3, two years
later, everybody was on P90X.
And now it's things like, I think it's Body Beast.
I still see some P90X, a lot of OCRs.
So let's talk about you guys.
Who here actually just works out at all, whether for fun,
or whatever structured program, not structured program,
just likes to play pickup?
Anything, just does physical stuff sometimes.
Oh, wow, awesome.
All right, so let's drill into that a bit.
So who actually does kind of some of that?
Oh, god, the CrossFitters are going
to sue me for saying this.
But who does, I guess, kind of the boot camp style stuff,
like CrossFit, Orange Theory, Barry's Fit Body,
anything like that?
Oh, you guys are my friends.
I love all of you.
Don't do CrossFit.
OK, cool. So does anybody here do obstacle course races?
Spartan race, Tough Mudder, anything like that?
How about specialized stuff?
Martial artists, dance, anything like that?
What do you guys do?
Jiu jitsu?
Sweet, awesome.
My people, let's roll afterwards.
I'm kidding, let's not.
Yeah, even better.
Awesome. Who else?
Any sports?
Oh, no kidding.
VR guy VR VR and exercise. See that. See that to me is like this. This giant like untapped market like VR fitness and air. OK, let's not get started on that. That's what this whole part is going to turn to you because I love that. But OK, cool. So what we're saying is though is you know there was this time in the long long ago where software developers taking and we were. Let's be honest, we're all classified as nerds, right? We're like the guys who sat around and didn't do things. Well, we all know that's BS. So but like I said, what I think is really interesting is.
watching the trends that have kind of that I've sort of seen in the industry and when I step back and kind of
analyze what I'm seeing what I see is a lot of
A lot of things that require high degrees of skill and movement variability and now to me that makes sense
right because we all work with our brain and and if you're not aware of this your brain is actually, you know,
Movement and physicality is very very tied to our nervous system
so I mean that's why you know, you see a lot of research now that says people that do things like
ballroom dance or jujitsu even or martial arts in general, you know, have actually,
I guess there's actually a study that showed that like the development of new white brain
matter based on these activities. So right off we see that, you know, that doing this
stuff is obviously good for us on many levels and like I said, I think that people who use
their brains like day to day are more drawn to those activities. Now, good and bad for
a couple reasons. The good thing about that is that
A, it's fun and we're all exercising, which is awesome.
The bad, well, let's not say bad.
Let's just say one of the overlooked requirements
of doing things like that is, like I said,
they have high movement and high movement variability
and high movement capacity requirements.
That means we need to be able to move a lot,
and we need to be able to move well in different ways.
So the problem is that we work in a job where
it's the exact opposite of that, right?
I mean, even if we have standing desks.
you know, half the time we're like this all day or we're,
you know, worst case, we're like, which, I mean,
does that even look comfortable?
Because if it does, I did something wrong and I apologize.
But, so, and the sad part about that is,
and first of all, I think it's awesome,
but the sad part of that is it's put us in this really kind
of, this really interesting and not preferable place to be,
and I call that the state of the union.
So, where we are now is,
There's been a lot of studies done in the last 10 years on the tech population
in general because it's been noted that the tech industry spends probably more per capita
on healthcare and research and payouts and everything around healthcare.
I actually have a number for you guys later.
And there's a reason for that.
Why?
Well, so 80% of us report that we're in some kind of back pain.
This is from a 2007 study.
Has anybody here ever had any kind of back pain, whether it's anything from like...
Okay, I'm not quite 80% but yeah, we all have.
I mean, I'm in pain right now.
No, I'm just kidding.
But hopefully you'll be out of that by the time we're gone here.
Actually, that's one of the things I like about doing this workshop.
One of the things I hear from people after this is something to the effect of,
wow, I had no idea I had a thoracic spine.
Well, you do. It's just been asleep for several years.
The interesting thing about the back, too, is the reason it's such a horrible, awful,
kind of all-encompassing, like you wake up in the morning and you're just like,
I'm just going to stay in bed. Think about what happens kind of like,
where can I get where everybody can see me? Think about what happens back here, right?
All these giant muscles, like our leg musculature and our shoulders and our lats,
they all kind of connect at this giant chunk of connective tissue called the,
I think the technical name is thoracolumbar fossia.
and it kind of acts like a corset. It just like gathers it all up and just kind of like,
you know, pulls it together and holds it tight. And the problem is, you know, our body is really
good at adapting to things. So, you know, as we sit here like this, that thoracolumbar fossa just
gets tighter and tighter because it's kind of, because your brain just kind of says, all right,
well, this is the position that obviously you're telling me that you need to be in, so I'm going
to stay in this position. And...
The back from a movement standpoint, you know, everything I said, everything connects.
So all of our movement actually starts from our spine.
And as an example, I'm going to violate the cardinal rule of GDC presentations and switch
out of my presentation and try and pull up a video.
This may be the end of my talk for all I know.
Yeah.
Okay, so this is my movement coach, Sarah.
Oh, hey, Justin.
What's up?
This is my movement coach, Sarah's child,
that she had back in August, I think.
August, September, something like that.
And he's just now learning how to kind of move.
And we were both really excited when she got pregnant.
I was probably more excited,
because I was like, oh, that's great.
We can actually watch your kid
go through the developmental patterns.
And we can actually see how he goes from the ground
to squatting to standing.
And you're gonna videotape all that for me.
And she's like, oh yeah, of course.
And so she did.
So I'm gonna show you two videos,
and pay attention to specifically
how he's moving in this one.
Good job, keep rolling.
There you go.
Also Sarah's Canadian, so she has weird...
You gotta pose off that elbow, buddy.
You gotta lift that schnog.
Schnog, like a...
Oh, you're so close.
Oh, look at you.
Oh, you're doing it.
Lifting, there you go.
Oh, you good man.
Look at you go into your sphinxies.
So that's the first movement we do,
rolling onto our stomach.
Oh, you're such a good boy.
Lee-oo-hee-hee.
He's adorable.
Need to roll back over.
I know. I love that part where she's like roll back over. You can almost hear him be like no mom,
F no. I'm not doing that right now. You're gonna roll back over this way.
Get a pose. There you go. Yeah. He's like I'm not gonna do it. I'm not gonna do it yet.
All right. So this is Leo three weeks later. I think three or four weeks later.
And I want you to watch the difference in the movement now.
Must resist the urge to check my notifications.
Oh no, don't. There we go.
Go for it. Show me your rolling pattern, you funny man.
Boom shakalaka.
Gotta lift the schnoggy.
Lift the schnoggle.
Atta boy, kick that leg. Kick that leg. Boom!
Hello, Darphin.
Hi Bubbles.
OK, so.
So I don't know if you guys notice it,
but in the second video,
what you saw was a lot more segmentation.
So in the first one,
he was kind of just like I'm just going to try and get over.
All right,
cool.
Or in the second one,
it was more of a OK,
well,
let me let me see if I like kind of reach.
OK,
yeah,
now I'm moving.
All right now,
maybe if I oh yeah,
awesome,
I'm over and.
There's actually a corrective strategy called the Functional Movement System.
I think you guys saw that there's a sticker that said FMS on that second slide.
And that's actually their approach to movement is when they're correcting somebody,
they actually go back to, okay, well, let's look at all your developmental patterns.
Let's see how you move your spine.
And the rolling pattern is actually a corrective exercise we give to our clients
that when we assess that people don't have good T-spine movement.
So.
Point being, you know, spine, it is literally the center of our movement.
So that's why back pain sucks so bad,
is because it literally shuts you down from doing anything else.
So that said, this next number will probably make a lot of sense.
That is that 45% of us have neck pain. Why?
Because A, it's right above our spine,
and what do we spend a lot of time doing now
since the inception of that horrible devil device called the mobile phone?
ever see people like that? Like, like, who can somehow just like, like, like this part of their
neck is almost just like vertically, like horizontal. That's the weirdest thing. It's like,
it's like something out of like Hellraiser. I don't know, but, but that's obviously not good.
I mean there's, there's a stat that says something like, I think it's like every,
every one inch or one degree of neck tilt adds something like 10 pounds of force to, to like,
to the weight of your head. So, so if you think about, you know, here I'm neutral here. I mean,
you know.
How far forward is my neck tilted?
This is like the whole weight of my head is just
kind of just cranking on my neck.
So even if I'm just standing at the bus
for five minutes doing that,
imagine if I do that during my day for,
I don't know, five or six,
at five or six different instances
for varying periods of time.
Well, yeah, of course your neck's gonna hurt.
So I'm not suggesting that you have to go on.
Does anybody here know who Kelly Sturette is?
He's this movement coach in San Francisco.
He recommends that if you check your phone,
you should kind of like,
you should check your phone like this.
Like, I mean.
I mean, it looks cool, and it actually feels really great,
but I'm not gonna recommend you do that,
but I mean, maybe once in a while, I don't know.
So those are some specific instances,
but pain in general is actually super prevalent.
I think the number that I found,
and this actually comes from a study
called Voices of Chronic Pain,
which is either the most depressing name for a study ever
or the most metal gospel choir mixtape in the world.
Like, you be the judge.
52%, so that's like who here ever went to college orientation, right?
Look to the left of you, look to the right of you, all right,
one of those people probably has some incidence of pain.
That's really sobering.
And specifically, one of the ways that manifests,
a couple of ways that manifests is that six out of ten people
actually cite having what we call breakthrough pain once in their life.
Now, breakthrough pain is anything from you wake up in the morning
and you're just like, oh, God, or...
You're just kind of sitting around, you have that,
I call it voodoo doll pain, right?
It just feels like somebody just like,
you're like, oh wow, I need to stop keeping
that voodoo doll in public places, all right.
And to kind of couple, to kind of give you an idea
of how serious that is, those same six out of 10 people
said if you were to ask me to,
if you were to give me a blanket tax of $1
on top of my income tax, regardless of my,
whatever percentage I'm paying, I would gladly pay that
if it went towards the curing of chronic pain.
So I mean, what's so serious that you would actually pay more taxes?
So that right there hopefully gives you a good idea of kind of what we're dealing with.
And even more so, so half of those people also said that the pain is so bad that I feel like I have no control over it.
Like I literally cannot do anything.
So I don't know about you guys, but that's terrifying to me.
Like the idea that, well, that's it for me, I guess.
This is kind of what I live with.
And.
You know, this is kind of funny, because when I was researching these stats,
I think I found this one, it was like a Wednesday night,
I'd done a jiu-jitsu class, then gone right back to the office
to kind of finish working on this.
And, you know, I was feeling really good.
I mean, you know, when you work out, you feel good.
And so I was like, all right, that's cool. Yeah, life's awesome.
I feel great. My neck really hurts,
because I think I choked on my own blood a little bit.
But I saw that, and I was just like, what would it be like to...
to just not be able to do things like that? What would it be like to,
you know, to just be in a situation where like, wow, I really want to try
and learn that new skill, but this pain is keeping me from doing that.
Or I really want to just, you know, worst case scenario, my friend,
one of my other coaches out the on Academy, a wonderful mover by the name
of Shane Hines, slipped a disc once and
after he had gone through surgery and after he was kind of into his rehab.
he was sort of that mindset of, well, I guess this is just the process and it's going to take a while and I'm going to be in pain for maybe the rest of my life.
And one day he goes to, you know, his son runs up to him. If you have kids, you know, they do this around you and they're like, Daddy, you know.
So he tried to pick his kid up and he winced. And his kid kind of, his son recoiled just in horror. He's like, oh my God, I hurt Daddy.
And in that moment, he thought, oh my God, I need to fix this because I don't, I don't want my son to think that, that hugging me is, you know,
like loving your dad is a painful thing.
So that's just an idea of how serious this stuff can get.
I mean, it's one of those things, like I said,
some of us, maybe we get to the point where it's like,
oh yeah, I have that nagging ache,
but it goes to dark places sometimes.
And kind of one of the really interesting things about that
is the way the human body works,
great quote from Sarah, whose lovely son you just saw.
100% of us have restrictions, tightness, or tensions
that could be addressed, reversed, prevented,
or otherwise mitigated through movement.
Now, the way the human body works,
so back in the day, and by the day I mean like six years ago,
to give you an idea of how fast medical research
is moving out, it's almost like technology, right?
We, what we thought was that the way your skeleton
is set up, if you were able to stack all of your bones
perfect, like if there was some mythical position,
I don't know, maybe something like the T-pose
for all you animators out there.
if we were able to get our bones into that position and then just relax all of our muscles,
like the bones would just would hold us in place. What we know now is anybody has anybody seen like
a tense what we call a tensegrity structure? It's like there's a bunch of like struts and
they're held together by cables and just the tension of the cables kind of holds them in
place but otherwise there's nothing that really anchors them. So what we know now is that the
human body is actually more like a tensegrity structure. So your bones are kind of sort of
floating in this sea of...
of muscle and fascia and fluids, and there's a certain amount of tension required to hold
that structure.
So we're always under some kind of tension.
It used to be, we used to think, well, if we could just figure out to—I mean, that's
why massage used to be so popular.
We used to just think, like, oh, if we could just relax everything, you'll be fine.
Problem is we know that's not true.
The problem is we know we need some of that tension, and not having that tension—for
example, if you've ever seen people who are really, really flexible, they end up having
joint problems because that tension isn't there.
But the problem is, like I said, having that tension means that at some point
it can build up if we don't kind of move it around a bit.
And if we think about where we are now,
well, let's think about some of the lifestyle changes that have gotten us here.
I mean, first of all, I'm not a Luddite. I love technology.
I love this. I love this. I love my phone.
But let's be honest, as these things get better,
we're bombarded with all sorts of things that are not good for us.
more blue light, more EMF.
Like I said, more time doing this, more time doing this,
less time outside.
And as our, let's call it, day-to-day technology
has gotten better, so has our medical technology,
but not necessarily to maybe the best end.
For example, nowadays, a serious injury,
where do we go from there?
We get referred right to surgery,
we get referred right to orthotics.
The problem is that may not always be the answer.
Back in the day, we were like, oh, God,
we can't do anything about it.
Then we got to this point where it's like, oh, great,
surgery, we can fix everything.
Now we're starting to realize, oh, maybe actually
by fixing things, we're just making them worse.
Because when we think about it,
the human body is incredibly resilient.
Guys, anybody here watch the Winter Olympics?
Anybody, anybody, Winter Olympics?
So yeah.
I mean, think about those athletes.
I mean, this continuum that is human performance,
whatever this end is and this end is an Olympic athlete.
I mean, any one of us can exist,
I was gonna say if we're able-bodied,
but actually I work with a coach out in Houston
who all of her athletes are what we call adaptive athletes.
And I'll tell you what, man,
when you see a guy who has a wheelchair
do more dead hang pull-ups and you can only do one,
like, I don't know, well, right there.
So point being that we're so quick
to try and apply this giant band-aid when maybe,
maybe we need to like figure out what the foundation of the actual problem is.
And one of the big issues with surgery,
expressed very well by my buddy Dr. John Russin,
so if you injure your right shoulder,
you're something like six times more likely,
I think the number's like 66% actually,
to re-injure not just your right shoulder,
but your left shoulder at the same time.
And this is actually played out a lot.
Has anybody here ever like torn your knee?
Had a, had, ooh.
Oh.
Tell us about it, please.
Which one?
What were you doing?
And there it is, you guys.
And that's the really devious thing about this stuff, right?
It's never like, it's, one of my other buddies,
a guy named Dr. Dre Spina who runs a system called Functional Range Conditioning,
says, you're always going to regret not training the position that you hurt yourself in.
And that's usually how it happens.
And it's usually not like, you know, it's not a,
it's not an immediate onset thing.
It's a cascade. It's a buildup over time.
And the problem with surgery is it puts us in the state where we're told, okay,
we're gonna stitch this down, we're gonna tighten it up,
we're gonna immobilize everything, and in weeks when we take the cast off,
everything will be fine.
Well, the problem is, we know now that that's not how tissue heals best.
It used to be that we thought that because your connective tissue has a poor
blood supply, unlike your muscles, we thought, well,
there's no way to repair connective tissue.
What we know now is that your fossia actually is very highly innervated.
So there's a lot of nerves that go into your fossia.
So it receives electrical stimulation.
And it actually holds water very well.
So what we need to do is, so when you're not moving around,
you're actually not providing the, I guess,
the stimulus that your fossia needs, A, to flush out the fluids,
like the old fluids that have accumulated toxins, waste products from movement,
and let new fluids and movement in.
So you imagine you're sitting in a cast for a month.
Well, all that connective tissue is kind of growing together,
but it's not growing better.
And back to the story about my friend Shane,
he actually just tore his ACL recently.
And actually, the story's going to start horribly,
because he tore one of his ACLs when he was a child,
and then he tore his other one when he was an adult.
So he's outside that year, at least.
But the interesting thing was that when
he went in to get surgery, his doctor said,
the one that you tore when you were a child,
I literally can't tell that you tore it
because he'd been doing so much
of this movement practice stuff that we're gonna go into.
And we're actually going to that right now.
I actually have a bunch of other slides,
but how many people are here?
Ooh, way more than I thought.
All right, well, we're gonna go ahead
and jump to the end and start the movement practice
because like I said, I wanna get you guys
out of here a little early.
So disclaimer, I am not a licensed medical professional.
I am a certified personal trainer.
I am a certified correctives coach,
but you can sue me if you want to.
Please don't. None of this is meant to assess, diagnose, or treat any pre-existing conditions.
And if you do want to adopt any of this later, please see a PT or an ortho first.
Don't go see a general practitioner unless it's to get a referral to a PT or an ortho.
So the first thing we're going to do is... I'm going to skip through all these numbers.
I'll leave them up so you can see them and be terrified.
But I don't know what that is.
All right, so the first thing we're going to do
is what we call a self-check.
And this is something you can do anytime you're at work,
you're at home.
And this is optional participation.
But what I'd like you guys to do is from that seated position,
so if you remember that first thing we did,
I'd like you to take your right shoulder,
and I'd like you to just look over it as far as you can.
And as you're turning back, if you ever
feel any sort of restriction, kind of breathe into that
and see if you can get.
little bit more. And work on your proprioception a bit. See how much of
your shoulder and your spine you're moving, but see how much you're having to compensate
with your hip. Now go ahead and turn back over the other shoulder. And breathe
through the movement. Good. Let's go back to the other side one more time. And
again, be cataloging where you're feeling tightness. Be cataloging your range of
motion. And try and use your breath light to go a little farther if you're not
feeling any pain or restriction.
Good. And back to the other side one more time, please.
Excellent. Yeah. And I see some folks have their have their arms up here.
This is this is really good.
You can if you know if it helps as a as a proprioceptor, go ahead and put your your kind of your knuckles at your sternum and just use this kind of.
Yeah, there we go.
Okay, so second part of that, we're going to turn and as we turn, we're actually going to we're going to turn our neck, too.
So we're going to turn our spine and our shoulders first, and then we're going to follow it with our neck.
Again, breathe out and crank your neck as far as you can.
Don't crank.
God, why do I say that?
Thoughtfully turn your head.
There we go.
And back the other way, please.
Very nice.
And again, be mindful of where your neck is pulling.
Are you feeling it in your scalenes?
Are you feeling it in your traps?
Are you feeling it...
You know, I mean, heck, if you're as jacked up as I am,
you might feel it down into your quadratus, your hips.
But...
Sir?
The ribs, is that normal?
It's not normal, but it does happen though.
I mean, because if you think about...
So your neck is interesting, right?
Because you have these two giant muscles here
that kind of run, that sort of attach here,
like along your clavicle,
and also attach kind of back here
on your traps and rhomboids.
And that all kind of...
And then there's some stuff here
that kind of runs out of that
down into your ribs, right?
Like your serratus and stuff like that.
That's the fascinating thing about all this.
All this stuff is connected.
So yeah, like I said, you might.
And that's why we're doing this slowly.
I mean, everybody remembers elementary school PE.
We do this sort of thing.
I mean, that's A, not great for you,
and B, you miss out on the opportunity
to kind of actually move the way you're supposed to move.
So that's why we do this slowly, like I said,
because you feel things like that.
I have a coach named Max Shank.
He has a great quote, and that is, speed hides need.
we can get away with things if we're moving very quickly.
It's funny, as a personal trainer,
when you teach somebody a bit more of a skilled movement,
or even a simple movement, when people get tired,
and we've all done this, right?
When we get tired, what do we start to do?
We start to move a little faster, right?
Just to kind of get the reps out.
Well, that's because our brain is saying,
oh my God, we need to just do whatever we can
to do the movement.
If we think about...
back to the Olympics, and we think about Olympic athletes, right?
So most Olympic athletes, most even high-level athletes in general,
are actually not great movers.
You can actually find mocap data of these guys,
and you'll see their joints all over the place.
But what they're good at is they are master compensators.
Their neural patterns are so developed that their brain just kind of says,
OK, well, you need to do this at this level, at this level of performance.
And hey, you're conditioned enough that I think I can make you do it this way
without hurting you too badly, but...
We all know that's not true, given the prevalence of ACL
tears in the NFL and the NBA and things like that.
So like I said, so that quick self-check,
I mean, it seems really simple.
But if you think about it, it hits kind
of like that major column, your spine and your neck.
And this is something, I mean, I do this every day.
I have an online, I just run what is it?
I think it's like onlinetimers.com or whatever.
But yeah, just set a timer for like three hours
and do this like every three hours.
Just kind of check in with yourself.
I mean, A, I think it feels good.
And B.
I use it to kind of diagnose what I should be doing when I train that day.
So if you guys know you're going to go work out that day and you feel something a little off,
maybe you warm that spot up a little more.
Maybe you don't do the thing you were going to do that's going to kind of rely on that pattern.
So, all right, awesome.
So the next thing we're going to do, I like to call it the 14-point inspection.
So I'm going to ask everybody to stand up.
And I was thinking about this, it actually is kind of a 14 points because, you know,
I've got, you know, neck, shoulders, my name, whatever.
But all right, so I'm going to come down here now.
And you guys can like filter over you want. I mean, I mean, let's all be friends. Geez, I like all of you. Thank you for coming.
Um.
Could I not?
Do what?
Uh.
OK, cool.
Nobody wants to look at me. Let's be honest. I mean.
Alright, so.
So the first thing we're going to do is we're going to kind of align everything.
We call this tall neutral pose.
So what I want you guys to do is we're going to go from the ground up.
And I want you to point your toes forward.
And think about this line on your outstep.
Think about pointing that straight forward.
So I know some of you might have heard make sure your instep is straight.
We're going to make the outstep straight.
And what we want to do is
imagine you're grabbing the ground with your feet and twisting out just a little bit.
So you should feel a little bit of tension kind of along this line here.
So we're going to soften our knees just a little bit,
because we don't want to lock anything out.
We want to make our muscles and our connective tissue work.
And we're going to take our hips and we're going to try and like tuck them under in a little bit.
You know, a lot of us kind of stand like this, you know, Instagram pose.
Yeah. Am I hot? No, I'm not.
And
Cool. So now from here what we're going to do is, now this is kind of, this is the tricky part.
So we're going to try and reach up with our spine but not flare our ribs out. So try and stand as
tall as you can. Imagine that, imagine using the muscles on the side of your spine to kind of
track your spine apart just a little bit. There we go. We're going to pull our chin back just a bit.
So actually do this. So I want you to force the, think about trying to force the back of
your head through whatever's behind you as hard as you can.
Now I want you to push your face forward as far as you can.
Now I want you to try and settle to somewhere that's in between.
Yeah, there we go.
Cool. So what we're going to do now is we're going to take our shoulders
and we're going to think about putting our shoulder blades in our back pocket.
So we're going to roll our shoulders back and down,
but we're going to try and make sure that our ribs don't flare up.
So we don't want to do this. If we do this, let's try and push those ribs back down.
Excellent. Now we're going to take our hands down at a 45.
and we're just gonna try, we're gonna reach out through our fingers,
kind of like we did like that first drill.
We want to kind of like, we want to feel a little bit of tension.
So this is what we call, so this is almost a perfect
H-Kin, you know, physiological alignment.
So, and this is a position you,
you practice it for like a month, you know, when you're,
and not actually, just like when you're standing waiting for the bus,
when you're at the gym, just kind of check in with yourself,
say, oh am I, and you'll be surprised at how natural this comes.
All right, so from here, we're gonna start from the spine out,
so we're gonna take our hands and we're gonna put them here.
We're going to do a variant of that first thing we did, except we're going to move a little faster.
So we're just going to think about moving our spine,
and we're going to try and make sure that our hips don't go along for the ride.
So we don't want to...
We want to make sure that our hips stay in place and just move from our T-spine up.
And we're going to use our fists at our sternum to kind of make sure that we're not reaching.
So our fists should stay on our sternum the whole time.
We want to breathe as we come to the extreme.
Breathe out as we come to the extreme.
Breathe in on the way through.
Good.
Five, four, three, two, one.
Awesome.
So now what we're going to do
is we're going to move up the spine.
We're going to imagine that we have,
let me see the original King Kong remake,
you know that part where the guy gets like,
like stabbed in the back with a spear,
kind of like he's got this.
So we're going to imagine that just happened to us, except it actually felt awesome, or we didn't feel it or whatever.
But we're going to imagine that we have a thing right here, and we're going to rotate around it.
So we're not going to, like, lean over.
We're going to try and just kind of twist from our T-spine up.
It takes a couple reps for practice, but...
And this isn't a big move. You're not going to get a ton of movement out of this.
Yeah, good. Awesome.
And what we're doing with this is we're moving up each of the major segments of the spine
and just kind of seeing how the movement feels.
Like, you know, can, do I have a T-spine? Can I feel that movement?
Awesome.
Okay. Good. Now, one of my favorite moments.
So from here, we're going to, we're going to, so that spear that just like punctured us in the chest,
actually, we're going to go ahead and pull that out.
And we're actually going to stick it through the side now.
And what we're going to do is we're going to glide back and forth.
So what we're going to try to do is make sure that our shoulders don't rise too
much. We want to just think like we're floating back and forth.
And check in with your hips. Like sometimes we tend to let our hips go so
we can get a little bit more motion, like you know this kind of thing,
but we want to make sure that we're still grounded, that we're still kind of
grabbing the ground with our feet.
Good. Now from here we're going to we're going to move...
back and forth.
So we're going to like, so imagine
that like there's kind of a rope attached to your sternum
and it's pulling you forward.
And then you can't really push with a pusher rope, can you?
All right, let's pretend it's like a pulley then, or a piston.
Yeah, like it's part of a train.
There we go.
That's uncomfortable.
And then we're just going to like pull forward.
And then we're going to let it push us backwards.
So the movement is happening.
So this is kind of from here up.
So I'm kind of like gliding this back and then gliding this
forward.
Yeah, you got it.
All right.
So now we're going to put those two together.
This is really fun.
So we'll segment it first.
So let's go ahead and glide forward first.
Now let's glide to your right or your left, whichever.
Now let's glide back.
Now let's glide to the opposite side.
And forward, side, back, side.
Good.
Let's try and smooth that out a bit now.
Very nice, you guys.
Let's try it back to the other side now.
Let's just go right into it if we can.
Just this time.
Seriously, do this every day.
Good. All right, so the neck. All right, so what we're going to do first is we're going to try and
go back to that tall neutral position because we don't want anything to move. And we're going to
try and look to the right side as far as we can with just our neck. So we don't want to be,
we want to try and just think about like you're just pointing with your chin.
And we're going to look back the other way.
Good.
And when you find kind of an edge, try and breathe out a little bit and see if you can get just a tiny bit more range.
So now we're going to nod yes and no.
So we're going to go chin to chest.
And we're gonna go nose to sky.
And like I said, we're gonna try to make sure
this movement only comes from our neck.
So let's not let our ribs kind of flare out.
Good.
All right, so we're gonna go ahead and look forward.
Now we're gonna try and touch our ear to our shoulder.
Again, try and make that motion, try and localize that motion to your neck as much as you can.
And you can do this at your own pace too, guys.
Like, yeah, we're actually doing this on time, not really for reps.
So, you know, get what you need to out of this.
You know, feel what you need to feel for.
You know, if you want to hang out on one side more, which is totally normal,
because we're all in balance, we're all asymmetrical.
Very cool.
And my favorite, neck circles. So we can go chin to chest, ear to shoulder, nose to sky, ear to shoulder.
And again, do this at your own pace. Whatever feels right to you.
You know, let's just let it run.
Yeah, you know what?
I'm cool with that.
And back the other way.
Wait for it.
Oh, there it is.
All right, good.
So to the shoulders.
And this is going to actually, well, no, we have to do elbows and wrists too high.
All right, so we're going to, so this is, you know, these are all my favorite moments.
So with the shoulders, the interesting thing is when we move our shoulders, we tend to borrow movement from our elbows and our wrists.
We don't want to do that. The point of all this is to learn to get that interdependence back into our joints.
So imagine that you're holding swords or TV remotes or something that you hold like this, Vive controllers for you HT guys,
and point your thumbs at the floor and try and not hard lock your elbows out, but try and make sure they don't bend too much.
And we're just going to like try and roll our shoulders without bending our elbows.
Again, we're trying to localize that movement to our shoulders as much as we can.
You can actually go hands forward too, if that's easy.
Let's go back the other way.
Yeah, yeah, that's, you know, compensation.
It happens all over, and we're actually trying to get rid of that.
I mean the more each one of our joints can kind of move interdependently when we go to do complex movements,
the less we have to borrow from other places that might not be ready for it.
So, all right.
Yeah, let's do one more shoulder thing.
So this is, you know, I mentioned my buddy Dr. Gary Spina.
So this is an exercise from his system called, we call these controlled articular rotations.
And there's a whole series of these if anybody's interested.
And you can hit me up afterwards and we can talk about.
But it's a multipart movement.
So we're going to start by...
with our hand down at our side, with our thumb pointed forward.
And we're going to roll this hand up.
Now, as it passes our ear,
we're going to try and push back as far as I can.
And then when I feel like I absolutely have to roll my hand over,
I'm going to let my hand roll over.
And then as I come down,
I'm going to keep rolling my thumb inward.
And I'm going to finish up with my thumb behind me.
Kind of a weird movement, but this is a great way of expressing your shoulder through its whole range of movement.
And I'm going to come back the other way.
And I'm going to push, push, push until I need to roll over.
And when I need to roll over, I'm going to...
And then I'm going to come back down.
And there's a great little self-assessment version of this you can do where you can stand up against a wall or something and see how much extra movement you're getting.
And it's interesting.
We compensate on this kind of movement
more than we think we do.
Let's go ahead and do the other side at your own pace.
Yeah, it's interesting how far, like, you're
trying to keep it in a, like, you know,
we think we're actually keeping it on a plane,
but we're actually kind of.
out here somewhere realistically.
Ah, awesome.
Alright, let's move down to the elbows.
So, we're going to hold our hands out, thumbs in.
And what we're going to do is we are going to
roll our thumbs in, point at myself.
I'm the man, yes I am.
And then we're going to roll our elbows in.
We're going to extend.
Roll over.
Extend.
Good.
Let's do that.
Let's just do that for a bit.
Let's just hang out here for a bit.
Yeah.
Oh, and don't forget to breathe.
Seriously, I've had people pass out doing this.
It's the weirdest thing.
All right, let's go back the other way.
And if you're old like me, you'll hear things crack and pop, and that's fine.
Good. Let's move down to our wrists.
Now, again, like we saw with the shoulders, so shoulders and wrists are interesting.
So, if we take kind of a joint-by-joint approach to movement,
some of our joints are meant to be stability joints, and some are meant to be mobile.
And injuries happen when...
we make a mobile joint try and be stable and vice versa.
So that's why when we're moving our shoulder,
we saw that borrowing.
That's because we're starting to juxtapose those roles.
The wrist is the same way.
When we move our wrists, a lot of times
we'll start borrowing movement up the chain.
So what we want to do here is we actually want to block
our elbows with our body.
So yeah, zombie pose.
And actually, you can even do this one-handed too,
or if it's subbed, you can actually block further.
But let's just try it here.
So what we're going to do is we're just
our wrists up or down.
And we're going to try and, actually try and squeeze your fists.
Like, see how far you get if you squeeze your fists.
And see like where your fists start to open up
when you're kind of moving up and down.
So you're going to feel it all along your forearms.
And you might feel a little bit on the underside too.
Yeah. Now let's go side to side now.
So same idea. We're going to block with our elbows and try to
not windshield wiper it too much. Let's just see how much we can get
ask of our wrists.
Good. Now let's like make circles. And again, let's try and
see how little movement we can borrow from our elbows when we do this.
Let's go back the other way.
Do you want our warm up according to the guide?
Yeah, yeah, because if not, we know that we're borrowing movement from.
So we're doing.
Alright, good.
So let's go ahead and shake all that out.
So, I do that for time usually.
I'll do 20 to 30 seconds each when I warm up.
And this is the kind of thing that,
this, you know, if you go to the gym, whatever you do,
this can replace your warm up.
You know what I mean?
This is when we start moving into what we call movement prep versus warming up.
Because this is actually good for your joints versus just like jumping on the treadmill for three minutes
or going for a sprint and not really priming the nervous system in the joints.
So let's do the lower body real quick and then I'll give you guys some time back.
How much time do we have left actually?
Oh sweet!
Actually not sweet, that means I'm behind.
So this is my favorite one.
So we're going to start by tilting our hips back and forward.
And one of the things that we tend to do when we do this move
is because we all have chronically tight hips,
is we tend to kind of like sit back and kind of break forward.
What we want to do is actually, so if we want,
so we put our hands on our hips.
And if you watch how my hands, what my hands do.
So I'm not really pushing my hips out of plane.
I'm just kind of tilting forward and back.
So let's try that a bit.
If you're like me and have chronically tight hips,
this will be a life saver.
All right.
So now we're going to go side to side.
And this is the one that loses everybody, which is fine,
because it's kind of a mind-eff.
So we're going to take, let's start with our right leg.
And we're going to straighten our right knee.
We're going to bend our left knee.
And notice how that pushes my right hip up.
So if I switch that.
Notice how my other hip moves up.
So watch what I'm not doing.
So I'm not doing this.
I'm not driving away from my hip.
I'm just driving my hip straight up off the posted leg.
So let's try that.
Can you do the vertical stretch again?
Sure.
So start by straightening your right leg, your right knee.
Now bend your left knee and let your right hip rise.
And then as you reverse that, so as you straighten your left leg and bend your right knee, let your left hip rise.
Yeah, all right, yeah, you guys got this. Awesome.
So now we're going to put those two together. So we're going to go,
so we're going to right hip up,
and we're going to tilt back,
and go left hip up,
and we're going to tilt forward.
Let's try and smooth that out.
You guys are horrible dancers. This will fix you right up.
You guys got your party scheduled for Thursday, right?
Like everybody knows where we're going, right?
Now let's reverse that.
It's only weird if you make eye contact, I promise.
HR, oh God. Do we have HR for GDC? Am I allowed to say that?
Alright, good. So let's move down to the knees.
You guys have all seen this movement before.
It's oldie, goodie.
We call it the Tootsie Roll.
We're going to add.
So it's basically, it's this thing right here.
So we're going to modify this a little bit
and make it a little bit of an ankle exercise too.
So take a slightly wider than hip-width stance
and try this out and see how it feels.
Some of us don't have great ankles
and I don't want to even get hurt.
So try to roll up onto the insides of your feet
and let your knees kind of vagus.
Now if you can hold that, awesome.
Drive your knees forward, come up onto your toes just a little bit.
Then roll your knees outside, come onto the outside of your foot.
And then push back onto your ankles.
Good, let's just smooth that out.
Awesome.
And again, try and be mindful. Try and feel where your balance is, where it isn't.
Try and feel your knees, and let's reverse that too.
Awesome.
All right, last one. Ankles. Super easy. We're just going to hold one foot up,
right, left, I don't care which one. We're going to point, flex, point.
Flex. And let's just hang out here for a bit. Yeah.
At your own pace. Like I said, get what you need to out of it.
Good. And now we're going to scoop. So we're going to scoop to the inside,
to the outside, inside. Same idea. Your own pace. Get what you need to out of it.
Yeah, it's almost like a roll.
So you're not actually rotating side to side.
It's like, if there's kind of like a z-axis here,
you're kind of wanting to twist along that.
Or whatever axis is forward in your system, I guess.
Tech art joke, don't laugh, please.
All right, let's do some circles now.
And again, this one's interesting because watch where your movement breaks down.
Watch and find for points where you can't necessarily move through smoothly.
And let's go back the other way.
All right, let's switch feet.
It's my idea. Let's start with the point and flex.
Let's go side to side, scoops.
And let's circle one way, whichever one feels right to you.
And back the other way.
All right, good.
Check it out.
And it seems super simple, but that's really
all it takes, you guys.
I mean, like I said, throw that into the beginning
of your warm-ups when you go to the gym.
Use it as cool-down.
Do it during your day.
Like I said, I mean, I work out during the day
myself, usually in the afternoon.
And sometimes it's just this.
Sometimes I'll just foam roll, just do this for time.
And yeah, cool.
So you are now all empowered to take
ownership of your own movement and your own joint health.
And like I said, it really is that simple.
So do this.
In fact, I'm going to challenge you guys to try this.
Every day for a month and see how you feel afterwards.
And alright, so now I'm going to go back up here.
You're at the important slide.
The ones you've been waiting for.
That is how to get in touch with me.
Cause I know you all care.
And so that's me.
If you have questions about any of this stuff,
please hit me up.
I can talk about this all day and I like to.
So that's that.
And we are actually out of time.
So you have to find me in the wrap up room.