So this is The Art of Thirsty Suitors.
I'm Chandanayak Anayaka.
I'm the co-founder and creative director of Outerloop Games.
been making games for a long time.
I started Bethesda when I was 19.
I was a baby.
And I've been making games in various roles, art design, narrative production, biz.
And then we started Outerloop Games in 2017.
The game we're talking about today is Thirsty Suitors.
It's our second game.
The first game we did as a team was called Falcon Age.
And Thirsty is a game about fighting your exes and disappointing your parents while skateboarding and cooking.
I kind of call it a baby Yakuza game if you've played Yakuza games.
Not that it has anything to do with Yakuza, but it's a narrative RPG with turn-based combat.
And it's a short version.
It's a baby version of it.
Here's a little snippet of it.
As you can see, it's very stylized.
So today we're going to talk about how we combine 2D and 3D techniques to create a compelling illustrative look.
Leveraging 2D, which we've learned the hard way a lot of times on this project.
Sometimes less is more, which also we've learned the hard way on this project.
Designing around the strengths of our art team, looking for scalable solutions, specificities universal, and cultural experience and inspiration.
The last two points are related because this game is really built on experiences and the fantasies of the folks on the team and myself.
of
and she is coming off of a bad break and she has really pissed off all her exes and her parents.
So the game is about you coming home and trying to reconcile all those relationships.
And that's where the turn-based combat comes into play with the exes and then cooking through trying to talk to your parents through cooking.
And the skateboarding ties into the narrative as well.
So there's definitely some surreal elements which we'll get into.
of the game.
And I think we're, yeah, we're at 18 or so.
We're at 16 right now, but it varies from how on the production.
And this has been about three years on this project.
Of those folks, nine is the art team.
But before I get to the art team, I want to say Justin and Anna are two main programmers.
None of this stuff is possible without them.
So artists, be best buds with your programmers.
Vijay did art direction concepts in 2D.
Emma is our 3D character in skinning.
Ong does, we have an animation team of one, which I know it's a lot of stuff, but he's a beast.
Alicia and Lisa are environment artists.
Darren does environments concepts in 2D.
Wade here, visual effects.
Ben, visual effects and tech art.
And myself, I'm still doing too many jobs, but I'm trying to do less.
with each project.
So we're fully remote, spread across four continents and seven cities.
So a lot of Slack and Miro.
We do all of our art meetings and design work on Miro these days, so for the async communication.
So this was the first, we had multiple iterations, but this was the first key piece of art that Vijay worked on to really set the style.
And we were trying to figure out how to build the demo and what we were going to do.
This is an early version of Jala that changed, and a version of Sergio, which is, if you played the, there's a demo on Steam.
It's her first ex, her ex from third grade that still have feelings for her, and your parents watching.
So this is gonna really set the stage for what the style is gonna be, the color choices, the texture ideas and lighting.
And then this is another concept art Vijay did to showcase what the end of a fight could look like, and some of the elements that could come to life.
So Jala went through multiple iterations.
The first piece that actually we ever did for a pitch was the image on the left.
And so, you know, it had a little more realistic art style.
And then the second version is what you saw in the key piece of art.
And then as the story developed, you know, she's in her mid-20s.
We thought that she looked too young for the type of relationship drama that she had gone through.
We did the third version, still felt, didn't quite translate well to 3D and then the current version is on the right side.
One of the early things we did was figuring out how many Xs there were and what all the color palettes were, so we did some initial color keys for each of the characters to try to set sort of a mood, because each of the characters also has their own world.
As you get into a battle, it's in the real world, but it goes into what we call their fantastical inner worlds, and each of those has a local color palette.
Some of these names have changed, and we changed color palettes along the way.
So from that color palette, we developed the ideas for the various Xs.
And they all have kind of a range of color values that we picked from.
And this took a while to iterate on.
And this is like three or four iterations on some of them.
And really, the art direction and the art design
evolved with the narrative as we figured out the story, because we really didn't know what the story was initially.
We knew Jella just has the worst luck with her relationships, but what that meant and what odor and who she battles, that came all through development.
So as we got into each of the exes' battles, there's a key color for each of the exes to design their world around.
And so these are some of the elements and some of the world ideas and kind of key pieces of art to define what those worlds look like.
Same with the costumes.
Each of the X's has a big wardrobe change as the battles start and they all tie into their key colors and personalities.
And each battle is a little different based on when Jaller dated them and what problems they had together and they're trying to resolve that through.
It's weird because the battles aren't, they don't really hit each other.
It's like all these fantastical holograms and things like that.
So it's really the personification of
them have an argument shown through a turn-based combat.
And in between the combat, there's narrative choices and dialogue choices, and some lines do emotional damage.
And so there's a lot of mixture of sort of the physical movements as well as the dialogue choices.
And this is one of the early design process for Dia, one of the earlier exes that you meet.
The whole theme for this is around the idea that in her world, she's a queen, and her palace looks like a 90s Hype Williams music video.
So there's a lot of 90s music video inspirations for some of these sets.
And again, keying off her colors to get the look that matches her outfit as well as the environment.
And then she has three minions or crystals that support everything she says.
I tend to come in on narrative design and then blocking.
So we'll block out the levels once we have the fighting system figured out.
And then this is Alicia's work.
She came in over after the concept work to do some initial geo.
And then this is geo lighting effects and some shader work.
And so by the time we go through the process, a bunch of us have touched the levels.
I'll come back and do a final lighting pass and rim lighting.
So we have a custom-tuned shader.
This is all done in Unity.
Custom-tuned shader and standard lighting.
And this is Dia's intro as we start her battle.
So there's a little sample of the battle.
It's a fully voiced game.
We're just in the middle of doing that right now.
So the way the battle system works in the game, which also affects the art and design, is you have to figure out your opponent's weaknesses.
So Dia has three question marks up there on her UI there.
And so Jala has to use various taunts and figure out her weakness, and then you can follow up with an attack that matches.
So you see we do, we mix a lot of 2D and 3D, you know, for every time Jala taunts or Dia taunts, there's a lot of sprite work.
And these are all just, you know, sprites we put together in Photoshop and then we lay it out in the world.
And they have sorting changes so that they don't conflict with the environment.
They always draw behind the characters, but on top of the environment.
And then when you put somebody in a mood, there's, you know, obviously very, very over the top effects.
So cooking is a way to build your relationship back up with your parents.
The game is laid out in chapters, and each chapter you can start the morning with cooking with your mom or dad.
You can go skate around in town, and there's random suitors that are trying to win your heart that your grandma's sending from India.
And then one of your exes will call you, and then really the big thing for that day is battling with your ex.
So there's a good example of how we set up our environments.
The top is the concept art, and the bottom is what a screenshot looks like in Unity.
So you can see it's very similar.
We bake in a lot of the lighting, sometimes into the texture, and a mixture of directional light and some point lights.
It's not very accurate, but we don't really care so much about that.
It's more for getting the look that we want.
So this was built by Lisa and Alicia came in to do some props and Ben does our shader work.
So we have one custom shader that we share for the environments as well as the characters.
And I came in and did a final lighting pass and post-processing.
So this is Jala's home.
You can come in, there's a cookbook.
There's different recipes that unlock.
And the cookbook is just frame animation.
So that's just the painting straight to the frame.
We did this the hard way.
We tried to model it out and tried to do lighting.
It just didn't look as good at all.
So when your mom eats, there's a memory of her.
This is her and your dad and their first date.
She'll never tell you she liked it though, so it's just, you know, that's what she's saying.
Again, we try to use 2D as much as possible where it made sense.
It's a lot faster for our concept artists to draw this than it is for us to build it, you know, the model out.
UI, there's a ton of UI in this game as an RPG and all the different systems.
Yeah, as well as game directing, I did all the UI work with Vijay.
So I'll do all the layouts in Miro and really white box it out and then sketch it out in Photoshop and lay everything out with Unity.
And then Vijay came and did some illustration work on top of that.
But yeah, I'm still working on UI.
And for each chapter, there's a chapter card that we layer together and animate in.
There's a plugin called DoTween in Unity.
I use that everywhere.
Every piece of UI that's moving or any piece of 2D element that's moving, it's a kind of procedural animation system.
It's really easy to keyframe.
And it makes it a lot quicker than just using traditional animation support in Unity.
So any 2D element in the game, I just use DoTween.
The cookbook was, I think it was four frames that was due tweened together and cross fading between it as it opens and closes.
In between the chapters, you can go to the Timber Hills map, and on the map is where Jalop, you know, decides where she wants to go skating or go back home cooking and go to the skate park, which is run by Soundy, a mascot bear.
There's a whole thread for that.
And this is what it looks like in game.
So concept to...
in-game version.
You also get notifications from each of the suitors, so you can do extra favors for them.
And again, it's a combination of 2D and 3D.
3D model for Jala and a bunch of 2D sprites layered with some polygons as well.
And these are little 3D models, flight models.
Official setup, because it's, I think we have 21 speaking characters, 18 actors that we're about to record.
We wanted to make sure, again, with one animator, how do we animate all these characters?
And we ended up doing blend shapes and a real basic set of phonemes.
I think there's eight shapes plus some extra smile, pout, teeth clench.
And we created an automated process to do a base pass where we can feed in the script.
to a spreadsheet, and then the WAV files, and it generates, and then we can go and hand clean up as we need it, but mostly it's animated, I mean automated, and it works out pretty well.
Speaking of animation, this is Eizo, our animation department.
He also does weird tricks when he's not animating, and a lot of that translates to, everything's keyframed in the game,
Yeah, he's a very prolific animator.
When we design the suitors, it's always fun to, you know, it's a combination of narrative and animation and, you know, everybody gets involved.
Being on a small team, I think that's what I really treasure, is that when we're designing these characters in these battles, everyone gets a chance to add to it.
It's been a fun project.
I think we're almost done.
So sometime this year we'll be out with it.
So that's Thirsty Suitors.
Thank you.
I know there's a lot to cover.
I just wanted to save some room for any questions if anybody had any questions about anything in the game.
Thanks for the insightful talk.
It's a really stunning vision with a really small art team that you have.
How long is your production cycle and how is it segmented?
Yeah, so we typically figure out what the game is in the beginning, so the first thing we did was prototype a suitor battle, and then that really went through a bunch of iterations until we figured out the current sort of combat, where it's like, okay, how much conversation, how much fighting moves, and what the elements are.
Once we had that down, we usually spent about, some of the levels, probably about two to three months.
There's a whole skate park that was in the first part of the video and that was like probably one of the biggest scenes and that took probably six months, a couple artists.
And then most of the sets are by one to two months.
And then characters, it varies depending on how many costume changes and effects, but those are probably
In a we have like monthly milestones that we kind of figure out what we're going to do.
So from design to Completion, it's probably two months per section of an area How long has it taken altogether so far?
Oh three years.
Okay.
Yeah three years and we started with a pretty full crew Well, maybe 12 and ramp up to 16.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you.
Yeah
Hey, looks great.
Um, I was wondering you at the beginning of the talk had cultural like inspiration stuff as the last two points.
And I'm wondering if you could go into more of that and how that's played into the different characters in the game and the setting.
Yeah, I mean, each of the exes is based on someone from the team or multiple stories that we talk a lot about.
There's a lot of immigrants on the team and we share a lot of shared trauma.
So, yeah, a lot of it's just based on our personal stories of people we know.
I mean, some of it's definitely, like, fantastical.
There are things in the game that I would never say to my mom, but we let the player decide if they want to or not.
Yeah, so it was interesting.
One of the exes is South African, our producer is South African, so we did a lot of, you know, she talked to her parents and we did a lot of research about like what's the region of South Africa we want to derive the visual look from.
And then we're casting.
Casting's been kind of difficult.
It's a very specific game and I wanted to, for each of the exes or characters, I want to be very specific about who we cast.
Yeah, so everything in the game is very culturally represented and it comes from the team.
The game actually started, when I first pitched it, it was a game about arranged marriage.
But we decided not to do that because none of us on the team had direct experience with arranged marriage and we didn't think we could speak to it.
well.
So that's when we turned it from Arranged Marriage to JALA and her personal relationships.
Thank you.
So I'm obsessed with this.
I feel so seen by this character, first of all, like literally attacked in every single slide in a good way.
But what I want to ask is about, you know, some challenges around designing a character like her, because as an Indian gamer musician, like in that type of vibe, age group, et cetera, I also recognize that even though it's like, oh, my God, a win, I feel seen.
At the same time, we have so many different experiences because
like this.
Yeah, we know we're not going to please everybody, right?
And that was, from the beginning, we're like, that's not a thing we're trying to do.
So Jala is half Sri Lankan, half Indian.
Meghna, our main writer, she's Indian, and I'm Sri Lankan.
And that's sort of like, we took our inspirations from that.
The colorism is also, you're familiar, in South Asia is a big thing.
So we were very mindful about like, Jala and her ex, Tyler, that's in the cover.
You know, seeing two
You don't typically see two dark-skinned women on any cover.
And we also made sure some of the men characters were lighter-skinned than the women, because typically it's the other way around.
So a lot of it is very specific, and we're not trying to really attract all South Asians.
So we thought if we focused on the character's journey, then we could be more specific about Jala.
And that's how we approach it.
And we're still going to get people that are probably not going to be happy with it.
talk a little bit more about how you decide between choosing 2D or 3D for a particular asset?
Yeah, a lot of the times we did it, let's build it 3D, and then we spent months doing it and realized that's like the bad approach.
And then we go, let's just paint it.
So for the cooking, there's at the end where she's showcasing the food to her parents.
We made that sure the camera never changes.
So it's like it's animated and it's fixed.
And then we painted something just for that.
And then for the map, and when that worked out, then we're like, oh, let's do the map that way, let's do the memories that way, let's do some of the UI that way, let's do some of the moods that way, and it just kind of expanded, just added a little more, and there wasn't really much tech to it, it's just standard Unity sprites, and sorting was the only issue, and then that kind of extends to the effects, the look of the effects as well.
So there was no master plan.
It's just, hey, our concept artist is really good at doing this versus what we can do in 3D.
And let's try to utilize the special powers of people on the team more.
Yeah, that's awesome.
Thanks.
Hello, sorry.
I think the art looks really good, although I'm curious about some of the game design decisions, mainly pertaining to the different gameplay styles and how they play into the narrative, because you see in the RPG moments, it's like QTEs and turn-based combat, while there's more action-y stuff when you're not in conflict, so I was curious on why you decided to go that direction.
Just for pacing and it worked out for the narrative we wanted to do.
So the cooking is very action-y cooking, like the combat.
But instead of battling somebody else, you're trying to win your mom's approval.
There's an approval meter.
And she'll comment on every time when you do something.
She'll never say you did well.
And then some recipes are harder or less hard, depending on... When you're cooking with your dad, it's a whole different vibe.
in the game.
And then when, I think in the video, when you fall in battle, there's a giant version of your dad that picks you up and then throws you back into battle.
Yeah, so we'd really try to key in on each of the characters and you can summon your auntie when you need to buff up and things like that.
There's a bunch of different summons that are like folks that you, might be some exes or your mom or
Whatever how it works out in terms of the mechanics We started with the idea of doing turn-based combat because we thought it lends itself to really for these narrative moments where we can have conversations Combat and conversations instead of doing like at the beginning as more of like a cutscene approach That's really a decision because the again the the conversational moments and decisions are as important as the the action that you do All right.
Thank you.
Yep
A bit of a specific tech question here.
With those 2D assets, were those lit or unlit, or just default Unity sprites, or how did you end up matching the lighting of a 2D asset with the 3D world?
They're completely unlit.
So there's just like straight PSDs in a texture sheet brought into Unity.
And then they're painted with general lighting and shadows.
Again, our lighting isn't so strong that you, I mean, if you've stared at it, you probably noticed the lighting directions, not exact, but for the moment it works.
Sure.
Thank you.
Anything else?
Okay.
Hi.
You mentioned that you have a lot of remote team and team all over the place.
How would you say, because it seems like there's a lot of interconnection between the art and the programming and the design, more so than most games.
I was wondering how you found success in making sure everybody's on the same page when not even in the same time zone.
Yeah, so we do, Mondays we do stand-ups at 4 p.m.
West Coast time.
That's when Beijing's waking up and Brisbane is waking up.
And so everyone's almost like either end of their day or beginning of their day.
So we do a lot of like what we're going to do for the week and any issues to talk about live.
And then I do my narrative mornings like 8 in the morning.
And then sometimes I'll go over stuff with the Australians when they wake up.
So I'm kind of doing on both ends, but we do a four day work week.
We've been four days for two years.
So Thursday afternoons at 4 p.m.
we'll do a play test with the whole team with wherever the build is.
And all those notes go into Notion and gets assigned to a different task.
And then after the play test we all hang out and just chat and check out games.
So that's how we kind of build a culture for over three years.
I have a giant beatmap that is the story for the game and what happens when, so everyone knows where things are and it gets updated as we change for narrative.
And then we have reference for each of the characters and each of the environments.
We have art meetings every two weeks, I think on Wednesdays.
And there's a giant mural that has all the art meetings from the last three years.
So we try to not do too many meetings, but there's like the three we try to sync up on.
Everything else is on Slack, or notes on mural to each other, or notion tasks.
Thank you.
Yep.
Anybody else?
Awesome.
I think that's it.
So thank you so much.