Alright, uh, hello everyone. Welcome to the science of off-roading. My name is Ed Pereira. I'm a
programmer at Naughty Dog. During this talk we'll be going, uh, bouncing between the high and
low level topics as we face, uh, going, uh, as we go through the set of challenges we faced
while developing the car that Drake drives around Madagascar in Uncharted 4.
Let me start with some of the goals we had in mind
when we set out to work on the 4x4.
At its core, we felt it needed to be fun to drive
for as many people as possible.
Uncharted 4 is an adventure game
that we felt that anyone should be able to pick up and enjoy,
and since the 4x4 is a critical part of the story,
we needed to make sure everyone enjoys driving it.
Secondly, we wanted a sense of realism
to keep the player grounded in Drake's adventure.
Finally, we needed to make sure whatever we designed
would work on the rockier, muddy terrain
found when driving around the mountains of Madagascar.
To accomplish these goals, we have to figure out
what kind of simulation we wanted.
When making a vehicle simulation,
you kind of have to figure out
where on the spectrum you want to fall.
You can choose the real side
with a game like Gran Turismo.
The tagline is literally the real driving simulator.
In games like this,
you can have a very realistic tire grip simulation.
Maybe the rubber wears down and the tire loses friction.
Your motor can be complex with details
like how much power is generated
when each cylinder fires.
The shape of the chassis can change airflow.
giving you different handling and efficiency.
On the other end, you have games like Super Mario Kart,
where simple fun is much more important.
There are aspects of racing introduced,
but they are largely game mechanics
rather than a simulation.
The best example is drifting,
where you end up hopping around
so you don't take a penalty
and play a canned spinning out animation.
Another aspect is the fairly simple motor
with the ad mechanics of boosts,
like when you use a mushroom
or rev the engine just right at the start of a race.
So where did we end up with the 4x4?
We ended up somewhere in the middle.
In my opinion, when you're dealing with an environment
that's going for realism, it's actually easier
to run a simulation on the more real side.
If you try to model it as simple as possible,
the complexities of realistic environment
require you to add several hacks
to get the simulation to look right.
With a more realistic simulation,
you can throw really varied terrain at it
and it should remain stable.
You might still need to tweak some of the parameters
to make it feel good, but you won't need
to fundamentally change the underlying physical model.
I'm gonna be going over the physical model in three parts.
We're gonna be talking about collision detection,
so that's the chassis and the wheels
and how they respond to collision.
We'll quickly go over motor simulation
and how it generates torque.
Then we'll talk about how that torque
is applied to the wheels
and how that generates forces applied to the vehicle.
So let's go over how the Drakemobile stands on its feet.
Stated simply, the vehicle is built out of rigid bodies
held together using constraints.
We start off with a single rigid body for the chassis,
a rigid body for each wheel,
and constraints that keep everything together.
We use Havok as the solver for these constraints,
but provide many of our own inputs.
We turned off collision on the wheels
in favor of Havok's point constraint system.
The system allows us to pass a point
that we want the tires to stick to,
and it also generates a normal force
based on the motion and mass of the chassis and the wheels.
Later I'll go over how this normal force
is used to compute friction.
In order to find the point of contact, we use a ray cast for each wheel from what we call the
hard point to the furthest point the suspension can extend. The hard point is the point where
the suspension is attached to the chassis and provides a nice reference point for the math we'll
be doing on the wheels. I turn off the tire display so you can get a better look at the ray
cast. In this image, the yellow sphere at the bottom is the detected collision point. So let's
take a look at how that all works driving on flat ground.
So this is a great start. We can make some turns, start driving. I'm a huge fan of getting
something up and running as fast as possible first and add features as they go. So this is
flat ground. How does it handle on our test track of rough terrain? That's obviously not so
good. We seem to have hit an invisible wall. I checked the level file, the designer
definitely didn't put one there. So we need to break down the issues. First and foremost, the
unpredictable collision response here is a big problem.
Second, collision response doesn't happen fast enough.
In this screenshot, you can clearly see
that the wheels penetrating the bumps
and the depth definitely does not meet our standards.
So how do we fix these issues?
First thing, it's obvious that a ray cast just won't cut it.
We consider options like moving the ray cast forward
if the car's moving,
but it just didn't seem accurate enough.
Instead, we replaced the ray cast with a shape cast,
using the tire dimensions as a cylinder for our shape.
Another tweak was to cast the ray from above the hard point,
in this case, well above the hard point.
There are cases where the nose of the vehicle
would spin a frame already in collision and get stuck.
Moving the start of the cast up made sure that never happens.
This screenshot shows the first collision point
detected by the shape cast.
On this round bump, there are actually
several points returned by the shape cast.
As a first step, we take the closest return point,
which looks fairly accurate.
This is a vast improvement.
We're getting much less visible penetration,
but it's not quite there yet.
As you can see, under certain circumstances,
it can be very unstable response where
you see a lot of jittering.
This is caused by the fact that we're only
taking the first collision point.
So it's ping-ponging between which
plank to put the tire on top of.
We now need to take more collision points
and pass them to the point constraint system.
This allows us to have this.
This allows us to have the tire sit on multiple planks,
which stabilizes the response.
We limited the number of points we used to three per wheel
since we felt more than that
would have diminishing returns.
So this looks pretty good.
One thing we discovered we don't like
is how rough the collision response is
to surfaces whose normal is not aligned
with the suspension direction.
You can see from the start of this
that hitting that first bump,
you completely lose all momentum.
This is an implementation detail of Havoc
that we wanted to work around,
so we fake it and tell Havoc that all normals
are in the direction of the suspension.
Smooth as butter.
We really liked how player-favoring the response is here.
If you run into any situations like this,
we know the 4x4 will keep momentum nicely
and not frustrate the player.
This is obviously quite unrealistic,
but this is one of the many times
we leaned away from realism
to make for a more fun driving experience.
There is an unfortunate side effect, though,
in that the wheels do not respond
perfectly to collision anymore.
You can kind of see the wheels penetrating the bumps now.
Our solution is to re-implement
wheel collision response ourselves.
Using the highest point from before,
we place the wheels so that it tangents the point.
The first thing we need to do here is figure out
where P1 and P2 are.
These represent two potential points
furthest penetrating into geometry.
Because the wheel could be at an angle,
we have to consider either side as the deepest point.
To compute the points, we take the wheel's
orientation vectors up and right
and offset from the center point.
Now we need to see which point is deepest.
We do this using dot products.
There are two vectors, one from C to P1
and one from C to P2.
If we dot these with N, our surface's normal vector,
we produce two scalars, S1 and S2.
S1 and S2 represent scalar distances,
meaning how far CP1 and CP2 travel
in the direction of N.
You can see these scalars
in their geometric sense in this image.
Whichever of these scalars is larger
determines which of the associated points is deeper.
In this example, P1 is deeper.
Now we can't use S1 directly since that's the distance
from the center to the corner.
We have to compute another scalar, S3.
That represents the distance from the contact point
to the corner along the contact normal.
We do this by taking the vector from the contact point
to CP1 and dotting that with N.
This resultant scalar is the final distance
we have to move the wheel by in order to have
the wheel's corner rest on the surface.
Now obviously if we just separate along the contact
normal, the wheel will be pulled out of alignment
with the suspension.
So the next step is projecting the separation vector
onto the suspension direction and moving along that vector
now.
Let's take a look at how that math works out.
So responding to low penetration distances,
we have a stable and correct looking collision response,
which is unfortunate for Drake.
He's probably asking if we can go around at this point.
Unfortunately, you quickly run into an issue
when you have to move the wheel so far
along the suspension direction
that it goes past the hard point
and into the four by four's chassis.
To avoid clipping the wheel well,
we limit the distance the wheel can travel upwards
so that it never passes the hard point.
To counteract the fact that you would now see
the wheel penetrating the ground,
we apply an upward force on the hard point
and it nets us two benefits.
First, it will get the 4x4 out of collision.
Secondly, when you slam it to the ground hard
it creates a nice jerk that the player can feel.
Side note, this force is then delivered to Nate.
Sorry, Nate.
By the way, if you're interested in how our character
animations are affected by physics,
and you didn't catch it this morning,
you can check out Mikhail's talk in the vault
after the show.
So with the wheels colliding properly,
we ran into another issue.
As you can see, we need to tweak what we consider
valid points of contact.
Because our cast will detect any collision,
these walls count as points to place the tires on top of.
The limit we made was based on the angle of the surface the
wheel probe detected. Taking the angle between the vertical
vector and the normal of the surface, we ignore surfaces
whose angle exceeds a designer tuned maximum angle. So what
does that look like? With the wall collision safely ignored,
the 4x4 bumps the wall and continues on. And now another
case. Okay, apparently sometimes you do want to drive on the
wall.
To solve this, we gave design the ability
to turn off the angle check in script.
Last issue regarding collision and chassis movement
is when you drive off of a cliff
into a place that is still a drivable space.
We wanted to avoid flipping onto the 4x4 side or roof
as this would disrupt the player's driving experience.
The quickest solution is to counter the jeep's rotation
using forces based on what direction
the vehicle is currently rotating.
Let's see what that looks like.
So as you can see, it's a little unrealistic,
but it's very important to keep the player happily driving
around.
In fact, for fun, we added some air control
where we'd apply forces to the 4x4 if it's in the air,
and you're pushing on a direction of the steering
stick, constantly keeping the player feeling
like they have some control.
So now that we have collision detection settled,
let's talk about powering the beast with our motor simulation.
We decided to go with a manual transmission.
It ends up being a simpler simulation
when you don't have to deal with the torque converter.
Who wants to deal with viscosity anyway, am I right?
Simulating a motor requires a differential equation
because the speed at which you're traveling
feeds back into the motor's power curve.
We implement this by breaking the problem into two parts,
the motor and the wheels.
So in this chart, we're looking at how much power and torque
are generated by any given RPM.
This curve is tuned by designers using the x and y coordinates
based on the size of the space and how responsive they
want the 4x4 to be.
Basically, the way this curve works
is your power grows as your motor spins faster and faster,
up to a peak power, at which point
you start losing efficiency and the power starts dropping.
In the simulation, the motor starts at a minimum idle RPM
and how much gas pedal is pressed
applies a similar percentage of torque
generated at the current motor RPM.
It's a big simplification of how gas is applied
to a real motor, but it's very effective.
So the second part, as I mentioned,
is how torque is generated from the motor
and transfers to the wheels.
To understand how that works,
I need to mention another aspect of our transmission.
This is a differential.
This allows the attached wheels to rotate
at different rates.
So if you slam on the gas and one of the wheels
is stuck and locked in place,
the other wheel will spin freely
and you won't flood or stall the engine.
During development, we took a look
at a lot of different elements of a real car
and considered which ones to simulate.
Looking at the benefit of differentials,
this seemed like a good element to include.
The primary reason we wanted this is to improve handling.
When the wheels are free to turn at different rates,
you get more grip on the outside tires.
To understand this, imagine one side of the car
carving one circle, the yellow circle here,
and another side carving another circle, the blue circle.
These two circles obviously have different circumferences.
So if the wheels were fixed to turn at the same rate,
there would necessarily be sliding
because the wheels are traveling different distances.
The secondary benefit is we get big amounts of wheel spin,
so our FX and foreground team have plenty of opportunity
to send mud and rocks flying.
Now with a differential, torque applied to the wheel,
torque, now with a differential,
torque applied to it will be divided evenly
between the wheels attached.
So assuming a forward and rear differential
and a differential between these two,
we now have a system where torque is divided evenly
among all four wheels.
Since each wheel is allowed to sprint freely,
we then calculate the next frame's RPM
using the fastest spinning wheel
because in a manual transmission with the clutch applied,
the wheels and the motor are directly linked.
With the motor generating torque,
I'm gonna talk about how that torque
ends up putting a force on the vehicle
to get it moving forward.
So let's talk about friction.
We have power transferred from the motors to the wheel,
now we need to transfer the power
from the wheel to the ground,
so the 4x4 moves forward.
Friction dictates how much force can be applied
to before there is slip, and how much slip there is.
Since friction is between two surfaces,
we have to define the friction for the tires
and the friction for the geometric surfaces
the tires will be driving on.
In order to accomplish this second part,
we break the environment up into several surface types,
each with a tuned amount of friction.
The designers and artists worked together
to lay out all the friction types
to make for a fun and interesting driving experience.
Let's take a look at how that surface is blocked out.
We have our grass here with very high friction
indicated by the yellow in this picture.
A muddy transition point here
with what would be an in-between amount of friction.
Then a very little friction in a muddy riverbed.
As you can see, it's really broken up very roughly.
We didn't go into fine details
of little bits of higher friction here and there,
and it still feels really good to drive across.
We spent a lot of time tuning friction on some of these surface types to make these
money climbs challenging while still being fun.
You really have to keep throwing at a plate tester with fresh eyes to see how difficult
they find it.
So let's get into some of the details
about friction and torque.
The first thing we need is the normal force N
applied to the tire.
This we get back out of havoc for each wheel
once we've applied the point of contact.
We'll let the solver give us this information
because the pressure on the wheel
is dependent on the downward momentum of the chassis
and the forces generated by the suspension.
So doing this is needlessly gritty.
For the coefficient of friction,
we multiply the friction of the tire
with the friction of the surface it's in contact with.
This coefficient is then multiplied with the force
returned from Havoc to generate a maximum friction force.
Torque is then the rotational force applied to the wheel.
With the friction resisting this rotation,
the opposite force pushes the wheel forward.
Our maximum friction force is split into two directions.
We take the torque applied to the wheel,
divide it by the radius,
and that gives us a linear forward force.
Our lateral force is a little bit more complicated.
We create a lateral slip coefficient
based on the lateral velocity
divided by the forward velocity.
Multiplying this by the normal force
returned from Havok,
we get a nice simulation where you regain control
in a reasonable amount of time
no matter how fast you're sliding.
Combining the two directions,
we get a total force vector shown here.
The length of this vector must be below
the maximum friction force we calculated earlier.
Dividing the two gives us a scalar
to apply to the input vectors
so that our total force falls below the maximum.
We apply the scalar to both directions
so the resultant total force falls below the max force.
So lateral friction force is applied
to the lateral velocity to slow the vehicle down
when sliding side to side.
In the forward direction,
we apply up to the maximum friction to the wheel.
The leftover difference is then applied back to the wheel
as extra rotational velocity
because the tire is slipping in this case.
In the other direction, however,
if the torque applied is less
than the maximum friction force,
we apply an opposite braking force
on the angle of velocity of the wheel,
so it slows to meet the friction
if the wheel is over-spinning and slipping.
One final request from design was, of course,
being able to power slide.
Tossing around some ideas, most importantly,
we wanted to make it easy to use.
We decided to implement a big fake with a hint of realism.
When you hit the handbrake button,
we simply reduce the friction on the back tires.
This lets the rear kick out,
but in a way we can easily tune.
So that concludes the driving and physical aspects
of the 4x4.
Design would give me a layout
that they wanted the 4x4 to drive on,
and we'd work together to get the vehicle
to feel and look right for the space.
Now with that working nicely, what do you do if a designer comes to you and says, hey,
it would be great if the car drove itself.
Okay then.
That sounds like fun.
So the reason for this tech is so that NPCs like Sullivan or Elena can hop into the driver's
seat and drive to Drake if he got too far from the 4x4.
Thankfully some of the AI work is already done for me.
I have to tweak some things but the NavMesh search code used by NPCs can be converted
over pretty easily so we have static paths generated almost immediately.
The interesting bit comes when we talk about how to make a car on four wheels drive towards
the next nav waypoint.
Questions to answer.
How do you actually turn to face the point?
How fast should you be traveling?
What if the next waypoint is behind you?
How do you even know it's behind you?
How do you know if there's a physical object in front of you that you need to drive around?
How do you drive around it?
Some basic principles.
Cars have a defined turn radius,
like we talked about earlier.
This is the radius of the smallest circular turn
the vehicle is capable of making.
The size of the turning circle changes
based on how fast you're traveling,
because the wheels won't necessarily grip the ground
hard enough to make the given turn.
The circle also expands the further the steering wheel
gets from the furthest edge.
Understanding these aspects of your physical model
lets you make decisions like how far
do I have to turn the wheel to make the target.
Let's go over how to calculate the turn radius
based on the physical dimensions of the car.
I based my math on the Ackermann steering geometry.
In this image, theta is the maximum angle
the wheels can rotate left to right.
W is the width of the 4x4 and L is length.
Putting it all together gives us
the radius of the turning circle.
I'm uncertain if this is the perfect calculation
of a tightest turning circle the 4x4 could drive along,
but it was close enough of an estimate
that it worked well for our AI logic.
Okay so now we're able to calculate if we can make a turn towards the waypoint. We
obviously know the location of these circles since they are attached to the car.
Assuming they're infinite cylinders, we use 2D algebra to figure out if the
waypoint is inside of either circle. If the waypoint is inside of either circle, we
turn uh...
We need to put the 4x4 into reverse,
turn the wheel in the opposite direction,
so now our nose will turn towards the target.
Once our nose is facing close enough to the target
that the target is outside of the turning circle,
we can switch back to drive and complete the turn.
This logic also applies to whether the target is behind us.
Reverse until we make the turn and continue on.
Now let's take a closer look at what following a path
ends up looking like.
Nice.
Next up, let's talk about obstacle avoidance.
Our NavMesh search gives us a really good path to follow
to avoid things like buildings or big boulders.
But what do we do if another car is in the way
and that car does not affect the NavMesh?
To detect this, we need several ray casts,
one per corner, forward and back,
whose length is based on the speed
the 4x4 is driving.
When one of the casts detects something,
we simply push the steering wheel in the opposite direction
based on how close the ray cast detected collision.
We never forget that we eventually want to steer
towards the target again, but the probe tells us
when we're clear to start that turn.
The direction the probe casts is tunable.
In these videos, the probes are directly
in front and behind, but depending on the environment
you're dealing with, you might want these probes
to shoot out at an angle to give more consideration
to what's around the vehicle.
For simplicity, we assume that design has not caused
some kind of traffic jam that we could never steer around.
This obviously wouldn't work in a city full of cars,
but driving around the hills of Madagascar,
this is an effective simplification.
A small feature requested by design was spline following.
For this, we turn off NavMesh search
and simply get a point on the spline curve
some distance away from us based on how fast we're traveling.
Obstacle avoidance is still on in this case,
since other objects can get in the way.
We want to steer around the obstacle
and continue to use the nearest point on the spline
as our target.
So with navigation, steering, and obstacle avoidance
put together, you've got a pretty good system
for getting around most spaces.
So to wrap up, first we went over collision detection.
Using rigid bodies, constraints,
and our own implementation of wheel response,
we created a vehicle that moves around
rough terrain smoothly.
Our motor, with a mix of realism and some gloss over details
we created a nice balance between a tunable,
realistic motor and avoiding the grittiness
of a deeper simulation.
Our tire friction simulation allows us to actually
drive the vehicle and make turns in an easy to use way
that most players can grasp.
We took new requirements from design,
where we had to add AI to the car,
and brought over navigation from existing systems.
And we layered on steering behaviors,
so the 4x4 can follow the generated navigation paths.
I want to give a quick thanks to some of the folks in Naughty Dog who helped put the 4x4 together.
It actually took quite a few people to put all the bells and whistles on it.
So these are just a few of the names.
Inkyo made the beautiful visual model that we all came to love.
Kristof helped with some of the rigging.
Rob is an audio designer and Jonathan is an audio programmer.
And together they worked to get things like the motor purring just right.
Jaros and Travis are programmers who helped with the simulation.
Kurt and James are designers who helped on tuning and level layout.
So that's the 4x4, the development is really
about problem solving.
We took a very design-oriented approach to development
and always focus changes on the needs
for making the game fun.
Thanks for listening.
So we have about five minutes for questions,
if anybody has anything.
You mentioned about a rigid body.
If you want to come to the microphone, please.
uh uh sorry sorry uh you mentioned about the rigid body I imagine you are not using unity
right? No we we use Havoc but it's our own game engine. Okay thank you.
Um, so I had a similar simulator for driving, and I found an issue with this.
You glossed over this real quick when you're falling down and you need to take
that wheel and push it up so it doesn't go through the ground using force.
Now you don't want to do that instantly, or you just suddenly pop up.
So you need to add force over time.
But if you're falling really far, that's a lot of force
and it would bounce my car up fairly high.
I'm wondering how you guys handled that.
So, because it's a lot of force
in a very short amount of time
because that collision when you just hit is very quick.
So to like move that,
I was wondering how you guys handle that.
So the question is,
well, how did we handle the force applying to the vehicle
to get it out of collision if it actually is already in?
We,
I'm actually okay with it being in collision for a little bit. So we don't push so hard that it
flies out of collision. And so I actually have a tuning where there's a maximum amount of
force that's actually allowed to be applied on it so that it doesn't ever get pushed out that
far. Okay. Thank you. Up over here. Hi. Uh did you have any trouble like if the vehicle
bottoms out and then the collision of the chassis gets snagged on some small rock or
something like that? Uh it
the vehicle does bottom out a lot, but the Havok rigid body system is pretty good at
making sure that it doesn't cause a problem. There are some cases, and you can still see
them in the shipped game though, where the rocks and stuff will go flying because the
chassis hits that rock in a bad way. It is something I looked into a little bit, but
it's not something we cared enough about to have to fix.
Is the 4x4 a one-off or is Naughty Dog going to look into more vehicle play in the future?
We had the boat.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, I mean we are definitely always exploring what other things we can do.
Like having the 4x4 in there was a starting off point for making the boat.
And so they share a lot of the same code.
So it's obviously a really good jumping off point for making any other vehicle simulation.
I was developing like a VR truck simulator. One of the problem I got into is like when you
got a trailer behind your car, while you're trying to like driving forward, of course the
like motor belongs to like a rear wheels of the like the truck head. But...
how do you manage to like balance those initial like uh uh you know the power when you're
trying to do some color uh the power uh uh on inner tile and outer tile they are different. How
do you like balance that out? I got a lot of problem with that. Uh...
I'm not... what's the problem you're having? I'm not sure.
Uh... when you driving your car too fast.
Yeah.
You know, uh...
we're doing color. In fact, uh, uh, uh, the friction on, uh, on your, uh, inner tire and the
outer tire, they are different. Uh, that, that's where my, like, uh, simulator went around a lot
of times. I like, uh, the way I'm solving it is that we tuned a lot to make it feel better. I
wonder how you like manage to solve that. And, uh, you know, uncharted 4.
the car is also running on uneven paths.
Sometimes it's like,
they are on the brink of getting in contact
with the ground a lot.
How do you try to make them in that very boundary moment
to make the car still getting the force moving forward
correctly?
Yeah, so the question summarizes, all four tires are running on different friction most of the
time. As you're going from the riverbed to the grass, one side is still slipping, the other
side catches. The differential actually helps in this case because we're splitting the torque to
all four tires. That makes it so that it's actually a smoother transition.
because you don't have a sudden, like, very hard grip
on one of the tires and cause it to just, like, stop.
And other than that, like, we didn't really have
any issues in that area, I think,
maybe, possibly because of how stable
the point constraint system is in Havoc.
We basically told it the lateral friction we wanted,
how much force is being applied there,
and it would do a decent job of stabilizing.
Okay, thank you.
my question was just also about the chase sequence and the other cars in the chase sequence and the
motorcycle, did they use the same model? Um a lot of that is um faked with splines. Um
there I think I think there's uh some of the same like the way the tires work and detect
collision I think is the same but the actual driving and movement is on a spline.
and they didn't run like obstacle avoidance or anything? No, no. Okay. Thank you very much.