All right, so a couple of quick housekeeping notes.
Try and keep those cell phones quiet during the presentation.
And the second thing is, if you could please fill out
the survey that you get towards the end of the talk,
you'll get it via email.
Everybody would really appreciate it.
So thank you.
To provide some context, what's my background?
So I've been working in games for a while.
I've shipped a variety of different games.
Like many people, start out in one role,
kind of transition to others.
So starting with gameplay engineering,
and then doing design work, and then moving into a more
a broader design role that then encompassed more UX.
And so for the more recent titles
have been a lot more heavily involved
in that particular aspect of design.
And today we're going to talk specifically
about the UX for Halo Wars 2.
So as a starting point, it's good to think
about what the constraints are for any given game
that you work on.
Halo Wars 2 is an RTS.
It's a sequel to a game that came out about 10 years ago.
And whenever we bring a new title to the Halo franchise,
we always have to think about what these kinds of constraints
are going to be.
So the first one of these here is expectations.
So 15 years of history for this franchise
makes for a lot of passionate fans, a lot of features
that have evolved over time, and making sure
that every game that we build delivers
on the expectation of those fans.
There's also our own internal team expectations, though,
which is how do we move the franchise forward?
What do we bring that's new, that's exciting,
that pushes the boundaries of modern UX design?
Another unique thing about Halo Wars 2
that's different from the original game
is that we wanted to take it to more than one platform.
So Halo Wars 1 was designed to be a console-specific RTS.
And a lot of the UX was built with console in mind
to be a good experience for that particular platform.
Not only did we want to bring it to these two platforms,
we also wanted to enable the ability to cross-play
with these two platforms.
And there's a lot of considerations we had to make
in terms of how we modify what that core game is
and what the right experience for it is.
Next one here is team.
So there are a number of folks at 343
that have worked on the Halo titles, number of Halo titles.
But there's also new people that come on board.
And we also had the good fortune to partner
with Creative Assembly in the development of this title.
And that was a lot of learning for all of us
to work together, basically, on what our design process would
be together, and then how we continue to evolve
this franchise together, and a lot of great debate
around what the core pieces that franchise to carry forward are.
And finally, it's something that we all deal with,
but it's a pretty important consideration
in the way that we design anything,
which is just time is always a constraint.
And I used to think that once upon a time,
perhaps, you know, that there was a bad design
that was implemented and who knew what reason it was
in any given particular title.
And over time, I've come to appreciate that for a variety
of reasons, whether it's the amount of time that you may
spend working on a feature, spending too much time on it,
or not keeping in mind when the
project needs to be shipped.
This is a constraint that basically forces us, in some
cases, to make imperfect decisions.
So from these constraints, we also
think about what our UX vision pillars are
going to be for the game.
So for Halo Wars 2, there's several here
that we're going to cover.
And we're going to talk about how these vision pillars inform
the decisions we made around specific areas of building
this game.
So the first one is, how do we instill the feel of Halo
into the titles that we build?
And there's a lot of different components that go into this,
but a lot of it comes down to the fact
that we really want to highlight the things that people expect
out of the franchise, get them to feel
as they come into the game that it's a good experience,
that it's something familiar.
And Halo Wars 2 is no exception in that regard.
We want to build an RTS for everyone.
So RTS has been around for a long time.
And Halo Wars did a lot of work to bring in a new audience
of players that maybe were intimidated by the RTS before.
But even still, matches could last for a long time.
And we heard feedback from folks that basically they
wanted a way to get in.
They really wanted to learn how to play the game.
But they were intimidated by the economy or the base
building or just some of the other features of RTS.
So we wanted to bring a new mode, a new way to play this
game that would help people to come in and feel like they had
a good entry point.
The next one here is being approachable and deep.
And this specifically applies to the way
we thought about this new mode, which is our new Blitz mode,
basically.
And it's a new mode where it's a hybrid of a card strategy
game and the RTS genre.
It's played in five to seven minute chunks.
We wanted to make sure this appealed not just
to new casual players, but also to players that
would get into it for the long run
and play competitively, playing tournaments,
make sure that this particular mode had legs.
It's also expected that a given for any given Halo title that
we offer a great multiplayer experience.
And this is everything to do with how you join up with your
friends, how you match make, and then the options that are
offered to you when you play custom games, all the way to
the controls and the feel of the game from moment to moment.
And once again, it's something that we need to think about
for each of these games independently.
And the final point here is to be a platform showcase.
So now that we are on these two platforms, Xbox and PC,
we want to deliver an experience that feels great for folks
that are coming in from both the console side
and from the PC side.
So let's talk a little bit about what the Halo feel encompasses.
So when you look at Halo titles, it's
something that you want to feel from the moment
you launch the game.
It establishes the mood.
Creates a sense of wonder.
It brings you deeper into the universe.
It makes you curious about the franchise.
We offer you fantastic worlds, and we
want to make sure that all players feel like they're
taken on this journey from the moment they start
to each of the different areas of the game
that they might explore.
So as they go through the campaign,
they're starting to think about what story elements are there,
what the characters are, what options are available for them
to customize their multiplayer experience.
We want to bring forward a lot of these memorable characters
and the heroes and to let you wonder about them
and to think about them in how it relates to the story
and to get you to come back.
And to also think about how you can customize your experience
and bring yourself into these games.
And importantly, we've built up a lot of history here.
And we want to make sure that things feel familiar.
So we spend a lot of time going back and creating style
guides and flows that we can apply for each game.
And it's not always the same, necessarily, from game to
game, but the ideas remain and the consistency remains.
It's something that feels comfortable from the moment
you get in and you start playing.
So as it applies to Halo Wars 2,
Halo Wars 2 is unique in that it's an RTS,
and so a lot of the game is played
from a fairly zoomed out perspective.
You don't necessarily get a close up view of these characters.
So one of the cool things that we really wanted to get
into that initial experience,
and Creative Assembly had spent a lot of time
building a lot of detail around these characters
and vehicles and units,
and you just don't get a good perspective on them
while you're fighting and playing the game.
So as you come into these menus for the first time,
you'll see these dioramas where the camera pans
around these characters.
It zooms in on them.
And it really gives you a good sense of what they look like.
And it makes you wonder about, OK, cool.
There's this deeper element to what's here, even though I
can't necessarily see it from the way that I'm playing the
game normally.
We also want to make you wonder about what's going on in the
campaign and what that experience feels like.
So when you switch over to this area of the game, again,
you're presented with the holotable of the Ark, which is
an important place where a lot of events for
Halo Wars 2 take place.
And once again, you'll see it from different angles.
It'll pan around.
It's an important unifying element throughout the
cinematics, because the characters will frequently
talk about how they're going to different places here and
what they're doing.
And by bringing this forward, we just create more of that sense of intrigue around what
the campaign has to offer.
And finally, we're delivering a new mode here with Blitz.
And this mode specifically, it's a card-based RTS hybrid.
And there's a lot of work that went into illustrating these
cards and making them feel very unique.
And when I first saw the screen, I was really excited
because I've played a lot of physical card games.
And I don't know if you've ever seen an uncut sheet of
cards, but it's a really cool thing to behold.
And these particular menus, as you get in,
you can basically see a lot of these illustrations put
together on posters that you pan between different sections
of that poster.
And it brings you into what it feels
like to have that card game there.
And it lets you know that it's a very distinct and unique area
of the game.
So let's talk a little bit about how we actually
went about creating that RTS for everyone,
and specifically with respect to the way
we iterated on the Blitz mode specifically.
So as I mentioned, it's a hybrid of a card game and RTS.
The matches are meant to be five to seven minutes long.
We want to make sure that there's a good focus on core
RTS combat and basically map control, fighting for
resources, but not having to deal with a lot of that early
game experience of how you build up your economy and
upgrade your tiers and knowing the tech tree and everything.
So early on, we wanted to establish some pillars
around what this mode would entail.
And we had some initial challenges
because we wanted to make sure that we
had the right controls, the right deck size, hand size.
Things played well on multiple platforms,
and it felt like a card game.
So an early version of this that we're looking at was being
able to deploy cards at the position of the cursor with
the directional pad, basically.
This is fast, but as you can see, the cards themselves,
they would have been small.
We've had different scales of this, but ultimately, they
didn't represent the same type of card throughout the
experience, right?
So it's just hard to see the details there.
The deployment was fast.
You don't really hold cards this way, so it didn't have
that card game feel.
And they took up a fair bit of space in the HUD.
So we started to think a little bit more about, OK, can we
basically take more elements of a traditional card game
and bring that in, and then maybe drop this down a bit in
the HUD, and maybe this would help us accomplish
more of our goals.
And so we did this basically card hand fan down the bottom.
You can see the cards are now bigger.
They're more legible.
Still not perfect, though, because you do have some
overlapping elements.
Selection's not entirely clear.
But we're starting to get a little bit closer into
something that feels like it fits in naturally with the way
the game plays.
And so for our final solution, we went with a four-card hand.
We laid them out horizontally, dropped them a bit down
in the HUD.
But all the core components of the cards, as you can see,
are fairly legible.
You can see the cost, the type, the name, and illustration.
And if you want to go deep and then deploy these cards,
get a little more information on them with just a click
of the mouse or a pull of the trigger,
you get the expanded card view.
And in here, you've got a very clear, large.
card and right your face there the selection elements are clear
and it feels natural feels like a card game it works well on PC and console
because it's just a couple button presses are a couple clicks away
and it felt like we had the right sort of the right look for we're going for
here
now thinking about this more though never wanted to be approachable for new
players but then also deep for players that want to play competitively
And we had a lot of assumptions coming in about what it meant
to be a card game.
So typically for a lot of card games, you've got fairly large
deck sizes, and you want to have all these really
interesting choices about what you can pull in and how you
can play those cards.
And when we start to think about this from the context of being
on console and having a deck editor, a deck view,
it starts to get fairly busy.
So ultimately, you've got some way
of representing your deck and the card library
on the same screen.
And you can move cards back and forth.
And there's variations on this for different console card
games.
But it's also something that is hard to keep in your head all the time, right?
If you look off to the sides, you're going to notice that, you know, you can't quite
see everything that's in your deck.
The duplicate, you know, the ways they're represented, it's, you know, not always obvious.
And then obviously you're only seeing a slice of your card library.
And on top of that, there's just a lot of buttons here.
So we changed our frame of reference.
We thought, well, what if we went to a model where the decks
themselves are only 12 cards, and the card could be
represented in its entirety on the screen in that deck view,
or the deck view that's there.
You basically can snapshot this, share it easily with
your friends.
you know, the way we get around the choices in terms of making sure that there's depth
in the choices is we only allow one of any given card in the deck.
And so you still have to make a lot of interesting choices around what type of units you bring,
the various costs that they bring, and how that shapes your deck.
And the leaders themselves add a twist to it because they have their own unique sort
of play styles that affect how you build these decks.
Now when we go to look at how we do deck editing, again,
it's a fairly similar presentation,
except this time now we've put the actual deck
on the left side of the screen.
We've put the rest of the library on the right.
And you can quickly and easily get your cards in and out
of your deck with a single button press or a single click.
One adds, one removes.
It feels pretty natural.
You can't obviously see your whole library at a time,
but you can page through it fairly quickly.
And it felt like we were able to solve a lot of these problems
just really by thinking about this in kind of a different way.
And there's still a good bit of deck variety,
and the leaders provide the variety,
and all those things work pretty well together.
So I think our next pillar it's really delivering on a great
multiplayer experience and this means many things right it
means how you're able to play with your friends and match
make what you can do for your custom games and then also how
we bring depth into the multiplayer experience and for
Halo Wars 2 specifically we wanted to go even deeper than
the original game in terms of how you differentiate your
armies.
So.
We had this notion that we wanted to bring in these leader command trees.
You know, something where if we play the same leader, for example, I may focus on faster
moving units that can capture points quickly and heal themselves.
And you may choose to focus more on, you know, long-range attacks, kind of AOEs, and a more
aggressive style of play.
And as we were building this out,
we felt like we were bringing in the depth.
But there was a concern that we had as a team,
and then also something that we wanted
to see through our beta, which is,
does this provide a bit too much of a jarring context
switch for a real-time strategy game?
Is there too heavy of a mental load for this?
And it came to be that we're pretty split amongst the team.
During the beta, the feedback pretty much
reinforced this notion.
And the way that you deploy these leader powers is in the
game, you basically pull the trigger and you get a radio
menu that allows you to actually activate these powers
and then target where they go off.
We wanted to figure out, could we potentially merge these two
concepts together?
As we started to think about changing it,
we started to think, OK, how can we
merge the depth of this command tree into this radial menu?
As you could see, in our initial pass,
there's a lot to explain here.
There's levels.
There's the differences between the lock state, unlock state,
how those powers change over time.
And there's a lot of things to parse here.
It's also something you don't get
a good sense of the larger meta level of what
your leader power state is.
And you have to basically walk the wheel in order to really
get a good sense of what exactly is happening.
So when we got to our final version, we did a bit more
work in terms of.
Pulling up those levels of those powers,
you can see the notches on the edge.
They're a little subtle, but you can see at a glance
effectively what levels are locked,
what levels are unlocked, and where you've invested in.
The tree itself unlocks in quadrants,
so as you spend points, the next quadrant moves,
you move into the next quadrant, you can use powers there.
And we actually removed a bunch of the text here.
And the thought was that players would organically
discover, basically, what the differences of these powers
are as you play the game more, you read about it,
you learn strategies.
And it turned out to be the case that this ended up being
a fairly good trade-off in the sense that it was quick and
easy to access.
Again, you can get in here, open this menu, upgrade
powers, change them very quickly.
You lose some sense of that larger sense of progression,
but overall the speed and ease of use made these powers
really a core piece of the multiplayer experience.
And we do see a good variety in terms of how players use
these powers amongst their leaders throughout the game.
So this is something where we felt like some things were lost,
but we also gained some things, and ultimately this turned out
to be a reasonably good solution.
Now, the last one I want to talk about here is being a
platform showcase.
So as I mentioned, we're trying to be a great Xbox title, be a
great PC title, and really satisfy people that are core
gamers in both of those platforms.
Now, in the original Halo Wars, one of the cool features
of how the leader powers were used is the fact that when you
were bringing these up, you would have this targeting
reticle come in.
And the screen dims, it goes into the scope view,
it feels very Halo, it looks almost like a sniper scope.
And it works really great on the controller.
So before we shipped Halo Wars 2,
we actually created Halo Wars Definitive Edition,
ported it to PC, and tried to bring over these powers
in a way that felt good for PC and mouse controls.
And it turned out these ended up being a lot harder to implement on the PC than we expected.
You can kind of think about it in some different ways.
So for example, without the cursor here, your normal PC cursor, you get a little bit lost
in terms of what you're targeting.
It also never quite felt responsive enough even if we mapped it to the mouse in a way
that we thought made sense.
If we tried to leave the main PC cursor up,
then you'd have this double cursor thing going on.
And if we kind of got rid of the overlay,
then it just didn't really have that same level
of anticipation and excitement of deploying these powers.
So ultimately, for Halo Wars 2.
We moved to a model where the reticles are more friendly
for both platforms.
And they look great.
The powers themselves look fantastic once they're
deployed, a lot of cool effects and explosions.
It's hard to deny, though, that some of that anticipation
of using those powers and that transition,
it's definitely missing.
So it doesn't feel quite as exciting
for that initial part of the power deployment there.
But at the same time, the game runs cross-platform.
A lot of folks are enjoying it that way.
It feels fair because you have the same targeting mechanisms
for both games, both versions of the game.
And one of our main requests that we get from our community
is for more cross-play.
So at the end of the day, this is also another trade-off
where, well, it feels like something was lost.
We gain something else.
So as we think about the various takeaways from the game
and what this iterative process brought us,
here's a few things that we would probably take
from one game to another.
So the first one here is know your core, right.
And so for us, yes, we've got a lot of history
in terms of what the franchise is,
but how that applies to each game is a bit unique.
And it's important for us to make sure
that we're constantly reevaluating what that means,
updating our internal documentation and specs for that,
and really just thinking about how it applies
to that new title.
And how we take what we've learned
and apply it in new ways for new modes
and new ways to play the game.
As I mentioned, you know, again, with our assumptions
around the Blitz mode, it's really rethinking
our frame of reference.
So sometimes we might have a tendency as designers
to kind of spin on something for a long time
because we feel like there's a better solution
that's available.
And for us, this was a key piece of, again,
thinking about the deck sizes for Blitz,
where really just thinking about the deck size
in a different way and depth in a different way
and how we make those choices,
it simplified a lot of our design around
how we build out the UI for those pieces of that game.
And finally, embrace trade-offs.
So as I mentioned, we had to move from being a console
title to a multi-platform cross-play title.
And while it's true that we did lose some elements of what
would have been great to have for native implementation of
each of those platforms, our community continues to play
with each other on these different platforms.
They enjoy it.
Some of our best players are actually still on console
today, even in a PC console cross-play world.
And they continue to ask for more ways to play, more
multiplayer playlists.
So at the end of the day, while there are some tradeoffs
in terms of the aesthetic and the anticipation
of those powers and things like that,
those are probably things that the upside of it being
that we have this cross-play audience is something
we didn't anticipate in terms of the demand for it.
So that's been really great to see.
And that's it. So thank you very much.
And if you have questions, please feel free
to step up to a microphone.
If you want to ask me via e-mail, there you go.
And, um, yeah.
welcome what's there.
Please fill out your surveys as well.
Thank you.
Oh, someone's got a question.
Hi there.
Yes?
Yeah.
Adrian here.
Thank you for the talk.
Really useful.
When do you know it's enough searching for a solution and it's time to embrace the tradeoff?
So the question was, yeah, when do you know you've iterated enough to basically get to your solution?
And again, that gets back to the knowing your core, right?
So I think at the end of the day, it's really just about, you know, for any given game, right?
What is it that's unique about it? What's your hook?
And then how does that apply to whatever particular thing that you're thinking about?
The other piece that, like I said, is just making sure that you're allocating enough
time down the road, because I think you always end up paying later for things that you end
up spending too much time earlier on.
So generally speaking, I think you're going to find your solutions faster for things that
are working.
And sometimes it's definitely worth it to pursue those things that will take you a while
to get to.
But really just knowing your core and knowing how you parse out that time.
Awesome.
Thank you.
So thanks for the talk.
And I was just curious, a lot of your solutions up there
went back and forth between making a trade-off
in the direction of gameplay or in the direction of UI.
And I was just wondering if you had any process for figuring
out, like, OK, so the solution here rests in changing the UI,
like with the cards, where they go.
But then there was also a piece of that that was like,
we're changing the hand size, which
has implications on gameplay.
Yeah, and that's why I said, like, I think it's,
that's why I kind of encourage the thinking
about the frame of reference, because like I said,
it's, you could have solved that problem
from a UI perspective, and what we're finding
is solving some of these challenges from a UI perspective
was taking a lot of cycles, and so,
that's where it came back to, you know,
does it really need to be this kind of gameplay?
Are there other models, other games, you know,
other platforms where maybe card games
have smaller hand sizes or smaller deck sizes
that we could look at?
So that's why it's great to just have a, you know,
kind of build up this pool of knowledge
of the different genres and then figure out,
can you pivot, you know, based on the gameplay or the UI?
So I don't know that there's a clear answer in any one case,
but I think it's really on a case by case basis.
And that just gets back to that point of like,
if you feel like you're spending a lot of time on something,
like try to look at it from a completely different angle.
Thank you. Yep.
Oh, hello.
There you go.
Great talk.
Thank you.
I have one question.
What was the biggest UX design challenge you encountered on Halo Wars 2 and or Blitz that
surprised you and you didn't think would be such a great challenge?
So the question is, what was the biggest UX challenge
we had that surprised us that we didn't anticipate?
To be honest, I think it was just really the multi-platform,
how it impacted the UX.
Because we really took for granted
how much of the original game was designed for console,
in ways that we didn't anticipate.
Like I said, the powers are a really good example of that.
Because you figure normally for RTS you're coming in and it's going to be you know something that naturally fits to a PC experience
We found we had to do a lot of work actually to get the PC experience up to where
PC players played it as so I think that's probably that was probably one of the harder pieces was
Maintaining what was great about that experience on console
But then coming back to PC and making it appeal to players that play a lot there
Great. Thank you. Yeah
No, another one?
No, me.
Me?
Yeah.
So, going on with this PC and console, do you have any problems in balancing?
Do you have a moment that felt that it was easier on PC or it was easier on console?
Because you said about cross-play, so it's like naturally you want to have it balanced.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's a good question.
So the question is, how is balance affected
by basically being on PC and Xbox and enabling cross-play?
And certainly, I think there are certain aspects of the game
that we saw early on in play testing where just for actions
per minute, PC players could have some advantages.
As I mentioned, though, we look at our balance data
across the game.
And still, I think, actually, a chunk of our best players
still play on console.
And I think a lot of that just comes down
to the core gameplay.
It doesn't require maybe the same amount of actions as,
you know, a PC game, RTS, with much larger army sizes
or a lot more micromanagement.
So there's a lot of aspects of the gameplay
with the way the units work and their powers that balances
that out because it's more about timing and positioning
and, you know, other things that you can control reasonably well
on both console and PC.
What was the size of your UX team on the project?
Like one designer, two?
That's such a hard question to answer,
because as I mentioned, part of the point of what
I was explaining with my background,
like every time I worked on UX for a game, that UX team
has been a very different kind of thing.
And it's typically a team of specialists.
And if I were to really think about it,
like there's a lot of folks within 343
and a lot of folks in the creative assembly
that are specialists in different areas.
So like if I had to put a number on it, I, you know.
I don't know, maybe 15, 20 people, I guess, roughly.
But again, it's a hard question to answer
because I probably don't even appreciate, in some ways,
the contributions that some people
would have made to what that is.
It's not a traditional UX structure.
And I don't think any of the projects we work on
really are in that sense.
But it's really just bringing in a bunch
of these different subject matter experts.
Good?
OK.
Thank you.