GDC 2018, who's excited?
Yeah, all right.
So I'm gonna get us started with a really uplifting talk
about surviving failure.
So I actually, this is my second time talking about this.
Last year I gave a talk specifically on
the technical failures of Brigador.
My name is Humana, and by the way,
I made a game called Brigador a while back.
And if you want the like nitty gritty of all the poor decisions I made, that's the last
year's talk.
Something like Brigadier Failure or something.
I hadn't yet graduated to being able to add the surviving part of the title.
So that's why I look forward to giving this one.
I'm much more concerned here with just sort of the post.
postpartum depression kind of period of like when you have this thing happen, how do you
deal with it? And so as part of some research and preparation for my talk, I figured I would
look into what other people have already said, you know, because I didn't want to just repeat
what's already the combined wisdom on the internet. So I actually...
decided to record some of the, some real helpful nuggets, um, that I found. Uh, I read an entire
article on how to become a growth hacker, uh, to, to deal with failure. Um, I read the
entire article and I still don't actually know what they meant. Um, another one is,
set yourself up to win no matter what. Um, I think that's just called cheating. Um,
Again, not entirely clear on that one.
Gamify your failure.
You know, because game dev isn't enough of a free-to-play grind
as it is.
You want to make sure you get some real good nuggets
in there.
And then my absolute favorite was just
remove absolute failure as an option.
If only I had known when I started this project that I can just not have failure as an option,
that would have made things so much easier.
But yeah, so just what I found was a lot of platitudes and quick tips and no one really
acknowledging how it can just really suck sometimes to fail.
And no one...
really acknowledge that or really talks about how to deal with that.
So here to talk about how things can really suck sometimes, my name is Hugh again.
I started a company called Stellar Jockeys back in 2011.
In the summer of 2016, we launched a game called Brigador.
And that launch went so well, we pretended it didn't happen and just tried it again a
year later.
And I don't know how many of you know me personally versus, like, the game versus a certain post I wrote one time.
Some people describe it as a meltdown. I think that's maybe a little aggressive.
But yeah, so, long story short is...
We had a launch in summer 2016, it went poorly.
And that's fine, like that happens.
But I was a lot more raw coming out of that
than I really needed to be.
And that dramatically affected
the next six months of my life.
And I also wrote some stuff on the internet,
which was maybe a little more spicy than it needed to be.
But now 210,000 people have read it.
So that's kind of a little too late
to put the genie back in the bottle.
But yeah, so why did I feel so burned?
I did, and accidentally, there were just a lot of things.
It was my first time shipping a game,
and my first time really committing
to an experience of that kind of magnitude.
I mean, the only other thing really commensurate to game dev,
especially when you're young.
We started working on Brigador when I was 23.
It was like going through college,
and there's other things to help relax you on that.
So one of the biggest things is expectation versus reality.
And for me, there was a huge gap between what I expected
for the launch of Brigador and what the reality was.
It's natural for, though, there to be a disparity there.
And one of the kind of frustrating ironies
of being a more experienced developer
is that you learn to better attune yourself to,
like, attune those expectations to what is likely to happen.
But what ends up happening is that at some point,
there's a moment of reckoning.
Or maybe if you're lucky, like a period of time
in which those two things come together.
And if that happens very quickly,
like with a game launch when you have
this kind of catastrophic realization
that I've made a huge mistake, then that can be very jarring.
Ideally.
Making that shift should be either it's a small shift
and it's going to be a soft experience
or you have enough time to gradually bridge the gap.
What happened to me in 2016 was more something like this.
So there's actually a great film called 500 Days of Summer.
And it's a great movie on the whole,
but there's also a segment that's a few minutes long
that I think very succinctly just describes and illustrates
not only the difference there, but the impact
that that can have.
The caveat here is that it's not that we shouldn't just
lower our expectations.
I'm not telling anyone to do that.
But I think there's kind of a third step you can add,
which is aspiration versus expectation versus reality.
We can aspire to be the best.
And there's nothing wrong with striving for that.
But you need that kind of middle ground of, OK,
what's actually going to happen?
Because if you don't protect yourself with that,
then you can end up with this kind of whiplash that happens
when you have to reconcile those things.
So the second thing that I did was that I, because I put everything into the launch,
and I sort of just assumed that things were going to go well enough that I would be fine,
when it didn't, I had nothing left in the tank to help cope with the failure.
So I was just sort of stuck in this awkward situation afterwards.
And I wasn't...
I got into this cycle where any time I was getting into any kind of recovery, any energy
that I was getting back, any joie de vivre, was immediately spent on working on the game.
So as soon as I got any of that back, I would burn real hard for like a day or a week or
a month or like however long that I had that juice going for.
And then I would put myself right back to where I was the day after that launch.
And the third thing is that I was,
you know, we talk about, you know,
burnout and crunch and a lot of these things.
It's different to be faced with that yourself
and then to have to actually acknowledge
that, you know, I'm not able to work
or, you know, to continue at this level of performance
that I had been going on for a while.
Because it's kind of a frustrating thing to admit.
And in that period afterward, I was like,
I'm just going to keep working the way
I have been for the last couple years.
And I couldn't accept that it's just so OK to have a hard time.
You need to have that kind of down period
where if you go through an experience like a really
bad launch that you spent five years on,
there's gonna be, like you need time for that fallout
to settle and to give yourself a chance to recover.
When you go through an experience like that,
you have two jobs, which is to get better,
and it was what I described with
don't like immediately burn yourself back out,
and also don't make things worse.
I got real close with that post that I showed earlier.
If that had been tonally a little bit different, or maybe
under different circumstances, that could have totally blown
up in a bad way.
It worked out OK for me.
you know, don't, this kind of stuff feels real good,
but that impulse is, you have to be very careful about.
The one time I think I did handle it much better
was following our early access launch.
I was getting hassled by a customer,
not even a customer, a person who was,
uh... suggesting that are
you know i i i i informing me politely that our price should be down
uh... fifteen dollars and it was
uh... was one thing to like to get a cup everyone gets comments and stuff
but when becomes like a daily
uh... repeat and like
genuinely confused like why didn't you listen to my advice
uh...
That was when I responded with the whole Price Post with the Nickelback poster thing.
But that was actually the second draft of the post that I had written.
The first response that I had written was a lot more inflammatory.
It was a lot more obscenities.
And if I had posted that, the response would have been something a little bit more like
this.
And I know people say that like any press is good press, but I think there's a line there.
So a final point is that this sort of relation of time to distance to understanding.
So one of the...
It wasn't until basically six months after our 1.0 launch in summer 2016 that I actually
calmed down and got enough perspective on what had happened to actually start doing
something about it, to start addressing it properly, both from a...
dev side and also from a personal side.
There's the classic phrase,
seeing the forest for the trees.
This idea that when you're in the middle of development,
you're right in the thick of it,
and you need to be able to back away a little bit
and see the whole picture.
And the only way that you can get that distance
is with time.
And then that last little bit is that
you have to get some understanding of your situation
in order to be able to assess it.
And once you have that opportunity to assess where you
are, whatever has happened, either game dev or personal
experiences, whatever that event in your life is, you can
then, the decision ultimately boils down to do you salvage
whatever, like spend more time and energy to salvage whatever
thing you're in, or do you step away and move on?
And so.
you know, happy ending. In our particular case with Brigador, I realized that a lot
of those mistakes were relatively small things that I could correct. And so we dedicated
another six months to actually fixing the game. We relaunched it and have since actually
made it to be a properly earning title. So that worked out okay. And the...
There's a nice little quote from the director, Christopher Nolan, which is, he just talks
about how persistence is 90% of the battle.
And then he goes on to say, well, it's actually 70%, but 90% sounds much better.
Something I had hoped to do with this talk and with other times that I've spoken either online or in person is just that we, everyone wants to cultivate a culture of success and an aura of success around them.
It's the whole Facebook syndrome, right?
No one wants to appear like they're having trouble.
And I think that's a natural impulse, but at the same time, that can be unhealthy for the community as a whole.
And I know for me personally.
It wasn't until I started reading about how other developers,
both in the games industry, but also in film,
like, you know, other people who have started these big projects,
had profound issues, either failures or, you know, struggles and things,
and was able to start relating those to my own experience
that I then was able to sort of pick up and move on.
But at the end of the day...
it just comes down to this guy.
I'm sure you'll be able to achieve your goal!
That's why I say,
NEVER GIVE UP!
Hello. Oh, he's...
Hi.
Yes.
Thanks very much, Hugh. That was really good.
Do you think that, for yourself, part of the issue is that, because of social now,
a lot of what we do is accessible to all, so you're watched constantly?
And did that have an effect as you were working on your game?
Uh, I mean, yeah, it's the, definitely being, well, I mean, that's a decision you have to
make, right? So we, uh, for a significant portion of development, um, uh, so I live
in Champaign, Illinois. Um, Volition is there, but no one else. Uh, and when we were just
starting out, I was too afraid to talk to anyone at Volition. So we functionally operated
in like complete isolation for about three years.
And it wasn't until we started having something to show that I started actually branching
out into social media.
Probably started doing that a few years too late.
But okay, so to actually address your question, yes, I think having a presence on social media
and having that observed effect or being observed has a huge effect on development.
But it also has to do with...
I think your ability to temper that as a developer.
So if you are someone for whom having the opinions of others,
like if that's an important thing to you,
and especially I think with smaller teams,
you feel that more intensely, that
can be a great impact if you're getting positive response.
But on the negative side of that.
So I guess there's still the option of sealing yourself off
and I think there are cases of giving a project
kind of time in the incubator until you're ready to show.
But then that is an active decision of,
because there's a lot of good and bad
that can come with that.
Anyway, sorry, I hope that addressed your question.
Cheers.
Thank you for your patience, everyone.
Hi.
Yeah, you, good answer.
Yes.
All right, so I'm going to talk about the Moonhunters mistake.
You might know me as the captain of Kit Fox Games.
Moonhunters was our biggest project, probably,
in press so far.
We also released A Shrouded Isle last year.
And we just announced Boyfriend Dungeon.
Woo!
And I'm co-editing textbooks on the side.
But it seems like most indies that get press and attention,
appear to err on the side of waiting too long to release their games, extending their launch
date again and again for years and years, and if that's right for you, that's fine,
and we're all different people.
Some people have that flaw.
My flaw is the other side of the coin, and I know that I need to worry about not launching
too early, because that's what we did.
Luckily, now I know the warning signs that I'm ready to share with you.
And this was 100% my call to make.
I want to emphasize that my team was incredible and they gave me all the power to make this
decision and I made it badly.
So here I am.
I called it wrong.
Back in early 2016, we were getting ready to launch our biggest game.
Moon Hunters was very exciting for us.
We'd been working on it for only a little over two years.
So it was ripe and ready.
And we'd done a lot of promotion throughout the years in Montreal, at events, at PAX,
and online with weekly live streams.
We basically felt like we were living in this giant hot spotlight.
And we had had a successful Kickstarter.
$178,000 isn't like breaking any records,
but for a first major game and a new IP from a new studio,
I mean, 400% and 6,000 backers was very exciting
and something to be proud of.
And I mean, we didn't even have a mid-campaign slump.
It seemed like it had its own word of mouth power.
It would somehow organically grow out there on the internet.
And in the years following, I gave lots of talks
about how to run a successful Kickstarter.
Haha, and I mean all this coverage and word-of-mouth
It seemed like it was paying off. We got into showcases. We won awards. We were on the covers of magazines
I mean we were bombarded with publishing offers, which we discarded
And so I mean we we got a little bit cocky
It was reasonable to think that it was a good sign of sales to come
Everyone that I talked to told me we had a hit on our hands
We actually launched with months of cash in the bank and a contract that was ready to sign.
We had no financial pressure to launch at all and yet we still launched early.
In fact, we had so much visibility and so much good fortune that our launch moment was filmed by a crew from PBS
for a TV series on tech and culture, which we'll come back in a moment.
The launch was bad, I don't know if you've gotten that from what I've said so far, but
we disappointed our fans.
You can't please everyone, of course, but we did have to admit to ourselves that we'd
launched with a lot of bugs and maybe, well, definitely worse, a few core systems that
we felt needed serious changes.
So we ended up with a mixed Steam review user rating
in the half, like on and off in the launch month,
which kind of tanked our whole visibility.
Metacritic was not much better.
And I think, honestly, the hardest thing
was seeing other devs, especially acquaintances,
kind of treat me a little bit differently
than they had back when they thought that I had a hit.
And now that I didn't, it was different.
And to make matters worse, mainstream audiences were already set up to doubt the game's integrity.
I mean, of course, some of these people would never have bought the game, they weren't our audience,
but it still kind of, like, was not fun to know that our technical problems would prove the indie skeptics right
in calling us low-rent garbage. Like, that's not a good feeling either.
And there were measurable consequences to this problem.
This mistake cost us a lot.
This is how you tell it's a healthy launch week, by the way.
Our next launch went much better
in terms of how the launch week went.
So you can see, even if that peak is not as high,
the fact that it's fatter throughout the days,
this is just the first three days of the launch week,
it means people who are buying it
are telling their friends.
That's a good launch week looking.
as unlike Moon Hunters, which launched and the hype train hit this big wall.
So you can see which one is going to have a better next four days, for example.
I mean, launch days don't determine everything
about your revenue, but it did determine
a lot of the coverage and apparent success
of the game for the next six months to a year.
I can't help but think if that we'd waited
to launch the game until it was actually ready,
then our Metacritic and user reviews
might have been much higher, and all of that
would have led to even higher spikes down the road,
which would have amounted to an additional
hundreds of thousands of dollars.
This is what PBS had to say.
Sales weren't great, thanks PBS,
but that's what happens when you release a game
that isn't ready.
And despite our launch day being better
than a lot of indies, I'm very grateful
for what luck we did have.
We could tell that this coming year,
we might not have enough money to stay in the studio
at the size and the comfort level
that we were getting used to.
And even aside from the money, I prepared myself emotionally for bad sales.
That's why I had signed this other contract beforehand.
But I hadn't really considered seriously that we might disappoint people and make what
could be called a bad game.
We were heartbroken.
It felt like we'd wasted years of our lives making something that wasn't really worth
all that time and energy.
It made me feel like I'd peaked and that I was old and tired.
And in hindsight, we totally should have known better.
One YouTuber went so far as to write me a heartfelt letter
during the beta, pleading with me to delay the launch.
But I ignored that and all the other warning signs
because hindsight's so great.
So why did we launch too early?
If we set aside the hindsight bias
and think about the moment,
I'm gonna lay bare all of my personal flaws for you
so that you can see if any of this sounds familiar,
you might have a similar problem.
Indies often go around saying you should double or triple all your estimates and then double
them again and it makes me want to scream because production is actually a skill and
it's worth practicing.
And so I get a little bit defiant when people start telling me you're going to keep delaying
your game.
Ha ha ha, your launch date isn't real.
In fact I got really like, fuck you, defiant.
And it is totally possible to release your game on schedule, I promise.
But don't give up everything and obsess on that, maybe?
And so it came to pass that each delay that we added to the game,
even like a week of delay, felt like a personal attack on me
and my production skill.
And I started feeling kind of fraudulent.
And so I irrationally had decided we couldn't delay again.
We just couldn't.
It was a law of the universe now, which was incorrect.
And the team morale was getting a little bit low,
and I'm a cheerleader type personality,
so we weren't crunching particularly.
We were working pretty hard,
and finishing projects is exhausting.
Even if you only work 40 hours a week,
you're multitasking, you're prioritizing, you're.
you're compromising and just finishing a game is really difficult. So I was looking at the
team and we'd already delayed by a few weeks and I thought well um you know I want I want
them to be happy again let's release the game. Um but releasing a bad game does not make
anyone happy it turns out.
And I also worried about launching next to a couple of other indie games and during other
game events like GDC and PAX and things.
And in the greater scheme of things, I think there are actually much bigger things to worry
about.
The quality of your game is much more important than probably any other indie game, to be
completely honest.
And this might be very Moonhunter specific,
but due to various factors,
we undervalued the online multiplayer
and we launched with it in a beta mode,
which we thought was fine.
We marked it beta.
Still, most of the down thumbs
were bad online multiplayer related
and they would never revise those
no matter how we pleaded with them
after we fixed the bugs.
And yeah, we thought it would be okay
if the online multiplayer took a little while.
That was incorrect.
And as I mentioned, we had lined up this contract
that was starting very soon afterwards,
and I'd already delayed that by a few weeks,
and so I let this external factor kind of influence me
and make me think that we absolutely had
to stop working on the game.
And it's true that at that point,
because I had scheduled this contract to start,
if I had delayed again, it was theoretically possible that.
the game would then sell zero copies and that contract would be null and void and then Kitfox
would close.
So it felt like the right thing at the time to prioritize this other external factor.
And we did eventually do okay.
Kid Fox survived.
Moon Hunters actually did pretty well over time.
Some of it is my personal excellent luck.
I'm a very lucky person,
and I try to stay grateful for that,
but we also did work really hard at it.
We spent a lot of time fixing bugs
and apologizing and answering emails.
We also spent about six months making a free DLC afterwards
called Eternal Echoes.
And that did the core systems revising
that I mentioned before.
And so that gave us kind of another attempt
at attracting press.
And it gave us more of a peace of mind
as well to leave the game in a better state
that we were proud of.
So even if it hadn't resulted in a sales boost,
we still would have been glad that we did it.
And also, making this would have been so much faster
before launch.
If you have something you want to add to the game
and you can afford to delay it,
just put it in the game first
because LiveOps is horrendously distracting.
And the reviews did trend mostly upwards afterwards.
After we made all those improvements,
I think we actually were able to harvest the goodwill
that we'd built up from the Kickstarter updates
that we were constantly making.
And maybe our community is more forgiving
than the average Steam player.
I guess we'll never know.
One thing that I do want to emphasize is the importance of our launch party, actually.
My team and I definitely felt like we received first aid from the Montreal community itself
by hosting our launch party three days later.
There's nothing that can replace the feeling of people who genuinely are happy for you
and being proud of you and excited for you.
Everyone on the team kind of wanted to cancel the launch party.
But we did it anyway, and we were all really,
everybody on the team was also grateful that we did afterwards.
There were sad tears and then happy tears.
So if you're thinking about cancelling your launch party
or making it hinge on the success of the game, do not do that.
Even if you have to make it BYOB, that's okay.
But take your moment to celebrate that you did something.
And personally, I was actually healed by coming to GDC
the week after launching.
I thought it would be massively humiliating,
and instead it was comforting.
Even though a few professional acquaintances
did treat me a little bit differently,
I did actually find out who my friends were
among the community who could share with me
their experiences from around the world.
Because whenever I told someone about my disappointment,
more experienced indies would lean in and nod sagely
and tell me a horror story that was way worse,
which I'd never heard of.
Like, we only talk about success.
I mean, all I say in public is,
Moon Hunter is totally successful.
Yeah, it was great.
But for those of you who are in the audience right now,
please understand that games go off the tracks all the time.
It's okay, you're not uniquely humiliated.
It's kind of part of it.
So that's part of why I volunteered to be here today,
because I not only want to combat survivorship bias,
but generally improve our culture
and help us understand that failure
is part of craftsmanship.
And all that visibility that we'd created before
didn't vaporize.
I was able to do some hustling
and get an indie box in the works.
And thank you, Jamie Tucker,
for including us in your cool Steam cross-promo.
That was great.
And then after we ported the game
to all three major consoles,
here's us porting it to PS4
when the actual porting programmers in Japan at the time,
which was a little bit funny.
Oh, I wanted to mention that the Halo effect is totally real.
At least it was for Moon Hunters.
That every time we would release on a new platform,
our Steam sales would get a boost.
And I think that if we had simultaneously launched
all of the games on all the platforms,
which is the conventional wisdom,
well, we couldn't have done that physically anyway.
We were incapable.
But even if we had, I think the Halo effect
would have been kind of negated by the fact
that our Steam score was so low.
So it was really good that we were able to
put the best version on the platform after we had...
kind of salvaged that.
And most importantly to the future of the studio,
we've incorporated all of these lessons
into our workflows going forward.
So our production evaluations for milestones
are now less about specific dates
and much more about what the deliveries themselves are
and whether they are up to par.
So we're more willing to add some time to the schedule
as assuming that everything is up to quality.
And survival of the studio is definitely number one still in my mind.
Kit Fox is not allowed to close.
But in the past we failed to prioritize beyond that.
So my own personal production neuroses would come through.
And kind of efficiency became more important than quality.
And that was by accident because we didn't really examine it.
So now we're very clearly, officially...
Quality is more important than efficiency,
so assuming that you're not gonna close the studio
with your little flares here and there,
then take your time and make it the best you can.
Because it's true what they say, you do only launch once.
Delaying your game isn't nearly as bad
as launching a bad game.
Reality is probably more important than your pride.
Your team's morale will be better
when they believe in the game
and feel good about what they've made.
So if you're like me and you're prone to rushing ahead
and you're an impatient person,
just take a breath, recheck your calculations,
bring in fresh eyes, double check all of your assumptions.
We're applying all of this to development
of Boyfriend Dungeon, which is our next game,
so wish us luck with that.
We actually have a milestone next week, so we'll see.
And hopefully we're learning from our mistakes
and making better and better games.
Thank you.
So yeah, we have plenty of time for questions for either speaker.
And just make sure to go to one of the microphones, please.
Let's start the interrogation.
And don't forget to do your evaluations.
Seriously, though, any questions are cool.
Actual questions, not I have a comment, maybe?
Hello.
Hi.
How's it going?
It's excellent.
This question's for you primarily.
I've had the experience where I've
had friends who have metaphorically grabbed me
by the shoulders and shaken me and saying,
you need to finish.
Finishing is super important.
And don't just stay in development forever
and almost yell at me to move forward.
Outside of actual financial pressure,
you're going to close if you don't start releasing something.
How would you respond to that?
I would say I am probably unusual.
It does seem to me that I am an outlier and that most people err on the other side.
Like I said at the beginning, I think most indies tend towards just working in a cave
forever on their perfect dream, whereas I am much more of a flurry of like, let's just
do it.
And so you have to look inside yourself to see what is your nature and how do you prevent
that from calcifying because on both ends of the spectrum there are problems.
And I guess my, I feel like my side of the spectrum
isn't talked about as much.
It's just seen as obvious, whereas sitting in a room
and working on it for way too long
is less obvious somehow.
But yeah, I can't answer for you in particular.
Only you can know your heart.
But I would say that finishing is important.
Maybe look up production practices.
I think if we all started being more hygienic
about how we estimate our tasks.
and think about how long things actually take us
and calculate that and check our assumptions
on our timelines, then we'll all be happier.
If I could chip in on that.
The, one of the biggest changes that we've seen in the industry
in the last 20 years is the fact that I think the vast majority
of us in this room when we're shipping a game,
we're shipping purely digitally, right?
And that, the environment
for shipping a game has totally changed, right?
So you've got options for early access, you can just get
on Steam for 100 bucks now.
You can also do various forms of closed beta or closed alpha,
look at spy party.
look at Saltzman's Overland, what was the...
Venge's current game, Overland.
There's a lot of different ways that you can basically
get the kind of feedback you need from a player base
and keep it to only the diehards to figure out
are we ready to ship or not?
Because if you've got a bunch of people,
the people who would love you screaming.
then it's like, okay, maybe we should delay it.
But otherwise, if everyone's like, thumbs up,
then yeah, you can get a degree of external evaluation
from people who don't have an influence on that.
One thing I would mention is actually,
there are part-time producers that you can hire out there.
Felix Kramer's incredible.
There's a bunch of part-time producers
that you should totally think about
throwing a couple hundred dollars on
because it's probably worth it to get a real professional
to look at your timeline and look at your game
and give you an expert.
assessment of whether or not you're ready to ship.
Thank you both.
Cheers.
You're welcome.
Hi, my name is Blake.
Hi, Blake.
Thank you.
My question is for Hugh.
You said you relaunched like six months after your first launch?
A year.
So, our first launch, so early access was October 2015.
1.0 was June 2016, up armored.
Our relaunch was June 2017, so year to the day.
It sounded like the second relaunch was better or more successful.
So the week of our relaunch was our highest grossing sales of all time.
And we we sort of defied the trend in that for most people
your first year is basically like.
the majority of what you're going to make.
I know Jake Perkett is here in the audience somewhere.
He gave some lovely talks about assessing
sort of first week and first year sales
and things like that.
For us, our second year of sales
is actually significantly higher than our first year.
Actually, ours was too.
Yeah, so my question is, after your first lunch,
What made you think you could relaunch and then what decisions are like?
What did you kind of what do you think contributed most to?
Kind of changing that trajectory and and had her be successful
Um, yeah, uh, so, uh, a couple things.
One is just that there were some very discreet decisions that became very
apparent were wrong, uh, after our launch.
So the biggest one is our control scheme.
So we launched Brigador with tank controls.
Um, turns out no one plays tank controls anymore.
And in my mind, so it's possible to be right and wrong at the same time.
So to me, I was right in that, yes, tank controls are the best control scheme for this game
because we designed it for that.
I was wrong in that no one wants to learn tank controls.
So once we added in a twin stick style, we actually had a working variant of that before
original launch, and I cut it.
Because I was like, I am more intelligent than these gamers.
Once we put that back in as part of the relaunch and a
bunch of other, there were very discreet decisions that I
could clearly say, these are wrong.
And looking at those in aggregate, plus localizing and
a few other things, it was like.
You know, I think this is worth it.
And I talked to a lot of people who were like,
this is, your launch sucked way worse than it should have.
So it was kind of like an aggregate decision.
Also the fact that I was emotionally incapable
of just stopping there.
So it kind of like wasn't really a decision, but anyway.
Thank you.
I mean, hit me up if you want to talk later, yeah.
So I'm Chris.
My question's actually of a similar vein,
and I guess it really goes to both of you,
as to I know a lot of people when they have a launch
that doesn't go well, like,
their concerns are that they spend more energy, more time,
it's just gonna be spinning their tires in the mud,
and they're not sure, like, should they cut their losses
and just, you know, was their timing wrong
and they gotta take their bet on the next thing?
Can you talk us through, I'm sure there's at least
some consideration as to that.
kind of like before you decide to really double down on that effort,
kind of what goes into that sort of thinking as to whether or not
here comes the next project as opposed to like
sinking all those resources back into it.
That could be an hour on its own.
I guess my core advice there would be to treat every game
differently.
It's not that you can look at any given game and say,
oh, this game did it that way.
I'm going to do it that way.
Every game has its own problems and triumphs.
So it is worthwhile to see if there
are others who have tried exactly what you're going
to try and have failed to do so.
It's very hard to find failures, but they are out there.
And I think you also need to ask yourself whether the costs,
emotionally and financially, are worth the risk.
Because we knew that we were going into this with maybe getting nothing out of it,
and we were okay with that.
But part of that might have been because we weren't completely bitter and burnt out at that point yet.
So it's different for every game.
What I would say about that is...
I think a lot of that has to do with, like, what is your intention as an indie developer?
Like, is this a one and done, or are you a lifer?
Because in my case, we, so my brother and I co-founded the studio together, and it's
We're in the kind of indie games or die kind of mentality
where our creations are so precious to us
that we're going to stick with it regardless.
And as much as he occasionally accuses me
of George Lucas-ing the game,
I think, uh, you know, because games have really long tails.
And I, hopefully, like I still play the original XCOM,
uh, and people like that, that game still has a living community.
And not, I mean, should be so lucky, but at the same time,
it's like, if someone plays Brigador in 10 years,
um, I wanted to make sure that that's still like a rock-solid experience.
And I realized that there were changes that we needed to make to do that.
And...
We were fortunate in that in our case,
we're working on a second game that uses the same engine.
So a lot of the additions and changes
that we made to the engine to fix Brigador,
it's like, well, we're just doing pre-production
for game two, so it worked out.
Awesome.
Thanks, Hal.
Hi, my name is Aubrey Scott.
I'm actually wondering, because you both talked
about the stories of other game developers kind of failing,
being a really healing experience for you,
to hear and kind of commiserate together.
I'm wondering what you feel like would have to happen
to make that a more normal part of the culture,
to kind of cultivate that and have those stories out there
and for it to be more normal to.
It's what we're doing right now.
I mean, I'm entirely serious where, like, that was...
I mean, I'm going to be honest, I didn't...
It wasn't my intent when I first, like, started yelling on the internet
about how everything sucks.
My mind wasn't like,
I'm going to help the indie community.
I'm glad that happened and I've kind of embraced that.
But at the end of the day, it's just, part of it is just building your community, right?
And like finding people who are in similar situations and commiserating.
I mean like it's, you, there's, it helps to just...
talk to other devs in all states of life.
And again, I have had a really wonderful experience
with the game development community,
both Indie and AAA, where I've cold emailed
the weirdest people where it's like,
you're a technical director at this place.
I'm an independent game designer.
Please read this two page long email.
And I've had people actually
not only humor me, but I actually give very thoughtful responses.
And I think just, it starts with just reaching out to people.
Um, and, uh, when you are going through a situation,
I mean, I, cause we talk a lot, we've, like, as in developers,
I've had a lot of private communications with, with other developers
who are having a hard time and other things like that.
It's not always necessary or even, uh, a good thing
to publicize some of these things, or some of your, your stressors.
But also, like...
you know, if you can talk to people about it, or if you do have an experience that you
think other people are going to have and could be shared, or you know, someone else who's
in that similar situation, I think if you contribute to that sort of body of knowledge
and that experience, that can make a difference.
I'd like to add I'm in my hobbies. I'm also the co-organizer of a feminist organization
And I can tell you that any cultural change is very slow and it starts personally
so anytime you in your life can notice when you are overvaluing someone because they have this aura of success or
when you catch you and your friends like admiring someone
because only they've kind of perfected this sheen,
just question that and really think about that
and think about who your heroes are
and what are the kind of values
that you want to broadcast to other people
and I think we'll make the world better.
Thank you.
We have to call it there
and I think that is a perfect note to end on.
Thank you so much.
It was brilliantly articulated.