Hey everyone, this is Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra.
Doing something a little bit different in this special episode of GDC Podcast.
We're talking to Lars Ducey. He's co-founder of Level Up Labs,
which made the successful RPG-slash-tower-defense hybrid Defender's Quest.
He also did some work with Valve on its Steam Labs experiments.
In this episode, we talk less about game development and design here, and more about our experience
as Texans amid the brutal winter storm that left people without access to heat, power,
and in many cases even food for days.
So you can feel free to skip on past this episode if that doesn't necessarily interest you.
We're going to get back to the purely game development related content yet this month.
But I encourage you to listen and stick around.
We do talk a little bit about systems and our reliance on them,
and we talk a little bit about Lars's...
experience making a game about power grids and energy and all of that stuff
which is obviously relevant. So one last thing if you'd like to help people who
are continuing to need help in Texas there are a variety of mutual aid groups
to donate to and that includes Mutual Aid Houston, Mutual Aid Austin, DFW Mutual Aid,
Feed the people, Dallas.
You can also Google Mutual Aid Texas to find more.
And there are people who are still going to be having issues for a while now,
even though we are now back to normal, beautiful Texas weather.
So, thanks for listening.
We'll be back in a sec.
Okay, so we are we're here with Lars, not Duckett, but Ducey. Lars and I were kind of tweeting back
and forth amid everything that was going on in Texas, so the reason that I decided to have him
on this this show is because I just feel like we both had a lot to say.
I think that it's difficult to convey what happened over the past week and what is still
ongoing.
It's difficult to convey the severity of the issue.
It really is kind of like, and I don't blame people for not...
Like just for context, we were both without power, heat, all of that for quite some time.
And people we know still to some degree aren't.
Yeah, yeah. We're going to get into the specifics of our situations.
But it's just something that...
I don't, I don't blame people for not totally absorbing or understanding the
severity of what happened here and is happening over the past week.
It's just difficult to convey.
So I thought that maybe, you know, using this venue, um, to talk about some game
developer related stuff, you know, with a game developer like Lars, um, but also.
Just talk about,
This happened and maybe people can gain a better understanding of the situation down here by
listening to us rattle on about it. Yeah it's so weird like my first game dev project professionally
was an educational game called Super Energy Apocalypse in which you as the leaders of the
post-apocalyptic republic of New Texas have to like balance your energy grid so it doesn't death
spiral.
And like, it was like funded by an educational, not educational, sorry, but a nonprofit, nonpartisan,
like environmental research group called Houston Advanced Research Center. So like right in Houston.
And like, so like, I have a lot of background knowledge about natural gas and coal,
and wind and solar and all that. And then this happens like 15 years later,
after I'm doing all kinds of other stuff. And it's like, it's like really kind of eerie to me.
That's wild. I didn't even realize that, you know, from having you on. I know from, you know, from your games and from working at, you know, working for Valve on different Steam projects, I didn't know about the, what's the name of...
It's called Super Energy Apocalypse and most of you probably can't play it anymore because it was a Flash game. It's still up on Kongregate. It's free. Probably got played more than any other game I ever made, even like the ones that did well on Steam.
You know, which is hilarious.
But it was like, yeah, like I went and I did all the research on different kinds of energy
generation and so like, you know, it does little things like when the wind stops blowing
the turbines turn off, you know, like nuclear produces nuclear waste, like, you know, what
is the relative cost versus the relative emissions of natural gas versus coal?
Like I had to crunch all those numbers, probably badly because I was like 20.
But you know.
Like, I still retain a little bit of that, but it's like so weird now.
Also, another background fact about me is I'm Norwegian, like a passport holder, it's my first language.
Um, and it's so weird being in Texas being this damn cold.
Like, I feel like it's kind of like a, finally a chance to use my degree kind of situation.
Because like, if you have Norwegian relatives, they'll just like make you all these sweaters
and stuff.
And you're like, that's great, I love it, it's so beautiful, you work so hard, I live
in Texas.
And I'm like, today the prophecy is fulfilled.
You open up the treasure chest of sweaters that you've been saving up this whole time.
Yeah, seriously. I also have a Russian friend from my church. She's Russian.
Her son's grown up now, so she's like, here's all these ski bibs I can't use anymore. You have
these for them? It's like, yeah, I might go visit my relatives in Norway one day. So we'll put the
kids in those. It's like, we used those. I'm so glad we had this stuff.
Where are you exactly in Texas?
Don't need your address or even like,
where are you in general in Texas?
I'm in the Brazos Valley.
I'm in central Texas, right?
Okay.
You know, so there's a Texas triangle between,
I always embarrass myself and get one of the cities wrong,
but it's like Austin,
Dallas and Houston and San Antonio.
I forget which one is the one that's supposed to be the western edge of it.
I think it's either Austin or San Antonio.
Right.
But I don't know which one's it's Austin is closer.
Okay.
I know geography.
So we're like in the middle of that triangle.
Right.
And you know, we're close to Texas A&M university, you know, and there's
like a big medical hub here and, um, that's where I am and you're in Austin.
Right.
Yeah, yeah. I'm in, um, Austin suburbs.
I've been down here for going on seven years and, uh, it wasn't quite like my
relatives are sending it from, from Norway or sending me sweaters, but like,
I felt like, you know, I, I spent about like 33 years or something like that in,
um, in Indiana, Northern Indiana.
So I felt like a total badass when I found my ice scraper.
And like, because I had to, the roads are terrible.
This is like, of course, there's zero infrastructure for clearing roads at all.
And that's something like...
Zero, as in nothing.
And this is something that, like, I think we'll get into, like, how many heads should
roll about this probably in a minute.
But, like, just a perspective for people, and I say this as someone who, like, you've
lived in Indiana where it presumably gets cold, and you've lived here.
I'm a Norwegian.
I'm a pathetic excuse for a Norwegian.
Like, I speak the language, but, like, I mostly only went there in the summer.
You know, like, I've not had to endure, like, a black Norwegian winter where the sun does
not come up, right?
You know?
Um...
But I have any kind of absorbed bioosmosis experience at all with winter weather.
And I think people like Canadians and people in the North are like,
Oh, Texas can't handle a little snow, huh?
It's like, it was five degrees Fahrenheit, which is...
Like, sub-freezing by a lot.
In Texas, parts of Mexico were snowing.
Like, this is the equivalent of 105 degrees Fahrenheit in Oslo.
Like, now I think they're probably, when all is said and done, and cooler heads have prevailed,
and we're done dunking on each other on Twitter and actually looking at the information,
we're gonna find, like, what was the actual cause of this,
and probably we should have done better preparing, but it's like...
This was kind of unprecedented.
But I also want to talk about the fact that like unprecedented...
Pardon my French.
Unprecedented shit is happening all the time now.
Like, just before this,
like, I had two 500 year floods in my area.
Just locally.
You know, Hurricane Harvey came a couple years ago
and like whacked my brother's apartment to death
in Houston and I had some friends
had to evacuate and stay locally.
Like, that was awful.
and then, you know, and like the amount of water that was dumped on Houston was ridiculous.
And then like, we're in the middle of a global pandemic already, right?
Yeah, that's the other thing. It's a disaster within a disaster.
Yeah, I mean, let's talk about our personal experiences here.
Okay.
I think you've had it worse than I have. I've had power.
Like my like I had three days of really bad stuff
Yeah, and what that looked like for me is probably easy mode compared to you and some other stories
I've had from friends and relatives. Yeah, we had let's let's go. Let's go to
So I want to just return to where you said like
You know people from Norway or for that matter people from northern, Indiana
Or like anywhere in the Midwest that gets way colder than than this
I mean we're talking about like
Double digit negative winch only type stuff and negative Fahrenheit right yeah, yeah Fahrenheit. Yeah yeah, so like
Super cold yeah, and it's it didn't get that cold
It did get down to like five seven degrees like where where I am, but it's kind of like
I can handle that.
So I was dismissive about it on Twitter because I get annoyed with...
Because I saw at the beginning of the pandemic people hoarding stuff from grocery stores,
for example, that they don't need.
And my feeling is that you're leaving your neighbor in the lurch if you're taking more
than your share.
So, you know.
It was, to me, that was overdoing it.
Like, why are you panicking to that extent?
Like, it's, you know, it'll be fine.
Oh, I have a lot to say about prepper culture
because I know some preppers.
But, yeah, we'll get to that in a sec.
Go ahead.
Yeah, and like, so, you know, like a day later,
so our power went out like right at midnight on Sunday
and it,
stayed off for
The coldest part of all this it was out for 36 hours straight. Yeah, so oh my gosh
Yeah, and we're lucky and like and this is one thing
What's what's cool about like Texans that I see them tweeting about this almost everybody is like I had no water for this amount of time
I know heat and power for this amount of time and it's always couching and I'm one of the lucky ones
I always see people saying that and that's how I feel like
Yeah, like the fact that we were having a podcast about this and I was able to like tweet live tweet the thing because I never lost cell service and I had rolling blackouts like I had four hours of power a day on the good days, like two hours on the bad days and they were like eat like it was one hour at a time spread out evenly so it was like big dark periods but like
Some of my direct relatives, I'm talking like brothers, sisters-in-laws and stuff like that.
Some of them didn't get power back until yesterday and some of them still don't have water.
And they went 52, 72 hours without anything. It was insane.
And then you just think of all the homeless, all poor people and stuff,
and the counties that have really...
One thing that really impressed upon me was the importance of my local utility.
Like, there's all this hoopla going on with ERCOT, which is, for those who don't know,
that's like the managing entity for the whole Texas grid.
But your local utility has, like, how...
How good they are at getting it down power lines.
So like, dealing with just infrastructure damage versus rationing, right?
And then their rationing strategy too.
Like, they were able to...
Like, it's kind of like a video game to like keep a grid up, right?
It's like, you gotta keep your people...
You gotta give them enough power to like get them through this crisis.
But you also gotta like manage the strain on the grid.
And like, everyone's pissed at you because...
You're rationing their energy, but you have to do it right or everyone's gonna get screwed.
And they were able to give us a couple hours of juice a day, evenly spaced,
communicate with us when it was happening through the local, like, news station and stuff,
and everyone was, like, giving them all this flack because they were mad it was happening at all,
but then I hear about these other stories, like, where you were and other places,
and it's like, maybe they had it harder there, but, like, man.
They did a bang up job and maybe they have good circumstances too, but I'm so grateful for my local utility.
So if anyone here listening works for BTU Utilities in the Brazos Valley...
I am super grateful for all of your hard work.
Like we talk about frontline essential workers, that's them out freezing their asses off to
literally keep their friends and neighbors alive.
It's kind of like, oh wow, everything does run on electricity.
So we have obviously like, you know, a power outage.
It's like lights off, yeah, you lose your Wi-Fi.
Like obviously that kind of thing.
It's like, okay, I can deal with that.
We've got gas, you know, our house is heated with gas.
Well, our furnace is activated by electricity.
And it runs on people.
Yeah.
And then it's like, okay, but we still have water.
Well, the water plant runs on electricity.
Right.
It's like, now you don't have water.
You don't have, you know.
Exactly.
Yeah, and all this stuff just dominoes and.
My thermostat is digital, right?
Yeah.
Which means they're telling me, like they're doing good communication, right?
They're like, guys, everyone, shut off your heat so when the power comes back on,
it doesn't instantly get shut off from the instant load.
And I'm like, when the lights go back on for my one hour, like, my, my, my,
hello?
Did it happen again?
Oh, it's just my screensaver.
Oh my God.
I've got PTSD.
Oh my gosh.
That's awful.
Okay.
I was like, no, I was just picturing you.
Oh man.
We're keeping that.
That's that's so awful.
Yeah.
That's okay.
That's, that's hilarious though.
That's, that's the kind of humor we need to get.
I'm, I'm, I'm moving my mouse right now to make sure that, you know, I don't get
freaked out and wake my computer back up.
Yeah, so anyway, so, um, what was I saying?
Yeah, so like, I have this digital thermometer, right?
And so like, the utility is telling me it's essential that I wait 15 minutes before I turn my heat on
when I get my rationed hour of power for, you know, the next, like, 10 hour block.
And I can't do it because my, because the power showed off while I had the heat on
and I can't change the thermometer setting because it's digital!
I have to like, run like a ninja when the light comes on to go,
Okay, okay, system, heat, off, done!
Yeah, yeah. Oh, geez.
And, like, that's impressive that you even got that communication.
So, we were...
Okay, let's...
So much to talk about.
We're going back. Yeah, it's like...
For my household...
And I've got kids, you know.
Me too, yeah.
Yeah, and...
So, 36 hours of that.
We're...
Like, luckily we have a gas range, so we can boil water.
I was like the whole water thing,
it started like we got a handle on staying warm
and our town tweeted out the amount of water
is like make sure that you have two gallons of water
per person for over the next 30,
like for the next 36 hours.
Yeah, and boil it. And I was thinking like, what? Because at that point our water
hadn't already gone out. It must have at that point just been draining out of the
rest of our pipes, but we were collecting the dripping with pots and bowls and
stuff. And I saw that 36 hours and I was like, what are they getting at here?
It's like, certainly they're just not gonna turn off, you know, turn off the water because people need that to drink and live.
And they did. And we, like, we resorted to...
So we went from level one...
water gatherer, water gatherer people who like, okay, we can get like these drippings in pots and pans and we can boil them.
And then we can we can use those and then once those were done
like my wife Anna, she became like a level 100 water farmer out back
collecting like, like we drank the the roof water. I know that it's like last resort stuff
but like what else are you gonna do?
So we're drinking the roof water and boiling it.
I am scooping snow.
I took a five-gallon paint bucket and went to the backyard and filled our bathtub with snow
so that we would have that reserved there.
And we would use that to flush toilets mainly.
Yeah, we didn't drink out of the bathtub,
but we did drink some boiled snow and roof water.
And you were filtering that too,
so you would boil it and then filter it
through paper towels, you'd said?
Yes, yeah, yeah, we had a strainer
and then we would just put a couple layers
of paper towel down and just run that baby through.
Yeah, I'm really impressed that
But we never lost our water.
They did give us a notice that we might lose water.
And I want to make sure, maybe not now,
but talk about the issue of panic prepping versus making
sure that you can take care of yourself
so you can also take care of other people,
because I think that's a distinction that
is really important.
Go ahead and talk about it.
Give me your thoughts on that.
So an example, you get a notice that you're about to lose water.
What does everybody do? They go fill up their bathtub, right?
And then the act of everyone filling up their bathtub
puts strain on the water system
and causes it to crash down for everyone, right?
It's like everyone doing a run on the store
and panic buying all the toilet paper.
Yeah, our water people said specifically,
do not do that.
Right, right, right.
And so, that is where...
like planning ahead matters because I did fill up my bathtub because but I did it early.
I did it.
But that's the trick with all these things is you have to prepare before it's obvious
there's a crisis when you might still be embarrassed for preparing, right?
Because like if I go to Walmart, not not now, but if I go to Walmart like three days ago,
and I just buy a bunch of stuff, I'm not being a strain on anybody.
If I do it right when they're like, I mean, Walmart just makes a bunch of money and then
they order new stuff, right?
You know, if I do it right when there's a crisis, then I'm doing like damaging hoarding
because other people need that stuff and I'm causing a crisis by causing a run on the stores.
And also like, also when people do runs on stores, they buy all the wrong stuff.
Like they just, they just like buy all the ketchup and all kinds of weird things, you
know, they just like, they're just like, you know, it's because they're panicking, right?
It's like, um, and so like even something like filling up your tub, you can do it the right way or the wrong way.
And I'm so impressed by your resourcefulness because we never lost water, you know.
The prep work that we did though was, um, try to do...
I always try to do the smallest amount of prep work I can that is going to be useful no matter what.
So, for instance, I have a Berkey filter. If you don't know what those are, they're like really top of the line water filter-like.
Brita's like level 1, this is like level 100.
Big aluminum or whatever cylinders, these big filters, they use them all over the world.
Like, NGOs use them throughout every kind of devastated country with no safe water supply,
right?
And they're just gravity fed filters, no moving parts, no electrical parts, no nothing, you
know?
And you just put water in the top, it doesn't matter how awful and brackish it is.
They love to do this test with food coloring in the top and then it comes out all clear.
So if you just order one of those after a crisis is over and not about to start, and just have one in your garage,
then, like, I wish I could have shipped you mine, you know, by jumping into my time machine and giving it to you.
Your life would have been a lot easier.
Because I certainly didn't wind up having to use it this time, but I'm glad I had it.
Because I live next to a creek, and when it's freezing cold, it's snowing.
Usually we prepare for a drought, not like...
Freezing to death.
But like I could have poured brackish water from my creek that is probably full of every
kind of amoeba and drain chemical possible and had fresh water.
But like filling up your bathtub the minute you know your water is about to go off in
ten minutes is going to cause your water to go off in two minutes.
Yeah, yeah.
It's all, it's all the same resources that, that we're pulling from.
And, uh, yeah, I I'm, I'm taking, I'm taking notes on, on the filter too.
And it's funny that, you know, so like my dad was, my dad was older.
Um, like he, he was born in 1930 and anybody who lived through the great
depression has these, uh, different, you know, quirks like hoarding.
It's like keeping, keeping everything.
My mom grew up in Norway.
Post-war without electricity. Mm-hmm. Yeah, like hardcore. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, my mom was
Born in the Philippines and they were the most abject poverty
So she also has these right, you know these resourceful
like cells in her body that you know are
Thinking about when you have nothing and then your your brain start like even through like one week of this, you know
like just a week
Your brain already by the end of it is adjusting to like when you're hearing the snow melting right now and dripping away.
It's like, we're wasting, like that's wasteful.
Right, right, right, right, yeah.
We should be collecting that water.
Like, like I had filled up, like I had filled up my tub, you know, before I thought there
would be a crisis, before there was any notice, you know, because it's just a game.
I'm not, I'm not trying to tub shame you, by the way.
No, no, no, I understand, I understand it, but like, like, I'm afraid to drain the tub
now.
Like, I'm like, I'm like, if I, if I, if I drain it, I might need that water.
I'm just like, I've got the filter, but like, I don't want to drink creek water.
You know?
And it's like, I'm afraid now, you know?
And it was so funny because we had,
we were so blessed with the intermittent power,
the rationed four hours of power a day,
that when the lights came on, we had like,
at first we didn't know what to do,
but we got a little dance.
I was like, okay, charge the phones.
All right, turn off the furnace.
Okay, everybody, like, you know, it's like.
That feeling when the power comes back on.
So ours was out for 36, it was on for six.
And then it was off for like 14 or 15 more hours.
Right.
And then it finally came back on and stayed.
Oh, so the first time the power came back on,
all that was about at like four in the morning, I think.
And our fire alarms all went off.
So, yeah, it was just like, what the heck is going on?
And we couldn't get them to shut off.
So we like I had to get on my ladder and then just
like uninstall all of them because there was nothing that that we could do and
I was looking around and smelling for smoke and it's like okay, this is definitely a false alarm and
It wasn't the carbon monoxide alarm because it's a different like right alarm. It says carbon monoxide
Oh, the carbon monoxide is such a thing though.
It's because you're like, I should get in my car and like shut the garage door.
It's so sad.
It's so sad because like you see people hospitalized or even die every time
something like this happens, because, you know, like some someone got carbon
monoxide from poisoning from charcoal, like using charcoal inside.
And and yes, of course, like people use generators in a closed garage
and it just poisons the whole house.
Right, and you can't tell that it's happening, you just get sleepy and die.
I have a fireplace too and I kicked myself.
This is where prepping is all about, like smart prepping, not crazy prepping.
It's all about thinking ahead.
Half the things I did, the real resource is family and friends and communication because
half the stuff I did is not because I'm smart, it's because someone told me offhand a couple
days before this all went down.
I'm kicking myself about my fireplace because I've got a fireplace and I couldn't figure
out, like it took me forever to figure out that I could actually burn logs in it.
And my Norwegian mom had given me a gift of these beautiful decorative birch logs.
But they're like, they'll burn.
And I have like 10 of them.
I'm like, we could burn that wood.
I was sure this fireplace wouldn't set my attic on fire because six years ago we had
So, we're going to look at our dryer vent.
And what's funny is the people who fix dryer vents are the same people who sweep chimneys.
Chimney sweeps, re-specialized and re-trained in dryer vents when all the fireplace work
dried up.
Like, they mostly do dryer vents, but they still do fireplaces.
And we had them come out for a dryer vent six years ago.
And it's like, oh, you've got a nice fireplace here.
I'm like, yeah, it's Texas.
We'll never use it.
And he's like, yeah, well, if you ever do want to use it, you should get me by to inspect
it so you don't set your attic on fire based on how your insulation's done.
And so like I'm there with my fireplace and I'm like, do I risk it?
I'm like, power's rationed, we've got heat, we'll do it if we're about to die, but no.
Yeah, yeah. Oh, I smoked a chicken on the coldest night.
Like we needed, I don't know, we needed food for a couple of days.
For those who don't know, Chris Graft is an amazing barbecue grill master.
He's the best, I'm told.
Well, I mean, I'm not bad.
He's as amazing as he is modest.
Folks, it is a treat.
Yeah, it's true.
So I smoked this chicken and I have...
He smokes chicken the way he smokes noobs.
I don't know about that.
Lars, what are you talking about?
But it gave me like, you know, it was like it was at that point I checked and it was like 14 degrees on its way down to seven.
And yeah, I sat I sat out there with the chicken.
I didn't want to go back inside and outside because I'm letting like what remains of the heat.
And luckily our house, even after the first 36 hours, it got down to 50 inside, which
is impressive that it was able to maintain that.
That the insulation was good enough?
Yeah, so like we and we just dressed like, you know, at night, we just dressed like winter, right?
They say they say heat your body, not the room, you know, like, I mean, I mean, I slept in like
long underwear, PJ pants, and like sweatpants and like a shirt and undershirt, a jacket, another
jacket and a hat.
Yeah, exactly. Me too. It was like I was going out to the grocery store during an Indiana winter, and I just slept like that.
Yeah, and like my mom was saying, I mean my mom, who grew up in Norway where it gets this cold and power had not been brought to her rural village yet, so that was just how life was.
She's like, wear a hat, son. You need to wear a hat, because most of your energy gets lost through your head.
Like all these little survival tips from the old country.
It's so true.
Like, uh, yeah, I put a hat on and like, I got warm and, and I know this stuff,
but you know, I only like re-appreciated it when this past week happened.
Like my life didn't depend on it until now.
Yeah.
And I, I'm like telling him, Hey, everyone try the hat.
Try it.
Go get a hat.
It really works.
Yeah.
So like if we're talking about, um, like systems and, and things like that, you
know, you talked about the game that you designed, uh, is there, um, have you
even had any chance to kind of think about and analyze, uh, what happened,
uh, as, as far as like the Texas grid, uh, goes in anything or anything like that?
Yeah.
Has your game design head kind of automatically went there?
I mean, there's a whole genre of games that are all about balancing power grids, right?
You know, and...
Like Balance of Power.
Yeah.
So, like, there was this really fun Flash game, like, tower defense game called the
Space Game, which is all just about building a power grid.
More recently on Steam, there's a game called Mindustry.
Which has, okay, okay, that's just my screensaver again.
Can you hear me, Chris?
Yeah.
How many times is this going to happen?
I think it is literally PTSD.
I think I'm not abusing the term.
No, you're, yeah, no, you're, that is what's happening to you.
I can, I can, I'm not, you're not even on video or anything.
It's palpable.
Yeah.
Your panic is palpable.
Yeah, so anyway, yeah, so like, Mindustry, I haven't played Vectoria, but I assume it has, and of course my game had it.
So, the thing about energy grid games is they're all about death spirals, right? Like, cascading failure.
Something goes wrong which causes something else to go wrong, and then something else you weren't even paying attention to, and like...
Like, and taking for granted goes around too, and then you're just screwed.
So in Energy Apocalypse, it's this like really simple one-screen tower defense game
where you build, like, a power grid, right?
So, you mine coal out of the ground, and then you burn it in coal power plants.
And the coal power plants give you energy, but they also create emissions.
And then the shtick of the game is that I just take all negative externalities and just arbitrarily reify them as mutant alien zombies.
And the rule is, they're invading Earth and they're terraforming it, and everything that is bad for us in terms of pollution is good for them.
And so, the more you pollute, the stronger the enemy gets.
And so, like, you're burning all this energy and stuff, and you've got lots of energy,
and then your defenses are powered by your materials.
So you have floodlights that use energy, and you have Tesla coils that use energy,
you have guns that use metal that you mine out of the ground,
you have flamethrowers that use oil or gas, whatever's available, right?
And so, as you're going through the game, you know, it's night,
and so your solar panels stop working, because it's night.
You know, or the wind stops blowing and your wind turbines don't work anymore.
And, um, or you run out of coal and your coal fire plant, which is just like amazing for generating energy, stops working.
And then, um, you build a couple of units so that you can, like, defend yourself and you used up all your metal and your gun stopped working.
Right? And you have these, like, cascading failure on cascading failure.
And so typically, like, you're doing pretty good until you stop paying attention to something. It goes down.
And then, like, you can't get back up.
And, like, the challenge is, like, not falling so far down the slope.
And there's also this inherent trade-off between efficiency and redundancy, right?
Like, an efficient system is one that has no waste.
And usually, super-efficient systems, like, run to the wire.
Like, to use a metaphor, like, um...
just like an Olympic athlete, right? Has like 0% body fat, you know, they're just made completely for running, say, right?
It's super efficient, you know, because that's what it takes to get that extra bit of performance.
Um, but if they get the flu they're gonna just like die, because they have no body fat. They have no reserves, right? And
Then there's also just mismanagement, which is neither efficient nor redundant.
It's just bad.
Yeah.
It's, it's interesting.
Like, you know, when you're talking about cascading failures and mismanagement,
it's interesting emerging from the past few days, uh, when, you know, you're
conserving your cell phone, uh, power, you're, um, you don't have any access
to like TV or, you know, your laptop.
So.
You're basically kind of in the dark about a lot of things and emerging from it and then seeing the way that you know
uh, you know
people like politicians, for example, uh, the things that they're talking about like
uh, whereas there's now this, you know,
The people are like our governor is using this as an energy, right like pitting fossil fuels against uh,
against renewable energy like windmills and
There was at one point at the beginning of it, somebody mentioned windmills.
This was on Monday.
It's like, well, it's because of the windmills.
And I was like, what? I didn't know what they were talking about.
And you emerge from this and it's like, people are using this as a debate point about different kinds of energy.
This is what you all were talking about,
like when we're trying to figure out
the roof water situation.
And those things need to be talked about,
and they need to be considered within
the overall power grid and tech and stuff.
But to see the discourse around that's happening
where people in tech,
while people in Texas are suffering,
is, it grosses me out.
Yeah, it did me too, you know, and it's like it's a little weird for me because like on the one hand, like a lot of my family is really conservative, right?
And the other hand, I'm also Norwegian and the Norwegian side is like a little more liberal, but like not in the way Americans expect at all.
Like Norwegians can be pretty provincial and not.
part of America's idea of what liberal means.
But then also, my entire game dev Twitter feed and friends are all really far left.
And so I feel conflicted because...
I log on, just check in what's going on, and everyone's having this big...
It seems...
The impression I get, which is probably false, is that everyone has these strong opinions.
And of course, yeah, Abbott and Cruz going to frickin' Cancun and all that nonsense.
I'm not a fan of our state leadership by any means.
But I feel like everyone's really busy making sure they score enough political points while
we're fucking freezing, and so are all our friends and family.
And like, and I see, and the really thing that like saddens me is when people who should know better are like, really like happy about it.
Like that makes me...
That was weird because I saw that also, and the only reason like the terrible stuff that people are saying about like, you know...
But basically what we're talking about is, you know, Texas is and has been a red state.
There is Republican leadership and there are some people that are just like, well, that's
that's what you get.
And it's kind of like, oh, OK.
We got this back in Hurricane Harvey as well, was it's like, well, you believe in climate
change now?
And it's like, thanks, my brother might be drowning, but good for you for being correct
on the internet.
Yeah.
And then, like, it's weird for me too, because like I said, like growing up in Indiana, no
one talks about Indiana.
No one talks about Indiana.
And then, like, when I come to Texas,
like, Texas is the central point for, like, politics and climate and, you know,
this being, it's just weird to log on and, like, see, you know, people that,
you know, aren't having the experience that we're all having,
have such strong opinions about it.
So it's a new thing to me.
You want to know something hilarious? In Norway we literally have a catchphrase that's like decades old called
That thing is totally Texas. Or in Norwegian it goes, det er is sikkert Texas, ja.
It's a very self-assured kind of braggy person.
Texas has great PR in terms of getting lots of it, whether all of it is positive or not.
But I think what people are reacting to on the internet is this, you know, very braggadocious,
like, larger than life Texas attitude.
I mean, I know people who have said things like, let the Yankees freeze in the dark whenever,
you know, someone's like, well, if you want green energy, then, you know, coal and natural
gas is what keeps you warm at night.
You know, it's so weird.
One thing that does bug me about Abbott talking about like windmills and stuff.
One thing I think a lot of people are surprised to know.
is that Texas in many ways like is this world that contains multitudes and contradictions
like it is oil and gas capital of the United States and the world but you might also wonder like
Lars is a Norwegian in Texas.
That's kind of weird.
It's not super weird.
Like, this isn't the reason I'm here.
You know, it's just because my mom married my dad.
But there's a lot of Norwegians in Texas, actually.
They're all in Houston, because Norway is also
oil and gas producer of the world,
and like Texas, a leader in green energy, which is so weird.
No one thinks of Texas as a leader in green energy.
But like, if you look at charts of wind, and solar,
and nuclear.
It's like we're really, really up there.
And that's why I feel kind of angry about people...
I do feel resentful, like the whole, like, ragging on windmills, because everything went down.
Everything went down.
And I do want to underscore this point, and this point is really important.
I really wish, in the wake of any crisis, everyone would just shut up for 72 hours and not have an opinion, not proclaim themselves an expert on whatever domain just happened, and just, like, look for some evidence.
Like, I am all in favor of heads rolling. Like, yes, let the heads roll.
But the problem is that a stopped clock, i.e. read, you know, idiot politician, can be right two times a day.
Just like a stopped clock.
And when we just like go off and like instantly it's like, oh, I know what the reason is.
It's the thing that I'm all, it's my dead horse that I'm beating is the reason.
It's like, you're gonna be wrong sometimes, and when you're wrong, that politician is
gonna love it, and he's never gonna shut up about it for six months, and the only thing
that matters, which is making sure that we take care of human beings and that this crisis
doesn't happen again, is gonna get lost in all that, you know?
There was one take I've read in the last 72 hours from someone who actually provided a
bunch of evidence for what went wrong, and he might be wrong.
I don't know if his account is going to check out, but he said, here's the data I have.
I've tried to be fair about this.
And my conclusion is that there was a problem in Texas, but we might have this problem nationwide.
And the fact that Texas has an isolated grid, and this is something a lot of people are
dogging on, oh, those Texans hate that federal regulation.
And federal regulation would have saved them.
Maybe, maybe.
Like, that could, I'm 100% willing to believe that.
But another thing that's equally possible is that the grid being isolated kept
Oklahoma and Louisiana and neighboring states from going down too.
Right.
I hadn't thought about that.
Yeah.
For, for like listeners that haven't picked up on this yet, like the power
grid from Texas, it is, it's ice, it's its own, it's isolated from, from
everything else and nearby States that have got, that had just as bad, um,
icing and things like that ended up faring so much better than, than we did.
Right, and so the conclusion is, okay, like you look at a map, Texas is like as black and dark as North Korea is on a nighttime map, right?
And so everyone's like, okay, well Texas screwed the pooch, it's all their fault, their infrastructure sucks.
Um, you know, and maybe it is, you know, but like, I'm not an expert in, you know, power grid engineering, despite the fact that I made a Flash game 12 years ago.
I really wish, you can wait 72 hours, the truth can wait that long and then we'll figure
out who's really to blame and then we can have all the righteous fury we want because
then we'll actually be directed in a positive, useful direction to actually solve a problem
rather than just score a bunch of little red hearts on Twitter.
I like the little red hearts.
They're so addictive, I love them.
And they just erode my soul.
So there's a couple other things I want to talk about.
So, again with the cascading, like, you know, failure.
Apparently, like I was reading a really good article today on Texas Monthly about what has happened and it's a really good, clear, like, telling of what happened.
And it's kind of what you're talking about. It's a step back looking at things in very near hindsight.
And it's called, like, the title is The Texas Blackout is the Story of a Disaster Foretold.
So, you know, with the benefit of hindsight, it talks about why this happened, why the systems failed, and how close we actually were to going total blackout.
So, like, we were able to maintain, you know, some levels of energy at different places in the state, but apparently...
Something happens like where everything is gone.
And once everything is gone, there is a really complicated way that they have to
use like diesel generators to start different plants across the state.
And it sounds like you're hand cranking like an old timey car, except
multiplied by like a trillion.
Yeah, I've been kind of a, sort of like keeping at an arm's length from, but morbidly interested
in what's called collapse porn, you know, which is just like post-apocalyptic literature,
right, and fiction, and non-fiction accounts of like what happened in Argentina and Venezuela,
like, and stuff like that, and prepper culture, who have these doomsday obsessions, and like...
Here's kind of where I'm at, like when I tell people I do some light prepping, like you get that pushback. It's like, oh, you're one of those people who hoards the toilet paper. And I'm like, like, there's this kind of person who's never
It's a game that's been through a crisis before, who doesn't really get it, and they think that it's about selfishness.
And it can be, because there's certainly people who like,
F you, got mine, gonna get my bunker, gonna shoot anyone who knocks on the door.
Right? Those people certainly exist.
And they have weird fantasy books that I've read that are disturbing.
But, um...
There's another school of thought that's like, do you have a fire extinguisher in your house?
That's the most likely crisis that's going to happen to you.
And do you know where it is? Do you have a drill to go get it?
If I say fire right now, will you know?
And like when I said that in some chat room or someone, like someone immediately pointed,
it's like, that happened to me. There was a fire.
I didn't know what a fire extinguisher was.
I almost died.
And you build general survival skills, like you don't have to plan for the zombie apocalypse.
Like I have a Berkey filter.
I built that in case the water was shut off.
I never anticipated a blizzard in Texas, but now I can filter water if I have to for the
cost of a hundred bucks.
I like, and this is, this is obvious, but like it, it, this past week really drove
the point home, like how reliant we are on systems and how there is like a single
node of failure that shuts everything down.
And then you get the, you know, the cascading failure that you were talking about.
Yeah, and some people say, like, if you get too much into the, if you drink too much of
the pepper Kool-Aid, um, the problem is, like, you start preparing for the complete breakdown
of society and it takes on this very, like, anarchist kind of everyone out for themselves
mentality where it's like raiders are going to come and, like, eat your flesh and stuff
and, and, like, people are going to shoot you and so you got to shoot first.
You know, but the other perspective is it's like.
like society doesn't have to be this fragile.
Like we can build a better society that is a little better.
And then at the same time, we can stop waiting for...
I really hate this one attitude I have.
I see a lot among otherwise enlightened liberals
that I look up to is when they're like,
it's not worth taking any personal measures.
We just have to like take over the government
and make a perfect society.
And it's like...
I'm not going to feel bad that I'm not going to wait for a perfect society to emerge.
I don't think it's selfish to take care of my family so that I am not a burden on everyone else,
so that I can have some overflow to help my neighbor, right?
It's like if my neighbor is freezing and I'm not in the middle of dying,
I have a warm house she can stay in, right?
You know?
And I think if we focus a little more on the local aspect of government and just society
and just helping each other out, I mean I think the term of art is mutual aid,
then we can build a more robust, to use the Silicon Valley fancy pants term, anti-fragile society.
Yeah, absolutely.
And that's, it's funny because that's the last point that I wanted to talk
about, about how kind people in my experience during this have been like,
I, like we have local restaurants that are already completely, you know, um,
hammered by the pandemic and not being able to, you know, uh, you know, run
business as usual, they're giving away food.
Like, in one of the, so down here we have P. Terry's,
which is like a fast food place.
And there's one that is pretty close to us
and they got a shipment of food.
And there was just like, and this was sad,
like there was like a line of cars
just like a couple miles long or whatever.
There were a lot of cars.
Going through this fast food
fast food drive-thru and all of those
Represent. I'm just like these aren't people there. You're not gonna wait like, you know hours in line
Because you just want you know a taco like these people must not have food like there
Yeah, there are people who are desperate to get to get food
And one of the things that I read is that,
or actually like that Anna told me,
my wife said that she saw that people
were paying for the people behind them.
Like, and just like going down the line like that.
There's that kind of thing we have,
like people who are offering up,
like, you know, somebody's out of medicine for their kids,
you know, and they're sick and, you know,
you can't go to the pharmacy, but they need it.
Post that on the Facebook group and it's like,
where are you?
I'm bringing it there.
Do you need anything else?
That type of thing.
And nobody is asking if you voted for Ted Cruz or not
before they extend some help.
We'll deal with that afterwards.
For now, we'll go get you fed.
You know, I'm thankful that, you know, you and your family
and sounds like your community are on the other side of this.
And yeah, I'm just.
Hopefully we all learn something from this.
Just I think we should just close with the fact that this isn't over.
A lot of people that you're not hearing from have it much worse because of survivorship
bias because they can't tell you how bad it is.
The damage, even once the temperatures are back up and the power is back on and the water
is back on for everyone, the lingering damage is going to last.
I agree with that and everyone out there take care.
We'll go back to our regularly scheduled 100% game developer centric conversations next
time and thanks for hanging out with us.
Take care.
Definitely going to play Frostpunk now.
Oh yeah.