Hi, I'm Katarina Mallet.
I am so excited to be here with you.
Last year, I returned to the games industry after a few years away, and I missed it so
much.
You know, there's just nothing like it.
the creative and passionate people, the groundbreaking tech,
the indies, the big shops, the art, the science.
But most of all, I miss that feeling
when a player tells you, I love what you made,
and playing it made my day better.
Our job is to delight people.
It doesn't get much better than that.
So there's a reason why gaming is larger
than both the music and the movie industries combined.
Yes, games are about immersion and play, adrenaline, distraction, but they're also about choice.
Through the choices that I make as a player, my experience will be different from yours,
and maybe even different from my own experience the last time I played.
And as game developers, we give players the power to make choices
that reflect and even change their view of the world.
The choices that we allow can influence how our players start
to see the real world around them
and how players feel going back into their day,
lasting far beyond a gameplay session.
You know this better than anyone.
With games, players tell stories,
they play out fantasies, and they even
discover what brings them joy.
And there are few greater examples of this than The Sims.
With over a billion hours played in 2021 alone
and over 560 million franchise copies installed
just since 2014, The Sims has made a unique mark
on the history of games.
It has a very real impact on the world
and few forms of entertainment can do that at scale.
Because The Sims is a game about life.
In The Sims, we give players the tools to interact with worlds that are new but familiar,
and help them recreate life as they imagine it.
But we can't achieve this unless players see some part of themselves reflected in this
game.
As game makers, it is so important for us to create content that authentically represents
the diverse world that we live in.
So we work hard to make a world in which players can see themselves,
where they can be whoever they want to be and play with life on their own terms.
We don't wait for it to happen in society first,
and even if we know we won't always get it completely right the first time,
we will keep trying.
We've had same-sex relationships in the game
from the very beginning in 2000.
And earlier this year, we previewed our work
incorporating gender-neutral pronoun options into the game.
So we want to continue expanding the tools that allow players
to express their identities.
This has been a case where society certainly
hasn't caught up yet.
And solving for this across all global languages
is not straightforward.
As I learned through this process, it is a lot more complex than adding a they-them option,
but we can start.
And there is still so much room for us to grow here.
And just like society, we evolve as it does.
So this work was ultimately picked up by The Hill.
a publication widely read by members of Congress.
It was a powerful reminder to us
that what we're doing is so much more than entertainment.
People are paying attention and looking to us
to see how we empower our players to tell their stories.
Through The Sims, players learn more about each other
and about themselves.
Our base game and expansion packs
allow players to explore a host of what if identities,
large and small.
Exploring what it might be like to have a family,
come from a different culture, have a new career,
a different body shape or skin tone to be richer or poorer,
live in an urban jungle or a tropical paradise,
have a different fashion sense, or I don't know,
be a vampire.
This is our motivation and why we show up to work each and every day.
We have a megaphone and we want to use it.
So we take this work seriously as we progress towards our aspiration for the Sims to represent
the diversity and complexity of life.
So I feel so lucky to be part of Maxis, the EA studio behind The Sims.
Our players are so passionate about the stories that they craft,
and we love seeing the impact that our games have on their lives.
This sense of purpose, of inspiring everyone
to make a better world through creative play
and our commitment to our players leads to a truly unique culture at Maxis.
In creating a more inclusive studio environment,
we provide a better experience for our players
and create a place where all sorts of people want to work.
So in the last year, 43% of new hires at Maxis
have been women, far outstripping the industry average.
This is an exciting signal that we are making progress,
but we know we still have work to do.
Our player base is highly diverse
and our team should be too.
And our players have told us that they want to see themselves in the game.
And bringing more of these perspectives on board will help us realize this vision.
In order to foster an environment where the most authentic games can be made,
we need to create a workplace that encourages and values different perspectives.
But you don't need to hear it from me.
Listen to our colleagues have to say.
I feel like I belong at Maxis because Maxis really embodies a people-first mentality.
It goes beyond just platitudes on a wall or in a presentation to the way that we
live, breathe, and act every day.
Creating more inclusive games by working with people and talking about lived experiences
and working with consultants to learn more about other people, other cultures, other experiences
creates an opportunity to make our games more approachable for everyone.
What we do here matters to me because it matters to all the people out there who didn't see themselves represented in games or media before and now have the chance to just explore lifestyle, explore themselves.
And that matters to the team.
Working on a product that's really beloved is wonderful.
Working on one that's beloved and able to enrich the world, that matters a lot to me.
huge honor to be able to work on the Sims team and be able to see people react to being able to
make a sim that looks like them. We're inclusive in the real sense of the word. The tapestry of
individuals that makes up our team is a collection of different life experiences and perspectives
and I think that comes through in our games. Before the Sims, I worked on a variety of games
where the primary verb was kill. Kill your opponent, kill the monster, kill the beast.
But here at Maxis, for the first time, the primary verb, what we do is create.
It's a world of difference.
We have a very imaginative and creative team,
and that just creates a space to experiment and to play.
I think it's really valuable.
I think there's a lot of one-to-one meetings at Maxis,
so there's a high premium on.
creating intentional conversations.
We have people who started working here
while The Sims 2 was in production,
and we have people working here
who grew up playing The Sims and now get to build it.
One of the reasons I love working at Max
is that we get to build stuff
that no one else in the industry even attempts.
We joke that we always try to solve
the hardest version of every problem,
but I think that's a good thing.
Hard problems can be the most engaging
and fulfilling to work on.
I've heard this pitch about, oh, let's add versatility to our game characters.
I've heard that so many times on every project, but
these guys who were talking to me, they actually meant that.
And for me, that was like, oh, you're bananas, guys.
I love it. Can I come work with you?
I came to Maxis because Maxis has a reputation of being a place that people can make home.
It's a place where people are taken care of,
where they're listened to, and where they're supported in becoming the best in their craft.
I've been in the industry for 10 years now.
This place feels like home.
Video makes me so happy every time.
Let's see.
So this team is just amazing.
At Maxis, we have such a strong group of people
who've been around a long time.
These are our cultural anchors.
They approach their work with humility, humanity.
and inherent curiosity.
They also set the tone
that we are a judgment-free workforce.
We embrace everyone's unique quirks and weirdness
so people can bring their full selves to work.
To complement this heritage,
we have an equally strong group of people
who are new to the studio
and bring a fresh perspective to the way we operate.
We've been growing a lot over the past few years.
Although our average tenure is eight years.
Over a quarter of the studio, myself included,
had joined since the start of the pandemic.
So we seek out suggestions from our new joiners
on how we can improve and what to try differently.
Regardless of our individual disciplines,
we are all craftspeople and tinkerers
and recognize that we must always be learning.
There's just no such thing as complete in our games.
We're always welcoming new ideas and ways
to break the mold to keep things exciting for our players
and engaging for our team.
So for 15 years, we had built rigs and mesh
in essentially the same way.
Then a few years ago, some engineers
wanted to experiment with ArcTech,
so they huddled together and proposed a new approach.
They had only been looking for clothing
that could be applied to male or female body types.
But the team saw something bigger.
So while this could have been
a more straightforward tech implementation,
we saw a chance to provide even more opportunities
for our players' expression.
And players can now create Sims with any type of physique,
walk style, tone of voice, regardless of their gender,
and dress or style these new Sims in any way they choose.
So not only did this moment expand gender expression
opportunities for our players, but it also fundamentally
changed the way our studio approaches
gender representation and to open our eyes
to a new way of planning content.
So I now want to bring you under the hood a little bit
and show you how we work behind the scenes
to create a game that not only reflects life,
but helps shape it.
First.
We know and use our values.
Everybody wants to be anchored
in something they feel good about.
Our values are not aspirational or what we wish we did.
They represent who we are when we're at our best.
We recently revamped our values to make sure
that they're fresh and that people feel connected to them.
And we didn't rely on an agency to do this work.
We had passionate team members conduct interviews
across the studio to distill our culture to its key essence.
So ours are create collaboratively,
challenge ourselves, champion inclusivity, and be authentic.
Company values can be such a cliched trope,
but they can be so impactful when used well.
Having strong values that help us
know what decisions to make when we're
stressed or under pressure.
is what makes the difference between scaling successfully
or dramatic collapse.
I have seen this firsthand.
When a team is small and everyone talks to everyone,
leaders implicitly model the team's values
through behaviors and interactions that everyone sees.
During periods of change, however, growth or a change
in strategy or an organizational shakeup or, I don't know,
pandemic, having articulated useful values
are an important compass.
So alongside goals or OKRs or whatever your model is
for saying, here is where we want to go,
values are how you communicate how the team should get there.
They become a social contract, a sense of cohesion that aligns the team even when they no longer interact with each other the way they could when they saw each other every day.
Championing inclusivity and being authentic are part of our values because it's critical to our game, to our players, to our team, to our business.
It's not a strategy.
It's who we are.
Next, to build teams with diverse backgrounds
to actually inform these authentic experiences,
we need to ensure that we're hiring free of bias
and have teams that authentically represent
the diversity of our audiences.
We look for diversity in all its forms,
professional skill sets, demographics,
and lived experiences.
And as part of our hiring process,
our recruitment panels are trained
to understand implicit bias,
and they're equipped with questions that favor inclusion.
Plus, our job descriptions, they're fed through a processor
that checks for language that might feel exclusionary.
We encourage our hiring managers
to consider alternative backgrounds
and complementary skill sets and are leaning into our efforts
to recruit early career talent into the industry.
And what's a big step for us, we've committed to a remote-friendly hybrid working model for the studio,
and can now hire the best talent regardless of location.
And this gives us access to a much broader range of lived experiences to inform our designs.
When we review interview feedback, we have a third-party person who facilitates these conversations
to ensure there's no bias in the feedback that we give.
And all of our employees receive training to make sure
that they uphold our inclusive culture.
Hiring is, of course, only the first step, though.
Inclusivity isn't just about having a diverse team.
It's about creating a culture
that encourages diverse perspectives to be heard.
So we seek to operate in a way that allows everyone
to contribute and make an impact beyond the limits
of an individual team or function.
For example, to pull off an authentic representation
of higher education for our Discover University expansion
pack a few years ago, we knew we couldn't just
draw from experiences in the American educational system.
So as we started brainstorming designs,
we reached out across the team,
specifically looking to explore
global educational experiences.
Through this process, we found tech leads
who went to school in India,
gameplay engineers who went to school in South America
and the UK, and artists who studied in Japan.
Workshops with these teammates.
helped unearth differences and commonalities
across these unique educational experiences,
ultimately informing the features
that allowed our players to feel
that their own unique experiences could be represented.
If we're exploring a topic
that is beyond our team's expertise,
we'll actively seek out people
who have those lived experiences,
either through the very popular employee resource groups
or ERGs across EA, or by bringing in outside experts.
For our fashion kits that were inspired by styles found
on Fashion Street in Mumbai or the airport fashion runways
at Incheon International in Seoul,
we partnered closely with external consultants
who helped us design collections that authentically celebrated
the trends and cultures in those cities.
This emphasis on listening to the team
extends beyond game features to how we operate the studio.
A few months ago, I started what I called a listening tour
to meet with employees across the entire studio.
It was so helpful.
I recommend it so highly.
I sat down with people of all levels, tenure and working style
to understand how they were feeling
about the prospect of hybrid work.
I wanted to understand their pain points, their preferences,
how they were juggling home life, integration,
and just what they were worried about.
So as a result of this, we decided to test run a large hybrid meeting,
roughly half in the office and half virtual.
It was a hot mess.
Half the people were staring at the back of my head while I was looking at those on screen.
Half didn't feel like they could speak up in the conference room.
And it was just not an inclusive experience.
So we realized that large meetings are best
for virtual platforms, focusing in-person meetings
on workshops and highly collaborative interactions.
And this has fundamentally changed the way
that we were thinking about the expectations we set
for our teams about working in hybrid.
We also learned that people love recorded meetings.
They like having the flexibility to check in
and what was shared on their own time.
We work across multiple time zones,
and catering to this has made a huge difference.
Most importantly, we were reminded that senior leaders
aren't necessarily equipped to determine
the best working style for every team and every employee.
Instead, we're here to set the tone, reduce barriers,
and provide the tools for people to work in ways
that make sense for them and their teammates.
We do engagement surveys, and we do monthly pulses,
and they're valuable.
but they don't replace just sitting and listening.
Pre-pandemic, I would have spent a lot of time
just walking around the studio, chatting with people.
But new working styles require new ways of engaging,
and so I'll be continuing my listening tours
and holding office hours.
We've also implemented cross-studio volunteer
committees.
We call them Sul Sul, after hello in Simlish,
to help support team health.
productivity engagement across the studio.
Focused on topics like recognition,
welcoming new team members, asynchronous productivity,
or whatever else the team decides,
these committees help us engage voices from across the team
who are passionate about a topic,
rather than just going back to the same usual suspects
or relying on seniority or function.
We also engage our community to understand what matters to them.
At the end of the day, our players are at the center of everything we do.
Alongside consumer and player insights research and playtesting,
we're continuing to refine our methods for listening to our community
and finding new and healthy ways to involve them.
For our work on customizable pronouns,
we've sought super valuable feedback
from not only our external and expert partners,
but the player community at large.
Sharing work in progress was a big step for us,
and one we'd really like to do more of.
We want our game team to be able to connect directly
with our players and fans in a psychologically safe way.
And we're exploring how we can create even more ways to do so,
whether it's live streams, dev diaries, forums,
listening sessions.
It's an ongoing journey, and one that we're getting better at.
We all want a relationship of transparency and trust
with the community.
Our players care so much about the Sims.
But we've seen at times that this passion can take a turn
from positive to negative,
directed at our team members on the frontline.
Our devs are working so hard to delight our players.
And when this happens, it is so hard for me to watch.
And it's not okay.
We value the feedback and insights of our community greatly.
and are continuing to refine how we engage the community
with mutual grace and respect.
Being part of a gaming community should be positive,
fun, fair, and safe for all, our players and our teams.
As you can probably tell,
I am extremely proud to be part of Maxis and The Sims.
Not just because we make a game that players love,
But I know what we do matters.
Our ambition is to inspire everyone to make a better world
through creative play.
Our employees are really good at what they do.
They have plenty of options for where they could work.
And we know that this sense of purpose
is part of the reason they choose Maxis
and what motivates us to show up every day
to deliver for our players.
Making impactful entertainment is hard.
Hiring the right individuals, it's hard.
Engaging and retaining large teams is hard.
Change is hard.
But working alongside diverse team members
makes these challenges a lot easier,
a lot more fun,
and a lot more likely to yield successful results.
And I actually think that our new,
remote-friendly working lifestyle is helping us.
Now we can bring in more geographic diversity
and work more seamlessly across North America and Europe.
We're going after the best talent, regardless of location.
And this not only helps us bring in more hard skills,
but also allows us to open the door to soft skills
and unique experiences that help us make a better,
more inclusive game.
Previously, almost all of our developers
were based in Northern California.
with Northern California experiences,
and they were mostly only familiar with Northern California.
And the pandemic changed that, and we're now able to benefit
from this global diversity of experience.
Now we can hire employees who understand what it's
like to be a parent in Stockholm or a recent grad in Toronto.
So working remotely has also led to a greater appreciation
of the complexities of people's lives,
and it builds empathy and trust across the team.
In the beginning of the pandemic,
working from home was a jarring experience.
And over time, it's become the norm, right?
We get glimpses into our boss's living room,
children bust through doors, cats walk on keyboards.
We understand if someone needs to go off camera or needs to go run,
pick up their kid from school.
And there's less of an expectation
that you have a work self and a home self.
And this openness has really helped lower many barriers.
Myself included.
I have three young kids.
I live in the Boston area.
And the majority of my team is on the West Coast.
Before the pandemic, I'm not sure that this job would have been doable
without uprooting my family's entire life and moving across the country.
I was able to take on a job that aligned with the impact that I want to make,
not because it was the most convenient or physically close to home.
My whole team is now used to seeing my kids come in for a hug
when they come home from school.
And I love that my eight-year-old daughter can see what my work entails.
When I grew up, my mom left home at seven in the morning, and she came home 12 hours later.
And I am so happy to be able to be a much more present role model for my kids.
Our new ways of working are also leading to more inclusive communication.
We have fun and extremely active chats during our town halls,
and we have entire Slack channels dedicated to giving kudos
to our teammates.
We have shared digital puzzles and impromptu huddles.
And with digital tools like Miro and Loom and Zoom,
people are empowered to jump into the conversation
and engage with people across teams and seniority levels.
And it works.
People who previously may not have been comfortable stopping a senior leader in the hallway are
perfectly happy to reach out on Slack.
And it's leveling the playing field across the whole studio.
It's fun.
So I'm clearly excited about our future.
We are committed to being more inclusive of different backgrounds, races, genders, geographies,
and ways of thinking than ever before.
We of course want to attract gaming experts,
but we realize that there's enormous potential
outside the industry.
We need fashion designers, artists, architects,
e-commerce specialists, machine learning experts,
and so much more.
We view non-traditional experience as an asset,
not a drawback.
So pulling this all together,
inclusivity allows us to attract a broader range of talent
and provide a more authentic experience for our players.
We all know that diverse, inclusive teams have better business outcomes.
Plus, it creates a more interesting and engaging environment to work in.
It's a win, no matter how you look at it.
Since The Sims 4 launched eight years ago, monthly active users has grown every year.
A testament to the passion of our players and the creativity of our team.
We are still tackling new technical challenges,
building groundbreaking new features,
and finding new and innovative ways
to engage with our players for years to come.
Plus, we're building something big and ambitious.
We're excited and we're passionate about what's to come.
And it's pushing us to examine how we build our teams
and how we innovate for the future.
And all this means we're taking a moment.
to reflect on our culture, consider how we work in this post-pandemic world,
and take advantage of the changes wrought by the last few years.
We're 21 years into this franchise, and we're just getting started.
So thank you all.
It has been so good to be here.
I haven't been to an in-person conference in over two years,
so I can't thank you enough for having been here with me.
We don't have time for questions,
but I am going to be in the wrap-up room over there
if anybody wants to pop by and keep the conversation going.
Thanks.
Thank you.