Hello. My name is Jason Vandenberg, creative director for Honor. Before I get started, just to get an
idea of who I'm dealing with here, how many of you all have played for Honor? Holy, wow, okay,
great! That's about half. That's cool. So that's good. I do have information for the rest of you,
so you won't be lost. I just wanted to sync up there. All right. So this talk is Forging Honor,
Providing a Coherent Vision for a New IP.
And the more I read that sentence as I was preparing this,
the more I read that subtitle,
the harder it was for me to look in the mirror
and maintain any of my self-respect.
because that is horrible corporate speak and not at all what
happened. So I'm going to rename this talk here because while we
did end up providing a coherent vision for a new IP, it grew out
of one very important emotion and that is this.
We had a big challenge and a lot of work to do to make it happen.
Now, when I showed my producer this slide, Stephan Cardin,
he was like, I don't think that it was desperation he gave me this other one.
I think it was more determination that we were doing this.
And that right there tells you a lot about me and my producer.
We're a good pair.
We'll hear more about that.
So this talk is not providing a coherent vision for the new IP.
No, no, no.
Let's rename it to what I actually want you to remember.
And that is that if you want to provide a coherent vision
for your new IP, what you need to do is never stop pitching.
Never.
Now, that will make more sense as we get deeper into the talk.
But that's the title.
Never stop pitching.
Never stop.
OK.
So the pitch.
Why is, if I'm here to talk about vision,
why am I here to talk to you about a pitch?
I mean, this isn't a sales presentation, right?
This isn't about getting the deal.
I'm a designer, I'm a creative director, what am I doing?
The thing is that hundreds of people simply can't agree.
It's not doable, right?
You can coerce a lot of people to agree, right?
But that's hard to do, and in a team project,
you need people to all be aligned
and moving in the same direction, right?
So, the pitch.
The art of the pitch is how you get people to see the same goal and how you get people aligned.
The first part of this talk is going to be an examination of how to do that.
And then the second part will be what that looks like, different tools that you can turn,
that you can use during your production to keep people in line.
Pitching.
Okay?
Keeping people aligned is all pitching.
So let's start by defining what a pitch is.
So never stop pitching.
Let's define what a pitch is.
This is one way.
We think that a lot of people
think this is how pitching works, right?
You get in an elevator,
get in the elevator,
you say, hey, I have a screen.
30 seconds later,
30 million dollars.
It's amazing.
We just gotta refine that pitch
so you have exactly the thing.
Doesn't happen.
That's not how it works.
This is another idea of how we think, where we have this,
and we get up in front of this room,
and it's very important people,
and we make this very reasoned, impassioned,
maybe very clever emotional appeal,
and then they think very cautiously,
and then they nod seriously,
and then we walk away with $30 million.
Right?
Now that does actually happen.
Once.
And that is not enough to keep your team on track
across an IP, right?
This is what pitching actually looks like.
This is an open house with a politician in the middle
talking to their constituents,
because pitching is actually a process of interaction
between you, the vision holder.
and the people who actually need to understand and comprehend and buy in and then feedback to
you about where you're wrong. And then that dialogue needs to occur. So this is actually
what pitching means and you do it all the time. Now, to be clear, this story, I'm going to tell
you about how this went on for honor. I kind of sucked at this at the beginning. So I'm going to
give you some, tell you some stories about what happened in the beginning. The early stories are
not going to be examples of good pitches, but we'll get there eventually. So,
To clarify, what do we think pitching is for?
We believe, a lot of people, that pitching
is for convincing to get cash.
That is not at all what it's for.
Pitching is a way for you to signal your values
to the people you are going to collaborate with
in order to earn their confidence.
in whatever that means,
confidence that their jobs are meaningful,
confidence that the project's gonna be a success,
confidence that they're gonna get money back
from their investment, whatever confidence means to them
and whatever confidence means to you,
this is what pitching is actually trying to do,
which is why it is at the heart of creative leadership
and why it is at the heart of keeping people aligned
over time.
Keeping people aligned over time
is not telling them what to do,
it is signaling that you are on the same team,
you want the same things.
and then you show them where you want to go
and then they see that they want to go there too.
Okay, that's what pitching actually is, not that one.
It's that one.
Okay, so a pitch is anything that connects people
to the reasons why their efforts matter,
which is why we do it in the beginning to get the money.
Now, that's a pitch.
What is For Honor? Before we go any further, What is For Honor? It's a video game where
knights, vikings and samurai crash together on an epic medieval battlefield. It was my 15 year
dream pitch game. It was my personal sort of quest that has now came out on February 14th, a
couple of weeks ago.
It's easier to just show you what the game is like. So this is a quick video that we'll
introduce you to. If you haven't seen it, this is what it's about. Warning, there's some
violence. We have swords. So it's not terrible, but there is some if you're sensitive to that.
Here we go. Oops, sorry.
This is a 4v4 multiplayer battlefield.
We also have a solo campaign.
The guys with shields over their heads are other players.
Oh, coward.
We have a system called the Art of Battle.
It's a whole new way to do melee combat. It involves stances on the right stick...
...blocks and attacks...
...and some rather spectacular executions.
Because yes!
Plays on an epic medieval battlefield.
and we can go on but that's the basic gist of the game. If you haven't seen For Honor that gives
you a lot of part of what you need to know for the rest of the talk. Okay, so where did it start?
How did this game get started? I'm going to give you a little bit of the background. I've told
the story to the press a lot so I'll do a fast version of this. But the idea, For Honor actually
began about 15 years ago when my wife bought the two of us a year's worth of stuff.
a subscription I guess, to a dojo, to a dojo in San Francisco that was teaching western martial arts.
Longsword, German longsword. And I studied this art of sword fighting, it's this really
rediscovered form, and I was walking home one day, and I was all impressed with how simple
the system was, and I thought what if we took these stances and we put them on the right stick.
And I had this new controller idea, like oh this is going to be great.
got really excited about it because I thought this would feel like real fighting and it would
move the fighting genre forward. Yay! Cool! So I pitched it and I pitched it to everyone who
would listen for 10 years. I pitched it. The answer was no. Again, no, no, no, no. We don't
make that kind of game. No, that will never work. No, I don't get it. Why would you want to
do that? No, no, no, no, no, no.
I want to be clear.
I'm going to tell you why I think,
I'm going to spoil the ending a little bit.
I'm going to tell you why I think I failed.
But I wasn't, it took me longer than this
to figure this out.
This is the core principle I want you to understand
about pitching.
Don't pitch your idea, pitch your purpose.
I was pitching an idea that I had about melee combat.
I was not pitching a reason to make a video game.
To demonstrate what I mean quickly,
I'll give you the pitch.
Here was the cool pitch.
This is my original pitch.
I have an idea for a better way to do melee combat with a standard controller.
We're going to put the guards of martial arts on the right stick.
And if we do that in third person, we end up with a whole new experience where the fighting
feels more like real combat, but in an intuitive way.
That is a terrible pitch. It's horrible. It's awful.
It works if you're able to squint and visualize the whole system
and kind of reach towards a thing.
But of course, I was pitching to executive producers and business people
and even designers would be like,
I don't think, I don't really think that would work, right?
It's a bad pitch.
Because I wasn't pitching the reason why it mattered.
So what happened?
What happened is I met this guy, Yanis Milat,
managing director at Ubisoft Montreal.
I was working at Ubisoft Montreal at the time,
and after years of trying to pitch,
he took me to lunch one day.
He took me to lunch one day, as he does,
he likes to, you know, let's go talk,
let's have our annual talk.
Like once a year he likes to go and talk.
And he looks at me and he's like,
so Jason, what do you really want to do?
What do you really?
want to do. And that's, his eyes are like that, they're creepy. He's really like, he's just
really like intensely compassionate but very dangerous man, right?
And I was pissed off. I had had a bad day.
Okay, I was really, I was flaming. I was raging that day.
And I was like, you know what?
You, what would I do?
I'll tell you what I would do.
And I said to him, you know what?
I'm gonna tell you, but you're gonna say no.
You know why you're gonna say no?
Because you can't see it.
I want to change the way melee combat works.
I want to feel the way that I feel when I pick up a weapon
and I go out with my nerd friends and we fight
because yeah, man, I do that.
I want to feel those emotions of battlefield
and I have this idea about how to make that work
but you guys can't see it, so you're going to tell me no.
Mmm!
The middle of this restaurant.
It's a nice restaurant too.
He's like, whoa.
And so I told him the thing.
And at the end,
He smiles at me. He says, no. And I'm like, I knew you were
going to. And he says, but. I have someone I want you to meet.
And he says, I want you to meet Stefan Cardin. Stefan Cardin was
the producer of a team at the time called the Fox team. They
had done Naruto and Prince of Persia and a bunch of fighting
stuff inside Ubisoft and they were looking for a creative
director.
And he had been going around asking and interviewing people, talking about, you know, he would
ask them this question.
He had this question that he wanted to ask me.
So we went to the bar across the street and Steph looked at me and he said, what would
be the game of your life?
What's the game that you would make?
What's the one thing you want to do?
What's the game that would make your life have meaning?
And I was pissed still, but I told him.
I'm like, rawr, right?
And at the end of that, I explained it all to him,
and he said, I think you should talk to my team.
So I put a deck together, and I gave this pitch.
I gave this pitch.
Now, it was a terrible pitch.
I want to be clear about that.
It was better than the pitch that I just gave you,
but I'm going to show you the key slide from the pitch
that I made so you understand what not to do.
I want to make Fight Club with Claymore.
Fight Club with swords, that's what I want to do.
I just want to fight with weapons.
Because I was so desperate, I was like, I just want to fight, I just want to do this
system, right?
I was like, uh!
So it's terrible, it's a terrible pitch.
But they said yes, they said yes, they said let's do this.
And there were a lot of reasons, I'm going to go through why that happened.
But the key thing again...
I had accidentally pitched my purpose because I was pissed.
I'd forgotten to talk about the controller part and I got so hung up on the,
God damn it, I just want to fight.
I want to feel the way I feel when I do this for real.
It's so cool.
And I don't feel that way when I play other games.
And I want to.
And I had accidentally put some passion and some thought
into some emotion into the context
and I connected with them accidentally.
So later, so we got a yes and we started.
And that's where it started.
That's where the game began.
So we kept going.
And, but at this point,
and this is the thing I want you to,
there's a key thing I want you to understand.
Remember the elevator pitch idea?
Right, you get in the elevator, ding $30 million, right?
Or the, you know, you stand up
and they ask for the $30 million.
So I had gotten the team.
I got the team and I got the green light.
With a terrible pitch.
I had not yet learned how to do it well, the way I hope you will feel I did.
So it still didn't work, but the pitch turned into a really, really strong vehicle for the
project because the pitch is only the beginning.
So what happened next?
I'm going to take a quick moment and I'm going to do, this is going to be a straight up plug.
So brace yourself.
because somewhere in the first four months of the project,
this group called the Think8 came to our project
and they did a workshop on their process
and they haven't finished their fricking book
and you guys, finish your book.
Ugh, these guys.
I want to read the book.
When their book comes out, read it.
And if you can hire them, great.
They did this process for thinking about
what you're trying to accomplish.
I highly recommend it.
We came out of that process.
with a pitch that actually was the one
that carried us through the first 18 months.
I'm gonna do the pitch for you now.
I'm gonna do the pitch that I did at the first like,
you know, I don't know.
I gave the pitch like 100 times
over the course of the first two years.
So I'm gonna do the opening bit.
So this is the pitch that I think actually carried
for Honor through its opening bits.
Here it goes.
So I have a belief.
Why am I making this game?
I have a belief.
I have a profound belief.
I believe this.
I believe that combat is an art.
Capital A, art.
I believe that combat is an art form
where the artist sometimes gives their lives
in defense of what they believe in.
I have a military family.
My father was a Marine, my dad was an infantryman
in World War II, and I have all,
my brother was a ranger, and my son
was joined in the Navy early on in his life.
I was the black sheep, okay?
I deeply respect warriors, right?
Even if I understand that the army can be used
for horrible purposes, right?
I believe that combat is an art form.
Deadly, terrible.
necessary, we don't want it yet, it is there. And I have a favorite style. It is this one. This is
a screenshot from Total War Medieval 2, which at the time, it's the actual screenshot I used for
the pitch, at the time was the only reference I could find to make my point. This is my
favorite style of combat. It is close, it is intense, you see her, you're right in there,
you're next to her, but I don't want to play this game. I mean, I do play this game, but this is
not the game I want to make, right?
I want to make this game.
I want to be that guy.
I want to be, or the guy that lives.
I want to be surrounded on the battlefield.
I want to know that my skill is what matters.
I can't do this.
I can't play that game at the time this game didn't exist.
Now it does, five years later, but that's the game I want to make.
That's a better pitch.
It's better. Even if you don't agree or you don't want to work with me on the project,
at least now you understand why I want to make it.
What's its value? What's the problem that it's trying to solve?
It's better. To try and demonstrate to you how better it is,
I'm going to try and do a little experiment here where I do that same pitch without the Y part.
Without the combat as an art bit. So let's just erase our brains. I know you can't do that.
But this is a mental exercise, it'll be good for you guys.
Try it out, we're gonna try this.
So here's a better pitch, here's the pitch without this.
I love this kind of combat.
Personal, it's brutal, difficult, exhausting.
And I wanna make a game about this kind of combat.
But I don't wanna play this game, I wanna play this game.
And I have an idea about how to connect the player
through the controller to this character
in a way that will change the way
these kinds of melee games are made.
Yeah, it's okay.
Combat's a fucking art, right?
And I believe it.
So, never stop pitching, but pitch your purpose.
How did I learn this?
I showed you the Think8. That was absolutely part of this. But I'm going to show you a slide.
And if you're on the internet, is anyone on the internet? Do you guys use the internet?
Yeah, good. You may be familiar with this guy. So I learned this technique from a guy named
Simon Sinek. If you've seen this guy on your internets in the last six months, it's because
he went viral with a video where he was saying terrible things about millennials.
Please do not let that video prevent you
from extracting the awesome that is this talk.
How great leaders inspire action.
It's the thing about the golden circle.
When people ask me, how can I do what you do?
How can I learn to pitch?
I say, go watch this video 20 times.
And when you've digested the lessons of this video,
go in there.
The quick version of this goes like this.
He has a story he tells about Apple and Dell.
People don't buy what you make,
they buy why you made it.
Dell's pitch for a computer.
We have great computers, great hardware, great service,
delivered to your door, affordable,
we can, you know, great warranties.
Would you like to buy a computer?
It's great.
Apple's pitch.
We believe that technology can be used
to improve the human condition, and it should be.
We happen to make a computer.
It's not bad.
Watch this video. I learned all this from him.
So, so that was the first part of the pitch.
Now, so, pitch the why.
Those are your two tools so far.
First, you never stop pitching.
You're always pitching.
Two, pitch your purpose.
Not your idea.
But you do have to do this.
The dreaded business case.
Do you need to make the dreaded business case?
Absolutely.
It is super easy to come up with a great pitch
for a game that's already been made.
Right?
I want to make a game.
that immerses you in the adventure of being a soldier,
captures the fantasy of being in the middle
of a modern battlefield.
Right, we've made those before, right, we know.
It's not okay goods, but what's something special
about that, right?
So I'm gonna give you the example
of the dreaded business case.
This is tool number three.
I've been sneaking my tools in on you
under all my stories.
Tool number three, the dreaded business case.
This is how I pitched the business case,
and it's an example of trying to point to
the problem that this game is trying to solve.
Here we go.
So I'm gonna do two charts for you.
First one was going to be gun games.
Second one would be melee games.
Do the same thing.
Here's an axis.
On this side we have PVP combat skill.
So the further out we go here, the more skill is required
to play this game.
The more skill the game asks of you, right,
or potential for skill expression there is.
And up here is immersion.
The higher up here we go, the more the world is there.
I believe in the characters and the space,
and I'm really in there.
I mean, I feel like I've been transported.
Okay, so with gun games in the beginning,
there were always this balance between,
and we can argue about exactly where the dots go,
but there was always this balance
between skill and immersion.
We quickly discovered this zone here.
where it was all about skill, right?
At the same time, we discovered this other zone up here
where it was all about immersion, right, generally.
But all along, there were these games.
These slides are a little bit outdated
because, remember, this project was five years long,
so excuse me for that.
But there was these games that were the balance of both,
had the best of both, the highest potential for skill
and the highest potential for immersion.
All right, so let's do that for Melee games.
Same thing.
So in the beginning.
Again, trying to balance the both, there were some interesting experiments.
Bushido Blade.
Right off the bat,
we found a zone here where we can...
where it's all about skill, right?
And who cares about immersion, right?
It's all about just player skill, player versus player.
And then we always had these games
that are about immersion, getting into the world, right?
A lot of these games you don't even play on hard, right?
There's no hard difficulty in Zelda or Assassin's Creed, right?
So not about skill.
But when it comes to games that did both,
there's some interesting experiments.
Name one.
Name one game that has melee combat as its primary topic
that has the immersion of a Call of Duty,
a Halo, Battlefield, and has a level of skill expression
of a Halo, Call of Duty, or Battlefield.
One game.
I've given this part of the presentation
to probably over 3,000 people now,
and I just gave it to the entire internet.
So, I'm sure I'll hear about it.
But no one ever said one game, right?
Okay, well, my point is, what the fuck, man?
I wanna play this game.
Like, I really wanna play it.
And I think that I'm not alone.
So that's the business case.
That was my entire business case.
But you see what I'm doing here?
I am pointing to a problem that I thought a lot of people might have,
which is the lack of a knights vs. vikings vs. samurai sword fighting game in their life.
And I am setting out to fill that void,
because damn it, the world deserves that kind of video game.
So make sure that you're solving a problem
that a lot of people have.
Now this doesn't just apply to your audience, of course,
because remember that pitch when I talked to Yanis,
and then I talked to Steph?
Well, I was also solving a problem that Yanis and Steph had.
Yanis had a problem.
He needed a new IP.
He was looking for something new to do
out of Ubisoft Montreal.
And he had a team that was looking for something to do
and didn't have a creative leader.
That's a problem for him. He's burning money and he wants something cool.
Steph, my producer, had a problem. He was running a team with no creative leader.
So my pitch also solved their problems.
So, never stop pitching. Pitch your purpose and solve someone's problem.
I want to underscore this. For Honor didn't just happen because I had a good idea.
I think I had a good idea, but it wasn't good enough.
I needed an entire design team to help fix it.
And they really did.
I've got one of my designers here in the front.
She was like, yes.
Yes, we fixed your game.
I'm not that great of a designer.
But the reason For Honor happened
was because a whole bunch of people had a problem.
And they were all different problems.
And the pitch was a solution to a majority of those problems.
So find someone who's got a problem that your idea solves.
And go talk to them.
And remember, I pitched to the team,
and it was the team that said yes.
Okay, oh yeah, so we had to, so now we have a pitch.
That's a pretty good pitch, and it carried us through.
So that was great, my part was good,
but we also had to build the, what's it called?
The video game, all right.
So we started doing that.
Now this idea had...
there wasn't such a thing at the time. So we started doing, if
you guys have attended, quick hand, if I say fail faster and
follow the fun, who has, is that familiar to you? Great. All the
rest of you if you are a designer.
or a producer or really want to make video games, attend Mark LeBlanc's lectures and learn
about fail faster, follow the fun. Because that's what we did. We did a series of prototypes. This
is the first prototype that was done. This was done in the first week of For Honor. This is our
two player experience here.
was two controllers and we had the guards in the middle there
and we could attack, little block windows and health bars
and stamina. That was where For Honor started, the very first
video game. Week one on the project. It was fantastic. Fail
faster, follow the fun means build as many prototypes as you
can.
over the course of the first 18 months of the project we made like 400 prototypes.
We would play every day, we'd rock and roll.
And as we played, as we built the game we evolved.
We played with stick figures for the first year, and it was great.
It was a lot of fun.
You can see us were experimenting with feedback systems and stuff.
One of the things that we learned is that when you play with stick figures
you can see the entire battlefield really clearly
because nobody has any flesh to block.
the field. So when we put real skin on the characters, suddenly the game changed and we had
to change all our maps and you know everything was... but we played with stick figures for a while.
This is a screenshot from an early game. Super Brain in the middle there, that's my producer,
that's Steph. And the Dark Lord, that's me.
And unfortunately it was Kaylin who got the kill. I was so pissed!
But it was great.
So what we were doing is we were iterating
and iterating and iterating,
but we were playing like this for a long time.
How do you know what the game looks like?
So remember that this talk is about keeping a team aligned.
How do you keep a team aligned, right?
We had a good pitch,
but what's the game gonna look like now?
Everyone's bought in, what do we do?
What are we really building?
So while we were doing this,
while we were iterating and iterating and iterating
and playing every day,
we had another thing we were building,
it was a thing called target gameplay footage.
You may have heard of this concept in other talks, I'm not sure.
But, what is a target gameplay footage?
It is an attempt...
to create, you create a video, a cinematic that shows you way in advance what the game
will look like. Or what it could look like anyway. Right? It's an attempt to sort of
explore the future through a video. And this idea sometimes gets a bad rep because of course
the question is why are we wasting all this time on assets that we don't ship.
It's a huge amount of effort, it's expensive to make.
What's it for?
And it seems like, often feels like to developers,
like it's a waste of time.
But in certain cases, and if you do it well,
I'm gonna give you a list of how you do it well in a second.
It can really help you.
I'm going to show you.
a little clip from the middle of the TGF that we built for For Honor.
This was done the second year, between the second and the third year of the project.
And you're going to hear...
In this clip you're going to hear an announcer come in and start talking about points and
you know, oh he's got to take the thing and doing sort of commentary stuff.
That was our way of injecting the game design rules into this video so that
if people wanted to watch it and kind of understand how the mode was going to work
that there would be a way for them to do that, but it's not really a big deal.
So this is the opening seconds, or opening minute and a half or so of the...
of the TGF we built.
Key thing to know, all of this was rendered
inside the actual game engine with actual assets
three years in advance of shipping the game.
Blades is really starting to overextend into that minion group.
If he's not careful, he's gonna get surrounded.
Our Astra Serpent and Blades are gonna tag team this Captain,
and that's gonna give their guys the push they need to really get this match started.
Now Blades is keeping it a little bit defensive right now.
He's waiting for his minions to join him so he can start this push against the Vikings.
Those catapults are really gonna screw with Blade's plan.
He's gotta take that flag.
It's also gonna give his team 200 points,
which is a solid step towards the 1,000 they need
to put the Vikings into sudden death.
Now, Blade should have an easy time
taking care of this point.
Nothing but minions here,
so his plan is exactly what he needs to take him out.
All right, the Knights take the lead!
Yes!
Oh, shit.
Ah, crap! Here comes Eric LaRouge. He wants to take back the catapult, and if Blades wants to hold against that axe with his flail, he's gonna need to keep the high ground. Let's see if he can pull it off.
that guy needs to practice. So that gives you a feel for that.
All that was mocapped. We just got actors in the motion capture
stage and had them go through that. But when we did the mocap,
we were sitting there with our game director and game designer
and we were designing all the moves to be how we thought it
would work and try to fake it so it would all come together. But
if you think about what I showed you in the opening.
right, the first charge through, that was three years before that, right?
Pretty proud of that.
So how did that work?
How did we get this asset to be useful to the team?
There's a couple of key things.
If you're going to do this, a couple of key things
that you really, you must do,
or it will be a waste of time.
Use real assets.
You have to be using the actual stuff
that you think you will be using in the game.
It has to be stuff that has the poly count,
has the right level of textures, right?
Something like the right process,
your best guess as to how you're gonna build
the real assets in the game, if you possibly can.
You need to use your real engine.
You're going to make a bunch of mistakes and there's going to be a bunch of conflicts
between your departments while you're making this TGF, right?
Those need to be real.
They shouldn't be fake, right?
They shouldn't be having discussions about how to make the movie.
They should be talking about, well, in the real game, we wouldn't do it this way,
and so we shouldn't do this now, right?
You should have your arguments be real.
Use the real team so that when the arguments you have,
so that the arguments that you have are remembered.
by your team. That knowledge is embedded inside your group, right? And it's tricky because
your team is not 400 animators in another country, right? It can constrain you, but
there's nothing more valuable for the team than the lessons that they learned making
this stuff. So use the real team. Stick to the core player experience, okay? Follow the
player around. Force yourself to not cut. Don't take shortcuts.
It's not a trailer. You're not trying to sell this game with
this TGF. You're trying to inform the team, the whole team
and the company about what you're building. And if you do
those things, then this is not a waste of time. Especially if
you have nothing else to compare it to. If you have a game that
is a lot like your game, then you can often just point at that
and be like, well, like this but different. That can get you
through a lot. But if you're doing something new,
If you're working on a new IP and you've got ideas that you don't have good examples of,
this is an incredibly useful tool for keeping people on track and aligned on the same idea.
Now, that's really expensive, right?
You're like, great, thanks a lot for rubbing it in our faces how big the budgets are at Ubisoft.
Thanks a lot, man, right?
Like, must be nice, right?
Well, we did that because we can, right?
But I'm gonna show you another clip
that was actually the first TGF that we made.
And this clip, there's not gonna be any sound
on this video because we used a soundtrack
from Two Steps from Hell, which is a soundtrack group.
And it's not, we didn't license it, right?
It's all internal stuff.
So there's not gonna be any sound here.
But this was made by one person, my animation director.
And I'll talk you through what we got here.
Oops, hey, give me the thing.
Give me my video.
There it is.
Battle.
Imagine epic music.
What we did is he went into, I think it was Maya.
Might have been Max.
And he stole a bunch of characters from Assassin's Creed
and posed them.
in a series of vignettes. And then he just cut between them and moved the camera around
behind the round to try and get a feel for what this game might feel like.
And we chose sepia tone. Why? Because it's artistic and cool? No!
Because we didn't have to texture anything!
There was no work to be done! It was complete!
Because we didn't care about the texture at that point, right? We just wanted to get it done.
Now, that's not, there was more, it went on,
it had sort of a sense of loop,
but I just wanna use this as an example.
If you think creatively, you can do something
that gives you 80% of the value that I just showed you,
of the previous thing, with 1% of the work, right?
The point is, go through the thinking through it process.
So, never stop pitching, you're always pitching.
Hopefully by now I've convinced you of that.
Pitch your purpose, solve someone else's problem,
and describe the target.
Describe the target as accurately as you can.
You've got a large team of people who need to be able
to make decisions when you're not in the room.
Last one, the last one and then there's two quick ones at the end.
Um, we're getting, we're alright, we're doing good.
Um, so, last, this one is a culture of play.
So now, where are we in the production?
We got the green light, yay!
We did a bunch of prototypes, yay!
We made our TGF, we know where we're going, right?
Cool, this is good stuff.
Now we're making the game.
And while it's useful to see the TGF and know kind of what it's
going to look like and we get a feel for how we're going to play
it and we're making all these prototypes, there's an
essential need that game developers have which is to
understand why their game is cool.
and to validate, to prove to themselves as often as they can
that what they're doing is working,
that they're succeeding today, not just in six months.
So the way we did this is instead of having milestones
on For Honor, we had tournaments.
Every three months we would all get together, we would have the
build and we would close the build. We would lock, stabilize
the whole thing. And I can tell you the programmers were very
serious about being sure that the build was stable because
they knew that on Friday the entire team was going to be
playing this game in a tournament and they didn't want
to be the one who was responsible for the game crashing
mid-match and then their friends coming over and being like, why
did they get it right? They put a lot of pressure on themselves
to make it work.
But then we would sit and we would play.
And it was awesome.
It was really fun.
I'm going to show you a quick video we made just to prove
that we actually did it.
This is the actual team.
So it's a quick video.
The end of the video that we made that shows the tournament.
The two teams fighting for the championship are Hat and Crash
and the Pixel Shredder.
This is the second tournament.
You can see our.
Prototype running in the background there.
Yay, we're here.
The champions of Warhammer.
Yeah!
Let's go!
The dev team would self-organize into teams,
and we would have just a, you know, normal tournament.
We'd have little trophies, and they would pass from team to team.
The trophies were great.
One of our devs took some clay one night and made a series of clay stick figures.
They were fantastic.
So we played every week.
If you weren't playing every day, everyone would play on Friday,
and then every three months we would have a tournament.
And we were always playing the game,
because for us, we were a multiplayer game.
It was really important.
For a single-player game, you need to do it differently,
but the same idea applies.
Quick thing.
I mentioned Yanis Malat in the very beginning, the guy with the beady eyes, or the blue eyes.
He's so intense, ferocious, this guy.
I wanted to just give you a quick taste of what I was dealing with every day of my life.
So this is Yanis here in the middle.
In the tournament, we were playing against my team.
I'm on the left there, and they just won.
And I want to show you the grace and the modesty and the pure...
Just.
Every day.
So,
never stop pitching.
Describe the target, culture of play.
The culture of play is one of the best ways
during the production to maintain it.
Of course you need to have all the other pillars in place
but it's a great way of maintaining and reinforcing it.
Alright we're getting near the end here, which is great.
There are two more tools that I want to mention quickly.
But one of them is obvious and you already know about them.
And the other one was, well, you'll see,
is a talk that I gave already.
So the first one is key art.
This is amazing.
You have to do this.
But duh.
So this was the very first image that my art director put
together that we all, when he came home one day
from the weekend and had done this, and we all went, whoa.
That's our game, that's what we're doing.
It's really cool, right?
And I mean, if you've seen the collector's edition
that we released, it's literally that, right?
It's three helmets together.
It was an amazing way to communicate
what we were trying to do.
This is the first image that we did.
This was an attempt to capture
what made our fighting different.
Um, because that style, that stance that that character is in comes from German Longsword
and is something that you don't see usually and there's kind of an intensity and a ferocity
that's there.
The reason that that stance is so tense is because I'm, he dragged me into a corner and
took pictures of me and forced me to stand like that for several hours and the day after
we took that picture and he did a paint over, my back went out and I was on my back for
three days.
So I paid.
for that picture. But it really captured the essence of our fighting in some ways.
Our world, we did amazing stuff in this natural world with all this beauty.
This was the first picture, the first time I saw a detailed render with all of
our lighting stuff. When I came over to my art director's computer I said, why do
you have a photograph
of a sword and a shield on your screen? And then he turned the camera...
And I was like, well that's in the engine, oh my god.
And I had this experience several times.
So it really, we had been working on the look of the metal,
the look of the leather, this feel of aged material
that we really wanted to capture,
and it really guided us through.
So that's not my department, it's not my expertise.
We had an amazing art team, but of course,
key art is a crucial way for keeping people on track.
Key art.
Get some.
The last one I'll give you is this one,
which is to know your audience.
I gave a talk last year called The Engines of Play,
where I talked about, I don't know if you probably
haven't seen it, but I talked about these things
called taste maps and player motivation.
We did this process, right, on the team.
I'm not gonna go through how we used it here
because that's what the talk was last year.
But it absolutely helps in defining
who you're making this game for and what they're going to get
out of it.
And that helps your design team enormously.
And it also helps your marketing team and your business team
understand how the design is going to work and function.
But there's a whole other talk in the GDCP vault about that.
So here we go.
Never stop pitching. I hope by now I've convinced you. Everything I was doing here was some
form of a pitch. The why is here in every one of these tools. Why are we doing tournaments?
Combat is an art form. I want you to understand combat. I want you to be in there and
experiencing that art form every day as much as you can. Describe the target. TGF. So never
stop pitching. Pitch your purpose.
Watch Simon Sinek's talk.
I know you probably think he's a dick.
He's not.
Or maybe he is, I don't care.
He's smart, okay?
I've never met him.
I don't know.
Solve someone's problem, for honor happened
because it solved like a lot of people's problem.
Not just because people believed in me.
It's a great story, and my ego would love you to believe that I stood up in front of, you know,
Ubisoft, and that the brilliance of my genius is that that's not what fucking happened.
That doesn't happen, right? And if they did do that, it would be a mistake, right?
It should be more complex than that.
Describe the target clearly. Show your team where you're going.
Generate a culture of play. Play your own game.
Make your key art so you know exactly what emotions
you want to evoke visually, how you're gonna do that,
and get to know your audience.
Last one I'm gonna do is this was,
I gave this presentation to Clint Hawking,
who was my advisor, and he pointed out at the end
something that there's one more reason,
there's one more place where all these pillars
and all this pitch and all this work
comes incredibly useful, and that is when you are
talking to your players, okay?
I showed you the TGF and I showed you the start,
that video is the way that the game starts.
That's how we did the same video,
the same setup was on the stage at E3.
And all of my stuff about combat as an art form
and all that stuff about why I want to make this game,
it's all in my interviews, right?
And not just my interviews.
This is Biazade's interviews, right?
When she goes on there and does her videos,
she sometimes does it better than me, right?
These ideas spread, right?
And if they're true, they're true.
They're gonna be as true to your business people
as they are to the players.
They should translate.
And so if you've gotten really honest
about why you're making this game,
and as a creative leader, you need to be honest
because cynicism spreads, right?
You need to be honest.
If you've done that, then your players will hear.
the same vision that your team has heard,
and with any luck, it'll solve their problem too.
That's my talk.
I think we have time for a few questions,
but thank you very much.
I think we've got 15 minutes, am I right?
We've got time for questions.
Yo, questions.
Hi, first of all, congratulations on the release.
Game picks ass, and it's super stable
and on all four wheels and running.
I have a question about key art.
What happens when you have...
key art that kicks ass and is awesome and is something very close to what you think
that you want but you're not sure or you're maybe sure that it's not. It's really good key
art but it doesn't show the destination that you want the team to be going towards.
Well, two answers to that question. And it entirely depends on whether you're right or
wrong. So which is it?
if okay let's see you're right or wrong you're right you're right the game doesn't want to go
in that direction but the key art is saying that then you need to have a clear conversation with
your art team or your art director or whoever it is that is doing the art right um about these
values start at the values and say this is where i need to find where you think it's gone wrong
you you need to be able to as a creative leader you need to be able to illustrate to those people
why
why you think it's off. You need to be able to do better than, well, I don't really get it. I
just don't think this is right. And these tools, if you take the time to digest and really think
about your own personal why, what this game is about for you emotionally, and then you look at
what they've done, you should be able to identify why the emotions are different. Which is the
different emotion? And then talk about that. Talk about, well, I feel like this. This art makes me
feel this way, but what I would like to feel is like this.
The mistake that many people make is, I think,
is to ask for, is to give your team solutions
instead of problems.
Everyone in the games industry, not everyone,
but almost everyone in the games industry
came in here because we're interested
in solving difficult problems.
So if you have a team of people who are interested
in solving difficult problems,
and then you walk up to them and you give them a solution,
what are they gonna do?
You're gonna go, okay.
But if you walk up to them and you say,
I have this problem, your art makes me feel like this
and I need to feel like this,
they're gonna be like, if they're interested
and if you've got good rapport with them,
they're gonna go, huh, I think I can do that.
I'll show you.
They'll give you something cool.
Thanks.
Hey.
Yeah.
Hi.
Thank you for the amazing session, amazing talk.
I want to ask, how early in the development
came this idea of mashing these different cultures together?
And how this crazy idea that, well, everybody
went along with it, and it came to the release?
So you mean it's the Knights, Vikings, Samurai thing, yeah?
So Knights, Vikings, and Samurai.
What?
So what happened there was I came into the project with the desire to make the sword fighting
part. From the beginning we were talking about what characters we could use. Who do we want to
be? Who do we want to be? And after a week or two of discussion along that track, the
conversation was really like we should do samurai. I want to do this viking over here and
I want to do this knight. And we should do these things. Knight, viking, samurai, knight,
viking, samurai. I turned to my producer one day and I said, hey, Steph, what if?
What if we did knights, vikings and samurai?
And he looks at me and he's like,
I kind of love that.
And he tried it out on people.
He went around in the hall and he would try it out
on people because he's like that.
He would go around and be like,
knights, vikings and samurai.
And we just, it was so much fun.
People just knew it.
They just loved it.
And the amazing thing about knights, vikings, samurai,
yeah, let's do a quick test.
I'll actually tell you why we're doing this.
It'll show you why.
Show of hands, knights, vikings, samurai, pick one.
Show of hands, knights.
My people.
Vikings.
Huah!
Samurai.
Always the most popular.
Who did not raise their hand?
Who did not raise your hand?
That's why we're doing knights versus samurai versus vikings.
Everybody knows.
You picked when you were eight years old.
you. How did you keep a coherent vision for the game rather than just letting it become sort of
an interesting feature you came up with? Where did the, and when did the game come through
rather than just the combat system you thought? We, because we spent, we did it by spending the
first 18 months of development almost exclusively on the combat system.
We knew that this was going to be the breakthrough.
At Ubisoft, this moment is called a breakthrough.
It's something that we look for.
So there's a culture around Ubisoft for looking for things,
gameplay breakthroughs that are like this.
And we knew that if we could crack this,
that we would end up building the whole game around it
because it would change melee combat in some ways for us.
So from the beginning it was clear that that's what we were going to do.
And we knew that we were going to be a new IP from the beginning.
So it was easy for us to define that from the start, right?
We weren't having to push other stuff out of the way.
That's the nice thing about doing a new IP is that you have this blank slate.
And so we were able to go, it's right there in the middle.
And then when other stuff would come in, we would be like,
well, this needs to stay here in the center.
And then we were able to prevent that from happening.
It was nice.
There's other problems with having a new IP, though.
The most important one is, what's the genre of For Honor?
Does anyone know?
Because I would like to know.
It would be really useful for me to be able to tell people
what that is.
You have other problems when you're doing a new IP,
but that's one of the great things about starting fresh.
Thanks.
Excellent talk, thank you very much for that.
I have a question about more details.
You talked about your weekly play test
that you did on Friday.
About how long did you spend on that?
Would it be the whole team at once?
Would it be individuals?
And how did you balance that against deadline pressure?
other studios with shorter times. So the answer is pretty
simple. We start at 4 o'clock and everybody plays. Actually we
used to enforce that everyone plays. It used to be required.
But when the team got really big,
we started to go, well, okay, maybe we don't have to have everyone play,
but you need to play every so often, and special cases were made.
So, we, and we would, the whole team would play from four to whenever the day was over,
and oftentimes people would stay and play until, you know, seven or whatever,
but they were just playing the game.
The way we enforced it was because the producer, it was his idea.
Like, the producer was like, we're going to do this.
Because he was, he was, he was, he had been on teams in the past
where the, where, where the team hadn't played their own game
and he didn't like the results.
And so he was like, we're going to do this.
And so it was just in force. He just paid the cost.
Steph just said, we're just going to pay that cost
because it's part of my dev budget
is having my team know what game they're making.
And so when you've got the producer
and the creative director and the technical director
and the art director all going,
this is what we're going to do everybody,
it's four o'clock, put your pencils down and start playing,
it's a lot easier, right?
It's harder if you've got people who disagree,
but in our case, that wasn't the case.
Thank you.
It was lucky, we were really lucky, yeah.
Thank you for the great talk.
My question is kind of more related
to the pitching part of it.
Yeah.
It's a two-part question.
Did you, when you thought your idea was a brilliant idea.
I never thought that.
Oh, well.
I was terrified I would die and never have it out of my body.
That was the only thing that I was worried about.
Oh.
Well, the question was kind of, were you ever afraid that somebody who heard your idea was
going to just take it and run with it?
Oh yeah.
And also, you know, what's the reality of that?
You're actually pitching and then you're like, they're going to steal my idea, but instead
they're like, no.
Great question.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, okay.
So.
I don't think you're going to like the answer. So here we go. Was I afraid that people would
steal my ideas? I spent ten years attending E3 going, please not this year. Please, I'm almost
there. Please, please don't be, this is not the year. Please, no. The year before we announced,
I was at the Xbox, the Microsoft show, right? You know what the first game was?
at the Xbox show that year?
Rise, son of Rome.
I thought, oh my god, that was a dark five minutes right there, right?
Like, oh no!
No, it was terrifying. I was absolutely terrified that someone would get there.
But the thing is, you don't own your designs.
Design is not copyrightable. It's just an idea. It's a form, right?
You don't own it.
And I, what I wanted to do was I had this idea about how to get melee combat into video games
and I actually didn't care how it got there.
If somebody else had the opportunity to build it, great!
Because I wanted to play the game, right?
That was my goal.
So I told everyone, and of course I was afraid
I wouldn't have a chance to make it, of course I was.
But I had to just trust that if I was the right guy
to do it, if I was the best choice to lead that project,
that it would happen, right?
For 10 years.
And so I took a gamble and I told everyone I could ever tell I told everyone who would listen right?
I think all my friends got sick of it. They're like yeah, we know you want to make a melee game
We know like we get it
Right
My friends here.
So the answer is you can't own it, you can't protect yourself, not with design.
Art is copyrightable, right?
And, you know, the implementation, the engines, I mean, the code,
you own the code that you write, right?
But design is ephemeral, it's ideas, right?
And that, you know, you can disagree whether or not,
like you can agree or disagree if that's a good thing.
It is the state of the world right now.
So...
Yeah, it can happen. It sucks when it gets stolen. It's a horrible thing. In this case, I would
happily have played someone else's melee game that used this system. Would have been great.
All right. Thank you.
Yeah.
Hey, so first off, when I'm not working, I'm main Lawbringer.
Hey, Lawbringer.
Be mindful.
I play Warden.
Okay. So long as you're not a warlord, I'm okay. No, so you
touched on this earlier with how For Honor being a relative, I
mean, it's a unique gameplay style. So from when you're
trying to pitch that externally to potential players, I mean, do
you try to make the sale entirely based off of
the feeling of the game since you can't articulate it through
oh it's like dark souls plus XYZ. So the way that we did that
actually we knew from the beginning that you had to play
this game to understand it. To really get what the appeal was
you needed to play it. But again you pick up the poster or you
pick up the box in the store or you download it you're not
playing it. So it's a problem. How do we overcome that? That's
what the knights and the vikings and the samurai are for.
Those three factions are the portal into the game.
That's the blue door, right, of magic,
that we were like, hey, Night Viking Samurai,
come on in, you can be a warrior.
It's a pretty good pitch, right?
So that was the lure, right?
We're like, come on in.
That's the thing that we're playing.
And then when they step through the door,
the very first thing we do is we hand them a controller.
Right?
Now play it!
and they're, oh, hey, this is cool.
And it's a surprise.
But normally people like it, right?
And so it works out.
That was why we announced 2 and 1 half years before we started.
We had two E3s.
The first one was our multiplayer one.
And we had a 4v4 demo on the floor, running on PS4.
We had 1,000 people come to the booth.
And then we did the same thing at Gamescom.
And we did the same thing on the next year.
And the whole PR and marketing push
has been about play the game.
So that when the game came out.
If you picked up the box in the store and went,
nice versus Viking versus Samurai, that's weird.
Is this cool, hardcore friend?
Hardcore friend would go, yeah.
Or, you know, nah, stupid.
I mean, who knows?
But they would have an opinion, right?
Because we knew that's how the word would get out at first.
And then once you tried it, it would be okay.
That's why we had a big open beta.
We had five and a half million players in our open beta.
Amazing.
or like six, anyway, lots, many.
So that's how we did it.
Yeah, so basically in that case,
rather than try and get bogged down in
No, the details.
Nitty gritty, it's just like,
no, no, no, just bypass the question entirely.
Build a portal.
Build a portal of invitation.
Right, what's the fantasy?
Warrior fantasy.
Hey, so you were talking about these business cases and you were showing all these different
games.
You also mentioned that it took about five years to develop this game.
So as you guys were developing this game, many other games come out.
So looking at all these other games, do they encourage or discourage any of the creative
decisions that you take while in development?
What we were doing was so new. We learned early on with
for honor, I think we have time for just two more questions.
What we learned was that we
Stuff that worked really well in other games, if we tried to reproduce it in our game,
there was a 50-50 chance it would fall on its face.
Because the base assumptions of the gameplay was so different in what we were doing,
we had to kind of throw out a lot of our expectations about what would work and what wouldn't.
So we learned to get really careful.
about where we were drawing our inspirations from
because it led to wasting a bunch of time.
And we didn't have much time to waste.
So we of course were playing everything all along the way,
but what we were doing was so different
that it was hard for us to draw
direct inspiration from other people.
We have two more.
Thank you.
Hello sir.
Oh, are we done?
Oh, we're done, okay, so we're done.
Thank you very much for your time.
Yay!
Good one.