Hello guys, thanks for coming out.
So yeah, this talk is called Hitman Levels of Social Spaces,
the Social Anthropology of Level Design.
My name is Mette and I'm from IO Interactive.
Oh, and I've also been told to just ask you to put your phones on silence.
Just in case.
So this talk is divided into three parts.
The first is the context.
I just want to tell you just a little bit about me and
IO, what Hitman is, in case you haven't played.
What it means to be a level designer at IO Interactive.
Then I want to tell you the story.
So this is pretty much about how I,
when I started IOWN, we launched HITMAN 2016
and how that went down.
I want to talk about a specific level
that was super popular and a level
that is super close to my heart as well.
And then I want to introduce you
to the concept of social spaces.
And then we have the learnings.
I want to tell you about how we used social spaces to look at all the levels and compare
them in Hitman 1 and what that meant for us going into creating Hitman 2.
All right, so this is me some years ago.
I just got my first computer.
I was sitting in an exciting day
and I got to paint the walls of my room as well.
It's a jungle theme in case you can't see it.
So I work at I-O, which is right there.
That's Denmark in case you don't know.
Denmark, we made Lego.
That's us, so you're welcome.
Then there was an incident with a giraffe a few years ago.
I don't know if you remember.
We killed a giraffe and showed it to a bunch of kids.
It was awful.
But anyways, in case, maybe now you remember us.
And we have a queen.
It's a monarchy.
It's very weird.
She doesn't really decide much,
but she's pretty cool, actually.
And we make Hitman, very proud of Hitman.
So what I'll be talking about is Hitman
that we call internally Hitman 2016.
And I'm going to talk about Hitman 2.
So what's special about these two particular installments
of the series?
That's a quite old series.
The first Hitman was in 2000.
But here's where we really defined the game in a way.
Like we went back to the concepts of blood money,
like where we make these deadly sandboxes as we call them.
We went back to a different recipe, a different design
mantra.
We wanted to talk about freedom of approach and creativity,
really giving the player the chance
to design how they want to play the game
and do their own approach.
And of course, that meant a lot for the level design as well.
So level design at IAO.
The reason why I have this slide,
because I know a lot of you probably know
what level design is,
is because I heard that it's a little bit different at IAO
and I assume it's different everywhere.
It seems like such a broad field.
So I thought I would just want to try and explain
what is it actually we do at IAO.
So we think.
Design is, of course, as you know,
about coming up with different approaches, like ideas,
and solving different problems.
And the level designer is quite central in just coming up
with stuff for the levels.
We're often being asked to pitch the levels, pitch targets,
locations, anything.
We're a really central part of the early process of this.
And preferably, we should try and do
something a little bit different, little creative,
little stuff, right?
Then we're part of the layout process of course and this is where we work very closely with environment artists our artistic counterpart
the ones who knows how things should actually look and
How it looks realistic
Yeah, and yeah, it's an important process
that we try and keep outside the editor.
We do a lot of paper prototypes
and a lot of different markups, layouts,
to see how it feels.
And I will say, when we do it for Hitman levels,
we talk a lot about the different activities
that we want to have in a level.
So we mark up activities first,
like different disguises and stuff like that,
and then we try to look at how would it actually feel,
like how would you represent it
in a physical way afterwards?
Then we mark up in the editor with gray box, white box,
all that stuff, whatever you call it.
And then the environment artist tells us that's weird.
You wouldn't have that many covers everywhere.
And then we implement pretty much everything.
My producer said when she had to explain what level design means
for other people, or to other people,
she would say it starts and ends with the level designer.
or starts and ends with level design.
We implement pretty much everything
that goes into the game.
We touch everything at some point,
and that's everything from set pieces
that game designers make for us,
and different acts that the animators make for us,
dialogue, everything.
And then we talk.
Meetings and stand-ups, and we constantly, constantly
talk to other people.
The level designer is a product owner at IOM.
So as the main level designer on a project, you own the level.
And you're responsible for making sure
that everything flies and that you talk
to everyone in the team.
And we have an awesome team, really, really talented people.
And then we do janitor work.
I guess this is the same everywhere.
People ask me at the end of a production, what do you do?
I just say I'm a janitor.
I'm a janitor.
Just walk the halls of the levels
and make sure things are still working.
Yes, this is what it looks like when we're in the editor.
And this is just like a small, simple setup.
But the reason I'm showing you this
is because it's a really central part of what we do.
Apart from mocking everything up,
one of the most important things that we do
in a game like Hitman is making life,
creating drama situations, as we call them.
We borrow it a little bit from the world of theater.
We talk about dramas and acts and roles.
And this is just like a simple setup where you just have a guy who's on the phone.
I just want to show you this just for context so you know what it looks like.
All right, so another thing that's super central when we design levels.
is looking at trespass.
Where can you actually go when you start the level?
And this is a situation from Miami in Hitman 2,
it's the first level.
You're at a race event,
and right now I'm trying to get into a backstage area,
but I'm not allowed because it's a big public event
and back here it's like for employees only.
But if I become the mascot of the event, this cool flamingo,
obviously I can go there.
And all of a sudden, I'm allowed.
This is what we call social stealth.
So you try to blend in.
And this is what makes Hitman the best
assassin in the world, in our world,
is that he's willing to do anything to get
wherever he needs to go.
I just want to show you a quick video because I think someone else did a really, really
good job of showing you the different ways that you can infiltrate in our games.
Yeah, and I'm just going to show you this quick video.
All this time with each attempt, each creative assassination and each unique exit, you're
learning.
You're learning the level.
You know that you can get into the mansion by dropping down here or climbing over here
or popping in this window,
or going up from the pier,
or using a keycard,
or blowing up this wall,
or just walking in the front door.
You're learning the schedule of your targets.
You know that Francesca will come down to the lab on her own if the virus is destroyed,
or that Caruso will come to the observatory if the roof is opened up.
you're learning which disguises will let you into which parts of the mansion,
ways to separate the targets from their guards,
where to get keys and key cards, and which exits you can take.
Yes, and I actually recommend that video if you're into Hitman level design.
He's super talented.
So yeah, so that was the context,
me, IO, Hitman, level design rule.
You know everything now, so it's good.
Now I wanna talk about the story,
what actually happened.
Yeah, and talk about this level that did really well.
Okay, so in 2016, sorry for the white screen, we launched.
And what was so special about this launch
was the fact that it was episodic.
It was the first AAA episodic game.
Maybe probably still the only one, I'm not sure.
And I had just started, right?
I was a new designer.
I was an intern at the time.
I was just trying to figure out how do you make a good level
in this crazy game?
Like, how do you actually do that?
And what happened was that we would get a Mesa score
for each level we launched.
And that makes for a super excellent case
for actually trying to find out how do we do it,
what works, what doesn't work.
It's a little awkward for the work environment,
I will say.
At like two tables down,
someone got a different meta-score than you did.
That was really weird.
So I can't recommend it.
But it was super interesting.
And this got me started thinking, okay,
like what worked.
And Sapienza, which was the second level that we shipped,
was where we really seemed to convince at least the reviewers
that this was working out really well.
And it was really everyone that seemed to love this level.
It was our fans, and it was user research.
And I love that level personally as well.
It's this Italian coastal town you just saw.
It was the same one in the clip before.
And it was actually just awesome to go and work in that level because it was like sunny and awesome
So I just feel like I was on vacation when I was working on it was really strange
But yeah, I tried to sort of dive into you know, what makes this cool because it's it was it's you know
The weather is nice. It's a nice place. It's beautiful to look at this all these things
The village is, like you have this big villa in the middle
and then you have like this village that's surrounding it.
And the objective is to kill Silvio Caruso
and Francesca de Santis and destroy the virus
that they have in the basement.
But when I looked at the reviews,
everything they seemed to talk about
actually didn't have anything to do with the mission.
Like they were all describing how it felt to just be there.
to just walk around in this beautiful little village
that had all these little stories and these weird characters
and these nice little places to visit.
So I love the ice cream guy.
He's going to figure it out.
So my question became, instead of like,
how do you make an awesome level,
I decided to dive into something a little bit different.
I wanted to find out how do you design everyday life,
and how do you design believable everyday life?
Because that really seemed to be what people were describing.
So I looked at my level design toolbox,
and I had all these cool concepts and terminology
to describe the gameplay elements of it,
like how do you make nice trespass and send trees
and blah, blah, blah.
But I didn't actually have anything
that could help me solve this problem
or answer this question.
So I went back to the books.
I had one semester of social anthropology in university,
and some of this stuff just seemed to click for me
when I started to think of it in that way instead.
So I went back to Pierre Bajeur and Erving Goffman.
who are specialists within sociology,
and Evan Goffman is also from the field of anthropology.
And they describe some pretty cool things.
Pierre Bojo, he talks about social capital.
He also coined the term social space.
And his idea is basically that...
that we are all in this social marketplace exchanging capital.
And if you do one thing in one social group,
that's going to get you in, in a way, right?
Like, for instance, if I buy a fur coat in one social group,
that's going to make me look super cool.
In another one, they're going to hate me for it.
So you have to choose wisely as you're navigating
this social marketplace.
And Evan Goffman, he talks about front stage, back stage,
which I think is one of the most applicable things also
to Hitman.
So that's the idea that we have different personas depending
on where we are and what we're doing.
So when I'm standing here talking to you,
I'm front stage meta, but when I'm
crying in the bathroom afterwards,
I'm back stage meta.
So.
And I think this is really interesting when you start just looking at spaces.
What are the rules of spaces in general?
When you're in a job interview, it's a super tense situation.
The space has kind of been laid out for you.
It's going to be four chairs.
You're not allowed to sit in those.
It's going to be a table between you, and you're
going to sit in that one chair being judged by the other.
That is the setup of that room.
And you just know what that's going to be like.
It's going to be uncomfortable.
And it's designed to be uncomfortable, I think, in a way.
And the square, I think these are really interesting
because they don't have rules in a way.
Like, it's, they have them, but they're very vague.
There's no owner of it.
There's like not, like that one person
who's gonna be like, you know, put those pants back on.
You know, it's a lot more,
a lot of different spaces can meet in a space like this,
and a lot of different people,
and it can change depending on who's there.
a sports event.
You know, it's that, you know,
you can almost do anything in a sports event
as long as you're just, you know,
voting for the right team and doing it at the right time.
And I think this really applies to games as well.
When we design these spaces, and that could be any game,
it doesn't have to be Hitman,
we're designing rules of behavior,
and we're designing something that's going to tap
into your knowledge of how should I be in this space.
And it's very subtle.
Like, people walk into these spaces and they don't go like,
oh, now I'm in a church, I'm gonna be like this.
No, they just do it without.
without thinking about it.
And that's very, very powerful, I think.
OK, so I tried to.
take these concepts and make it applicable to Hitman levels.
So I divided it into two different categories,
so public-private.
Private just being anything that's trespass.
Public is anything that's available to you
when you start playing the game.
And then I defined it a little bit further than that.
I'm just going to go through all six of them,
just so you know, and give you examples.
So the first one is a public space.
This is the square. It's the park. It's like the space where you feel like you can kind of do anything and you won't be judged
There's going to be no expectations towards you
This is where the player can just like
Relax, wait, take their time
You know look in their inventory and not feel like an idiot
And these are just really great spots to just let the player breathe. They're great for starting locations
Then the next one is the public purpose space
and this is where we just ramp it up just a little bit.
Like there's still no one who owns the space necessarily,
but you feel like you should be doing
maybe a specific activity when you're here.
Like this, like a back alley, it could be a cul-de-sac,
it could be like a marketplace,
anything where you kind of,
you feel like you should have a purpose when you're here.
And these are great spaces for just like creating life
and flow in the level.
And we have the public rules space,
this is one of my favorite spaces.
So these are the spaces that are, again,
still available to you from the start,
but they have super strong social rules.
Like this is where you know that you should behave
in a very specific way, like the church or an ice cream shop.
And they're great for role playing, because they,
you know, as you walk in, the player knows,
like, this is the way I should behave,
but I can also go against it and break,
you know, break the rules, act like an idiot.
And that's fun too.
And they're really, really good for us
when we have to communicate trespass rules.
Because often when you have a super powerful rule space,
then the player will just know, OK, I'm not allowed
behind that door into the priest's private room.
Of course I'm not allowed there.
And I know there's going to be a priest.
I know there's going to be a choir boy.
I know all this stuff.
I don't have to tell the player anything.
It's awesome.
It's ripe for the picking.
Then we have the private space, kind of like the first public space.
It's very vague.
It's just, this is just trespass.
It's not necessarily going to be a lot of people or someone who owns the space or
any special activities.
But these are really, really important too.
Really important because these give you little breathers.
So you need to make sure that they're there as well.
They're represented as well.
You don't want to cram it with too much stuff.
Private professional.
Yeah, so these are like the most important for us
when we design spaces,
because this is where we can just,
there's gonna be specific rules.
You're probably not gonna be allowed there when you start,
but the player can easily figure out who's allowed here.
Like the kitchen,
the kitchen is like one of our favorite rooms in Hitman,
because...
So many things can go wrong in a kitchen.
It's a nice place for accidents.
And you can find poison there and all that stuff.
They're nice.
But they're really good for social still.
They're good for role-playing.
Because again, you can just walk in and you know,
I'm going to be a chef.
I'm going to stand here and chop some onions.
No one's going to notice me.
Yeah.
And then the private personal space.
So this is the reward for the player.
Like, we don't have a lot of these and we shouldn't.
They're like these little gems in the level.
This is where you,
where we tell you who the target is through the environment.
This is really where you feel like,
whoa, okay, I've gotten super close to the target now.
I'm not allowed to be here.
There's so much stuff here that's gonna tell me
how to manipulate them or...
or take them out.
And these are just, yeah,
great for stealth, social stealth, and role-playing.
But you shouldn't have too many of these.
They need to feel special.
Okay, so I tried applying all of these
and tried to map it out on Sapien
so to try and see is there anything
that stands out from doing this.
And one of the things that struck me,
was the fact that the public area is just enormous in this level.
Square meter wise, it's not half,
because the mansion has many different storages,
and you have the whole cave and all that stuff,
and as you get into the church, there's more stuff.
But it's an enormous area,
and it really allows the player to get all the way around the mansion,
which we coined the fortress,
because we have lots of these fortresses in our levels.
and you have a chance to just traverse
and you have a chance to just see,
well, how do I want to get in?
I really have a chance to just find all of these
different opportunities to either infiltrate our fortress
or try to pull out our targets.
Yes, so now you know.
about all this stuff, you're experts.
And now we can talk about the learnings
of where I just want to compare it
to the other levels in Hitman 1
and just talk about what did we decide to do for Hitman 2.
So I did this on all of them.
Took a while.
Looks simple, but it took a while.
To try and see what can we learn from this.
And there's tons of little things.
I'm not gonna go too much into details,
but I am gonna talk about two levels
that are really sticking out.
One of them, Sapienza, the other one
is Colorado down here in the corner.
So what is of course super obvious as you look at it
is the fact that Colorado is only trespass.
When you start the level, you're trespassing.
It's a hostile environment.
You're not allowed to be here.
Good luck.
And I just want to say first of all,
I think this is an awesome level,
but it did get a lot of critique
and it got a lot lower meta score than Sapienza did.
Meta scores are not everything,
I'm really not trying to say that,
you should always be critical,
but I think it's interesting to see what happens
when you take away half of our tools
in making a Hitman level.
Yeah, this is basically what we're doing.
We're only using half of the palette.
And the way that this looks from the top
is actually quite representative of how
it feels when you're playing it.
Everything is kind of, it's very hard
to define the different areas.
It's sort of murky.
Everything is soldiers.
It's this orchard that they've taken over.
And it's really hard to figure out, OK,
these soldiers are allowed here, but they're not
allowed over here.
But in Sapienza, the ice cream guy is allowed over here,
and the priest is allowed over here.
So it's a different metaphor that we're using.
It's very hard to tell apart.
OK, so I'm just going to go through the findings,
just so you know where we are.
It was four.
big things that we felt like were worthwhile highlighting.
So public spaces are just very useful for us
because it just represents the initial agency of the player.
It shows you where the player can actually go
when they play the level, just when they start.
And they have a chance to just get an overview,
figure out what they want to do.
The public rules space are just they're just so powerful
When playing into player expectations and and we we enjoy
When our expectations are being fulfilled, it just feels nice. It's like oh, it's an ice cream shop
I wonder what's oh, it's there was ice in here. Like, you know, it's it feels nice
You're kind of like I already know what I'm doing
The private personal spaces are just so rewarding
because they create this backstage experience
that Evan Goffman is talking about, right?
Where you feel like I'm onto them now.
They're super expensive to make
because it's just so many special unique assets
and all that stuff, but they're worth it.
They're really, really worth it.
Yeah, and by using the whole palette,
it's just way easier for us to just create interesting levels
and where players can figure out what to do
and how the whole thing ties together.
It feels more believable and, yeah, and more rich.
So we turned this into four objectives.
We wanted to create large and meaningful public spaces.
We wanted to create rural spaces that play with the player
expectations.
We want to create these rewarding personal spaces.
I want to use the whole social space palette.
And I think we did that.
We've all got barcodes on the back of our heads.
Most people just never notice.
I know...
what it's like to have everything taken from you.
It's a dangerous thing...
having a conscience.
Why are you doing this?
I like to think no one's untouchable.
Yes.
OK.
So I just want to take you through what
Hitman 2 looks like now.
So this is Miami, this is the first level of Hitman 2.
It's an innovation race,
and you're here to eliminate the CEO of Kronstadt,
who is in that big building on the top,
which we call the Expo building,
the Kronstadt Expo building,
and his daughter, Sarah Knox, who's a race driver.
She's driving in her car, and at a point,
she's gonna sort of roam around in these public areas.
So I did the same thing to just try and see what it looks like.
And it's okay if you don't go like, oh, okay, and instantly you have all the information.
I just want to show you, this is the public space.
And I really feel like we took all these findings and I really think we applied them in a really
good way.
really good way.
And even though you can go this far right when you start,
it doesn't mean that it's an easy level.
I don't know if any of you have played it,
but there's still a lot of work to do.
And I think it's just really enjoyable
that you can get this far
and basically get all the way around our fortress
to get an idea of how the whole level is shaped out.
So I'm just gonna show you some pictures
of our large and meaningful spaces.
What I feel we created.
Yeah, this is also from Miami.
This is Mumbai.
Also an enormous level.
I think it must be the biggest level we've ever made.
And almost like so much of it is public.
You have these big two fortresses on either side
and everything else apart from a few areas is just public.
You can get almost everywhere to just.
Get an idea.
Santa Fortuna, this is kind of our Colombian Sapienza.
It's also, it's an amazing level with this,
this drug cartel mansion in the middle
and you have like jungle you can explore
and you have this whole fishing village.
Wilton Creek, the suburbia level in Vermont.
Yeah, and as long as you don't trespass
on people's like property, then you can just,
you can just keep.
Traversing, our social spaces, I think we, yeah.
There's some really interesting ones in season two.
We have the stands where you can watch the rays.
There's a pretty cool moment in the barbershop.
I don't want to kill anything.
Whoops, Freudian slip.
I don't want to reveal anything.
Yeah.
Yeah, the bar in Santa Fe Tuna, the barbecue.
Of course, you need a barbecue when you're in suburbia,
right?
I wonder what's going to happen here.
Oh, and this is, I think this is a cool example.
I love scale.
So I talked a lot about sort of using everyday life experiences
for creating real spaces.
Obviously, you don't always have to do that.
You can also, like, we have all these expectations based
on movies and fiction.
So here we're going a little bit with an ice white shot
and all that stuff.
Yeah, in our personal spaces, I think we,
yeah, there's some really,
I feel like I'm spoiling a lot right now
by showing you these.
It feels different when you're there,
so I think you should go try them out.
Our slum queen in Mumbai.
She's taken over this huge train yard.
It's a super cool location.
And where we have our CEO of Kronstadt.
Yes, okay, so I just want to do a little quick reflection
on what happened when we did this.
Obviously, someone made Sapienza before I
started drawing colors on it.
Someone did all this stuff without having
these social spaces being so formalized.
So this was just an exercise of formalizing knowledge
that was already in the company.
It just wasn't accessible to me as a new designer.
So by doing this, you help new people get into it faster.
And we use this analysis also for our embedded teams in Sumo.
And yeah, just for new people joining the company.
It helped us develop a terminology
and words started popping up
that had nothing to do with this thing.
I've used some of them already.
We have the fortress.
The dweller is a target that lives in a fortress
and won't come out, so you have to go in and get them.
Then we have a roamer, which is a target
that's gonna roam around in the public spaces.
And this, like, we're forcing the player
to try different approaches.
If they got super good at infiltrating,
well, maybe you have to think about
how you're gonna do it when they're out and about,
but you can't do anything, right?
Because they're in public.
And the snail house, it's like an idea
of how we create shapes, like general level shapes.
And we found out that the snail house shape
is just super awesome for making Hitman levels.
Yeah.
And then it just got us talking.
we started like, you know, we actually started reflecting
on what is it actually we do.
And I think that was just really, really valuable.
So all this in mind, I just, yeah, I want to promote this.
I think you should try it out.
It doesn't have to be a social approach.
It can be whatever you think could be interesting
and try and apply it to your game and see what happens.
Yes, that's it.
Thank you.
All right, I guess we have lots of time for questions.
I don't know.
Do you have any questions?
Not sure how this goes on.
Yeah, oh, I think there's a mic up there
if you want to go to the mic.
Sorry, I was supposed to say that.
Do you want to start?
Yeah, because you used larger public spaces in Hitman 2, did you notice during playtesting
that people explored more options within the level sooner because they started in a more
safe and low stress environment?
Yes.
Yes, it could also be overwhelming.
Because I was saying that we had a new problem
all of a sudden that we hadn't thought of.
It was a little bit overwhelming for players.
So we had to find ways to kind of...
quickly give them something they could go with,
and then say, okay, for the more seasoned players,
we're not gonna run over to that guy
with the exclamation mark over his head.
They can just keep going and keep discovering cool stuff.
But we had a new challenge all of a sudden, yeah.
All right, thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
I'm wondering if you could elaborate on the snail house
bullet point.
Is that where the layers begin to, I saw in Sapienza,
goes in a half circle of sorts.
Yes.
Yeah, I think it's easier for people to navigate in them.
When we did this analysis, Bjarne from the company,
who's also a level designer, he joined in
and we started looking at season two.
And he realized at a point that our levels in Hitman 1
was either like, either they were like flat
or they were like horizontal.
Like we have like Paris as horizontal
and we have Bangkok as horizontal.
And then we have these other shapes
where it seems to be a little bit askew
and it helps players navigate.
It's easy to figure out where you are basically.
And there's also something about that we create a path, right, of infiltration,
and then we allow you to kind of...
We talk a lot about Swiss cheese at IO as well,
that you constantly need to have a way out.
We hate dead ends.
Dead ends is forbidden.
So I guess it's the same in other games as well.
So yeah, so it's basically about...
giving you a path, but allowing you to kind of learn
these little other ways in,
and then the other fortress at the end, right?
So it also depends on what kind of level you're making,
but we will often have a fortress in our levels.
Did that answer everything?
Yeah, totally.
Okay, cool.
Yeah?
Yeah.
So it appears that the level designs are very much geared
towards the actual primary targets.
Was there any ahead of time consideration
for the elusive targets or kind of escalation missions
where targets are all over the place?
Yeah, yes.
So when we're designing these, that's a really good question.
When we're designing these levels,
we're constantly trying to keep in mind
that these are supposed to keep on living.
right, that we have lots of content
that we want to keep adding.
So yes, definitely, that goes into it.
And often, if we have an idea for something,
where we go, oh, this doesn't really fit here,
but maybe we can use this in the future for an elusive
or for a bonus mission or something like that.
Yeah, we try to keep that in mind.
There's lots of stuff you have to design at the same time.
And sometimes it feels completely impossible,
but it's a...
But creating these huge levels like Mumbai,
where you just have tons of real estate,
like you just have a lot of slum and lots of places.
And yeah, definitely, we try to do that.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Yes.
Hi.
So I know that your goal is to make
these realistic environments to portray everyday life.
And a lot of the levels are based on
actual real life cities and places.
How strict are you with
trying to portray that city exactly how it is versus adding in fictional areas or fictional events, things like that?
Yes, that's a really good question. I think I'm actually supposed to repeat the questions.
So this is about how detailed do we go in recreating levels and trying to make them real.
We, I think we have like this mantra
that we're not trying to create real levels,
we're trying to create believable levels.
And I think that's very important for this also to be fun
because it's also a pretty, you know,
It's basically a hitman game, right?
You don't want to go too real, because then it's not fun anymore.
And then we want to keep that sort of stylized aspect on most things.
We try to just take a lot of inspiration from these places.
But like a level like Sapienza, there is a town that looks a lot like Sapienza.
I can't remember what it's called.
But you can go visit that place.
And some of it at IO actually have.
So I mean, we draw inspiration from it.
And we go visit the places, like for Hitman 2,
people actually went to these places to kind of get that feel.
How does a slum in Mumbai actually feel?
And took tons of pictures and stuff.
But we have to make our own version of it, of course.
Did that answer the question?
Yes, thank you.
Good.
Hello.
Oh, sorry.
Are we doing the back and forth thing?
I don't know who came first.
By all means.
Okay, you go.
Okay, yeah, thank you for the talk.
Just had a question on sort of streaming in Norway
that you actually put your levels together at IO
because the levels are so dense.
Is that something that happens automatically
or like when you're indoors,
you're kind of chunking out big parts of outside
or have you got big level streaming volumes
around the whole area or?
What do you mean exactly?
Sorry, just a...
Level streaming.
Does it all happen automatically or are you turning off big sections of the world?
No, everything is just... I'm actually not completely sure.
Do you mean for the player and not when we're working in the editor, I'm assuming?
Well, yeah, sort of the development part of it, actually.
So are the level designers setting down level streaming volumes
or do you just make the levels and that's that?
I'm a little bit unsure what you mean,
like as in like when we design them from the get-go,
like how we, if we design everything at the same time,
or if we like go like from this area and then out,
or do you mean?
Just the technical side of it,
so if you're inside a building.
Ah, okay, like that.
It's outside unloaded?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So we divide things into rooms, that's what we call it.
Sure.
Yeah, sorry, it's just the terminology.
Yes, so everything is made in rooms, and then we have gates between those rooms, right?
So we try to not show as much as possible.
And then for some of these levels, there was a huge limit.
And for instance, in Miami, right,
you can't go and see the whole level at the same time.
We try to make sure that we put things in the middle,
and we divide it, and make sure you
have these super nice vistas, but we can't show you
everything at the same time.
So yeah, that's a big part of it,
but it's something that sort of happens
as you're designing it.
And we have people in the team that
are worried about that stuff super early,
and like, oh, this is way too much.
We have to just drill back.
OK, thank you.
Hello.
Oh, sorry.
Sorry, I'm completely forgetting this guy.
Sorry.
Over here.
Great talk, by the way.
Thank you.
So I'm curious if during the development process
you categorized players based on their play styles.
Yes.
And based on that, how did you balance out the opportunities
that you designed?
Yes.
That's an excellent question.
So this is about how we design for different play styles.
Well, we need a sneak path always, right?
We need to make sure that you can,
we need to make sure you can do it suit only
in Silent Assassin and all these things.
Like we need to make sure that that's doable
when we make them.
And when we do like social stealth,
there are different types of players.
Like we have the center stage social stealth,
like Helmut Kruger in Paris.
I don't know if you played,
but like where you're basically in the spotlight,
you're the main character, so like walking out there.
And you know, if you're a real hit man,
you'll be going, maybe that's not the place you wanna be.
Like everyone can kind of see you, but.
But it's awesome to have those experiences,
and it makes you feel like you really cheated everyone.
They think I'm actually the main attraction of this thing.
So we try to do that, and we try to do these more like,
you're doing social stealth, but you're more like sneaking.
You're the janitor.
we make sure that you have sniping opportunities
and all this stuff.
Yeah, we try to design these different paths,
but players can just, like, they find a way.
Like, you know, sometimes you just go, they did what?
You know, like, how is that even possible?
So I'm not, there's some players who are like,
we're not too worried, they're gonna find a way.
They always do.
So, but yeah, yes, we try.
as much as we can.
Sorry, then back here.
So it sounds like a super intuitive
and really useful rule set, or philosophy rather,
and I'm a big fan of rules for making levels,
it makes life a lot more simple, but
is there a danger that it becomes potentially formulaic?
Or like, can you break those, your own rules?
Yes.
Can you disrupt the system that you've basically established now?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Yes.
That's a simple answer.
Because you're saying, like, Colorado.
You should.
Yeah, true.
Yeah, and I want to say, these aren't rules for how, like,
we may want to make another Colorado.
Yeah, that's what I was going to say.
Right, because I think Colorado had
some super interesting things.
And I think we just learned so much in doing this
that we know the pitfalls.
So we can do another Colorado now
and make sure that the players
have those same opportunities.
So definitely, yeah, yeah.
I don't think this should stop anyone.
And as was also said before,
like did any issues come with actually following these rules?
And they did, right?
Like we did this and we're like, oh, okay, right.
We need to make sure that they're not overwhelmed
by public space, right?
So yes, definitely, yeah.
It's cool.
Hi, I was kind of curious if there were any issues regarding player retention or hidden
challenges specifically regarding the proportionality of the particular zones, especially regarding
like the public zones, like if players would get less engaged if they were just walking
around too much without any necessary challenges.
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
I think it's like, again, you need to make sure it's varied.
So I think the reason why big public spaces work
is because they're varied, that they change.
If it was just the same, same, same stuff,
like if it was just a huge park
and there's two mansions on either side,
that would be super boring, right?
So I think it's about keeping the player engaged.
And I think it's just what we learned
was that you can keep the player engaged
without introducing trespassing.
that part of their brain is still going.
Like, what should I do here?
Who's allowed here?
Who are these people?
What's going on?
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
I think so.
Yeah.
Hello, and thank you for the talk.
So in a previous talk, you guys spoke
about how you went through the process of creating
a tutorial for the stages, and how difficult it
was for the players to figure out what all the actions
in the stage are.
Now, before you spoke about the Swiss cheese approach
to getting yourself in trouble, but being able to come out
of it.
Yeah.
relatively easily.
So, could you tell us a little bit about how you
modulate the player motivation to fail
and think of something else to try again
and keep going through that process,
even though there's very hard stops in those paths?
That's an excellent question.
So it's about how
when you do trial and error in the level,
how do you make sure that the player keeps,
can get out of trouble and can keep going basically, right?
Yeah, I mean, this is kind of a little bit more
over in the game design department,
because this is about systems, right?
When do we cool down the level and say,
okay, everyone's forgotten that guy got an ax in his head,
we're fine now, you know, back to work.
And that can get a little weird.
But we try, like I mentioned,
like having lots of these,
making sure that you have these safe spaces.
Like making sure you have spaces that have,
that are not filled with rules and expectations or NPCs.
Making sure you have places that are just like hallways
with not that many people or.
So you can get away and sort of feel like you're going from one social context
and moving away from it and maybe getting into an entirely new one
because then it's okay that they don't know about X, this guy.
So, you know, I think in the level design that's what we can do, but I think it's...
there's no perfect, like there's no like,
this is the way to do it.
And I think it's something that we keep,
like we need to keep getting better at,
because I think it's a really important thing.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, with the addition of multiplayer in Hitman 2,
how does that affect how you design the levels with the public spaces?
So you're thinking ghost mode?
Yeah, ghost.
Ghost mode, yeah.
So that's a tricky question.
Because, yeah, that's a really hard question.
I'm not sure I'm the right person to answer that question because I haven't worked on Ghost Mode.
But I would think that it's, okay, so what's really tricky about Ghost World is
that the game tension kind of stays even though you're playing again, right?
So that's like one of the challenges we're facing is that if we do the X
head scenario again, right?
So in big public space with a lot of people and
lockdown has happened, right?
I think that's something that we need that.
especially when we design Ghost Mode,
that we need to be mindful of that it's not,
that the area isn't entirely ruined
because there's so many people who saw you do something bad
and now when you're playing it again.
So yeah, I think it's, you know,
when we design the levels, we need to, of course,
worry about the main missions
and we need to think about elusives and all that stuff.
And now we also have to think about Ghost Mode.
It's a lot.
So.
Yeah, I think it's about that, making sure
that you don't have too large open spaces with a million
people in it, because that's going to feel weird
and go smoke.
Hiya.
Because your level design and locales are so inspired,
are there any settings that you really
want to incorporate into a future Hitman game?
Or do you feel like you've already made your dream level
with one of the previous settings?
Oh, I'm working on my dream level right now,
and I can't talk about it.
So I'm sorry, but yes.
I look forward to playing it.
Cool.
Thank you.
Hi, so my question is about when you create a level which has such a large amount of content,
such a large amount of different things you can do, different things going on, different
things happening, different ways of entering, different missions, there's so much variety
and so much there.
How do you encourage a player to actually explore that as opposed to go down the path
of least resistance and find just quickly how do I get to my target as fast as possible?
Amen.
A second follow-up question to that is,
have you ever thought about,
or I mean, obviously you have,
but what are your thoughts about sort of reusing levels
to sort of encourage getting them to,
or getting a player to discover more about a level
so that way they can actually use more
of what they've previously learned?
Yes.
Okay, so this is a good question.
It's about replay and how do you make people explore
and not just go down the beaten path.
So we have challenges.
I think challenges is an excellent tool for highlighting some of these things that we put in the level that we really hope that someone will see.
But I will say, I like that there are these little pockets that you may not notice until the 10th time you play a level.
Like there's still parts of some levels that I haven't seen and I get surprised when I see it
And I think that's like a really cool experience
but yeah, we have
Challenges the challenge system and we have these opportunities like our quest system where we can take them to some of these cool areas
That they may not necessarily see from the get-go
And the other question was, yeah, making sure,
like, highlighting areas for bonus missions
and elusive targets.
I think it's an excellent opportunity for us to do that.
And I think that kind of answered the first question
in a way.
Yeah, because I think there's like,
if you played some of the bonus missions,
like, for instance, in Sapienza, there's
like three bonus missions in that level.
And each are, like, very different, I feel.
And they highlight other...
like really nice areas of that level.
So yeah, we try to do that as much as possible.
Thank you.
Oh, yeah.
They were first.
His first, sure.
Sure, go ahead.
So polite.
So you had all these great different space terminologies and you worked together with
the environment artists about how they set those up.
But was there any sort of environment or LD make any visual indications as to the different
space types?
So like was there different lighting for the privates there versus the public spaces and
did that continue through different levels?
Right. Oh, it really depends on the level, right?
I mean, we try to use these visual cues
like that could be just having
things that aren't very presentable.
like, you know, like bags of trash or something like that.
It could be like stuff like that,
or here they just put up some chairs for later,
like fold up chairs or things like,
we try to do these little things to make sure
it very quickly feels like,
oh, okay, I'm not allowed to be here.
This is a backstage area or whatever.
And then, like, we had all the different spaces,
and then a lot of the layouts that you showed
had the public spaces sort of intruding on,
or sort of wrapping together with the private spaces.
Is there some sort of, like, percentage
or anything that you followed?
How much public space needed to, like, touch the...
The private space? Yeah.
Well, this is your chance to have the player see your private space, right?
This is where you get to really show them this is where you want to go and this is how you can get there.
So I don't think it's about how much, but I think it's about how clearly you do it
and how you show who's allowed there.
In Hitman, that's a huge part of it, right? The disguises.
So you have a chance to see behind the fence
that it's like chefs walking around there
or whatever, backstage people, right?
So yeah.
For implementing the stuff you talked about
in other games or other types of games,
do you have any ideas or recommendations
for places that
might not fit what most people understand about like the people that work there where it's like
I am seeing someone do something and I want to either become that person or
do what they're doing but I have no idea what they are doing like in
it's hard to think of many examples other than fantasy,
but where we as normal people don't always have the ideas
of what is expected of a person in that area.
Right, right.
So you're thinking like if we go to like more exclusive,
exotic places where you don't know
what are they actually doing?
Like what's their job or whatever?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, that's a challenge.
I think that's a, if that's a question you're asking,
like how we deal with it or, yeah.
So I think it's about, like,
even if you're at this super exclusive weird place,
like a Isle of Skye where it's like,
everything is over the top, right?
And people are wearing robes and stuff like that.
You still have waiters.
You still have kitchens, you still have bathrooms, they need to pee.
You have all these things that's going to be there because they're humans
that you can just play on from there.
Or you use, like I mentioned, examples from movies and other games and fiction
so people can go like, oh, he's a cryogenics guy or whatever.
or detective, you know, it's a,
then you try and play on those stereotypes kind of, yeah.
Yeah, but it is super difficult or you can,
like again, then you have to invent something new,
but then you have to tab into other, you know.
design tricks, like everyone has a different color
or something, and everyone who wears yellow
will do this thing.
Like, it's super difficult when we do that,
when we go out and explore those areas,
but I think it's doable.
It's just making sure it's readable for the player.
Thank you.
How long do we have left?
Are we done?
Four minutes?
Four minutes.
Okay, cool, yeah.
Hi, I have a question actually about the integration of your design and art teams with as richly
detailed environments as you have in Hitman and is how intrinsically linked gameplay and
mission design is to the environments.
How did you guys sort of integrate the work of your environment team and your design team?
How closely did they work together?
We work very closely together.
Very closely, yeah. We spend all our time together.
Yeah.
Like, the level designers and environment artists are buddies.
We're partners in crime.
We try to do everything together and make sure we're aligned.
Have our desks right up against each other and eat together.
smell each other and everything.
It's a...
Right, well it shows.
I think that's super important.
Like, the problem as a level designer,
I think I was always, I want my,
like every, someone from the whole company,
from each team representative,
to just sit around me in a ring.
So I can just like, a writer, an animator,
like, cause you need to talk to all of them,
all the time, all the time.
But the environment artist is your,
is the most important person for you.
All right, thank you.
Hello. I have a question for the design of Hitman.
You have so much possibilities and solutions to the level.
Even the system you can make many actions to solve a single problem.
I was wondering how do you mitigate that as a level designer
as you have your players so much possibility.
Do you do some kind of technique in order to make it intentional?
So how do we decide when the level is done?
You mean like how do we show the player
or as we're designing or what do you mean?
When you're designing, you have a system
and a level that has so many solutions.
Okay, like that, yeah.
Yeah, that's tricky.
I think there's like many different ways of doing it,
of trying to show you how this works.
Like there was one example,
I don't know if it completely answers your question,
but there was one I thought was a little funny
where writing also helped us out a little bit.
There's a place in Paris.
where you walk, like you have,
you can just walk right into the building
and if you walk to the left and this is backstage area
and this is a chef who's like, wants to go in
and the guide is like, listen buddy,
you don't have to keep asking me this question.
You're allowed here and you're allowed all the way up
to the second floor and you can just walk right in.
Like, and I was just listening to that.
I'm like, all right.
Fair enough.
So we do all kinds of little things.
Sometimes it's not that much on the nose,
but it is super hard to communicate.
Like what can you do here?
And as you're saying, there is a system,
there's all these things,
and the minute you knock out someone in front of everyone,
then the AI takes over,
and it's anyone's guess what's gonna happen now, right?
So we're trying to cater for all of it,
and it's a crazy job.
It's so much fun, but it's a crazy job.
Did that answer your question?
Sort of.
OK, we can talk after this.
OK, good.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And you're next.
Yeah.
Hello.
Hi.
So I'd like to ask, because there's
a lot of maps in the game.
So every map's really different.
So how do you guys decide on what kind of map to use?
Do you think about reusable assets?
Or you recreate every single different assets
for different maps?
That depends on a lot of things.
Like we try to make them as different as possible in general
and that's just expensive to do, but we try to do that.
Cause I think it's important that they feel different.
we don't like reusing.
Sometimes you have to, if you're time pressured
or anything like that, or if it's just like,
okay, we don't need a million different toilets.
Like we can maybe reuse a few toilets,
like no one's gonna notice.
Like it can get a little insane once in a while.
But I think it's super important
to make them feel very different.
And we do lots of things to make sure it feels different.
Sound and lighting and all this stuff making sure that the time of day is different and the mood of the level is different
And how they look and how they act and how they talk like this so many aspects to making sure they feel buried
But it but I think it's very very important that they feel different. Yeah. Thank you very much
And oh we're done can I one last question or oh
We're done. Oh, we got to go. Okay. Well good talk after this. Okay. Yeah, cool