Join me, Cole Hicks, composer and sound designer, and Chris Hunt, the creator of Kenshi, as we
discuss the details of crafting audio for a world that doesn't care if your characters
live or die.
Kenshi is a gritty squad-based RPG, but unlike traditional games, and RPGs especially, we
didn't want the music to fulfill the typical role of positively reinforcing player actions.
Rather, Kenshi's oral world feels subdued.
It makes use of silence, and its music almost exists separately from the game.
At GDC17, join us as we discuss the details of not only how we created Kenshi's Oral World,
but how it was implemented in Wwise, and of course, why we made those decisions.
Thanks, and hope to see you there.