Hi, everybody.
My name is Stephen Hottie.
I'm responsible for audio at PolyArc.
This is just a reminder to silence your cell phones
and to fill out your evaluations afterwards.
That's super important to GDC as a whole.
And so rehearsals have been going straight up
to the 30-minute mark, so it's likely
that I'm not going to have time to answer questions afterwards.
But we can hang out in the hall or go get a wrap-up room.
One of the CAs is going to help us with that in a little bit.
So, um, finally, uh, things seem to be sounding pretty good in here, but if your listening
experience is substandard in any way, you can go play MOST at the IGF pavilion. So, uh, Jason
Graves, uh, did a great talk yesterday. Um, it was awesome. His music is incredible if
you've played MOST. So, uh, you should go check it out on the vault. It's sort of a
companion talk to this one.
So, and finally, if you're not familiar with the technical jargon in this talk,
just don't worry about it. This is fundamentally a talk about ideas. It's a talk about finding
the heart of what you're working on and thinking about design before sound. This is about the
perspective that emerges when you've been on one creative path for a really long time.
And then suddenly you're here with a mouse in a new world,
starting over from the beginning.
This is about what makes you a sound designer.
So what makes you a sound designer?
Is it knowledge of plugins that makes you a sound designer?
No, recording engineers know about plugins.
Is it knowledge and use of synthesis?
No, musicians also have this down.
How about Foley performance?
How about system design or implementation or scripting?
The game part is coming into focus,
but it's somehow not enough.
Is it your ability to craft supremely realistic weapon
LODs?
Are we any closer?
The answer to what makes you a sound designer
is in the portion of the name that gets the least attention.
Sound designer.
All that other stuff, plugins, editing, scripting,
it's all craft that you implement
in the service of design.
So unpacking the term designer is a bit of a trick,
so let's zoom out for a second.
If we're doing our jobs well,
player experience is continuous and holistic.
The sum total of the many choices
and details of development wash over the player,
bathing them in a kind of metaphorical light.
Our job as designers is to deeply understand
the light of player experience
through the prism of design intention.
This prism refracts the player's complex,
holistic experience into discrete components
in service of the game's design.
So the application of sound into a game
is the expression of this design intention.
So you might say that compelling sound design
starts with design and ends with sound.
Sound design starts with design and ends with sound.
So before you cut the first sound,
you're thinking about design.
And when you're thinking about design,
you're thinking about player experience.
You're wondering about what impact
you're making on the player at a fundamental human level, which
becomes their reason for playing the game.
But early on, these reasons may not be entirely clear.
And each player has their own reason for playing.
So you must listen carefully for that central design intention
to emerge during development.
So you're still not thinking about sound yet.
You're thinking about human impact.
And while the game is coming together,
there's a circular process where you're
embodying player experience.
What is the game telling you, not just
on a moment-to-moment basis, but after you
put the controller down?
What does this even look like?
As an example, I'll tell you the story of my first player experience with Moss.
The first time I met Quill was in November of 2016.
During my first visit to PolyArk, I played a very early Moss prototype that a few founding members had built over 12 weeks.
So, I put the headset on and I saw a cute mouse, which was pretty cool so far,
and then she looked at me, which was surprisingly compelling,
and then I pushed the joystick to move Quill around and started to sense how this could be a game.
I reached out, grabbed her, and felt her heartbeat through the controller's vibration.
And that's when everything changed.
I caught the first glimpse of what made Moss special.
I felt something like genuine concern for this little VR mouse.
Like I wanted to protect her.
This experience felt wholly unique in all my decades of game playing.
Over the next few days, I wondered,
what would happen if my relationship with Quill
was central to the game's design?
What would it be like for a game to condition players
to feel empathy and a sense of protection for a character?
If we had more games that focus on powerful beings
protecting weaker beings, what would this world be like?
And is there anything this world needs more
than the cultivation of this sense of connection?
A simple mechanic, grabbing Quill with the controller
and feeling haptic vibration, generated
a ton of complex questions.
Tam Armstrong, PolyArc's studio director,
often says, a game is a function of its inputs.
And here, Moss was asking me to reach out
and to bond with another being.
Reduced down to its essence, the human impact
was enabled by one thing, an emotional bond with Quill.
So you see a design intention began to emerge,
but it didn't solidify magically overnight.
These questions continued to persist throughout development.
And three months after I joined PolyArc,
we started showing a new demo to players,
and the results we observed confirm our intuitions.
Sort of hard to gather what's going on here,
but off screen, the player's friends are coaxing her
to continue on with the demo.
But she's content just sitting at the dock, petting Quill.
She's so happy that she wipes tears from her eyes.
Okay, okay, I'm sorry!
So we understood
that the emotional bond with Quill,
the trigger for empathy, protection, and connection,
was what made Moss special to players.
So let's check in.
We understand the game's central design intention,
initiated by our own intuition, and more importantly,
solidified by observing player reactions.
We can use this intention, the focus
on Quill's emotional bond, as the prism I referred to earlier.
If compelling sound design starts with design
and ends with sound, this brings us
to the expression of the game's design using sound.
So how do we support this design intention,
the emotional bond with sound?
First, we must clear the way with comfort.
We all understand intuitively that certain emotions blot out
others, like how it's hard to feel compassion when
you're tired and hungry.
VR is wrestling with its own version of hangry,
which is VR-related discomfort and fatigue.
Poor frame rate, resolution, weight of the headset,
and the disconnection between player body movement and camera
movement are some of the more prominent examples that
induce discomfort in players.
If players are comfortable, we create a space where other, subtler emotions can arise.
If players are agitated, the beauty of the world of Moss recedes.
Players stop caring about Quill, and at its worst, they quit the game because they feel
they are physically unable to continue.
Danny Bulla, Polyarch's design director, often says,
VR is an amplifier.
And what he means by that is that we have to take care
that whatever we put into the amplifier is a clean signal.
Subtle discomforts that may not manifest meaningfully
in console games in VR may cause players
to take the headset off.
Sound can absolutely play a role in contributing
to VR fatigue, both through physical discomfort.
like listening fatigue caused by loud sounds,
and psychological discomfort caused
by intense or grating sound.
A great advantage of the current generation of VR headsets
is that players use headphones, which
allows us to take advantage of actual high dynamic range.
In Moss, the range between the quietest moment
and the loudest moment is somewhere
in the vicinity of 45 loudness units relative full scale,
which means the game can be quiet most of the time
and loud only when it needs to be.
The sounds themselves contain very gentle high frequency
content and are offered with careful use of limiting,
distortion, multiband compression,
and subharmonic generation.
So even if players are wearing a pair of headphones
that hype or exaggerate high end frequencies,
they're still going to have a comfortable listening
experience.
So we covered discomfort related to the physical sensation
of hearing.
However, even sounds that conform to a gentle aesthetic
can produce a grating effect.
During one playtest, players reported fatigue because of howling cave winds during one section
of gameplay.
They mentioned that the low, persistent rumbling frequencies created a sense of claustrophobia
and unease.
To combat this effect, we used Low Frequency Oscillators, or LFOs.
As most of you know, an LFO is a repeating figure that can be used to control or modulate the volume, filtering, or other properties of a sound.
And that by tying the value of sound properties to these moving signals, we can maintain the initial moodiness of the scene, but that feeling diminishes over time as the LFO value changes.
Multiple LFOs set to different rates and amplitudes can sum together to create more variable textures of modulation.
Overlapping LFOs can be used on any ambient bed with discrete layers to increase movement
and to create an undulating mosaic of unpredictable textures, reducing perceived repetition and
providing relief from psychologically intense sound.
So we're on our way to supporting the design of the player's emotional bond with Quill.
Now that the player is listening comfortably, we are free to focus our efforts on the world
that Quill inhabits.
Let's engage design before sound for another moment.
Immersion reinforces the player fantasy
of the virtual reality.
When the virtual reality is sufficiently convincing,
actual reality falls away,
and players have a chance to be along with Quill
in her world.
In Moss, players manipulate objects to help Quill progress.
If these interactions are sufficiently detailed
and responsive, and the weight feels right
in the player's hand,
then it will increase their sense of immersion.
The blue orb here represents the player's hand as tracked by a controller as it reaches
into the world and manipulates objects.
Small, delicate sounds that might not read in conventional games end up carrying a lot of the responsibility for selling this fantasy, like the crackling glue of the binding in this book.
Or the drifting ratchet of the spindle as it glides to rest.
The effect of the player fantasy extends beyond the interaction
and into the realm of environmental ambience.
In reality, much of what we attribute to ambience
is perceived as noise that the brain filters out.
So it's often not enough to take a single nature recording
and use that as the basis for an environment.
To cross over the barrier between the passive, neutral experience of sound and into a realm
where the player actively registers the emotion of the world, we must saturate the listening
environment with story and narrative context.
Here's an example, starting with a few sounds over our logos.
You arrive in a library, delivered from another realm.
A clock ticks slowly in the distance,
and you sense that time works differently here.
You hear the gentle scratch of pen on paper
emanating from the books piled on the tables
and lining the shelves as those stories are emanating,
or as those stories are forming on their blank pages.
Opening the book, it calls to you and you feel a force tunneling through the eons, having
waited and found you at long last.
Here's another example.
The bright forest pulsates with the life of childhood adventure.
A time without worry, possessed only by discovery
in a search for freedom.
Birdsong pours in from every register.
Squirrels chase each other, their claws
scratching the bark, squeaking taunts.
Tree branches creak and groan in the wind.
A beetle's wing clips your ear as it hums by.
And finally, one of my favorite scenes.
It's nighttime now, and the wind whips through the pines.
Unseen creatures rustle and howl in the distance.
You're not supposed to be outside the hut at night,
but the fear of what might happen if you stay
drives you farther and farther away from safety.
So you can see how sound covers mundane things like time of day, weather, biophony, and geophony.
It tells you where you came from, where you are, and where you're going.
But it also triggers less precise phenomena like memory, nostalgia, joy, peace, mystery, and fear.
Quill and the player characters journey together. The experience that forges their bond
is reflected in the emotion embedded in the world of sound.
But the process of getting from room to room is just as important as what the player finds once they're inside.
In theater, there's a problem with changing scenes.
The curtain drops or the audience sees the vague outlines of the set moving around.
They're reminded of where they are.
In a theater, not the world played out on a stage.
The spell is broken.
The video game version of dropping the curtain is loading transitions.
It's easy to miss what's coming up in this next example,
but blanket ambience, or the environmental sound
that does not correspond directly to level geometry,
isn't tied to camera position within a volume.
Rather, each room is assigned ambience metadata,
which is prefetched and positioned around the camera
before the room even loads.
Seamless continuity of sound over hard load transitions creates a feeling in the player of having teleported and arrived,
accompanied by an imprecise feeling of the passage of a small amount of time where Quill travels from one threshold to the next.
So these environmental sounds we just covered, the player interactions we referenced earlier,
and all other in-world sound needs to interact with the geometry of the world in some way.
Reverb is like lighting for sound.
Through subtle shifts in technique,
it can take a simple scene and imbue it with complex emotion.
And like lighting, reverb design is its own rich craft
worthy of attention.
Some reverbs provide a sense of endlessness.
Others provoke claustrophobia.
And so reverb is not purely a functional description
of acoustical space.
MOS uses a little over 20 different reverbs across the span of about 75 rooms,
and each reverb has three layers. A convolution layer, a traditional algorithmic layer,
and an early reflection layer. These were designed in a digital audio workstation,
mixed together, swept with a sine wave, resampled and deconvolved back into the engine,
back into a single impulse response for use in real time in the engine.
So the room we are in may be too reverberant to adequately hear the subtleties in this clip.
However, try to listen to how Quill's sword and voice bounce around each space.
See if you can track not only your perception of the space,
but the emotional load that accompanies this change.
And just so you can calibrate your ear, the first clip is dry, so it doesn't have any reverb,
and the subsequent clips feature reverbs from different environments.
With the player comfortable and immersed, they are free to establish an emotional connection
with Quill.
Let's explore another idea that starts with design and ends with sound.
One of the ways that we connect with each other
is by sharing our perspective or empathizing with each other.
Moss is a self-co-op game where players simultaneously
control a third-person character, Quill,
and operate as a distinct character in the world.
If we only chose sounds that operated
at a scale that reflected the player character's point
of view and focused on reinforcing
the reality of scale, what might this flaming door sound like?
So use your imagination and focus on the reality of scale.
So from Quill's point of view, it sounds like this door might feel a bit larger and more intimidating.
Choosing sounds with more mass and weight doesn't simply add a layer of listener satisfaction.
It superimposes the player's perspective onto Quill's, so players can hear the world through her ears.
You might call this empathetic sound design, her mixed perspective.
The larger sounds also provoke a sense of danger,
elevating the player's protector instinct.
Can you guys see the screen okay?
Okay, cool.
These larger sounds also provoke a sense of danger, elevating the player's protector instinct.
So the player is comfortable and immersed, and has a sense of Quill's experience.
How Quill expresses herself in-game will clearly influence the formation of the player's emotional bond with her.
Should Quill speak a language?
Should she deliver story?
What about sinless gibberish or exertions?
Should she remain completely silent?
How mouse-like should her vocalizations be?
How female or male?
What's the right decision here?
Understanding this problem through the prism of the
player bond can yield a lot of compelling solutions.
But what if we want the player to determine who Quill is or
what she may be thinking?
That starts to narrow our options into the range of content requirements that call for ambiguity.
In this way, the players become equal participants in the construction of her inner life,
and can project onto her their own interpretation of what she may be thinking or feeling.
Having a human perform these vocalizations
also gives us more access to a wider array of expression.
And although relationships between humans and animals
can be deep and complex, relationships between humans
start with an assumption for the shared capacity
to deeply understand each other's life experience.
So we knew we were successful with this fluid approach
when we observed some players giving Quill a unique identity
and interpreting her actions in ways
we couldn't have ever anticipated or planned.
So the player is comfortable and immersed and has a sense of the stakes,
and they can construct an ideal version of Quill in their own minds.
Can you see how each new approach to a problem reinforces the goal of establishing a bond between the player and Quill?
The fluid approach is only part of the picture. Quill is not a total blank slate.
We thought players would enjoy learning Quill's backstory and growing with her over the course of the journey.
The story of Moss serves a few purposes.
It mechanically propels both player and Quill
from room to room.
And it also seeds the gaps between story moments
with emotional resonance that players
can use as the basis for their own construction
of Quill's inner life.
We found that the fluid version of Quill
coexisted comfortably alongside story narration.
So there's a field of established options
to draw from with narrator direction,
like.
curmudgeonly but loving grandpa, or ethereal otherworldly being, or plain-spoken albeit
earnest protagonist, but what about your mom?
If the narrator establishes the world in a warm, safe, inviting way, players would be
inclined to connect with Quill.
We worked with voice actor Morla Gorondona, our narrator,
over the course of several theater-style workshopping
sessions to find a sweet spot somewhere
in between a maternal bedtime story
voice and an omniscient being.
We hoped the maternal style might activate
some familiar feelings like safety, rapt attention,
and wonder.
Luckily, Morla had about six years
of practice in this role, reading to her son each night.
So, starting with design, looking through the prism of the player bond,
approaching each new small problem with this prism,
how would you approach microphone selection?
To support the audible perspective that occurs during bedtime stories,
we chose a large diaphragm microphone, which is probably no surprise.
But the large diaphragm captures the richness of her voice.
As opposed to a shotgun microphone, which has a more hyped and aggressive tone,
we positioned her close enough to the mic to achieve a sense of intimacy
without the player perceiving a two-dimensional, inside-my-head kind of sound.
You'll hear a subtle amount of reverb applied to the voice in some story moments
to place her in the room with the player.
Quill's hands trembled as she showed him the glass.
What is it? she asked.
A look of panic spilled over her uncle's stoic exterior.
Where did you find this? roared Uncle Argus.
Quill had never seen her uncle so shaken.
Hey kid, over here.
I know where your uncle went.
I can show you. You're two-fold now. Very important.
Bring that glass. And your sidekick, too.
We're going to need them.
Quill called out.
Hey, Stardin, wait!
So the stack of techniques used to support our design grows even higher.
What about sandbox sound effects? Because this is a game, after all.
As sound designers, it's likely you're always listening
as an extension of your craft.
You hear a sound that affects you in an interesting way,
and you take note of it and file it away in your brain.
If you're lucky, you have access to a recorder
that you carry with you so you can document these moments.
In the winter of 2012, I decided to document my sister's
pregnancy with her first son, Isaac.
I accompanied her to an ultrasound appointment
where I heard this very sound in real time for the first time.
I was moved powerfully by that sound.
There's something about it, the swishing rush of fluid and pumping valves.
It triggers a protector instinct, one that is crucial to the formation of a bond.
But even though the sonogram technology is relatively new, it reaches deep down into
some evolutionary drive and twists a knob.
When it came time for us to explore Quill's low health indication,
a fundamentally protective game mechanic,
this recording surfaced in my memory.
Unfortunately, as you heard, Isaac's sonogram recording
had room tone, reflections, ambient conversation, and speaker distortion built into it.
But thankfully, you can get just about anything on Amazon.
Like this pocket fetal doppler monitor.
Which...
This one even has a headphone output jack.
So whenever Quill is in trouble and needs your help, you hear this.
This is one example of emotional sound, but it requires you to take something real and
authentic from your life and to give it to the game.
These are really hard opportunities to find, but they do exist.
So let's put it all together.
The player is comfortable.
They are immersed.
They have a sense of the danger Quilla is in and have access to her point of view.
They are co-authors of a deep relationship and are primed for the bond through story.
And the sound effects are sending emotional messages to the player.
The good news is that there are other examples of other choices that support the emotional
bond.
We didn't even talk about music or spatialization techniques or Foley.
When you're making choices, looking through the prism of design intention, these small,
even innocuous details sum together and create a powerful, cohesive player experience.
Compelling sound design starts with design and ends with sound.
If this type of abstract, human-oriented approach to sound feels awkward or weird, I promise
it's worth the discomfort and confusion.
Because it's important to remember that people are giving precious moments from their lives
over to the experiences that we make.
So we have to find ideas worthy of that gift, and to fill them with sound.
Thank you all for listening.
I hope you found this valuable.