I think in game writing circles my official title is The Other Richard.
So today I'm tired to are we good on the Mike there is this
one this one's good and this one's off all right.
So thanks everybody for coming to a dynamic stories for
dynamic games, I always start off and saying split a little
bit of a spoiler warning. People always complain when I
maybe talk about and things of games during talks I don't do
it too badly in this, but if you see a game you're really
intent on not knowing anything about I recommend you cover
your duck your head and cover your ears quickly.
I don't spoil anything that's come out in the last couple years.
Also, I have a lot of references to some other articles in this.
I will be putting the slides up on my website by this time tomorrow.
Let's say that's my deadline.
So you can go grab them off of here if you want to get some of those references
and some other links that I had to cut out for time.
So, it's funny, when I come to GDC, and I swear it's like this alternate reality, where
everyone is talking about narratives and branching and player choices and empowerment and innovative
stuff and to do with stories and games, but I found the world outside of GDC is a little
bit different.
You go back to your development team and like, we should do this cool thing I saw, and they're
like, why would we do that?
Dynamic stories?
That doesn't matter.
It's crazy.
You got to get back in your hole, writer.
So why, you know, so I get this question a lot.
Why do you care about dynamic stories?
Why do that?
Why do you want to have multiple endings?
Why do you want to change the story
based on what the player does?
You know, and for me, literally,
it's why I wanted to get into working on games
and making games,
is I love the idea of setting up situations
where the player,
comes into a situation and has to make difficult choices and then sees the ramifications of those.
So for me it's so innate that I want to tell these stories. So it's tricky to explain it.
And believe me I've heard all the reasons not to do this from all the different disciplines.
So you have reasons not to from programmers. Programs always talk about how incredibly hard
it can be to do interactive storytelling. And they're right. It can be incredibly hard,
if you take it to that sort of extreme. But programmers, you just need to tell them,
look you guys are really smart. You're able to, you know, simulate incredibly complex physics.
You're able to render things that look like the real world.
and you had to make concessions and trade-offs to do that,
and we can do the same thing with any sort of dynamic storytelling.
You know, I also hear from producers,
and usually the answer there is, not surprisingly,
it'll cost too much money.
But that's what producers say about everything you ask them for, right?
It's just like when the artists go and ask for their fancy shader set,
or the combat designers want to do some crazy motion capture suit.
You know, they're shot down by the producers too, but they go back and they fight,
and they say, no, we need this to push the game forward,
and this is what's going to make it great.
We need to get used to fighting, you know, to have dynamic elements in our stories,
if we really want them, just like the other departments do.
But I also hear reasons not to from writers sometimes.
And probably some of the people in this room right now are saying,
well I came to this talk because I know I hate dynamic stories
and we'll see if he can change my mind.
And I think there's a lot of good reasons for that, right?
The history of storytelling, you know, outside of games
is certainly very linear and is used to certain structures that have worked well
and things we've learned over many years of telling stories
to which I say, you're right, those things are true,
those things do work and they have worked in some games.
But I think this is a new medium. We need to try new things.
I know it's a little scary, but I'm hoping it'll be better in the end.
And finally, from designers, the answer I always get there is,
but players only play the game once, so who cares?
And I want to, you know, as an answer to that,
look at the types of games that are the most popular right now out in the world.
you know if you set aside sort of multiplayer games as sort of a separate
entity we can look at
a lot of the other successful games are ones with these big gigantic open worlds
of one kind with tons of things you can do them tons of
dynamic things you can do with the gameplay often still with sort of a
linear story in the middle
uh... but they end up having a lot of dynamic storytelling elements around
that
And these games typically have tons of content to support all of this.
If we look on the other side of the spectrum, though, we'll see for smaller, single-player games,
players have been gravitating towards a different type of style, things that are procedurally generated.
Things like roguelikes or roguelike-likes or roguelites or whatever we're calling them this week.
These present games that provide an infinite variety of challenge to players.
And interestingly, most of them eschew traditional storytelling,
opting just to set the tone and the setting,
and then go from there with Sunless Sea maybe being a notable exception.
So why do players like these games despite their lack of narrative?
Well, players, we have to recognize, have a limited amount of money, right?
They want to buy a game they can really get value out of,
that they can play over and over again, that they can...
feel that is really challenging they feel that is
is reacting to what they're doing you know another reason that is
recently arrived is the
advent of streaming as a thing
that is everywhere uh... and you know everyone watches games being streamed
now
and if you want to make you know a narrative game but it's the same every
time you play it
it's not going to be that interesting stream frankly
you know and both of the consoles now have really easy clip sharing where you
can share
game pay clips with your friends and there's nothing more depressing than
sharing a clip with someone else only to look at his clips
and see his clips of the game is exactly the same as your clips of the game
and to realize hey wait a minute maybe these games aren't as dynamic as I
thought they were.
So now we can't get away with that and I think we need to work
at you know making games that are dynamic that people react to well
in a variety of ways including streaming and sharing and I think
you know as long as we're doing that we should also focus on how can we make the
stories
in those things dynamic as well.
So I still wonder why these games are focusing on having such static stories in the middle of it,
but not all of it is. And I think there's a lot of techniques that games are doing already that we can use
that can really open things up and tell dynamic stories.
So I'm going to go through a number of techniques that games are already doing today
and talk about how those have been done before and how you might apply them to your game.
The first thing I want to talk about is something I call the explorable story space.
So I'm going to go through this technique fairly quickly because it's pretty basic and it's used in a lot of games
successfully already.
So we look at something like Fallout or the Bethesda games in general.
These are often, you know, these giant RPGs and these giant worlds that have that core
narrative, but then they have a lot of side narrative around them.
Little stories that you can do or not do.
And we can look at this in smaller games as well, like Gone Home,
you know, despite being a much smaller scale game,
still had a lot of pieces on the side of it that you might find or not find,
depending on how you looked, how long you looked at the game.
and how thorough you are trying to be.
The important thing for this sort of side content
is that it has to be completely optional.
And that allows different players to find different pieces
and to come up with their own version of the story
based on the pieces they find.
uh...
and the players who want to put more time into it will find more of it
and the other ones who just want to get through it quickly
uh... can do that and then when they compare stories later
they will be talking about a different experience they both had and this will
increase their engagement
uh... in the
in the work. Now when I say
explorable story space I don't necessarily mean physically exploring
the space
obviously her story is a recent example
uh... where you were literally sitting glued in a chair in front of a computer
terminal the whole time in the fiction of the game
but you were exploring the story through all these clips you were finding on the
computer
Another, one more example I want to bring up of this before we move on
is the excellent adventure game the Last Express from a number of years ago.
Amazingly well-written and structured
where you're sort of moving through this very last, the last Orient Express
right before World War I
and seeing all these different stories in different parts of the train.
I don't think you can actually get the entire story
through one playthrough because of all the layers of it
that you can see depending where you are at what point in the game.
So the next technique I want to talk about is something I call the open-ended story.
And it's hard to call this a game technique because really this works
in stories you might be writing, you know, in any medium.
So if we look at, say, novels, we can look at novels like Slaughterhouse-Five
or the Martian Chronicles, tell stories that leave a lot out or that are
fairly convoluted and involve you, you know, trying to interpret what's going on
in them, trying to figure out what's going on.
Certainly there are a lot of movies like this as well.
If we look at something like The Shining or Inception,
a lot is left up to personal interpretation in these movies about what exactly is happening.
These tend to have, these type of works that are still linear,
Encourage repeated viewings just to try to figure out what's going on.
And fans come up with their own theories and debate them with each other,
and in so doing, make these stories interactive in a way.
Indeed, Brian Upton, in his excellent book, The Aesthetic of Play,
talks about this, where he says,
as we leap from beat to beat, we choose a set of interpretive constraints
to explain each beat's presence.
These interpretive constraints generate expectations about the direction and significance of the story.
Future beats either confirm or falsify these expectations,
triggering either satisfaction or frustration.
It's a really fascinating book to check out.
He talks about how just the act of reading and interpreting is interactive in its own way.
So if we extend this to games and we look at something like, you know, Dear Esther,
which is on some level completely non-interactive in terms of the story, because it's really
just the voiceover narration you're hearing juxtaposed with the imagery you're seeing,
there's really nothing you can change about it, but it's so sort of minimalist in its
structure that you really have to, you know, you can't help but interpret what you're seeing
and hearing as you're playing and coming up with your own theory to figure out what exactly
is going on and being said here.
Another example of a way to do that is to make your characters, you know, really abstract
and cartoony would be one word even, where, you know, maybe they don't necessarily say
words that you even understand, but that you get just a sense of them from these sort of
broad strokes and you end up having to bring a lot of yourself to the experience to fill
in those details yourself and get invested in the work that way.
Or, you know, you can take another approach.
In Silent Hill, they have a very specific, very detailed story,
but they just show you only these tiny slices of it,
and you're just left with these big holes that you have to fill in one way or the other.
So a final thought about open-ended stories.
You know, a word of warning I guess, I've seen a lot of games have really great open-ended
stories that you're interpreting as you're going and then at the end they feel, you know,
at the end of the game they feel the need to resolve it all and explain exactly what
happened.
And that can be very frustrating.
I think some of the best open-ended stories in other mediums, like say the end of The
Shining or the end of Inception.
they kind of open it up again, right?
They bring in some sort of resolution
to help you understand what the heck just happened
in the movie, but then they have something at the end
that twists it a bit and is like, well, actually this,
and then you're left sitting there going,
oh, wait, maybe my theory's still valid.
The worst thing you can do, I think,
is get to the end of one of these very open-ended experiences
and then shut it all down so the player feels like
all of their theories are thrown out the window.
So the next thing I want to talk about I refer to as reacting to player actions.
You know this is one of the most common things that people talk about when they
talk about
interactive storytelling and branching.
So obviously I'm going to go through this quickly as well.
You know we're all familiar with Bioshock that had the choice
of the little sisters, whether you harvested or rescued them, basically the
same choice
that you're making over and over again throughout the game.
Mass Effect handled this differently with their, you know, blue for Paragon, red for Renegade type of choices.
But the game is balanced in such a way that you're really encouraged to pick one and just keep making that choice for the entire game.
Sort of having that same shortcoming that Bioshock had.
Some interesting other examples of this where it worked a little better.
If you look at the indie game The Novelist,
you have much fewer choices than you have in Bioshock or Mass Effect,
but they're not coupled to each other really.
You're able to make one choice here and make one choice here,
and it doesn't push you to any one of them as the right ending
or the right choice to make.
And it can have all these sort of interesting ramifications
in the story, and there is no right answer.
The Walking Dead game certainly, that first season,
had a lot of interesting choice points throughout it and never labeled which
one was good or which one was bad or anything like that. It had so many of them
throughout the game that they started feeling like a real system and you never
knew which one
was going to be the important one that would be remembered.
and they were really good at setting up complex situations that didn't have a clear right or wrong answer.
Interestingly, Firewatch is an interesting evolution of this, right, where
Firewatch builds on that same idea of tons of little dialogue choices affecting things
and it's interesting to see online a few complaints that
oh well, all the choices you make don't actually affect the plot of that game very much
but to me the heart and soul of that game is really the relationship you have with Delilah, the other radio tower operator
and that does change substantially based on
how you talk to her and that's sort of what's most important about the game so
it
it is very impactful what happens even if the plot is is relatively similar.
Of course there are other games that approach branching not through these just narrative choices,
but actually through the choices you make in gameplay.
Like this is the classic way to do it in an immersive sim,
like Dishonored sort of situation,
where the way you go about playing the levels affect not only gameplay ramifications,
like those rats that swarm you, but also narrative changes.
And this is sort of aggregating all the choices you're making throughout the game.
Not dissimilar to Papers, Please,
which does the same thing where all the choices you're making are during gameplay
and add up to the different endings you can get.
There's been a lot of exploration of branching.
It's very interesting in the interactive fiction space.
If you want to check that out, I recommend
Googling Patterns and Choice Games.
There's a great blog post by the Sam Cabot-Ashwell,
I hope I pronounced that right, where
he talks about all the different structures that
have been done in different games.
And it was a really fascinating, quick read on the subject.
So next we have shifting story elements.
And this is something that's really not done as much in games
and is really fascinating to me as a result.
So this is, we can think of this,
if you think of this in terms of say adapting
a murder mystery, like one can think of
the act of reading a mystery novel,
like one of these books,
it's really a puzzle of a sort, right?
You're trying to figure out the, you know,
who did the murder.
before you get to the end, you're trying to find a resolution to that puzzle yourself
before the private investigator or whatever gets to it by the end.
The second time you read a book like this, it's much less interesting because you already
know who is responsible for doing the killing.
Even for books like this that are expertly well-written, it's definitely a different
experience when you read it the second time.
So when they adapted this into board game form originally
uh... they made board game clue which I'm sure you're all familiar with
and here they randomized who was responsible for the murder and who did
the murdering
and voila you now have a replayable murder mystery.
Interestingly when they turned this into a movie they said hey well
so we've got this clue board game it's got random
uh... you know random people who are guilty what if we did something similar
with this movie where we had different endings
that would give you different people who were uh... who were guilty of the crime.
Of course this kind of doesn't really work very well because
because they had to make the endings work with any of the possible
you know they had only one version of the main film and then these different
endings sort of tacked on
the main version of the movie had to support any ending that happened to come up
so now you had no way to actually figure out who did the murder because all of
these different endings were possible.
So of course when you adapt this into game form you can do better than that.
So the example I like, and there were a number of these in the 80s that did this actually,
that had these murder mystery games where you were trying to solve a mystery but who actually had done the killing
and who was killed was randomized each time you play.
And because it was a game they were able to plant little clues all along the way that you were playing
and you would be able to solve it unlike the clue movie.
Another example I like to bring up all the time is the...
blade runner game where each character in the game could be a
replicant or not depending on whether
uh... depending on basically a die roll at the beginning of the game and then this
would affect what you had to do with them because you were you know
hunting for these people and had to
make choices about about what happened to them
So some of the really interesting work in this sort of randomized story space is
actually done in board games.
You know, going back to the classic Arabian Nights game
or more modern games that sort of randomize the narrative in different ways.
Obviously these have the benefit of having multiple players in them,
but they still do good things to change up the story every time, so it feels like
a very dynamic experience and different every time you play.
An interesting example you might want to check out is this game, The Black Closet,
which is actually nominated for an IGF award this year, and I believe you can go play it on the show floor.
This is sort of an interesting mix-match of several different game types,
sort of like a dating sim mixed with sort of an adventure game.
And here you're in this all-female boarding school,
and there are these things like who's going to betray you,
and each game is randomized each time you play along with the other stuff.
By making, by sort of combining it with the...
sim in these random narrative elements you're really uh...
getting to uh...
very different experience each time you play
So my own game, The Church in the Darkment, which is now in development, is set inside a religious cult in the 1970s, but the player doesn't know whether that cult group is merely happy socialists who want to go live in the jungle, or if something more dark and apocalyptic is going to happen there.
And the key to this is the leader's personality is randomized each time you play the game, so you don't know what exactly you're dealing with, and you're sort of acting as a detective going into their sort of jungle compound to figure out what's going on.
So beyond just the interesting factor from a replay factor,
I thought it was also interesting because
I felt it fit thematically with the hard to understand nature of cults,
where they can be really hard to tell if it's actually a good group or
or something more sinister from the outside.
So it's my hope that by including this shifting story element,
you're able to see both sides of what can be a very complex story.
and I like specifically games that combine this sort of
uh... you know shifting story elements
with player choices like that the unfortunate thing about player choices
when you make them in a game if you ever want to go back and replay the game
you know naturally you're probably going to want to make the same choices
uh... and often when you go back if you want to see all the content you'll force
yourself to just make the choices you don't want to make which is not really a
great experience
however if the context of the game is shifting
you know, so that it's different this time, you'll want to make different choices the second time you're playing
because the context is different, because the reasons you're making these choices are different
and that makes games like these hopefully replayable in a more interesting way.
Alright, so the next thing I want to talk about a bit is character simulation.
So this is one of the harder methods to implement,
but also represents sort of one of the less charted areas, so I think a great area for future experimentation.
With character simulation techniques, each character in your story has a simulated personality
with their own wants and needs, desires, friendship, allegiances, and these dynamically change
based on your behavior as you're moving through the story, sort of based on what you do.
This sounds super complicated, and it can be, but its simpler forms are possible that
still produce some interesting results.
So probably the most commercially successful example of this is The Sims, right?
In The Sims, you're able to manipulate the personalities of these people
and play them off each other in these interesting ways.
The possibility space of The Sims is intentionally, I think, quite broad.
It lets anyone live out whatever version of American suburban life they want,
whether that's getting married and...
whatever fashion they find suitable, or having a goth family, or even torturing their sims.
This all feels like it fits because the game is so cartoony, because it's so broad.
Any goofy thing that happens feels like it fits okay into the game.
Another game that people don't often think of as a storytelling experience, but I think
is doing this, is Civilization, and the different sort of leaders of the different countries
that you meet as you're playing.
And they'll come to you, you know, trying to negotiate peace, or talking about threatening
war, or setting up a trade deal, or whatever it is, and they'll remember your past interactions
with them, and they'll remember...
whether you betrayed them before, who else you're having a fight with,
and then try and negotiate.
And this was taken even farther in the sort of cousin of civilization, Alpha Centauri,
which treated the heads of state even more like believable characters.
And they each had their own sort of political agenda and their own philosophical beliefs
that affected whether they were going to want to side with you.
And they sort of gave you feedback based on how you were playing the game,
whether they agreed with it or not.
Few consider these types of games really story games, yet there's no reason this sort of
faction-based reaction system of these games couldn't work to, you know, emphasize it even
more and make it feel even more like a narrative.
There's a couple of games that used character simulation that were definitely going for
something more narrative, and the first of those is Versu.
This was an interactive fiction system that used a much stronger story framework and much
more limited player choices than you would find in The Sims or something like that.
So this was a much more confined social situation.
The player was able to engage with all the characters
in a number of different ways,
and these choices would persist
and then affect their relationships with each other.
And the first setting for the Versus stories
was this sort of Jane Austen-ish social settings
where character dynamics are everything.
Prom week is another interesting example of this sort of social simulation
in a very carefully chosen setting, the week before high school prom,
a time rich with narrative possibilities and potential conflicts.
It takes a Sims-like approach to controlling these characters
where your only goal is not, you're not just playing dollhouse like you're
playing in the Sims, you're actually trying to get people to pair up with each other.
and following some pretty, you know, more confined goals.
The game uses a pretty elaborate personality model
that replicates the social graft you might find
in that hellish time of high school.
But to work both, you know, it's interesting to look
that Versu and Prom Week, you know,
both had really elaborate AI systems.
So in addition to requiring, you know, a kick-ass AI team
to implement something like this,
they also made very specific, careful choices
about the setting they were in.
They would have a tone that would allow
this kind of gameplay to work.
So you want something that allows for these interesting narrative simulations in the case of sort of the Jane Austenish story
or a prom type of situation.
And they both sort of chose a tone that was very deliberately silly, even slapstick, farcey,
where the player might try to do all these goofy things but they would still feel like they would fit in with the game.
You know, there's many potential settings, I think, where if you tried to do character simulation, it would be much harder to do,
particularly when I think the technique is in its infancy.
as it is now.
And the other thing these games were really good at was telegraphing what was going on
to the player.
And I think that's super important when you're trying to do something as complex than this.
You know, Versu used, or rather Promweek used a menu system that was very much like the
Sims that really gave you all sorts of bars and graphs and things about how everybody
felt with everyone else.
And even with all of that, it still was very hard to try to understand what was going on
in the game if you didn't understand the simulation decently.
Versu tried a more integrated approach where they had those little images at the bottom of the page
and they would actually change facial expression based on what their social state was at the time.
And if you wanted more information you could tap on them and a little box would pop up
that would explain to you why they felt the way they did.
And I know that over-telegraphing something like this can feel sort of aesthetically jarring,
particularly as a writer.
You know, I feel that way myself.
But I think a technique like this is in such its infancy that we really have to overdo it
to give players, you know, a chance to catch up.
It's like people didn't learn how to watch movies, you know, they learned over the years
and films get more and more subtle in their techniques.
And I think we have to see games the same way when trying something this ambitious and different.
And indeed, Emily Short, the co-creator of Versu,
had this great quote.
She said, my general rule of thumb
is it's pointless to simulate anything in AI
that you don't also have a plan for communicating
to the player.
Otherwise, they don't see how clever you're being, or worse,
what is actually sophisticated behavior winds up
looking like a button.
And if you want to hear more about Versu or Prom Week,
there's this excellent talk on the GDC Vault.
It's up there for free.
You can just search for Beyond Eliza, and it pops up.
And they talk about both of those projects
and how they worked in there.
Now the final example I want to talk about is drama management.
You know, I like to think of drama management as the flip side of character
simulation, whereas character simulation, the characters can sort of
drift in sort of interesting ways,
but that maybe don't end up feeling as much like stories.
Here this is actually steering things back towards something that feels like a
story. You can think of this as
akin to a D&D session. We have a really good DM who's trying to shape
things into a
into a certain narrative form. He allows a lot of agency for the players.
but he is constantly steering things back to the story he wants to tell
while still letting the players feel empowered.
So the most interesting example of this in digital form,
or the most well-known example, is Fassad.
In this game, the player enters into the apartment of a couple that is having an argument.
before as part of a dinner party and you're sort of there while their marriage is falling apart.
The player here has a tremendous amount of agency, you can say whatever you want to the characters and they'll try to react to it
and the game really does a pretty good job of steering it back to the main story it wants to tell.
So, Facade was always, you know, sort of interesting as an academic project, as a PhD project like it was when it was released.
But then it found this interesting second life on the internet because it became very popular as a Let's Play thing.
And people loved streaming this game because it was so reactive to whatever they would try and they would make all these Let's Play videos.
of like, oh let me try to get it to do this.
And this is sort of going back to what I was saying before about streaming being a thing that's popular.
Where people who are streamers really want to find games that will do crazy interesting things each time you play them.
The other example I wanted to bring up of something that I consider to be drama management
is the Nemesis system in Shadow of Mordor.
You know this is obviously a much more commercial application of it,
but it takes all the interesting sort of simulation elements of an open world game with combat in it
and shapes them into these little player stories
that give you a lot of motivation to keep playing the game.
And indeed Michael Platter, who's sitting right over there,
has said that the Nemesis system is emergent procedural narrative
that's neither linear nor branching.
Which is an interesting way to think of what drama management is really trying to do.
So just to give a quick summary of how this works,
the game turns the common experience of dying in the game,
turns it into a little piece of fiction basically, where the player
dies but the world keeps going without him and the player reincarnates
and the enemy who killed him is sort of
shown how he's moving up in the ranks because he did this great thing
of killing the player and indeed he might get a promotion or something like that.
and you now are, he is marked as a nemesis for you to go kill later in the game
and it's very good at creating these little vignettes when you come and find these characters
they'll show you a little cutscene of this guy and they have all these lines of dialogue that they'll say
to sort of taunt you at this time, they all have custom names
and all these little elements that went into the system that made it work well.
And it's interesting that it's just taking completely the thing that you do in every open world game
and just giving it all this context that makes it extra meaningful.
Sort of creating drama out of the simulation so that when you finally find this guy and kill him,
it's a very satisfying moment.
Alright, so those are the six techniques I wanted to go through today.
You know, I think it can be interesting to look at your own projects and try to see which of these six things you're doing already.
I'm not saying that every game should try to do all of these things, though
that might be interesting if someone were to pull that off, but
you know, if maybe you're doing one or two of them, maybe you can add a third of some kind, really depends on the needs of your game.
But I think if you find that you're doing zero of these things, I would argue maybe you're not making a great game story.
And I think, you know, at the beginning of the talk I talked about how it was important
to look at this because of streaming and sharing and all of that stuff.
And I think the reality is that streaming has revealed a dirty little secret that we've had in making single player games for a while.
And that's that we made the experiences feel dynamic to the player, but they weren't actually, right?
That everybody felt they were having a unique experience, but really it was just exactly what we wanted to happen.
And I think we can't hide behind that anymore.
And I think even if a player never actually streams a game,
or never actually shares it or sees it in any other form,
it's still important just for player investment.
It's still important for players to feel like they're
involved in the story, if it's dynamic in some way,
and that they can affect it.
I think you have to recognize that there have been many games that are very successful using this technique.
Whether it's, you know, finding that last safe that has the final clue to the side story and the part of the game you really want to figure out and feeling that you found that.
Or, you know, the abstract experience that really lets you invest yourself in it and feel that, you know, this becomes your story through that.
Or even just hunting down that guy and finally killing him.
after he's been your nemesis for a while, or that scene at the end where you remember all that time we had together and all the choices we made along the way.
I think if, in short, you know, I think when dynamic storytelling really works,
you know, players really love it, really become invested in it, and feel that they've told their own story.
So, thanks.