stuff. So, and we're just going to kick this off and this is going to go pretty quickly.
So yeah, thanks for coming. My name is Clint Hocking and today's talk is about dynamics.
But before we get started, I feel it's important to warn you that by the time this talk is
over, everyone in this room is going to think I'm a communist. So we might as well get that
out of the way right now. Over the course of this talk, I'm going to espouse to you
the virtues of contemporary Cuban urban agriculture. I'm going to mesmerize you with images from
the proud history of Soviet cinema.
and I'm going to convince you that some of the most beloved American heroes, guys like
Ernest Hemingway and Thomas Edison, are also communists. I might even talk about some communist
games, like Tetris, and by the time I'm finished, you're all going to be signing up to join
the party and await the reanimation of our once and future leader in revolution. You've
been warned. I'm also going to talk a lot about elephants for some reason. Dynamics.
Why do I want to talk about dynamics? Well, mostly, this is a talk that I've been wanting
to give and actually trying to give for a long time, but it's a really difficult talk.
Also because dynamics are pretty central to games, I really wanted to make sure I was going to have the time to do it right.
And the last few years have been kind of mental for me.
I got married, I shipped Far Cry 2, I went on honeymoon in Africa, where I had absolutely no problem with responding guard posts,
but I did almost get killed by a rampaging elephant.
I fucked up my back, I got better, I lost 50 pounds, I left my job at Ubisoft, I took a job at LucasArts, I immigrated to the US, and I had a kid all in two years.
So, the good news is that...
Now that I have like 15 years worth of like crazy life changes, all packaged up and out of the way,
I finally feel like I have the time to give this talk the rigor it deserves.
The bad news is, my son must be part hobbit or something, because he has these really big feet,
and I have all these jammies with feet in them that don't fit, and little baby shoes that he's never worn,
and so if you're looking for baby shoes, check on Craigslist.
Anyway, the thing that really kicked my ass to buckle down and tackle this talk finally was,
back in 2009, Chris Hecker gave a GDC talk.
and that picture's not actually from there, but,
where he said he felt one of the most important
near-term questions for game development
and for game researchers
was to answer the question,
how do games mean, right?
And I'm not a game researcher guy,
but I'm gonna give that a shot anyway.
When trying to understand games as a cultural form,
we often talk about the meaning of specific games.
We ask, like, what does Thief mean?
Or what does Go mean?
Or what does Far Cry 2 mean?
And, you know, putting aside for a moment the fact that...
The answers to those questions are definitely subjective.
The problem with even asking them is that we haven't even come close to agreement on
what the sort of power plant of meaning generation is in games in general, right?
Some people will say thief is about territory control or domination or collection.
Others will say it's about a thief named Garrett caught in the midst of a conflict between
like progressive industrialists and like anarcho-naturalists or something.
Some will say it's both and some will say neither.
And until we have some kind of consensus...
on how games can even be about anything at all, we're kind of wasting words, right? We
need to understand how games mean before we can really talk in a sophisticated way about
what a specific game means. So this is Topsy the Elephant. Back in 1903, Topsy got in some
trouble for, like, trampling to death a bunch of trainers, you know, at Four Paws Circus
out on Coney Island.
This was right around the time that Thomas Edison was leveraging sort of his many patents to try and push through this
national infrastructure that would see a network of DC power distribution bring electricity on demand into every home in America.
Unfortunately for Edison, Nikola Tesla, who is the dude who invented the fucking Tesla coil,
had patented a polyphase system and was doing some work on rotary magnetic fields and AC transformers and was promoting this system of
national infrastructure for AC power transmission.
that rivaled Edison's.
So this boiled over into what we now call the War of Currents,
or the AC-DC war.
And the long and short of it was that although Edison had a head
start, because sort of all the core technology that his system
required was sort of proven, the infrastructure demand that
would have called for a DC power station every three to five
kilometers was due to the sort of extreme power loss that's
incurred when you try to transmit DC power over long
distances.
Tesla's system, on the other hand, required some sort of fancy mapeteering and some new inventions like step-up and step-down transformers and all this stuff.
But once that was all figured out, the ability to centralize electrical power generation at coal-fired plants and massive hydroelectric dams like the one at Niagara Falls,
to transmit energy over long distances with little to no loss, kind of tipped the scales in Tesla's favor.
So Edison sort of fought back by launching this smear campaign against AC Current.
He even went so far as to sort of covertly fund the invention of the electric chair
and, you know, see it brought into use for the meeting out of capital punishment, like here in the US.
His goal was actually to just terrify people about the dangers of AC Current
and show them how dangerous it was.
So Portofcy the Elephant was a casualty in this war.
Once it was basically over...
and the push towards sort of a national AC distribution system was underway,
Edison presided over and filmed the execution of Topsy the Elephant,
which is performed by coursing like 6,600 volts of AC current through her body.
I'm not going to roll the film electrocuting an elephant 1903,
because it's kind of gross,
but I will point out the irony that the laptop that's displaying this image
and the projector over there and, you know,
the speakers that are amplifying my voice and the mixing board at the back and...
and the lights and the heat and everything in this convention center, everything in this city,
everything in this country, basically, is running off of Tesla's AC power distribution system.
So, even though Edison's film was seen by like thousands of Americans,
it didn't have the horrifying effect that he had hoped.
It basically didn't work, right?
So, about a decade after Portopsy was executed in the 19-teens,
Russian filmmaker Lev Kuleshov conducted an experiment where he filmed...
matinee idol Ivan Mazookin staring into a camera looking intense. He also filmed a bowl
of soup being eaten and a dead child in an open coffin and an attractive scantily clad
woman. He then sort of popped up in Final Cut Pro and he added together his footage
and cut back and forth between the actor and the soup and the child and the woman. This
is the final film that he showed to audiences.
have to do it the clumsy way. Where did it go? Sorry. Why is
it not working? I tried it before and it worked. Now it's
not working. There we go. That sucks, I'm sorry. It's over
here. Yeah, I should have just acted out. And I can't find the
fucking button. Okay, well...
Okay, it cuts back and forth from his face to the woman, to the soup, to the child, to
his face.
Okay, that's how it goes.
Come on.
I can't hit the space bar.
So that was the final film he showed to audiences.
After seeing the film, he sort of polled audiences about how Mazookian was feeling in each shot.
And the audiences reported that he appeared hungry when he was looking at the bowl of soup,
and he appeared sad when he was looking at the dead child in the coffin,
and he appeared lustful when he was looking at slave Leia.
Um, Mazookian was even praised for his acting ability and probably nominated for an Oscar or whatever.
Um, what's awesome though, and so that's the film, right?
It goes from there to there to there to there to there to there in like 15 seconds.
That's the whole film.
Um...
So what's awesome though is that not only was Mazookian not looking at the soup or the dead child or the hot chick,
as actors aren't often looking at the things that they're acting to when they're being filmed,
it wasn't even three pieces of footage, right?
Kuleshov was actually cutting back to the exact same frames of the exact same footage of Mazookian after each shot.
So what the audiences were reading as emotional responses from this actor to these things he was looking at
actually just didn't even exist.
We call this the Kuleshov effect, and we interpret it to imply that at the lowest and most fundamental meaning in film,
at the lowest most fundamental level, meaning in film is generated not by the moving picture itself, really,
but by the juxtaposition of the images, in fact, by the editing.
Thomas Edison did not understand the importance of editing to generate meaning and thereby move his audience.
Had he intercut the footage of Topsy the Elephant's execution
with, like, footage of a little girl crying,
I pretty much guarantee you that instead of, like,
an ice rink down the street right now,
we'd have, like, a solar power station.
So...
what's interesting is that I want to point out
that sort of how the moving recorded image
generates meaning at its lowest level
still leaves us sort of miles away from, you know,
between Ivan Muzukin and feeling lustful, sad, or hungry
and the sort of complex layering of images and emotions that we get.
and that intertwine and evolve over the course of a film like, like Tampopo, for example.
Tampopo, or indeed sort of any modern film, has a meaning that arises out of the harmony
of many different techniques sort of all acting in concert, right?
The lowest level meaning of the edit gives us the sort of raw emotional sense of the
adoration and compulsion shared by the gangster and his young lover while they're playing
lossfully with their food and each other, right?
The music and the lighting and the staging kind of all work together.
to give these extra layers of meaning and make the scenes sort of more meaningful and give us a sense of how the raw emotions develop and interconnect over time.
And at the highest level, the story and plot kind of ties these actions together, allowing us to witness the sort of profound evolution of that relationship and experience the sort of beautiful tragedy of its conclusion in the end.
But let's imagine for a second that instead of traveling back in time and killing Hitler
so that Tesla could rise to power, Albert Einstein instead went back in time and killed
Kuleshov, right?
And as a consequence, we never really figured out how film meant at its lowest level.
There would be sort of no method underlying how we edit together film and no way to generate
that lowest level meaning, that sort of core meaning generation that happens in film that
acts as a foundation upon which the sort of rest of these higher level meanings are synthesized
and put together.
So our films might have these great high-level stories,
but these stories would effectively be sort of
randomly in harmony or discord
with the emotional noise,
which is effectively what it would be,
being generated at the level of the edit,
because editing wouldn't have any sense to it.
If we were even able to identify this effect,
we might begin to think that filmic meaning
and narrative meaning were somehow irreconcilable, right?
We would say that film as a median
suffered from a dissonance.
between its narrative and its editing.
If we wanted to be pretentious,
we could even take the Greek word for cut,
which is temenos,
and the Latin word for narrative,
which is narrativus,
and name this inherent defect of the undeveloped medium
temnonarrative dissonance, right?
And, oops, got a slide ahead here.
And then we could sort of
try and figure out ways to fix that problem, right?
One way would be to sort of minimize the ways in which accidental and poorly understood meanings
generated by cutting and editing interfered with the meaning of the narrative.
We could take movies where the high-level story and plot was where all the meaning lay,
and we could reduce or eliminate camera cuts that seemed to make people feel something
that didn't reinforce the story.
For example, we would probably shoot everything wide.
We'd never show character faces in close-up.
We wouldn't want to cut between character reaction shots and actions or objects because we wouldn't know what those cuts were meant, right?
We wouldn't understand why people felt sad when we were trying to tell a joke because we were cutting to like a corpse and back to someone's face, right?
We'd probably also try to avoid opening and closing scenes on a character, right?
We'd have characters sort of exit frame and then we'd cut from establishing shots of environments to establishing shots of new settings.
Scenes would get longer.
they would get more stagey. In fact, what we're really talking about is making movies that are essentially like stage plays, right?
You would strip away all the inherent meaning generation elements that are native to the medium of film
and rely on the meaning of generating elements of tools from a different medium.
The problem with this approach, I think, is obvious, right? I mean, I hope.
If you make a movie by pointing a camera at the stage play, right,
the resulting work is going to be less good than a stage play and it's going to be...
less good than a movie because it's missing something fundamental about both of those
sort of experiences. Once upon a time, it must have been an amazing feeling to go to
the World's Fair and watch like Edward Maybridge's or Maybridge's Running Horses or Fred Ott's
Knees and see poor old Topsy the Elephant being electrocuted and marvel at the cool
things that this new medium of film could make us feel, right? But eventually those
like simple random snippets of decontextualized feeling
must have began to feel hollow and weird, right?
And people began to look for the bigger picture, right?
And laying the foundation for understanding how film means,
Kuleshov enabled us to kind of step forward
from the early days of film as curiosity
into the 20th century, where film would become, sort of,
possibly the most important medium in human culture, right?
So, sadly, I think this is more or less where we're at
in terms of the development of our own medium today.
An entire generation of people who have grown up alongside games as curiosity
are now starting to sort of look for the bigger picture.
And in order to do that, the very first thing we have to do
is understand what that core meaning generation element of video games is
and how it works.
And in order to do that, we have to answer Chekhov's question, right?
Fortunately, I happen to think the answer is really easy and obvious, okay?
I think the answer is that games mean via their dynamics.
So, thanks for coming.
Who's got questions?
No.
Asserting that games mean via their dynamics is like asserting that film means through
editing, right?
We need to go a lot deeper than that.
And, you know, while I believe that games do mean via their dynamics, the rest of this
talk is going to be about sort of how games mean via their dynamics and why it matters
to you with examples.
Yay.
First of all, what are dynamics? So in like 60 slides or less, here's the 101 part of the lecture.
Back in 2004, Robin Honecke and Marc LeBlanc and Bob Zubek published a paper called MDA,
Formal Approach to Game Design Research. MDA stands for Mechanics Dynamics Aesthetics.
Mechanics is defined as the particular components of the game. Sorry, I'm just spewing this out.
You should know this. At the level of data representation and algorithms,
dynamics is defined as the run-time behavior of mechanics acting on player inputs
and each other's outputs over time.
Aesthetics is defined as the desirable emotional responses evoked in the player when he or
she interacts with the game system.
To make that clearer, I like to think of MDA as being RBF, because those are better letters.
Mechanics are the rules of the game, dynamics are the run-time behaviors of the game player
system, and aesthetics are the feelings that the game evokes.
So that's enough theory.
How about some examples, finally?
So this is Spelunky.
So Steven Lavelle, also known as Increpare, and I'm not sure if that's Greek or Latin,
but it doesn't matter.
because the dude has made over like a hundred games in the last three years, okay?
Um, you know, he said this, um, at one point.
Um, he said,
As with using a whip in real life, attacking with a whip in Spelunky is not an immediate action.
It has to be raised before you can hit.
This slows the game and makes hitting airborne creatures harder, and thus deadlier,
than if whip strikes were immediate.
The extra layer of timing you must factor in the game makes it less pew-pew
and more dash deliberately in, whack, and dash out.
It encourages a certain degree of premeditation and creates an overall atmosphere of deliberation.
So what's interesting here is that even though he's not talking about the NBA framework specifically,
his natural discussion of Spelunky draws him to point out that the rule that the whip animation
must be played before it can do damage makes the game slower, harder, and deadlier and
causes the player to adopt certain ways of playing, thus giving Spelunky the unique aesthetic
signatures of being premeditative and having an atmosphere of deliberation.
Ultimately, I think that's the question
when we're asking, how do games mean?
I think we're asking...
from where do aesthetics,
such as premeditative and premeditative
and deliberate, originate in games?
And I think it's a tricky and elusive question.
Does the meaning of Spelunky, right,
come from the rules governing the whip
or from the way the player uses the whip, right?
In the end, I think the question is difficult
because there's a really ambiguous verb.
that lives at the center of this debate, at least in English.
Maybe if you speak another language, games are way easier to understand.
That verb is play.
It seems fairly clear that at the most fundamental level,
the aesthetics of film come from editing.
But the verb edit only has one meaning, right?
And play has several meanings, right?
For example, instead of saying...
If instead of playing Spelunky, Stephen Lavelle played piano...
and created a piece of music, there would be no argument about where that meaning came
from, right? It comes from Stephen playing the piano, right? From the dynamics. If, however,
I came along and recorded that music and burned a CD and gave it to Checker, and Checker played
the CD and appre- and Checker played, there's the other play, the CD, and appreciated the
aesthetics of the music, there would again be no argument about where the meaning comes
from, right? Whoops.
But it doesn't come from the act of playing the CD, right, from the dynamics.
It comes from the data on the CD, which is like the mechanics in this system, right?
It's like the code that's embedded in the system.
So, you know, games are not like pianos, right?
And they're not like CD players either, right?
They're a thing that you play, but also a thing that you play, used to play things.
Games are actually kind of both at once.
They're kind of actually...
like player pianos. Does everybody know what a player piano is?
Player pianos are basically...
The player piano was to 1905 what Guitar Hero was to 2005.
I love these two pictures, they're like identical.
The chick on the left even looks like the chick on the left.
The player piano is a piano that has a machine in it that you wind up, right?
And it unrolls this giant punch card kind of thing across, like a music box,
across the inner workings of the thing, and the piano plays itself, right?
So it just plays its little music.
You wind it up and let it play.
However, you can also play along with it, right?
So you can obviously get, like, different kinds of player piano rolls to, like,
you know, play part of a duet or play, you know, things that help you learn how
to play piano better or, you know, things that make you look like you're
Rachmaninoff or something.
The only real difference between a player piano and a game is that the player piano can play by itself, while a game cannot.
And of course if you say, yeah, but you could make like two chess bots play each other, that's not a game playing itself, that's two AIs.
That's a different situation.
Dynamic interaction is a requirement for anything that we define as a game.
And because of this fact, we have a very important distinction to make when we kind of author our equivalent of these piano rules.
Speaking of Rachmaninoff...
who apparently wrote compositions so complex
that they could only be played by people with 12 fingers.
That's not actually true, by the way.
He just had really big hands.
I kind of wonder sometimes if his parents
had to sell his cute little baby to design a big Craigslist.
Anyway, the point is that game designers
have this really important choice to make
when they're authoring their games, right?
We can choose to subscribe
to the sort of message model of meaning.
And if we do that,
we can attempt to sort of heavily author
the meaning of our game by putting...
say, ten fingers worth of meaning into the piano roll of our mechanics, and leaving only
two fingers worth of room in the dynamics, whoops, like that, for the player to play
the piano and sort of contribute to the overall meaning of the music. Conversely, we can kind
of abdicate our authorship of meaning to the player, putting two fingers worth of meaning
in the piano roll of our mechanics and leaving ten fingers worth of room in the dynamics
for the player to make his own music. So, I mean, certainly there's no right way to
make games.
I personally have a strong preference, both as a designer and a player, for games that
advocate as much authorship as possible to the player. But no matter how much authorship
I advocate, my authoring of the mechanics will always yield some kind of influence over
the dynamics. In fact, this is a road that I've been down a couple times already, and
in order to talk about sort of range of possible authorial control that we can attempt to exert
over the dynamical meaning of a game by the mechanics that we author.
I'm going to look at three different games
that live at different places along this spectrum.
And there happens to be an interesting set of games
that I'm highly qualified to talk about
that provide a fairly good coverage of this spectrum,
and that's the three games that I've shipped.
The first two, the original Splinter Cell
and Splinter Cell Chaos Theory,
live over there on the left side,
where the meaning is fairly heavily authored.
My most recent game, Far Cry 2,
is quite a distance over on the right side,
where sort of a great deal of authorship
has been advocated to the player.
You could go farther out that side easily, just as you can go farther down to the other
side. And there's, it's a complete analog range. Games live all across this band. But
how do each of these games mean in their dynamics? And how is that meaning influenced by the
authored mechanics in the game? So back at the Montreal Game Summit in 2005, actually,
I gave a design talk where I spoke a little bit about the meaning of Splinter Cell Chaos
Theory. I talked about how it wasn't really a game about
international espionage and covert operations and all that stuff. I said Chaos Theory is
actually a game about chaos theory. It's a game about the sensitivity of complex dynamic
systems to minor perturbations. It's about the fragility of, you know, a security system
like a simple lock and the uneasy timers that are sort of counting down under the hood as
you're trying to pick that lock before a light comes back on or something. It's about being
in close proximity to like aware and dangerous guards who can detect you and react.
performing these sort of complex and challenging tasks in close proximity to fragile systems
that, if they're disrupted, can spread their information to other nearby systems and kind
of cause cascading problems that are difficult to recover from.
And that's what Splinter Cell Chaos Theory is about.
In fact, it's not just Splinter Cell Chaos Theory that's about that.
The original Splinter Cell is also about chaos theory.
And these ideas of sensitivity and proximity and fragility are actually central to what
the series was about in the beginning.
So it's illuminating to kind of look at how the meaning changes
between these two, frankly, extremely similar games
based on only a very slight change in the balance of authorship
that's exerted into the mechanics.
In the notorious example from the original Splinter Cell,
the player was sort of tasked with getting through a series of keypad-locked doors
by closely following a patrolling guard.
And in each door, he would have to use his thermal vision.
to like read the warm fingerprints on the keypad that the guard would enter before he
went through the door. That would give the player the code and then he could enter. But
this was sort of forced, right? If the player was good enough that he could get up behind
this guard and follow the guard into the room without being detected, you would actually
get a game over because you were being forced to use your goggles to read the keypad. It
was just completely arbitrary and stupid, actually.
But it put the player in fragile proximity, right, to this sensitive guard, and by forcing
you to do the sequence this way and gating these other behaviors with mission fails,
you know, we can say that the mechanics of the game that we authored forced a set of
dynamics that ensured the game was about this designer-authored meaning of sensitivity,
proximity, and fragility.
It's forced in the dynamics.
You can't not have that experience.
You can have the experience of that, or you can have the experience of turning your console
off and doing something else.
In chaos theory, we kind of loosened up some of these pressures, right?
The player was never forced to tackle specific challenges using specific tools, right?
For example, he could still read thermal fingerprints off of keypads if he wanted to.
If he sees a guard going through a door, he can go,
well, that's a good way to- I'm gonna go use my goggles and read his thing
and get the code and go through the door.
Pretty cool.
But he could also just sort of follow the guard through the keypad-locked door,
you know, before it closed behind him.
Or he could interrogate the guard and find out the code,
because the guard, if he knows the code, he knows the code.
Or he could find the code on a computer and open the door that way.
Or he could just hack the door with his little remote hacking device and open the door that way.
So by removing sort of a bunch of the mechanics that were enforcing certain dynamics,
and by adding mechanics that allowed other dynamics,
and then letting the player sort of choose which set of dynamics become the backbone of his play experience,
what happens?
Well, obviously, I mean, the meaning of the game changes, right?
Depending on how you play as a player...
Splinter Cell Chaos Theory is sort of only probabilistically about Chaos Theory.
It could be about Chaos Theory, right?
It could be about sensitivity and proximity and fragility if you play a certain way.
But if you play another way, it could be about the same things as Quake, right?
And I think that, you know, while most players would still say
that despite the range of possible meanings,
Chaos Theory is still mostly about Chaos Theory.
What happens if you abdicate authorship even more
and you move much, much further down this axis towards...
towards having sort of less authorship in the mechanics
that are impacting your dynamic meaning.
So, what is Far Cry 2 about?
Well, in our original pitch,
the meaning of the game was supposed to be
that human social savagery is more disturbing
than the simple savagery of teeth and claws.
That's literal block of text from a very ancient document.
We often use the example that a bunch of schoolgirls
had a greater capacity to be cruel
than something like a crocodile.
And that capacity for social cruelty
is what makes us the most terrible creature on Earth.
So basically, like, Far Cry 2 is supposed to be, like,
sissy fight with flamethrowers.
Um...
We embedded this sort of message in the game
with mechanics that encourage dynamics
like shooting to wound,
executing people in cold blood,
euthanizing your friends.
You know, in the end, Far Cry 2, I guess,
is a little bit about some of these things.
Tom Bissell in his book Extra Lives says at one point,
Far Cry 2 is a game about chaos, which you enable, abet,
and are at constant risk of being consumed by.
He goes on to tell the story of...
Whoops.
He goes on to tell the story of a skirmish that ended with, like, a wounded enemy
that was lying in the grass and calling out,
but he couldn't see the guy in the grass,
and so the guy's taking pot shots at him,
and he's getting all freaked out.
So he says...
When I had put enough distance between us, I lobbed a Molotov cocktail into the general area where the supine dying man lay.
Within seconds, I could hear him screaming amid the twiggy crackle of the grass catching fire.
Sitting before my television, I felt a kind of horridly unreciprocated intimacy with the man I had just burned to death.
Far Cry 2 may reward your murderous actions, but you never feel as though it approves of them,
and it reminds you again and again that you are no better than the people that you kill.
In fact, you may be much worse.
So maybe Tom was, maybe for Tom it was kind of about these ideas that we were trying to author, right?
Maybe it's the case that, you know, one day we're going to look on Wikipedia and see that the early games of Clint Hawking or something explored themes of chaos, right?
Like, you know, maybe it's a game about chaos.
But in the end, it wasn't me that burned that, you know, poor bastard to death in that field.
It was Tom, right?
And maybe the chaos that he was struggling with was...
you know, some kind of, like, inner chaos that's in him,
and it's not a chaos that I authored, you know, who knows?
Well, I suspect this guy maybe knows.
Blogger Ben Abraham played the game several times.
One of those times he played the game using Iron Man rules,
and he wrote a 300-page journal about it
called The Permadeath Experience.
In an interview with Justin Caburn,
I think that's how you pronounce his name,
on the Groping the Elephant blog,
Ben said this about Far Cry 2.
He said,
I guess my approach reflected my desire.
to have a fun experience, so I played it quite safe at first. When the initial sense of tension
and danger wore off, I experimented and I courted danger a bit. When playing normally,
I would stride right up and punch danger in the face, trusting luck and skill to get me
by. But by prioritizing my survival, I became much more reserved and cautious. Kind of boring,
really. Practical things that changed how I played include, you know, picking safe options
and utilizing optimal killing strategies. Basically, any time there was a dangerous
option and a boring safe option, I took the safe one.
So, and that's an instance I guess like, no.
The authored meaning that we were sort of going for
didn't really come through so much.
So does this mean that in the end,
that sort of the more authorship we advocate,
the more we leave our game open to being what Ebert called
a smorgasbord of meaning?
Let's talk about elephants.
So in 1927, Ernest Hemingway wrote a short story
called, Hails Like White Elephants,
which is the story of a man and a woman
sitting in a bar in a train station in Spain,
having a drink, talking.
It's a pretty slow story.
Pretty short, feels long.
A lot of people would say that it would be a better story if it at least had some elephants
in it or something.
As Ben said about Far Cry 2, Hills Like White Elephants is actually kind of boring, really.
But it does have an elephant in it in a sense.
At least it has what we call an elephant in the room, right?
Even though what the story is about is never explicitly stated by the author, it is entirely
obvious to the reader what it's about.
Although short, it feels like White Elephants is probably too long for us to sort of read
together in the middle of this lecture, so we can examine how it means at runtime, the
way we did with Tetris. We didn't do that with Tetris yet.
Oh, well. So let's look at another Hemingway short story that's sort of similarly powerful.
So that's the whole story.
There's some question about the attribution of this story to Hemingway, but one thing is clear.
The story is like a 40-ounce overproof of Hemingway's sauce, right?
Absolutely every single extraneous thing has been stripped from it,
and nothing at all remains except for this sort of sinking realization of what that story is about.
On the one hand, the meaning of the story is sort of irrefutable,
and on the other hand, Hemingway did not put the meaning there, right?
The audience brings the meaning to this story.
Hemingway has sort of abdicated every last possible inch of authorship to the audience.
He couldn't have given you more freedom to write the meaning yourself if he gave you a moleskin and a pencil.
And there is absolutely nothing else that this story could be about than what it's about.
In my mind, this kind of goes beyond what we would call sort of minimalism in literature, right?
This isn't sort of the art of removing everything unnecessary.
This is the art of showing your audience that they are, in fact, artists themselves.
With Far Cry 2, I think our push to achieve
our originally intended meaning
caused us to kind of lose sight of an irrefutable meaning
that lives in the dynamics.
In the end, I think Tom may have had it right
when he said Far Cry 2 is a game about chaos.
He was embracing it when he threw the Molotov
into that field, while Ben's boredom,
I think, was probably his refusal
to be seduced by the danger of it, right?
On the dev team, we were trying to somehow
tie the meaning we found.
and we were finding in our dynamics
a sort of overarching narrative concept
in order to make sure it was being experienced and understood.
But in reality, the meaning was already living and breathing
in the dynamics, and our sort of direct efforts
may have only confused things.
Now, that's gonna get me to talking about narrative
and, you know, about that highly narrative game, Tetris,
which I guess we're all familiar with.
You know, show of hands, how many people in this room
have played Tetris?
Yeah.
Actually...
Stupid question, how many people in this room have played so much Tetris that they can close
their eyes and hum and play Tetris in their heads?
Yeah, that's a pretty good ratio.
Tetris is really simple, right?
Pieces fall, you rotate them around and fit them in among other pieces and if you complete
a row with no holes in it, the row disappears.
If the rows stack up to the top of the screen, you lose.
If these are the basic mechanics...
What are the dynamics of Tetris, right?
What does Tetris mean in its dynamics?
Well, there's a certain amount of dexterity and precision,
obviously.
You have to be able to effectively put the pieces
where you want them, right?
Beyond that, there's this sort of great deal
of strategy in terms of how you deal
with the random chain of pieces being thrown at you.
You need to anticipate and weigh the probability
of different configurations that you're
creating to get them to pay off.
you need to be removing rows in the short term while at the same time sort of keeping
opportunities alive for like multi-row completions in Tetris's, right?
In fact, Tetris is about a lot of really interesting things, but because of its abstract nature,
it's very hard for us to talk about what Tetris is about in any kind of larger sense.
And that's okay.
By that I mean, you know, Tetris isn't really able to comment on the world at large,
or on people, or on their emotional or psychological reality.
It's very hard for us to imagine, though not impossible, how Tetris informs our perspective
on the world, right?
Tetris is able to be about itself, right?
And it's able to be about who is playing it.
But you would never, for example, say that Tetris is immoral or evil because it de-responsibilizes
you for participating in a system of institutionalized discrimination, right?
You know, once again, I'm not saying Tetris should do any of those things.
I love Tetris the way it is.
I'm just using Tetris.
I love it.
because in its abstract nature, I want to elaborate on it and talk about how narrative can be used to influence dynamic meaning, or dynamical meaning.
This is Rod Humble's game, The Marriage.
The game is also very abstract, right? It also requires a certain amount of dexterity and precision.
You also need to have strategy, you need to anticipate weight probabilities, keep opportunities alive, all that stuff.
But The Marriage is not completely abstract.
The Marriage is about marriage.
It says so right in the title, right?
And more than that, the blue piece sort of represents the man in this particular marriage,
and the pink piece represents the woman, right? In effect, the title, the marriage, and a
couple of the sort of tiny little decisions about RGB values have a massive impact on
the way the dynamics of this game unfold and consequently what it means or the way it means.
So what if we decided to add a kind of thin fictional layer to Tetris, not with the aim
of trying to make a better game, that's not what this sort of...
thought exercises about, that's absurd, right? It's with the aim of observing how adding
or changing a narrative layer to a game can impact the dynamics and thus the meaning,
even if the underlying mechanics do not change, right? Is Brenda here? No? Okay. So this is
Brenda Brathwaite. For the last several years, she's been working on a series of art games
that she calls the Mechanic is the Message series.
Perhaps the most renowned work in the series is a game that you've probably all heard of
called Train. How many people have played Train? More than I thought, but very, very
few, right? This is largely because of the game's nature as an artifact. Very few people
have actually played it. I haven't played it either, so I can't talk about it specifically.
I'm just going to borrow from it thematically. In our new version of Tetris, we're going
to say that the field on which the pieces fall...
is a train yard on the edge of the Warsaw Ghetto in like, yeah, back then.
And the objective of the game is to pack people into the boxcars and ship them off to camps.
Of course, the people that you're grabbing are scared and are themselves clinging to their family members
and all that kind of stuff, which rationalizes the fiction of why you get these pieces in different shapes
that you have to deal with.
Of course, the trains are under orders not to leave the station unless the cars are completely full.
So if you leave too many trains partially full, the train yard will overflow.
with non-optimally filled train cars and stop the Nazi war effort. Game over.
Now to be clear, I'm not changing any of the rules of Tetris.
It's exactly the same game, except now under this narrative,
every line you clear is a boxcar full of innocent people that you are sending away to a concentration camp.
So, with that in mind, and the reason I chose Tetris is that we can now close all our eyes
and evaluate the changes that have been made to the game.
by playing the game in our head, right?
We can emulate Tetris and think about what we would do
if this was the game we were playing, right?
What would you do?
Well, there's a couple of options.
You can play the dutiful servant of the Reich
and play the game exactly the way you played Tetris before.
You can try and pack each row full,
clearing out full rows and preventing the field
from getting jammed up
so you can get the highest score possible.
What a wonderful game.
You can take on the kind of Schindler role.
which is to kind of back up the system as slowly as possible
by optimizing the way you lose the game.
By leaving one and only one spot empty in each and every box car,
you can maximize the number of people that get pushed through the system
while minimizing the number of people that get sent to concentration camps.
That's an interesting way to play the game.
Or you could play the saboteur if you want,
and you could immediately just stack up pieces as aggressively as possible
and try to get to the game over state
without sending anyone to a concentration camp.
Of course, if you stack pieces up like this in the real Tetris,
and claim that the game was about sabotaging and attempting to...
a game that attempted to de-responsibilize,
what did I say before, its participants for a system of institutional discrimination
that was bent on genocide, right?
I think any sane person would laugh at you and think that you just sucked at Tetris, right?
But in this game, this approach is actually really meaningful.
It's a meaningful and important way to play.
And that's the point that I'm sort of trying to make, right?
By changing the fictional skin, the game has new potential meanings that Tetris didn't
really have before, right? These meanings don't come from the mechanics. They come from
the behavior of the game player system acting under the influences of the narrative, right?
My point here is not just to show that narrative can sort of powerfully influence dynamics,
but it's also to point out that the claim that sort of a game's fiction is only and
exclusively a skin, it's kind of a greedy reduction.
A game's fiction might not touch the mechanics at all,
but it still strongly influences how we evaluate the field,
how we value game pieces and optimize their interactions.
Regardless of the explicit value we give these things
in mechanics, right?
The fictional skin, excuse me,
can lead to changes in the way the game is played,
which fundamentally is how the game means.
So it's important.
Now that we've looked at a couple different ways
that dynamical meaning of a game
can be influenced by the designer.
or in the fiction case, a writer or writer-designer,
whatever, whoever,
and can sort of modify the dynamical meaning of a game
to a greater or lesser extent,
depending on how much authorial influence
we sort of try to exert over those parts of the game.
There's another really important factor
that can influence how games mean,
and this one is really, really different
than the other two.
Street Fighter is...
Very obviously, a game about reflexes, precision, timing,
pattern recognition, anticipation, et cetera.
But what's critically important to understand is that it's
fundamentally not about a battle between Ken and Ryu.
It's about a battle between two players, right?
And more importantly, between their perspectives on what the
game is about.
Competitive pressure has a massive impact on how games
mean in general, and also on how a specific game means.
And a close examination of competition
also reveals that unique meaning
also exists within specific instances of a game.
When two players sit around and talk about
their beliefs about what a game means,
that's sort of one thing, right?
But when they test their perspectives
against one another in direct competition,
their ideas enter into a kind of literalized debate
over what the game means.
In 1938, the respected Go master Honinbo Shusai...
played a retirement game against up-and-coming star Minoru Kitani.
The match was covered for the Japanese press by Yasunori Kawabata,
who would later go on to win the Nobel Prize for Literature
and be recognized as one of the greatest Japanese authors.
Taking his reportage of the game and other notes,
in 1951 Kawabata published a chronicle novel of the match titled Meijin.
The English title of the book is The Master of Go.
At the heart of the story, and at the heart of the match that the story is about,
The expression of these two players' personalities and their embodiment of a sort of shift in Japanese culture from the conservative, honorable, and sort of artistic, classical, imperial Japan to the sort of, you know, progressive, pragmatic, and industrious culture of modern Japan.
Admittedly, these ideas are kind of pretty cliched now, but when you take into account the historical context, the match itself was sort of played just before World War II or at the very start.
and that the novel was written after, these kinds of ideas are the real deal.
It's not sort of like tacky, you know, the tacky cyberpunk version of those concepts, right?
Now, Go is actually a really simple game in one sense.
It has only nine mechanics.
That's them. I'm not going to read them.
Because Go games can reasonably last for dozens of hours, however,
there are also rules for tournaments that govern how long each player is allowed to play.
consider his move and rules for how moves are sealed prior to the adjournment of a play
session just like you would have in chess or whatever, right? In the case of the match
in question, the way the rules worked was, you know, sealing a movement, writing it down,
and then giving that move to a judge so that neither side would have the advantage of having
hours or days to think about what their next move would be, right? My move would be determined
and the other player wouldn't be able to know my move until the play started, so he wouldn't
be able to think about his next move for days or weeks.
So the question is, how do we get from a few very simple and abstract rules to a game about
the shift of cultural values that took place in 20th century Japan? I mean, that's a pretty
monumental theme, right? And in order to answer that question, we have to, again, like we
tried to do in the Tetris example, we have to observe the game at runtime, right? So
here's how the game unfolded. I'm sorry if you don't understand Go at all, but we're
going to go a bit deep into it.
Although I don't think an understanding, a deep appreciation of the rules is that necessary
for me to get you through this.
Around the middle of the game at the 120th move, the board looked like this.
The master was playing white and it was the master's turn, right?
So he moved right there.
Now, what's important here, and I'm not a great Go player, really, but my understanding
is that this sort of formation of white pieces is sort of offensively aggressive, but it's
defensively weak.
and as a consequence, it sets a tone for a skirmish
that is gonna happen in this area of the board, right?
This move is effectively the master saying,
all right, we've now sort of gotten to the midgame,
if you want, and we're entering into the battle
that's gonna determine the outcome
of the entire rest of this game.
It's a really important move
because he's sort of making a claim
about what territory he thinks he's gonna be able to grab
in this middle part of the game,
and it's gonna determine how the rest of the game goes.
how the challenger is going to respond to this move is just as important.
And the challenger thought about his move for over an hour and a half
until that day was done.
And so he sealed his move and they adjourned.
So two days later, when they returned to the match,
the judge unsealed the move, and to everyone's surprise,
the judge had a really hard time finding where the move was, right?
That's because instead of moving in this really important battleground
where, you know, the guy was supposed to move
and everyone thought he was going to move,
and where everyone sort of knows that the climactic moves of the game are about to take place,
he actually moved up here. See that black stone there?
At first blush, this is a strange move.
Not because it's a bad move, but because it's a bookkeeping move.
It's kind of like, you know, when Tiger misses a putt,
and then just walks up and taps the ball into the cup,
and we don't worry about the fact that it wasn't his turn,
and it's just a little tap-in, and we're done.
It's a bookkeeping move. It just gets things moving along.
The point is that these eight stones, eight white stones up here belonging to the master,
are not technically safe from capture.
But practically speaking, any threat to these stones is immediately answered with another
necessary and mandatory bookkeeping move from the master that guarantees their survival.
The master moved there.
So, essentially what was happening is that by making that bookkeeping move in the sealed play,
he was forcing the master to make his own bookkeeping move.
heaping move in response, giving him two days to think about what he was going to do when
he moved in that big open battlefield in the middle. Now, because the move was sealed,
yeah, he bought himself two days. And to us today, right, we look at that and we go, oh,
yeah, very clever, you know, good move, dude. This is what the master had to say, though,
in 1938. He said, the match is over. Kitani ruined it with that sealed play. It was like
smearing ink over the picture we had painted.
The minute I saw it, I felt like forfeiting the match, like telling them that was the last straw.
I really thought I should forfeit, but I hesitated, and that was that."
To the master, the move is ugly, right?
The master values these conservative, honorable, artistic, cultural ideals of classical Japan.
And his play style, and consequently the way he expresses himself through play, reflects these ideals, right?
He sees the game not only as a competition, but as a work of art that the two men are creating together.
Calabada, the author, sort of restated this point, and you have to take this as editorializing
anyways, but he said, that play of black upon white, white upon black, has the intent and
makes the form of creative, and takes the form of creative art. It has in it a flow
of the spirit and a harmony of music, as of music. Everything is lost when suddenly a
false note is struck, or one party in a duet suddenly launches forth on an eccentric flight
on his own.
A masterpiece of a game can be ruined by insensitivity to the feelings of an adversary.
The challenger, by contrast, is progressive and pragmatic and industrious.
He takes a pragmatic approach to a fairly obvious problem.
He does not violate any rules, right?
In fact, he doesn't even think that what he has done is in any way wrong, right?
This is just the way he sees the game.
The way the game player system behaves at run time for the challenger.
is different from the way the game player system behaves at runtime for the master.
Consequently, the master lost the match by five points and was dead a year later.
Now let me be clear. Go is not about the conflict between conservative, honorable, artistic,
cultural, classical Japan, right? And progressive, pragmatic, industrious culture of modern
Japan, right? This one game of Go, however, this instance of Go...
was about that. And this leads me to make sort of three points about meaning in competitive
play. First, meaning is synthetic. And by synthetic, I don't mean artificial like polyester,
right? I mean it's created by the synthesis of two players' perspectives on the game's
dynamical meaning. I mean it in the dialectic sense, right? One player's perspective on
the meaning is a sort of thesis. The other player's is the antithesis. And the resultant
meaning is the negotiated meaning that is synthesized in the dynamics at runtime.
Second, meaning is rigorous.
By this I mean that how seriously the two players invest in the ludic contract determines the rigor of that synthesis, right?
In a sense, the two conceptions of meaning are competing for survival, I think is a way of looking at it.
If the two players are like kids playing badminton in grandma's backyard on the 4th of July,
then the synthesis is really not very rigorous and the meaning is not very important.
If the two players are Djokovic and Federer, then a single shot has the capability to literally
make nations question their very cultural identity.
Finally, meaning in competitive play is instantial.
By this I mean that the dynamical meaning of a competitive game is not inherent to the
game necessarily, but to the instance of the game being played.
So while it's hard to talk about how Go means for the same reason it's hard to talk about
how Tetris means, we can talk about how a specific game of Go means.
based on how the game is played by its participants.
All right.
So over the last, what, I don't know, seven or eight minutes,
I've talked about how meaning is generated in dynamics
and about a few ways we can influence
that meaning as designers.
Now, I'm going to be the first to admit that this stuff is
neither incredibly mind-blowing, and it's not really
all that useful in a practical sense.
But neither is long division, and I
think both are really important.
Understanding long division.
is important because it helps establish a framework in the developing brains of kids
in like grade three or whatever that they will build on for the rest of their lives.
It's the same with understanding how games mean because that framework is going to shape
our industry and our medium and the psychological and possibly neurological structures that
we develop to parse it for decades or centuries to come. In 1991, following the collapse of
its primary trade partner, the Soviet Union,
Cuba lost 80% of its imports and exports and its GDP dropped by a third.
Even worse, because they were energy dependent on the Soviets, their oil imports dropped by 90%.
We now refer to this period euphemistically as the Special Period.
Without fuel for farm vehicles or access to petroleum-based fertilizers or pesticides,
Cuba's entire food production industry completely collapsed.
Now, since that industry was basically entirely based on growing sugar to trade for Soviet
oil, it didn't really matter that much because the oil wasn't coming anyway and you can't
fuel cars with sugar and you can't eat it either, contrary to popular belief. But between
1991, when food shortages began, and 1995, when they sort of started to come under control,
the average Cuban lost over 20 pounds. This was probably the best thing to happen to Cuba
ever.
The Cuban people adapted and overcame most of the difficulties, but by far the most important adaptation was the invention of the organoponikos.
Organoponikos are a system of organic urban agriculture that arose from the bottom up when individuals and communities in the urban areas started reclaiming land for use, growing food in response to the food shortages.
Today, there are over 7,000 organoponikos in Cuba.
And in Havana alone, over 200 such urban organic gardens
provide 90% of the fruit and vegetables consumed
by the population of 2 and 1 half million people.
This is what happens when massive industrial era
networks fail.
Their former customers reappropriate
the abandoned networks and start pushing value back up
into them.
This is what happened in Cuba, and it
is what would be happening here now if time traveling Einstein
hadn't thwarted Edison's plan to put a power
station every three kilometers.
so that pushing energy back up into the grid from solar, wind, or community bike programs
or whatever would actually be sort of a normal situation. And, you know, maybe you're sitting
there saying, you know, this dude's been living in San Francisco for too long, but just as
Organic Pornicos and distributed energy grids force us to question our aging paradigms of
industry and energy and agriculture by showing us the power of bottom-up systems.
Games are also forcing us to question our aging concept of art.
And it turns out that's okay,
because apparently we're all really good at making art.
Dynamism in art and entertainment is not a feature, right?
It's not something that you add to a game.
Dynamism is the fundamental driver of how games mean and why they matter.
It is the reactor core of what we do,
and it is already changing the world faster than we can keep up with it.
Dynamism is revolution.
Thanks.
So I have more time than I thought I would have for questions.
So I guess you guys can nail me to the wall now.
Are there mics?
There's mics there and there.
Yeah.
So Clint, great talk.
I'm just interested.
Your Tetris example was really striking,
and yet it seems in some ways to sort of undermine your point,
as I understand it, in that the story shows
that the dynamics of the game actually
can be subjugated by the story and not, you know,
be the direct meaning of the game.
I'm not phrasing that well, but I think you see where I'm going.
Yeah, no, I don't feel that using the narrative layer
is necessarily subjugating the dynamics in the way you say.
I'm trying to draw a parallel between the kinds
of authorial control we have to influence dynamics.
One of those ways is by
more heavily authoring into our mechanics by authoring rules that constrain the dynamics
into a certain set or only allow certain dynamical things to happen. Another way you can do it
is by putting things into the narrative that constrain the likely behaviors of the player.
So I guess what I'm saying overall is that, you know, we have this core meaning generation
mechanism which is dynamics and like in film you have
different elements that you can leverage to change the way that lowest level thing generates
meaning that resonates outward. One of those things is mechanics and how you offer them.
Another of those things is narrative. And a third thing that actually you have absolutely
no control over is when dynamics are being generated between two players or multiple
players. Does that clarify that for you?
Yeah, absolutely. Thanks.
Okay. Yep.
Hey Clint, Trent Custers. I was just got a question about Far Cry 2 and the dynamics in multiplayer that arise from the mechanics as opposed to the single player experience.
And how do you, I guess, control or track how much the dynamics of the experience from the competitive side, because as you've just said, it's a much different experience.
And how do you make sure that you're not just creating a completely different game?
Far Cry 2 was something that I absolutely loved and played to death, but multiplayer.
didn't appeal to me because I felt that those dynamics didn't carry across.
So, unfortunately, the answer... So, for those who didn't quite hear the question...
Did people over here hear the question or...
Okay, because I didn't hear it super well.
Unfortunately, the answer to your question isn't an interesting theoretical answer
about how we should balance, you know, ways competitive meaning
and ways, you know, narrative-influenced and mechanically-influenced meaning connect.
The answer to your question is, do a better job of managing your multiplayer dev in parallel
with your single player dev. And I actually, I wish I could give you a better answer, and
probably there is a better answer. We just completely failed to do that well. So I didn't,
I don't understand the problem well enough to answer the question in the way I would
like. I apologize.
I appreciate it. Thanks, Clint.
And I apologize that it wasn't better. You can blame me. Yeah.
Hey, my name is Eric. I'm an MFA Game Design student and researcher at Parsons in New York.
Just to clarify about your manifesto, is this a call to arms to games researchers to forge the new way,
or is this a call to arms for the industry to change the way, or is it sort of a mix and match of both?
I don't think there's a call to arms here. I just think we need to...
I think we don't understand the way Kuleshov understood or the way a modern...
Like, Kuleshov figured out.
how film means in its most fundamental way.
There's some probably debate about different flavors of that,
whatever, that's fine.
We haven't had our Kuleshov yet.
No one has really figured out how,
at the lowest level, dynamics generate meaning.
I'm trying to touch on some of that stuff here
and get people to think about framing the problem in the right way
so we can try to understand it better
and literalize it a little more and learn from it.
As a consequence, though, of Kuleshov figuring it out,
We now live in a world where, like, I guarantee you when, I don't know, famous, when George
Lucas makes a movie, my boss, right, I guarantee you when he makes a movie, he isn't thinking
about low-level editing in this kind of abstract sense as being meaning generating.
He has completely internalized that process.
The same way when you see footage that's being cut back and forth and edited on a screen,
you read it and you understand it, right?
So there's an entire universe of people who have internalized how film editing generates
meaning and it's just part of our understanding of the world. We don't even realize we speak
this language. We haven't arrived there yet for games. There are people who are, I think,
starting to figure it out and who are starting to experiment with it and illustrate some
things that are very interesting. But even as professional developers, we have a hard
time reading this language. We have a hard time writing in this language.
And, you know, it's not a call to arms, it's just a here's the domain of this problem that we need to look carefully at from all kinds of different directions, I think, over the next few years.
Right. So the chance to define this vocabulary, there's an opportunity and potential to, and that's pretty much what you're saying, right?
Sorry, I couldn't hear.
There's still a potential and the opportunity to define these vocabulary.
that kind of show. Absolutely, absolutely. Yeah, this is, it's still very largely undefined.
Most of the terrain is unexplored and I think we need to keep exploring. Great, thanks.
Good. There's a guy here who's been there for a while. Hey, uh, great lecture. Um, I
uh, I may just have not gotten the Kuselov thing. I understood and really appreciated
the um, the, the, for game, uh, for game design, the narrative being the skin and the mechanics
being underneath. I thought that was...
I think that was the whole point for me for this lecture.
But I didn't quite get the narrative versus editing for film, because it seems to me that
the editing is kind of a tool of the narrative.
So I was just wondering if you could maybe re-explain exactly what the relationship was
between narrative and editing in film?
Okay.
Yeah, I'm not a film theorist deeply, but I don't believe that editing is a tool of
the narrative.
I believe that editing...
I think it's like, that would be like saying that the Lego pieces are tools of the Lego spaceship, right?
I think that editing, when you cut a person's face looking at a flower and it creates some kind of feeling,
that is a building block which we then piece together to create something larger.
And we can, when an editor sits down, yes he has a map which is the narrative,
but I don't believe that, I don't believe that...
I don't believe that the meaning comes from the narrative down into the low level editing.
I believe that there are these raw elemental chunks of meaning and feeling that we sequence
together and then we put into an overarching framework.
So yeah, I just don't believe that that's the case.
I think editing by itself makes people feel things in interesting ways and having an overarching
story and scenes and stuff like that that we plug this stuff into.
allows us to sustain having these kinds of feelings
in a meaningful way for a long enough period of time
that we can call that a whole experience.
That kind of answer your question?
Well, so wouldn't you determine how to edit a film
based on kind of the narrative and the,
like, what would you call then
what drives the way that you edit the film
if it's not the narrative?
It would be, I guess, the vision,
some sort of thing like that, right?
Yeah, I mean, I don't.
Obviously there's a director who has a vision who's trying to make something meaningful.
I don't think that you... I've never edited a film.
I don't think that you... Yeah, I'm just not an expert on this.
I can't really speak to your point. Sorry.
Okay. Thanks, though.
Yeah.
Good talk.
So I'm wondering, do you have, like, an understanding of a generalized way to go from...
Like, so you know what the purpose of the game is that you're trying to make, but you
want to know where on that scale of authorship you want to place it.
How do you decide that?
Do you have, like, an optimal way of deciding that?
There is no optimal way.
It's a personal decision, I think, for any developer.
Like, if you're the kind of developer who wants to really heavily author an experience,
you have the tools to do that.
And certainly we're actually quite good at that.
Um, that's not the approach I prefer to take. You may be the kind of developer who likes to give away as much of the meaning generating stuff to the player as possible.
Um, that's the approach I, I, I, I like in the games I make and in the games I play.
Um, how do you do it? Um, so I can only speak to how I do it, but I mean, you...
OK, to answer the question kind of quickly,
you give away as much autonomy to the people who work under you
and with you on your team, and you encourage them to give away
as much autonomy to the people who work around them
and with them on the larger part of the team.
And then you encourage that philosophy
to spread outward until it encompasses players.
It really sounds like a Hallmark card or something,
but it's like, in my perspective and what I believe,
And what I feel in my experience is that the more you give, the more you get back.
Um, and I just try to give away as much as I can.
All right. Thanks.
Yeah.
Don't do that if you want to control everything, though,
because that would... then you would fail.
Ha!
Yeah.
Um...
Uh, I guess...
I guess we're done.
Okay, go have lunch.
I'll take your question.