Good afternoon, everybody, and welcome to this session about the art of Child of Light.
So, to make sure that everybody knows what the game looks like,
let me take two minutes to play to you our reveal trailer.
Child, tuck yourself in bed.
Let me tell a story of Lemuria, a kingdom past, and a girl born for glory.
Lost from our world came she.
Treachery gave close chase.
She raised her sword and flew, for she feared not the race.
Three long lost lights to save.
A mad queen to defeat.
The journey we transform her.
Her destiny to meet.
The path home tragic and faint.
Beware the night, child of light.
So in this talk, I'm going to talk about first what inspired
me at the start of the project.
So I spent a couple of months just looking at pretty pictures
to get inspired.
So we're going to talk about what were those
and why did they inspire me.
Then after that, the various iteration that we add
on the R direction to reach the final product.
So it's been a bumpy road a little bit
to be able to find the R identity.
And finally, we'll talk about how we did the tribulation
or the trial and tribulation to create a main character that
is not a badass space marine.
So yeah.
OK, so in terms of inspiration, in 2007,
personally, I like to visit museums when I'm on vacation.
That's what I like to do.
And especially every time I could
travel on different cities for maybe press stores or stuff
like that, I love to drop by some museum and watch some art.
And in 2007, in Montreal, there was a show, an exposition on Walt Disney as the source of his inspiration.
And that's where I, you know, because Disney in the 1920s went across Europe,
and he collected art and books to build the Disney library.
And in those art pieces, there's a lot of illustration from the period called the Golden Age of Illustration.
So that's like a 40-year period at the end of the 19th century, beginning of the 20th,
where books were really popular, and the quality of books, of printing, really increased.
And for children's books especially, there was a need to do a lot of drawings,
because it's a little bit like books today.
for children, there's like an image per two pages or an image per page.
So the quality bar really raised and some
of those artists really brought the art of
illustration and watercolour to really high level.
You know, we can think about Arthur Rackham, for example.
He did illustration for Alice in Wonderland,
or he illustrated the Wagner Opera
on the cycle of the ring.
Edmond Dulac, he really had that sense of romantism
in his art.
The one with the cape, for me, there's a sense of,
there's a promise of adventure.
I was really allured to...
on that style.
Kane Nielsen, interesting fact on him,
he actually worked at Disney on the concept
for the backgrounds on the movie Sleeping Beauty.
So if you look at Sleeping Beauty,
you're going to see that art being on display.
And of course, Disney, what he did is he collected those pieces and he created its own, like, Disney genre with it.
And for me, that was, you know, really something inspiring.
John Bauer, an artist from Sweden, and for me, that was my, you know, the one that I liked the most.
I really liked this little creature.
Here you see, you know, dwarves and trolls.
It's really different than what you see from the traditional Tolkien-esque dwarves and trolls.
So for me that was kind of like a reinvention, well it's returning to an older era to rediscover
those, that type of fantasy. Especially if you look at the main character, we're going to talk
about it a little bit later, but you can already see some of the things I'm going to talk later.
And finally, it's a more contemporary artist, but Yoshitaka Zamano, especially his fairy book.
So he made a book where he illustrated fairy tales, one painting per fairy tale.
And for me, I really loved being able to be drawn to those universes.
In one image, and reading the text, the poems.
you would be completely enveloped by that universe.
And that's basically what we're making when we're making games.
We're creating a universe and we're inviting players in.
And for me, that's exactly the vibe I wanted to touch.
And at the back of the fairies book, there's a quote that for me was like it really crystallized my decision to make this game, which is, you cannot paint fairies without entering their world and believing in them.
And that's really what I wanted to do. I wanted to create something that would be a little bit like a flower, precious, delicate. And to do that, I wanted to do that without any irony.
because you know at the end of the day you can be the little fairy game and
people you know everywhere can dismiss as the fairy game
and if it's not done with like uh... something where it's really sincere
yes I think it's open for criticism
but I think you can feel it when
you're
at least for me I really wanted to believe in it, believe in magic
believe that this world is real so that it creates something of value.
So this quote really for me was something where it's like, yes...
I believe in fairies, and let's make it happen on screen and let people see that world that exists.
And the thing is, for fairy tales, what I like about them is the use of symbols.
There's a lot of symbols in fairy tales, and that's why those stories really...
capture the emanation, well, went through the age. Nobody knows who, you know, who came
up with Cinderella, for example. It's a hundreds-year-old tale that has been told from generation to
generation. And most of them are symbols about the passage from being a child to an adult.
I'm telling you how it is going to be a little bit later.
You're going to go through a dark forest.
And at the end, it's going to be OK or not.
Because sometimes the world is really cruel.
And you can be eaten by that big, bad wolf.
So be careful of those big, bagged wolf.
And at the same time, RPGs.
And I'm a huge, huge, huge fan of the console type or Japanese type RPG.
And they're about growing stats.
So you're small, and you're weak, and you become strong.
And in a fairy tale, you would start as a child and finish as an adult.
So for me, I was really interested into the parallel between both.
So I knew I could make a game that would make sense narratively
and with gameplay.
So for me, it made a lot of sense.
And in a vibe where, for me, the importance was to create a playable poem.
So maybe, you know, it sounds ambitious or...
But the idea is to make something that would be delicate.
That's the goal.
So, you know, let's go there.
I want to make...
And that angle really forged everything
about the choice of music, the art style,
and even the story, which in the end,
we had the whole game written in verse, even.
And I knew I would be able to use the UB art framework.
So I had some friends in Montpellier,
like, send them a couple of email, send me the...
the engine and it's like okay this is what I'm going to use
and the thing that's interesting with the engine is that
we could finally...
instead of going with a pixelized version of concept art,
we could actually display the concept art straight in-game.
So, one of the first things that I pitched to people is like,
what if we make Final Fantasy VI but with Amano's concept art
instead of the pixel version?
So then people could really start to create a sense of what that game could be.
And I even made a little creative director concept using John Bower's painting.
It's like, okay, you know what? It's going to look like a side scroller.
It's going to feel a little bit like this.
And that's like the initial...
At that point, basically, I was alone with my little PowerPoint pitch
and trying to lure people to come join my project.
So then, you know, we went to Conception. That's when we started to have some people joining in,
especially one guy that is extremely talented. He's right now in Montreal. We're finishing,
we're in the final days of the production. Thomas Relous, our art director. Just to tell you
like the skill level before that, he's the guy that created the art style for Just Dance.
We went from Just Dance to Child of Light, so his palette is really wide.
He's a maestro.
So he joined the project and he started to build the pillars of the art direction.
So the first one, fluidity, a sense of illustration.
He wanted to make something that is contemporary
and to use the inversion of convention to create the feeling of a magical world.
Fluidity is for something really important because,
and one of the example here is by using
kind of the logic of your, the sense of caustic
that you had underwater,
and you recreate that using the trees.
So then you're not underwater,
but you have that sense that,
you know what, this place is ethereal.
Same thing with fluid.
So then early on, we really talked
about how could we create a sense of fluidity in the game?
Once again, feeling like we're underwater
to create that sense of a magical place.
And so we started to do some concept art.
And the idea was to use those concept art directly in game.
So that's one of the first one, an altar in a forest.
Then, you know, giant trees we could go inside.
Interior of a cavern.
Another part of the forest.
So, and finally, I wanted to have, like,
that thing where it's, like, a giant where,
in level design, I'd be able to walk on him.
So that idea for me was really interesting.
So we used those to create our target render.
So to show to upper management what the game, the final game, would look like really early.
So it gives us a good milestone for moving in production and test it.
So I'm going to show it to you, what we've shown to...
That's in February 2013, so a little bit more than a year ago.
Way, way, way back when I was very young, long before you were born, there was a magical
kingdom called Lemuria.
Thanks for watching.
So, I was really proud of that video.
And so we went to Paris to talk about the...
We received some feedback.
And the feedback we received is,
the game is, you know, it's going to be beautiful.
But at this point, it would need a clearer sense
of visual identity.
Right now, the feedback was, we can only say,
oh, it's beautiful.
And the example was, in Limbo, it's clear.
It's black and white.
So if you have two people that, you know.
talk about, hey, I played a beautiful game yesterday, what is it? Oh, it's the black and white game.
And you know, it's Limbo. So they wanted us to continue, push, and to find a style that would be unique
and be able to be told in, like, one word.
And I said, Limbo is black and white, it's three words. But anyway.
And the second feedback is there's a sense of the need
to create a stronger main character.
And I think especially because we're
far away from having the badass space marine,
then it's like, OK, so yes, it's not
going to be a badass space marine, but can you find?
a main character that could be an icon for the game.
I think for...
So that's the feedback we took.
And really, like for me, it's time to return back to research and to just dig,
to see where we can go with it.
Worst case, we're just going to continue with our art style.
But can we push, can we use that as a challenge to push ourselves
to reach a higher quality for the art in the game?
So we returned for the art research. That was like a tense period because you don't want to arrive and go like,
okay, we start from the beginning, everybody.
Because, you know, everybody would start panicking. It's like, no, let's do some research for a couple of weeks.
So we took like, you know, a month, and we just went into any direction possible to make sure we would be able to capture the...
the right mood. So that's one of the examples using trees that would look a little bit more like
you know, Chinese ink. Another one, that's one from our director. So his personal style is a
little bit more graphic. So he wanted to like, let me try something a little bit more graphic
with it. And Ae-Joon Ji, one of our artists, she drew this. And I was like,
I liked it, except that I felt like it was, you know, lacking a little bit of drama.
So I asked her and Thomas, they sat down and then they iterated on it.
And also I wanted to make sure that we had a character in it so that we felt,
I could feel that the character would belong in that world.
So this is what they come up with, and this is where I, you know, instantly fell in love with the art style.
And we integrated one character from John Bauer illustration in.
And that's when I really knew that going with a watercolor art style, you know, would be the style we need to push.
And then the thing was just to make sure
that we could reproduce that art style multiple times
on multiple environments.
So that's what we did the next month.
So that's the example for a village
that we'll meet in the game.
After that, a bridge with a strange creature behind.
A forest.
Another bridge.
And finally, I don't know why, but I love hot air balloons.
For me, they're kind of magical.
So we had hot air balloons floating over the forest.
So with that, I knew we could reproduce that style
and use it, use those assets in-game for Child of Light.
And that would be our identity.
The water will be the watercolor game.
So I'm going to take a couple of minutes to talk about what's the process between when I say we use the concept art directly in game, what's the process in terms of production to achieve that result.
So basically...
Thomas, what he did is he just did mood boards.
So basically, at that point, the story was already written.
So we knew everything that we, all the environments
we needed to produce.
So for example, that's the forest at the beginning.
So he creates those mood boards and a little doodle
of what the forest could be, or some assets.
And then he let the artist create the concept art.
So we would spend some time, make some beautiful paintings.
And that would actually inspire level design in their work.
And that's a screenshot from the editor.
So the level designers would just basically make their level.
And they could use the key art, the concept art behind
to help give a sense of where we are, where that place is.
use that to inspire themselves in devil design.
So for example, the altar, the bridge, the tree,
and where we would pick up the sword inside the magical tree.
And after that, what Thomas did is he took that screenshot,
put it in Photoshop, and he directly painted it over
to make a quick paint over to give to the artists
so that they will be able to fill the whole environment
and to get the final result.
And he would integrate the concept art
so you could see the tree with light, the tree bridge.
So you could get a sense that suddenly all those concept art would be well integrated and create a cohesive environment.
So once again, I'm going to give you another example from our second region, the plains.
So that's the point of reference that we have in terms of visual, that the art is the color palette you want it to have.
Then in terms of concept art, we painted some ant ailes,
and we could see a giant in the distance, some wind wheels,
that we could do some level design in it.
Then level designers would sketch out a rough map and us,
and we could get.
That one especially, the first time I saw it in-game, I was like,
okay, where is it going? I don't know.
You're playing in it and it's really abstract, but then as soon as Toma did this paint-over,
it's like, ah, this is going to be a really awesome place to play in.
And finally, that's the look in-game that we achieved for this region.
So that's the process that we went through for production.
And basically, we could use the concept art even
to inspire level design.
But also, you could use those assets directly in game.
So that's for the art style, the watercolor art style.
That one was relatively easy to nail down,
especially in terms of it was following
the original inspiration.
For the main character, it was way difficult
for us, at least for me and Thomas.
So in terms of first iteration, you saw her in
the fake footage or the target footage.
So at the beginning, you know, we had that name, Aurora,
because, you know, it's the beginning of the day,
the sun comes, and for me, in terms of...
Sorry, I'm not English, it's my first language.
But, you know, in terms of meaning, it's, you know,
she will bring hope, you know, from the darkest of night,
then the little girl would bring hope to a magical world.
So that's where the name comes from.
And we looked up, and then Aurora is also a butterfly.
It's the beginning of the day.
For me, there was a sense of the redhead, red hair girl,
who's soft and delicate.
For me, that was somebody that would
be appropriate for the game.
So we started to sketch out some characters.
At the same time, you could see that it's
difficult to create.
kind of like a clear image of who those characters are.
But we still managed to make, like, one key art
that would be our main character.
I really, I liked her.
You know, she was soft, dreamy, hopeful.
So, you know, for me, that, you know, she was great.
Except for one thing, where we couldn't have long hair.
with the 2D character.
And we were talking about fluidity
and the fact that it would float and be magical.
But in 2D, they really look like little cardboard air.
So it didn't work.
So we went with, OK, let's make some first sacrifice.
Let's go with a shorter air version.
And we really looked at various, how can we bring that character, what's the right type of haircut.
And the one at the bottom, my lead programmer is not going to like it because one artist drew her for inspiration, but she looks great.
So that's the design we proposed for the target footage.
So I still think it's a great character, but the feedback was to go a bit further, to create
something that would be even more iconic.
So we went with it and started to look for a second iteration.
And that second iteration, it was difficult because one of the feedback is like, ah, she's
not badass.
So then suddenly you have that thing in your head.
she needs to be badass.
And then you have the people that goes like, oh,
but look at all those female characters.
They're all badass.
It's all great.
And then you're like, oh, badass, badass.
But it's like, no, no, no.
I don't want.
So that was that thing where it was difficult to balance
between.
So then we looked at something a little bit more
with a little bit of attitude and then even with some armor.
But then it was really difficult to balance
between a little doll.
and Jeanne d'Arc.
So at least either she was a warrior or she was that princess.
That's one of the latest ones in terms of those faces that I like,
but in game it didn't work.
She was just looking like a little Barbie with a sword,
and it wasn't necessarily what I liked.
Even though in those pictures I really liked the attitude and...
And if you noticed here, Selenish has long hair in those concepts.
Because there's a point where it's like, I don't care how we're going to make it.
I want long hair.
And especially because we started to look at Disney's Princess, and it's like I had
some Ariel envy.
It's like, I want the hair from Little Mermaid, it's so beautiful!
You don't hear that probably when you make Call of Duty.
But so you get the idea.
They're super well animated.
And it's like, it's magical.
It's like, can we make this?
And it's like, I don't care if we'll find a way.
But first, let's go back with long hair,
aurora, that's the direction I want.
And then we'll find a solution.
So at the same time, Jeffrey O'Hallem, the writer on the project, he came back from Japan
and he brought, I'm a huge Final Fantasy fan, so he brought me some little figurines.
And I was like, oh man, how come the, you know, Square, they can make like, like tens
of iconic characters, I can't make one.
So I start to be very obsessed about those little box.
And there's like one thing that started to pop with me,
especially those, because they're not even close to what
they look in game.
They're really small, like one inch figurine,
and they're really abstract.
And I kind of start thinking about, you know what?
What they're doing great is that they can define iconic trait
so that whatever how the figurine would look,
it would be the same character.
So for example, Zidane from Final Nine.
He has, you know, every character in those little box, they all have a different haircut.
Every one of them has a different haircut.
And so it's well defined.
And he has a puffy shirt, the long tail, and a dual sword.
So even on those two figurines, there are completely two styles, but then you can recognize,
oh, you know what, this is Zidane from Final 9, and in-game it doesn't even look like him.
So it's like, okay, so we need to define what are the iconic things that our character has.
And at the same time, I return to John Bauer.
Like, it's returning to the roots.
And there was one story where, in that story,
the little princess grew from being a child to an adult.
So I just created this collage, in fact, of pictures.
And it jumped to me.
I can see that it's the same character, because
throughout the adventure, she has the same crown.
Well, she has a crown, she has the long, blond hair,
and a white dress.
So.
What I did is that I went to Thomas and said,
hey Thomas, check this little character from John Bauer.
Can you just do me a little doodle about somebody
that would have a crown, long hair, little dress,
and a sword.
Took him like five minutes.
And he drew me this.
And I was like, OK, I love this.
Boom.
So we did actually like many drawings of different things,
and it took five minutes to fall in love with the character.
So the next step would be, how would she
look in the environment?
So we asked Serge Merino to draw her in color
and with the final result.
So here you can see she had the crown, the long flowing hair, the dress and the sword and then she had a little spunky attitude.
And even though it's not necessarily badass, then already you see this and you love that character.
And at that point, nobody asked why I'm not playing a little boy.
Once you have a cool character...
that people can identify with and love, or it's strong,
then the gender or whoever that person is, it's irrelevant.
So original image with the second character, Nicholas,
in, I mean, it's just perfect.
For me, it was perfect.
Same thing here on the bridge.
So and the other thing is.
I was like, before we had that version of Aurora that would be already close to be a
woman.
So what if we just go instead and actually make her grow physically in a game, so the
metaphor is going to be stronger.
So that's the design that we have.
And in the game, she is actually going
through her various phase.
And then at the end, she is the white queen of Lemuria.
And you can see also it's reflected in the dialogue.
So we drew that and go, this is going to be perfect.
And it's, once again, reminiscent of the John Bower
illustrated story, the fairy tales.
I was really happy with this direction.
And.
But so basically, OK, so once again,
how are we going to achieve that Ariel feeling in the game?
And so we start talking about that with programmers.
We're like, OK, what can we do with the engine
or push technology?
And one Monday morning, our architect, 3D architect Jeff
Breschin, he said, oh, Pat, I coded a little something
yesterday.
So I'm not encouraging overtime, but he really
wanted to work on a Sunday morning to code that.
So he said, I have a little something playable to show you.
You want to see it?
And this is the prototype that he showed me
that Monday morning.
I saw this and I said, yes, finally.
You need to make that leap of faith.
But you could see that the fluid interacting with the air.
And you go like, oh, yeah, I can project that eventually they're
not going to look like spaghettis.
Are you sure, Jeff, it's not going to look like spaghettis?
Oh, yeah, I think so.
OK, great.
So basically, this is what we're going to do.
So instead of going, like, it's impossible,
then by letting people come with solution,
when we are talking about a vision,
then magic happen in this case.
We're really lucky to have an amazing team to work with.
It would require to move the character to be 3D, however.
So that was a risk.
And also a risk in terms of production,
because it would actually take three months for him
to code to work.
It's not three months.
In three months, it's going to be fully polished.
And we were on a year-long production.
So we would take the best programmer
that we have for three months to see
if it's going to work in-game.
But.
It was totally worth the investment so we went with it and yes, Ariel happened.
So the final result, so we went from the two characters,
the first iteration, still like her,
but I think that the second one is a more iconic character.
I'm really, really happy with that evolution in design.
I think that the way we were challenged
was the right challenge to give us.
And I was really happy to have decided to answer the call.
And one of the things that happened is, so we released the first trailer and since then
we got a lot of fan art.
I'm really happy about that.
And you can see it, that whatever the style that the artist decided to depict Aurora,
you can see that it's still the same, you know, it's the same character, because people
understand.
Even the last one, this one is my favorite.
It's been the one from the little child.
That's Salome Strapazone, one of our artists, little daughter.
She's like a four-year-old.
And she decided to make a little drawing of Aura fighting monsters.
And at that point, you're like, yes, that's the character.
So on that side, I think, at least for me, it's great.
It's just great to be able to see that people want
to participate or push them to paint or draw that character.
So it's really humbling on our side.
So to conclude.
The thing is, that talk for me was difficult at first to write because I didn't draw a
single art piece in the game.
So I'm going to talk about the art.
I really want to thank the artists of Child of Light, Thomas Rollus, John B. Garn, Ajunji,
Young Jin Theo, Serge Merino, Nicolas Roque, Elie Recre, Vivant Recre, and Salomé Strapazon.
It's their work that is going to make Shadow of Light so unique, so vibrant.
And every time that somebody is telling me how it's going to be, the game is going to be great,
I just hope that the game is going to be.
as fun as it is beautiful because they really brought like artistry in this game.
I just went with that little vision of like, let's make a game that would be a playable painting
and they just created the art that is, at least for me, it's really touching.
I just want to finish with some IRS screenshot that we took straight from the engine last week
sitting with Thomas.
And I really think that that vibe of creating a painting
was really achieved by our artist.
So that's it for the Art of Childhood Light.
Thank you very much.
So we have time, sir, for some questions.
And you can go get the microphone.
And please state your name if you want to,
so that it's there for posterity because it's filmed.
Yes.
Hello.
I'm Sonja van Vuren.
I've got a terrible cold, sorry.
I was wondering if, like, everything
is made with real watercolor.
If what?
OK, if it's made with watercolor?
Yeah.
No, it's made with Photoshop.
But no, what we actually did is Nicola Roque,
one of our artists, he actually did some watercolor spots.
So he painted a bunch of spots.
We scanned them, and we could use that for our brush.
OK, like texture brushes and stuff.
OK, awesome stuff.
Thanks.
Yes.
Hello.
I just wanted to ask you, since you're probably all fans of Final Fantasy, and like when I
saw the little child with the really big sword, so that was part of the inspiration to see
Cloud with a really huge sword.
Yes.
Well, the inspiration with the big sword, one of it is, yes,
clouds, but then there's also that thing
where, since the character grow, you
have that thing where the sword and the crown
would be too big at the beginning,
because they kind of like symbolically,
but it's too big because she's not ready for that quest.
So the sword would be, she would drop it,
and then the sword would be too big.
And then when she would be an adult,
then it would be the right size, and the crown would fit.
So, that was one of the main reasons why I love the big sword, especially at the start of the game.
To convey that feeling that she's not yet ready, and she needs to go to that journey to be ready for being the queen of that world.
Thank you. Absolutely beautiful game.
Thank you.
Hi, could you talk a little bit about the challenges of integrating the 3D character
into the 2D world and making it match with all the 2D creatures?
Yeah, okay, so to be technical, at first we integrated the characters straight in the
environment, but because the assets were flat...
she would clip in it.
So what Jeff did is he,
the character is running elsewhere,
like far away in the world,
and we're displaying a 2D film
of the character interacting with it.
So I don't know how he managed to do it,
but that's how he does.
So basically the character is flat in the game,
and has some cel shading,
but the 3D character is not in the environment.
It's a movie of that picture.
that we're seeing. So that way she's fully integrated, she's not clipping with anything.
So that's how we managed to have that 3D character in 2D.
Cool, so it's like an orthographic camera that's projecting it?
Yep.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, my name is Jialing.
I was interested in, because in recent modern times
we were talking about Western gaming,
especially the integration, as you said,
the concept of a badass female character.
Like, what actually solidified,
I feel like your character is very
feminine and I really like that because it's not as if we have to push the girl into being like a strong tomboy
while being strong and it seems like it from the screenshots that you kept that you keep
that sense of femininity all the way up to the points when she grows through
Like what was the choice of that to fight convention in some way in comparison to what other games expect?
Well, all the art from like Kay Nilsson and John Bower especially and Yoshitaka Zemano,
there's a sense of femininity that I really loved.
It captured what I wanted to do.
So for me, that was important to keep it.
I didn't want to have anything too badass.
That's the initial creative inspiration was that.
And then Jeffrey wrote, Jeffrey Reilly, my writer, he started to write the story.
And I loved that character.
I just loved her.
So then at that point,
I wanted to have the character that was on paper.
represented on screen.
So it made no sense to turn her into a badass.
So that's the principal reason why it didn't work for me.
Of course, somebody can make a female badass character.
It's OK.
But for this project, where we were,
what was interesting for me, it just wasn't connecting.
So we kept going with something more delicate.
Out of curiosity, did you receive a lot of contention?
Not contention, maybe I'm not using the right word.
Did you receive a lot of, no, we should go for the badass
instead of actually accepting the way you went
with the art direction?
From co-workers, not on a project, yes.
I got some guy at a bar that says,
never going to play your game because it's a little girl.
I said, I don't care.
So that's the point. It's not important.
The important thing is, you know what, this is what I want to create.
I think there's going to be some value there.
And not everybody in their room plays Madden,
and they're not going to make the Madden player more feminine to attract another crowd.
Every project has its own direction.
And for me, I was sure in my heart that that was the game it needed to be.
Thank you.
I was wondering if the idea for the game was inspired by the UB art framework or if you
had this idea for a 2D game already?
So the thing is, what I play on is JRPGs.
That's what I play.
So I made open world games and shooters.
And there's a point where you may, especially when you start making those open world games,
when you make Assassin's Creed, you don't want to start playing Batman, because
you're not enjoying Batman, you're deconstructing how they made stuff.
So to have some pleasure, or to stop working when you go home, then I would
return to the Japanese-style game.
If there would be one, and personally, I've been in the industry for 10 years,
so 11 years ago, if you would have told me that you had the chance to make a turn-based RPG,
I would have believed it. So for me, that's kind of a dream project.
And the fact that the UbiArt engine would be there, then I kind of see it as, you know,
I wanted to go with, try that engine. I could see it as an opportunity to realize
thing in my bucket list.
To be able to, you know, what I can make a JRPG,
console type or J type RPG,
I can, after that, I can die happy.
I had the pleasure to meet Mr. Yoshitaka Mano
and he did one art piece for us
and that's another part of the, you know,
bucket list that's been scratched.
And it's like, so yeah, so for me, that's like, it's an amazing project, an amazing year.
So I hope that for everybody that you're going to love playing the game after, but you know,
for at least for me, it's a kind of a dream, a dream project.
Thanks, I'm looking forward to it.
Thanks.
So that's it, no more questions.
So thank you very much.