Hello, everyone.
So today, I'm going to be talking to you
about freelancing.
The way I do my talks is I prepare my slides.
I sort of practice them a bit, but I don't actually
create a script.
So I may go off script, or who knows,
or I may forget what I'm talking about,
and it'll be a disaster.
So we'll see how it goes.
So the title of my talk is Freelancing,
How to Live the Dream and Avoid the Nightmare,
which is some terms I'm going to be interrogating and looking
into a bit throughout.
My name is Greg Buchanan, and I'm a writer.
So some of my slides and some of what I'm going to say
will be slightly from the perspective of game writing.
So your mileage may vary in other disciplines.
But as far as possible, I've tried
to make it agnostic to those concerns
and make it broader, drawing on several friends of mine
who are in other disciplines as well to see about applicability.
So first, who am I?
Some of you may know who I am, some of you may not.
It just says independent next to my name.
So what have I done?
So this is why I'm talking about freelancing.
So I've written over 20 games between 2015 to 2019,
the majority of which were work-for-hire freelance contracts
across indie, AAA, VR, mobile,
like all the different types of writing and projects you could do.
So one of my earliest ones was a political game called Paper Brexit,
which was just by myself.
One of the more high-profile things I've worked on was the...
Sorry.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, great.
And a 30-hour story campaign for No Man's Sky, Atlas Rises.
So this was like a big story that was added to the game after release
and added like a huge narrative to it and several other updates.
And I've also, for example, worked on additional writing support for games
such as Metro Exodus quite recently.
So lots of different games, and you can find out more online about my work.
Before that, I've also had some background in academia.
I did a PhD in identification and ethics in novels and video games.
I've been in various list-type things, like Forbes 30 Under 30 this year.
Just, just.
I was about two weeks off turning 30, which I now am, so snuck in.
And another list.
And I'm also now an author, as of quite recently as well.
So my debut novel, 16 Horses, was recently bought in a deal by Macmillan, and will be
published across the world in 2021.
So that's very exciting as well.
I'm also known, and some of you may know me for this reason.
for tweeting advice about the games industry
and game writing in particular.
So you can see my Twitter at the bottom.
I tend to tweet about games things a lot.
And I also have a guide that I update game writing
and maybe expand to other things as well.
So that's the backdrop on which I'm giving you advice.
So what I will be talking about today.
One thing I'll be talking about,
which is probably why some of you are here,
is about strategies for getting work
and how to think of yourself as getting work.
What's the overriding principles you follow?
So I've successfully freelanced on a lot of games
and made a living with that,
so that's why I'm able to give that advice.
Why did I choose to freelance?
So I was awkward and liked to be free,
hence the term freelance.
Now this has a kind of positive and negative aspect to it
as the talk will discuss and as I'll go on to in a moment.
I'll be talking about the dream of a freelance lifestyle.
So it sounds great.
You can work from home, you can travel the world and work,
you can work on loads of projects,
you can build a portfolio very fast.
So it sounds really good.
There's also some weird inverted nightmare realities of being a freelancer.
So it's not great.
It's actually all those things are actually kind of terrible at the same time.
And there's a kind of bad side to a lot of stuff that sounds initially good.
And also talking about emotional well-being strategies.
So every bad dream is manageable and is just a bad dream.
And I'll also be talking about survival mode and my definition of survival mode as BITS
freelancers.
So how you can get through kind of.
bad times as a freelancer and how you can keep going.
So I'm going to start with this, and this is going to be linked
into throughout the talk.
This is my rough pitch for how I think of myself
and how I try to get jobs in the industry.
And I'm very happy to expand about this after.
And I did a little mini Twitter thread already,
which I'll retweet about where I go into more detail
than I will now about this particular point.
Beyond what I've just put up on the thing,
I'm just gonna say something first.
None of this will work unless you're actually able
to do what you want to do.
So you have to actually be able to write to become a writer.
You have to be a proficient artist to get an art gig.
You have to know how to code to be a programmer.
So if you don't have the sufficient skills there,
it may be difficult to get jobs.
However, as we all know, some people are able to get jobs
who may not be the absolute top of their field,
but they have other assets that are able to help them,
which is a useful thing to think about
when you're trying to get gigs,
as presumably very talented people in your own right.
So, I did a tweet on Twitter a while back where I said something to the effect of,
if you don't talk about what you do, no one will know you're doing it.
This, at its root, is not always true.
We know of situations where people can be lucky enough or have networks enough
that they are broadcast or they produced something so good that it's...
Captured the hearts of many but we also know of projects that are really good that didn't get the attention
They deserved games that were really well written or well developed
That just didn't get out there as much as what you might see as more mediocre titles
There is not a direct correlation between talent and people knowing about talent
Which is a key thing you have to solve as a freelancer because you aren't selling yourself on the basis to a small number of
People in a room in an interview once you are ongoing selling yourself to loads of different projects
throughout the year
So people have to know who you are in some respect.
Now I say here somehow promote yourself
because there are many ways of doing this
which you might be comfortable with one more than the other.
And people often claim that they don't self-promote
themselves and that's either because they've defined it
very specifically or they're being disingenuous.
So here are some ways in which some people
might self-promote.
They might have a website where they have their projects
listed and some of their skills.
They'll have a business card.
They might attend events like this one right now, GDC.
This is a networking event where you can meet people
and find out new opportunities.
People might have an active social media presence
where you discuss things online,
you join in communities, you do that.
Now, some people...
will tweet all the time about projects they've worked on
and try and spread the news.
Some people will hardly ever have expressed themselves
in that kind of presence or that kind of venue,
but they will in person be going to networking events
or be in circles or know people that will get them work.
They are doing something to be known by the people who hire.
Because otherwise, if you analyze it,
whatever the discourse is about self-promotion,
it doesn't make sense that someone would hire you
if they have no idea who you are.
That's a causal, no relationship there.
So thinking about the way in which you're comfortable doing this and the way in which you can best do this is a really important thing.
And privilege will also affect this.
So geographically where you're located, certain other things about yourself may make some of these strategies more or less easy.
So I would always advise never looking down on other people who do different methods to you,
because they may have to, as opposed to the things you do.
Beyond this, an idea which I would class on to self-promotion is knowing how to hunt gigs
and when to chase emails and opportunities.
So knowing the venues where things are advertised or discussed within your discipline.
For example, for game writing, there's a Facebook group about game writing, jobs are routinely
posted on Twitter.
Loads of other disciplines as well will have different areas or different places where
people discuss things, meet-up groups for disciplines, and so on.
Also knowing when to chase emails and opportunities.
Loads of people I know who are talented and miss out on gigs
because they don't follow up.
So they'll apply for something and they'll never hear back.
And then that's the end of it for them.
Whereas you shouldn't be afraid of,
if you wait a polite two or three weeks
after you've sent in an application,
if you don't hear anything back, send a chase up email.
Being polite, not harassing them or anything.
And you tend to get a sense of how to do this,
of being like, hi, I noticed,
I was just wondering what the status of this application is.
Could you tell me more?
If there's anything else I can provide, let me know.
This will often get you an opportunity that you might have missed otherwise,
just because for game jobs, you might get 200, 300 applications,
and things can get lost in the cracks.
Likewise, as a way of thinking about obtaining gigs,
you want to build portfolios that can be appreciated by non-specialists.
Those hiring for roles, particularly in freelance,
often have very little expertise
in the discipline they're hiring for.
This is especially true of writing,
but is often the case for other things as well.
They'll have some knowledge enough to discuss with you,
but they won't know as much as you do.
That's why they're hiring you.
You're the expert who has the skill that they don't have.
So by building portfolios that can be appreciated
by non-specialists, you have to try and think
of the mentality of those people hiring you,
and you can learn this through trial and error.
If you're ever in the position to help hire for a job, try and get involved or at least sit in,
because it gives you such a mindset, an insight into that mindset that will alter how you then pitch yourself.
So a key principle is reducing ambiguity that you will be able to do what you were being hired to do.
So people often ask, like, I'm an amazing writer, I'm an amazing singer, I'm an amazing voiceover artist,
I'm an amazing animator, all these things.
produce many projects, there's an understandable ambiguity that you'll be able to deliver,
even if you can show the skills.
They don't know if you've worked in the kind of environment that they work in, they don't
know if you're reliable with deadlines, they don't know if you know the compromises required
in game development to work through multiple types of project.
So if you reduce that ambiguity and you're somehow able to convince people, limit risk
in hiring you, that's a great thing to do and there's quite a few different ways of
doing this.
For example, I advise people having a range of samples
for a variety of gig types and studio sizes.
So for example, in game writing,
people might have, an early mistake is people have
portfolios of very highly branching, dense,
complex, interactive fiction.
People designing games that have kind of a very
strange mechanic, or kind of very specific feature set.
And then trying to go to like massive AAA companies
with a portfolio type that is nothing like they produce.
And so thinking about the kind of stuff you're applying for and having things that is very useful those of you in the audience
Who already are freelancing or already have worked in games because this is range. This is aimed at all levels
Trying to think about how you can diversify that portfolio
I'd work on projects different to those that might be like your dream project are really useful and when your early career trying to perhaps
We do different types in that regard is really good. So for example if you want to make really kind of
tragic dramatic
Emotional games
That's great, but apply for other types of games as well,
especially early career.
Get that diverse portfolio.
Get a portfolio that makes it look like you will be trusted
to do lots of different types of tasks, rather than just one.
And finally, and this is a very important thing, possibly more important even than pure talent,
is suggesting you'll be good to work with and you'll be able to work in a team.
In games specifically, this is hugely important because it's often producers who hire you,
who are about working and establishing good team cohesion.
the greatest writer in the world wouldn't necessarily get a job,
but a very good writer who is good to work with will get the job
when that greatest writer wouldn't get that job.
And being able to demonstrate that and prove that is a very useful thing to do.
So obviously interviews and your communications,
you'll come across a certain way with them,
so not being too insistent in chasing up stuff,
but chasing up stuff in a friendly manner.
If you're ever asked in an interview,
do you have any questions, always have a question.
It just makes it seem like you're listening more.
and engaging with the material that they're discussing with you.
If you have worked in any kind of team, which you should be if you're applying for jobs,
so even game jams or any kind of free group task like that where anyone can join, do it.
Try and get some sense that you've worked in teams.
Communicate the kinds of teams you've worked with and the kind of roles you've worked with.
As soon as you have paid work or kind of...
projects that have come out or student projects or whatever, try and get some
testimonials from people you've worked with and put them on your website. That
will be a sort of, that would be incredibly useful for communicating
these factors about you and often it's also quite nice for your kind of self
care to see what people, nice things people have said about you as well. So
those are two ways of bolstering these principles and we can return to this
later and I'm very happy afterwards to discuss with people about their own
stuff how to further address these things.
Now, I want to discuss motivations many freelancers may have for freelancing in the first place.
So, some people may freelance out of necessity.
There may be no available in-house roles that they would rather do.
They'd rather be a full-time staff member somewhere, but it's not, so they need to apply for other jobs.
It may be due to layoffs.
So the games industry, particularly over the last year, has experienced a lot of layoffs from a lot of big companies.
People may have to freelance for short periods of time when it may not be their desired thing in order to pay rent.
And others may just have gaps in the career
between larger gigs that they'd rather do
and want to find work in between.
Some may, for example, freelance because their early career.
So a lot of game applications will say,
you must have five years experience.
So for this, it's like, how do you
build that five years experience if you don't have any work?
So you freelance is often a solution.
Why I chose to freelance.
Part of it is my disposition, and this may apply to some other people as well.
I valued the ability to control my time and workflow as much as I could.
Others are not so.
Others really like kind of ongoing rigidity and kind of safety net and security of certain
in-house structures, which can often really enable people's creativity and free them from
a lot of worries that you might have here.
Whereas I wanted other things in this regard.
There were certain issues about security for me.
So it's often presented that in-house jobs are more secure and safer than freelance work
in terms of your earning flow.
But as we've seen in the last year, and especially in different parts of the world with different
laws about employment, you can often be let go at the drop of a hat.
It's not as secure as it looks.
Likewise, there's a sense of security that's emotional as well, for me at least, in terms
of the idea that instead of one boss could...
have vast power over my emotional life day to day, as happens in any workplace, I'd rather
distribute that and have multiple bosses, which makes me more of a force in what I can do in my own space.
Likewise, there's an ambitious aspect, so I wanted to learn fast and efficiently and make my own projects as much as possible.
So if I was to be in-house at some of these studios, I would have worked for three or four years on one project,
which is amazing as an experience, but I wanted more breadth.
I wanted to try lots of different things.
That's how my mind works, and that's something I value and want to do creatively,
and it's helped me and benefited me going forward.
So talking about the alleged dreams of freelancing,
so pros of freelancing that people discuss.
Organizational.
So you might get to be your own boss,
get to organize your own time.
Insurance against mass layoffs of particular companies.
So if you've got loads and loads of jobs lined up,
then it doesn't matter if one contract cancels with you
because you've got others.
It may be very bad in the short term,
but you've distributed your work time.
greater freedom from internal politics and crunch.
So because you're a contractor,
you have a business relationship
rather than an employment relationship,
you may have some kind of separation
from some internal problems that a company may have.
Regarding crunch, you may, for example,
have a different contract kind of terms
which allow you to charge for such extra time
or to contractually guard against that time.
You don't have to sign those terms all the time.
Finally, you might get a greater ability to promote yourself and your own work.
So you might be able to talk about what you do more or do your own projects at the same
time as other ones you're working on and actually get your name out there and what you want
to do out there.
No one can stop you speaking at a conference, whereas they could if you work in a company.
You can remote work as well.
There are also creative benefits to being a freelancer.
So you work on projects you choose to work on rather than those your company assigns
to you.
You might have freedom to create your own solo work and IP in multiple mediums.
So a lot of games companies, as some of you may know, for full-time roles
do not allow you to work on any projects outside of the one they ask you to, even in different media.
So, for example, as a writer, if I wanted to write a novel working for some of these companies,
I wouldn't be allowed to, unless they gave me permission. Otherwise, they'd own it.
Which didn't sit right with me as an industry norm.
Likewise, as I mentioned before, learning and developing skills much faster due to working
on a range of projects in different types of studios and genres.
Now, as I said at the beginning, there's a bad side to a lot of these things as well,
which must be considered carefully if you were to make the proactive choice to become
a freelancer or stay a freelancer.
A lot of people will present it as very positive in a career, and it does have its positive
aspects, but you have to accept, due to the nature of the world we live in, that there
are various consequences of some of these things.
So for be your own boss.
That sounds great in your own respect, but you also have all the anxieties, worries,
and lack of security that come to that.
You're your own boss, yay.
You're also your own boss with all the...
You may treat yourself like a boss would treat you,
which is a strange relationship to have with your own work,
and you can be very hard on yourself as a freelancer
in a way you wouldn't be if you were an employee.
Likewise, organizing your own time.
That sounds great.
And have any of you ever tried to do massive projects
in your spare time?
It's very difficult to organize your own time
with no one making you do things at particular changes.
You have to have a lot of self-discipline.
You have to be able to get up off the,
back on the horse at certain times.
Insurance gets mass layoffs.
So yeah, fine.
But it's often way easier to determine a contract
than employment in many cases.
So you can like,
There is some level of security, but you have to be very careful who you work with.
You may sometimes get paid late, sometimes you may not get paid at all, and might have
battles with companies going on behind the scenes.
Due to NDAs, you may not even be able to say that you haven't been paid, which is a really
weird scenario to be in.
Likewise, you may have greater freedom from internal politics, but you may actually be
more vulnerable than this person.
to this than others, and you may be seen as an outsider.
So yeah, fine, you're free from that day-to-day situation
in the studio, but there are certain familial benefits
you often get in teams where people hang out
with each other all the time.
If you're not there, you might, for example,
be excluded from meetings.
People in the studio might resent the fact
that you're being given all this stuff to do
when they want to do it, and so on.
And you might have various conflicts
that are just totally not in any way your responsibility,
but it kind of rides.
Likewise, yeah, fine, you can often promote yourself, but non-disclosure agreements are
very constant throughout the industry, and you may never be able to talk about certain
projects to the extent that you'd like to, and even when a project comes out, often NDAs
will last in an indefinite amount of time, so you have to ask permission to talk about it.
Finally, you may have an ability to remote work,
but sometimes, no you don't, you have to go in-house.
So there are loads of jobs which would require you
to move across the country or the world for five months,
with no promise of employment beyond that.
When you do do remote work, there'll have to be
a whole host of other potential issues
about movement of time, about wanting you
to check in nonstop on an online messaging service,
for example, when you're actually working on other stuff.
Time can be a strange thing, and companies
don't always know how to deal with that process.
On the creative side, working on projects you choose to work on, yes, but often the
process to get on a project can be very strange.
So in writing, there's a common thing where you might have like a six-month long selection
procedure that's kind of calf-grass, and you might be kind of selected or not selected
for various kind of indeterminate reasons that you're never really given feedback on.
If you have the financial luxury to wait for perfect projects, yeah fine, you can work on projects you choose to.
But if you'll need those contracts every month for different jobs, you'll often just have to take things as they come
and convince yourself and others that you're the best person for that project.
And yeah, sure, you'll do a great job, but is it the one you really set out to do when you wanted this freelance life?
Not necessarily.
Likewise, yeah fine, you've got freedom to create your own work, but time and energy
can be a huge issue of actually being able to do that when you're working on contracts
all the time.
However, I would argue that this isn't really as much of a nightmare as it sounds because
you are still free to do so ultimately, which for many people there were value that you
can make something because you want to make it and you're not told by a corporate entity
that you cannot.
On the final point, I actually don't think there is a weird nightmare side to that.
I think you do learn and develop skills faster in some ways.
They're not necessarily the same skills you'd learn if you were on a project for multiple
years, but you can learn a lot if you leverage the opportunities correctly and rapidly diversify,
see multiple studio types, styles of working, genres of game very quickly.
Cool.
So overall, there is no dream, as the title of the talk suggested.
You always wake up.
move past those positive aspects.
But likewise, there doesn't have to be a nightmare.
It doesn't have to be as bad as those bad things sound.
You can find something in between,
which is what partly I'm advising today.
So be mindful of your emotions and energy levels.
Mitigate inevitable psychological threats
and prepare for challenges.
So it's a hard life being a freelancer.
It's very rewarding, but it's hard,
and not everyone wants to or is suited to doing it.
But may have to, so hence the advice today.
So two such major psychological threats, which actually link into the advice about careers
in general that I was discussing at the beginning.
You may suffer from imposter syndrome.
So many of you in this room may suffer from imposter syndrome and wonder about your own
skills.
It's a common thing.
You have to constantly pitch your own work and abilities to gain new gigs and maintain current relationships.
You're often isolated from teams and colleagues.
That kind of friendship throughout the day or that kind of camaraderie you may lack.
You may not have anyone telling you you're good because you've been hired to do a task.
And if you do it, then that's often paid.
That's often seen as you being told that you're good.
No one may ever tell you that your work was good until you find out in a review that it was good, which can be a very strange life.
You don't have performance reviews or anything.
Likewise, you may not be able to discuss your own work, so certain sources of pleasure that
you'd normally have about talking about what you do, you don't always have, you're not
in control of, even after release.
You may often also face the threat of burnout, so the unpaid labor of self-promotion, tests,
applying for work, economic fear can take a toll on a lot of people.
You have the excitement of all these different things,
but the associated cost and risk of,
what if I don't get a gig in the next few months?
What if I have a period of unemployment?
What if I have to borrow money?
What if I get into debt?
These can all be huge issues that are emotionally exhausting
in addition to the work you're doing.
Likewise, being pushed to meet aggressive schedules
and manage multiple projects can also be a bit of a toll.
So it's great you get to work on loads of stuff,
but you're working on loads of stuff,
which can be quite a big problem in itself
and create an emotional toll.
So some strategies for dealing with these things if you embark on this career.
So client dealings will often add to your sense of imposter syndrome.
So having to convince people, not getting the kind of feedback you might want, weird
internal politics and all the other issues I've discussed can add to it.
So you want to make sure the situations you get involved in are as good as possible and
setting expectations.
Often companies aren't intentionally acting in a way that's detrimental to you.
So consider interviewing them as much as they are interviewing you.
Like assess.
Try and get, even if you're gonna take the job whatever
because you want the job and you need the money,
you can still stand up for yourself
in the interview process and try and make sure
that the working environment's the right fit.
So set expectations about your schedule,
your hours, your involvement in the team,
your role, your working habits, how you work.
Tell them how you've worked on the projects.
That's a great thing to do in an interview
because once again, that whole idea of ambiguity
about whether you can do it, that answers that topic,
but it also helps you in terms of your working time.
It sets up, that's how I'm gonna do it.
You know this is hiring me.
And you can refer back to that if there are problems later,
like you knew that I worked like this,
and how you get feedback.
It's often good to have an arranged feedback cycle
so that you actually get some affirmation on your work.
Gain contractual protections regarding crediting
and post-release discussion.
So always ask for in your contract
that you are definitely credited.
and make that a compulsory thing about working with them.
Likewise, have some kind of protection
that may allow you to in some way
discuss your work post-release.
And I can post some extra stuff about this online afterwards
about how I formulated this.
So I'll post that on Twitter later.
This is a more of a strange thing, but kind of schedule your worrying about things
to particular times of the week.
And I'm going to discuss in a second like career time, planning time.
Don't just be in a constant fear mode about arranging stuff.
Make that part of your job.
Book that in like you would something in a job for a particular time.
Curate your site for self-care.
So websites are great for advertising yourself.
They're also great for advertising yourself to yourself.
Reading about your achievements, seeing what you've done,
editing that and keeping that going.
It's really...
I find that fun, so I can just edit it for the sake of it.
I'm not doing anything.
I'm just making it nicely arranged and looking good.
Find communities, join in with other people, talk with other people, make sure you're not
alone.
Likewise, with burnout, manage your time.
Easier said than done.
Schedule and quarantine a block of career time daily and weekly, even if contracts.
Even if you're in jobs, spend maybe like half an hour a morning or an hour a week or whatever
trying to...
Build those self-promotional strategies.
Look for talks to apply to.
Look for game jams to go to.
Look for communities to join.
Look for new projects, even if you've got stuff arranged.
Never stop.
If you stop, that's where more risk can be created for yourself.
Try and reduce the cognitive load of too many tasks
by finishing short ones first, which
is generally a good idea to try not to be doing too many things.
And there's a principle I call soft and absolute rest time,
because I'm very unhealthy in my own working habits.
This is just what I try and do.
But soft rest time is where I'll say in ideal conditions. I will relax here
Absolute rest time is in non ideal conditions. I was written. I was still rest
I was still have this rest break no matter what unless it's really bad, and I have to sure
So for example soft rest time I might take the evenings off during the week in a Saturday
And a Sunday if things are going good in absolute crisis conditions where I have to burn out
I even then will not take Sundays. I'll take Sundays off. I'll make sure I take that rest
It's extremely important.
Try and have someone you trust hold you accountable
and encourage you with this.
Make sure they know your schedule
and make sure they keep you to it.
I'm just quite going quickly again,
because I've got a little bit of time.
So dealing with career gaps.
Follow previous advice and self-promotion.
If you've got a gap between gigs and you're really
hunting for stuff, extend those blocks
to longer periods of time, the career blocks.
devote more time to things.
So one thing, for example, I'll do on Twitter
when I'm in these gaps is I will search for certain keywords
like game writing, game writers,
narrative designers, so on.
That will take ages to trawl through.
Most of the tweets are totally irrelevant,
but I will find a gig maybe once a week
or something like that.
Loads of people aren't willing to do that,
but that will actually deliver me from crisis.
That will actually give me jobs
no one else has found when I have to.
And being willing to do that is something
you have to as a freelancer.
Reach out to your professional network directly for support, always a good idea.
Other people will then actually possibly give you projects or make you aware of things if you have to.
Also, work on a project of your own, even if you don't have work.
Your work is your business, which can include your own solo projects here in Creative Medevas.
So keep going, even if you don't have paid employment.
Consider a side hustle if necessary.
Various times throughout my game career, I, for example, tutored or did teaching briefly
to be able to make rent and so on.
It's nothing to be ashamed of.
Not everyone can be constant and things will happen.
Exiting survival mode, so being able to move out of that, that can be really difficult.
Once you've had a few periods of time with big cancellations or things you've had to
move past, it can be quite hard to get back to normality.
So one thing I'll do, for example, and you can define this on your own basis, is if I
have less than two months of work arranged, I will then hit the mode I just described
where I try and find work and I do all those things, and that gives me a bit of a safety
net from absolute crisis.
Exiting survivor mode can be really difficult, so writing a commitment and putting that somewhere
of when you'll feel safe is a really good idea.
And get an accountability partner to help pull you out of this when you've reached this
point.
So try and get someone who will be able to recognize and be around you enough.
to recognize when you need to move on and let go,
because it can be very dangerous otherwise.
And finally, make sure you try and finish the solo project,
but don't be unkind to yourself,
because keep going, do your own stuff.
That's why you're a freelancer, you can do this.
So in sum up, be kind to others in your position.
We're all in this together,
and a lot of freelancers may try and build each other up
or cut each other down.
Those who build others up will often be helped far more
than those who cut others down.
Others will help you, others will recognize your goodness
and your willingness to support.
Be just as kind to yourself.
We often are very hard on ourselves
in a way others are not, and as freelancers,
we're very much at risk of this.
You will create your best work when you're inspired,
not when tired, miserable, resenting creative activity.
You may draw on those emotions to produce work later
that you've had in other times,
but when actually creating, that deserves no one,
so don't drive yourself into the ground.
So that's the end, exactly at time,
but I'll be available for questions afterwards
and around the area and stuff, so yeah.