Good morning. Thanks for coming in so early.
This is Watch Dogs, Hacking It to 11.
Thanks, everybody, for coming over,
and we're really grateful that GDC had us
and allowed us to come and do this talk for you guys.
We did Watch Dogs, and we shipped it about a year ago,
and we're really glad we can talk to you about
a bit more about the music system
and everything that's music in the game
and how that came about for the game.
I'm Olivier Girard, I'm the audio director on the project.
I'm Pavel Maximichev, and I'm the audio designer and the
composer for the game.
So essentially, we wanted to do a talk
that covered the whole aspect of audio on Watch Dogs.
And we started writing it, and we figured
that was way too much stuff to talk about.
So we decided to figure it.
We figured we'll stick to music, which is what proved to be
the most challenging thing for us
as we had to, you know, reconcile the open world
with our own creative objectives
we're gonna get to in about a second.
What we knew from the get-go, we got on Watch Dogs
just when we finished SpinnerCell Conviction
about 5 1â„2 years ago.
And...
all we knew at the time, Watch Dogs was becoming its own thing, was we were
establishing a new brand, and all we knew was a Serious Stone open world game
focused on hacking and the concern raised by technology and all that.
So, Serious Stone was basically all we got, you know, as a major direction from the game.
And that's going to be reflected throughout the whole presentation, because that's
the one thing we kept grabbing onto,
you know, we want to do a Serious Stone thing.
Obviously, you know, doing open world games with a lot of driving and shooting.
uh... there's a lot of of of other
games happening at the same time and some are humorous some are goofy and all that
and I think
that was our way of trying to be different it was you know trying to stick
to that serious tone.
It was a long development cycle and it was the first time for us to actually be part of the pre-production phase.
I'd been at Ubi for a while and had done a lot of crunches, a lot of production phases, but never in pre-production.
So that was a bit uneasy at first, getting into that rhythm of not actually always wrestling with tasks and all that to be doing,
but having deeper thoughts about the whole creative direction and the sound direction of the game.
Also, it was a very large team.
I was used to working with five, six people maximum on a project.
And then we got on Watch Dogs, and eventually we were, you know, this team working just
in Montreal.
And we had other friends as well working in the Paris studios.
We had friends in Newcastle, and we had people in Quebec City all working on sound.
And I think the guys at the Star Control talk...
said it best yesterday.
They said, you know, they embraced standing
on the shoulder of giants, of other people.
And that's pretty much what we're doing here.
I mean, we get to be here today
because all these people worked really hard on the game,
and we wouldn't be here without them.
We needed that many people just to ship the game
in the state we wanted it to be.
So we're really grateful about that.
And also the relationship we had
with our creative director, Jonathan Morin,
and our producer, Dominique Guay,
who really enabled us to, you know, achieve our goals
and really reach as far as we could.
with this brand-new IP.
So we're really grateful about that as well.
So as I said about the audio direction,
uh, you know, it wasn't like we came on board
the project five and a half years ago
and said, oh, this is what it's gonna be.
It was, uh, there was a lot of iterations,
obviously because, you know, the game was finding itself.
We were trying to define what we were gonna be.
And we were trying to, you know...
get in sync with what the creative direction was doing,
what the game designers were doing and all that.
But what was really, really important for us on Wazhogs,
and another thing we're really grateful about,
is we had full control and full authority over sound.
It might not be so obvious when, you know, you don't have it,
but to get that on a project...
is really important because we get to push our ideas,
and then we get to sell them to the creative director,
and they can buy in or not into this,
but at least it comes from us.
It's a, you know, bottoms-up perspective on things,
whereas other times, you'll be on a different project,
and the creative vision is gonna be so strong
that you'll become a service to that creative vision.
On Watch Dogs, we really were given a lot of, um...
of room to define ourselves what we wanted this game to be about from an audio perspective
and that really helped us define exactly what Watch Dogs was about.
And what it was about, basically, as I said,
we were just coming off of Spinner Cell Conviction,
and we'd done a lot of interactive music,
but also music that reacted really closely
to what the action was.
And we really, really enjoyed doing that
with the systems for Spinner Cell.
And we decided, well, now we're doing an open world game,
so in theory, this wouldn't be the best approach.
But we decided to challenge ourselves a bit and say,
how can we make the most tailor-made music
for all these moments the player is gonna live?
but still try to make it work with a total freedom promise of the open world.
So that was basically the challenge we put ourselves through
because we really, really enjoyed those moments.
And we said, you know, this is the best way to get, you know,
the maximum emotional impact of the game
is to support these moments with as close a soundtrack as we can have
that reacts to what the player is actually doing.
So, you know, if we realize that the player is, you know,
taking a car and crashing through windows, then can we...
find a way to note that, and can we see that,
and can we support the music?
Can the music support those actions?
I'm not saying this is what we did in the end,
but that was our reasoning from the beginning.
This is what we were trying to achieve.
minimal systems and more mission-based custom tracks.
Obviously, we couldn't get, you know, too far away from systems
because the open world still demanded a lot of feedback
and still demanded a lot of attention
because gameplay was kind of king on Watch Dogs
and we wanted to be sure that the gameplay
was getting all the feedbacks it needed.
And a lot of times, a lot of what was happening in the game,
like the vigilante system and all that,
was very subtle and since you know our character didn't necessarily have a
a spider sense thing or whatnot
oftentimes the the solution to those problems how to bring the players
attention to something that's going on
you know very far away down the street
was to change the music or have a specific cue play at a specific time
or when the the police were chasing you and all that so
a lot of the times you know we we did need those systems to be there
just so we could have the proper gameplay feedback for the player so
obviously that created
uh... you know if we have a few conflicts in the game and you know how
we resolve them
is is pretty much you know the the meat and potatoes of this talk
So reconciling all these systems obviously there was technical concerns as well because we couldn't have you know 11 streams of music playing all the same time
Technically we would have gotten a lot of angry engine programmers at our desk if we'd attempted that
And also we were doing a cross gen game which implied that you know however far we would push with the next-gen technology
The current gen guys would hate us that much more so we still want to be friends with them
So you know we try to find a common ground that everybody was happy with what we were doing
but also from a technical perspective,
there's just so many stuff you can cram
at the same time through the streams.
We had a lot of readability concerns as well
because it, you know, we could have a lot,
you know, a guy with a boom box
and then you're in your car with your own radio
and then there's mission music playing on top
and that just creates a mess of music really.
And if you have, you know, music everywhere,
then you get to the next point,
which is the density concern.
If you got music playing all the time,
the next time it comes in,
it kind of loses its impact a bit.
So, you know, we wanted to be sure
that there's also some times where there's no music.
Or the player can choose to have new music,
so when it comes back in, then it actually means something.
And also, the open world promise, obviously,
was the main thing that we always had to keep in mind.
Because every time we thought we had a good idea,
suddenly we switched our brain to QA mode.
And we're like, so what happens if the player decides
to take an ambulance and drive backwards through the store
as people are calling the police?
Is that still going to work?
And most often, that answer would be no.
And we would have to find another solution.
But that's everything, you know, that's setting the table for the project for the next four years we had to do.
And the first casualty of that was the Muse ambient system.
When we started thinking about Watch Dogs, we knew it was a serious game,
and we knew it was an open world, so we started thinking about our favorite references,
and when that came up was obviously Fallout.
And so we played a lot of Fallout,
and we're like, oh, wow, this game really nails,
you know, selling the Fallout universe
through music and through those small musical cues
that come in and out of the environment.
They're not pieces.
They're just small musical phrases
that come in and out.
I'm like, this is brilliant. Let's try that.
So we had our composer make a bunch of these things,
and we had, you know, a bunch of them
for every act of the game,
and we were super happy with the system.
And then it hit us, once everything was in place,
that, you know, a...
a dense, living Chicago,
is not the same audio landscape at all as the wasteland.
So there's much less room in the mix
for these small, subtle things to come in.
And obviously, we reached that density concern as well,
where there was always some kind of music playing at the same time.
So we said, all right, let's take all these very expensive things we bought
and put them aside for now
and see if we can do something else with them later on.
So we, you know, we learned a hard lesson right there.
This is an example of these small musical phrases we had.
So really the objective there was really let's sell the flavor of the game.
Let's say this is Watch Dogs, this is new, this is a serious game.
So hopefully that's what you got from this small piece.
But that was the direction we were going for.
Obviously.
conflicts, many systems trying to fight at the same time.
And we had to make sure all those systems existed together
and the system was smart enough to realize
when there should be a transition.
So what you see here is our glorious music tree,
which was made by our programmers in Montreal,
which basically looks at the game and sees,
well, what part of the game am I in?
Is this the first act?
Is this the later act of the game?
Maybe what kind of, what district am I in?
Or am I in a mission?
Am I not in a mission?
Is the police chasing me?
Is there a vigilante of it going on?
And there's a whole bunch of priorities
within all those systems.
And this is basically the overall,
I'd say, music system.
Because once you get into an actual mission of the game,
then this is kind of overruled.
And then the music, the missions actually take over,
and they have their own music conditions
that are set through scripts.
So let's say a mission had you, uh, obviously,
from, uh, let's say...
pick apples because that's very watchdogs.
But let's say a mission had you pick apples in an orchard,
then maybe we would try to hook ourselves up
to the amount of apple in your basket,
and then the music would fluctuate around that.
So that was the main objective.
And every mission had different objectives,
so we would try to find the objective of the mission
and make sure the actual scripts reacted to that.
But when you were not in the mission
and all the other systems were trying to play the music,
whether it be the source diegetic music,
whether it was the in-car music,
all that had to go through the music tree.
and then the music tree would decide,
okay, now we can play this, now we can play that.
So this is a bit of a closer look to it.
Obviously, it's very programmer-friendly.
I wouldn't... we weren't working too much in there.
We were just sitting down with our programmers
and telling them what we wanted, and they made this.
I captured it because I think it's really impressive,
but I wouldn't be able to remake it myself.
And so obviously now this is the theory behind it.
And here, what we decided to do as well is,
what we were doing on Splinter Cell actually was,
you know, the music was interactive
and working on a layer system,
which would have different layers coming in and out,
depending on the action on screen.
And we wanted to work with parts for our music
so we could have a better impact at any given moment.
So how parts work, Pavel can explain a bit more.
He's more musically minded.
Right now or later?
Yeah, now, right now.
OK, sure.
But the thing is that with parts,
it's very economical memory-wise, processing-wise.
It's a perfect solution for us.
I mean, we can basically construct the piece,
chopped it up, and then we can reuse the parts accordingly.
But the best concern, well, I mean,
the most concerning problem was really the memory constraints.
Because if we have a three-minute piece,
times eight layers, three minutes.
It takes a certain chart on the processor and memory, so.
Exactly.
So basically, the themes we're calling them,
because that's how our system called them,
basically the themes were being shuffled around
depending on the action on screen.
So that's what you're going to see here in this example.
And basically, you see everything that's happening
in the game, and you'll see the system react
to what was happening.
And the theme thing is that it's,
since it's, you know, working in parts,
sometimes it's gonna work,
it's gonna wait until the end of a part
to switch over to the next part.
Uh, so that's why sometimes you'll see
there's a bit of a, maybe a, of an,
a bit of a delay between the actual action
and when the music reacts to it.
But when it does, it's not just, you know,
a new layer fading in.
It's really, uh, there's an impact there.
There's a, a better, uh...
There's a bit of editing going on for, you know, time's sake.
Sorry.
Watch all units. Initiating CQS scan for suspect.
All units, CQS scan completed. Suspect location is being distributed now.
We've got a patrol car in pursuit of suspect.
Damn, where did he go?
Squad, suspect active. We're on him.
To the cliff, over.
Suspect on the move. Track location and report back. Over.
Copy that. A patrol car is heading your way.
Now!
Shut off your vehicle and give yourself up!
So this wasn't a mission, this was all due to systemic aspects of the game.
So that was the main music system driving what you hear and what you see on screen right
now.
As some of you have noticed, during the gunfight when the police are actually firing at you,
we cut out all the music and that was a conscious decision on our part.
because we had this mandate to make the gunfights feel impactful
and feel, you know, important and be really, really, you know,
something very important for watchdogs.
So, you know, we watched a lot of Heat, Michael Mann's movie,
and, you know, we dissected it and like, okay, so what makes this work?
And we realized, you know, a lot of what made it work
was that basically the guns were the music in those scenes.
There was no actual...
score on top of the big shootouts in heat.
I said, well, you know, let's try that and try to bring up the guns and the bullet impacts
and the pass-bys and everything once there's a gunfight.
Also, it says, you know, the music goes away once the player is fired at
because we also didn't want the player to be able to just shut off the music by shooting his gun in the air
because that would have been a bit too obvious.
So you have to be fired at, and then the music goes away,
and then there's a countdown, there's a cool-down period,
and if nobody shoots at you again, then the music will start back again.
Our composer for Watch Dogs, whom we worked with first, was Brian Reitzel.
And it was a really great experience. Brian worked on a lot of Sofia Coppola movies.
He did the...
Hannibal series he did boss set in Chicago as well. It was a great experience for us working with him. It was really interesting
How we we came about working with him because when we started watch dogs
We had this very clear vision of what we actually wanted
It was like oh, it's gonna be very neat film noir music with a lot of brass and we were super
excited about our direction and we sent out kind of a pitch request from
composers and we got and it was so precise and we were so you know very
determined about what we wanted and very precise but we what we wanted that what
we got back was 20 times the same thing like ah yeah maybe that's maybe we did
we give to precise the definitions of what we wanted so what basically we took
those pitches and you know we there was a lot of good ones in there and we got
that through our creative director and he said
we mean film more and that's what i want that i'm like okay
so it was a bit of a of a disconnect there between us and a creative director
and so we decide we let's go with an ambient approach
and more of a of a electronic approach and yet
to watch dogs and we took a bunch of stuff from brian writes all
and just you know put it to the images of the game
this this works the sticks so you know we contacted him
and that's how we start working together
and uh...
It was a fun experience, but since Wazhack was such a long project,
obviously there was an evolving scope to the project.
So what we decided that we were going to get from the beginning
didn't necessarily fit the scope of the game in the end,
and that's how we had to be a bit more creative down the line.
and the final game needs often for the game
as i explained earlier with the muse amiences
uh... there were no need for that in the end but then once you've bought those
things you kind of stuck with them and your budget has been spent so
you know there was a lot of of good learnings for us in terms of you know
how to deal with composers and and how to
when especially when to buy music from the composer
uh... and uh... you know it was it was a lot of fun learning those lessons
Here is, uh, Brian worked a lot on the cinematics, uh, for us.
Uh, and he did a wonderful work,
and this is my favorite cinematic for the game.
So this is an example of Brian Weitzel's work on Watch Dogs,
which I think really nails the emotional impact
that music can have in the game
with the very specific Watch Dogs flavor he set.
I followed you because I idolized you.
Like Jackson does.
And I kept hoping that you would meet around.
Eventually, I just hoped that you would look back.
All I can say is I'm sorry.
But I'm not following you anymore.
I know.
All right, sweetie.
We're leaving now. Say goodbye to your Uncle Edie.
Are you coming with us?
No.
Your uncle's staying here.
Bye, Jax.
We got a lot of amazing stuff from this collaboration,
and we're really grateful we got to work with Brian on this.
And now it's Pavel's time to take over.
Absolutely.
So I would like to go a little bit more in-depth
on the technical side,
a little bit more musical side of this thing.
So basically, the first time we got to work
on the music concepts for Watch Dogs
was around the first E3 we presented back in 2012.
We got a lot of stuff from Brian.
It was all... actually, it fit perfectly.
But as the demo progressed through the iterations,
we noticed that there was some lack.
In certain key moments, we lacked musical cues.
So we decided to give it a shot,
and the first, the really first integration of music
from our part into the Watch Dogs game
was the club.
seen in the E3 demo.
So basically, Aiden had to go through the club,
private club, and we needed music to be played in the club.
So Olivier and Dave, our...
audio artist, went through a lot of tracks, commercials and commercial tracks and everything,
and nothing really fitted the mood we wanted to create.
So at a certain point Dave said, well look, I can handle it, let's try it out.
So he composed the track, we put it in, and people loved it.
It was kind of a stealth thing as well for a AAA Ubisoft game.
It's not something we asked if we could do.
We just, you know, like we were iterating,
trying to find the proper track.
But it wasn't something that we kind of did usually,
you know, compose on the floor in-house.
But eventually, we were just like, all right,
you know, this really works.
But we never really said where it was coming from.
We just put it in.
And then once we got the, you know,
very good reaction from E3, and then I, as a producer,
said, what does editorial think?
And all I said, oh, they really like it.
I was like, oh.
Well, that got us thinking about what opportunities this was opening up for us.
Absolutely. And people loved it on YouTube. They made remixes of that track.
So we said, all right, we might be onto something.
So since we wanted to be really precise about the musical intentions,
the integration of music in Watch Dogs,
that fitted our kind of musical ambitions because...
We want to tailor, make music for very specific moments to work within the systems.
We're tightly scripted for the missions.
And since we work with people in the engine and tools and animation everywhere,
we know how things are hooked up in the game, so for us it was much easier to...
to just be part of the team and iterate with the team
as the team made progress, we were right there.
So that added tremendous flexibility on our part.
So, I mean, we knew up front what was coming
in the next version of the demo.
Uh...sorry.
Let me go right there.
So for the in-house production,
we were working with three people.
They were Dave Christian...
The gentleman on your right, Peter Connolly on the bottom and myself.
Three of us, we have really different musical backgrounds and history.
So Dave is a mostly film composer and electronic musician for the past 25 years.
Peter Connell is a hard gun. He's very versatile. He can do almost everything.
And I'm mostly rooted in rock and jazz, a little bit of classical music also.
So with those flavors, we...
always trying to mix and match because Brian Reitzel gave us the first kind of vision of what
Watch Dogs should be and then we kind of followed his lead but bringing our own background and
I think what it provided us because we wrote a lot of music for the Watch Dogs.
I mean with the DLC we up to
I think four or four hours of in-house composed music.
We wanted to be so close to the actual mission.
Sometimes we were so close to the mission,
once that mission was done, we couldn't necessarily reuse that track for anything else.
So we had to make custom-made tracks for a lot of the missions.
Always, yeah. And we wanted that. I mean, it wasn't constrained, basically.
So we, me and Dave, we work with the sonar in our mixing studio, little mixing studios.
And we brought in our own musical instruments.
You know, Dave works with the modular synths.
I work mostly with guitar and amplifiers and effects.
And it gave us really a more diverse approach.
So instead of being redundant, we always kind of
spiced it up a little bit with different things.
This is how we can schematically represent
how we treated the music, interactive music,
in Watch Dogs.
So basically, going from left to right,
you can see we subdivided always in musical measures,
basically, in bars.
So we got always starting with the intro.
Usually four bars, skipping to four bars.
And then we've got a little F1 thing.
This is what we call the filler.
So a filler is basically a really short.
musical idea. It could be rhythmic, it could be melodic, but it has to be really short, one bar or less.
What it was supposed to achieve is that
you will go through intro one into intro two, a little development, and then it will loop on the filler one
waiting for a trigger from inside the game to be sent to the musical engine.
So basically, since it was so short and looping so fast upon itself,
we can trigger something really fast, and there will be almost no lag between the event that was sent from the game engine
and the music reacting, switching to the main thing.
Then again, four bars, let's say, for the first main pass.
going into M2, M3, M4, and M5, which are shorter sections of the main one with little development,
perhaps. And that allows to be, again, to be responsive from the input from the game engine.
If the player accomplishes something, boom, we can chop at, let's say, M3 and skip to
main six right away without going through M4 and M5. And also, it's much more reactive.
And then usually we had after the whole main six, which is usually a big development with themes,
so we didn't want to cut it up so we can proceed with a more melodic development.
Then we will go into filler two and wait for the outro, usually a little punch or
cinematic or something like that. So this is in a nutshell how it works.
uh...
yes so uh... the uh... the main consideration my part was uh...
established themes the main characters
in what dogs this is
things i prefer to do because
i mean it raises an identity to the game people can
recognize
uh... the the characters by the teams and it creates a lot of
interesting small ideas you can reuse elsewhere in the game and create identity because over four hours of music
I mean I personally want to create a dent so if a person randomly listens to whatever track on the internet
And so oh this is I heard in watchdog, and this is this is was my goal, so this is the really
small
Redux of the main theme for Aiden slash watchdogs
This is only an example on the example on the piano solo
It's real simple stuff, and so it could be easily reusable.
But I will speak about it a little later.
Here's a development of that theme a bit more fleshed out.
This is from DLC, so we incorporated DLC theme
in it, mixing them together.
So it's kind of.
It's always useful to have themes in game, I think.
I switch it to there.
All right.
So this is one of the aspects of themes we use, melodical themes.
Also, I think always in the thematical approach, usage of clear instruments associated to each
character, this is my approach.
For Clara, which is the sidekick of Aiden throughout the game, I wrote a little theme
for her with the usage of clarinet.
But since the Watchdog is all about hacking
and digital error and glitch and all that,
so I tried real little things.
I just processed the clarinet
to make it a little bit more aggressive
and a little bit more distorted.
So here's how it sounds.
This is the regular clarinet.
And here's the treated version.
So there's a little distortion, a little delay,
and it sometimes, since the delay catches the distortion,
kind of clashes with the following notes.
It's a real supple trick.
Also, within the range of the recognizable sounds,
we used a lot of synths, of course, since it's Watch Dogs.
And one of the main patches we used was this one,
which we used throughout the main game and the DLC.
It sounds like this.
So it's really, I like that patch a lot because it creates a rhythmical movement right away,
plus it sounds really dystopian kind of.
There's a small example of all that coming together in one of the scenes in the early scene of the game where you actually get to meet Clara.
So you're going to hear a bit of everything and it's, we tried to tag what was going on at the top of the screen,
but basically it's just all these techniques coming together in this small clip.
You don't look 17.
Do I look like a bad boy?
No, you look like a wild card.
I hope I don't frighten you.
What, do you have a reason to frighten me?
Now you're being paranoid.
Am I?
Someone is fucking with my life.
Threatening my family and at the same moment
the mysterious bad boy wants to meet me
and he is a she.
He is a lie.
Listen.
I need to trust you.
I wouldn't trust me if I were you.
But here's a reason to listen.
The text message you sent me?
I know where to find him.
Yeah. Well, we don't need to meet face to face for that.
No.
We needed a face to face for this.
By the way, this wasn't the final mix of the game.
When we were preparing these clips,
we did a version with the music mixed up just a bit
so it would become more clear when we were presenting them.
Absolutely, yes.
Another thing I'm really fond of is to bring new stuff in the soundtrack, something nobody
else can have, right?
Something really unique to the project.
I'm really a do-it-yourself guy, so a couple of years ago I built a guitar which looks
like this.
Oops, sorry.
It's a fretless, a real technical mishap,
it's a fretless baritone guitar.
I was saving it for a little special project
and Watch Dogs was the one, so it's kind of,
it's a guitar, but I mean, when you hear it,
it creates a really specific palette of sounds and it's.
It's a very nice, useful tool to have,
and it creates a musical imprint,
something you can easily recognize
as being part of Watch Dogs, again,
being part of the hacking and all that.
So this is an example of that guitar being used.
And another example from Bad Blood, which is the DLC for the game.
But of course, all that is nice, but when you have to compose for an interactive project or an interactive music system,
you always have to be composing with constraints within constraints.
And I really like to approach composing backwards, kind of.
So I start with the main thing, with the main theme.
and incorporate it into the game and see how it fits, what are the main challenges, what could cut it,
what, basically, what's the worst that could happen within the usage of that music.
And then I try to compose the...
So I start with the main thing and go back to the intro or to the ending,
and starting with, like, with the main course.
So it helps a lot to really tailor-mate the music,
so basically you know how many bars you will need to fill that gap and all that, you know, so...
It really helps a lot.
Another little trick I would like to share with you,
this is personal observation,
is the, for me, it's the, what I call the piano validation,
is, uh, me as a guitarist,
I mean, I always try to compose the guitars and all that,
but, you know, sometimes you find that cool riff
that really sounds amazing with the distortion and effects,
and you're really grooving and all that,
and then you try to establish more of the harmonic content,
and you sort of...
and you notice that your riff is really charged and it's too many things going on at the same time
and you kind of find yourself squeezed and you kind of abandon the idea.
So what I really like to do is to find whatever riff on the synth sequence or guitar or whatever
and then reproduce it on the piano.
Clean piano sound and see if it works.
If it works, I can proceed.
I know that harmonically it will be stable and I couldn't elaborate on that,
but it's really just...
Bring in to the simplest expression of the music through the piano and see if it works
And if it does you can proceed it will avoid a lot of death traps from the music point of view
Yeah, so going a little bit more a little deeper into the harmony aspect of watchdogs production
Here's the few examples I prepared for you.
So the first example, and the example,
the first point is being, keeping the harmony
really simple.
This is, I cannot stress it enough.
Well, this is for my behalf.
I think it works better, especially within the watchdogs.
And here's the example itself.
This is the watchdog theme.
A little bit of a performance going on here so we can really
stretch out how it works.
And I was going to take you through it.
Yeah.
So here's the core, right, for the progression.
It goes through.
starts well another thing while I'm at it is the for the whole watchdogs I always
tried to keep everything in the same key so we chose C minor as the key dominant
key for the whole game and there's a lot of advantages
It's really simple.
And the main advantage is that you can mix and match different systems and they all will
kind of fall within themselves.
Because right, you start, let's say, a vigilante event in the game, then suddenly something
else happens in the systemic world.
Boom!
You have, you trigger a felony.
But if your musical cues...
are in the same key, the transition will be much smoother
through, through, it's kind of really basic,
but I wanted to stress it out.
So back to the Watch Dogs theme.
It really goes like, right?
C minor.
Back to A minor.
This little trick, progression thirds, minor thirds.
is reused throughout the game.
I mean, every cue almost that I did
had this incorporated in some way.
Because I think it's one again,
we're going back to the theme approach for the game.
And I think it's really part of it.
And this creates a kind of
mysterious sound a little bit.
You don't know what to expect
because it's two minor chords,
not really related tonally.
And it goes both ways.
You can go lower
or sharper.
So, let me play this little example for you.
you
So while it's playing, you can always add, of course you will need to, to add a little
bass to that thing, because it's only the...
So you can stay in C, right?
For the whole progression.
But I prefer to follow the progression through the root, but I will explain both examples.
Thank you for watching my video.
Thanks for watching!
So now we have the bass and the rhythm going on, and I will add up for the next playthrough,
I will add up the melody, so we can hear how it all blends together.
Thank you for watching!
And there you go, right there. This is the melody for the whole main theme.
Part of the time.
Thank you.
It's really basic stuff. You see, we always repeat the same almost four notes.
Three notes.
This is a part of the main theme, which is...
that little A flat in there.
But since the melody and the theme is so simple,
it's really primitive.
But while it's being so simple, it's really versatile.
You can reuse it everywhere.
Reuse it through different harmonies, different keys,
mix and match notes.
It's really, really fluent.
And since it's short, you can reuse it
within the context of the interactive music.
So it's recognizable, short, and reusable.
I mean, you've got everything in there.
Here's another example, what I call the borrowed chords
or model interchange.
This is the Clara theme.
Again, real simple, four chords, nothing more.
See again, this little example I told you about,
the C minor.
Going to E flat minor.
Kind of a little.
Let me play it out, this one for you,
so you can kind of relate to what it says.
Three chords, let's outline them with bass.
Again you can stay on the C root note through the whole thing if you want
But I prefer to follow it once again with the root notes
As you can see, there's a little model thing going on, there's a lot of chords that are
not part of the C minor, the flat minor, nor the F major, are not part of the... actually
the F major could be, but...
Now let's hear the melody.
So while being extremely simple, this melody, again, is very repeatable.
I mean, it is easily integrable into other themes and it is interchangeable.
There's a few little tricks.
I prefer when I change chords like this from going, let's say, from...
C to E flat to F.
I prefer to highlight the most,
well, a little jazz approach, you know,
I mean, you can highlight the most important notes
of that chord you play in a puff.
So basically, you know, in this case,
you know, you're going like,
let's start at measure one.
You're going to the root of the E flat
and, you know, a little diminished passive.
Then to go on the F chord.
It could be...
This is straight, the notes from the triad of the F chord.
And we're going to C minor again, so it's real simple.
The chord inversions, another real fast example.
Here's another really simple progression.
Again, you will recognize that sound, you know.
C minor to A minor.
Going to F minor.
Fsus4.
What it gives us, you see the bottom line
is always a straight C.
So it goes like, let's do a little example of that.
Excuse me.
♪ Tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk, tsk,
So we create a little bassline, let's say this is a synth arpeggio or whatever, you
know, it could, it stays in C, it plays throughout the whole song, for the whole duration of
the song, right?
Since we're using the chord inversions in this example, so we're always keeping the
C note on the bottom in the root position of the chords, you can reuse any one of those
chords in an interchangeable manner and it will kind of flow, still flow nicely in all
that C.
I can switch chords.
Let's go, let's start with A minor.
Go on to F.
Etc, etc.
You can do whatever with those chords and it will kind of still be acceptable to the
human ear.
But, then again, this is Watch Dogs.
I mean, the game is all about hacking, the game is all about the glitchiness, so I kind
of tried to integrate the...
the theme of glitch into the harmony itself.
So sometimes, you know, I mean, the changes we play through,
they're not really, let's see, it's not top 40 material,
right, but I mean, within the, if you...
If you use them a lot through the whole soundtrack, the player's ears get used to it.
And when sudden changes arrive, I mean something you didn't expect arrives,
it will not surprise the player as much because he's already kind of used to the sharp and ambiguous quality of those chords.
Then we have to move on soon to the music licensing aspect all right that we're really speeding through this
There's there's not much time left. I hear
my bad
So we basically use the odd time signatures
Through game also to create that sense of instability again. I can approach
Here's a blue example. I won't play the whole thing for you, but
You
Odd number of matters per musical phrase is another trick we used.
is balance the musical straightness of the whole thing, right?
So basically when the player is used to the subdivisions of four measures,
we kind of mix it up, make five measure progressions, seven measure progression,
just to mix little things a little bit.
So again, when the changes, sudden changes arrive,
people are already used to that kind of feel.
Common notes throughout progression,
we will quickly see those chords again.
usage of the minor, C minor back to E minor again,
with transition through B major.
I always love to arrange the chords,
so we always keep one common note throughout progression.
In this case, it's an E flat.
And by keeping that E flat throughout chords, I mean you can launch a melodic phrase
Let's say the musical theme for Aiden or Watchdogs
And it will work right on top of any of those chords without any
constraints
Here's a, we're gonna have a very quickly an example of in-game music integration where
we try to blend all the systems in.
So basically in this mission you're about to see there's a bit of editing going on as
well so for brevity's sake.
But what's going on is we go from diegetic music coming from the club which blends into
music inside the club and then it becomes composed music.
that's been made to sound like it's from the club and then it escalates into a mission music.
So you'll see the example here.
And this is the type of things we did to try to blend all the systems together
and try to reconcile everything in the world.
And we're pretty happy how it turned out for this particular mission.
The music here is coming from outside.
Now there's a different perspective as you're in the lobby.
I'm going to have you listen to me.
I am default. Welcome to my party.
Damn, he's good.
Look at that, he's hacked into the profiler system.
He's totally with me.
We've got some club music and full-on score right now.
And eventually, through that mission,
the music then becomes even more.
There's even more parts of that music
coming on down the line.
When it works well, you know,
we didn't invent anything there,
but when it works well,
and we can blend all our systems together,
then it really elevates those missions
to a higher level,
and we're really happy doing that.
And we did that a few other times.
I'm gonna skip one example here we had,
which was basically the same idea,
where actually diagecting music
coming from somewhere in the mission
and then becomes the score music
for that specific mission.
We had a Wu-Tang Clan mission.
and that we called it, that had the Wu-Tang Clan song in it
that we really liked how it turned out.
We had another one in a junkyard with Ministry playing
through the speakers, which was really cool as well.
And I want to touch a bit on music licensing
just before we're done, because that was a big one for us.
It was the first time we had to do that to such an extent
in a game and try to get all that music in.
And, uh, it...
We, when we started thinking about licensed music, we thought about all the open world games, what they were doing, and you know, the first answer to that is, oh, well, they're doing radios.
And I'm like, well, you know, radios have been done, and the Watch Dogs flavor is not about radios. It was about your, you know, your telephone, your PDA, what you've got in your pocket.
And we figured, you know, that's how I listen to music in my car. It's my playlist, and we figured we're going to do a playlist for the player that he's able to fill out.
as he progresses through the game.
But our angle on it was that we wanted to be meaningful as well.
We wanted to be sure that that playlist had something to say about the game.
And since Chicago was such a big part of Watch Dogs,
we decided we're going to make our playlist Chicago-centric.
It ended up being about 80% bands and artists from Chicago,
and we're quite happy about that.
But it's not something that we sold well, I think.
It's not something that we communicated enough,
because we were really happy with the playlist.
I don't think it really necessarily set the world on fire,
but if I were to do it again, I'd do the exact same playlist.
And we had a lot of help from the whole Ubisoft studio
in acquiring those licenses,
and we were really happy how it turned out.
There was a bit of everything for everyone in it.
In the end, you know, the diegetic music existed in the world, and we had to be sure that, you know, for the conflicts,
there was always clear rules about what was going to happen.
And as I said earlier on, gameplay was king, so we always had to be sure that, you know,
when there was important gameplay feedback, diegetic music would go away.
And when mission music would come in, diegetic music would go away as well.
So that was basically the rule we had, and it ended up working well for us.
This is our cutting-edge license management tool at Microsoft Excel.
So we kept track of everything in there
just to be sure, you know, this is the ones we've cleared,
and this is the information.
Do we acquire this at the very start of the game?
Does it come in later? Et cetera, et cetera.
So we had this very powerful tool
to keep track of everything.
As I said, you know, you could, you know,
build up your musical playlist
as you progress through the game.
You could edit it.
There was a lot of, you know, hidden information
about the place, which we thought was really cool.
We had artist bios in there
if you wanted to learn more about the artists and all that.
You could actually hack the music away from the speakers in the world if you didn't already have it in your playlist.
We had a Shazam-like app in the game as well.
So that was a lot of fun to set up.
And the way it was working, the whole licensed music system, is every time we had a song playing,
we had three versions of that track that were pre-processed,
and the system would switch between which version of the track should be playing depending on where it was playing from.
So this is how it sounded within the different emitters.
That's when a vehicle is driving down the street, that's the version you would hear of that track.
Coming from the speaker.
You listen yourself to your music player, if you're sitting in that car, that's what's going to happen.
Those are the very different versions.
And we chose that system instead of having real time processing on the tracks,
because it was much easier to handle for the current gen guys.
the main reasoning behind this technological decision.
We also had an additional filter on the music
to account for the vehicles and how broken they were.
So if you would break the windows, filtering would be different
on that very specific version of the track.
And to wrap it up very quickly, because I think we're going over time,
what we learned about doing Wajang, and what we learned doing it,
structure and planning is important, but as well,
really the relationships you're going to forge with the other people on your team,
and especially the other teams, whether it be animation, programming, and all that.
Those are the ones that are really going to pay off down the line.
We bought ourselves a lot of goodwill from the engine team,
and that allowed us to do a lot of stuff and work well beyond
where we could have been expected to be locked out of the data.
So that's really important to keep in mind.
Play nice with the other teams.
Also, doing in-house music allowed us to reach our creative objectives,
which was really have that tailor-made music to the missions.
I think we, you know, we aimed pretty high,
and I think for us, we reached our objective
as close as we could get it with this project,
and we're really happy we got to do it.
But it wasn't, you know, there's some tough lessons
learned as well.
We're still having a hard time reaching polish phase.
The music for the last mission came in
as we were doing the final pass on the mix of the game.
So that, what you hear in the game in the final mission
is the actual first draft of that music.
Thank God it worked well.
As you can see, Pavel is already...
You know, he's a very rigid and rigorous guy when he makes music.
So that worked as it was, but, you know, it got in just as we were mixing it,
so we didn't have a lot of time to iterate on it.
And we can manage the conflicts within the music system,
but it's not always seamless transition, as you can see,
for example, with the Vigilante systems.
We still haven't found the perfect formula,
but it's going to be a lot of fun, you know, trying to refine that on different projects.
But, you know, we're happy with the balance we struck on this one.
And a lot of needs for a project this size
only materialize close to the end of the game.
So you always have to keep that in mind
and be reactive to what's gonna happen later
and maybe try to keep a bit of buffer,
whether it's budget or time,
close to the end of a project
to be sure that you're able to react to these things.
I've been closed on a light note.
This is it for our presentation.
There's one thing we like to try.
I've got a few Easter eggs here,
but I'm just gonna play one, which is my favorite one.
During the course of the production,
something got left on the cutting room floor
and it involved a very...
thorough narrative aspect which was you know there's this cartoon playing in the world and kids are really into it and it's all about
These Pokemon like characters, and we really got carried away trying to imagine the theme song for that cartoon
Which was really like this 80s song for an 80s cartoon with a bit of a Japanese flavor to it
So I'm going to play this song, and this got, you know, this didn't make it into the game,
but what did make it is a small three-second portion of that song.
I'm going to raise my hand when it plays, and that small portion is what we used as
the news jingle for every news broadcast in the game.
So you're going to hear it.
That's the story behind that.
I was playing the song and performed on the team.
Forces of nature have fought each other since the dawn of time.
That was it. That was our newest broadcast jingle right there.
And it...
All right, we're going to cut it short.
That was a lot of fun.
And who's singing right now is an AI programmer on Far Cry, actually.
So, you know, we got to work with other teams as well.
It's Raphael Parra, and we're really grateful he lent his voice to our little project.
So that's about it for us.
Thank you so much for coming to our presentation.
We really appreciate you guys coming.