This is my talk, Platforms are People Too,
The Importance of Finding Your Champion.
Resume timer, okay.
Thanks to GDC for having me here,
and thanks to you guys for spending
your precious GDC time with me.
And I'm excited to have an opportunity
to speak on this topic,
and share what I've learned in my time in the industry.
And I gave an earlier version of this talk
at a couple places last year internationally,
but this is the fancy jazzed up GDC version,
which was supposed to do a thing when I said that.
Please hold.
Or not.
Next slide.
Okay, it worked that way.
All right.
So glad this is being recorded.
All right, so I'm Nick Suttner.
I'm a writer, designer, consultant.
I'm gonna give you a decent bit of background on myself,
but hopefully you'll see why that's important
and how it leads into this topic.
So, like a lot of people, I started working in games in retail around 2004.
I had a lot of first-hand customer experience there, championing games,
and it felt like being on the front lines of the industry.
And sometimes I feel like I've sort of only gotten further from that in my career,
which is a weird feeling.
I handled this highlight on the corner there.
That's Shadow of the Colossus, that's the PS4 remake,
but back with the original release,
I got the most pre-orders of Shadow of the Colossus
in my district, because I was a champion for the game.
I loved telling people about it.
And there was an interesting experience
where people would come in and they'd say,
what's cool, what should I play,
especially people that didn't buy a lot of games.
And I had the opportunity to walk over to the shelf
and grab something and say, like,
you should play this thing.
And they would come back two weeks later.
and say, oh, that was awesome, what else do you have?
Which is a pretty rare experience,
and I really enjoyed that,
and that was maybe my first taste
of being able to sort of recommend things,
and I got a taste for it.
I also had a gaming blog at the time
with my friend Tom McShay, who's sitting back there,
who has that in his face, he's not in here.
But, and that's what sort of helped get me to my first E3,
and I got more interested in it,
and moved out to California here in 2007.
I got my first industry job writing for EGM magazine, which I had grown up reading, and
writing for 1up.com.
And this was my first cover story, which also ended up being the last issue of EGM, so I
guess I killed the magazine.
And while I was there, though, at 1up especially, I reviewed a lot of games for those outlets,
especially some of the early seminal indie games on Xbox Live and PlayStation Network.
And I got comfortable championing smaller, more interesting games, and championing them
came naturally to me.
And I'll make a note here of N Plus and Braid, two of my favorite games, and I'll bring those
up again later.
If you're dying to read these, you can read them later on.
Well, I don't know if there's a lot left, actually.
One up sort of comes and goes.
So I moved over to PlayStation in 2007,
and I worked there for seven years.
Started in product evaluation and worked with big publishers
like Rockstar and Activision, but I was always the happiest
when I got to work with independent developers.
And I was vocal about the games I cared about,
and people got to know me as sort of a content expert
in that space, and as an advocate for smaller games.
And I became the lead account manager
in developer relations on that team.
I worked with hundreds of developers
and helped make indie games a part
of the PlayStation culture in a bigger way,
especially leading up to the PlayStation 4 launch.
I signed a lot of games while I was at PlayStation.
All these ones.
and a bunch more, and I worked with all of those devs
to help them release their game,
and served as an advocate within Sony
throughout the process.
And I spent tens of hours, and sometimes hundreds of hours
on each of these games of work,
so it was a lot of my time spent on this stuff.
And again, here I'll call out The Witness and N++,
both sort of the sequels or spiritual sequels
to things before that I'd championed in the press.
And so I'd sort of gotten to those developers
and so those relationships were sort of mutually beneficial.
And then I moved over to Oculus in 2016.
I worked there for about 14 months,
again, advocating for smaller, more experimental games,
and found out that a lot of the same challenges exist
for developers in VR, like visibility.
Especially when most press aren't really covering VR in a meaningful way yet.
I also along the way wrote a couple books on the work of Fumito Ueda while I was working
those day jobs.
And if you remember when I was a champion for Shadow of the Colossus back in my EB Games
days, well it became my favorite game and my book is basically a love letter to it.
So I used to have to champion games one by one at the store, and by this point I had
a larger platform to speak from to champion something that I loved.
And now I'm a game developer.
I've actually been independent myself for longer than I worked at Oculus, which is weird
because I guess I wasn't there too long.
But this is a shot from a board game prototype I'm working on.
But I'm working as a writer and an editor.
I contributed to Celeste and Guacamelee 2 and Escape.
I've done consulting work for a bunch of developers, including several that I work with at PlayStation.
I'm also an advisor on Untitled Goose Game.
I just wanted an excuse to put a big goose in here.
And also working on a few of my own game projects and writing some upcoming games and doing
biz dev for a few of them.
So you know a bit about my background.
I've been a champion across retail and in the press and at PlayStation and at Oculus
and in print.
And there's really others like me at every big company.
There's people who care about interesting,
artful, diverse games across PC and mobile
and VR and console.
And if you only remember one thing from my talk,
it should probably be this.
It's that companies don't care about your games,
people care about your games.
And you might ask why this distinction is really important,
and this is sort of the whole point of my talk.
Developers often ask these questions.
They ask, will Microsoft care about my game?
Why does Nintendo care about my game?
How can I get Sony to feature my game?
And I think these are really just
fundamentally the wrong questions.
Really the right question you should be asking yourself
is who will help fight for my game?
Because really I believe that any promotion, support, or funding of your game happens because somebody cares about it.
This is true of platforms, publishers, press.
People often refer to Sony's like indie program, and there was never a program really. Nothing formalized.
It was just people who cared about indie games.
And I should say too, by the way, this talk isn't about getting your game funded,
but I think finding your champion is also a critical first step towards funding.
And this talk also might feel sort of like Video Games 101
to someone who's released a successful game
and seen the results of this sort of thing,
but for everyone else, I think its importance
really can't be overstated.
And also, this was the best image I found
when I looked for Video Games 101,
because I like the bold choice of intercapping video games.
And it's a kid's YouTube channel,
so you probably should like and subscribe and comment on it.
And also, though, even I should say for experienced or successful indies, I think you can always
use a reminder of this.
And your game probably sold well because you made a great game, but somewhere along the
way someone else had to fight for it and chose to promote it.
And also this talk is not just for indies.
AAA needs their champions too.
They might have an easier starting point, but they still need someone to fight for them
internally, and I've seen this firsthand.
So sustainable game development isn't just about making your game.
So many developers focus on making a great game and then don't spend the time telling people about it.
Oh, by the way, I forgot to tell you to silence your phones
and please fill out the evaluation afterwards,
but you're gonna do that anyways.
So sometimes developers don't even tell
their launch platform about the game really,
and they just submit it to certification when it's done,
which seems crazy to me.
And a lot of developers just don't even upload a video
with their game, and you have to ask
why a storefront would be excited to promote a game
when people are gonna have a hard time
finding out more about it.
I tweeted this recently, I said,
if you don't have a trailer ready to launch
alongside your game on the storefront,
you're not ready to release your game full stop.
And I had a couple of people saying
that they just didn't have time
while they were finishing their game,
and to me, you really shouldn't consider your game finished
until you're ready to launch it properly,
that's all part of the process.
And you shouldn't really be committing your date
to fans or a publisher,
because I think having all of this ready
should dictate your date,
not just release based on when the game
is gonna be finished.
And games almost never do well purely organically.
Sometimes people just don't show up to buy them.
And some developers feel like releasing a game
on a console is enough to have decent sales,
and I can tell you that that's not right.
And sometimes games go viral and word of mouth is enough,
but you can never count on that,
so you should never plan for it.
The rest of the time, you really do need a champion
to help connect a great game to its potential fans.
And once a game has a bad launch, it's much harder to get future promotion.
And it makes sense, because why would a storefront want to repromote something
that didn't make them any money the first time around?
That's really their primary goal.
So I'm going to talk about how platforms work.
My background is primarily on the platform side, so that's going to be my focus.
And we'll touch a bit on publishers and press later.
But a lot of this is relevant to working with them as well.
And this is also relevant for finding champions, I think,
who are streamers or YouTubers and non-traditional marketing
and PR channels.
But that'll be a different talk.
So I'm going to give you sort of an overview of how platforms
are set up.
Content teams are typically the game experts.
Oh, wait, sorry.
Hold on, let's talk about those first.
Yeah, so we have the sort of promotional teams.
And so we have the store teams at a platform,
marketing teams, PR and social teams, the events teams.
And then we have a content group sort of separately.
And those people are the game experts basically
across consoles, PC, mobile, VR, this is true everywhere.
These are basically what you would call third party
or developer relations, product evaluation,
account management, that's usually the same thing.
And that's where your champion is going to reside.
And promotion often goes, those people go to the content people and they say,
OK, what games are cool? What should we be featuring?
What should we be talking about on the platform?
And the content team says, well, it's probably Ape Out,
because that's an amazing game.
And so that's what we should feature this week
and talk about on all of our channels.
And people running digital storefronts
tend to be experts at running storefronts,
but probably not at games.
And the people working at the storefronts,
usually their goals, their KPIs,
are to make the most money every day.
So they're going to default to promoting
the most reliable things in the biggest games
that are already successful and already making money.
So it's up to the content people
to sort of help steer that and tell them about new stuff
that they should consider promoting as an alternate.
And every time there's an event at a GDC or an E3 or wherever,
the events team is going to ask the content team what games they should feature.
So again, that's going to come back to that same champion helping feature your game at an event.
And these are also the same groups who are going to promote your game out into the world,
and ideally they should be doing most of the work.
The caveat being that you can't really ever rely on any of these things, so you still
should plan on doing as much promotion as possible yourself, and that platforms don't
really tend to create promotions from scratch, but they'll very often boost your signal.
You know, Apple has a store editorial team as well.
You should submit great assets with your game.
They care a lot about how your games make their platform look.
I assume Google and Stadia are also going to have some sort of storefront, and if it
does, I can pretty much guarantee this is going to hold true there as well.
Steam still makes editorial decisions about what to promote.
Even if a lot of it ends up being algorithmic, those first few hours of your launch can make
a huge difference and be really important.
And all these organizations are full of people.
Everyone has their own tastes and likes and dislikes and their own priorities.
You know, a caveat being that there's different ranges of skills and empowerment and not everyone
can help you as much as everyone else and sometimes you have to find the right person.
And some platforms are more automated than others and still ask you to, you know, email
an alias instead of a person, but there's always people at the other end of those aliases
and you can still do your best to connect with someone.
So briefly, just for some context, these were my priorities I felt like when I was working at the big platforms.
My first priority was to the players, to sort of share cool games to more people.
And then to developers, to have them have a good experience with the platform.
And then to myself, really, in my own career,
and what I sort of wanted to make that into,
or how this all affected me.
And then, really, to my platform.
Like, I didn't fundamentally care about Sony's bottom line.
Why would I?
I still, I'm a huge, you know, I grew up with PlayStation.
I'm a huge fan of the platform,
and I want to make their storefront an awesome place,
but, you know, these were sort of roughly my priorities.
I really, you know, I genuinely was more interested
in a good experience for players and developers
than maybe myself, with the platforms being less.
And this is true everywhere I've gone.
And honestly, I think this is what made me good at my job when I was at these places because I cared more about my work than the job itself.
And I think my point here is that your priorities probably align a lot more with biz dev people than you think they might,
because they really do genuinely care about your games and success, often over their own platform.
And also I should say you don't really have to be a partner title to benefit from this.
You don't have to have a formalized agreement with the platform.
You know, even if you come out first on PlayStation and later on Xbox or first on mobile and later on PC,
you know, a champion can still help you with those things.
And typically, you know, there's less reason to promote a later release on a platform.
And therefore this can be just as important, if not more so, you know, if not more important on an eventual platform
that might end up making you more money.
And I'll say too, if a platform ever offers you money of any sort, even if it's a small amount,
you should probably take it, because the extra support there is gonna be, you know, that'll be the real win,
because that leads to so many more promotions and opportunities.
You know, these platforms tend to have sort of buckets, where any game that they're partnering with
or funding even a small amount is that sort of the first priority, and then everything else.
So even taking a small amount of money can make you a much higher priority,
and the, you know, the long-term dividends of that can be much more important than the money that you took.
I didn't know quite how to do this,
and this was a late slide,
so I apologize for the awkwardness.
But a lot of people have asked me how to navigate
sort of exclusivity and multi-platform launches.
And this is probably a good rough guide
of the sort of support that you'll get,
and it's basically the same for each platform.
But essentially, if you self-publish
with some exclusivity on a platform,
you're likely going to get some degree of the support
from the platform, and that's your best chance of doing so
if you put the game everywhere,
like you can see on the bottom.
Maybe not as much, or actually the fourth line, I guess.
And if you work with a publisher, then it really depends on that publisher's relationship with the platform.
But coming out second on a platform, again, doesn't mean that they're not going to give you any support.
It just means you need to find your champion there.
I've said in the past, you only get one launch, so you should nail it.
But also, that's not true when you get lots of launches across every platform over multiple
years.
And if you do do that, then you're going to need the best champion you can find for all
of them.
You can have multiple champions, and you should have multiple champions.
Platforms largely understand that you need to make
the most sustainable decisions for your business
and that you should take the best deals offered.
And there were lots of occasions
where I would tell a developer
to go take a deal from someone else.
And if someone was bitter about that,
I think you probably shouldn't be working with them anyways.
So weird that they gave us milk to drink for this.
All right, oh yeah, that was my drinking milk break.
So let's go through the steps of this,
of how to find and maximize your champion.
What does this mean, making the right game?
Step one, can you make the wrong game?
And I don't like that idea, I don't like how it sounds
because I believe that games are art first
and products second, and I really want you
to make the game that you wanna make.
However, it's still good to understand what you're making
and its implications on your potential champion.
And this could be a whole separate talk,
but we're just gonna cover the basics of it.
So I think really the easiest types of games
to get excited about generally.
are games that are either doing something fundamentally new.
So these, you know, these games are getting older at this point,
but I'd say all of these that are you are doing something fundamentally new in games and not just in their genres.
Or you could do something that's sort of the best of a genre.
Here's some other examples of things that are maybe not radically new, but did what they did really well.
And if you're not doing one or the other of these things, you're going to have a much tougher time.
And it's less likely, probably, that you're going to make something that's the best of a genre,
just because that's a lot tougher, but you can definitely make something new, or you can try to make something new.
And I'd also say that the one thing to me that all these games have in common is either great art, or at least memorable art.
So visuals really do matter.
And this past Saturday I was hanging out with my friend Zach Gage, and he said something
else that I really liked about what sorts of games might have the best chances of success
right now.
And then last night I was up pretty late and I started Googling pictures of Zach to add
to this talk, and he's just such an impossible dreamboat.
So let's just all enjoy all of these.
I just want to hang out with all of these Zachs.
These Zachs Gage.
It's like Attorneys General.
So basically, let's just put this really bad chess logo, it's less distracting.
So Zach was talking about making a game that people want to play now, especially, to be
able to participate in the conversation around a game.
And if we go back and we look at those Something New games that I pulled out, I think there
is a certain zeitgeist around them that's really true to that idea, and they weren't
known quantities, and that's part of what made them really true discussion pieces, and
that can be a huge factor in success.
And again, all ties back to giving your champion reasons
to want to fight for you.
I believe that a screenshot should sell your game.
This is Inside, of course, by Playdead.
It's beautiful, evocative.
It makes me want to play it.
But not everyone has six years to polish a game
and make incredible lighting.
This is Plug and Play by Etter Studio.
And sometimes simpler things can be just as intriguing.
I don't know what it is, but I want to play it.
This is Prune by Polyculture. It's sort of a less-delayed example, but this is simple, beautiful color,
it's intriguing, makes me want to know more about it.
And if your game is hard for you to describe,
it's gonna be hard for your champion as well.
And they probably won't be excited to be your champion,
not because they're not excited about the game,
but because it's gonna be too difficult
and they're gonna run into too many roadblocks internally
when they're trying to talk about your game.
Salt and Sanctuary.
So I don't think that the best game pitches are really
it's this thing meets this other thing.
And I think that usually means your game
is not unique enough to stand out.
However, it's still better than being able to describe,
you know, to not describe it or talk about why it's unique.
And Salt and Sanctuary really has an easy pitch.
Stark Souls in 2D.
And I don't think I actually overtly said that,
but that's what was clear from when I played it.
And it has a great demo and a team I wanted to work with.
Really, it was a no-brainer for me to sign and work with.
And as a counter-example, there was a lot of discussion about why Tacoma didn't maybe sell as well as expectations at launch,
despite great reviews and being from the Gone Home team.
And for me, just in my opinion, a big reason of that might have been that you...
To me, you could never really tell what the experience of the game was when you were watching a trailer.
I didn't really know what sort of gameplay it was gonna be,
and I had to play it to appreciate the game,
and I love the game, but I had to play it to find that out.
And I'd actually also argued that
Where the Water Tastes Like Wine had the same issue.
It was hard to watch a trailer and really understand
what the gameplay experience was gonna be.
So your champion really has to believe
you're capable of making the games that you wanna make.
I think if you say you're going to make the next Apex Legends, then it's not going to
go anywhere because you're probably not.
But if you say you're going to make the next Stardew Valley, with enough time maybe you
can, who knows if it'll be successful, but you can probably accomplish something of that
scope.
And I think having examples is really important, even if you haven't made a successful game
yet.
Just showing that you're able of making anything is much better than nothing.
And also I should note that your champion really only cares about the concepts of your game, not really how the game turns out.
I think that's usually true actually when people are funding things.
So I don't think you should feel pressure to deliver exactly the thing you're showing them up front.
And knowing when to show your game I think is important too,
especially when you're pitching.
This is something actually that Tyler Sigmund
of Red Hook Studios, who did Darkest Dungeon, reminded me.
You know, basically if you're making the next No Man's Sky,
then you're fine to show your game at an early concept stage.
But if it needs to be something
that needs to be proven out further,
you should wait until you have a demo
to showcase the game well.
And this is sort of a paradox
because you might need publisher support earlier,
but you might be more likely to get it later
if you can wait until when you show the game
at the right point in time.
Something else to consider, maybe don't post programmer or placeholder art online before
release if it's going to change significantly.
It might come back to haunt you.
If you're going to use placeholders, make them obvious.
Chris Hecker told me that the art director on Spore would put big pink triangles in screenshots
to be clear that they weren't final.
And as much as people say they can look at something early and imagine it, they're really
visual by nature.
Everyone's visual.
And if this image had come out pre-release, then this game would have been a lot less
appealing when people were searching for it.
And of course that went on to be Braid and David's gorgeous art.
So thankfully when you look up Braid online now, you don't see this, you see this.
So that was the first step, making the right game.
And sometimes your champion will find you entirely by themselves,
but you can never really count on that.
So we should talk about making yourself findable.
First thing, go to events. This is the great first step.
Submit a talk to events if it will help get you there.
These are just a few of the ones that came to my mind first that I've gone to,
but there's tons all over the world all the time.
Aaron from FlipFly, who made Race to the Sun,
he told me a story about when I stopped by their booth at PAX in 2013.
He said, we felt that really made the trip worth it,
and those types of meetings make going to GDC worthwhile as well.
We know that dev relations people typically manage a lot of accounts,
and so we put a lot of value in face time.
And we've always sort of assumed that by showing up at events like this
and making time for meetings,
we're communicating commitment to the platform as well,
which I feel is totally the case.
So just relax, talk to everyone at these events.
They're not just an opportunity to meet fans and potential fans of your game,
but really with potential business partners too.
You can sell a few copies by staffing a booth
and hanging out with your game.
Meeting the right business person
and having the right meeting can unlock
selling tens of thousands of copies.
And I think it's important to talk to everyone
at a platform or not, specifically,
don't talk to people who aren't business people
and not just the business people
because even event staff, PR,
other people can become your champion as well.
And if someone from Nintendo PR loves your game,
then your other Nintendo champion
will have a lot less work to do
when it gets to the PR stage.
I would always take it pretty seriously when someone from another department at PlayStation
would say, hey, have you checked out this game?
Especially if I didn't know about it already, because we can't possibly see everything.
So I would always put stock in that.
And other developers can be your champions too.
This is like not great pictures of the indie megabooth online somehow, but...
You know, the community, your community is very,
my community, our community, is very supportive
and good things can come just from
having casual conversations.
Developers might share press lists with each other,
contacts, other helpful connections,
and maybe you can even find someone else
to collaborate with or connections
with artists and musicians.
And also if a highly respected developer recommends another developer to a platform that can go a long way.
Dan Edelman, who used to do biz dev at Nintendo,
he told me that this whole chain of people, Kyle Gabler from World of Goo, introduced Edmund McMillan,
made Super Meat Boy to Dan, and then Edmund introduced Derek Yu, who made Spelunky.
So it's this whole chain where, you know, if you have a good relationship with a platform,
they'll take your advice seriously. So this networking can have these great knock-on effects.
This is the JW Marriott hotel lobby during E3,
also not great pictures,
but this is where a lot of the business gets done at E3.
And you've, I'm sure, experienced some of this around GDC.
Hotel lobbies, bars, coffee shops
are all great places to meet people
and have sort of more personal conversations.
And even if you can't afford a pass to a show,
a lot of them are still worth going to
just for the networking, like GDC, obviously.
This is my old laptop from, this is like a sheet of stickers
that I peeled off from when I worked at PlayStation.
Because I actually do believe in like, you know,
if you meet a platform representative,
give them something small.
If you have it, give them a cool sticker,
a business card that has a code to download
your game or your demo.
Nothing big, but I still have this
and I'm a nostalgic person, but it's a cool thing
and I don't know, I'm weird.
Remember people's names.
It sounds obvious, but you won't find a champion
by seeming like you don't care.
Always reintroduce yourself with your game,
with the name of your game, I should say.
It really helps your champion to associate the two
because they're meeting a ton of people all the time.
Don't be offended if they forget your name
because, again, they're meeting a lot of people.
And even better than an event is going and visiting an office of a platform.
If you have a contact already, I'd say offer to go visit them.
I think it's always worth it.
Tell them you're coming to town, you'd like to come by and present your game.
I think they're often likely to accept.
It's nice to just say, oh, sorry, I can't do my regular work.
I'm going to go have lunch with the developer this afternoon.
And it's a much better context to see a game in.
It'll be a lot more memorable for them as well.
Hopefully you know about Presskit,
something else that really helps
with making your game findable.
Presskit's by Rami Ismail of Flumbeer
and some other good folks.
You should really be using it.
This is gonna help you get some basic facts up
about your company if you have one in your game.
Make sure you have your contact info listed online,
which sounds obvious, but you'd be surprised.
And a personal contact is better than a generic one.
So I think nick at company.com
is better than info at company.com.
It might feel more professional that way, but it feels like screaming into a void otherwise.
And it really does drive me crazy.
It drives me crazy how many games don't have websites or a trailer online.
Don't make your game hard to find. Make sure the name of your game is Googlable.
And if you're lucky, someone might be looking for you.
I think being persistent is good in this case.
And as far as reaching out to your platform and trying to stay on their radar,
DevRelations folks get hundreds of emails every day,
and so checking in often helps.
It keeps you near the top of their mind.
Personalize your emails. Don't just put people on a generic mailing list.
And keep your emails concise.
Include a video or a GIF, something moving for them to see.
Don't send email blasts to everybody that you know at a company.
This is a way you can maybe get an important problem solved quickly, which is important
sometimes but it's not going to help you find your champion.
If you can't go to events or don't have a contact somewhere, you can check on Twitter.
Again everyone is just people, they're probably going to respond to you and if they can't
help directly, they're probably going to send you to whoever can or whomever can.
So we talked about making the right game, making yourself findable, and then you need
to give your champion the best tools to help you to find your game.
So we're gonna talk about arming your champion.
So a big part of this is sending thoughtful demos
when you send a game somewhere.
I'd say that Steam keys are ideal,
better than a standalone build probably, but not essential.
If you have a dev kit already,
sending a build on their hardware
shows that you're sort of serious about the platform
and that helps a lot.
If a game is planned to have controller support,
you should have controller support in your demo.
The only game that I managed to not get funded at Sony
that I really wanted to and fought for
was because they didn't have controller support yet
in their demo, and so it was hard
to extrapolate the experience.
And don't make people have to read separate documents.
It's better to mock up a simple control instruction screen
and put it at the front of your demo.
I'd also say a YouTube link is always better
than an attached video.
It makes it easier for people to share around internally.
And if you provide a private YouTube link, you can track the views.
You can see if they shared it.
Maybe you can, like, guilt them into watching it.
And I would say beware if you're making, like, a multiplayer game.
Developers making a multiplayer game
would sometimes try to schedule me times
to play their game online with them,
and it never really went quite well,
especially when you're trying to fill a room of people.
And it also means your champion might not
be able to show it at events, since it's
going to require multiple stations.
So again, make multiplayer games,
but just be aware of those challenges
when you're trying to find people to champion them.
Yeah, make it self-contained.
And some things I can share.
I talked about those already.
So research their platforms as well.
Be aware of any similarities to other first party games
that are coming, that they're developing themselves.
Be familiar with their storefront,
just passingly familiar even.
You'd be surprised how many people I'd be in meetings with
and would not really know how the PlayStation store worked
because they just hadn't used it.
And think about their priorities as well.
Does the company have a new peripheral coming out?
Can you support it in a cool way?
That's sort of the ultimate ammunition for your champion
if that's something you can do, of course,
without shoehorning it into your...
And this is true of publishers as well.
You should know their lineup, you should know their taste, so you're not pitching them something
that is just not a good fit from the start.
Your personal story can be just as important as your game.
Knowing about your situation, your team, this will help people remember you.
Do you have a unique development story, a unique background?
Your champions are going to tell your story for you when they talk about the game.
The story of Axiom Verge was a big part of why I was able to sign it.
The developer, Tom Happ, had a day job at a bigger studio and worked on his passion
project at night, one that he'd had in mind for years.
And we could help him have a bit more freedom to focus on the game.
We knew that the game was going to turn out great.
And I'd also say the story of your game, don't confuse this point with the actual literal
narrative story of the game.
The setting of your game is plenty.
People really won't care about the larger story of your game.
When you're pitching it.
And I'm sad to say that as a writer, but it's true.
And think about really talking about why you're making this game.
Companies can only fund so many games and you can only make so many games in your life.
Why did you choose this game?
Why are you the one to make it?
Not your relevant experience, but your personal motivation.
I think that's part of your story and what people will respond to and pay attention to
when you talk about it.
A lot of developers have asked me this, they say,
what are you looking for?
And I think, again, that's the wrong question.
If you think about everything we've discussed,
people are just looking for projects that get them excited.
It's just a personal thing.
If anything, what aren't you looking for
is an easier question to answer.
Maybe they have a lot of one genre already
or know that they have trouble getting
certain types of games supported.
I think being specific is actually better than being flexible when you're pitching.
I think you want to provide very specific budget and timeline breakdowns.
You don't want to give people a menu of options of different sort of compromised versions
of the game you could make for this amount of money, but I'd rather make this version
of the game for this amount of money.
It might feel counterintuitive, but really I'd say you should pitch the version of the
game that you want to make.
I think that's the version that's most likely to get signed.
I was actually just right before this talk, I was meeting up with Matt Dixon, who's a director of business development at EA,
and he said this verbatim without me prompting him. He basically said, yeah, you should pitch the game you want to make,
because that's what's going to get funded. And I was like, oh, that's in my talk. I'm going to say your name.
Think about shared goals.
Every platform has their own goals.
For instance, with mobile,
how nice might your game make their hardware look?
Nintendo has a strong heritage of platformers,
Microsoft of shooting games and racing games,
and Sony with art games.
Maybe there's an annual seasonal promotion
you can align with.
Maybe they need to launch a new feature you can support.
I think framing the conversation that way is good.
How can my game release best support PlayStation?
And for subsequent launches,
second, third, distant launches.
You know, adding new game content is helpful.
Maybe there's a new game mode you can add.
Maybe it's just some new costumes.
Maybe all the DLC is now included in the main game.
You know, give people a hook.
Make them a new trailer for the new platform.
Cut a new trailer and make new assets for them
so it can feel special and unique for their platform.
Consider platform-specific features, like we talked about,
if there's a way you can support that without too much work.
And treat them like your first launch.
You don't want to feel like a second-class citizen on a platform,
and you shouldn't make them feel that way either.
And the more serious you take subsequent launches,
the more seriously those platforms are going to take you,
and then that release gap of time will start to matter less.
So we talked about making the right game,
making yourself findable, arming your champion,
and really you wanna keep your champion around
for a long time, from when you put it on the radar
to when it comes out and well beyond that,
and then on to your next game.
Your champion should always have access to the latest major build of your game,
that has new features and polish, it doesn't need to be small iterative builds.
And if it wasn't a Steam build that you can push updates to,
just give them a link to a folder where you can keep the latest build,
the latest assets, trailers, screenshots, and all of your contact info, your phone number.
You never know when someone wants to call you up with an opportunity.
I'd say trust your champion in my experience.
If they don't need to ask you permissions for small things, more opportunities will open up.
Flexible and willing and trusted developers really get the most ubiquitous support.
And if you're sort of difficult to work with or precious about your games and these opportunities,
people just skip you over to save time, even if it's a great game.
They're just going to want to work with the games that are easiest.
You know, your champion might need to go argue with their legal team on a contract,
and I think that's okay because really, again, I think they're on your side most of the time.
And similarly, don't, you know, you need to choose your battles.
So don't push back on things that your champion said won't happen,
just accept it and move on to the next thing,
and think that they might genuinely have your best interests in mind.
Learn organizations and their tool sets.
Don't just email your champion about everything.
If they've introduced you to another department to work with,
then email that person and CC your champion.
For example, well, I've been gone long enough,
I don't know if it's true now,
but DevNet used to be sort of the backend
tech support message board stuff at Sony.
There's a learning curve up front,
but that's the place to get your questions answered quickly
and then just asking your champion
is gonna end up sending you back there.
Don't announce anything without checking with your champion first.
You might be excited to share things publicly throughout development,
but always check in with your champion.
They might have an opportunity you don't know about.
Always give them the opportunity to debut the news or boost your signal
because a lot of times they won't do it if you already have.
It's sort of less exciting on their channel as if it's old news.
And maybe even try talking to platforms before you announce a game.
It's sort of more fun for them to be able to announce
and that unlocks bigger opportunities a lot of the time.
And that's a defer to your champion on your launch date.
Think about that.
Don't choose a release date and then ask them
if they can support that date.
Defer to whatever date they say is best,
because this is gonna make you eligible
for more promotions and support.
And they can often warn you away from bad dates,
even if they can't tell you why.
Like, hey, there's a big game launching on that date.
You should probably push back a few weeks.
So, this one's sort of about saying thank you.
So consider sending them something nice
when they help with the milestones.
I think it really is worth the cost, like tenfold.
So Axiom Verge, Tom Hap sent me a couple gift baskets
when we signed the game and at release.
The Star Wars guys sent me a $100 Starbucks gift card.
That was really nice of them,
and I'll always remember those things,
and it meant a lot to me.
It doesn't need to be anything decadent,
and most companies have a gifting policies
of what they can accept, but even a small thing
to say thank you really goes a long way with them
and helps maintaining that relationship long-term.
A friend texted me this picture when he saw my name in the credits of Guacamelee 2.
Give credit when it's appropriate.
It means a lot to the people who help you and it will make people want to work with
you again.
It's been really mutually beneficial for me and having these connections is helping me
now.
And the credits can also actually be a great place to find the names of platform or publisher
people you want to work with and then hunt them down online if you don't have a contact
otherwise.
So let's go on a journey together.
This is Jenny. Jenny has a game. Jenny goes to GDC.
Maybe she gets into GDC in some way that she can show her game.
So then a person from a platform comes by
to check out that game. So then Jenny can email them afterwards. Or maybe not.
Maybe she didn't show to GDC and maybe Jenny has to go on Twitter and hunt them down.
You know, Jenny's going to send a build of the game.
Then maybe the platform person is going to be able to send them a dev kit back.
And then Jenny's gonna keep them up to date
with videos and screenshots
and all the right ammunition we talked about.
And then the platform person is gonna help
release it into the world.
And this workflow is just how it works most of the time.
And I think it's important to recognize all these steps
and have that dialogue.
So, oh yeah, and then you should say thank you as well.
That's important.
We're gonna do a little case study with my friend,
Mr. Phil Tobitoski right here from Young Horses.
So,
Yes, that's Phil.
And I love, by the way, how the red on your jacket
lines up with the tie.
That's perfect.
You have too many arms, though.
So thanks to him for helping me with this session.
I didn't know he was gonna come to this talk,
so I'm glad he gets to see this in person.
So back at GDC 2011, which is a long time ago,
the original Octodad was an IGF nominee
in the student showcase.
Some assets that Phil Kamde sent me.
And it didn't look quite as nice,
but it was still goofy and fun.
And I saw that the team was from DePaul University
in Chicago, which is where I grew up.
And I approached the team about it there,
but it was sort of too early for them
to consider doing something commercial with it,
so we decided we'd just keep in touch.
And then they showed the game later, a couple years later,
at PAX East in the Indie Mega Booth.
And everything looked a whole lot better as well,
and they started pursuing it as a commercial product
and as Young Horses as a new team.
And the timing then meant that we could have
early conversations with them about PlayStation 4.
This is a nice quote that I can't see
on either of these screens to read myself
that was from a Polygon article
where Phil said some kind things
about just having this relationship
where we could talk and I could help push
for the game internally.
But you can probably read that.
So we sent them a PS4 development kit,
which no one was supposed to post pictures of online,
but somebody did.
And they got the build running great in four weeks,
which meant that we were able to showcase the game
at, you know, in our E3 booth, which was huge.
And it was even on stage as part of this Indie 8 event
that we announced, which was a huge moment for PlayStation
and for the team.
And I think none of the big platforms
had really done anything like this before,
and there's actually not great screenshots of that
somehow online either.
And yeah, that's about it right there.
So, you know, we ended up bringing them to over 26 different events.
There's me and Phil and Adam Boyes, the old VP from PlayStation,
and this costume that PlayStation made for them,
which ended up being sort of one of the earlier, like, PS4 mascots almost.
We had a private room for Octodad at the PlayStation 4 launch event,
where press got to play the final PlayStation 4 hardware for the first time.
And Sony Japan, you know, they were champions as well.
They even helped localize the game and made a special logo for it.
And so these guys have sold, I mean this is even out of date now, but after five years sold over two million units.
Amazing. Let's give Phil a round of applause for that.
And you'll notice too, only 17% of those sales are on PlayStation and 28% of the revenue.
But I think that together we helped boost the profile of the game massively,
which helped it go on and have this great tale across multiple platforms.
So a lot of that was really important.
And I'll say, sorry Phil, I don't know if Octodad is a great game.
Maybe you don't know either.
And the team has had some fun with that themselves, despite the great sales.
But I thought it was a great game.
And it felt new to me and it had a lot of charm.
And it made me want to fight for it.
And I think that had a big impact on the game.
And the team was always really easy to work with.
They were a really responsive partner.
And that made me want to work with them.
And the timing worked out in their favor.
And they didn't know that it would when they started talking to us.
But we just kept in touch.
And then an opportunity like this presented itself.
Okay. More milk.
So, a quick note on publishers, and we'll have some time for Q&A as well.
So there's a lot of different indie publishers. This is an incomplete list.
All of them have different priorities, different deal terms, different expertises.
They also have different relationships with each of the big platforms.
So I'd say make that part of your research.
Is the publisher you want to work with released multiple games on a platform you want to be on?
And they all have something in common, again, they're comprised of a bunch of different people with different tastes and you should think about them the same way you do your platform champion because they're going to have to fight for you as well.
And almost no one you talk to initially is going to be the final decision maker. So there's always going to be this step of them fighting for your game internally.
So I'd say also identify your needs from them.
Is it localization?
Is it QA?
Is it help getting hardware?
Is it just submitting the game and pressing the big red button?
Is it marketing and PR?
Or is it just money that you need?
Is it just funding?
Publishers tend to be very different from each other, more so than platforms.
Helping to decide exactly what you want beforehand is really helpful.
And with regards to funding, you know, is the money recoupable, is it not?
Do they recoup at different rates?
Some recoup the marketing and event spend that they put towards it,
or want the right of refusal, or to own an IP.
And these are all different negotiating knobs to turn.
And usually when you have to turn one up, you'll have to turn another one down.
And no one's going to give you exactly what you want.
I'd say also in my experience you can usually tell from someone's response time how they're going to be to work with.
Just because they're slow doesn't mean it's bad, but it's a consideration of working with them.
And the same key elements are the same when you're talking to potential publishers.
So the things we talked about making the right game, making it findable, arming your champion, and keeping your champion.
I reached out to my friend Brandon Sinclair from Games Industry.
He's been a journalist for over 15 years.
He reminded me that press like to lurk and that if you post things with the game dev
hashtag and other developer communities, press are often watching.
And if a journalist has awareness of a game already,
it's going to be a lot easier pitching them to cover it.
And think about what's interesting about your game.
Is it in your pitch?
Is it the game mechanics?
Is it the topic or the theme?
Is it your personal story?
Is it the development method, something non-traditional?
And targeted outreach is important too.
I think reaching out just totally broadly to press won't get you the best results.
Consider the audience for your game in which press outlets, you know, target that audience.
You know, so Double Fine, I've talked to them about how they targeted influencers and streamers for Gang Beasts,
but, you know, for everything, more of an arcade, they targeted Polygon and leaned hard into both of those things.
And you can think about targeting press
who have covered similar games.
So if you're making a game for niche hobbyists,
maybe you don't want to target games press.
Maybe you should find where your audience is.
Maybe your game about quilting would
be better targeted at a quilting magazine than Game Informer.
And do your research.
Don't reach out to an outlet asking them to review your game
if they don't do reviews.
Just make their job easy.
I have no notes there.
You know, don't just say,
here's my game, want to interview me about it.
Give them the news hooks.
This is the first quilting game developed in Australia.
And as a reminder,
you should use press kit at the bare minimum.
You can add a statement giving people permission
to stream the game, help them to share it.
And really, every time someone needs to email you
asking for something,
there's a chance that press won't bother covering your game
because they're busy people.
So give them all the assets they need up front.
So let's talk about the wrong way to do it a little bit with press.
Sending out big mass mailings, you know, you should reach out to writers individually. They're much less likely to cover your game from a mass mailing.
You know, not being transparent is not great.
If you've pitched two writers from the same site on a story, let someone know if the other person picks it up.
Being negative sucks. Don't pitch your game as a solution to a problem that other games have. Find a more positive angle.
And don't be a jerk.
Being willing to express a strong opinion on an industry issue can be refreshing,
because AAA often can't do that.
But badmouthing other games is just not a good look.
So I'm going to help you cheat a bit.
These are just a couple of good starting points for these things.
One of them is a list of a thousand press people
maintained by an EA employee from DICE.
And another one is a list of people and outlets and influencers
who have covered indie games before.
Let's leave that up for a second.
I mean, you can always tweet at me later if you want this, too.
So in closing, I'd say make the game that you want to make.
Find someone to fight for it.
I'm Nick Sutner.
I'll be here throughout the rest of GDC.
So come talk to me, and thank you guys for your time.
And don't forget to fill out the evaluations later online, please.
And if anyone wants to ask some questions, please come up to the mic or yell it out and
then I'll repeat you.
I have a quick question.
Hello.
Is the mic on?
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
I'm sorry.
How do you feel about, I guess, console or platform exclusives going forward?
Do you think the player community will be less annoyed?
Sorry, I missed the second half.
Will the player community be less annoyed about people going exclusive going forward?
It seems to be happening more often.
Sorry, it's a little echoey. Will who be less annoyed?
Sorry, console and platform exclusives.
Yeah.
Will the player community become less annoyed over time?
Right.
Is it happening more?
No, I mean, the players are always going to be annoyed,
and this is just how the industry works.
People need to find sustainability for their studio
and find funding, and exclusivity is a part of that.
It's hard to say whether the sort of, like, you know,
I don't know, entitled parts of game culture
and people who...
You know, are just the vocal minority fans
yelling about stuff?
If that will change, I would guess not anytime soon.
So people are gonna be angry about those decisions.
But you know, I think there's some,
you should have some consideration about that.
But I think a lot of that, for better or worse,
tends to be directed more at the platform, I guess.
But I think you should do what's best
for making your studio sustainable, your game sustainable.
That's a knock-on effect that hopefully
will improve over time, but it's hard to say.
Yeah.
All right.
I don't know if it was yesterday or earlier today, Outer Worlds was announced to be on
Epic instead of Steam.
And based on his question about people being upset about exclusives on certain platforms,
I was wondering if it's on us to champion our champion.
Say, hey, Epic is helping us out a lot here.
We are working with them because they have helped us.
Obviously, I'm not part of that.
Sure, yeah.
I think that particular issue with Epic Store stuff right now
is probably pretty touchy,
so you have to be careful about getting yourself involved
and embroiled in that.
But definitely, generally, I mean, again,
Phil said some really nice stuff about working with PlayStation
and me personally over the years,
and that made a difference to the platform.
What are your thoughts on this?
So there's a lot of really good advice on how to find who you want your champion to
be and what to do once you've recognized that they are now your champion.
But how do you know that they've become your champion?
That's a great question.
Where's that moment where you can start emailing them regularly and you know you're not bothering
them at that point?
Yeah, and you'd like the step five.
I think you can tell in talking to someone whether they are genuinely excited about your
game.
And I think if they're excited about your game and you start to feel that through the
process and things getting done and positive momentum towards release or promotions or
whatever, I think that's one of those things you'll feel when you see it.
I think there's not ever really going to be a moment when it's like, oh, you're my champion.
In fact, a lot of the times I'd say a lot of devs successfully release games and working
with me a lot and never thought about this piece of the puzzle and never thought that
oh actually, again, some cases I spent like hundreds of hours just working on your game
but it's, you know, understandably from the outside it can be the black box of just things
that happen for your game but it is always people fighting for it.
It's a good question, I'll think about it more.
But I think, yeah, they'll, you know,
if someone genuinely isn't excited about your game,
that's not your champion.
Like, you need to find that person.
And if no one, if you can't find anyone who's excited,
that's maybe a self-reflective moment.
If it's like, okay, maybe I'm not talking
about my game the right way.
So, yeah, I'll have to think about that.
And once you do find that person who's doing champion things for you, and you've got a
hunch that they're it, would they like to hear, like, hey, you're my champion, thank
you, or is it awkward to be given that label?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Because I actually would think that might be kind of charming to be told that by someone
if I'm trying to help them, but also it might be a little bit awkward.
I mean, thank yous are always hugely appreciated.
I think, you know, if you can do it in a way without putting pressure, because you don't
want them to think like, oh, now you think that they're going to go and do everything
for you, where maybe it was a one-off thing or a smaller thing.
You know, I think just I appreciate you being,
you know, you going to bat for us.
I appreciate this opportunity.
I appreciate the things you've been helping me with.
Like, I think you can sort of say it without saying it
and imply that, you know,
you know that they're going to bat for you.
But maybe I think labeling it overtly
early on in that relationship,
especially there might be like a weird pressure there
and setting yourself up for some disappointment potentially.
So that's, I don't know, off the top of my head.
Nice. Yeah, sure.
We've got eight and a half minutes.
You guys can go enjoy GDC or come up to the stage
and talk after, or fill.
Do I think these relationships will change at all with streaming services becoming more prevalent?
Yeah, that's the big part of my talk I think I am missing, is that the future is coming soon.
I think it depends what the execution looks like on what the delivery method of games is there,
and storefronts or subscriptions or whatever it is.
I think people are always going to have to fight for your games.
I think that's just always going to be true.
And what that means and how it looks on the consumer end will change, but I think it's
always going to be someone at a company caring about a game.
I mean, if it goes fully algorithmic and you submit your game and it gets sorted based
on genre or whatever, it's like, yes, there's a scenario where it is taken out of the hands
of people.
But I think...
Even streaming services or subscriptions or whatever,
it's like what games you see when you look at a platform,
like someone's gotta choose what games to show there.
So I think that's always gonna stay true.
Or not always, never say always.
Cool, well thank you guys for coming.