Hi.
Here we all are at GDC 2017.
I hope that you're well today.
And I hope that you've been learning, expanding,
and feeling deeply in your experience at this conference.
Even more so, I hope all else, above all else,
that on this journey this week that you
take the advantage of accessing the brilliant minds and hearts
to congregate here.
This place, this time we share, and these people around you
are something really special.
I'm grateful to have you in my life,
and I'm honored that you've chosen to attend this talk.
So let's begin.
Firstly, now that that's awkward,
let's make sure you're in the right room.
Here's everything that we'll be discussing today.
I'll briefly introduce myself,
I'll tell you a little bit about what Tacoma is, and...
why the VO production needed to be so weird.
The majority of our time today, thankfully,
will be spent focusing on the pre-production,
directorial, and technical techniques
developed specifically for this project
and the lessons we learned along the way.
Damn, you know, I was really, really trying
to get technical techniques out so much
that I just flubbed the next, but whatever.
And finally, we'll wrap up with my personal favorite,
the Ask Me Anything style Q&A.
All right, let's do this.
That's me.
My name is Michael, and I write and direct video games.
I am the casting and voice director of Tacoma.
I used to be the dialogue lead at a company called 2K,
and then I started a company called
the Bright Skull Entertainment Group.
I'm originally from New York.
I currently live in Los Angeles.
In the rare hours when I'm not making games,
like most of you, I do other things.
So what exactly is Tacoma?
And again, why did it need the fancy hoopla?
Well, in short, Tacoma is Fulbright's follow-up game
to their inaugural divisive smash hit, Gone Home.
It's a narrative exploration game
and it takes place on a lunar transfer station
midway between the moon and Earth
in the not too distant future, 2088.
You arrive at the space station to discover it abandoned
and need to figure out what happened to the crew.
You do this by uncovering fragments of footage that shows
in the environment around you AR security recordings of the
missing crews' interactions and movements.
You can choose to follow and observe any of the AR ghosts of
whichever characters you wish, and at any time, then play,
pause, or rewind the footage and explore the playback from
other perspectives.
If any of you guys are familiar with the off-Broadway theater
experiment that is Sleep No More.
Tacoma's gameplay is heavily influenced by it.
And if you are not familiar with Sleep No More,
I highly encourage you to get your ass on a plane,
fly to New York, try and get tickets,
wait until you get them.
No, you should probably, you know what,
buy your tickets online and then just go.
This is very much so one of those things that's best shown
by visualization as opposed to verbalization.
So here's a short clip of Tacoma's gameplay
to show you what I'm talking about.
I can't believe it.
Well, you told me we could renewed.
Yeah, but I mean us, us, not the whole crew.
I guess there's just something special,
something special about Tacoma Crew 88.
Yeah, not just special, it's unprecedented.
I looked it up, it's never happened before.
Well, everything happens once.
I don't know, personally I'm happy for us.
Happy to be stuck up here with these people for another year.
Some of them?
Some of them aren't as pissy as you.
What's so bad about these people?
Well, they live in a tin can for one thing.
I think it's a pretty nice can.
Oh, you have a pretty nice can.
Oh, yeah?
Well, I think you have a pretty nice can.
Shut up.
So the name Obsolescence Day is more like a joke.
You could say it's facetious.
Kai, you probably think I'm an idiot for never even thinking about why it's called that.
Out of curiosity, why did you think it was called that?
I thought maybe it was when some old type of AI had become obsolete.
But, well, I guess that doesn't make sense.
I think you get the idea.
And I also want you to remember that scene there where they're baking something, because
it's going to be relevant later.
Okay.
So, as you can see, the narrative paths often split and rejoin, creating very complex scenes
where timing and performance of work are concerned.
Combined with the aesthetic choices made for the vocal performance in this game,
we knew the traditional solo and even basic fixed mic ensemble recording were just not going to cut it.
So we made the decision very early on to do full cast ensemble sessions,
but then also decided to add choreographed full movement performances on top of that,
focusing solely on the VO performance and not actually performing any motion capture.
because we are very, very clearly insane people.
Um... click.
The end result is a technique I've been semi-jokingly referring to as FOCAP.
So without further ado, I'm going to share with you some of the experiences we had
and the lessons that we learned.
Usually one of the largest hurdles in ensemble recording is scheduling,
which is as mundane as it sounds.
Coordinating recording sessions where all the actors, studios, creative stakeholders
and so on are available at the same time is no small task.
I did a talk specifically on this at GDC a few years ago and in the same year also at
MIGS.
So I know it's available on the vault if you really want to dive down that rabbit hole.
Hope you like Excel.
Because pretty much every scene in Tacoma has every actor in it,
having disjointed and separate conversations,
it made it actually really easy to juggle what would have been a
complex shot list.
We didn't have to rework the scripts and all the actors could show up at the
same time,
which made actually scheduling this really the easiest ensemble I've ever
done.
We did have one major setback though.
In order to get the material together for the early press builds,
we wound up finalizing the cast a year before the principal recordings.
Then that year later, when we went back to do the principal recordings,
one of our core cast members was unavailable and shooting on location
on the other side of the country.
So we had to make a really hard call, and it's a call that I don't really take lightly.
I hate recasting. I hate it, I hate it, I hate it.
And especially when you're doing an ensemble.
because the actors grow attached to each other and they get attached to each other's characters.
So part of the psychology behind Ensemble is the actors look forward to coming back and playing
with those same people over and over again. Their actual real human being interpersonal dynamics
start blending into their characters that they're playing and it really echoes in the performance
quite nicely. However, because of this recast we had to bring a new guy in.
And man, he did really good.
He slotted in very quickly.
We were very fortunate with this.
And he really brought something to the character
that I hadn't seen before.
And it's a very complex character,
so it was a nice addition.
That I just, you know, I'd have been remissed
if I didn't give you a big old warning
when doing ensemble and having large gaps
in your production cycle.
On the plus side.
Because of these pre-alpha sessions we were able to stress test our work flow and the
techniques we invented for the project to make sure they worked.
Some of them did.
Some of them became lessons to be learned.
And it became really valuable.
So that was cool.
I'll show you some of that.
Script preparation and shot lists we talked a little bit about before.
This is usually a complex part of producing ensemble content.
This too is covered in the talks I mentioned in the vault, so I'm not going to go too far into it.
And again, for this project, it was dead simple.
We actually wound up being able to very neatly package everything into three and a half hour long sessions.
And then with a half hour buffer for everybody getting there and being like, oh, hey, the traffic's terrible
You know getting to know one another and so
So yeah, we actually had the opportunity to do this project end-to-end linear, which was amazing
We basically got to do it as a play
And because of that, we were able to have something that sometimes is really difficult to manage in ensemble work,
where you're disjointedly going back and forth between scenes.
We were able to ensure, without a shadow of a doubt, that the emotional transitions between the scenes would be consistent.
Which was very nice, I thought, and it worked really well.
onto something new, choreography. So because we
were entering, because we wanted the talent to be able to move
around and interact with each other and do things with props,
every scene needed to be choreographed. So here's some
excerpts from my blocking notes. Now, I'm going to bring out the
laser pointer because my drawings are shitty.
Where is it?
Pointer options.
Laser pointer.
Great.
So on these pages I have blocking notes for every scene.
Most of what you're seeing here is set dressing and movement.
The actors are these crudely drawn circles with their characters' first initials scratched
into the center.
Okay, here is an example of two people starting in a location
crossing the room to meet up with another two people.
And here's an example of two people walking back and forth
to simulate having a walk and talk in a long hallway scene
which I'll show you the results of that in a second.
Actually, have any of you guys seen the footage
from Tacoma, like the 15 minute gameplay or anything?
No? Okay, cool. That sequence that's choreographed right there is the opening shot that you see in the station.
I kept the set dressing as minimal as possible, and I wanted to use what we already had in the studio.
So, we use chairs, which are these insanely weird H-shaped runes that are sort of pushed
onto the page with quite an eloquent hand, I must add.
And then music stands are notated by these crudely drawn straight lines.
So I also sent this little beauty to the studio ahead of time for setup.
It is, if you can't tell, a room layout drawing that is labeled because my drawing is terrible
because my handwriting apparently makes things clearer to no one. For those of you who can't
read my handwriting, which is all of you, this says music stands, this is the director's
stand, reader's stand, talent chairs and chairs because I just can't draw a chair, okay?
We've got Ashley cool to draw some chairs.
All right.
Why aren't we going?
There we go.
No, get back.
Good, sorry.
So would it have been simpler to record the game
by bringing everybody in for solo recording sessions?
Absolutely.
Would it have sounded nearly as good?
Hell no.
I've said it before, I'll say it again, and I'll say it on every freaking opportunity I get to say it until it is the norm.
Acting is reacting. You can't react to nothing and nobody while you're standing in an isolation booth with an Excel sheet in front of you.
I think Matt Mercer said it best when we were recording Masquerada, he said...
Ensemble is giving us the opportunity and the ability to make adjustments in real time,
which is a really good way of looking at it.
From my point of view, it removes the mandate for me to have to have the actors play to
the voices in my head and allows them to collaborate with me and build scenes together organically
and actually do the fucking jobs that we were hired to do.
So that's always nice.
It was decided early on that the creative direction for the
games dialogue should be what I've been referring to as sci-fi
mumble core. The emphasis here is being placed on getting
organic realism focused performances as opposed to
cinematic realism. A good sound design analog for any of you who
may happen to be sound designers would be like an explosion
sound.
Audience expectations are big, boomy, oofy, and utterly ridiculously over the top,
but a realistic explosion sound is a big pop.
So, it's the difference between realism and audience expectation.
So, when an actor is stationary, standing in front of a microphone,
as you would in solo recording, or even in large room ensemble,
their instinct is to focus more on their own vocal performance,
which naturally draws them back into cinematic realism.
This is generally the desired result for pretty much every other project
on the planet, but not this one.
Think about it really. I mean, in your day-to-day life, are you focused on the quality of your voice
and emoting effectively as you talk to a friend or co-worker or giving a lecture at GDC? Probably
not, because you sound ridiculous, though I could probably sound a lot better. I'm really sorry.
I tried to go to bed at 10 last night. It did not happen. So for organic realism,
the more distracted the actor is, the better.
Movement helps put the actor in the scene and it gives them honest pacing and it also allows them to focus less on their vocal
performance. So here's some example of performances that without the help of movement in the faux capture methods
it's my opinion we would have never gotten to. Now
please note before I show you this the audio and the videos is from the camera and not from the board.
So be gentle. Oh my god. Wait is today obsolescence day?
Yeah
Didn't Odin give you a job to do?
No. A computer playing favorites. Well, one does never cease.
Are you okay? Can you feel your feet and hands? Yeah. Oh, my hip just hurts.
Bert? Bert!
You enjoy it while you can, Williams.
You won't have microgravity on your side forever!
Oh, I will dunk on you in any gravity!
Jupiter gravity dunk!
Ha ha ha!
Maybe I stopped thinking we should really like each other.
She called me!
Ha ha ha!
It's like, um, it's our dirty dancing move.
Sorry, I had to leave that, uh, that out, that out to get you.
So that last shot by the way, where she jumps into her arms,
that is the final screen use take.
The audio quality was fucking perfect, which blew me away.
And I'll talk a little bit about how we got to that
in a moment.
In addition to the stage blocking, I also used some basic props to further distract the talent and help them with the scene pacing.
Being in a treated recording environment though, I had to be extremely eudicious in which props we could and could not use.
Obviously we wanted to steer away from anything that generates self-noise,
but we also needed to avoid props that would make noise by way of manual manipulation or brushing against.
Also, I wanted to give the talent the smallest possible tool set so that they could familiarize
themselves with the props quickly and not have to learn new mechanics for how to handle
things.
So I narrowed it down to these.
a set of rubber coated dumbbells and a couple of packs of broken in bicycle playing cars
of which my house has many. I used the weights to help in scenes where the talent needed
to show efforts or if they were like unpacking supplies, carrying large objects or catching
something. The cards I used in scenes where the characters were doing detailed tasks like
checking in on lab equipment or
decorating a cake. And what I would do is I would have them, I
had like a red deck and a blue deck and I would have them sort
the cards in suit order, in natural deck suit order and then
also by red and by blue. So it was something they had to focus
on while they were performing and you'll see in a second how
cool that sounded. It does. And I have proof. And action.
So, the clean room?
Yeah, it's fucked.
But we'll be able to breathe on the drone,
so that'll be nice.
Oh, come on, lift.
I thought maybe it was some old type of AI
that had become obsolete,
but I guess that doesn't make sense.
Yes.
No, AI, art-like designer hardware.
As soon as the new model's out,
you trade in the old one for customer loyalty.
AI are more like, well, they're more like mighty redwoods.
Ancient organisms growing and adapting year after year,
decade after decade.
Right.
How do you think this looks?
that man, both of those guys, all the actors that you just saw
are really, really talented people. T.J. Ramini is charming
as fuck in real life. All right. Another little trick I used
concerns the 7th member of the crew, Odin, the ship's AI. He's
a sort of ubiquitous 7th crew member that can be in multiple
locations and engage in multiple dialogues simultaneously. It's
very similar to the AIOS structure in the movie Her. Has
everybody seen Her?
wanted the performance between the human crew members to feel
so naturally organic but I wanted to have a psychoacoustic
cue that was different when they were interacting with Odin. So
we did something a little different there.
To get to there, I had Odin record outside of the ensemble
in a traditional solo isolated recording session.
We also did this with the protagonist,
who is not a crew member.
She's actually sitting right there.
Sarah Grayson, everyone.
And we did that so that they would
have a disconnected feel from the rest
of the organic performances that were going on around them.
It came out really cool.
And what we did in the ensemble sessions though,
was I had my production assistant stand in as a reader,
face to face with whoever was talking to Odin at the time.
That was the two little crudely drawn sticks.
They were on the other side of those
whenever they were talking to Odin.
All right.
So let's get into some technical stuff.
Script preparation.
Something we do on every project is
to take the script as it's delivered to us
and reformat it into our game script template, which
is basically the standard theatrical format
with a few minor modifications like scene numbers,
individual line numbers.
If the game has it, file names. If it doesn't, then we just leave that blank.
Usually, by the way, when we do file names, we do them in micro text on the far right margin,
in case you're really nerdy about script formatting and really want to know that one.
But the reason we do the line numbering though,
it allows me to quickly tell the talent
which sections of the script we'll be working on
for each take.
I'll call things and say like,
all right, let's take one and two,
and we'll grab those two takes back to back.
And then I'll say, all right, let's move on,
and we'll do three on down to 12.
or in this case I'd say three to end of page.
And it allows us to quickly communicate
what chunks of script we want to be working on
at any given moment.
It also allows me to, after we're doing the ensemble takes,
if there's something that I feel
that we didn't get there on,
a line that we didn't quite get to
and needs a safety pickup,
go back and give me four
and give them the lead in on three.
So give me three and four.
It's just a quick way of communicating.
It takes.
like 30 seconds to do it, or that's how much I assume that my assistants take to do this.
It's probably a lot longer.
It's also very important, and silly for me to have to say this, but numbering your pages
When you're using paper scripts, it gets really messy in the studio, and you will totally
kill valuable actor and studio time having your actors or an assistant or an engineer
or you digging around on the ground looking for page 6 when you're on page 200.
Not fun.
Well, I mean, you can easily do it if it's numbered 6, but if it has no page numbers
on it, you're fucked.
It's also really useful when you're using tablets, which we pretty much exclusively do now.
This motion happens all the time.
And then, oh fuck, where am I? Everybody else is on page 20? 20, 20, 20, 20, 20.
If they have the page number, they can see that it's page 20.
I'm telling you this because when I first started out, nobody was numbering pages.
I'm hoping by now this is standard. I'm sorry, this is really boring stuff.
Um, I love actors with all my heart.
Truly. But for the most part, actors, they don't really have a lot of knowledge about audio and what microphones pick up and what it sounds like at the end, and how it gets from their mouths to the in-game.
I mean, it's not that they don't have the vaguest of ideas, I'm talking about really technical stuff like shirt motion or things like that.
But mostly I'm talking about paper. So that's why we use tablets.
And there's been so many times when we were using paper that...
the actor be performing, they'd be in the middle of the most beautiful take you've ever seen,
little golden BAFTA trophies were just smiling in your eyes, and then...
Can't use that take.
One of the biggest lessons from our pilot session was that paper scripts absolutely
need to be eliminated when you're doing any sort of movement in the studio for the same reason.
For the same reason.
So tablets for everyone. You get a tablet, you get a tablet, you get a tablet.
And for- you get a meme for anyone who didn't get that joke.
All right, when working with Focap Ensemble
or any Ensemble project really,
pre-populating your markers and Pro Tools
is practically essential.
So, and the same with providing shot lists
for the engineers to work off of
and for you when you're at your director post
to understand how much time you've used
versus where you should be in your estimates.
Here's a sample of the shot list and then following that the
template that I sent over for the engineering team a few days
before the session. Here's the shot list. If you want to
effectively manage your sessions, not waste money and
make your engineers happy.
you need to be really fucking organized. This shot list shows
the engineer on the B column every name of every scene that
we're doing in the order that we're doing it. This one was
easy because it was linear. Column C is showing the
estimated time for how long each shot should take to record. And
then the other columns are all a list of who is on mic and should
be being recorded at any given time.
That's a really, really, really, I can't make it any smoother than that.
But on the Pro Tools side of things...
I had this made. It's one track per actor character. The track names are pre-populated with
the file naming convention that I've been using forever. It's year underscore month day
underscore actor name underscore character name. That way when your files come out and if
you've ever seen me talk about my post production process.
When your files come out, they're all auto-numbered.
Pro Tools is one of the only DAWs that'll do underscore 01,
which is one of the reasons that I use this, sorry.
It's one of the only reasons I use Pro Tools. Every other
system uses the operating system's file naming convention
in order to name its files. So your first take will always be
named file name. Your second take will then in Windows be
named file name parentheses one end parentheses dot wave. File
three will be end parentheses two end parentheses. The reason
that I use Pro Tools isn't because I think it's a great
DAW.
because file number one is named underscore oh one so that when I'm tracking all it when
Either I or somebody else is tracking all this stuff in an Excel sheet, and they're saying okay
That was take 1a was the select
That we have a tool that parses that Excel file at the end of the day
Goes through and auto renames all the file names with zero margin of human error
into the, into the depot. So that saves a shit load of time.
Alright. Boo, boo, boo, sorry. Markers are then pre-populated
horizontally across the timeline. Uh, what I do is, is I use the
estimated time, uh, that I have in the shot list, and then I add
a healthy 5 minutes to each, between each marker. So if a
scene took 10 minutes, there's 15 minutes worth of timeline to
work with, uh, there.
It makes post-production so much faster
because when you fire up your sessions later,
all the scenes are there,
all of the actors' takes are there,
and you can just quickly identify where you need to be.
And there's a lot of separation,
so it's not all clumped together.
So rounding things out, we did some serious homework on mic selection.
I needed to have something that would work for full motion and not have any proximity
alteration, you know, getting too close to the microphone or getting too far away from
the microphone.
microphone. Any movement noise, self generated noise. And what
happens with lavaliers a lot too because really thin cable and
really shitty shielding is self noise made from conductance. So
that you hear like a movement noise when the cable is moving
around on you. So we tested a ton of mics. I also if we were
using lavaliers.
So we tested a ton of mics. I also if we were using lavaliers.
Wanted all the warmth and fullness that can really I thought to this moment only be provided by a large diaphragm mic
Because you know, I'm I'm really easy like that
After numerous shootouts with a cater of really disappointing
lavalier solutions, we found a clear winner in the DPA4061.
Oh man, that mic sounded so good. I'll play you some stuff in a
few seconds. After some experimentation with several mic
placements, which is very important in lavaliers, we
which included the headgear with the head-facing microphone
placement, which we found to be much too prone to plosiveness.
And then also hairline mounting, so over the ear
with a little countryman B3 style kind of thing.
And you see that all the time in stage and on pop singers
and stuff like that.
We found that was too prone to cross nose air movement
problems. Which your nose is basically a fucking little
baffle. Yeah. So we ended up wig micing. So center forehead.
This got rid of all plosives.
It sounds super clean. It also makes everyone look ridiculous,
which is great. By placing it here, we removed all of those
things. So if you're going to use a lavalier, that's where I
would put it. If you don't believe me, which I wouldn't
either, here's some raw, completely unaltered audio from
those sessions.
I think. Oh, it's still on the laser pointer. That's the pen.
Sorry. Sorry. I'm not going to sing for you while we're
waiting. There we go.
Yeah, that was that little walk and talk from before.
And again, there's zero editing on this.
I just pulled these straight out of Pro Tools.
So the clean room?
Yeah, it's fucked.
But we'll be able to breathe on the drone,
so that'll be nice.
Oh, come on, lift.
That was the little weight scene that you saw earlier.
And then I'm telling you, this is completely raw.
This is the jump scene.
Then I start thinking we should really make the most of it.
Fucking clean as a whistle.
I couldn't believe it.
When that happened, I was just like,
oh yeah, we're not gonna be able to use that take.
And the engineer's in my cans like,
yeah, no, that was clean.
I stopped the session.
I went into the, sorry.
I stopped the session, I went into the control room
and I said, play it back.
And I heard that and I went.
So yeah, there's DPA4061s, I really like them.
All right, so here's an area
where you really don't want to scrimp.
You do not want to try and save yourself a few dollars
by getting four sets of labs for six actors
and have them switch out in between scenes
and then start dividing your shot list
so you only have four on mic while you could be using six.
The logic there being that you're going to save a few dollars renting or purchasing microphones,
but your talent is the most expensive commodity in that studio when you're doing ensemble.
you will absolutely come out cost negative factor
and the time suck that is swapping out between takes.
So one mic per actor, belt clipped with an XLR.
The engineer would come in in between each shot,
he would unclip and he would recoil all six mics
and then start addressing everybody else.
Additionally, when I wrote out that stage blocking, I was really conscious and made
previsualization drawings, which I then erased because they were even shittier, to
visualize the cable pathways when blocking out those scenes so that I would make sure
the actors didn't cross paths or do anything stupid like wrap themselves around a chair.
I mean, who knows, what, right?
That's pretty much it for the technical stuff,
which really kind of rounds us out.
And that's it. So thank you all so much for coming. Please stick around for Q&A which is
again like I said my favorite and I hope you guys have questions because this is really weird
shit. There's mics in the aisle so if you have questions please line up now and use them. Also
as you leave please thank the CAs and the AV team for doing such a great job at this show.
Without them this entire conference would be an unmitigated disaster. So please also
Thank you.
And please also remember to fill out your surveys,
especially if you really like the session.
And my review of you today,
I just really enjoyed having you here.
So without further ado, Q and A.
You were here first, I believe.
Fight it out.
Okay, I win.
Okay.
Really insightful talk, really awesome.
Thank you.
On your shot list, you had time budgeted for each of your shots in the scenes that you were recording.
Mm-hmm.
Um, did you ever go over time for any of those shots?
And if so, like, how was the best way to deal with that?
Thank you. That's a really good question.
Uh, so...
What I do is I buffer in a little bit of time for each shot.
I also know that the earlier shots in the day
are gonna take longer than the later shots in the day
because like I said, that's everybody's getting there,
especially if it's the first day,
you gotta buffer in like half an hour or so,
maybe even an hour.
I don't even call that buffer. I actually just call that getting to know each other and try and do like an hour of dedicated just
Hey, let's meet each other and figure each other. Oh you were in that
I was I know so-and-so from that like all that kind of crap
So you need to put that in once everybody gets to starting to work
Yeah, you need to make sure that you're going at a pretty good clip and making sure that you're staying on schedule
But you also need to have the foresight to know that you're gonna need a little bit of buffer
Also on multi-day shoots if you go if you if you do hit a little bit under it's okay because you have you you have
Thankfully left space on each of your sheets because you're scheduling this
That's why I schedule them at three and a half hours and not like max to four
cool. It's also, if you're doing it like we did, you also need to
factor in time for getting everybody mic'd up, wig taping,
wig un-taping, all that kind of stuff. So, yeah.
Awesome, thanks. Hey, no worries.
Hi.
This was great.
Thank you.
So what I was really struck by was even
your use of the word ensemble, because especially talking
to voiceover actors, often they'd never meet each other,
and they have the other human in their ear.
So what is the moment that they all went and had pizza together
and became an ensemble?
What is that?
That's a really, really good question.
I'll tell an anecdote, and then I'll
answer the question, the specific question.
Is that OK?
So we're working on another project. We're working on Masquerada Songs and Shadows, which was a
1,200 page, 60 person cast, full ensemble that we did end to end ensemble. It's great. And if
you haven't played it, which I know most of you haven't, you should. Story is brilliant. But I
remember there was a really, really, really seasoned high profile voice actor. And I don't do
the name thing. He came in.
to our studio and was just like, he walked into the room and was just like, oh, you guys are
recording? I can go wait out in the thing. It's just like, no, dude, we need to get you in here.
We're performing ensemble. Which his agent should have told him, by the way, because we told
her. That's a whole other mess. And he just fucking froze.
And was just like, I could see the shock on his face
and the happiness that was exuding off of him moments later.
And this is a guy who's done hundreds and hundreds of games
and animated films and he's like a major commercial voice
that you hear all the fucking time.
And he said, I've never gotten to do this.
And he gets in the booth and it's like, it's just fucking,
it was just incredible to see him be overjoyed.
I mean, his character needed to be mean,
but to see him be overjoyed with the idea and concept
of being able to play off each other.
And I think that's when Matt said that quote from earlier
that, you know, like you're able to make those adjustments
in real time, which you cannot do in solo recording.
So the specific question that you asked though,
is what was the moment where they all like pizzaed up
and got to know each other?
Yes, and how do you convince people to pay for that extra time to have everyone in the room?
Ah, that's a great question.
Um...
If someone is hiring me to do ensemble,
they've got a pretty good idea of what I'm going to bring to the table,
and they usually trust my methods.
If it was when it was earlier on in my career,
and I was just starting to try this kind of stuff...
It was a little bit of a challenge.
So what we did was we called it a table read.
And we had everybody come in for the table read.
And yes, they familiarized themselves with the material.
Yes, they got to know one another.
We also, because we labeled it as a table read,
brought in all the writers.
We brought in the creative director.
And we brought in the audio producer
and the executive producer.
And we all sat down with the actors.
And I had the writers, I had each one talk about
what their contributions were to the project.
I had the creative director talk a little bit about the high-level concept of the game.
And we gave... people had their character sides ahead of time,
so they were able to ask intelligent questions about their characters.
I made sure that the writers were explaining the dynamics and relationships between each
character in that room.
So this is how you feel about them, this is how you feel about them.
Usually what I do when I'm writing is I make a character relationship matrix for every
single character in that game.
Even if they don't know them, I will want to know how they would feel if they had met
that character.
And then I usually end up doing that just naturally when I have a script handed to me
that I'm trying to think about the dynamic relationship between each character.
So does that help you?
That was great.
I want to see that Matrix.
You should share it online.
Hello, thank you for the wonderful talk.
Thank you for coming.
I had a question about, assuming that you knew that you were going to be doing this
sort of more experimental method for the actual sessions, did that in any way influence the
means by which you auditioned actors and made your casting decisions?
Yeah, that's a really good question.
We did actually have the agents, we highly encouraged them
to submit their theatrical resumes, which you sometimes
can't just pull up.
So we had them submit their theatrical resumes
and any footage that they may have had
that highlighted movement.
So whether it be like a walk-on role or a recording of a stage performance, things like that.
The reason that you don't recognize a lot of the people in that room is because most of them came from TV and film.
So that was something else that we ended up doing on this.
I mean, a few of them, like Abigail Marlowe and Natasha Loring are like killing it in voiceover right now.
But the others are like, are film and TV people.
one of them wrote the damn Cosby theme song and was on one of my favorite shows of all time.
So that was cool. That's a really good question. However, because we were centered on vocal
performance, we were able to do a lot of things that were not necessarily
we really, really leaned into who was going to provide the best characterization of the voice
because movement is natural and we didn't need like, okay, so T-pose and then freaking go into
your thing and hey, I am angry and rush in or whatever, you know, like.
Oh, that's a whole other thing.
Localized movement should absolutely be a thing.
Does that answer your question?
Yes, thank you.
That was very insightful.
Thank you for the question.
Hello.
Hi, Michael.
Thanks for your talk.
I'm wondering, you said earlier that it
would have been easier had you done non-ensemble recordings
for this game.
But it wouldn't have been as good.
uh... if you had to estimate how much more time it took to do the ensemble recording
like percentage wise uh... could you? Is it like twenty percent thirty? I will give you a
really uh... really good answer to that I hope. Um... so with ensemble
by its very nature, more of your time is spent in pre-production and post-production,
but less of your time is spent in the studio. And in fact, most of the time, and I can't
guarantee this for anybody out there who's like, we're gonna do ensemble and this could be great,
and Michael Cervix said this, and we're taking that to our producers, but most of the time is,
and that's how you all sound in my head, by the way, most of the time it ends up being cost neutral.
and I know that that sounds insane but it is. It ends up
being cost neutral. That's a good argument. Thank you.
Thanks. Cool. Yes. Hi, Michael, thank you very much. It was
terrific. My question is were there any unforeseen challenges
that came in on the post side of things from doing the ensemble
sessions? Like I guess if you...
had a performance from one actor that really worked well for the take,
but maybe not from the second actor or third in the scene?
Did that make editing those lines more difficult once you got into post-production?
Would you mind repeating your question and possibly rephrasing it?
Sure.
Because you had multiple actors in the scene, I guess within the recording,
did that make editing those lines more difficult
once you did post-production?
Got it, thank you.
So I think what you're talking about is step over lines.
So yeah, so like just there.
So, and I'm sorry that I didn't go into too much detail
on things like that.
I've just, I've given a lot of talks about Ensemble at GDC.
So I was hoping that we would highlight
just the stuff that's specific to the Tacoma project.
But I've covered that before
and it's an excellent question.
What I do is I have them perform the scene as best as possible.
Get the scene to sound amazing.
And if there's a line that's a step over line,
now that they've already got it in their system
and know what it is, I tell them to do the scene again,
but give me pause for the ellipses.
And it works really well.
This game had very little step over.
It worked out really well.
But for things like combat and that too,
like when, you know, that was a good example
of how you saw I had a three burst pain reaction in there.
That was because in the scene,
she's pain reacting while other people are talking.
So you do that one time,
because you don't want to stress the actor's voice.
You want to let them do that one time
so they get the amplitude of the scene
to the place where you want it.
And then you go back and have them do the scene
without onomatopoeia or any sort of stressful voice work
and save that for the end of the scene.
Does that help you?
Yeah, absolutely.
Thank you very much.
Does anybody else have questions? You can literally ask me anything. You want to know how
magic works? Hey, how are you? Hey, great, how are you? I'm well, thanks. Awesome, thank you for
the talk, it was really great. Thank you, thank you for coming. So the arm jumping take, if the
one you thought wouldn't work, what alternative way would be that you would have recorded that?
That's a really good question.
The reason that we did the arm jump
was because we had done like three or four takes
of that scene that just weren't getting there
with that joyous, exuberant, movement-based performance.
And so, because we had them standing still and just being like jumping for joy,
or just like, just moving or hugging, like air hugging each other,
and just wasn't getting there.
And I'll be honest with you, like, as a voiceover director, working with voice actors,
sometimes it's really challenging to do things like ask an actor to do something physical
to interact with each other.
You don't want to make anybody uncomfortable or to put them outside of their sphere of comfort
And damage the relationship between you and the talent and also between the talent and the other actor. They're not fucking toys
They're people so you can do things like ask them like I want to try something that might be a little bit weird
It's okay to say no. Would you mind actually jumping but in this case
In this case, the two actresses that were playing the couple
really, really, really liked each other,
like right off the bat, like in reality.
And Natasha's just a very, very much so her character,
like they're both very much so their characters.
And so Natasha's just like,
would it be okay if I just actually jump on her?
And Abigail's like, and she looks at Abigail,
and Abigail's like, yeah.
Which is why when Natasha comes off of that,
she's just like, she comes.
I can't believe it!
And that ended up just being really cool.
So I wanted them to do that just the one time,
because I didn't think that the audio quality was going to be very good,
but to get that amplitude of emotive response into the scene work
and be like, oh, that's how far we need to bring it.
That's why that scene worked out really well.
There was a couple of other points in the production as well where that happened.
without getting out, I did this to be as spoiler free
as possible, by the way, but there is a scene
where the scene just played better,
where one person had their head in another person's lap.
And it worked out really well.
And again, I asked permission, said like,
hey, would it be cool if we tried this?
And they were just like, fuck yeah, let's do it.
I was like, all right, great.
So yeah, does that answer your question?
Yeah, well, another part would be if that didn't work out,
how would you adjust, what would an alternative thing be?
I mean, you got the weight and they know how it'd feel,
but if the audio didn't come?
Oh, if it hadn't have worked out, I guess.
I mean, I don't want to like, at the risk of sounding brash or arrogant, I think I'm
a pretty okay director, and I like to think that I'm able to coach people into difficult
situations if need be.
Again, this one worked out, but I see your point, like what if she jumped and she was
just still emoting, just like, yay.
That wasn't how she was doing it, by the way.
But if she had been, it's one of those things where there's a few subtle triggers that you can do to help to coach that performance without being obnoxious.
One of them is to... Have you voice acted before?
Yeah.
Okay. Who is someone who has not voice acted before?
Who is someone who has not voice acted before that would be totally cool with standing two feet away from a microphone and giving... You? You?
Okay, we'll do both of you.
Why don't you come on up?
And while they're coming up, I'm...
I'm not very good at miming, I'm sorry.
Oh, five minutes, thank you.
Okay, so you're in a fight.
You are going to be punching him.
It's going to be a one-hit punch.
So, and remember, I already have previous knowledge that neither of these guys are professional voice actors.
So, I want you to do a one-hit punch to him.
And it's going to be a quick, quick burst of kind of thing.
So you're going to be like,
And when he hits you, your reaction is going to be like,
Wait, no, face, sorry.
There, that. You're gonna go and break a little bit. Is that okay?
Don't actually...
Okay, so how hard is he gonna hit me?
He's not actually gonna hit you.
Is it more about the speech or the reaction?
It's much more about the reaction, and the way that I like to describe combat,
which I'm totally stealing from DB Cooper, is this.
When you're hit, it's always a surprise.
So you're caught off guard and things are very vowel-driven.
They're diaphragmatic, but in the face especially, your mouth is caught open.
If you are doing the punching, the combat comes from a place of knowledge.
You know that you're going to give a punch, so you're secure.
Your jaw might be a little bit tighter, so things can be a little bit more consonant
driven.
Okay?
So, I want you to punch him.
Not really.
Go ahead.
Okay.
That's my... This is my reach.
Don't actually punch him.
No, I...
I don't want to be that guy.
Okay.
And here we go.
That was pretty good.
Can you give me one more take?
And instead of coming from the...
Coming from the belly,
come from the chest.
Really get it...
Really get your face set.
Okay.
That was really good.
Do me a favor this time.
I want you to stay on mic.
And I want you to...
Keep your hand like this on your face.
Good. Sharper.
Coaching people into doing combat rapidly like that really, really helps set the tone
for the urgency of the scene.
You're faking them into being in a dangerous environment.
Faster.
Oh my god, I have to...
They're in a panic state when you get them to do things really fast.
So that helps great.
And thank you guys both so much.
I also pretty much always put audience participation in my talks that I hadn't planned to this
year.
So I'm just so happy that happened.
Yes?
First of all, awesome talk and awesome audience participation.
Great job, y'all.
Thank you for being here.
Thank you.
I got to play the demo down at Day of the Devs, which was really cool.
I was really curious about how you got the zero G scenes to work.
The what now?
The zero gravity scenes where they're like in the Tacoma Dome.
Oh, as far as the voice stuff was concerned?
Yeah, and like the...
We played a little bit of it before.
I don't know if you saw, but when...
Oh, okay, so we played a little bit about that before.
So what we did was we had them just trash talking each other.
You know, here, I'll just go back to the slide,
because it's fun.
Boop, boop, doo.
And then I think that,
why don't I answer your question
while I'm getting the scene queued up?
Just a quick question.
How much rewriting was there during the sessions?
I know with this type of game,
it can be pretty heavily structured,
but was there a time when the ensemble was like,
what if?
Or no rewriting?
Wait, one more time, what was that?
Was there any rewriting during the ensemble work?
No.
Yeah. Writing during rewrites or rewrites. Yeah, there were minor tweaks, but I mean, it wasn't like
It wasn't like how Amy...
You're talking about the way that Amy Henning does her stuff?
Um...
Steve is the writer on this.
They're a little bit different.
He and Carl are working very creatively together outside of the studio.
And they work great together inside the studio too.
But they're just very, very rigorous in making sure that everything is like scratch-recorded
and play-tested a million times before they bring it to the studio.
I want to point out, this game, we had a very limited budget for the audio recordings.
So everything they could do to prepare properly, they did.
And we had been working together for a very long time on other projects, so it was just
a very natural, like, hey, this is what we're doing, can we do this?
And I was like, yes, we'll make that work.
So you know what?
See me after class and I'll play you that video.
Unless everybody really wants to see Jupiter Gravity dunk.
All right, fine.
Do I have time to fire up Jupiter Gravity dunk?
All right, cool.
Yeah.
All right.
Do you want to keep your ink in?
No.
Get rid of that stuff.
All right.
And then after.
So after this, I'll be in the hallway,
and you guys can all find me there.
I'm around all week.
This conference is about meeting people.
It's about building connections.
It's about having friendships.
Please, please, please don't be frightened to talk to a person.
Just remember that they're a person and be kind.
I encourage you, if you want to talk to me, please just do so.
I was really scared and nervous at my first conference.
and George Sanger made everything okay for me, just like he did with DB if you were in that talk before.
So I hope that at some point I can, I or somebody that I know or one of you can
pass that along to somebody else. Here is the motion video with Jupiter Gravity, donk.
Oh my god, wait, is today obsolescence day? Yeah, but didn't Odin give you a job to do? No.
Huh, a computer playing favorites.
Oh, wonders never cease.
I don't think I can fast forward.
Are you okay? Can you feel your feet and hands?
Yeah.
Oh, my hip just hurts.
Bert?
Bert!
Here it is.
You enjoy it while you can, Williams!
You won't have microgravity on your side forever!
Oh! I will dunk on you in any gravity!
Jupiter gravity dunk!
Ha ha ha!
Might as well see it.
But then I stopped thinking we should really make the most of it.
Ha ha ha!
She called me!
It's like, um, it's our dirty dancing move.
Sorry, that was me tapping my rings on my giant jug of water
that I usually carry around.
It's a weird thing.
So that's our talk.
My talk, okay.
Thank you for coming, and I hope to see you outside.