Good morning, everyone. Good afternoon. If you're on the East Coast, good evening.
If you are our developer guests, my name is Brian Francis.
I am a contributing editor at gamastructure.com.
I am a community manager for Game Developers Conference.
I am the invisible voice inside your head, but today everyone you hear will be the invisible
voice inside your head.
We are here playing GreedFall.
This comes from Spiders, which is a Parisian game development studio that I believe was
recently picked up by Big Ben.
I'll correct myself in a minute if it's not that recent.
But today, we are checking out GreedFall, which is a party-based RPG from Spiders.
Just repeating myself right there.
And I'm joined by some wonderful guests who are unfortunately all invisible.
One of those guests is frequent co-host, although I haven't gotten to hang out with her in a bit on this stream,
Alyssa McAloon. Alyssa, how are you doing?
Hi, I'm doing great. Coffee's kicking in, so we are doing wonderful over here.
Right on, and then over in the lower left hand corner of the screen, which would be normally where I've just put this nice image of our hero can green ball.
I have... so you won't be seeing them, but you will be hearing them, are our two guests, Claire and Sebastian.
Claire, how are you doing?
Hello! I'm fine.
So, it's a good evening in fact for us, because it's 5 o'clock in Paris.
And we will go in the stream with you, so...
Nice. I really quick Sebastian, could you are you there? Are you still with us? Yeah, I'm here. I'm here. Hello, everybody.
There are two guests are let me get their full names up for my own benefit. We have it is clear
leisure leisure and Sebastian de Rosa. I hope I said those names. Right. That's Yeah, that's fine.
I technically can speak French. Claire, would you please introduce yourself for our guests?
Yes, so, hello guys, I am Claire Léger, I am the game producer on Grid 4.
I was joining the company two years ago, during the production of Creed IV.
And that's wonderful to see people play our game for one week now.
And I hope we can share with you some thoughts about the game and answer your questions.
And Sebastian, would you mind introducing yourself as well?
Yeah, I'm Sebastian. I'm the game developer manager at Spiders.
We managed all the game design team and the level and quest design team during the project
and we're pretty happy to participate in streaming to answer your questions.
Right on, for the folks at home, this is a stream where we talk about how games get made,
we talk about the art and business of making games like Greedfall.
I suppose the best place to start off is, would you both mind explaining how the development of GreedFall started and what were your roles in, and what was sort of each of your jobs when Spiders got together and said we're going to make an RPG about exploring a colonial new world in a fantasy setting?
So it started like more than three years ago now and we wanted to...
We wanted to continue a game based on the foundation from a previous game, Technomancer, which was also an RPG.
Regarding all the feedback that we collected from the players, from reviews, etc., we wanted to improve the formula.
So we focused on the exploration and we learned to craft a bigger environment to improve that.
Also we wanted to enhance the combat system, but we will talk about this later I think
when we will have combat, and to give more predictable and tactical feeling on the fighting
systems and we wanted to push the different ways to solve quests that was appreciated
on our previous project, but now we wanted to push it further so we started with that
We had an ambition regarding all the game design and feeling of the game.
And after, we worked on the universe with the art director, cinematic artist and with John
to create a new universe that helps to support all the gameplay pillars.
So, discovering a new land was a good setting to encourage the exploration for the player.
So it started like that, and we went.
a better game.
That is to say, we have really focused on the last six months
on really all the small settings for level design.
And we have made a lot of playtests with our publisher,
with Focus Home Interactive,
in order to correct some mistakes that we had in the game,
especially for combat, the fighting system,
also for the tactical pause.
which was a big challenge for us to create this tactical pose
because it was really new compared to our previous game.
Then, we have also changed several times some things in the game
concerning the way we travel in the game.
For example, we have added some...
some points to teleport from one place to another, more points to travel for example.
It was something present at the beginning of the development but we have really made some
iteration on development with the player community and with playtests to enhance the game experience
and also because we are quite a small studio, we are 40 people so it's not big but
It's a challenge to do such a big game with such a small team.
Also, we have corrected a lot of bugs, more than 3,000 I guess.
Also with our publisher, of course.
Basically boil down to do we extend development, do we crunch or do we cut features?
How does that conversation kind of play out?
How do you decide the route that you want to take and how do you kind of work through
that complicated issue?
In fact the main idea at Spider is more how can we do a better game?
We have talked a lot with our publisher to make difficult decisions sometimes to see
what we continue to improve and what we don't, how much time we add to the development, and
is it really necessary to add this development time.
But we had the chance to be able to make a better game without...
Not too much constraints concerning a launch date, in fact.
We have gone through a stronger iterative process and made a lot of iteration for the
fighting system, for example, or for tactical pose and etc. So we focused on iteration on the main
content and improving it as much as possible during the development.
Just a reminder for folks at home, we are taking your questions in chat.
If you have something you'd particularly like to ask Claire and Sebastian, we would love to take your questions.
Yes, just concerning the streaming, we just have met Saira.
Saira is your native companion who is with you during the game.
And yes, she will represent you during the game.
The native faction, in fact. So the native people.
It's similar in that it's a stat-driven RPG, but it's also different in that I think a lot more of these stats influence the way the choices in the game branch out for your character.
Would you be able to explain the foundation that Spiders worked on for building this RPG and why it sort of did it that way?
We wanted to give a feeling with stat matters, and we wanted to give more control on random stats, for example.
Our previous game was having a critical hit system based on random chances to trigger
the critical effect and here we work on a fury bar that gives the player the control
to trigger his fury attack when he wants it.
It's one of...
The pillars that we put on and also the character development is not class-based.
We've got three main presets in the skill tree and we wanted to give the player the free opportunity to specialize himself and to re-specialize and test different builds inside one single run.
Also we wanted to have more range of weapons. We've got many different types of weapons.
big weapon funnels, and we wanted the player to have a good immersion regarding objects
that he can find on enemies, and allows him to use any weapons that human enemies use
in the game, for example. We wanted also to give a more tactical feeling with the tactical
pose, which allows you to...
Displaying all the details on the stats on your attack, etc
and in the menus, for example, like
In the equipment menu, you can have access to advanced statistics. We wanted to have an accessible game for
people who like
narrative branching stories, but we wanted also have core mechanical RPGs for
people who like more
Dragon Age
games or even people who like old school RPGs such as Bargescale for example.
With the tactical pause you can play almost as a turn based game for example for a few
moments and take the time to analyze the situation and all the stats helps the player to find
solution regarding the weaknesses of the enemies with the tactical pause you can analyze.
What are the strengths and weaknesses of your targets and adapt your strategy and your tactics
regarding that. So we work a lot on that beside our produce games.
Yeah, that's actually really interesting.
What do you think is the difference between...
When game developers go into a game, they often use specific structural restraints, like classes,
like only allowing certain weapons and builds on a run in order to manage the scope of the work
and to manage what combat encounters will feel like and such.
How did you accommodate for building a system where you wanted players to have more openness
in the character tree than on your previous games?
First, we started with...
The first iteration of the skill tree was very huge.
It was more divided, but we worked a lot on the improvement,
like every skill point should empower your character.
So we decided to focus on a smaller skill tree,
but with different type of skill that costs...
1 to 3 points. We got active skill that costs 2 points, passive skill that costs 1 point, and ultimate skills that cost 3 points.
And that represents the ultimate skill tree of the 3 main archetypes.
So at the beginning, we didn't notify the player that we have 3 types of main styles that he can mix up.
But we decided to help players to understand that there are...
We have three main orientations, but we want to feel the player that he keeps in mind, that he can specialize in different ways at the same time.
So we chose to make a skill tree that is more circular, where you start at the center, and regarding how you want to develop it,
you can...
put your points in different directions.
Also, we wanted to have an adventure skill tree, something like that, which, skills that
impact the story and your adventure, and not only the combat.
So we worked on talent.
It's a system that we started to have on Technomancer, and we pushed it further in that by adding
some talent points that allows you to...
progress in the levels, for example, to do a balance part on a full tree or to jump across
small holes.
And we add also charisma, intuition that you can use on dialogue or to find secret passages
on the environment.
Right on. We are going to bounce around the world of questions.
Alyssa, is there anything you'd like to get in before I move on?
I was kind of going to ask, following up on that,
when you give players all those different ways to pick up different skill points
and different options to resolve an encounter,
where they can talk their way through something,
they can have a secret dialogue thing,
how do you kind of manage your quest design
and you're designing conversations that...
give players plenty of options without making them feel funneled into one specific route
for an expansive game like this?
It was an iterative process, a lot with playtest and testing your own quests, also regarding
the team testing each other's quests.
It was an hard job for the quest designer.
to make the different paths regarding some quests.
The most important was to make the player aware that he can do a different path if he has the right skills.
Because if all elements are hidden to the player,
the game could have some... give a false vision.
of a linear game.
For example, on the product that you have played before,
or on every quest we put an accent on,
showing on the level design
which doors are locked,
to make the clues for players
like it should have a key,
or if I have lockpicking, I can lockpick here.
It's a lot of work.
and a balance between level design and quest design.
And in the dialogue, you get feedback that you don't have the intuition talent point,
for example, it will appear in red.
So, okay, this option is blocked because I don't have the right talent.
So maybe I will invest in that talent to find another opportunity to resolve the quest,
for example.
Regarding the narrative branching, we work a lot with the writers, Jan and Jan Rousseau
also work iteratively with the quest designers to change some elements in quests and we do
a lot of iteration during the writing after the first rough quest design.
to make it balance on all the games.
Yes, and we have also...
You know, we are using our own engine,
so the Seek engine.
And for this game, we have also developed
a new nodal system for quests.
So it was really something better
to create multi-branches stories
with a visual system.
All the systems in Quest Design and the dialogue system are using nodal tools.
It allows us to do many different types of branching and to visually work with the branching
on the screens to help us to build the different situations.
Yeah, and all the complexity in all the situations and relationships between one quest and another.
Because there is a main quest, but also there is side quests, companion quests, and quests of factions.
And everything is quite interconnected.
So of course it was a...
A big, really big work for all the team here to connect everything all together and to create a global story, which is, we hope, interesting for the players.
I'm going to jump to our chat real quick before I've got some follow-up questions about that.
Statustat, a frequent friend of the show, is hanging out in the Twitch chat.
I'm going to give a brief shout-out to Arcelon20 as well. Thank you both for dropping by the stream today.
Statustat has a lot of great questions. We will probably...
We worked a little bit on paper work, but we quickly always
try to have a first iteration on our engine to see what it feels or where things can lead.
It depends on the different parts.
For example, we got like three iterations around like that of the fighting system, three
big iterations through all the developments regarding quests.
Some quests were...
having like one or two iterations, but some quests can have up to eight iterations depending
on their position in the game because the middle quest in the game can be really affected
by the previous quest, etc.
So we had to make a bigger iteration on the middle quest of the game and on the ending
also.
In fact, sometimes you think that the idea on paper is great, and when you integrate it,
it's not so well for the player.
And what is important is not to have a good idea on paper,
it's to have a good idea for the game experience.
So sometimes we have decided to cut the content.
It arrives a few times, but it arrives sometimes.
Or simplify the content.
Most of the time it was simplifying the content and doing iteration in order to make what
we had in mind really interesting in the game experience.
I see that somebody is asking if it takes more time to do some iteration.
From my point of view, it takes some time but it's really better to do it like that
instead of...
creating all the game as it was in the head of only one person,
and then at the end, understanding that everything is not so great for the player.
So, I think, really, iteration is a good way.
working on small details every time.
For example, Sebastian was talking about the iteration for the fighting system,
but also we have done some iteration on the environment,
because some of them were too big,
so we have decided to reduce them.
We have also decided to add some small details
in places where it was not planned at the beginning.
Always for the same reason,
because...
We need to make the game experience interesting for players.
On my point of view, the only way to do it is to redo one time, two times, three times up to the right results.
Different things during iteration can be affected.
For example, sometimes iteration on combat system was mostly UI iteration.
more than animation iteration or stuff like that.
So, now, during the development,
the iteration doesn't focus on the same working type of job.
So, depending on that,
we have more iteration that we can count than others.
For example, sometimes quest design was affected on how the player was using the local map.
So we had to work a lot on our local map UI to make the different paths readable, to make
the player understand where he had to go following the quest.
I'm going to toss the question ball your way in just a moment, because I'm trying to balance
RPG things and talking to people at the same time, and it's always hard.
But there's one really cool feature I wanted to ask about.
Sebastian and Claire, we've seen so far, I've now traveled through two different areas on
the way to my quest destination.
And in between, the second that the...
But the next level began loading, I was popped into a campsite where I could talk to my companions and do inventory management.
There's a merchant here who looks like he wants to help me out.
This is really cool. I've never seen a game sort of skip past, instead of using a loading screen,
give you kind of an option to just sort of hang about your base and do stuff while the level loaded.
What did it take to implement that?
Or maybe I've seen examples like it, but I certainly haven't seen it in an RPG like this.
So, do we have a specific question on that?
Yeah, where did you come up with the idea and how were you able to make it so that you could access CAM?
In the previous game, Technomancer, we were having some dialogue cutscenes when you travel from location to others.
Using that system, while we were loading, we were having some cutscenes dialogue with choices, etc.
It was like we wanted a game where you explore different locations and go and come back from
different locations to others to report stuff to continue your journey.
It was like we had some kind of constraint with loading so we have the idea that let's
make this constraint a strength because we are able to load a little area.
during the loading.
So we have that idea that many RPG players have to make some rest scenes to manage their
inventory, to upgrade their character, talk to our companions, etc.
And we thought that it was a good idea to take that.
to the loading screen to help the players to manage, upgrade their characters
and to have all the static RPG adventure gameplay inside that loading screen.
The idea came up like that, and we were having a small break
that helped us push further to allow the players to move around.
And this is how the game comes into the game.
Basically, you have a merchant, you have your storing crate,
and you have your companion.
You can trigger side quests involving your relationship with them.
Also, we can see we have a home in every town, that is similar to that.
And also, we wanted to...
Make a relation with all the fire cams that you can find in the game to set up shortcuts
on all the different areas.
So this is how all cams come from the fire cam and the loading system.
Right on.
I'm Claire.
Before we move on from this topic, was there anything about implementing a system like
that that was different than how other games you've worked on?
Not really, in fact, loading is always a moment where we need to keep the player involved in
the game and having this area is a really big, is an interesting idea because you have
something to do here.
But concerning the development, it is also a challenge because it's loading, so we don't
need to have time to load this area in more of loading the...
So it has to be really light and interesting for players.
The main idea was to put there some action which takes time and will be useful for the player,
like walking on your stuff or talking to a merchant.
It was easy to do and not too hard to produce, in fact, and light to load.
build it from the ground up for...
It's the same engine that I've built since more than 10 years now.
Oh wow.
It's just, yeah, the engine was built the same as the company's.
We're still on the same engine.
Is there, do you think, because obviously managing an in-house engine requires a level of work that you don't get,
or that you see with, especially with a smaller team.
So would you say that there is...
The benefit to working with your own engine kind of makes all the extra work and the extra
team members required worth it there?
On my point of view, it has advantages.
For example, we can develop the tools we need especially for a feature.
For example, the novel system for quests.
It's exactly what we engine bind.
So the localization system that we have to create the game in multiple languages
is sized to what we need exactly for this project.
So having our own engine is really useful
because we can develop what we want when we want it.
But...
But of course, that's to say we don't have...
updates like for example on Unreal, of course you have updates from the developers
and there are many many more people working on the engines compared to us
and that's what is sometimes a little bit difficult, that's to say maintaining
the level of qualities that we need for our in-house engine.
with a small team is a challenge of every day.
Yeah, but we manage our own updates so we have better control when the Chinese are updating.
We know that what will be updated and it's always oriented on the project to update the
project.
So it's, I think, more...
easier to know which update will affect your project, rather than a middleware when updates
are a general update for every people who use this engine.
So maybe some of it can be on the wrong way regarding how you want to make your game on
the middleware, for example.
We're about halfway through our stream.
Folks, we love taking questions from Statustat, and we're going to grab a follow-up question from here in a second, but we also want to hear your questions.
Join Statustat in the ranks of the folks who ask questions on the GDC Twitch channel.
As I make my way here through this adventure, as we just watched a pretty disturbing scene just a second ago,
we are going to quickly follow up on Statistat's question.
So he kind of asks, when you're having trouble with an in-house engine,
you can't Google or go onto forums, as you would with the Unreal or Unity engines,
when you're running into a particular bug or challenge.
But I guess the flip side of that coin is you don't need Google.
Google is your engine developer down in, you know...
I prefer to speak with the engine developer directly than Google it.
We have wonderful engine developers. They have always answers for us.
Yes, we get people who have answers exactly in the studio, so Google might have the right answer.
Statue said we do appreciate and love your questions. I was just trying to celebrate your choices while
Begging for questions from our other listeners begging and all I always sound so desperate
Claire and Sebastian, let's dive a little bit into the content of GreedFall.
I think we've had a nice chat about design and tools development.
There's first one question that I feel like we need to, we'd like to talk about.
GreedFall sort of has an interesting setting, I think for both of our countries, just because
both of our countries have such interesting overlaps with this fantasy setting in each
of our respective histories.
As we just saw in Greedfall, you are a visitor from a far-off industrialized nation coming to this island that has a native population, it has magic and monsters.
So, we're going to preface this question by saying, obviously, this is not a historical game, there's not a real historical context hanging over this, but there are still huge metaphors hanging over every moment of the game.
When tackling the tone of...
In the United States, we are still reckoning with this history in many different ways.
Whether...
Like, people say, you know, our age of colonialism is hundreds of years past and it doesn't matter.
Well, in reality, we're still dealing with the impact it had,
even in legal cases that are still in our court system today.
How did you... I know this is maybe a question for other members of your team,
but I'm curious what your thoughts were about approaching a subject like this,
about sort of the invasion and occupation of other lands,
especially lands where people were already residing there.
And I'm curious if you all had any thoughts about portraying that content and what your...
How would you navigate doing it in a way you thought would interest players and make them think?
And how would it reflect to their understanding of these events?
One of the main acts of reflection when we constructed the universe
was also to make an opposition between civilization and nature,
which is more an actual...
an actual subject today with our civilization and the planet and the nature.
So we started first by thinking about that type of setting before a more historical inspired
setting.
After, regarding the faction, we didn't want a black or white situation.
We wanted some great inspiration, like every faction had their motivation, but maybe their
lack of information, and this is why they're probably acting the wrong way.
And we wanted to put the player in a situation like a diplomatic person that tried to make
people evil in a way or another.
But people are not, all the factions are not the factions that want to do bad things necessarily.
They are doing things because they want to, for example, say, find a cue for the Malico
on the continent, stuff like that.
It was more the thing that we wanted to talk about than colonization stuff.
This was more the subject we wanted to put at the end of the players.
In fact, there is also an interesting thing.
The game is live for one week now.
And in fact, Spanish people say,
oh, satisfied by our Spanish history.
Portuguese people are saying the same,
French people too,
and American people say that...
It's related to our American history.
So in fact, it's interesting to see that people
identify their own culture in this story, which is not true.
It's a fiction created from scratch
with people from a continent which does not exist,
with an island which does not exist.
And it's really interesting to see how people.
interact with that.
We wanted to bring humanity during all the different factions and all the interactions.
And I think that this is why many people from different countries and with different historical pasts
can go through the universe, I think.
I'll ask one follow-up question, and Alyssa, unless you have anything, I may move on.
Have you heard from any folks from... I mean, it's great to hear that people from different cultures have weighed in and said,
oh man, this feels like our history, this feels like our history.
Have you heard from any folks who are from different native populations who've had thoughts about this game?
We don't have specific feedback on that.
I think that...
We inspired a lot of Gaelic and Celtic populations for the native people.
So I think now, nowadays, all of this population has evolved to this.
So it's kind of the same type of feedback.
I guess we don't have an oriented feedback like...
Like we had people who identified the native as the good people, I think, because they are invaded.
And so it's a situation that nobody wants invaders.
So I think that every player, many players, take the native as allies.
in the game. So we cannot see if people are more
voluntarily there or not. That's the thing that
just, they want to protect nature and want to protect
people that are grounding to, bound to their ground.
Uh, Alyssa, I'm gonna throw the question ball your way. Oh no.
Oh no. Oh no? I am a through... I have some...
Questions about combat, but we haven't seen combat yet.
So my question is a little...
Oh, well, I missed it. Sorry.
Wow, you don't appreciate my bears?
I don't appreciate your gameplay.
There is one.
Continue there and you will have one soon.
Find some bears, please.
I wanted to ask about...
You mentioned the tactical pause quite a bit earlier when you were talking about
developing as an iterative process.
I guess I haven't played this yet, and I haven't seen much of TechRomancer, unfortunately, but
you made it sound like the tactical pause is a feature that's quite different from
what you've had in the past, right?
Yeah, on the previous game, it was like an active pause with a circular radial system.
So we moved on a real pause because tactical pause...
Active pose was putting the player in danger, like he was almost taking a hit and he wasn't
able to choose a life potion for example.
So I wanted to move to a pose, a real pose that poses the game and helps players to pick
up the right thing regarding the situation.
After we moved from a Radian menu to a bar menu, because it allows us to avoid limitations
regarding the Radian menu.
A Radian menu will have 6 slots, 10 slots, but when it's done, it's done to keep the
symmetry regarding the design, etc.
Here we were free to add...
additional type of potions and we had for example the revive potions that allows you
to revive your companion and we added like at the end of the development but we were
free adding that because we didn't have the radial limitations.
So it was quite interesting to add 3D content on the game to balance it.
and to add more choices to the player.
Yeah, it seems like an interesting reflection of some of those like RPG and skill tree systems
you mentioned earlier on that give players a lot of options to approach things how they want
and as their own skills dictate.
I'm going to jump in with another question.
Claire, we're going to loop back to the narrative content and the game content.
There's one thing that I think is a painful contradiction in game development,
which is handcrafted, interesting content is the thing that players,
especially ones like myself, love and adore.
It also takes lots of time to create and create well.
One little detail that I don't know how late in development it was put in, I really appreciated the camera work during these cutscenes
because I loved the way it sort of creeps around these characters for a minute, but I also know that's the kind of thing that
someone has to place that camera, even if it's a procedural camera, it has to be made procedural.
Um, what was...
We talked about how content can vary for the player depending on the choices they made and the skills they picked up.
What was your strategy for keeping all that content organized and efficiently made during production?
ready in a rough at the two-thirds of the production.
That is to say, everything was ready one year ago.
And then we branched all together at the same time.
Concerning the dialogues, we have created a new system for this game
that allows you for the dialogues to have an automatic camera.
And that creates these dynamic dialogues from one people to another,
with different points of view during the dialogues.
It was something new.
We have also decided at the beginning of the game that there is some key point in the story,
which needs some cutscenes.
There is a little bit less cutscenes than what we had in mind at the beginning of the development,
but there is still more than one hour and ten minutes.
30 minutes, I guess. It's more than, yeah, one hour and a half.
So that's quite huge for our small size.
Sorry, what was the question at the beginning?
Oh, how did you manage, how did you just manage all of the game's content?
What was your top, sort of your broad procedure?
It was, what was difficult is there is so much text to record.
And we had all the voices at the end of the development.
Because of course, it takes so much time to record all these dialogues with all the actors.
And that changed the feeling of the game a lot, to have the voiceover or not.
And we were focused on several details in the same time in the last third of production.
That is to say, we need to improve the fighting system.
We need to improve the 10 quests.
We are a little bit boring to make them more interesting.
But we can't change part of the text because that is already recorded, for example.
So that kind of things.
are on the top of our head during the last third of the production when we patch all things together.
There is also a part concerning GUI because GUI is important in RPG games and there is so much
details, so much information that we need to connect all together. We have changed the GUI
a lot of times, maybe from scratch two times and then maybe I don't know.
15 different iterations, something like that, to have all the right information at the same
time on screen and not too much everywhere.
That's the reason an RPG has too much stats everywhere and information that you don't
need when you fight against an enemy, but you need some other information.
For example here, you just add information concerning the factions on the top right for
this specific place.
But you don't need to have this kind of information in all places of the game.
And it was a big deal to connect everything at the end,
and to enhance the global experience,
because there is more than 35 hours in the main quest,
but you jump to more than 60 hours if you do all the side quests.
And we were not sure before branching all together that it would be fun.
So it was a...
That seems terrifying.
Yeah, it is a little. In fact, it's a little bit.
We know what we do and we hope that we will be lucky.
That's true, that's true.
It's always a lot of things that we control in how we create the game.
And there is a risk that when we branch all together...
That will not be as great as what we had in mind.
And then the only way you have to do it is to redo it several times to make it better.
Oh no, you were gonna, you were gonna say, oh no, I guess Sebastian, were you gonna jump in?
Yeah.
Uh, no, no, it's good.
I know the answer is going to be something along the lines of it's like you can kind of only go with your gut when you're in a situation like that, but is there anything that helps you determine when it's good enough?
Like you said, it's terrifying, you're working and you're working and you don't know if it's all going to work together.
I need to say maybe that we still prototyping a lot at the beginning, during the production we
prototype a lot small things before putting it all together in the game so that reduce the risks
a little bit. Very good. When you're working on prototyping, sorry, and like going through that
iterative process that has been like really critical to the game's development from what
you guys have been saying, how do you...
I don't know when something's good enough, because I'm the kind of person where if I go through and keep polishing and polishing and trying to make something better, I will be at it until the day I die, because it's never good enough.
Is there feedback within the team? Is there some kind of communication system you guys have worked out to help you know when to set a feature down and let it be?
It's quite hard.
We always have, as a game development crew, we always have the thing that the...
The things are never really finished.
Actually we are working on the next patch, so we still have improvements and we can always
make improvements, but I think that you get to put your pen on the desk many times during
the production and the game has to be released on a certain date, so there's a time where
It had to be ready.
And the fact is that we...
I think the right way to know it is not to look at the feature that we are working on,
but how the feature is represented in the game,
and what is the global state of the game.
We have to keep balance every feature to have a constant finish and polish in all the game.
Because different type of polish, for example, if we have things really polished and something
unpolished aside, it will trigger the player.
Pull him out of the game.
But if you keep the same balancing between all different things,
you will have a constant gameplay experience.
So I think that the best way is to stop working on it,
take a step back, play the game,
and see if we have to push further on that feature,
or maybe go back to another feature.
Maybe sometime develop a new feature that lacks in the global experience.
In fact, playtests were also a bit useful for that because on first playtest for example
there is some feature where on red it says ok we can't continue with this feature like
that.
And we have improved it, improved it, improved it, and there is one moment where it becomes green on playtest.
That's to say, okay, players say, that's enough.
We are fine with this feature.
And then you know that what you have provided is enough fun for the player,
but you can still improve it a little bit for what you want to propose to the player.
But, yeah.
When you read a feature, then you know that's in us.
And you can make it better, but it's not an obligation anymore, in fact.
OK.
Sometimes also, if in the playtest the feature is not mentioned,
that could be also a type that, OK, the feature is good enough because it is not mentioned,
so it doesn't lax or it doesn't...
It is not the best feature ever, but if it's not on the...
core experience, that's good enough.
I am currently doing some wheeling and doing...
I am a side quest fiend in these kind of games.
I will not stop until... I will not go on the main quest until I have completed the tiniest side quest.
Like, the volcano could be burning in the background, the end of the world could be beginning,
and I will be there clearing out my side quest log because that's the kind of player I am.
I suppose my final question for the moment will be...
Claire, this is kind of a production question.
I know France has super great labor laws.
We've talked to a lot of French developers and we talk about crunch.
It's a very different conversation in the United States.
Because the underlying legal structure is different though.
Games like this, especially with only a 40 person team, I can't get over that number.
40 people is so small to me.
Games like this still take a lot of energy making, a lot of time, and a lot of passion.
And what do you think was effective about managing people's time so that the team didn't have to pull incredibly long hours to the point that it was affecting their health?
Unless you did have to pull incredibly long hours and maybe that's something I have wrong.
As I said at the beginning, here we prefer to extend the time development than crunching, for example.
So there is few to no people here who are doing crunch.
It is part of our company politics here to say that we need people who are enthusiastic and safe at work
and do not...
working 20 hours a day.
Because of course game development when it's two or three years, it's long and it's better if people are great in the game.
And they want to continue to working on it instead of everybody is totally tired and don't want to work on it anymore.
What is difficult is sometimes when we extend the development time, people had in mind that
that would be finished, for example, I don't know, in last March, and it's extended to June.
And when we make the decision to extend the development time, sometimes that could be a little bit difficult for people,
but because everybody here is...
know that that's better for the game and that they will not do some extra hours.
Most of the time it's great. Everybody is okay to continue working in the game.
I hope it answers your questions because of course it's really something really important for us
that people at Spiders feel great about the production.
I low-key apologize in that I really honestly believe that discussions about this topic
take more time than the five minutes at the end of a stream, so I appreciate the frankness
of your answer, even in that context.
With that, Alyssa, do you have any questions you want to get in before we wrap it up?
I've ran through my list.
Sweet, that's a good list.
With that, I will begin closing things down.
Thank you all for watching the GDC Twitch channel.
This is a place where, just like we do at GDC, we talk about how games are made
and we talk to the people who make them.
Um, uh, today we've been playing Greedfall, but if you check back in the next couple weeks,
we are checking out some other really cool games.
One of them I'm very excited about, and I guess I can go ahead and announce it.
Um, next week we're gonna be talking to, uh, the developers who worked on the original Jedi Knight 2, Jedi Outcast.
Um, those are the folks at Raven Software, which is still around.
They are just making games, uh, under Activision.
Um, so we are going to be talking to them next week.
The week after that we are in looking, looks like we're going to be talking to the folks
from Finji about the making of Overland.
So we've got some really, just like in September when all the great games are coming out and
there's too many games and your Steam, your Epic, your PS4 backlogs are full, just so
too is our backlog laded with amazing devs to talk to.
I'm really excited about Jedi Knight 2 because that was a game I played a lot when I was
12, 13, 14 years old.
And getting to talk to the people who worked on that is going to be really good.
With that, we'd love it if for folks who are new, if you click the follow button, you'll get live and you'll get notification when we're going on those interviews.
Otherwise, this channel is pretty dedicated to just running some classic GDC talks.
And, you know, we'd like it if you followed us.
Sebastian and Claire, if they have more questions about the making of the game, where should they ask them?
On the contact address, I think.
Yeah, you can send emails to our contact address.
You can also post your questions on the Focus Interactive forum of Fritful,
and we'll try to answer as soon as we can.
Right on. With that, I will wish everyone a happy Wednesday.
Enjoy the middle of the week. I hope wherever you are, your work week is going well.
Thank you very much for this stream.
And have a good day, because for us it's 6pm, but for you it's early in the morning.
Have a nice event.
Get some drinks. Bye everyone!
Bye, thank you.