We are here today to talk about Always Be Composing,
the flexible music system of Plants vs. Zombies Heroes.
I am Becky Allen, audio director and composer
at PopCap Games, and I worked on Plants vs. Zombies Heroes
for the last two years.
You may say, what is Plants vs. Zombies Heroes?
A collectible card game, that's right.
Who here has heard of it, played it?
Yay, all right, thanks.
So, this is an interesting project, so I'm here to talk about the music design, the music
systems and the composition, and all of the different phases of iteration throughout the
process.
We'll start at the beginning.
At the very beginning, I decided on a guiding principle, support gameplay and the player's
experience.
I met with the game designer, Devon Lowe, and talked about...
the music for the game.
We'd already made a prototype of the game in Unity
and with Wwise and put in some initial hooks,
lots of hooks actually, utilizing old PVZ sounds.
But we knew that this was going to be a new game
in a new genre with CCG,
but still in the PVZ franchise, PVZ universe.
Also at that time, Hearthstone was very popular
and still is very popular, awesome game.
and awesome sounding game.
So we were looking at that and seeing how that sounded
and music and sound design and that,
and also looking back to other PVZ games,
and I was thinking, hmm,
how can I stretch out a little more here?
I wanna support the gameplay and the player's experience
maybe even more with more interactivity,
a little more responsiveness,
move that needle a little further for this project.
And meeting with the game designer, we talked initially about what was he
envisioning for the music.
And he said, well, I'd like there to be a progression, like a beginning,
a middle, and yeah, some kind of development there, so
that you feel the progression of the game.
And also there would be heroes in this game, so whatever that would mean.
So this is the early phase and thinking about different music styles and influences,
there was a lot of pressure early on from the team to make this sound very
PVZ1-ish, and even a little PVZ2, because they wanted the players to come over
from other PVZ games into PVZ.
So I did listen to a lot of PVZ themes,
especially PVZ1 themes by Laura Shigehara.
Of course, the wonderful PVZ2 themes of Peter McConnell are fantastic as well.
But I did sit down with Laura's music and analyze that.
And so I sat in my studio and just kind of analyzed that in a traditional, analytical way.
And I was like, okay, mostly minor, lots of bass lines.
incredible melodies, strong melodies.
So I sat in my studio and I started writing
and trying to write in that style
and finding what are the edges of that style.
Oh, if I do this too much, it doesn't feel PVC.
If I go over there too much, it doesn't feel too PVC
and finding where those edges are and still feeling PVC.
So I was doing that for a little while.
Meanwhile, during this sort of explorational style phase,
I was doing a lot of yoga in the morning at home.
And my daughter was watching Power Puffs in the background,
and I would hear the music of the Power Puffs,
and I'd hear these little fragments,
these little personal stingers and small phrases
that were kind of in and out and really fast,
but very identifiable, and I really liked that.
And I thought, hmm, maybe that also
could influence PVC Heroes.
So we had a gameplay prototype and in order to really flesh out some of these ideas,
I took a linear capture of that gameplay prototype and brought it into my DAW
and started exploring with some themes and thinking about what the role of the music would be.
I talked to Devin Lowe again, our creative director, and asked him,
What are the average number of hands, do you think, in this game?
Well, I think probably about eight hands would do.
And how long do you think an average session length would be?
He said about five minutes.
Okay.
And then he said, there's also going to be these sections
in the game where you play actively,
and then a fight combat section
where the game sort of plays for you
and the cards are battling against each other.
I'm like, okay.
Getting the ideas here.
And he also said there will be 20 heroes.
10 plant heroes and 10 zombie heroes.
So I started to explore and this is an early prototype of the music where I'm exploring
the hero themes. So this guy down here, Super Brains on the bottom, he's our zombie hero,
and up at the top is Green Shadow, our plant hero. And you'll hear three different things in here.
The zombie theme for Super Brains and then the plant theme.
for Green Shadow and the combat fight section, so three different things playing.
Back to super brains. ♪
Bright shadows coming in. ♪
So during this proof of concept phase, I was trying to explore going back and forth between
the heroes and also that combat music because really at that stage they didn't think that
the combat or fight music needed to be different.
And I thought we could do something.
It could be fun.
So along came a feature in the game called the phase indicator and it was in the right hand side of the screen and
it told the player what was happening and it was first it would say zombie turn then plant turn
zombie tricks
combat phase, post-game, and then back to the next hand.
So this was awesome, it communicated to the player
what was happening, and also it gave us hooks
for the music to hang our switches,
basically switching from one kind of music to the next.
And we decided to use that as the music structural driver
for the game.
So.
With that, what are some music considerations when you have some kind of structural driver
in the game like that?
Well, first of all, the melodies per hero are indeterminate lengths, can be interrupted
at any time based on the different gameplay.
So that's going to be tricky.
And I knew at that point that transitions would really, really be coming into play.
And I didn't know what to do with them or how they would work or anything, but I knew
that was going to be hard.
And then I thought about, well, if we're going to go from one hero to another hero in a hand,
what could make that hold together?
And I thought, well, let's have common key centers per hand.
So say you're in hand one, whether you're a plant or a zombie, you're in the key of
G minor.
Jump to hand four, both of them are in the hand of C minor, so common key centers per
hand.
Also, I decided at that time that I would set a common tempo of 125 BPM for the whole game.
And I just set it and kept it there, and it kept everything tight and feeling together,
and I'm glad I did that.
So, these are choices and things that I was thinking about what to change, what not to change.
Also in the hands, I thought about the drums and the progression of the drums.
So in the early hands, you have light hand percussion, kind of mysterious hands,
and then as you go...
to the later hands you get the drum kit.
So whether you're plant or zombie,
you have the same kind of percussion.
So that carries the glue between them as well.
Of course there needs to be differentiators
and I will talk about those.
So.
There's the plant faction and the zombie faction,
and they're much like teams, right?
So I'm on the plant team or I'm on the zombie team.
How should that sound?
And we're dealing with instrument sets
in terms of how should they sound,
not colors of uniforms, but instruments.
I decided that there would be a common set of instruments between the plants and the
zombies and that was mallets.
Mallets are used all over the place.
The walking baseline, pits, of course, is used all over the place as well throughout
all heroes.
There are a couple strings that are used also and a couple of other instruments that are
the shared common set.
But then you go into the perfection set.
And for the plants, I decided they should be woodwinds.
So woodwinds are the identifier for the plant faction.
And within that, let's say you are a hero
and you've selected your hero.
There also will be one or two unique instruments
per that hero.
So every time you hear that hero, you go, ah, that's my guy
or that's my gal.
Like Spadau, for example.
He's a funny, weird hero.
And he has bassoon.
And so that, of course, reflects his personalities.
I should say that those choices of instruments
came along as the personalities of the heroes
came into being.
So, you know, Spadaw being really weird,
Bassoon seemed unnatural.
So as the art came into place,
I would choose different instruments per hero.
So zombies, how should they sound?
We had the common instrument set, as I mentioned,
and then we had the per-faction instrument set.
And so for zombies, I chose trombones and lower brass,
because they're a little heavier,
and that seemed to fit very well
with their art and their style.
And then, of course, there's the unique
instrument set per hero.
So as those heroes came into play,
for example, like Rustbolt, who is really angular and weird,
he got the eight-bit keys,
and Gargantuar, who's,
but he has a little guy up there, he's got the tuba and the Harmon muted trumpets.
So these kinds of instrument choices reflect their own quirk.
So, you know, I'm going along and playing with these different instruments and
exploring, and along comes a marketing trailer. And most of the time,
marketing is over here, right, and development's over here, and they're
quite disparate.
And we're all kind of used to that.
And that was still the case right at this moment,
I should say.
The creative franchise director and head of marketing
came and said, hey, we've got this great marketing trailer
to announce the game.
And the franchise director's like,
hey, can you make it like The Incredibles?
I'm like, sure I can.
Okay.
So I go out and I buy the Incredibles
and I go out and buy the Incredibles soundtracks
and I think any composer in the room,
if somebody says, hey, can you do it like this?
You go out and you get that music
and you study it and you breathe it and you live it.
You try to become it so you can kind of understand the style
and I did that and then spent a couple of weeks
working with the franchise creative director
on the trailer and we came to a really nice piece,
a two and a half minute trailer with that style
and we were going to do a live recording, which is awesome.
So it's Monday and I had told Panther Modern that I would be handing him the music or the
sessions the next day to prepare for our session at Bustier on Friday.
But that Monday night, our head of marketing and franchise director played it for EA's
VP of marketing.
And he's like, oh, okay.
That's great, but what if it's a little more Batman-y?
You know, like 1960s, but kind of the 1980s remake.
So they brought me in on Monday around 7 o'clock,
and they said, well, what do you think of this?
And I listened to it, and man, I had to agree.
It was really awesome.
It was so good.
You know, I had to quickly let go of the two weeks of work that I had done and the idea
of how it was going to go.
And our head of marketing said, so what do you think?
Hmm, yes, good.
Can I have till tomorrow morning and I'll try to do that?
And he said, oh, sure.
And meanwhile, I'm like, oh my god, I've got Stan lined up.
We're going to record on Friday.
But I just worked that night and tried to write in that style
and came up with something pretty good
by the next morning.
And they came in and like, oh yeah, that's great.
So I wrote it all out.
We still recorded on Friday.
And then we brought in a drum kit and bass
and made this kind of 60s spy genre type thing.
It worked out really well, and I'm really grateful for this marketing trailer
because it was this watershed moment for part of the style of the music of the game.
And also a big trust was established with the team.
And from that point forward, I feel like smooth sailing for me.
So I was really grateful.
And another thing that I want to mention here is,
as I said, normally marketing's over here
and development's over here,
but the marketing trailer actually really impacted
the sound of the game,
and I took that style of the trailer
and put it into the combat fight sections.
So, I'll play that for you.
Oh, sorry.
And a PowerPoint problem.
Sorry.
I want to play it for you.
Uh, whoo! Thanks!
Damien's here, yeah!
Uh, haha,
anyway, I still enjoy this trailer,
I listen to it, it makes me happy.
Um, but yes,
I took part of that trailer and put it into the combat
fight sections, uh, right after this
trailer happened, and we lived with that in that
section of the game, internally
for quite some time.
So,
we go into what I call the
content phase of the game.
where both Luca Fusi, lead sound designer,
you're there, there you are.
Yay.
He and I were working pretty much in tandem at this point.
We'd have like a hero.
on the board and we'd both be working alongside each other
and kind of laughing about the weirdness of the characters
and he'd be making the weird voices
and it all just came together really
in a very fun and playful way.
Like I said, Spadao and his bassoon and his weird voice
and then Rustbolt and his 8-bit keyboards.
Yeah, it was just a great and happy content phase,
I should say.
So it took me about one week to compose
for these heroes and it was eight hands and I would write the set for that hero and then
I would bring it into Wwise to integrate.
Also during this time, I should say, calculating it out,
I realized that 20 sets would be two hours of music.
So reduced it to 10 sets and started
thinking about a little bit of sharing with some of the heroes.
And it did work out for size on mobile
and also for time in terms of production.
So now I'm going to go into WISE,
show you a little bit of the integration.
So, here's WISE.
I wanted to show you a bit of WISE because in here I'd like to show you how the hands were laid out.
A bit of the progression from hand one to hand eight.
Also I'd like to show you some of the transition work between the zombies and the plants and how that was done.
And so I'm going to show you through a little bit of that.
So here we are, interactive music hierarchy.
And we go into the hand counter.
You know, these are the hands, like the phase indicator would indicate next hand, next hand.
And we did set it up with the eight hands as Devon Lowe, our creative director, told
us it would be on average.
So here is hand one, and as you open up the container for hand one, you see there's a
bucket there for plants and then for zombies, and then surprise zombies are zombie tricks.
We called them eventually.
They were called surprise zombies for a while.
some transitions that I sometimes used,
combat fight section here,
and a post-combat that became important eventually as well.
And those are all things on the phase indicator
for the most part.
So let's just open up the plants
and the zombies.
All right, so here we have super brains.
The early hands are more mysterious.
You hear, of course, a lot of mallets, instruments as well.
And now when we go to Penelope, who is known as Green Shadow in the game.
Also mallets.
That's like glue, the mallets.
You hear the bass.
They both.
Some flute and her.
Again, these early hands are very contemplative.
Not a lot of action yet.
Okay.
So that would be some of the hand one.
I want to play you a little bit about of the zombie tricks.
I'm going to show you an example of this.
Let's say we had all three fingers.
So I'm going to increase D.
So this is awful.
I may be a little early.
This is worse.
So D is higher than E.
So that's all four fingers there.
So this just makes you think of all these different strategies.
Idea one of them is this mittens, minusing one.
So I have a mitten, minus two.
I have another mitten.
It's just a little bit longer than three fingers.
I have an left hand.
So this is the case.
This is what would interrupt, right here would interrupt the plant.
There's a tense moment.
What's happening?
And then that would be interrupted by combat.
et cetera.
So that is the combat.
I wanted to say a quick note here.
This score is a hybrid score.
It's a mix between MIDI and WAV.
And I'd always thought it would be a hybrid score,
and it did indeed develop into being a hybrid score.
And there are some challenges that come up
along the way about that.
But I'm pretty pleased with how they live side by side
and how they all sound together.
The last part of that sequence really is the post-combat.
This is just at the end of the combat, plays until the next hand.
And then you go into the next hand.
Alright, so that's a bit of how the sequence of cues goes.
And then we want to look at transitions.
Now, we have our transitions up here on this higher level
switch container.
We did experiment with having our transitions
in lower levels, and that got really complicated
and eventually found that there's actually
consistency between them, and we're
able to control it from a higher level.
Of course, when you have some rules established
on the higher level, then it trickles down
to everything below.
So here we are on this level, and we set our transitions
here.
In this tab, I go to, that's not the level,
it's actually this level, here we go.
All right.
And whenever you're playing as a zombie,
now you always play zombies first,
and they're always interrupted by plants.
So after through a lot of experimentation with,
this is the hardest one actually,
in the game, I realized that it had to be custom cue,
transition from zombies to plants.
I tried immediate, I tried next bar, I tried all sorts of things with this one in particular.
But it didn't feel right musically in the game to have it any other than the custom queue.
And I'll show you how those work.
So that was what zombies to plants were.
Let me show you in the queue now how that looks.
Over here in super brains.
Let's look at that for a second.
Okay.
So you see down here,
these white markers are custom cues.
That means if you play from here,
and you get a call for the plant,
if you interrupt, it'll change out
at that white marker or that white marker.
Now there are white markers,
custom cues on all of these.
So at any time,
if it's called here,
it'll go out at that white marker.
And here as well.
I'll show you some of those later in the hands
because they get a little more complicated.
In any case, custom cues from where the transition points
established from zombies to plants.
Now, plants, let's go back up here to our transitions.
Plants to
they get interrupted by the tricks, zombie tricks.
And that is immediate.
Because if you tried to do it later,
though it sounds better musically,
it didn't feel responsive enough in the game.
So again, you play the game,
you see where you need immediate,
where you can actually extend maybe to the bar,
or to the end of a phrase, or to a custom cue.
And this is something that you just have to play with
and find what feels best for gameplay.
Super important.
Let's see, any to combat was next beat.
Now this one you wouldn't think necessarily,
you might think to combat needs to be immediate,
but next beat felt just a touch better.
So actually consistently,
next beat works best for this transition.
So that's where we set transitions.
And they are slightly different per hand
if we go down through the hands,
but we set them right there on that hand one
for the transitions in hand one.
So, now I'm gonna go and play a little bit further in,
hand four, just to show how it sort of develops
and sounds a little more active.
Now you're into the game a bit. ♪♪♪
Got hand percussion still here. ♪♪♪
But it's a little more energetic.
The contemplative phase.
And a little bit of green shadow.
All right, so it feels you're now in the meat of the game.
And now I'm going to play a little bit of Hand 8.
So we can see where it goes, it gets more intense.
Boop, boop.
There we are, super brains.
And then we have drum kit here.
Sing along.
Ah.
Thank you, Damien.
All right.
And a little green shadow.
I bet you know this one, too. ♪♪♪
Also drum kit.
Gluing them together.
Does it work?
All right. So you hear a progression from one to eight,
you know, as per our creative director's request.
Beginning, middle, end.
progression and then you saw here the transitions and a bit of how the segments work.
So with that I'm going to go back to PowerPoint.
So this content phase continues.
Remember how I used the trailer music
in the combat sections for,
trailer music from the marketing trailer
in the combat sections?
And now we've been living with that in the game
for a little while and so has the team.
And how was that working?
Well, not super great actually.
Because it was like too stingery.
Ba-da-ba-da, ba-da-ba-da.
And it was a bit.
jarring and irritating. It was the right style, but it wasn't quite the right thing.
So I decided to go in for a second recording session, which fortunately was approved in
the budget, which is a blessing. And I wrote eight specific combat cues, which are slightly
more melodic, but still completely in that same style.
Also for this second recording session.
These things called comics or narratives were coming on board.
And each hero would get an introductory comic.
And it would be, hi, I'm the hero, and
then it would have these panels, comic panels, panel one, panel two, panel three.
And then they also had three more comics, adventure or story comics.
Also again, panel one, panel two, panel three.
So I talked to the art director and I said, well, let's see, if we had four,
Comics per hero, 4 times 20 is 80.
That's a lot of music, right?
That's really too much for this game.
And so I, so I thought we need to develop a system here.
If we can set some some consistency within the panels,
we can have a bucket of a mix and match type thing.
So it's four seconds per each panel.
one, two, or three, and now you can pull from panel one bucket for any time, which didn't
matter which comic, and it'll pull from these different buckets.
So it was good to work that out, and we recorded that in our second session, and this is how
it sounded.
So any time a comic comes in, it'll pull and sound different, but they all work really
well together.
So, along comes the MIDI phase.
I like this part of the story.
So, Guy Whitmore had decided, you know,
this is a great pop cap enterprise project
that we should record our own sample library
for our games, for mobile games.
He and I worked together to decide which instruments we should record based on the projects that
were in production at the time and also looking out to the future what would be good ones
to have in general.
So we came up with a list of 24 instruments.
I always knew this was in the plan.
It didn't happen, it happened midway through production for Heroes.
I'd already finished seven Heroes by this time writing for East-West libraries.
But we were undergoing this sample library exercise and knowing that we'd be moving over
to those samples eventually.
And you may ask why?
But mobile, you know, we're always thinking about size and ways to be smart.
and this is a really smart way to do it.
And also no licensing fees by having a sample library
that you pull from within the game.
So, we went to Studio X
and we recorded these 24 instruments.
Three different articulations,
three different dynamics per instrument.
And then Guy,
hired Panther Modern and his team of specialists,
which maybe there's some in the room today.
There are many people who helped us
in terms of editing all of these materials
and creating these mirrored sets,
a mirrored set for contact and for WISE.
So you write in your DAW with your contact set
and then you bring it over to WISE
and it's pretty darn close set.
So it worked beautifully and they did a great job.
So thank you, thank you so much.
So some of our instruments here, alto flute, saxophone,
this is just our list of instruments that I used mostly.
Then I brought them over to Logic and I'll talk about that.
Hired Panther Modern to help with the MIDI arrangements
because I was going to take.
the seven sets I already had and moved them over to the PopCap sample library.
So I asked him if he could help with that.
And also asked him about MIDI exporting,
because Pro Tools didn't seem very good at MIDI exporting.
So he said, yeah, Logic is way better.
So I decided, well, OK, then I will learn Logic.
And I think at PopCap, no one's too shy to learn a new DAW
in the middle of everything.
And I thank you all for being so brave.
Because I'm like, OK, I can do this too.
So I decided I'll learn logic.
And what was great about that is some of you probably all
know this, but there's such a great community around logic.
You go onto YouTube, you ask any question,
and there is a tutorial video.
And I basically got up and running very quickly,
one or two weeks, and I felt like I was fluid.
And if I had any questions, I'd just go to YouTube.
Hello.
all you gracious people who've shared information,
really helped me.
So I was able to get up and running quickly.
And I want to say, I am not a Pro Tools hater.
I still do like it for multiple movies,
I think it's a great tool,
but I do think it's good to choose the right tool
for the job.
And Logic was the best for MIDI,
and I still also use Pro Tools.
So, I had given
Green Shadow was the first one to Stan Lippard to do the MIDI arrangements and to the PopCap
samples.
He came into PopCap and we sat down and we listened to it.
And it did not sound the same.
I'd been writing to the East-West libraries, primarily,
that are beautiful, and different.
And our PopCap sample library is fantastic, too,
but it's totally different.
So the sounds were not the same.
And the music, even though they were the same cues,
it just felt wrong.
And I had a day of depression.
But I pulled right out.
And I learned at that moment that a French horn
from one sample library is not the same as a French horn,
necessarily, to the other.
or the mallets, or several instruments in this case, weren't matches.
And so I think it's very important, if you can, to write to the sample library that you'll
be using ultimately at the end.
Try to start there if you can.
It took a lot of time and effort to get to a place where I was comfortable with this
sample library.
A couple of weeks with green shadow and then I was fully comfortable with it.
But we had to learn techniques.
So we did.
We sat down for a couple of weeks and we learned that layering helped, layering different kinds
of instruments, switching out, reorchestration in some cases, velocity changes.
Actually, duration changes in the mallets were really key.
It took, as I said, about two weeks on that.
And then after we learned some of these tricks,
it went faster per each hero after that.
And this is some of the layering that was done.
Didn't lean as, I leaned a lot on the French horns
in East-West, and then for PopCap,
I leaned more on the trombones.
And then did more layering with vibes.
This is how it sounds for Superbrains MIDI.
Aaah...
All right, so I think it turned out really well and eventually after getting
them all into MIDI and into the game, I totally forgot what it sounded like
before. I love it and I actually think it fits way better with the aesthetic and I
love it. I just grew to totally love MIDI and I'll tell you more why later.
So, I wanna talk a little bit about size.
We are a mobile studio, and we have to be very mindful
of our size because of the devices that we are played on.
And about midway through, we went through an exercise
and established what our size would be.
And we sort of claimed 80 megs.
40 for music, 40 for sound effects and VO.
Luca made a beautiful pie chart.
We met with the TD, we showed it to the executive producer,
and they said, fine, okay.
Now, at that time, we were still kind of in this Hearthstone
era, that's sort of a big game.
But now, at this point, we're in late production.
I wanna switch to late production.
And along came Clash Royale, and that was a quick game.
It loaded quickly, and everybody was loving it,
and we had some pressure to come down to 30 megabytes.
Right, we got an email over the weekend,
and we're like, oh, you're too big,
you need to be 30 megabytes.
I think we all broke out in rashes at that moment.
The executive producer came by our meeting fortunately that day and he said, hey, just
see what you can do.
So we saw what we could do.
And we held to 60 megabytes.
And with our wise wizard, Damien Kastbauer right here.
He pulled all the levers and whys to make it work
and to go down to 60 and make it sound awesome.
He used over 21 different compression settings
for the different sound types,
really massaging it and crafting it.
We switched some things from stereo to mono,
but not everything.
We streamed all the wave music
and we streamed larger wave assets, like hero assets.
We also reduced the instrument ranges for the instrument sets.
So in some cases, if there's a higher range that's not needed,
I could just stretch out the note or just remove that.
So I just went in and kind of did some pruning.
And that worked out well.
Also reduced the variation on the stingers of the block sounds.
Bow, bow, end of game.
And we got down to 60, and it sounds great.
And that's where we stayed.
Now, music, the late phase.
We'd been playing the game now for quite some time.
The music has been in the game,
and it hasn't changed too much for several months.
How's it working?
How's it not working?
Luke had been playing it a lot and he was like,
well, he was saying that in hand eight,
because his games were longer than five minutes.
So some real world stuff, real world info is coming in now.
You know, these are, sometimes they're shorter
than five minutes, but sometimes, you know,
it's an eight minute game.
And how's that working?
It wasn't responding quite as much as we wanted it to,
as I wanted it to.
You remember, I wanted it to really be the
connected to the gameplay experience and responsive
and for it to give emotional feedback to the player.
So, how could we make it more responsive?
MIDI was going to become our friend.
Now, one thing I thought was,
ha, well, when you get further in the game
and you're up by a certain amount,
you wanna feel good, you wanna feel lifted.
You know, remember Barry Manilow.
How he did that?
He transposed.
Okay, and it worked.
So, not all of you remember Barry Manilow,
and I realize that.
Anyway, he did transposition.
I'm like, oh yeah, we should try that.
So, Damien and I sat down together and figured out,
Damien was like, oh.
we could, huh, could we do this with MIDI?
And so we created an RTPC
for players' relative health in Wwise.
And with MIDI, what we were able to do
was if you're up by five points,
all the MIDI music went up a whole step.
And if you're up by 10 points,
all the MIDI music went up two whole steps.
And it worked.
It was awesome.
That's why we love MIDI.
It really was flexible.
It was something that you can really work with.
And at that point, the waves were
starting to become an issue.
Because remember, this is a hybrid score.
And the super block waves, ba-pow,
would actually happen over the sections
where there's MIDI music.
And if you transpose your MIDI and you don't transpose those brass stingers, it does not
sound good.
So they were feeling kind of like clunky, the waves, like pulling us down.
And we utilized the same RTPC, but used playback speed for the waves.
And we're able to get that working, but it was really not as easy to do.
But it did get sounding great.
Then we utilized the same health parameter,
same point spread, and added an overlay track
to the plants when they're not doing well,
and the zombies when they're not doing well.
For the plants I used a bass clarinet pattern,
and the zombies I used a trombone pattern,
and so the same RTPC would call that for a negative
when you're down by 10.
A different health parameter that we used
when the player was not doing well
was we utilized parameters to drive switches.
And by that, I added a horizontal music layer,
an overlay track, and it switched to a low health sub-track
to a cello, ostinato, and bass pitts part.
So whether you are a zombie or a plant, it's the same.
You're down to your last five and you're not doing well.
Yeah, you kind of got that JAWS type thing happening.
We also, at this phase, because we're kind of like,
how can we get this more responsive?
Luca had been thinking about those kinds of ideas way early on, and he had this EKG, we
called it, game parameter, which was a combination of many different things of how the player
was feeling.
So a combination of many different things I cannot explain right now.
But basically, if you follow that parameter,
it would be an intensity change.
And so we thought, oh, we'll try that with Spadau and Cyborg
on some drums.
Let's try it on some drums.
So we added some subtracts and layers with drums.
And it was working in the game, and we could hear it.
But the material itself, the drum tracks,
it was live drums that I had recorded at Bastyr.
I never recorded really very much variation at all, never
any variation in intensity.
So there wasn't much feeling difference and I think I'd love to come back to this someday with different drums and put in more intense drums to have that match and follow.
Because I think it's a great feature but we decided it's not actually, you actually don't feel the lift because the material wasn't there.
So we tried and it was awesome and we decided to not use it for now.
So other late music changes were in the combat section.
Remember I wrote those phrases, we recorded them in our second session.
And they would get interrupted at the next beat in the game.
But it sounded a little weird to me early on in the game or
if there weren't many sidekicks on board during the combat sections.
So we decided, I could probably edit those combat phrases into shorter,
a shorten along.
So we utilized a game parameter.
based on how many cards are on board,
on the deck, in the combat area,
and if there are three or less, I believe,
then it goes to a short combat,
and if there are three or more,
then it goes to a long combat.
So we've changed that as well,
and now it's more responsive.
So all these changes, a little more responsive.
And now I'm gonna play for you
a little bit of how the transpositions sound.
So right now it's 16 for Solar Flare versus 15 for Tisha.
So no transposition.
But now she's up by 7.
Transposition on.
Alright!
So that's how that sounded in the game.
So I just want to recap a little bit.
The guiding principles that we set early on to be for the game
player, the player's experience, always coming back to that
as our guiding principle allowed for changes
to happen along the way.
And for our phases, I would say from the prototype
to content, MIDI, late phase even, where you think
you might be done, no, no.
You're not done.
You can re-look at it.
You can reassess it.
You can say, can this be better?
And utilizing your tools and an open mind and a flexible mind,
and flexible team, I should say as well,
you can make these changes all the way along
through the process.
So speaking of a team, it does take a village,
and a very fine one, indeed.
So I want to thank everybody on PVZ Hero's team.
Luca Fusi, lead sound designer extraordinaire, thank you.
Technical sound designers RJ, Mattingly,
Damien Kastbauer, interactive mixer Damien Kastbauer,
and Wizard of Wise, as we all know you to be.
Panther Modern, MIDI and orchestra arranger,
music mixer Corey Krockenberg,
for all those trailers and the brass,
it sounded so good, at Bastyr.
our additional sound designers, Sound Rangers, Formosa, RJ and Jacqueline, and of course
our studio audio director, Guy, for trusting this project to me.
I am so grateful for having this opportunity because I loved these last two years on this
project so much.
It's been the best of my whole career.
And then thank you very much for your time today.
I'm ready to take some questions if you have any.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Have a good day.
Bye.
Thanks.
Have a good day.
Bye.
Thank you.
the first 11 people, I think, that asked questions,
you get a mushroom, so don't be shy.
Okay.
Thank you.
So, thank you.
Wow.
A little shoot.
I kind of went through the same thing as you.
I was tasked with a mobile game
and went to listen to what was out there.
And this was the first game I listened to
and realized I was out of my league.
So kudos to you and the PopCamp team.
My question is, why when you realized
that the Stingers weren't working as real-time music,
did you not just convert everything,
or pre-recorded music,
did you not just go all MIDI all the time?
Yeah, I guess I could have done the stingers as samples.
That is possible.
But I really like the live brass.
And I didn't want to use the PopCap Sample Library brass
because the stingers had these great bends to them.
Pow, pow, their articulations.
You just, you only get that in live.
And so for brass I decided that just had to be
the live waves.
Thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
I'm sorry, Masha, if I hit you.
Oh, that was a good one.
So I was wondering about the transposition
with using the wave files.
Did you have to change the tempo at all,
or were all the wave files such short phrases
that they didn't change tempo when you transposed them?
Oh, okay, so the only ones,
only waves that transposed were the block stingers.
Bam, ba-dum!
And...
When we did that pitch thing, they of course sped up just a little bit, but
that was fine because they were not time based anyway.
They were just kind of attacks.
The combat phrases, the fight music, that did not transpose.
I'm like, how will that sound?
But it did sound fine, in my opinion, to transpose up and
then combat section does stay where it was.
So we did not transpose the combat section.
Okay, thank you.
Hi, thank you so much.
I believe they sort of asked the questions
that I was about to ask, but now I have the mushroom,
so I might as well just leave.
No, okay.
But no, I actually did have a question.
So what, I guess it was related to the key
that you chose to have things in.
How did the different kind of gameplay keys work together?
You have sort of each character has their own theme
and motif in the right key.
I may maybe just touch on that a bit.
Sure, sure.
Yeah, each character has their own motif.
And each in each hand, I set common key centers.
So hand one through hand three, it's all G minor.
And then at hand four, they all switched to C minor.
And then hand five, I started getting a little more crazy.
And I did C and D minor.
So it could be in C and D. And then seven and eight,
it was C, D, and G. And they're all complementary.
So it was fine to switch between those keys.
OK, thank you.
That kind of stayed safe, I think.
I'll pass on the mushroom. I've already got one.
Are you sure? You don't want a double?
No, give it to somebody else.
Is that a little friend?
Give it to somebody else.
I'm curious about your decision, because you guys are always pushing the envelope, which I love,
but I was curious that, you know, you were talking about these late changes etc, which,
knowing the way you guys do things, were probably fairly, you know, you know you're going to be
changing up until almost the minute it was done, so I'm kind of curious on why there was the
decision to do the live recording, what seemed to be sort of earlier on in the process, because then
you've, like as you even sort of said it yourself, it's kind of like, oh.
we can't do anything with that.
So whilst obviously the live recordings
give you a really awesome sound,
wouldn't it have been sort of more flexible
to do a semi-okay version of that in samples,
which you could then leave the recording to the end
and then if you've changed things, it sort of,
so what was the benefit of doing the live recording?
What was the decision on that one?
Oh, well, I think because of the marketing trailer.
Marketing trailer came quite early
and it was, they had budget for live recording for it
and.
So you took advantage of that.
Took advantage of that.
Right.
And then in editing and chopping that up and those, the beautiful brass sound that
that brought to the game and putting that into the game, I'm like, ah, I kind of
fell in love with that brass.
No, no, no, no.
Thank you.
That makes complete sense.
Cause I do exactly the same thing.
It's like, well, I'm not going to waste this.
Right.
But, but through your talk, it's like, but that would have been really much better
to do at the end, but of course you did have that choice.
Well, and yeah.
And that's, you know, kind of like how things go.
You don't know always where things will happen and you flex and you follow.
Thank you for sharing.
Yeah.
Thanks for asking.
Hi.
We're getting good at this, yes.
Sweet.
So, always be recording.
Always be composing, always be mixing, all of this.
You had someone come into your office
and basically say, cut out half of this.
Was there any concession that you had to make
in the composing?
Was there anything you had to change?
Or was Damian just that good and made it work?
He was that good.
For real?
Yeah, we did not.
Wow.
Well, no, you know, we took out variations.
Our concessions were in variations with the sound effects and the music.
So some concessions, but never really a large amount of content was changed.
I think we really held to it because we believed in how it was all working together.
And because Damien is so good with wise and knows the tools and how to really...
get it working in, I think that's why we're able to not really have to change the content.
Cool, thank you very much.
Yeah, I think if we didn't have Damien, we would have had it too.
Cool, thank you.
You're welcome.
Hello, thank you for your talk.
Ah, sorry about that.
That was like a ground ball.
I was just curious, for your live recordings, where were some microphone configurations that you use?
Oh.
Hahaha.
I don't remember.
We went to Bastyr and, oh, OK.
So we were in Bastyr, and we had an 18-piece brass group.
It was a giant church.
It's a giant church.
And I think they had many different sets of mics.
I don't remember exactly on the brass,
but I do really remember the drums.
They built out a little room in the middle of the stage,
a little drum room to record the drum kit in that space
so it wouldn't just be such a wash.
And so that was fantastic.
And then we recorded the bass inside the studio
and the brass, we took advantage of that beautiful space.
And so I can't remember exactly all their micing technique
that they used for that, but thank you.
Yeah, standard kind of, yeah.
Thank you for your talk.
Oh yeah.
Come on.
I'm just curious about the MIDI sample library.
And you said you made 24 instruments.
It sounds really good, but I want to know about more.
And how many variations in each instrument do you have?
Oh yeah, we did three different articulations
and three different dynamic ranges.
So usually a soft, medium, a loud,
and depending on the instrument,
what kind of articulations.
So that was about pretty much what we did for each,
sometimes four articulations.
And then we went and chose which ones we wanted
and needed for our games and further called that down.
But now we have all of that for the future.
Huh?
Each note.
Imagine Guy and I sitting for two weeks.
Baap.
Oh, no, that last one was pitchy.
That was our reality.
Total zen.
So three articulations, three dynamic range, and for each tone?
For each pitch.
Each pitch.
Each pitch, yeah.
And it did take about two weeks.
It took exactly two weeks.
to do 24 hours a week.
It's a fantastic job.
Thank you.
Hi.
Thanks for the talk.
You're welcome.
I just wanted to ask a question, obviously.
So, you sounded like you composed or maybe you just arranged in Logic and then exported
MIDI and were playing a similar or the same samples back in Wwise.
I just was wondering if you could talk a little bit about...
Any mixing that had to be done in Wwise,
or I'm assuming you're applying your ambience,
your reverb in Wwise, and what was that like to like,
did that make, did that help sell the transitions to have?
Absolutely, yeah we had the same kind of reverb in Wwise,
and we used that as a glue between everything,
and I think that's important,
because it makes everything feel like
it's coming from the same space, so yes we did.
Yeah, I wonder if you could do that even with waves, or if you just didn't mix it with reverb
and then you applied it in Wwise.
We had a little bit of reverb on the waves, but we also utilized the same reverb within
Wwise.
I don't think we brought anything in too wet because we knew that we would be utilizing
the reverb within Wwise.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
I think we have probably time for two more questions, and then our time is up.
Thank you.
This is perfect.
Hi.
I had a question that I just changed my mind though.
The first question was about musical genre.
Did you go back and look specifically
at certain references, styles, composers,
or did it just come out of your experience?
But I was wondering about MIDI controllers,
just based on that last question.
Were you using expression control and things in Wwise?
Oh, not really much, no.
I didn't really use much of that in Wwise.
I've been using the pitch bend lately.
Thank you.
Yeah, it's fine.
But you can.
I bet you can if you want to and it's flexible enough to do that.
The MIDI system in Wwise has a little ways to go.
Definitely there's no editing in there.
So if you wanted to even change any kind of velocity at all, you have to go back to your
DAW and then bring it back in.
but still love it.
Thank you.
Okay, last question.
And before I forget, everybody please fill in your surveys.
Ooh, and mention how great the mushrooms are.
Okay. Thank you.
First of all, this is a great, sorry.
This is a great talk, you have a brilliant mind.
I really, really do.
Thanks.
My question is kinda when you talked about
when you had to reduce the size,
when you mentioned different techniques,
like kind of carving and compression and things like that,
was it a matter of reducing the data
in the actual file and the playback?
Because was that the result of all the changes you made
in reducing it from like 80 to 60?
Was that the result of it?
You understand?
It's more about, well, we did a lot of compressions.
Right. Compression.
So if that's what you mean, yeah, we did a lot of that.
And then we did some...
But I mean, maybe let me clarify.
Like the net cut that you achieved,
how would you summarize the achievement you got
with all the changes you made?
Was that a reduction in kind of like the size
of the print of the file, or what was the actual result,
the cumulative result of all the processes?
60 megabyte memory footprint on device
was the result of all the different wizardry
that Damien did in Wwise.
Okay.
So we had 80, and then we went to 60.
And then we did have a lot of things that are streaming.
So basically it just became smaller and helpful to the game
because when, you know, especially on mobile,
they want download to be quick.
And also for the footprint on the phone
to not be too large because people will just remove it.
Yeah, that's probably true.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you. Appreciate it.
Yeah.
Well, thank you everybody.
I appreciate your time.