We called it the Traveler, and its arrival changed us forever.
But the traveler had an enemy.
So welcome.
My name is Tom Slattery.
I am the localization manager at Bungie,
and I'm here today to talk about
how we delivered the universe of Destiny
into the hands of millions of players
in a way that would hopefully make them feel like
it was one that was created for them.
So there's four main topics that I want to talk about today.
The first one is how we went about building a world
that would not only be as immersive as possible
for everyone playing the game,
no matter what language they were playing in
or where they were in the world.
but also one that would be easy for us to create and maintain.
The second thing that I'm going to talk about
is what we did beyond that in terms
of supporting the localized player experience, the things
that we did to make the game even better for players
in other languages, even though we didn't
need to do them for English.
The third thing I'm just going to touch on briefly,
but was our approach to localization for web and mobile.
Destiny has a mobile companion.
that is spread across web, iOS and Android.
So we also had to think about localization for that.
And I think there's some things that we did there that are kind of interesting and possibly
applicable to other people.
So I want to touch briefly on that.
And then the last thing is our approach to staffing for localization on Destiny.
What we did, why we did it, and what it allowed us to accomplish.
So how do you build a world for the entire world?
We had some unique challenges with Destiny.
One of the first things that we had to think about
was the fact that the setting is essentially
a real world setting.
Obviously, if you've played Destiny,
it's set in the future.
There's gratuitous space magic,
but it's our solar system.
It's the real world.
Parts of the game take place on Earth,
albeit in the future.
So if you have a fantasy series,
something that's completely made up,
like take Dune or Game of Thrones,
it's set on a world that doesn't really exist.
You can kind of suspend disbelief.
You can have everyone speaking English and that works.
In Destiny, it's set on Earth and in our solar system.
We have a real world and our real world has real languages.
So we have to be consistent with reality
while also making the experience work
for the players who are playing it.
The other challenge is that it's a shared universe.
So in Destiny, you could potentially be playing
in the same place, in the same space,
with someone else who's playing the game
in a different language, in a different country.
So we always had to keep that in mind too.
So one of the philosophical questions that pops up
as soon as you start thinking about that,
when you have players that are occupying the same spaces,
is do they see the world in the same way?
How do their eyes perceive it?
Do they see the same thing when they look at it?
And the answer, at least for Destiny, is yes.
We decided very early on, the decision was actually made
before I started at Bungie, that we wouldn't localize
any art assets, we wouldn't localize any textures
or graphics in the game.
And that wasn't to say that we would just give
a decidedly American gesture to everyone playing
in other languages, it just meant that we were gonna take
a very calculated approach in how we built the world
so that we wouldn't need to.
So why did we do that?
There's a few reasons, the obvious first one,
is the resource drain. There's a cost associated with creating those extra assets. And I don't
just mean a cost in terms of like dollars and cents cost. There's a cost to the project.
In any project you have limited amounts of time, resources, in terms of people, artists,
and money. So when you think about how you're going to use that, all things being equal,
personally, I would rather have an artist spend his or her time making more cool things
to put in the game or polishing the stuff that's in there.
Rather than creating the same rusty sign in seven languages.
And I'm a loke guy, so I usually get off on that stuff.
But beyond that, there's also a couple of very concrete reasons why we decided that
it wouldn't make sense for us to localize art.
The first one is what I touched on before.
It's a shared universe.
So players exist in the same space.
And the moment that you show two players who are in the same virtual space, different
things, you're essentially lying to those players.
There's a glitch in the matrix.
It's an inconsistent world.
And we didn't want to create an inconsistent world.
We wanted to create a persistent universe that was believable.
So you can imagine a situation if you've played Destiny strikes are basically cooperative
repeatable missions that you can jump in and play with friends over and over.
So you can imagine a situation where on a Friday night I ping my buddy in Japan and
you know he gets on and we jump into a strike together and we're playing and we get to a
certain point where he's like, okay, I need you to focus on that guy with the red dots
on his armor.
I'm going to go take care of those other dudes.
And I'm like, dude, I have absolutely no, where are you?
What's going on?
I don't even see a guy with red dots on it,
but this Stars and Stripes guy's kicking my ass.
So you can think of situations like that.
I mean, obviously that's a little bit exaggerated,
but you could think of things like a sign
on the top of a building that you're using as a waypoint,
or maybe you get separated from your friend
and you're trying to describe the things you see.
So you spell off a logo that's on the side of a building
or something like that.
And those sorts of things are where it breaks down
when you have players in the same space.
The other reason is again something I touched on before,
the real world setting and also the fiction
that builds off of that.
So for example, parts of the game take place in old Russia.
When you're in old Russia, obviously signs are in Russian
because that's what they speak in Russia.
And there's also fictional backstory
behind the other destinations that you go to in the game.
So fictionally in Destiny.
There is a base on the moon, and that was developed by China.
So all the signage for the moon base is in Chinese.
We also have colonies that are on Mars and Venus.
And these are fictionally English-speaking colonies,
so all the signage there is in English.
The one thing that I would point out there is
it's very easy to fall into the trap
of being an American developer
or being someone who only speaks English.
and naturally just wanting to make everything
fictionally English because it's easier.
If that were the case throughout the entire game,
the end result for players is that it still is going to feel
like a half localized experience.
You might be able to justify it fictionally all you want,
but when you jump into the game playing in French
and you're seeing everything you look at in English,
it doesn't really jive.
So the way that it actually turned out in our game,
you start off initially in old Russia.
And then you go to the moon, so you're getting this progression of Russian text on signs
and then Chinese text on signs.
And by the time you make it to Mars and Venus, as a player, you've kind of been trained.
You know that that information is not gameplay relevant.
You know that you don't need to pay attention to the signs, that it's basically decoration.
So it builds the atmosphere and fiction of the world.
But it still doesn't give that impression that we just didn't localize it because we
didn't want to.
It's clear that it's an intentional fictional decision.
So there were, of course, some challenges associated with this. One of the big ones
is working with text and languages that you don't have support for is very difficult.
And just about everything that can go wrong will and did. So we had things like
Concept artists who decided to go off and they wanted to make some Chinese concept art,
so they pulled out Chinese propaganda posters on Google, started picking characters at random.
You know, nothing that actually was problematic, it was just gibberish, but the kind of thing
that makes you really nervous.
We had things where maybe something like that happened and then the designer actually provided
an updated version for artists to implement that had correct Chinese or Russian text on
it.
But the artist who went to implement it
noticed it was different from the original concept art and corrected it back to what
it was or that sort of thing. We also had Russian signage, for example, where the text
got flipped upside down or backwards, which is a really easy mistake to make because Russian
is basically just like the English alphabet with half the characters turned backwards.
But if you don't speak Russian, it's really hard to notice that sort of thing. So we ended
up in the end having to go through and have testers take screenshots in the environment
of every...
foreign language text and send it off for review through professional Russian and Chinese
game translators to make sure that everything worked in context, was implemented correctly,
and wasn't offensive, which was another problem we encountered because
It turns out you might have something that's perfectly fine, but then you put some dirt
and rust on the sign and cover up a few characters and suddenly it says something different.
Like you can imagine in English a sign that said, wanted assassin, where the end of the
word gets a little bit obscured and it says something very different.
So yeah, we had those kind of problems, quite a few actually, that we had to fix.
Another problem that we had was something like I mentioned before, having mostly English
speaking developers, there's sort of this bias, this natural tendency to go English
with everything. So there was English everywhere in the game. We had things like people wanting
to put English translations on all the signs that were in other languages or just wanting
to put English signs everywhere because they wanted more text.
And the biggest challenge of all was the tower.
If you haven't played Destiny, the tower is sort of our hub space, our social space where
players go back between missions.
So in the early versions of the tower, we had essentially guide posts that would tell
you where all of the things in the tower were.
There was no mini-map or anything like that.
So your only way of really getting information about where things were other than exploring
the whole space was to go up to the signs and read them.
So early on, this is an early concept that we had.
The design of the tower has gone through a lot of iteration over the past few years before
launch so at this point in time the tower contained three different sectors basically
that we had called the underwatch, the military district, and the bazaar.
And each of these areas had different factions in it, each one was associated with a different
player class so you know the hangout for the titans was in the underwatch and that sort
of thing.
So, the basic art that they had created for that was a big capital letter that was the
first letter of the name of the section, so U for Underwatch, which makes perfect sense
when you're playing in English and the word for Underwatch starts with a U.
Then the name of it in English underneath and the list of all the NPCs and vendors and
things that you could find in that area.
Which again, if you're playing in any other language than English, isn't really helpful
because none of that means anything.
The names of those areas are going to be translated, so Underwatch won't be Underwatch.
The names of the classes have been translated, so Titans aren't necessarily Titans.
It's basically just not helpful.
And if that's the only way that players are getting that information, then you're basically
failing to convey important gameplay information to other players in other languages.
So we took another stab at it, and this was the next iteration of that, where we said,
We can't use the acronym approach. We can't take the first letter of each one. Let's just
call these sectors, like, sector A, B, and C. Because that makes sense to anyone who
sees it. So this is, you know, sector B here, which is the military district, the former
military district. Let's just put all the languages on there. So let's just translate
it into all the languages that we support in Destiny and throw all those on a sign.
And this is Google translation, by the way. So if the thing in Russian says something
offensive, I'm very sorry. I should have probably checked that.
But there's some problems with this, too.
You've got a whole bunch of languages,
which makes it really difficult as a player
to walk up to the sign and get the information that you need.
Like, even in this example, I think there's six here,
but if you're looking at six different languages
that say the same thing, it's a lot of information.
You're gonna have to scan through and go,
oh, oh, there's the one I can read.
That's the little tidbit of information I need.
It's also not sustainable, right?
Like, if we want to add more languages over time,
If we, you know, tomorrow decided to add another language to Destiny, we'd have to go through
and either update all this art or not provide that information to players in that language,
which would be kind of terrible.
And what do you do if we end up with like 10 or 12 languages?
Then suddenly you can't even squeeze that much stuff onto a sign.
So we didn't really like that approach.
Artistically, I mean, the art team also just didn't like it because it's messy, it doesn't
look good.
So some challenging problems there.
The other problem that I mentioned was English everywhere and that was something that we
very much had in the tower.
This is an example of a very early build.
One of my favorite games when I started working at Bungie was to prop a new build every morning
and go into the tower and see how much more English text the artist had put all over everything.
So this is actually from an email I used to take screenshots and send to my manager who
used to handle localization at Bungie and vent and get angry.
Obviously you can tell I'm a loke guy. This was a build before our character heads were
rendering so I'm running around in the tower. My character has no head and the thing that
I'm really upset about is the tiny little wording beneath the picture on the sign. But
this is an example where that one might be kind of hard to read up there but it says
new monarchy. New monarchy is one of the factions in Destiny. But in other languages it's not
new monarchy. In French it might be nouveau monarchy or something. I don't actually speak
French. And it's also just kind of
It breaks immersion. It's weird that you're playing the game, for example, in German.
You're in the tower. All the characters are speaking German. All the signs are in English.
It doesn't really make sense. Like, fictionally, if you're playing the game in Italian, for
you, the tower is an Italian space. The characters speak Italian. So you would want things to
be in Italian, right? So how do we solve this? We've got this decision
that we're not going to localize any art.
We've got a setting that contains a mix of languages.
We've got this tower that's a kind of complex problem where we need to make it feel like
home for everyone.
How do we go about setting rules to make sure that everybody has a good experience?
The first is, do not communicate any important information through text and graphics.
There can't be anything like a this way sign,
like the guide posts are a good example.
Any information like that that needs to be communicated
to players needs to be communicated in some other way.
So through the UI, which can be localized,
through dialogue, through some kind of visual cues
in the environment that give that information to players
without spelling it out.
Next is avoiding what I call Anglo-centricism.
This is the thing that I was talking about before,
that trap that it's really easy to fall into
when you only speak a particular language.
Don't just put everything in English.
Try to show, I mean, we have a world
that has diversity of language, so show that in the game.
Try to show that we have multiple languages
in this universe wherever you can.
Avoid putting English translation on things
just because you can.
The problem with that is that same thing
where suddenly instead of having this diversity of language,
you're showing again that this is a game
that was made for people who speak English,
but you know, you can play it too.
And that's not the impression that we wanna give people.
And also just don't use English text where you don't have to.
I mean, it's fine if there's some text here and there,
but if it's everywhere, it starts to be
that constant reminder, that sort of constant slap
in the face reminder that this game
wasn't really made for you.
The third, which is very important,
was solving the problem of how to make the tower
feel like home for everyone.
Because again, the tower is our hub space.
It's fictionally.
where all of the characters, which we call guardians, are from.
That's where they live.
It's your home.
And it would be very strange to return home and find a place
where you didn't really feel like you felt a part of the community.
It wasn't for you.
So we needed to make it feel like an international space somehow.
We need to give all players the impression
that this is not just a place where English speakers live.
This is a place that is filled with a lot of different people.
It's the last city on Earth.
So it makes sense that there's a cultural mix there.
Fourth, this is the one I mentioned before.
Absolutely avoid defacing or obscuring text on signs.
We had quite a few issues with this and we eventually just made the rule that any text
in a foreign language or English on a sign needed to be kept the way that it was originally
created and not covered up in any way that could make it say something else.
It's very important.
in this situation. Because if you make the decision not to localize art, even if you're
just putting up signs in English, you need to make sure that that English text doesn't
mean genitalia in Italian or that sort of thing. You need to run each example of signage
through all of the languages you support to make sure that it works for them.
And finally, no references to the English terminology.
Things like taking the first letter of the term in English,
which may not be the same in another language,
or putting the names of factions up on signs
where that name would actually be something different
in another language.
So there are some things that we purposefully decided
that we would not localize,
like the weapon foundry names,
the names of our NPCs in the game,
that are the same across all languages
and give us things that are safe to use.
But for the most part,
all terminology in the game gets localized.
Almost. This is my badge of shame. This is my one big localization fail on Destiny. This
was already on a T-shirt in our store when I started working at Bungie, so it was kind
of a little bit too late. It was all over the tower. But this is the logo for one of
our other factions called the Future War Cult. And obviously the logo is an acronym for Future
War Cult.
You can probably imagine translating future war cult into seven other languages in a way
that preserves the meaning and also happens to start with the initials FWC is not achievable.
So some languages fare it a little better than others but FWC only really works for
a couple of them.
So most of our languages, the logo here doesn't actually match the term for the faction name
and that's kind of sad if you're a localization person.
We do, if you've played the game, there's also an alternate logo, which is just the F.
And one of the, you know, solutions I propose to try to mitigate that in the future is
let's just try to use that one where we can, because that does work for most languages.
Future, in most European languages, still starts with an F, so that one doesn't feel as off as FWC.
So how did we go about solving all of the problems in the tower?
One thing that we did was pull out information that we needed into the UI.
So like I said before, originally we had no map in the tower.
The only way you were getting the information about where things were
was to go look at those guideposts.
So we actually pulled that out and we did implement a map.
And the map is all UI, so we're able to localize that
and provide that information to players in all languages.
So you can pull up a map of the tower, see what the different areas are called,
see what the different vendors and things are in that space.
So any of that critical information needs to go in there.
You can't rely on the environment art to provide that to players.
Another thing we did was try to lean on iconography wherever we can.
So teach players what icons mean and then use those,
rather than putting the text for it.
So this is the final New Monarchy faction space in the tower
that we actually shipped.
And you can see on the left, it still has that triangular logo
for New Monarchy.
under it, it just stops there. And players know that because they've seen that symbol
a lot. They know it's associated with the faction. There's no reason to put a sign on
them all.
Another thing that we did to cut down just on the amount of English text, one of the
problems with cutting out all text together is human beings use text.
So if you just cut all of the text out of an environment, it starts to feel fake.
It doesn't feel like a real inhabited human space.
So part of the pushback that I got from the artistic side on removing text was just that.
They still wanted to be able to use text in their designs to make the space look inhabited.
So one of the things that we did was try to find things that were globally palatable.
So for example...
The names of the weapon foundries, like I mentioned,
we kept the same across all languages.
We made sure that those names would work
in all the languages we were shipping,
so things you can see in that image,
like Omolon and Suros,
those are some of our weapon foundries,
and we used a lot of those on labels and things
to just add some text for decoration.
We also use things like industrial gibberish,
so just numbers and letters that don't mean anything,
you know, labels on a crate,
so that it feels like a real object,
but it doesn't necessarily say something.
It doesn't.
remind people that it's all English because it's not. It's just numbers and letters.
Latin is also easy to fall back on because Latin is just cool and nobody knows what it
says and the U's are V's and it's, you know, it's Latin. So we put a little of that in
there too in places. And we did actually go back to using some
multilingual signage. So this is how that guide post ended up in the final tower.
We don't rely on it anymore.
It's basically just decorative because there's a map.
You can find out where the stuff is without reading this.
But artistically, we just decided to narrow it down
to three languages.
We just went with English, Brazilian, Portuguese,
and Japanese.
So it accomplishes the idea of telling people
this is an international space.
There are not only English speakers here,
or only speakers of whatever language
you're playing the game in and hearing.
It's a space inhabited by lots of different people.
But it also solves the problem of us not needing to redo all of the art if we ever add another
language or anything like that.
So how did we arrive at those decisions?
Well, mostly through a lot of challenging compromise.
And I think that's an important, it's important to have those healthy discussions about what's
important for localization but then what does that mean in terms of art or story or that
sort of thing.
So a lot of these decisions came about after a lot of discussion with a lot of people.
So one example of that is what we call the human colonial palette,
the set of textures that gets used on Venus and Mars where all the text is English.
Like I said before, if that had been the decision for everything,
that every space in the game was just fictionally English,
that wouldn't have worked.
And I would have protested that decision,
but because of the way we present this in the game, it works.
And so I think this was a good place to just say,
you know what, it's okay that both of those spaces are English
because it's not really a problem the way it is right now.
Another example is the multilingual tower signage.
That was a compromise in the end of going back and forth,
having a lot of discussions with the art team
about what looks good and what's sustainable
and things like that.
And we ended up with something that I think
accomplishes what both sides wanted,
which is giving that impression of a multicultural society
that lives in the city,
but also not putting every single language on the wall.
Another one that I hadn't talked about was
We used to have a lot of text on our weapons. That was another thing I used to take screenshots
of all the time and send in angry emails. All English, of course. But you'd get things
that were literally in your face. Almost every scope on every gun had English text on it
that was very often associated with the city. Things like city armory, blah, blah, blah.
So again, it's feeding that impression that the city is an English-speaking city, which
doesn't jive with what people are getting when they're playing the game in another language.
So we looked at that and we ended up making pretty good compromises.
We tried to pull it off where it was extremely visible like that.
We left some text in places.
There's things like on the safety of a weapon, F and S for fire and safe are used generally
by international weapons manufacturers, so it's normal.
to see that even though it's English. So we kept things like that. And we didn't remove
all of the text because there's some weapons that have, you know, the names of the weapon
manufacturers which some of those are not English words. So you get a nice mix and it's
not all over the place. So we did cut out a lot of it. We tried to remove anything that
fictionally wouldn't work in relation to the tower in the city, but we left some of it.
And another one that was kind of similar was the opening cinematic for the game.
So if you've played Destiny, there's this opening movie which you're about to see where
there's some astronauts walking on Mars.
And it has text in it.
And our initial plan was just to render out the video in seven languages and everything
was fine.
And we did that.
It wasn't going to be a problem.
And then all of a sudden at one point we didn't have enough space on disk and it was a problem.
So of course the art team said, yeah, you're going to have to subtitle that.
And I said, well.
Well, we could do that, but then again,
this is the first thing that players see
when they pop in the game is this opening movie,
and the impression that they're going to get is,
this is a game that was made for English speakers,
and I have to watch it with subtitles,
which is not a very good impression.
So the compromise that we made
was to alter the artistic direction
of the video a little bit to work in multiple languages,
again, just a sampling,
but where it would appear to be an artistic choice.
And players who spoke one of the languages that were in there would be getting that information through there.
And players for the other languages, where we did have to throw in a subtitle,
wouldn't think that it was, oh well this is just an American game and that's why it's this way.
It's, oh well, this is the artistic direction and they have these three languages in there,
but they're providing this information because not all players speak those languages.
So here's where we landed in the end.
So, I mean, we don't really explain it.
And as a player, you can sort of interpret that however you want.
There's three astronauts, there's three languages, maybe they're from different countries and
speak different languages.
It's kind of up to you to interpret, but it solved the problem.
It didn't make the first thing that players see an English-only experience.
So, I basically told you that I was going to give a talk about localizing destiny,
and I've spent half an hour.
basically explaining how we didn't localize Destiny.
So I'm gonna actually switch modes now
and talk about the things that we did do.
How did we go about making the game
better for players in other languages?
So one of the big differences between Destiny
and the games that Bungie had been making, like Halo,
was that you can create your own character
and invest very, very deeply in it.
So in Halo, you were Master Chief.
Master Chief was you.
Master Chief was a dude.
In Destiny, you don't have to be a dude. You can create a character, you can choose your
race, your class, your perks, your weapons, your gear, and your gender. So if you're a
player playing the game in English, the gender choice doesn't really have a lot of impact.
It changes the voice for your character, it changes your model, but that's basically it.
It's a cosmetic decision.
In other languages, that's not the case, especially for romance languages like French, Italian,
Spanish, Portuguese. The very concept of gender is built into the language and the grammar.
So once you make that decision to play a female character, you suddenly need things to be
said differently about your character than they would be if you were playing a male character.
So as an example...
Here is French, so the English term guardian. In French, you've got le and you've got la.
There's no gender neutral way to refer to a guardian. You're either a male guardian
or you're a female guardian. Same thing with class names. You've got hunters, chasseurs
or chasseuses. So we basically are presented with a choice. We can either stick our head
in the sand here and just ignore that this problem even exists and just refer to everyone
as a dude. Or we can...
to actually support and affirm the choice that we've allowed players to make.
And that sounded more difficult, so we went with that.
So here's a quick example in Italian.
Probably a little bit subtle and hard to pick up if you don't speak Italian, but
Italian, the male version of guardian is guardianno,
and the female version is guardianna.
Depending on which gender character you're playing.
the other NPCs in the tower will actually address you with the correct gender.
So in terms of implementation, how we went about doing that, there's better and worse
ways to do it.
We wanted to do it in a way that wouldn't have huge memory impacts.
We didn't want to do anything dumb like just duplicate the set of lines that are used for
male players to female, and if one of them needed to be different, put a different wave
file in.
That would waste a lot of space.
So for actual implementation, what we did was, we have dialogue sequences in our game.
So for a given dialogue sequence, we look through each language, and for any line in
that sequence, if even one language needs a female version of a line, we create a branch
node.
So that line of dialogue will branch for male and female.
So if you're looking at this example here, English, we generally don't use this.
So the English dialogue sequence, it has a branch for male and female on the second line.
but it doesn't actually use that.
It's the same as the male line.
For the French dialogue sequence, it does.
So on the English one, all it does on the male,
or I'm sorry, the female node is just point to the male line.
So there's not a duplicate,
it's just referencing the other dialogue event.
And then for the other lines
where there were no female versions,
you just have a single node, a single line of dialogue.
And then at runtime, we filter based on.
the cause of the trigger of that dialogue event,
which is generally the player's character.
So we look at the gender of the cause
and play the correct line.
So a lot of games don't do this.
Most games actually don't do this.
But we thought it was very important
because that idea of creating and investing
in your character is fundamental to Destiny.
You put a lot of time into building that character.
And actually, I talk to a lot of people.
I talk to a lot of gamer friends,
European friends.
translators and whatnot about their own feelings.
And the thing that I just kept hearing over and over again
was, yeah, most games don't do this,
but whenever I play a game and I choose a female character
and it actually respects that, I just think it's so awesome.
And we want it to be awesome.
So we've supported this throughout our entire game
in the dialogue system.
So anywhere from random NPC lines to story,
mission dialogue, that sort of thing.
If you're playing a female character, that should actually be respected.
And if it's not, it's a bug and please tell me about it.
The other thing that we did, initially in our dialogue system, we had some pretty nasty
restrictions.
Our mission dialogue lines needed to be exactly the same length as English.
Which if you've done any kind of translation, you know is not fun.
To make a line in another language match exactly with the language you're translating from.
As a translator, first of all, it's just challenging because naturally the way that you say things
is going to be longer or shorter.
So you might have to pad a line with some fluff.
You might have to cut out some information.
You might just need to write a line of dialogue that's pretty awkward or force the actor to
rush through it to fit it in the amount of time because there's no way to cut it down.
But it also adds a lot of cost.
When you go into recording, it's the same problem.
The actor in a normal recording session can just read a line and if it sounds good, you
move on.
You're trying to match length of another language.
you have to repeat it and repeat it and repeat it and try to get it to work.
And when it doesn't work, then you might have to have someone rewrite it on the fly.
Or you know, add some padding in or try to stretch it out and see if it doesn't sound
too weird when you do that, you know, with audio processing.
So we fixed that.
We decided that was not a restriction we wanted to put in place.
So our mission dialogue can now be free length.
The only dialogue actually in the game that needs to match English was our cinematic dialogue
because
There's motion capture and you need to match the actual things that are happening on screen.
So there's a little bit of restriction there.
But we were able to get rid of the rest.
The other thing that we put a lot of effort into was making sure that the UI supported
what we need for localization.
So we actually did a lot of early work, throwaway translation, just so that we could get real
text in the game in all languages.
and test out every part of the UI.
So we just took a file or two here and there for each portion of the UI, got it translated
and started looking at what worked and what didn't.
And some of the things that we noticed very early on were there weren't enough space for
item names.
Our UI, if you can see in the little purple box there, it capitalizes all item names,
which makes the text wider, which means you have less space to begin with.
A lot of our item names in the game use compound words or possessives or things, so when you
have something like Dust Walker Boots and translate that into French, where you can't
use compound words, it turns into something like
boots of the walker of the dust or something like that, which gets really long.
So what we realized was we could probably find a way to make that work for Destiny.
We could just call them dust boots in French or walker boots in French.
But this isn't just one game.
This is an IP that we wanted to span a decade or more.
So we had to think long term and that wasn't a situation we wanted to get ourselves into.
We wanted to make sure that we were doing things right.
So we expanded it so that the UI will just automatically resize and we can go up to a
second line for localization languages.
And we did that in most places in the UI.
If you look at the tool tips there, anywhere the text gets longer in another language,
it automatically resizes.
We implemented font scaling.
So if we have to, we generally try to avoid it because it's not as pretty.
But if the text is just too long to fit, it'll scale down a pixel or two so that you can
actually squeeze it in.
Yeah, scaling everything essentially in the UI.
And the next part I want to touch on a little bit, like I mentioned at the beginning, was
our approach to web and mobile localization.
When I came into Bungie, we had an English-only website.
There was a new website in development that rolled out shortly thereafter, which had locales
built into it.
It was intended to be localized, but naturally had never been localized or tested in any
way.
So we had to think about how we wanted to implement localization for the website and
get it working.
So challenges that we had, things that we were thinking about when we sat down to spec
out how it would work was we knew we were always going to be lagging behind English
a little bit in terms of translation.
It's always going to take time.
Our community and marketing team tends to post very timely information.
They move very quickly, so things are always coming in pretty hot.
And we knew it would never be possible to keep up with things in six other languages
on the same timeline.
So we wanted a system that would be flexible, where we could get stuff out as soon as it
was possible, but still make sure that people were having a good experience without that.
The other problem was that we had no real tools support at all.
We had a content publishing system that was designed to create English content and post
it to the web, but there was no concept of localization in there.
When an item got updated, if you went in and updated it in English, we had no way to know
that that had happened.
We had no way to track what had been translated in the system and what hadn't been translated.
And we also have, essentially, not all of the game strings, but most of the text in
the game.
Also used for web and mobile. If you've used the destiny companion at all, you can look at your character so you can see items and their names and the flavor text. You can look at missions and their descriptions and all that kind of stuff. So the bulk of the text from the game is also used for web and mobile. That fortunately turned out not to be an issue for localization just because of the way it was set up to begin with. Our website pulls that content from a build of the game. So whenever we update the game with a patch or something, we
have a new content build that contains the text that the website can then use.
So that's something that we didn't have to worry about at all for localization, thankfully.
Because if we didn't have that, you get in a situation where you have two sets of duplicate
content over here and over here, and it's very easy for something to get updated and
changed and to forget to go back and do it on the other one.
So how we solved the big problem there with our content publishing system was, first of
all, to implement localization queues.
So any time that a particular piece of content
got updated or created in English, it would go into the queue for each of the other languages.
So each language had its own queue that could work at its own pace, go through and translate
items, submit them, push them out onto the web.
Within that, I mean, we've iterated on this for a couple of years now, so it's gained
a lot of functionality, but within each of those queues, we now also have priority queues.
So five different levels of priority where
If I'm going in and writing a piece of content in English, I can decide for myself basically
the priority that I think should be assigned to this.
I think this is super urgent and critical information to get out, so I'll mark it as
priority number one.
Or this is something that, yeah, get to it when you have time, but it's not super critical.
It's just a minor update, so maybe that's like a priority four.
And within each of those cues, then, an individual translator can go in and reassign.
If French has a huge backlog and a lot of things that are all set to priority one, you
could go through and say, well, yeah, these are all important, but, you know, these ones
are more important, so I'll put these other ones in a lower priority queue.
And the other thing that you can do whenever you're updating an item is add a note, a sort
of revision history.
So if I go in and update the English item three times and then the Italian translator
goes in to update his, he'll see the comments that I put in and see what has changed since
the last update.
And we also added.
import and export functionality to work with computer-assisted translation tools so that
we have the benefits of translation memory when we're doing this stuff, too.
So the fundamental philosophy that we tried to apply when we were thinking about the localization
of the site was that we wanted anyone who went to the site for the first time in, say,
French.
to experience a website that was fully localized in French.
If you go to a lot of websites that are localized,
you'll see a little flag at the top and you'll click on it.
And maybe you click the French flag
and like three words change to French
and the rest of the website's still in English.
And I don't like that, it's a big pet peeve of mine.
So what I wanted was the best localized experience
that we could provide by default.
But what we also wanted to do
was make it so that people had the option
if they speak English or
Maybe they don't speak English, but they just want to see, like, you know, there are fans
who might want to see a trailer the moment it comes out, even if it's not available in
their language yet.
We wanted to give people the ability to see the untranslated content too, if they so desired.
But understanding that the vast majority of our customers don't speak multiple languages,
so we don't want to just flood them with English content when they most likely don't speak
it because they've actively selected a different language.
So our solution to that problem was to implement English fallback settings. So each individual
piece of content in our content system has a property of whether or not it should fall
back to English if there's no localization available. So we have that on individual things
like news articles, but we also have it on content sets, which are another content item
which is basically a container of other items. So using that, we're able to do some kind
of interesting things.
each user's account settings, they have an option they can check to say, I want to see
content in English if it's not translated yet.
So between those things, we're able to do some kind of powerful and interesting things.
So here's one example.
Until very recently, our website had this top news set on it where there would be the
three spotlight news items we wanted to show to people.
The iOS and Android apps still use this.
So for this one, we would make the content set.
not fall back to English. Because we would never want to be in a situation, for example,
where we posted a new weekly update in English and it wasn't translated yet, but we decided
to go ahead and throw that on the front page for English. We wouldn't want that to show
up in other languages because it wasn't translated. So this is one where we curate the content.
We don't fall back to English. An individual translator can go in his or her language and
say, these are the three things that I want to display in my language. These are the three
most recent, most relevant articles that are available in my language.
Then the other pattern that we use is this one.
This is what we use, for example, on our help site
where we have a set of the trending help articles.
So the most generally useful or relevant things for users.
Maybe something happens in the middle of the night
and we need to post information for people.
This is one where, A, it changes pretty frequently.
So on the localization side due to staffing,
which I'll get into later, we don't wanna be responsible
for having to update this all the time.
But also, in general, at least for help information, I think it's better to give that to people
even if it's not translated yet. If there's something critical that's going on, I think
being able to get that information and at least, like, Google translate it. I just said
a dirty word, but I think that's better than nothing. So for this one, we've made the active
choice that this one will fall back to English. So the set of items that's displayed is always
the set of items that's displayed for English. But there are situations where we want to
remove some of them.
So for example, our game is only available on Sony platforms in Japan.
So on the Japanese version of the website, if there's a help article about Xbox, it doesn't
make sense to show that.
So we mark that one not to fall back to English.
Don't localize it for Japanese and it disappears.
So quick example of that.
This is a snapshot of our website from last month.
So here we've got a weekly update that was posted on February 12th.
And beneath that...
There is a content set of calendar events that are upcoming.
So it looks like five of them for English.
When you look at the website in German now, we have the spotlight item being the weekly
update from the week before.
So the English one was just posted.
It hasn't been translated into German yet.
So it just shows the most recent one that we do have for that language.
The calendar set beneath it also, there is one item that had just been added, hadn't
been localized into German yet.
So that one isn't displayed.
But it's okay. As a user going to the German site, nothing seems wrong. Unless you actively
go to English and see that there's something different, you're getting the most recent
information that's available in your language. But if you are a user who speaks both German
and English and you've set your account to show you that content, this is the view that
you'd get. So because there is a more recent article that hasn't been translated, suddenly
the spotlight news item becomes that one in English.
The calendar shows you all of the events that are translated in German, but the one that
was not translated yet also shows up.
So part of the reason that we did things this way was because of the situation we have for
staffing.
So I want to talk a little bit about that.
So I'm going to take you on a journey into the distant past, 2012 to be exact.
So in 2012, Bungie had no localization staff at all.
We had an English only website.
mobile apps. We had games that were only coming out on a single console. So things were simpler
then. Today we've got a fully staffed localization team. We have a game that we're supporting
that's a live game with frequent, you know, patches and releases and things like that.
We have apps in seven languages and those are the website and the mobile apps have two
weeks sprint release cycles where we're constantly updating them. So all together, it says seven
languages and platforms up there.
for consoles and then we're also supporting web, iOS and Android. So seven separate platforms
that we're supporting for localization all together.
So I want to talk a little bit about how we went about doing that in terms of staffing.
So for Destiny we used basically a hybrid staffing model. We had me, internal localization
manager. We had external translators that were in country working externally. We had
a internal localization editor.
working at Bungie, one per language.
And we had internal testers also at Bungie,
one per language.
And one per language is pretty small.
But like I said, we were able to start early
and do a lot of early iteration
that made it so essentially
when we got to the end of the project,
there weren't a lot of things to fix.
So things like getting that translation in early
and fixing the problems in the UI
meant when we got to localization,
almost all the problems that we had
were things we could fix in translation.
We didn't have to ask for features and support.
for that sort of thing.
We were able to get in at a stage where it was still early enough to solve the problems.
So localization editors.
This was an idea that was already in place before I joined Bungie.
But the basic idea would be to have someone who would be the main tester for that language
but was also capable of doing translation.
So when we got to the end of the project, if we needed very quick turnaround on things,
we would have someone in-house who could do that translation.
hearing stories from the past at Bungie.
One of the problems for them in terms of localization had always been not being able to turn things
around quickly enough.
Because Bungie is a company that likes to iterate and do things, if there's even a little
bit of time left where they can make something better, they want to.
So very often at the end of the project, there are changes going in.
Something something Jason Jones, something something.
pistols or something. Anyway, things go in where we need quick turnaround and if we don't
have the ability to do it, we can't make improvements to the game or we can't fix a bug. So that
was the basic idea. That's not actually how it worked out. We've ended up using our localization
editors for a lot of things. So we have them doing all of our web and mobile translation.
So all of that is done internally.
The actual builds of the website and the apps but also all of the content that gets published
is done by that person.
We have the ability to, like I've talked about, work on things before they're really ready
for localization.
So being able to go in and do that early translation meant we were able to make changes to the
UI while the UI was still being developed.
So rather than having to make people go back and repeat work, we were just able to identify
it.
problems for localization and make sure that the UI, the final UI when it was implemented
supported those things.
We also have done all of the game translation up to at least the capacity of our team.
So almost for the past year, not quite a year now, but most of the past year we've supported
all the game translation internally too.
So after we did the bulk of the translation on Destiny.
We took back ownership of the text in-house. We closed out the game. We've done all of the feature work for patches.
Our first expansion that came out last year, we translated in-house.
And at least so far, we've been able to keep up with everything internally.
We've also been able to use localization editors to do all of our testing between the major releases.
So again, being a live game with patches, there are things that are constantly being added that require a little bit of translation.
A little feature here that has some text associated with it or a bug fix over here that needs
something changed in all languages.
So there's not a lot of test work.
It doesn't really justify keeping a full-time test team for localization all the time.
But having those people who speak the languages in-house means that we're able to still do
that internally.
And finally, and probably one of the most important things, is that they review and
edit everything that's done externally.
So we essentially have a single funnel point
where everything flows through for each language.
So there's someone who is ensuring
that the translation is consistent,
the quality's consistent.
If something's done externally,
you might have something that references,
for example, a line of dialogue in the game.
And a translator who hasn't worked on the game
might not realize that.
So they translate it a little differently
than it actually appears in the game.
Having people in house means
that they'll catch that sort of thing
and actually be able to preserve those references,
keep up the quality.
because they're intimately familiar with the game and with Bungie.
So benefits of having an internal team.
One of the biggest ones and the reason that Bungie wanted localization editors
to begin with is agility.
It means that we can do things very quickly.
If someone comes up with an idea in the afternoon,
generally nine times out of ten we can get
it done in all languages the same day.
Obviously sometimes people are sick or on vacation or whatever, but most of the
time we're able to turn things around very, very quickly.
Another one is security. Bungie is a company who is very, very tight on security and does
not do things like send builds outside of the building. If you work in localization,
you can probably imagine not having access to the game that you're translating makes
things very challenging. We on Destiny, we flew over the external translators for a week
to play through everything and get familiar with the game so they
at least had a sense of what they were doing.
But having that person in-house then who can check everything that comes in and communicate
information, recognize where people are misinterpreting things and provide more context to the translators
is very, very valuable.
And finally, quality, which is, I mean, what all that kind of comes back to.
Having that single person who has a vested interest in making things better.
And no conflict of interest either.
When you're working with external translators,
I mean external translators are great too,
and I haven't met one ever who isn't passionate
about what they do, but they're kind of in the position
of being forced to do what they think you want,
which is generally translate things very quickly
and don't ask too many questions and send it back.
Whereas if you have someone internal,
they will actually point out when you do the things
that you shouldn't be doing, and they will fight
for the things that should be fought for.
It's a person who will be very steeped in the game
and care about it and ensure that the quality
of everything that's done for it stays high.
So that's another big gain.
So the other thing that I've been asked to remind you
is there are evaluations that'll be sent to you
after this talk, so please, they're electronic,
so check your spam folder and be sure to fill those out.
And also, Bungie is hiring.
We are hiring for localization.
We're hiring for many, many disciplines.
And one of our recruiters, I actually spy in the back of the room.
So if you have any interest in coming to work for a really awesome company and doing awesome
things, feel free to come up and talk to me or talk to Jessica in the back.
She'll be happy to give you more information.
Thank you very much.
I think we have about seven minutes for questions.
So if anyone has any, feel free to go up.
Give me a quick introduction, your name and who you are.
I'm Jack Ward Fincham, I'm a producer from Europe.
And for anybody who is working in localization, I worked in localization for years before
living in a country that wasn't localized to my needs.
And it taught me a hell of a lot about what I should expect out of localization.
That was great.
I've got a question.
You support seven languages, two of which were a form of Chinese and Japanese.
Is that correct?
So the question is what languages we support. We support English, French, Italian, German,
Spanish, Brazilian, Portuguese and Japanese. So within Japanese particularly there are
obviously nearly 10,000 individual characters. All of which you probably don't want to load
into memory in your phone, lest kill it. So what techniques did your team use to minimize
the memory footprint of your localization process?
That would be a better question for UI engineer. I want to say that it actually turned out
not to be a problem this time. I know in the past when I've talked to them about that on
past titles they've done things like actually scan the strings in the game and see what
glyphs are actually used and only put those into the font set to conserve memory. I want
to say that we were able to have the whole Japanese font in memory but you would have
to ask someone who is not me because I don't actually do the coding.
Hi, my name is Juan Pablo.
I work in Cartoon Network Latin America.
First, I want to thank you for the talk
and congratulate you guys on a job amazingly well done.
Thank you.
It's so good, actually, that Zur is a dick in any language.
So good job.
But one thing that I thought was really interesting,
do these localization, how do you call them, editors?
Editors, yeah.
Had access to the main development team, especially
the writers, because I noticed in the Spanish,
at least the Spanish localization,
it's really, really very good.
And there's a lot of things that.
were adapted, not necessarily as literal as they could be,
but it really makes sense in the concept of a game.
So I was wondering if they actually did interact with it.
Yeah, the external, so the question is,
did our translators have access to the writing team
and to be able to ask questions and things?
The external translators did not accept
that they did have access to us,
who could then ask the writing team.
But Bungie is, I mean, we're essentially a big open.
floor plan studio so everyone can talk to everyone. So yeah, the localization team,
the editors that we have in house go to talk to the writing team all the time. So we have
pretty much free access to anyone, which is really, really nice.
But there wasn't a centralized process to have that happen?
Not a super centralized process. I mean, we did, because we have so many languages, we
didn't want to have six people asking the writers the same questions. So we do things
like
build a spreadsheet where we put the questions in and then once a day or once every couple
of days, send that to the writing team to get answers.
But a lot of stuff just happens organically too.
You run into someone by the coffee machine and have a conversation about something you
were wondering or that sort of thing.
All right.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Oh.
Sorry, over here.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm Miguel Forte.
I work for Capcom.
I'm the manager of the localization group there.
Oh, hi.
Yeah.
I'm the manager of the localization group there.
Yeah, a lot of the problems you were highlighting here
are the same things we face every day.
And we do have an internal team, especially with figs,
to handle all those problems that arise.
So my question isn't really localization-based.
I'm more curious about your source language, English.
Who's editing the English?
Who is watching the writers?
Do you leave that to your QA team?
What happens when you find mistakes in the English?
I'm sure your internal localizers
are very vociferous about finding mistakes in English,
because it impedes their language.
So.
Who handles that over at Bungie?
Yeah, so the question is who checks the English content?
And the answer is, we're sort of in the process of changing how that works.
We just hired a copy editor, so we're kind of implementing a new process there.
But it's always been the case that anyone can report anything.
So the localization team definitely.
Translators see every bit of text in the game very closely and have to understand it.
So like you're saying...
It's very often translators who find the bugs in English and report them.
And yeah, they did.
I mean, we can file, anyone in the studio can file bugs on things, so they would file
bugs or just give a heads up to the writer that they knew were in, was in charge of that
particular bit of content.
Kind of curious what your approach is to localization of some of the legendary and exotic names
of things like Dr. Nope and The Devil You Know.
How do you handle that as it's translated into other languages and does that affect
how you name things in English that might not translate as well?
No, we don't give them any restrictions in English. English is what English is and we find the
best way to deal with it in other languages. How do we go about translating things like
exotics? I hire good people and I basically trust them. So I basically give our editors a lot of
flexibility to name things in their language the way that they need to to make it good. I mean,
there's a lot of things like Dr. Nope. It's not going to directly translate but maybe you can
come up with a similar name that captures that.
that theme or that idea and works for a French audience. So kind of play it by ear.
Hi.
My name's Lauren.
I am getting my MBA in localization management,
and I'm a freelance Japanese-English proofreader.
I have two questions.
One of them is that you said that you
rely sort of on iconography.
Do you do any culturalization of that or any checking
to make sure that the images that you're using
are appropriate for those markets?
And also, in terms of your web development and the web
portals, do you use sort of a global gateway,
or how do you address people coming
into that for the first time and being
able to adjust their language settings?
So, a couple questions there.
So the first one is iconography.
How do we go about making sure that the icons and images we're using are okay for other
regions?
We have a geopolitical review process where we send stuff off.
So all textures in the game, all those assets go off to people to be reviewed for that sort
of thing.
And a lot of that, I mean, because we have...
Activision as our publishing partners, we have the ability to lean on them for help
with a lot of stuff like that.
But yeah, we definitely do reviews because you can get into a lot of trouble with that
sort of thing.
And because we don't localize graphics, that is something we have to worry about because
we can't change it for another language.
And I'm sorry, the second question was?
About the web portal.
The web portal, yeah.
So I don't know a lot of the details because again, that's stuff that engineers implemented.
What I'm told is it redirects based on the locale from your IP.
So if you don't...
I believe there's a cookie that gets set, and if you're a first-time user and you don't
have anything, it tries to figure out where you are in the world based on either IP or
browser settings or something like that to initialize it.
Considering a lot of developers and publishers in the states are kind of ignorant about localization
and usually localization happens in the end of the production.
Considering that, it seems like there was a huge leap from 2012 to 2015.
Can you tell me what exactly happened to change that mindset?
I think at Bungie, a big piece of it was they went independent.
The last game they published, they were still a part of Microsoft.
And being internal at Microsoft, they had Microsoft's localization team to work with.
Localization had never really been something they needed to worry about internally.
It was something where towards the end of a project, someone who had another job would
just be tasked with, you know, okay, get the strings together to do a localization handoff,
get those assets implemented back into the game.
But there wasn't a need to have dedicated internal people.
So it was a combination of that, I think, and also just building this new IP and wanting
to do things right and build a global brand.
They wanted to make sure that we were...
taking a good approach to localization.
Was it just for this game, or was it just
as a Bungie company itself?
It's hard for me to say because I came on
after they'd already decided to start building
a localization team internally.
So yeah, half answer, but sorry.
All right, thanks.
Yep, thank you.
I'm sorry, I apologize,
but it's now time to end the session.
There is a wrap-up room in cell 300.
You're welcome to ask additional questions there.
All right, thank you.