Hi everyone, thank you very much for coming to my talk on Environment Design as Visual
Storytelling. So before we get into the talk proper, a little bit about myself. So my name
is Miriam Bellard and I'm the Art Director for Visual Development at Rockstar Games.
So I have a background in architecture and film as well as video games.
So I hold a first class honours degree in architecture from Auckland University in New Zealand.
The highlight of my film career would have been as a set designer on King Kong.
So that was a Peter Jackson film filmed in New Zealand.
And the highlight of my video game career is most definitely my current job at Rockstar.
However, I haven't just worked on big budget and triple A. I started my film career working on
short films, music videos, and low budget productions. And I started my video game
career at an indie studio, and I returned to indie work in the middle of my career as well.
So this talk isn't just aimed at big budget and triple A. This talk is aimed at everybody.
Within Rockstar, I lead a team of visual development artists,
and they all come from similar backgrounds to myself.
So architecture, interior design, film set design,
concept art, things like that.
This is the type of work that my team does.
So our focus is on environment pre-production.
So we're doing architectural layouts,
set dressing passes, reference boards, and so on.
So our role as a department is to make sure
that designs are going to work for everybody.
So they need to work for game design,
for environment art, for art direction,
for animation AI, the narrative team, and so on.
So this talk is a companion talk to one that I did a couple of years ago now,
and that talk was on environment design and spatial cinematography.
So when you are designing, you need to design for a number of different criteria. You need to design
for spatial cinematography, but also visual storytelling, which I'm going over today.
player interaction, aesthetics, and practicalities.
So a good design is going to take all of these into account.
Sometimes we do need to make some compromises,
but it all needs to work.
So moving on to the talk proper,
so environment design as visual storytelling.
So a good way to get into this
is to think about our role here.
So we are very much like
actors and actresses in that we are playing a part in creating a character.
The biggest difference between us and actors and actresses is the medium that we have to work in.
So they are working with their own bodies and their own physicality,
whereas we are using the environment in order to create our characters.
So the talk today is going to be a very fast-paced talk.
I'm going to be going over quite a lot of different points.
This is very much a broad overview.
Those points are going to be grouped into four sections.
So we have mimesis,
which is all about mimicking and copying reality.
semiotics, which is all about signs and symbols and how we communicate, cognition, which is about
neuroscience and psychology, and then we're going to end on some aspects of the structure
of your visual storytelling. Now for advanced people in the audience,
some aspects of the Mimesis section are going to be a little bit basic for you,
but I ask if you'll just bear with me because there'll be more for you in other sections.
So if you want to know more when the talk's over,
I will be putting a bibliography up on my website
that will cover not just the references
that I'm going to bring up during this talk,
but also other things on the topic as well.
So, starting now with mimesis.
So this is all about mimicking and copying reality.
So a good way to start here is with role-playing.
So when you're engaging with a design,
you want to think about who are the characters
that were involved?
What resources did they have to hand?
What was their taste?
What was their interest?
What was the fashion at the time?
And then who came later?
What were their needs, their tastes, their interests?
what environmental factors were in play as well.
And so you really want to think through all the different layers of history
and all the different characters.
Now, sometimes that will lead you to designing something like this,
which is, of course, a piece of contemporary architecture.
but more often than not we're going to be designing something that looks much more old-fashioned and
historic or that looks completely undesigned. So here the storytelling is, you know, an underground
bunker space, it's not supposed to look architecturally designed, so even though it was
designed by an architect we can't make it look like that. Again, we are actors and actresses
and we're playing a part.
So all the images I'm going to be showing you today
are all from GTA 5 or GTA 5 Online DLC.
That is, I should say, all the in-game images.
So next, under mimesis, so again,
mimesis is all about mimicking and copying reality.
Next, we have personality.
So this book here,
which is by an environmental psychologist,
he talks about how your personality is portrayed in a space.
So he talks about behavioral traces, identity claims, and mood modifiers.
So behavioral traces are the traces that you leave behind in an environment as you use that
environment. So they are of course things like mess and clutter, but it's also things like a
couch or a chair under a window or next to a lamp because somebody is using it to read or to write.
So next, under personality, we have identity claims.
So identity claims are the claims
that people are making about themselves,
and that can be self-directed,
so you could be reminding yourself who you are,
or it can be other-directed,
so you're letting other people know who you are.
So they are, of course, things like photographs on the wall
or certificates, but it's also things like your choice
of artwork that you have up
or the types of objects that you have up.
So are you somebody who has authentic,
traditional arcade cabinets,
or are you somebody who has a modern reinvention
of an arcade cabinet to show how modern
and cutting edge you are?
So next under personality, we have mood modifiers.
So these are things that people are doing
in order to adjust their mood.
So a lot of this is happening in the audio
in terms of the music that people choose to play,
but it's also happening in the visuals as well.
So it can be things like candles or incense
or the colors that people choose to paint their walls.
Now, it's not just about being calming.
It can also be about amping up the volume as well.
So next under mimesis, so mimicking and copying reality,
we have affordances.
So affordances are the actions that an object allows.
So a chair affords sitting, a car affords driving,
and a door affords opening.
So we normally think about affordances
in terms of interactivity and gameplay.
However, affordances have storytelling components as well.
So to start out with an extreme example,
so let's say you have a cellar.
And in one version of that cellar, you have a torture chair,
and in another version, you have wine barrels.
Now, as I'm sure you're aware,
the storytelling is going to be very,
very different in those two.
Now, that is the case even if the torture chair
and the wine barrels are not actually functional
in your game.
It's the affordances from the real world
that are adding the storytelling.
So to take a less extreme example,
let's say in one space we have a lot of furniture
and in the other we don't have any.
So the affordances of furniture are of course
that it's there for human use.
You can sit in chairs and you can be comfortable.
So that is the storytelling that it's adding to the space, the sense of welcome that the space
is for humans, and that sense of comfort as well. Now that is the case again, even if those are not
functional in your game, this is about the affordances from the real world, that's what's
providing the storytelling.
So next under mimesis, so mimicking and copying reality,
we have sizes.
So sizes affect how we see the materials and structure.
So here with these two bridges,
a steel bridge is going to have very different sizes
and spans in comparison to a masonry bridge.
However, if I look at a slightly more subtle example,
so on the left, you are looking at the steel structure
that's in a tunnel leading to a missile silo,
and in the right, that's the steel structure
for an airplane hanger.
Now the structure on the left is much thicker and much chunkier because it has to withstand the
shaking from the missile when it takes off. So again the different sizes here are communicating
the different functions. So sizes also affect how we see the characters. So to start out with stair
sizes, so these are normal stair sizes and the character looks very normal.
However, these here are oversized stairs.
And the effect that oversized stairs does
is it makes these characters look small and weak
and childlike as they're climbing up the stairs.
Now, it's perfectly acceptable to do this
if that's your intention.
If you want your characters to look small and weak,
then by all means have oversized stairs.
But quite often in game,
we have, if not heroic characters, at least powerful characters,
and the last thing we want to do is to make them look small and weak.
So, as a public service announcement, the size of stairs is in proportion to a human stride.
As the rise gets higher, the run gets shorter, because it's the rise and run together
that are in proportion to a human stride.
So there are equations for this online.
This is just one from Wikipedia.
So interestingly enough,
you could take the stride length here,
the human stride length,
and you could replace it with the stride length
of say a dwarf or a giant or another non-human race.
And in doing so, you could actually make stairs
that were correctly proportioned for non-human races
for sci-fi and fantasy games.
So this isn't just about stair sizes,
this is anything that is about human ergonomics
and human proportions and anatomy.
So it's things like chair heights, table heights,
desk heights, counter heights, bar heights,
that kind of thing.
If you have any of those too big,
what you're going to do is create this kind of mini me
effect on the character.
Now this can actually be a bit of a practical problem.
So if we look here at the first picture on the left,
that chair is 100% real-world size.
In many games, that is going to look too small.
It's just not going to have enough presence on screen.
Whereas the middle one.
We've enlarged that, but that is now
having this mini-me effect on the character.
However, the one on the right, what we've done
is we've scaled the width and scaled the depth,
but we've kept the height at 100% real world.
And so that is giving us more on-screen presence,
but it's not having the mini-me effect on the character.
So next, under mimesis, so this section
was all about mimicking and copying reality.
Next, we have layout.
So if we look at these two buildings here, the first one is a US building from the early 1900s,
the second is a UK building from the 1800s. So there are a lot of differences between them.
So obviously one's freestanding, the other is a row house, one has wood, one's made out of brick,
they've got different cells, windows and doors and so on. But another extremely important
difference is their layout. So that first house you're entering
directly into the lounge, and you have this very interconnected layout.
Whereas the second one, you enter into the corridor, and the corridor and the stairs
create a linear spine through the building, and everything comes off the corridors.
Now if you were to mix up those two, and if you had that corridor in the very first one,
you would completely undermine the visual storytelling of that space.
So it's just as important the same way that you would research, say, things like the style
of doors and windows that would go in a particular style of building, you also need to research
the layout for that style of building.
Now I'm going to take a slight tangent for a second.
So if you remember, right at the beginning of the talk,
I spoke about how we need to design
for multiple different criteria,
and not just visual storytelling.
Well, it's very possible that a layout like this
would have issues when it comes to
both the spatial cinematography side
and also the player interaction side because a linear layout like this with lots of dead ends
is going to mean lots of turning around for the player and lots of stopping and starting
and it's not going to be very fluid movement. So what we would probably do or look at doing
in a space like this, again depending on the gameplay of course, but more than likely we're
going to be end up
adding some extra doors in order to create looping layouts.
Now, this of course does undermine
this visual storytelling to some extent,
but what we're trying to do is we're trying to make things
work for the other criteria as well
and have as little impact here
on the visual storytelling as we can.
So what we're not going to do is we're not going to walk,
we're not going to change this
into a completely open planned layout.
we're not going to walk directly into the lounge like the other one,
we're just going to make as small and as subtle changes as possible
in order to make this work.
So to sum up now the Mimisa section. So this section was all about mimicking and copying reality.
We had role-playing, which is thinking through our different characters and the layers of history.
Personality was all about identity claims, mood modifiers, and I have forgotten one of them.
Behavioral traces, that's right. Affordances, that's the actions that an object allows.
and that the real-world affordances affects the in-game storytelling, sizes affect how we see
materials and structure, and also how we see the characters, and finally it's as important
to research your layout as any other aspect of a design.
So next up we're going to talk about semiotics.
So semiotics are all about signs and symbols
and how we communicate.
So a good introduction to semiotics
is this painting by Magritte.
So what the text on this painting says
is this is not a pipe.
That is entirely accurate.
This is not a pipe.
this is a painting of a pipe.
In fact, if I'm going to be particularly pedantic,
this is a digital representation of a painting of a pipe.
Now Magritte was very interested in semiotics
and this actually was what he was referring to here.
So at its heart with semiotics,
we have signifiers and what is signified.
So the painting here is a signifier
and what it is signifying is the pipe itself.
So we have a number of different types of signifiers.
We have symbols, icons, and indexes.
So before I get into actually explaining these,
I just to point out to the more advanced people
in the audience that the examples I'm going
to be giving here, all of them are things
that you're familiar with already.
So what's new or useful here
is actually the words and the structure in order to explain what it is that we're doing already
rather than adding anything new here in terms of actual practice.
So a symbol signifier is a signifier that is culturally arbitrary and needs to be learned.
So language is the classic example here. So in order to understand that the English word rose
means a rose, we need to understand English. You know, we can't just figure that out. I can't look
at any of those words from the other languages and know that they mean a rose.
In terms of visuals, something like a traffic light
would be an example of a symbol signifier.
Again, this is culturally arbitrary.
You need to learn it.
You can't just guess by looking at the traffic light
what it means.
So in terms of in-game examples.
So texts and plaques and things like that that we have in game are examples of symbol signifiers.
And when we use logos and cultural references in the game, those are all symbol signifiers as well.
And so the more the player understands the cultural references,
the more the player will understand the signifier.
So an icon signifier is a signifier
that physically resembles what it is signifying.
So male and female icons,
and also, of course, this picture by Magritte.
So the painting itself was an icon signifier,
and again, what it was signifying was the pipe.
So the painting looks like the pipe,
which is what makes it an icon.
So icon signifiers would be the most common
type of signifier in game.
So here we've looked to what modern contemporary casinos look like and
contemporary hotels and we've applied that knowledge to the design of this building.
So this building simply looks like a modern casino and so that would be the most common
type of signifier in game.
So an index signifier is a signifier where we have a linked or causal relationship
between the signifier and the signified. So here the smoke is an index signifier
and what is signified is the fire that's causing the smoke. So an in-game example would be all the
money and drugs and alcohol that you're seeing lying around here. All of those are index signifiers
which communicate what the player and the characters have been doing.
So to move away from theory for a second and to talk just about practice, we have the concept
of aesthetic language.
So most of you are going to be familiar with the term shape language.
So by aesthetic language, I am meaning something a bit broader.
However, let's start with shape language to begin with.
So you will also be familiar, I'm sure, with the use of shape language in sci-fi and fantasy,
where you might, say, have round shapes that you associate with the buildings and the vehicle designs and so on of one particular race,
and then sharp angular shapes that you associate with another race.
And by having different shapes for different races, it makes it easy to tell them apart.
Well, you can use shape language in realistic designs as well.
So let's say we were designing either some art deco moldings or some colonial moldings.
What you could do in order to design moldings that fit within those styles but that were
fresh new moldings is you could look to the shapes of those moldings
understand those shapes and then do something in the same language.
So with the Art Deco ones you're looking at the fact that they're made out of
rectangle squares and simple curves and the colonial ones are of course much more complex shapes.
And so that is the way we've approached this design here.
So this brutalist design on the right looked to existing and proposed real-world brutalist designs
and it didn't copy any of them, it didn't copy any particular parts.
What it did was it looked at the kinds of shapes that you see in those and we learnt the shapes
and then created something new using those shapes. Now this is the same approach you can take if you
say want to design a piece of furniture within a particular style or even if you want to do some
artwork in the style of a particular artist.
So another good use for shape language
is when doing construction and structure.
So that was the approach taken here,
and we looked to marine architecture
in order to create this design.
And so again, this was done using shape language.
So it treated it like with those moldings,
learnt the language of the shapes,
and created something in that language.
Now, there is another way
we could have approached this design.
We could have instead done it
through a more role-playing approach.
With that approach, you would design like an engineer would,
and you would design it following principles
about construction structure, the forces, and so on.
Now, there are advantages and disadvantages
to the two approaches.
The advantage of the role-playing approach
is that the final design is going to be much more realistic.
The advantage of the shape language approach
is that it's faster, it's more fluid, it's much easier to be creative and to make things up,
and of course you don't need the same level of knowledge as you do for the role-playing approach.
Now a good design will usually use, will usually always use, aspects of both. So it will use
some aspects of role-playing and some amount of shape language.
and how much you lean towards one and how much you lean towards another will depend on the needs of
the project or the needs of that particular design. So how important is realism versus how
important is speed and creativity?
So as mentioned, this is broader than just shape language.
So by calling this aesthetic language,
what I'm meaning is that everything
that you can do there with shapes,
you can do with other aspects of aesthetics as well.
So you can look at your reference in terms of the level of density, how sparse is it or how
dense and detailed is it, and you can learn that level of detail and create something
again following the same aesthetic language here.
So you can do that with cohesion as well. So how cohesive or not is it? Is it like the one on the
left where we're getting a lot of repetition of shapes and colors and a limited palette,
so it's more cohesive? Or does it have more variety like the one on the right?
And also, what kind of colors are you seeing? What are the actual hues? What kind of variety
are there? How limited is the palette? And are the colors coming from the objects or from the lighting?
Also, what level of order are you seeing?
Is it simple order like the image on the left,
complex order like in the center,
or is it chaotic like on the right?
Now, it's also important to consider the different layers as well.
Here, both of these images look very chaotic.
However, the one on the left,
the chaos is all coming from the set dressing,
and the architecture is actually quite ordered.
However, the one on the right,
the architecture itself is chaotic as well.
So when you're analyzing your spaces and the reference,
need to be looking at all these different aspects
in the different layers.
So what's the architecture doing?
What's the set dressing doing?
And what's the 2D graphics doing?
And then when you analyze all of those layers
for all the different aspects,
so shapes, colors, textures, cohesion,
order, chaos, and so on,
then you can learn the language
and start creating something by speaking in that language.
And of course, like we mentioned earlier with the shape language, you want to mix this with some
role-playing, because if you don't have any of the role-playing in there, then the space won't
be quite as solid and real. But how much role-playing will of course depend on the needs of the project.
So finally, under semiotics, I'm going to talk about tropes.
So I'm not meaning here the use of this term
that we are most familiar with,
which is, of course, an overused cliche.
Instead, I'm meaning the use of this term
that you see in literary theory or semiotic theory.
So there, tropes simply means figurative language.
So it's figurative language in general rather than just a cliche. So there are a lot of different
examples of tropes that you see in literary and semiotic theory. I'm just going to go over a few
today. So metonymy is when you use something, is when you're referring to something that is related.
So in other words, you could use the White House to refer to the US administration.
Synecdoche on the other hand is when you're using a part to refer to a whole. So we could use the
Eiffel Tower to refer to Paris or to France. And then metaphor on the other hand is when
you are comparing two seemingly unrelated things.
So for example, I could say, he has a sunny disposition.
There I'm comparing two things which are seemingly unrelated,
the fact, the sun, and then this person's disposition.
And by comparing them, I am adding shades of meaning
onto one of those things.
So I'm changing how we see him.
Now we can do that kind of metaphor visually as well.
So this one here is using shape metaphors,
but we could have also made metaphors
with things like colors or textures or lighting
or anything else as well.
So the first, the one on the left
is using circular shape metaphors
and the one on the right are jagged angular shapes.
So the circular shapes are going to remind us of things like rolling hills, bushes, fruit, babies,
other humans. It's all nice things and friendly things and so that is the meaning that gets
applied to the space. The one on the right however,
The angular shapes remind us of things like broken bones,
cleft edges, teeth, claws.
It's all things which are far less pleasant,
and so it's those kind of associations
that that's the meaning that gets applied to this space.
And by the way, I'm going to go over the science of that
in the next section, but to sum up semiotics first,
So semiotics was all about signs and symbols and how we communicate.
At its heart it's about signifiers and what is signified. We talked about the different
types of signifiers, so icons, indexes and symbols. And then we went on to aesthetic language.
So we talked about shape language and we extended that into other aspects of aesthetics.
And then we finally ended on tropes, which was how we can have
figurative language and how that can be done visually.
So next we're going to talk about cognition.
So this section is all about neuroscience and psychology.
So first up, we're going to talk about associations.
And this is the science behind the tropes
that we just covered.
But before we get into that,
I do just want to talk a little bit about the science
that I mentioned in my previous talk.
So in that talk, I talked about evolutionary theory
and habitat theory.
and how we evolved to like and dislike certain things because it helped our ancestors to survive.
So I still think that science is accurate and it's definitely useful in some areas,
especially things like what players will avoid and what players will move towards. However,
when it comes to visual storytelling, the associations that I'm going to go over today
feel far more useful and more applicable and much broader as well.
So this is something of an update on the science from my previous talk.
So this lecture here, which by the way is a fascinating lecture and I'd highly recommend
watching, it's a neuroscientist talking about aesthetics. So in that lecture he talks about
synesthesia. So synesthesia is a mixing of the senses and the most common form of synesthesia
is when people see numbers as having a colour. So if I was to show this diagram to someone with
number colour synesthesia.
And if I was to ask them what shape the twos are making,
because this is a mixture of fives and twos,
they would immediately be able to tell me
that the twos make up a triangular shape.
And the reason they could tell me so quickly
is because for them, the twos are tinted
a different color to the fives,
and so of course they can see that shape straight away.
Now, what's going on in the brain of a synesthesiac
is that early on in the brain's development,
we have a lot of extra neural connections.
As the brain develops, a lot of those get cut.
In the brain of a synesthesiac,
some of the connections that get cut in the rest of us
don't get cut for them.
So with someone, and it's not that surprising,
that number-color synesthesia is the most common
because numbers and colors are right next
to each other in the brain.
So what's going on in the brain with somebody
with number-color synesthesia is that when the number
gets triggered in the brain, there is a hardwired connection
to the colored part of the brain
that's automatically triggering a color as well.
So this kind of mixing of the senses is something that all of us do to some extent.
So if I was to show you all these shapes and tell you that one of these shapes is called Buba
and one of these shapes is called Kiki, the vast majority of you are going to say that the first
sharp shape is called Kiki and the second soft shape is called Buba.
because a sharp shape obviously goes with a sharp word,
and a soft shape obviously goes with a soft word.
However, this is a mixing of the senses.
We are mixing here shapes with sounds.
So interestingly enough,
synesthesia is actually eight times more common
in people with creative roles.
compared to people with more technical roles.
So the reason for this is, is that being able to create
links between seemingly unrelated things is at the heart of creativity.
It's also the very definition of metaphors which we described before,
where the metaphor we are relating seemingly unrelated things
And so that is exactly what's going on in the brain when we make these kind of visual metaphors.
What we are doing is making connections in the brain between things which are seemingly unrelated
in order for the meaning and associations of one to be applied to the other.
It is also important to be aware that there are cultural differences.
So in this lecture here, this is a psychologist talking about aesthetics.
So he talks about a number of different studies that together create an interesting picture.
So in the first study, he looked at how much people liked or disliked different colors.
So the bright blue that you're seeing at the top right, everybody likes that.
and the dirty yellow in the bottom left,
everyone dislikes that.
Next, he looked at what people associate
with those different colors,
so that bright blue was associated with the sky,
and that dirty yellow was associated with vomit.
And next, he looked at how much people liked or disliked
the things that were associated with those colors.
So how much do people like the sky
and how much do people like vomit?
And next he compared how much people liked the colors
or disliked them and how much they liked or disliked
the things associated with those colors.
So to give a layman's interpretation of his results,
80% of how much we like or dislike a certain color
is coming from how much we like or dislike.
the things associated with that color. So again, Leibman's interpretation here,
80% of the visual storytelling of a color is coming from what we associate with that color.
So next he did a study of different cultures.
So he looked at Japan, US, Mexico, and Serbia,
and looked at the color preferences
in those different countries.
So every single country liked a nice sky blue,
and every single country disliked a vomit yellow.
However, when it came to the other colors, there was a lot more variety.
So what this tells us as visual designers is that when we're making associations,
so when we're making references, if we're referencing something that is a universal
human experience in the same way that the sky is a universal human experience and vomit is a
universal human experience, if that's what we're referencing, then we can be confident that
everyone will understand us.
However, if we're referencing things which are a bit more culturally specific,
then not everyone's going to understand it. So in terms of what to do about that, sometimes we
don't need to do anything at all. Some aspects of visual storytelling are sometimes in there
just to create an extra richness to a design, but sometimes it is important that people understand,
and when this is the case, what we need to do is we need to communicate via multiple channels.
So we need to communicate via, you know, like not just colors, but maybe shapes as well,
or textures, or maybe you look to other sections of this talk and maybe you add an index
signifier or a icon signifier because those aren't culturally specific.
So next we're going on to spatial metaphors.
So what's going on in the brain here
is that the brain creates social cognitive maps.
So the brain takes the neural infrastructure
that was developed in order to understand
and navigate the physical environment,
and the brain has co-opted that
in order to understand and navigate the social environment.
So I could say something like,
somebody is close to me,
somebody else has been distant recently,
somebody else is above me at work,
somebody else is ahead of me at school.
All of those are spatial metaphors
used to describe social relationships.
And so this article here
goes into the science more, if anyone's interested.
And again, all of these references will be on my website.
So what's interesting is that kind of social spatial metaphor is obviously
what's going on in terms of why film high shots and low shots work. So when
the camera is above the character it mimics being spatially above and
therefore socially above the character and the reverse when the camera is below.
So when the person is socially below you obviously it makes them look
weak and socially above you obviously it makes them look strong.
So we can't normally control cameras to this extent in a video game, but what we can do
is we can set up the spaces in order to create the same storytelling.
So here we can simply create the space
so that the character is simply above
or below other characters.
And for us in video games,
this is an area rich with potential as well.
3D games are so fundamentally spatial
that we really have a lot to play with here.
So next under cognition, so we're talking all about neuroscience and psychology in this section.
Next we have the concept of peak shift. So before I go into peak shift though, I want to talk first
about caricature. So caricature is when we take the features of somebody and we exaggerate the
features that are different to normal. So Lincoln's ears are bigger than average ears,
and so the caricaturist has made them even bigger.
and often this kind of caricature can be easier to read, especially quickly and at a glance,
compared to far more realistic representations. So the science of peak shift explains why that's
the case, but first we don't just get this kind of visual hyperbole just in caricature.
So an example in art would be something like this Indian statue from the 19th century.
Here what the artist has done is they've taken the difference between a male and female figure
and they've exaggerated those differences. So in the same way you could immediately tell that that
was a picture of Lincoln, here you can immediately tell that you're looking at a statue of a woman
rather than a man.
So in in-game example, so this is GTA V DLC.
Here, we've taken the difference between somebody
with a lot of money and somebody who doesn't,
and we've exaggerated that difference.
And so by having all of this money lying around,
we can immediately see how rich and well-off the player is.
So even in the base GTA 5 game that hasn't gotten as extreme as some of the DLC,
even there what we're doing is we're focusing on the interesting bits, we're cutting out the
boring bits, and we're really concentrating on the areas that give us good storytelling.
And by doing that we're creating something that is hyper real rather than real.
So the science behind why this kind of visual hyperbole
can be easier to understand
than something that's more realistic,
the science behind that is the concept called peak shift.
So that is from the same video that I mentioned before.
He goes over a couple of different studies in this video.
There's not time to go over both of them now,
so I'm just gonna talk about one of them.
So a rat was given a square and a rectangle.
and the rectangle had more cheese,
so of course the rat started preferring
going to the rectangle.
What was interesting is when the rat was introduced
to a far more extreme rectangle,
the rat immediately preferred
going to the more extreme rectangle.
And that is because the rat didn't learn that a particular size and shape of rectangle equals
cheese. What the rat learned instead was that rectangle-ness equals cheese.
And so when it saw a more extreme rectangle, the rat assumed more cheese.
And so that is what's going on with this kind of thing here.
We don't remember that the size and we
don't remember the exact size and shape of Lincoln's ears.
Instead, we remember that they are larger than normal.
And so when that gets exaggerated,
it makes it easier to read.
And so that's why visual hyperbole
can be much easier to read and understand rather
than being purely realistic.
So next under cognition, so this section is all about neuroscience and psychology. Next we have
gestalt, but before I get into gestalt I want to talk first about affinity and contrast.
So these are concepts from film and there's more about them in this book here.
and what affinity and contrast are.
So affinity is when things are similar
and a contrast is when they're different.
Affinity can be used to communicate
social cohesion and bonding
and contrast can be used to communicate conflict.
So here in this still from Edward Scissorhands,
we have a lot of similarity and therefore affinity
with all of these suburban houses
and so that communicates social cohesion there.
whereas we have a lot of contrast with the house on the hill and so that
communicates conflict with the house on the hill. So reading about Gestalt
psychology this is very obviously the science behind why affinity and contrast
is working.
So Gestalt psychology is all about how we understand things as a whole rather than as parts.
So how is it that we understand that that tiger is a single tiger behind the bushes
rather than seeing that as a whole load of kind of smaller orange-colored objects?
So that is all through the laws of Gestalt.
There are quite a lot of those laws.
I'm just going to mention three here.
So we have the law of similarity,
the law of continuity, and the law of closure.
So the law of similarity helps us to see all those different patches between the bushes
as belonging to the same thing because all of those patches are a similar color, texture,
and pattern, and so on. The laws of continuity and closure help us see the edge of the tiger's back
as a continuous curve.
And so with those and the other laws of Gestalt,
we can see that that is one whole object,
a single tiger behind the bushes.
And so that is obviously what's going on here
with affinity and contrast,
what the brain is doing
with all the different suburban houses
because they're so similar,
is treating them like the different patches of the tiger,
and it's tying them together
and saying they belong to each other.
And whereas the house on the hill,
because that's so different,
it's treating that like the bushes
that were in front of the tiger,
and it's separating them out
and treating them as something separate.
So to sum up the cognition section,
so associations was all about synesthesia
and the connections we make in the brain.
and that was the science behind why tropes and metaphors work.
Spatial metaphors, that was about how the brain has co-opted the infrastructure that was
developed in order to understand and navigate the physical environment,
and it now uses it to understand and navigate the social environment.
Peak shift was the science behind caricature and visual hyperbole,
and gestalt was the science behind affinity and contrast.
So next we're going to talk about some aspects of the overall structure of our visual storytelling,
starting with layouts.
So there are two aspects that are important here, the layout of the form and the layout of the path.
So the layout of the form is going to affect the player's mental model of a space,
and the layout of the path is going to affect their experience over time.
So some examples of layout of the form.
So these all come from this book here,
which is a fantastic book by the way.
So we have a centralized layout, a linear layout,
radial, clustered, and grid-like.
So a centralized layout is something like this.
Linear, like this.
Radial, similar to linear, except there are multiple arms.
Clustered looks like this.
and grid-like is similar to clustered except more ordered.
Now the layout of the path is not completely dictated by the layout of the
form. For example, if we look at something
like this, a centralized layout, we can imagine a number of different
path layouts in it. So we could imagine taking a radial path,
a more grid-like path, or a linear path through that space.
So obviously a linear path through these three different forms, so a linear path that goes
around a centralized form, versus a linear path that goes along a linear form, versus a linear
path that meanders through a clustered form, those linear paths are going to feel very,
very different because of the different forms. And this is because the layout of the form
is dictating our mental model of the space, whereas the layout of the path is dictating
our experience over time. So it's the two of these together which creates the overall structure of
the experience for the player. So there are a few different types of layouts of path,
so just a few examples here. Linear, circular, radial, clustered and grid-like.
So it can be hard to make something that is rich and complex working just from first principles.
So my advice here would be to look at reference and look at perspectival reference as well as
plans and sections. So because you get different information from each of those different types
of reference. Also you're not looking here at the dressing and the details and the textures
and so on.
Instead, you're mentally stripping that away and you're just looking at the spatial design.
And so what you can do is you can look for inspiration here for the kind of experience
you want the player to have and combine that with your direction in terms of the layout of the
space and the layout of the, sorry, the layout of the form and the layout of the player path.
So next under structure, we have intensity.
So it's very important to vary the intensity over the time
because a consistently high level of intensity
will get overwhelming for the player
and a consistently low level will be boring.
So you need to vary your intensity
in order to make a rich experience for the player.
Now, the final intensity that the player experiences will be a mixture.
It will come from a mix of the environment, art, with the gameplay and the narrative.
So you could imagine a situation like here,
where we have a very serene environment,
and it's mixed with incredibly intense gameplay,
and so the player's experience is going to be very intense.
And of course, we could also imagine the reverse,
where you get a very intense environment,
but the gameplay is very calm.
That is still going to result in a more intense experience
than having calm gameplay in a calm environment.
So in terms of where and how we can increase visual intensity,
so we can do that through affinity and contrast. So the more contrast you have in an environment,
the higher the level of intensity will be.
And that's all from this book here.
But we can also increase intensity
just purely in the aesthetics alone.
So we can do things like have more intense colors.
We can have more intense shapes.
So angular shapes and jagged shapes
and things which are unbalanced and top-heavy,
they are going to be more intense
than square shapes and vertical shapes
and things which are very stable.
And of course, increasing density
will increase your intensity as well.
So finally, under structure,
I'm going to talk about contrast.
So as humans, we understand things through contrast.
Somebody is short compared to somebody who is taller.
Somebody is young compared to somebody who is older.
So if we want to communicate
that a particular building is very modern,
if we have that building in a sea of other modern buildings,
that meaning is going to get lost, nobody will notice.
However, if we have our modern building
in a context of buildings which are much older,
then the player will notice.
Now, it sounds very obvious when I say it.
But in practice and in the moment,
this can actually be counterintuitive.
Often the obvious thing to do
always feels like to be consistent.
However, if we're too consistent,
then we lose any contrast
and we lose some of our storytelling for the player.
This isn't just about contrast over a single visual field.
This is about contrast over time.
So there is a concept in environmental psychology
called adaptation, and that's about how we become adapted
to things over time.
So somebody who lives in a busy city will become adapted
to the faster pace of life in that busy city,
and somebody who lives in the countryside will get adapted
to the slower pace of life in the countryside.
So what that means for us, let's say we were going to do a design like this and we wanted
the players to notice how ornamental and intricate and detailed it is. However, if every other space
we've given the player looks like this, the player is going to become adapted to this level of
ornament and detail. And when the player eventually sees this space, they're simply not going to
notice how ornamental it is.
However, if every other space we've given the player beforehand looks like this,
then the player will become adapted to this level of ornament and detail, or lack of it,
and then when the player eventually gets here, it's going to seem incredibly intricate and
ornamental to the player. So to sum up the structure section,
layout was about the layout of the form and the layout of the path.
and the overall player experience comes from a mixture of both.
And with intensity, it's important to vary the intensity over time.
And with contrast, it's important to have contrast in order to communicate to the
player. And to sum up the whole talk now, so the
first section, mimesis, that was all about mimicking and copying
reality.
Semiotics was all about signs and symbols and how we communicate.
The cognition section was all about neuroscience and psychology
and then we ended on some aspects of structure.
And to remind you again...
If you would like to follow up in terms of some more books and references on this topic,
I will be putting a bibliography up on my website and I'll be putting that up for when
this goes live. So anyone looking at this early, it might not quite be up yet. So thank you very
much for listening to my talk and I hope you got a lot out of it.