Good afternoon, everyone.
Sorry about the heat.
Welcome to Practical Contract Law for Indie Developers 201
Not Scary Edition.
Or actually, Moderately Scary Edition.
Last year was Not Scary Edition.
So before we get started, I want to remind you this will
be in the vault.
And also, please fill out your session evaluations.
My name is Chris Reed, and I'm the founder of Chris Reed Law.
We're a firm that works with game developers and game
industry professionals, helping them with a wide range of
legal issues, including today's topic, which is contracts.
But before we get started, I would like, with the help of
my co-counsel, Mr. Phoenix Wright, to remind you I am not
your lawyer, and this is not legal advice.
It's legal education, and I hope it will be helpful.
My goal today is simple.
I want to help indie developers be less scared and
understand more about the common contracts that they're
going to encounter.
So, we're gonna cover some legal basics,
and then I'm gonna go over five contracts
that you're likely to run into as an indie developer.
For each contract, I'm gonna tell you when it comes up,
what you need to know about it, why you should care,
and how that gets scary if you don't,
and what terms we need to look after.
Last year for my 101 talk I estimated that we'd need
probably about this much time to go through everything you'd
need to know.
And it turns out that was an underestimate.
Just to get over contracts, we're probably going to need
about this much time.
So unfortunately, we still only have enough time for two
games of Hearthstone.
So consider this more of a tutorial.
Let's start with a couple of basics about contracts.
A contract is a voluntary agreement between two or more
parties to do something reasonably specific with an
exchange of value for something that isn't illegal.
Sorry, Dark Brotherhood.
So when do you need a contract?
This one is very simple.
Before you do anything with anyone, please remember this.
Contracts are everywhere in the game industry.
We've got the five that we're going to talk about today.
But there's also a host of other situations where you might encounter a contract and need to know about it.
I know that most people hate contracts.
You have the same opinion that Mr. Torg does.
Mostly people say they're written in legalese,
it's impossible to understand, what's wrong with lawyers,
why do they write that way?
There's probably a lot that's wrong with lawyers,
but for the programmers in the audience,
I'd say you wouldn't write crappy code
just because someone said it looked programmery.
The words are there for a reason, they do things.
Specifically, contracts help provide clarity
and predictability in a business relationship.
They also get the parties thinking and talking about things they might not have considered
just by negotiating it, which means it's less likely that there's going to be a dispute.
And if there is a dispute, having that contract provides for the worst case scenario, but
it also provides for unexpected success.
If you start making millions, if there's this runaway success, it's important what those
percentages are suddenly.
And finally, some things require a written signed agreement
to accomplish, specifically the transfer
of copyright interests.
This is incredibly important.
You can't do this with an email.
And if you don't have that contract,
you don't own that code.
Basically, contracts are a rule book
for a business relationship.
You may not need it very often,
you might not have to look at it if things are going well,
but you're gonna be really glad that it's there
if you have a dispute.
And on a related note,
my friends no longer play board games with me.
A word about boilerplate, the so-called boilerplate sections.
This is generally in the general section
at the end of a contract.
A bunch of small, boring-looking fine print.
I want to urge you not to skip it.
There's a lot of important settings in here.
Are you agreeing to arbitration?
Where do you have to go to court?
Does one side have to pay attorney's fees?
So look through this section in any contract.
And finally, some practical concerns.
My number one rule here is that contracts
don't enforce themselves.
They're not magical.
It's not Harry Potter.
You actually have to take action.
It's not going to stop someone from failing to pay you,
even if you have a good contract.
And enforcing that legally might take time and money
if there's a dispute.
And my second point here is please don't use what I like to
call Franken contracts where you get something off the
internet and then your friend sends you a contract and you
put a couple things in from there and then someone else
sends you a clause and then you say that's probably good
enough. This is often worse than having no contract
whatsoever because you're now effectively using code that
you've never read. You have no idea what it's going to do and
it may not even make sense if there's a dispute.
So let's get on to our first contract of the day,
the non-disclosure agreement, or NDA.
This is between someone disclosing
confidential information and someone receiving
confidential information.
It comes up in a couple scenarios,
perhaps if you're interviewing a contractor for a job
and you don't want them to be able to disclose info about it
if you don't hire them, and also if you
were making a confidential game pitch
and don't want them to reveal details about the game idea.
So why do we care about one of these agreements? Well, first off, it's the only way to really
protect abstract ideas and mechanics. As a note, these are things that are not protectable
under regular copyright law. It's also a good way to protect trade secrets. That's a type
of IP that covers things like customer lists or pricing models. And finally, it's just
a way to keep certain stuff secret. You know, maybe the launch date or some details about
the main character that you were hoping to save for a marketing splash.
And these can be scary. Just recently, Oculus lost a $500
million verdict in part because they were found to have breached
an NDA. These contracts have teeth just like the cock a
demon. So what do we want to put in one of these? First off, you
need to know if it's going to be a mutual NDA or a one way NDA.
Meaning are we both sharing information or is only one
person receiving that information and the other one
sharing it?
But the core of an NDA is going to be the definition of confidential information.
You're sharing some stuff.
Well, what is that stuff?
How broad is that definition?
Everything I tell you?
Or is it narrow?
And do I have to mark it?
Is it going to be saying confidential on the top of every document?
What happens if I tell you on Skype?
Do I have to email you later?
These are things you have to consider.
You then have to think about what the permitted uses are.
So what can they do with this information?
Are they signing the end age just so that they can look
over your stuff and decide if they want to work with you and
they're not allowed to use it for any other purpose?
Or is this something where you're working together and
they're going to put it into a game?
And finally, you need to know what their obligations are for
keeping it secret.
How long does it last?
Is it for a year or is this to their grave?
And who can they tell?
How narrowly do they have to keep this information from
their employees?
Finally, a couple of practical concerns.
First off, they can just say no.
Not everyone's gonna agree to sign an NDA,
so then you still have to decide if you wanna tell them.
And, like I said before, enforcing costs time and money.
It's not magical.
They're not gonna be forced to not say anything.
They could still disclose this stuff.
So let's move on to our second contract,
work for hire agreements.
These are incredibly important, and they're between a
developer and a contractor, or really anyone that's
contributing something to a game, which actually includes
the owners of a studio.
There's a related type of agreement called an invention
assignment agreement.
And the owners need to sign this, as well as contractors
signing work for hire agreements, because.
This is the agreement that allows the studio to own the IP
that's created. Brief copyright lesson. The default rule is
that if someone creates something, they own that
copyright. Meaning your artist owns the art, your sound person
owns their sound, coder owns the code. Unless you have this
exception, which is that it's work for hire and you need this
written signed agreement to accomplish that in most cases.
It also helps with some tax issues, but I would say ask
your accountant. I don't do tax.
These can absolutely lead to disasters.
I've dealt with clients who've had games pulled from Steam
and an angry former contractor with a bad
or non-existent contract did a DMCA.
I've seen very expensive fights
where they've had to pay people off.
You just wanna make sure that it's clean
and clear up front to avoid this.
So how do we make that happen?
Well, first off, we got to look at the IP rights section.
It's called work for hire agreement
because it sets up this work for hire arrangement
where the company is the owner of the IP.
You also want a little backup clause that says,
look, if for some reason a court doesn't agree to that,
then you agree to assign it.
One way or another, company owns it.
There might be an exception if an artist wants a license to display things in their portfolio,
and that's fine, but just make sure that you have some control over when they do that and what they display.
You don't want them putting art assets up before you launch the game.
Then you gotta figure out how you're gonna pay this person.
Normally, you'd pay them either hourly or maybe with milestones, maybe there's a cap,
or with rev share, which is quite popular among indies.
Let's take a little bit to talk about RevShare,
because this comes up a lot.
RevShare's fine, but you can't just say 10% of the game.
That doesn't mean anything.
You need to think of a couple of key details here.
First, 10% of what?
What is net revenue?
So what are you deducting from that?
Is this before Steam's cut, after Steam's cut?
What happens if a publisher's involved?
Those sorts of things.
Then you need to think about whether this
takes time to vest.
So are they immediately entitled to this money,
this rev share when the game comes out?
Or do they have to have earned it by working for the game
for a certain amount of time?
You need to think about which platforms are covered.
If they're working on the Steam version and you think maybe it'll be on console later
and they're not working for you, do they get console revenues as well?
And finally, which products does this cover?
Are we talking just the initial game or are we talking sequels, prequels, DLC, that kind
of thing?
This can massively change the scope of what you're paying.
Speaking of scope, you also need to have
a written statement of work that describes
the scope of work, what someone is delivering to you.
What is this contractor doing?
Not just a sentence, some art assets.
You need to list it,
because then they know how much they have to do,
and you know what qualities need to be delivered
for you to pay.
And if you're not satisfied or honestly if you need to cancel
the game, there needs to be a clear right for the developer
to terminate. You don't want to be obligated to pay people for
work you don't need. And then you're going to need to think
about what happens when you terminate them. Are you going
to pay them? Look over these things. That can lead to a big
dispute.
And next, we have a trio of very scary sounding sections
called Representations, Warranties, and Indemnities.
Basically, this just means, what are they promising,
and what happens if it's not true?
Specifically, you're gonna wanna make sure
that this is about intellectual property infringement.
They promise that they didn't steal this stuff from Disney,
and if they did and Disney sues you,
they're the one that's on the hook.
The contractor's on the hook.
And that's doubly important because as a developer,
if you do a development agreement for a third party
or you have a publishing agreement,
you're going to end up making this exact same promise
to your publisher.
And it needs to be true.
And finally, sometimes you'll see non-compete
and non-solicitation clauses in one of these.
Some people don't like them.
Some states won't enforce them if they're very broad.
But be aware that they could be there.
So let's move on to development agreements,
which I just mentioned.
This is often between a client
who is paying for development
and the development studio that they're hiring.
It's gonna come up sometimes when a publisher
foots the bill and it's more of a hybrid model,
but more often for indies, they might be hired
just to make some money by say, Cartoon Network.
They want you to make a game.
Okay, great, so why would you need
a development agreement?
Well, because this game could take you a year,
two years to make, and it's gonna ensure
that you get paid while you're doing that.
It's also gonna make sure that you know
exactly how much work you're signing up for.
This is one of the ways that studios go under.
First off, they get a project that ends up
taking twice as long and they don't get paid
a single cent more, which could sink you.
Or I've seen studios go down when they had
a project canceled right in the middle
and they had to fight to get paid
what they were already owed from that project
and they had to look for new work.
So we can avoid this.
First off, a familiar face, intellectual property rights.
In an agreement like this, probably the client
is hiring you to make the game for them.
So they're gonna end up owning the rights.
That's fine, but with two key exceptions.
First off, you don't assign these rights
until you get your final check. And that way you have leverage if they decide that they don't
want to pay you. Which can be very important practically. Another important thing that you
need to have in this section is what's called developer tools. This is an ownership right that
you have and what I would call your special sauce. So basically engines, code libraries,
know-how that you've developed while working on this game that you might use in your own games
in the future or in future projects.
you want to state that the company that you're working for
doesn't get to own this. They get a license and the developer
keeps ownership of this. That way they can never stop you from
using it in the future and in fact they can't even reverse
engineer it.
Next, you want to know how you're getting paid. That's why
you're doing this, right? So you're probably going to get
paid some flat fee for the project, but you want to make
sure that some of that's up front. Ideally 50 percent if you
can swing it. And then you're going to get paid the rest in
milestones as you deliver the content. So first playable
alpha, beta, that sort of thing.
Make sure that there are clear terms as to when you've
delivered.
They can't just sit on it for three weeks and then tell you
they don't like it.
Five days.
And if they don't tell you, then it's deemed accepted.
That's the kind of thing you want.
If there's rev share, make sure we do all the same sort of
math that we did before when we talked about rev share.
You've got to think about those details.
And you also again have to think about scope of work.
This could be a big project.
You need a game design document, tech specs,
that list the features you're developing.
Not just what the features are, but how many.
Are you doing five levels or 50 levels?
Two character models or 20?
That's a big difference.
And to go with this section.
You want a section that allows for what are called change
orders, meaning if they want more stuff outside the scope,
they have to sign an agreement that says they're going to pay
you more money.
You tell them how much it costs.
And if they don't want to sign that, you
don't have to do it.
This prevents what's called scope creep.
And that can be the death of a studio, death by 1,000 cuts.
Clients don't understand game development.
They think it takes two minutes to change something.
Really, it takes two weeks.
So this protects you.
And likewise, you are protected by a good termination section.
You need to be able to get out of a bad deal
if someone is not paying you.
So you should have an ironclad right
to get out of the agreement if you have a late payment
and the right to claim what you're still owed.
Additionally, your client is probably going to want to know
if they can have the right to terminate for convenience.
What this means is essentially they need to stop the project
because match threes aren't hot anymore,
whatever they decide.
That's fine, but you want to make sure that you're going to
get paid a kill fee.
That means they're going to pay you a flat amount that you
agree to, or maybe all of the next milestone.
This gives you a cushion so that you're not caught with no
money when you're looking to find a new
project for the studio.
And finally, I told you you'd see reps and warranties again.
They're definitely going to make sure that you promise the
whole game you deliver is free of infringing material.
And for that to be true, you've got to make sure that
you've signed all those work for hire agreements.
They're also going to make sure that you don't have any
Easter eggs hidden in the game.
They do not like hidden features ever since the GTA 3
hot coffee issue.
So make sure that you disclose this, because you could be on
the hook if there's liability there.
So some practical concerns about development agreements.
If you're not getting paid, don't wait.
Contracts don't enforce themselves.
You need to speak up for yourself
and assert the rights you have.
So give them notice of breach
as soon as they have a late payment.
Stop working, don't do work for free.
And if it's the last payment,
don't hand over the code
until they've given you that final check.
To politely paraphrase one of my fellow lawyers,
F you, pay me.
So let's move on to publishing agreements, which I'm sure
you're all familiar with.
It's between a publisher and a developer
with respect to a game.
These come up basically if the publisher's funded development,
which is sort of the old school AAA model.
You still see that.
And then it's more of a development
publishing agreement.
But a lot of indies end up with a mostly finished game.
And they need a publisher just for things like distribution
or marketing or help with QA and that sort of thing.
So why do we care about a publishing agreement?
Well, if you have a publishing deal,
you want to define how broad the publisher's license is,
how you're getting paid on your game,
because it's your game,
and what exactly the publisher's actually doing for you.
These can easily get scary.
Games can get stuck in limbo with a publisher
that doesn't care about them and no way to get out.
I have had, for example, two clients who both came to me
wanting to get out of publishing deals
with the same publisher.
One of them got out, I sent a single email, took one day.
The other one, it took months and they had to pay a lot.
And the difference was a single sentence
that was in the termination section.
So, let's make sure we know which terms to look out for.
By now, I think you can all guess what is coming first.
IP rights.
You want to make sure, A, that you're not assigning
the rights to your game.
So if you're assigning the copyright, that means you've
sold the game.
They own it now.
And also make sure there aren't any sort of gotchas
where if you're late, they suddenly own your game.
But if it's just a license for them to sell your game,
that's not good enough to say it's a license.
You need to know a lot of things about how broad this is.
So first, how long does that license last?
Forever?
One year?
How broad is it geographically?
You may not want the same publisher in China that you
have in the EU.
They may have different connections.
And then you need to know which platforms it covers.
Does your publisher know anything about mobile?
Then why are they entitled to publish you on mobile?
And finally, and this is huge.
Which products is it covering?
Is it just your game?
Or are we talking about sequels, prequels, DLC?
Or maybe we're even talking about games that you make
later that have nothing to do with this game.
I have seen all of that sneak its way into the IP right
section, so have a close look at that.
Also have a close look at how you are getting paid.
Normally, this is done in a publishing agreement as
revenue share.
You'll see 30-70 in favor of the developer as the standard.
I don't buy that as a standard.
I think that you should argue for every percentage point,
and that they should justify what they're doing for you.
But as it's going to be revenue share, you need to
think about all the things we talked about before.
But you also need to consider one additional key point, which
is recoupable expenses.
So your publisher may say, hey, we're
going to give you an advance to finish the game.
We're going to spend x thousand dollars on marketing.
Great.
But if those are listed as recoupable expenses,
it means they're going to get paid back before you see a cent.
So now your 30-70 split is as, you know.
is 100 zero percent split in their favor and you don't see
money for a while. You can negotiate this and you can make
sure you know which things are recoupable. Next, make sure the
publisher is actually promising to do specific things. I see
this all the time. It drives me nuts. The developer's
obligation section is like one sentence that says we're going
to, you know,
publish and promote the game. That doesn't tell you anything.
They should be telling you how much money they're going to
spend on marketing. And if they're not going to tell you
that, they should be delivering a detailed marketing plan that
you have approval rights over. They should be telling you
things like are they going to be flying you to GDC in packs? Are
they going to put you in the booth? Are they going to pay for
that? How often are they going to put you on the website? You
need to know these things. They should be promising specific
stuff. Because you're giving them your game and they're
taking a cut.
And finally, if they're not doing a good job,
you need an escape hatch.
The termination clause that I talked about before.
Ideally, you want the ability to walk away
with 30 days notice.
But if they're not okay with that,
at least limit the time that they have this license for.
Try them out for a year and then renegotiate.
Or you could ask them to guarantee
a certain amount of revenue per year.
They said they'll make it a hit.
If they can't do a good job, then kick them to the curb.
They shouldn't be your publisher.
Finally, some practical concerns.
It's not 1993.
You don't need a publisher.
But if you do have a publishing arrangement, you
definitely need a contract.
And you need to make sure that they earn their percentage and
get out if you're not happy.
Our final contract today, End User License Agreements, or
EULAs, this is between a developer and your players.
You need to have it in place before anyone downloads and installs or uses your game,
and that includes your beta testers. And look, I know that nobody cares about EULAs. You
basically have the same opinion as the Doom guy has of expository dialogue. Get out of
my way, let's get going. But these are important because they're the only way you're going
to impose legal obligations on your players with respect to your game. And that's the
way that you're able to control what liability you might have.
They can easily get scary. Users can and do sue game developers and publishers, as famously happened with Linden Labs and Second Life.
So what do we put in one of these things that nobody reads?
Well, first off, it's a license agreement.
It's not a sale.
You're not selling a copy of the game.
You are selling a license to use it as long as they play by
the rules.
You can then set some of those rules.
You need to make sure that players aren't doing things
like uploading malicious code, hacking, impersonating the
server, doing hate speech, griefing people.
All of these can be laid out in your EULA.
It's also a good place to talk about IP rights.
Make sure you know and that they know
that the developer owns the game.
If they don't have a license to steal your stuff.
But you might want to let them use it for machinima
or for streaming and that's fine,
but you need to be able to impose rules
so that you can stop it if they're doing something
that's offensive with your game.
Likewise, if your game involves user-generated content,
as many games do, either people uploading things that are
their own or creating within the game, you've got to think
about two things.
One, wrap some warranties again.
Make sure they promise that they're not uploading
copyrighted material.
You don't want to be on the hook for that.
And two, you should have a think about whether the
company owns what they create or the player owns it.
If the player owns it, great.
But.
you want to make sure the developer has a right to use it,
because it's going to be on their servers.
You might want to use it for things like future development
or marketing campaigns.
So you should have that license in there.
Likewise, if you have virtual items or currency in your game,
it needs to be crystal clear
that these are not real property.
They only exist in these people's accounts
and you can delete them
if they break the terms of the license.
Sorry, not sorry.
Okay. Finally, or penultimately, you might want to put age
restrictions in if your game has adult content or if there are
privacy concerns as we talked about last year in the 101. And
lastly, this is the place where you limit your liability. You
need to disclaim certain things. Limit how much you can be sued
for. Explain that you're not guaranteeing anything about the
game, that it's going to be the best game ever, that multiplayer
is always available, that the servers will be eternal, that
sort of thing.
And of course, you really need to address zombies, the most
important part of the EULA.
What happens if organized civilization collapses due to
a zombie infestation?
Well, I would ask that you look at the Amazon web service
terms for lumberyard for a good example
of how to handle this.
This is real.
So finally, some practical concerns on EULAs.
Third parties like Apple and Steam will require you
to put certain language in your EULA
and forbid you from having certain things.
And lastly, make sure that they actually click through.
I know, I know, crazy.
Some people don't read the EULA, insane.
But you need to be able to show that they clicked I accept
each time that you update it,
because that could be a barrier to enforcing it
if there's a dispute.
So, we've reached the end here.
What have we learned?
Well, I need a time machine so I can advise
my six-year-old self not to sign this contract
that my brother provided me with.
And in all seriousness though,
if I leave you with one thing,
don't cut corners on contracts.
I know it seems like that's something that's for later,
but it is so much cheaper to get this taken care of
in advance than to deal with a rolling dumpster fire later,
which basically might not be able to be fixed.
I want to thank my paralegal for all his help.
And with that, we're at the end.
I'd be happy to take some questions now
and in the spillover room,
and please make sure to fill out your session evaluations.
Thank you very much.
Really quick, on behalf of a friend of mine
who's starting something new,
better to have a verbal agreement
or to scratch things on a piece of paper
if you can't afford a lawyer?
It's definitely better, I mean,
the answer is it's better to talk to a lawyer,
but to the extent you can think through
some of the things I talked about
and try to put it in writing,
that's always gonna be better
as long as you've thought through that writing.
Because...
If it's an oral agreement, you're just not going to remember.
Both sides will think they remember,
and they'll remember different things.
But there's a lot that people don't think about.
So yeah, better to have it in writing, but much, much better
to have a formal contract.
Yeah.
So if you get rid of a contractor
before you even finish signing the contract phase,
but they've actually done one round, which you don't use,
can they later come back and make a claim?
So, well first off, anyone can make a claim.
No, and that's not just a technical point,
because I've dealt with situations
where people who basically have no legal rights
make a stink, right?
And those practical problems are real.
They cost time and headache and money,
but you're gonna make it less likely
that they come back angry if there was an agreement,
because then they can look at it and be like,
oh right, I don't own this.
You can always try and fix it retroactively.
I mean, basically what's happening is
if people work without a contract.
you're taking on risk that they might become angry. If you don't use any of the stuff that
they created, you're probably fine, but there's always the chance that something else that's in
there was inspired by it and they'll make an argument that it's a derivative work, so it's
better just to have the contracts. Yeah.
For enforcing the EULAs, is it sufficient to just show that the code or that the process
requires them to click through the EULA or is there some kind of record that needs to be
maintained?
I just realized I'm supposed to repeat the question.
So the question was, for making the EULA enforceable,
is it good enough to basically just show that there's code
and that you have a flag that resets
when it's a new version?
Or do you need to really show that they clicked?
I think that, so this is mostly going to come up
if you're actually in litigation.
The only time it's really going to matter
is if a judge is deciding, is this an enforceable contract?
And the reason that there's an issue here
is that normal contracts, you sign between two parties,
so you can show they talked about it and then they signed.
A EULA is kind of a take it or leave it,
and so that's already on thin ice, legally speaking.
So you really want to make it clear that there was no way they installed this without being
aware of it and making it clear that you're supposed to agree. In fact, at the top of
the EULA, there's usually really bold text just to double check to say, this is a license
you don't own the game, don't install it if you don't agree. So that you can argue that
even someone who just kind of looked at it has to have known. There was no way they could
have avoided that with their eyeballs. That's what you want to be able to show.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Okay, so I'm a freelancer and I sign contracts all the time,
but I never write them myself.
And the truth is I wouldn't know what to write
if I had to start one myself.
So the question is, is there any resources
or like any templates, any place that it's like,
if I had to start a contract myself, I have a guide.
So the question was, if you're a contractor
and you need resources to figure out
how to approach creating your own contract,
presumably because you don't want to go get a lawyer,
don't have time, what are those resources?
That's a tough question for me,
because I'm torn between wanting everyone
to do the right thing and have these contracts in place,
but
you can screw them up if you kind of do a hack job of them.
I'm not going to lie, of course there are people post
contracts online all the time. Some of these sites are better.
If there is something that actually has comments on it that
explains what's going on and it looks relatively professional,
that's probably less sketchy. But I don't want to tell you to
use stuff off the internet. It's easy to become a franking
contract. And a lot of my worst
scenarios that I've had to deal with come from,
oh, we've got a contract, and then I look at it,
and it's, you know, it doesn't even apply
to the situation they're using it in,
and so it actually makes both sides think
that they totally have rights that they don't.
So.
I don't have a clean answer for you there, unfortunately.
OK, so is your suggestion just a lawyer, basically?
Yeah, if you can get a lawyer.
Again, it's not like you're going
to have to have them draft it from scratch every time.
When I do a work for hire agreement for a studio,
it's not going to be like I spend two hours every time.
They're going to get a form.
you know, put the settings the way they like it,
and then slight tweaks depending on
how they're gonna pay different people.
But it pays, if you do a lot of work,
it pays to get a form once,
where you've talked to a lawyer and said,
look, here's what I want, here's the protections I want,
what should I be thinking about?
And then you can use that going forward, right?
And that's sort of a tool,
it's like buying a copy of Photoshop
or something like that, right?
Okay, thank you very much.
Yeah, no worries.
The whole get a lawyer thing makes a ton of sense for all the contract work if we're just a small
Studio for the EULA is that something that's a lot more approachable from like a template or you know hey
This is what everyone on Steam does sure so
The chances that you're going to have a large litigation based
on your game, well, it depends on what the game is
and how big it is and what the features are, right?
If it's multiplayer and there's all this virtual currency
and people are putting in micropayments,
you can see there's probably a lot more risk than if it's
this couch co-op game.
rule that applies to all of this. Obviously scale what you can do to your budget. And
EULAs, yeah, there are some fairly just cut and dry very simple EULAs. The biggest thing
is just have the limitations on liability. Make clear that it's a license. All that other
stuff I talked about, though, you should think about it if your game has those features.
Yeah, it's not top priority.
If you're a small studio, top priority is having those work
for hire agreements, making sure you own the IP, and not
signing random publishing agreements without reading
them.
But all of it's important.
It's just, yeah.
There's triage.
Yeah, Yule is probably not as important if
your game's simple.
Thanks.
The whole idea that these things are not magic
and you need a lawyer sounds great,
but how do I find a good lawyer who can respect
an indie's budget and actually know something about games?
Sure, so the question was, it sounds great to say
contracts aren't magical, get a lawyer,
but what do you do on an indie budget
to find a lawyer that understands that indies
don't just have piles of money, to paraphrase.
So two things, one I would say that
As far as them not enforcing themselves,
some of that advice is actually just about
once you have the contract,
remember to stick up for your rights that you have.
And as far as finding a lawyer that will respect
the fact that you're an Indy,
I would talk to them.
I do initial consultations.
I think most other attorneys do things like that.
I would ask them hard questions and say,
look, we're an indie, are you okay with this?
Are you flexible?
That sort of thing.
And make sure they understand the game industry
and they're not just like sort of a general contract lawyer.
So I maybe don't spend as much time with lawyers as you do.
Where would I find them?
Well, I am one.
So you found one.
Is it good to have someone local to where you live,
though, so you can meet in person?
Sure.
So there are a mix of topics.
The question was, is it good to have someone local?
To what extent do you need that?
And where do you find them?
Right, so as far as finding them, I would say Google.
Most attorneys are going to put their name out there
and advertise what they work on
and what their practice area is.
As far as locality, there are some,
lawyers in the US anyway are licensed to specific states,
but a lot of what I talked about
is general principles of contract law.
There might be small differences between states,
but.
a work for hire agreement's gonna look the same
in almost every state.
And things like IP are federal law.
So if you're forming a business though,
probably get a local business lawyer.
You know, you don't have to,
you probably don't want to use someone
from a different state.
Okay, I swear this is my last one.
Yes.
Are there like professional organizations maybe
that specialize in games and indie game development?
Like, is there a place I can go?
Because I have tried Google and even Bing.
Like, I've tried many search engines.
What?
And I still don't have a great answer.
AltaVista perhaps?
HotBot?
Excuse me?
Ask friends in other studios. I get whatever it is all the time.
Yeah, and I would say that, I mean,
I would say, normally the answer would be
go to the bar association, but
They don't really know a lot of people who do what I do.
The truth is there should be more of us for the game
industry given its size.
But yeah, I would ask around if there's any kind of like the
local IGDA might have connections.
I know I'm involved in that.
I'm involved in an organization that Indies work
with called PlayCrafting that's in New York.
So like lawyers, if they're in the industry, they're going to
be enmeshed with the developer community.
So you can ask through that.
Sure, okay, we have time for one more
and then I'll take the rest and the spillover.
Hello, you briefly mentioned like independent contractor
versus employee classification issues and you've said it was
Very briefly.
And you said it was kind of outside your wheelhouse.
Who would you talk to in more detail about that?
What kind of person am I looking for?
Sure, so.
Easy two answers.
One, talk to your accountant, a tax person,
someone who understands tax.
Could be a tax attorney or just like a CPA.
And businesses definitely need a tax person.
Two, I just want to note a tiny bit more detail.
It matters, the difference for tax purposes.
This contract cannot magically make them
an independent contractor.
A lot of indies want to classify them
because if they're an employee,
it means that there's other obligations,
paying taxes, that sort of thing.
The fact that you write,
this person is definitely an independent contractor,
doesn't naturally make it so.
There's a lot of things,
so basically the IRS is gonna say,
okay, that's nice to know.
I'll take that into consideration,
but I'm gonna look at these six other things.
Does it look like you're treating them that way?
So just be aware of that
and definitely talk to an accountant.
Okay, all right, so we'll.
CPA or tax attorney. Someone who knows tax. Thank you very much.
I'm happy to go to the spillover room.