Okay.
Let's do this.
["The Star-Spangled Banner"]
You
Well, we had a lot of water on Uncharted 3.
This talk is about creating the flood effects in Uncharted 3.
I've been Cook.
I work at Naughty Dog.
A little bit about me.
I've been in the industry for about 11 years.
Most of that has been at Electronic Arts, working on
Medal of Honor, and then Naughty Dog, working on the
Uncharted series.
And now I'm working on The Last of Us, our new game,
Naughty Dog, which looks really exciting.
Um, let's see, uh, before all that, I studied graphic design,
um, with a minor in computer science at the Uni- University
of North Texas, and, uh, that computer science minor is
becoming more and more valuable, uh, as a, affects artists in
games, um, and I think it's gonna continue, uh, in that
direction for sure. So, in Uncharted, we did lots of kinds
of water, we did puddles, we did waterfalls.
oceans and floods, which is what we're gonna talk about today.
Uh, first of all I just wanted to give a shout out to the
Naughty Dog engineers because they really do an amazing job at,
um, eking all the performance out of, uh, the PS3 that's
possible and, uh, we really couldn't get the, the level of
visual quality that we get without their amazing work. So,
first shout out.
And this is the effect we're going to be looking at today.
So as an artist, I look back on this,
and I still just feel like there's something missing.
It's kind of hard to put my finger on it, but maybe
it's Subway sandwich.
$5 for one.
So to make the effect we started with a fluid sim.
We did a pretty coarse fluid sim inside of Houdini.
And we were able to iterate pretty quickly
and use it as pre-visualization to work out timing
and the flow and the amount of water
and all those details pretty rapidly
without having to go back and forth into the game.
But it wasn't just for pre-visualization.
We ended up using it throughout the whole production
of the effect.
We created the in-game mesh from the simulation.
We also looked at the simulation for inspiration
on where the particles should be spraying,
and the direction, and speed, and all of that.
And finally, we used the actual SIM data to push the rigid
bodies, all the debris in the hallway, all the boxes and
things, those are pushed along by the actual SIM data.
And since the mesh came from the SIM data, the particles
were inspired by the SIM data, and then the rigid bodies were
pushed by it.
It all kind of comes together and it matches.
So to create the mesh, we had a
we had to figure out how we were going to do this because the
surface obviously has to morph constantly. Um, we considered
possibly doing a point cache, but, um, quickly rejected that
idea, um, because it would require a lot of new tech that
we just didn't want to invest the time in building. Um, we
did a first attempt, uh, which, um, was more programmatic and
parametric.
in nature where it was allowing us to basically glide bumps across the surface.
We abandoned that because it was very hard to work with as an artist and we just couldn't
get the level of fidelity that we wanted.
And so we decided to go with the brute force method, which was
essentially to do skeletal meshes, because our engine
supports skeletal meshes really well, and to do one joint per
vertex. The engineers actually were able to increase our joint
count to about 580 joints per mesh, which wasn't quite enough
to get the entire flood, but...
I'll cover that in a bit.
In order to optimize, fortunately we had sort of a
fixed camera angle.
We knew that the camera was going to be tracking away from
the flood itself, looking back at it.
And so instead of using a mesh of squares, I elongated those.
So if you look at it top down, they're actually rectangles,
which allowed me to cut out about a third, or two thirds
actually, of the.
the points and therefore the joints
that were gonna be required.
And when you're looking at it head on
because of the way perspective kind of squishes it all
it looks like a uniformly covered mesh.
So we used a ray casting method
to kind of extract a surface from the fluid sim.
This was also done in Houdini.
But sort of the default.
way that you would do a ray cast is to just cast along the normals of the surface.
And in this case, that would be just going completely vertically up.
And that was going to cause some problems, some artifacts that we didn't like.
And so I experimented with casting the rays more in the direction of the camera.
And that actually solved a lot of our problems.
So you can see here with this diagram that...
casting rays along the normal in that striped area, that's
creating an error where there's meant to be an overhang, but
there's actually just a wall. And the camera is looking, you
know, right at that and it looks horrible. So changing the
direction that we're casting from to face the camera a bit
more, it reduces the errors altogether because of the way
the water is kind of shaped. But also the errors are more hidden
from the camera.
So that really helped the look.
So, like I said before, there were more than 580 points
required for this half-led, so had to actually like
make three separate meshes that were all driven
by their own skeletons.
And because...
that gets a bit tedious to work with.
I created a little tool that would allow us to
treat the entire surface as one thing,
even though it's in the game.
According to the game data,
it's actually three separate things.
And it allows us to build it all as one thing,
and it really cuts down on the iteration time.
It's not as important on this one because it was only three meshes, but we use this technique in other parts of the game
including like in some sand simulations with flowing sand and
It became more valuable there because some of those surfaces were like 12 to 14 separate patches
which
Would just be insane to to iterate on if you're doing it all by hand
So here's what it looks like with just the surface and no
shader on it.
It's a little bit dark on this display, but you can see a
little bit how it's morphing.
So the surface shader, we use sort of our standard water
shader that we used throughout the game and
other types of water.
It's a really big shader and it has lots of features, but
these are some of the relevant ones for this effect.
does refraction, which basically takes a copy of the screen buffer and it distorts the UV lookup
based on the normal. So the normal will change where it's going to look at the screen texture,
and then also the depth. So the deeper the water is, the further away from the
screen pixel that it would show without refraction.
the further from that it gets.
So it gets more distorted the deeper it is.
And then there's also opacity based on depth
that helps it to look like there's particulate in the water.
So where it's deeper, it gets more opaque.
And then for reflection, the surface changes so much
and it's anything but a flat plane.
So doing real-time reflections wasn't really an option.
But the cube map was totally adequate.
So we did that with Fresnel to make it a stronger reflection
on glancing angles, sort of standard reflection stuff.
And then lastly we did foam on the surface,
which just kind of helps it look a bit more churned up.
Here it is with the surface shader.
So it really lacks a lot of the visceral quality
that it needed to have if you wanted the player
to feel like he's really being chased away
by this giant deluge of water.
So that actually came from the particles.
Particles ended up being just the real,
the really important part of the effect.
The surface was sort of secondary.
We ended up doing 31 separate emitters that were all hand
keyframe animated to match the animation of the water.
And eight different particle definitions, so eight
different types of particles that those
emitters were emitting.
So at Naughty Dog, we have a really great tool set and run
time to go along with it.
Our UI is all done through Maya.
and we share a lot of the same features that, um, Maya particles have. Um, one thing we can do
that's really useful is create custom attributes so we can store off any kind of, uh, date
custom data that we want.
And we can give those data values using expressions.
And expressions are huge.
If you're unfamiliar with expressions,
you should get familiar with them
and beg your programmers to add it to your tool set
because it's super flexible.
It allows you to manipulate data
pretty much any way you want.
Our expressions are really similar to Maya's expressions.
can even piggyback off of Maya's like, um, syntax error
detection and all that. Um, so if you know Maya expressions,
you pretty much know Naughty Dog expressions. And then we have
the ability to use ramps, um, create gradients basically, and
um, we can use our custom attributes as indices into the
ramp, so we can pick where on the ramp we want to pull a color
or value.
um using the custom attributes and we can define those through expressions so it all
comes together and gives you a lot of power. And then we can also send these custom attributes
to the shader uh which allows you to further um control the way the effect looks by controlling
shader attributes and stuff like that. Um so it's all very powerful and then one of the other
cool features I mean there's a lot of them but this is just.
One last one I wanted to mention is custom orientation.
So our sprites don't necessarily have to face the camera,
and they don't necessarily have to be velocity aligned.
We can use our custom attributes and define
vectors that will orient the particles any way we want.
Super flexible.
It's really nice.
And all of this is due to Marshall Robin.
He's pretty much the.
lone programmer at Naughty Dog who does all the effects stuff.
He's really incredible. He has a talk today at 2.30 in room 309.
So go to that if you want to learn more about uncharted effects.
From a more programmer-y technical perspective.
So, um, as every game effects artist is aware, fill rate is the enemy number one. So...
We do a couple of things to get around the fill rate problem
and allow us to draw a lot more particles, which
in this effect gives it the really full, frothy look
at the front of the wave.
We render our particles to a quarter res buffer.
So already we're drawing one quarter of the pixels.
So that's a big gain.
And then with most of the effects that we do,
they're roughly round shaped.
and the corners of a quad are usually completely transparent.
So we just chop them off and make octagons instead of quads.
And it's a good trade-off between number of points
and number of pixels drawn because pixel,
we're usually fill rate bound.
So that's a really nice win as well.
So the main particle that you notice in the effect
is the froth particle.
Uh, this, these are the color and alpha, uh, maps used for the froth particle.
Uh, they're based on source photography done by a colleague of mine
at Naughty Dog named Ikki Ikram.
He's a great photographer.
I love photos by ikki.com.
Um, and then to get more variation, uh, we had four, um, different, uh, looks
and just the color and alpha, and then to get.
more variety, we just smush around the UVs using this color
texture map. And then the other main feature of the shader is
sparkles. Before I added the sparkles, it really did look
like flat, dry cards. It still had a real, um, kind of a
lively motion to it and stuff like that, but it didn't really feel like water.
But just adding little glints of light really helped a lot, and that was achieved with this on the left of the
it's like a black field with sparse white dots, and then that's multiplied by a
uniform noise that's scrolled across it, and it ends up just making it twinkle basically.
So
Um, the quarter res buffer, um, buys us a lot, um, back in
terms of, uh, fill rate, but, um, it also is half, or a
quarter of the resolution, so it's, it makes things look a
lot more fuzzy. So to combat that, um, I did custom mip
maps. I took the, um, alpha and the color texture into
Photoshop and down sampled using nearest neighbor, uh,
filtering, which.
gives it a much better histogram. The lower image, the
lower standalone image is the nearest neighbor sampled one and
the top one is, is bilinear filtering and you can see that
there's just higher contrast and a sharper image. So I recommend
doing that if you're, if your engine supports it. This is what
it looks like inside our previewer, our material
previewer. One thing to note is that the sparkles on this, the
scale of them is not correct.
That's because the scale is controlled by a user variable
that's passed from the particle.
So when I was showing you the particle UI,
and you had the ability to pass data to the shader,
that's, this is one of the things that's affected by that.
So when you run the effect in the game,
the sparkles are smaller, not so big and blobby.
So Keith Garrett.
He was the lead effects artist on Uncharted 3,
and he's doing a talk that'll cover more of our
techniques and tricks that we use for shaders
if you're interested in that.
Go hit that one up.
So here it is with just particles.
The particle lighting turned out to be really huge.
Um, it really sits it into the environment and gives it depth
and, uh, the color variation that, uh, makes it look much
more realistic. Um, you can see it looks really flat without the
particle lighting. First thing to know about the lighting is
that it was a hack. Um, we didn't really have good lighting
techniques for particles in Uncharted 3. We basically used a
lot of hacks. Um, this hack was, um, using two ramps. One ramp
ran the length of the hall.
So, the darker area at the top is sort of the back recessed
area, and then the light spots are where there's light in the
hall shining on it.
And then one across the width of it, and the two are
multiplied together.
And it basically makes sort of a low-res looking texture.
And that's projected down, straight down onto the
particles.
And the wonderful thing about this was that it was all done
with existing tech.
We didn't have to go.
to programmers and ask them to implement this kind of lighting,
which is sort of a pseudo light map kind of technique.
Just with the flexible tools that we already had,
we were able to come up with this idea
and implement it without any programmer support.
So here's the final image with lit particles.
that's pretty much it. So, Naughty Dog is hiring. Candice Walker, I think she's going to be
outside the room. You can check with her. See if there's a spot for you. There's another shout
out there. And of course I wanted to thank all of you. Appreciate you coming. And
I wanted to mention that there is a mobile evaluation and check
your spam filter in your email to make sure that you get that
and fill it out.
And at this point I can take a couple questions.
There's a couple of mics if you have questions please step up
to the mic.
starting to see a couple of people.
awesome, awesome talk. Um, question I have is, um, Houdini is used a lot in film effects, a
lot of game guys, um, use proprietary engines. What sort of took you guys down that
route? Did you hire someone who was a Houdini expert or did you guys, um, train in it?
Basically, between Uncharted 2 and Uncharted 3, I started
learning Houdini because I knew how flexible it was and how
sort of a more technically minded artist can actually
make really useful tools and stuff like that.
So I started learning that and then put it to use in
Uncharted 3.
It was basically just my call.
It was a little hard to convince them to shell out the
money for it because it's really expensive, but we got
over that hurdle.
Hi. Um what was the uh purpose for uh taking the uh oh here
sorry. Uh taking the fluid from Houdini into Maya was that just
uh because of the pipeline that you guys had for uh the joint
placements and all that? Yeah actually um uh it was a little
unclear. I we did the fluid sim in Houdini and we actually
created um the mesh with the mesh animation inside of Houdini
brought that mesh over, we left the fluid sim in Houdini,
brought the mesh over with its animation,
and then that tool that I was showing that I created
also adds all the joints at all the points
and sets it all up to be used in the game.
Okay.
I will be outside to field more questions.
Just wanted to mention that this will be in the GDC vault.