Thank you.
Yeah, so I'm Francois.
So welcome, thank you for attending this.
Just a disclaimer, so I'm heavily jet lagged
and heavily caffeinated.
So if I say something weird or very French,
just tell me and I will try to correct that.
Okay, so Rings was made by myself and a team,
very talented team, so Mieko Murakami did the art,
the very specific art of Rings,
and we had an exceptional music team
with Disasterpeace, Matteo Dugo,
and Eric von Amorongen,
who did a great work on the SFX notably.
and I did the writing and the game dev, if you want.
So I'm gonna talk about ranks.
Ranks is a swipe your own adventure.
It can be described as a mix of Tinder and Game of Thrones,
and it's a relatively accurate way to describe the game.
You play a dynasty of king taking binary decisions,
so yes or no by swiping.
And you have a double objective,
which is to rule as long as possible,
and to discover the secrets of your dynasty.
And that's the long game that you play
over centuries generally.
It's been quite successful.
So what am I gonna talk about today?
I don't know that yet, so it will be a bit dynamic, hope.
What I know for sure, it's what this talk will not be about.
So this talk is not about a list of success,
of things you have to do to make a successful indie games,
as it's not a pipe either.
I think a success is the result of a very dynamic path.
And we made good choices, but we had also a lot of luck
and probably some bias.
So I really want you to be careful
about what I'm gonna say today.
And I will need you, the audience,
to take some distance with what I'm gonna say.
So use your critical thinking,
try to extract the interesting matter
in what I'm gonna say today.
The useful information is something that's specific
to your own use and practice, but I don't know.
So that's an important point I wanted to make,
and I will start by an example.
So be careful, this is very treacherous.
For me, laziness is my goal in life.
So just like in this drawing from Valotto,
I dream of myself naked on a bed
with scratching a cat, if you want.
Because game development is a very painful enterprise.
You know that, all of you.
Where you work like hell with a very, very uncertain success.
It's not really sane nor sustainable to make games,
let's be honest about that.
What I mean by that is not that I am lazy, of course,
but my goal is to sort of search that
optimization of all my means and my design
to sort of go towards this goal of being lazy.
I'm not saying I'm lazy, we're all professionals
who spent a lot of hours on our bloody bugs
and the two pixel animation that needs to be perfect.
And I'm just like you, I do that.
But I try as much as possible to make the most
of the time I spent on game making.
And instead of, I always try to use that in a useful way.
you
I think being the most efficient sloth possible
is a very interesting drive in game making
because it's where you will find new mechanics.
You will optimize your design choices.
And optimization is not just something
that's related to game engine and code.
Optimization is also about practice
and about the way you make the game yourself as a designer.
So I will start this talk about Reigns,
around Reigns Inception, the scribbling of Reigns,
from the first sketch we made with Mieko, the artist.
So we talked about this idea of making a game
around the same mechanic as Tinder,
and the main elements of the game
were already present from the start,
so that's the first visual of Reigns.
You play a king managing a kingdom, so you have advisor.
They are coming and talking to you about the kingdom
that you never see.
You never see the cathedral.
You always see just the advisor,
and this creates a gap that we will see is interesting.
There are only two answers, yes or no,
but each one has a profound impact on the kingdom
that you see on the data at the bottom of the screen.
And that's it. And we had this from the start really.
It's like two weeks after starting the game.
This was heavily inspired by L'Edoleon from Divine
for the visuals.
And from...
by Asher also, Royals,
which was a very important inspiration.
You will see a lot of small mechanics that we used in Reigns
like a one-year turn and stuff like that.
So to give a bit of perspective to this first sketch,
I just compare it to the final game,
like one week after the release.
It's mostly the same, basically the same layout,
and as I told you, I always aim to be lazy,
so I can't just scratch everything.
But there are two interesting changes
that I want to talk about.
First, you see the data on the top of the screen
and not the bottom, like at the start.
So that's the sort of dumb test
you have to do very early in development.
So as the game was supposed to be played mostly on mobile,
when your player play on mobile,
generally he has the thumb.
if you want to swipe, the thumb is on the bottom of the screen.
So you never see the impact of the swipe
if you put your data at the bottom of the screen.
So that's a dumb test.
You have to do that very early,
just not to push that sort of bad idea too far.
The other point on this is that we scratched the numbers,
as you probably noticed.
So that was a difficult design decision
that occurred very late in the development.
For a very simple reason,
when you playtest that sort of thing.
the player will always prefer the first version
because it's easier for them to optimize their decision
if they see the impact.
But we decided against this because we noticed that
very quickly the players
stopped reading the text.
And they were just optimizing their system, if you want.
And that's not what we wanted.
We wanted to have a focus on the text,
as we will see just later.
Just after that, on writing rings.
When we first playtested the game,
I quickly noticed that players wanted to go beyond
the management side of the game,
which was the very basic version we had.
They naturally started to create links between cards
that I didn't in any way link together,
like building a cathedral and fight a plague outbreak.
So they were creating their own stories within the game.
So we decided to support that and encourage
and build basically the game on that.
So that's the writing, it has three points.
I will start by evocative writing,
which is very useful tool,
where we don't use that much in games,
and that's a shame I think.
If you see this picture, it's a still life, it's a bit boring.
It's called Breakfast Table with Blackberry Pie.
But if you look a bit more closely and you think of this painting as a scene in a game,
it's actually very entertaining and very thrilling.
glass broken on the left, is it the result of a fight
or does it contain poison?
Why are things left out like that?
There's a cane in the middle, you see,
and it hides something, maybe it's a weapon.
And the thing on the right, is it a clock?
Maybe it is a time travel device.
And the key, what does the key open?
interesting things that happen by evocation.
And I use that a lot in Reigns.
If you take this card, for example,
you got the unknown body, you got the hands missing,
you got the garrison and the dungeon.
So all this creates some sort of structure to the whole game
that we really heavily worked,
that we used a lot because this evocates
the kingdom that's behind the game.
And that was very important to really build on this.
about comedy and rhythm.
We quickly discovered that there was a very strong
comical gap between the decision you take
that impact your kingdom, you send people to the death,
you deal with earthquakes, you deal with a lot
of easy stuff actually, and the way you have to deal
with this by swiping, which is like the most casual way
of dealing with a situation if you want.
And that creates a gap that's very comical.
And only that, only creating very serious cards,
was actually very funny for the player.
And player were like, well, how do I do that?
And the fact that the only options were swiping
makes it very funny.
And we basically just built on this.
hiding more and more weird card,
more and more with unfathomable consequences
that generally bring you to your death very quickly.
As some sort of illustration of a very casual power
that just deal with binary decisions,
is bad and can quickly become sore.
So, also an important thing for the writing of this
was the rhythm.
The rhythm in the game is very important
and it took me some time to learn to do that rhythm.
The pace of the game is very quick
and you have to go from tac-tac-tac and boom you die.
I had to keep in everything I wrote for the games
this sort of very strong rhythm
that Jenny finished with these dafts
that are like a clash that just
breaks you in your pace.
So making that sort of thing was difficult for me.
to find the right tone for the game.
I had to train myself to write games cards.
There's no easy way to do that.
So I wrote 770 cards in the game.
And it's really only after the first.
200 cards but I had the tone, I had the way to play
with my mechanics if you want, and how to define
the sentences so they make sense.
I studied French literature and we like to make
long sentences, so it was very painful for me to do that.
So probabilistic driven narratives,
so that's also very painful, I'm sorry about that.
So, as I told you, players started to create
their own narratives within the game.
So we decided to encourage that,
and that was difficult because we also needed
to keep the flow of the game.
The flow of the game is very important in ranks.
You really have to be able to play hundreds of cards
in the sessions of 20 minutes, for example,
which is generally the time you spend on the game.
And...
That was basically creating a narrative
that's basically infinite because you can loop
and loop and loop, like on Tinder,
you can loop and loop as long as you want.
So to do that, I created a system
that I call Probabilistic Driven Narrative
because it's a bit pedantic and I like it.
So I couldn't do branching path narrative,
especially as I am to be lazy.
It's just crazy, you have four draws here,
imagine.
or I would deal with hundreds of cards, it's not possible.
And it creates a lot of garbage.
So instead I created this probabilistic driven narrative.
It's a relatively simple idea based on basic probability.
and that are actually very useful tools
that I will try to explain here.
So basically, I check the state of the kingdom,
which is made of different variables that I collect, okay?
And against that state, I select all the cards
that fit in that state.
And I put them in this bag, like a bag of cards if you want,
that adapts to the number of cards that are in the bag.
And I select one by randomly.
The fact that the cards have different volume in the bag
makes that just enables to generate
different sort of narratives that will adapt
to the state of the kingdom.
It's a very simple system that creates narratives
that could be purely random,
like in draw four at the bottom here.
I selected in that state,
cards that are relatively the same weight.
So the card that's selected is random.
purely or randomly selected.
I can also color that random selection
by adding cards that have a bigger volume.
Generally I do that when it's around different thematic,
like for example the war of
the spice trade.
So the cards that are related to the spice trade
will be fewer but bigger,
so they have a better chance to be selected by the system.
Within a system that stays random,
so I still have variety in what's happening.
And also I can use the kingdom state in a restrictive way.
So around very small or narrow narratives, even linear narratives, like one card after the other.
And that's what you have in DrawFree and I will show example of that.
And basically that's the system that structures everything that's happening in Reigns.
And as players never know if a card is the direct consequence of a previous choice
or a more random selection by the engine, everything becomes meaningful.
So every link between the cards actually makes sense for the player
because they don't really know if what they're deciding has an impact on the next card selected.
Okay, so this is the, I told you it was painful,
so this is the, I am writing a range.
Basically, I'm writing the card in a spreadsheet.
Sorry about that, it's a bit of a.
And I pass that in Unity.
Each line in this spreadsheet is a card,
and it works like that.
So you got the question and the advisor,
which is the guy who bears the news, if you want.
After that, I got the lock turn,
which is the number of turns a card will be locked
until it's able to be played again
in the probabilistic system.
And the weight of the card,
which is the volume of the card in the bag, if you want.
After that, I got the conditions, which are basically I check if the card fits in different
kingdom states by this system of conditions.
And after that, I got the answers, yes.
So that's the answer, yes.
So both on the values of the kingdom,
the different four values that you see at the top,
and on the, more generally, on the kingdom state.
And everything, all this affects the kingdom state
that evolves basically at every card that you select.
And I have the same for the no answer.
Okay, so that was writing range.
That was very, the structure and the tools I developed
at the start, and don't make any difference
between the code, which is basically
what you have behind the engine,
and the writing, because all that process
was made basically together, and I really switched
from the code to the writing quickly.
So these three things I just saw in writing,
enabled us to make the prototype with round-root cards,
which is the thing we showed to Devolver.
So now the main part was to actually write the whole game.
I call that breaking rings because I really think
it was more about creatively breaking things
than it was about seriously writing cards.
And I have this sort of perverse urge
to break and hack my own systems, if you want.
Because I think it's important to surprise the player
and the fact that in Reigns you can die but you carry on with the next king in the dynasty and so on and so forth
sort of limited the frustration that it can create, although it's quite frustrating sometimes.
The party, so the party, it's one of the thing
I'm the most proud of in Reigns.
It's that we did the impossible, the unthinkable.
You can die of having too much stuff in Reigns.
including money.
It generally happens like this,
so you maximize your money,
and you throw a party,
and then you die choking.
And it happens every single time.
So, I'm serious, I received eight mail about that,
because you suppose, you expect as a player,
as a normal person actually,
to be able to just scoffer stuff without boundaries,
and I think,
On the contrary, the notion of power
is something that needs to be balanced,
and that doesn't make sense if it's not balanced.
So yeah, I'm very proud of this.
Even if it was a bit cheesy to die every time
because of the party, but this is the sort of thing
that make the message of the game went through.
Okay, so the dungeons.
managed to squeeze a rudimentary procedural dungeon crawler
in Rains, which is very inspired by Land of Lords.
So, there's the same system as everything,
except you don't have a visor, but you have a dungeon,
and you go left or right, and things happen,
so I won't spoil you.
And that's interesting because we use
the same probabilistic system as everything else.
But instead of having the system on the whole set of cards,
I just narrow it to a subsystem, a subset of cards,
which are the cards of the dungeon.
So basically I do like this.
So I open on the consequences of the card
that starts the dungeon.
I open dungeon one, okay.
And after that, it will collect, the system will collect
all the cards that share that name and play the probabilistic
system only among them, okay?
And that's how I randomize my dungeon.
And after that, I can loop in the dungeon by just
recording the same subset of cards.
I use this system.
a lot, notably in the Red Dwarf,
which is like a game in the game,
and the Duel on the right.
So, both have a very light layer of code on top of the general system, but I tend to keep
everything in the spreadsheet.
So all the things that you read here are in the spreadsheet and not in something else.
So, Vdevil.
We noticed something very troubling about Tinder.
It's like, it's a hell of a design, but quite literally so.
I mean that, like Tantalus, you're a bit stuck
in some sort of loop that's both numbing,
compelling, and less.
So you see the apple, you want to reach for it,
and you can't, so you come back,
but you try again and you can't, and so on and so forth.
If you replace that with profile on Tinder,
it's a bit the same mechanic.
So this is how the idea very concretely entered,
the idea of the deviant entered the game.
Basically, the devil traps you in this endless loop of kings
and you have to trick him to escape and solve the game.
structure, the Devil backstory was very important
to structure the whole game, give an end goal to the player
and also gaffer all the stories around
the main plot like this.
It was also something we used to trick our YouTubers
and freak them out a bit.
So because when you reach 666, you played 63 years,
so you know how the game works, you're sort of familiar
with it, you play 10 to 15 minutes, so you play through
100 cards about, so that's the perfect moment to just
break everything and that works very well with YouTubers.
So I want to conclude now.
I'll try to sum up the main idea that's behind
most of the things I described today.
Which is basically that for me,
game dev, and I try to do it in rangs,
game dev is more an exploration
than the completion of a system.
I think it's more interesting to try to explore a concept
than just try to make the perfect game, if you want.
What I mean by perfect system,
I think we sort of all game designer
wants to create the perfect game
that's perfectly balanced, like a perfect machine
where every cog just is connected to every other cog.
But it's perfect because it's complete and clean
and defined in a specific space.
Like the big machine in Modern Times from Charlie Chaplin.
I think this is a bit past this vision of things.
I think it's more interesting to start to think
about exploration of concepts
and exploration of game mechanics.
It's a different attitude.
Exploration, what do I mean by that?
I really mean the two phases of exploration,
which is the preparation and the expedition itself.
During preparation, you will try to be as precise
and as perfect as possible, actually.
You have to gather all the skills you will need
to make the game...
As you want it, you will have to define a budget and a planning
and gather the tools that you will need to do the expedition itself.
You have to stabilize the core game mechanics and the main code
while keeping them scalable and expandable.
So it goes really beyond the idea of a basic prototype.
You have to think in your prototype,
it's not just the prototypes,
the prototype and every tool that you will need
to actually bring your game to its final state.
After that, you've got the exploration phase on the right.
So it's when you go exploring,
so you manage your resources dynamically,
you don't stay on your toes, okay,
you have to move, you have to be dynamic,
and adapt everything along the way.
Like we did, for example, with the Devil,
that was not initially in the game,
and we sort of adapted also the game
to fit that sort of backstory.
You may have an end goal, like reaching the softball here,
but maybe you don't, because it's not very important.
I think the most important thing happens during the journey
because it's where the science happens,
it's where you will actually discover new stuff,
and it's where I think it becomes interesting
to create variations around game mechanics.
And what we tried to do in RANX, until very late in the dev,
I had no idea when the game would be finished.
770 cards is actually very, I mean, very arbitral.
So it's not really something I defined at the start.
It's when, through playtest and through my own
understanding, I thought that the game was complete,
if you want.
So as a result of this exploration,
RANX is not a perfect system and it's not a perfect game.
I mean, it's pretty imbalanced
and some things don't actually make a lot of sense.
But it's an ample trial at exploring a concept
and just make the most of it.
And I hope to think that's what also a reason
for the success of RANX.
Why am I spending so much time on this?
Because I think this idea of exploration
is actually, it's not just an interesting way
to make games as a designer, that's a bit selfish.
I think it's always about the player,
and in the end it's always about the players.
When you consider a game design as an exploration,
you embark your players with you.
and you make them part of your exploration.
Like in Spelunky, some things happen in the game
that are not anticipated by the designers themselves.
You let them find different routes in your games,
you let them break your game,
and they will make a connection that you didn't anticipate.
They will use their imagination and their critical thinking,
and I think we need that.
On the contrary,
when you...
attempt to make a game that's supposed to be a perfect system,
the player is just generally only considered as an operator
of the overall game itself.
An operator defined by a demographic and a set
of behaviors. Like Charlie Chaplin in Modern Times,
the only way you have to interact
or to go be, to become creative with that sort of system
is actually to break it and walk away.
So I personally think that this way of designing stuff
is a very strong poison of our modern societies
and it's not just games, it's a lot of stuff
that goes far, far beyond what games.
My mentor and a guy who was a philosopher and sematician,
Jean Shagibov, said it's an object on mechanist
sort of way of thinking.
By that he means some sort of pragmatism
which is actually trapped in a set of values
that make it toxic, okay?
I don't want to finish this talk on this.
I want to finish this talk on the metamorphobate,
which is for me a perfect example of this sort of stuff,
far better than the rings.
Because with very simple mechanics,
like a couple of ideas,
like discovering the letters and the words.
and very simple interactions which are basically touch and drag
and a lot of very interesting tools to play with that.
It created a word that's both evocative, crazy, mad, meaningful.
So that's very interesting. If you don't know that, just check it out.
Thank you.
I hope we have a couple of minutes for questions.
There are a microphone somewhere.
Yeah, here and here, if you want to ask questions.
Hi, I'm Chris.
I just want to ask, do you use Tinder?
What I answer to that is I signed a non-disclosure agreement with my wife.
Any other questions?
Yeah, ask the question, I will repeat it.
you think breaks itself well?
So, the question is, what other games
breaks, you think breaks itself well?
I think,
so,
Yeah, I would say in a control way,
definitely Spelunky.
I think it's very important work
because it's not broken,
but it sort of allowed some sort of broken behaviors
from the players,
and that's very interesting stuff, I think.
Yeah.
All right.
Thank you.