Hello there, everybody.
Welcome to our talk, Creating Narrative Visual Effects in Temtem.
We're super honored to kick off the Visual Effects Summit right now.
And yeah, without further ado, let's go.
Let's show some magic.
All right, of course, it's good to know who you're listening to at least.
So my name is Kees.
I'm a senior visual effects artist at Crema Games.
I started my visual effects career as a 2D artist working on Lethal League Blaze and eventually transitioned to a 3D real-time visual effects style combining the 2D elements.
And currently I'm a full-time animator on Temtem and also a teaching assistant and mentor at Visual Effects Apprentice.
As you can see already from my pictures, I'm a dog lover.
And for me, dogs are here, cats here.
There needs to be some balance, of course, in the Visual Effects team, and I like to explain everything in sound effects.
Hello everyone, I'm Mireille, I'm the Lead VFX Artist here at Crema, and so far I have developed my career mostly working in Crema and Intentum, also some minor previous projects, but mostly there.
Also, one of my main tasks within the team is to translate Kei-san's effect to the rest of the team, because you may know that not everyone speaks VFX language, so that's a thing.
And also, whatever he said about cats and dogs, still under discussion.
We'll get to it.
Okay, so for a lot of you that may not know what Temtem is, Temtem is a MMO monster creature collector that's equipped with turn-based battles that are mostly 2v2 battles.
It was created by Crema Games, which is a small Spanish team of around 30 people.
And regarding visual effects, there have been four VFX artists in total, but never more than two at the same time.
For us both, we've been working there, me, almost three years, and Case, a bit more than two years.
And yeah, we've tried to put a bit, a lot of emphasis on handling the different narrative of the different creatures that appear in the game.
We also wanted to say that the game has been developed using Unity with its built-in runner pipeline.
Okay, and now Kees will tell you a bit about what can you expect from this talk.
All right, so of course you want to think, what are the things we're going to talk about?
So the main red line of our presentation will be the narrative aspect that we try to incorporate with our visual effects technique animations.
So along this, we'll tell about the different tools we use to make this a reality.
So we're going to show you the tool or the videos first without, then we're going to apply the tool and tell you what it does and how we think it makes the narrative visual effects storytelling a reality.
And we want to point out these talks for intermediate to experienced visual effects artists that maybe want to put a bit more emphasis on narrative storytelling in their visual effects work, because we think it's really important.
And of course, it might be interesting for other art professions that actually want to start out as a visual effects artist.
Are there actually any people in the audience that aren't visual effects artists?
Well, maybe after this talk you want to become a visual effects artist because it's a really cool job.
And you could have already seen it repeated a few times on the screen.
Along the presentation or during the presentation, we'll show you many different visual effects to kind of set the tone.
To set the tone already for the talk, over here you see one of our many temtem called Drakash, not being smashed once, not twice, but of course three times by a giant pixel block named Turbo Attack.
But of course, what makes it narrative, Mikko?
So, what do we mean when we say that Phantom has a space for narrative visual effects?
Okay, so Temtem has little gameplay limitations.
We, of course, have some design constraints when it comes to how much damage a technique does, how much stamina it uses, the number of targets it has, but not really apart from that.
This comes from the fact that the visual effects are mostly contained in 2v2 battles, where information that would be key in other games can make competitive games like League of Legends or, you know, adventure games, soul flight games, that information is not really relevant for us.
This means that we can focus and investigate a bit more into other aspects of the visual effects, like for example, the narrative ones.
We also wanted to say that since the game came out as an early access game, we've had a lot of interaction with the community.
For us, this has been, I think, a privilege, because it's mostly been a lot of constructive feedback.
Also, Temtem has a space for signature moves, and these are special moves that only one Temtem can use, and we've used them to further and deepen the different stories of a particular creature.
Okay, so in here, you can see the main three techniques that we're gonna talk about in our presentation.
From right to left, you can see leech, repress, and cozy net, but for now, we'll let you wondering how do the sequences look, and we'll tell you a bit about our production workflow.
All right, so we think it's always nice to see how different games get created.
So we want to show how it starts from getting an idea of a technique animation, up until applying and thinking of gameplay details, up until the final product.
So what Miguel already said, we have little limitations in creative freedom.
So we have done things like creating a giant black hole, sucking everything inwards, or a giant lava wall, which eventually pours hot lava over this little platypod, which is fine and is still fine to this day.
I guess that's what happens when you let visual effects artists decide mostly what happens with visuals in the game.
But how does it actually look?
So, we have some information on the screen.
Of course, we have an idea.
This can be a designer's little story, like, hey, I got, for example, a lava wall and I want to pour hot lava over this platypad.
Or we can even have a lot of freedom that we can create even our own ideas.
So for example, next up we get some gameplay details.
And you can see over underneath here, for example, we have Thunderstrike, of course.
What kind of typing is it?
Electric.
How much, what is the category?
Special, physical.
What kind of damage does it do?
Stamina and holds.
And these little details I'll explain further down because we think gameplay details are very important to even begin, starting with the visual effects animations.
Again, next time, for example, Fire Tornado.
What kind of category is it?
Of course, element fire.
For example, you can see two holds.
This will also depend on how long will the technique take.
Next up, we have the concepting phase.
And this really depends on actually the choice of the visual effects artists.
Of course, we're an indie game, so of course we're an indie game.
We're an indie company, so we don't have a lot of people in the company, around 30-ish people.
So we don't have a dedicated 2D concept artist that helps us out.
So what we like to do, we just draw our own concept art.
So we like to draw the key frame, the biggest impactful key frame of the technique animation.
And this is a very fast way for the art director, lead visual effects artist, to already discuss within 15 minutes already, this is what we want.
And it's really fast.
We also think maybe sometimes faster than kitbashing in a way.
And also little scribbles, like this stampede scribble.
And also, it's a very team collaborative effort that Miko and I work together.
So we constantly go back and forth, overpaint, timing changes, tune in little details.
And that's really fun to do.
But let me explain further now what the gameplay elements actually are.
Because we do have gameplay elements or restrictions, but we have different ones than compared to player versus player games, for example.
So we have the duration that you already saw in the picture, spectacularity, and some other elements.
So duration, what you saw is we have three holds.
And basically, the bigger the hold, or the more turns you have to wait, the longer the technique animation has to be on the screen.
So we can have technique animations that we have to make visuals on two to three seconds, or the highest holds eight to nine seconds.
So that's a very good thing to point out.
Okay, we need to create an effect that takes nine seconds.
Next up, we have Spectacularity.
This is mostly based on the damage, because if we make every technique 150 damage, of course, none of them would stand out.
So we have some restrictions.
Some techniques are zero damage, some are 10 damage, and some can go up to 150 damage.
And we have some other elements such as stamina.
How much stamina does it cost to cast a technique animation?
The priority, does it go first, second, third, or fourth because of the turn-based battle system?
How many target numbers?
One temtem getting targeted, two temtem, or the whole area, or the whole battle zone?
And what are the conditionings applied?
Is it poison, burned, frozen, and so on?
So even in the end, it doesn't look like this much, that much on their own.
It's really a combination of
of the elements together that we can pinpoint, okay, how big does the technique get?
But, Migo, can you tell us something about the unique game aspects?
Of course.
Okay, so this will be the last bit of information before we dive into the techniques.
And as for now, Tentame is 12 different elemental types.
Each, of course, with its own color palette and shape language.
And we have water, electrical, fire, earth, melee, crystal, you name it.
And we have developed these color palettes for each one that are useful for more things that you may think of.
For example, for us, VFX artists, it's super helpful to have this as a reference to fall back to.
And also, for example, case is colorblind for some values of yellow.
And since we mostly want yellow electricity and yellow fire, even if green fire is cool, green fire is really cool.
But yeah, having this to fall back to has proven super useful.
Also, the game is divided into main areas, as we call them the battle zones and the free-roam area.
The free-roam area is where the game itself happens.
It's where you find the other players, since it's an MMO game.
It's where you find the NPCs, where the story itself happens.
And then we have the battle zones areas.
This is where the 2v2 battle happens and where we have developed most of our visual effects.
And finally, Temtem right now, we have 164 different Temtem, and more than 350 techniques.
And if you think about it, this has been one of the hardest parts of developing visual effects for Temtem, because we have to consider that every technique has to look good on every Temtem, because every Temtem can potentially use every technique, and of course they can re-sit them.
So we have to play a lot with the scale of the techniques and the different effects because it's not the same if a small temtem like this body but receives a technique, a middle-sized temtem like this ballast over here, or the super huge electrical mythical temtem like this mulligan.
Okay, so that was it for the information and right now we'll dive into our first big technique that's called leech.
All right, so we have all the very important information out of the way that we even think of before we're starting.
So we know, okay, how long does it take and everything.
So let's talk about Leech.
And of course, first, what's the narrative?
How did it start?
So let me introduce you to one of our many temtem called Typhoo.
And we can say Typhoo is a pretty big meme in the community.
Because well, Typhoo is a meme.
Why does T-Pose Typhoo look like a dollar store scissor?
Like once every couple of months, people are like, hmm, Typhoo.
And then after a few games, don't play Typhoo, even for the memes.
Typhoo doesn't deserve to be good.
Typhoo deserves to be left in the dirt.
So, of course, us as visual effects artists, I can look at everybody in the audience.
When you hear from your, in this case, from a designer, hey, Typhoon needs a new special signature move, so it's really special only for Typhoon.
Of course, we want to make Typhoon matter, because who doesn't love this T-pose and dollar store scissor?
So when thinking of like an idea conceptualization, we think of, okay, what does fit the best and makes Typhoon matter and be part of something bigger than the Temtem universe?
And eventually we wanted to give Typhoon a very nature godly feel that is like part of something bigger.
Of course, we take much, much reference from games you have worked on, TV shows, everything we can take references off, anime also.
And we thought a very fitting thematic for Taifu, a godly nature feel, was the Watcher from the What If series.
I don't know if you've watched the What If series, but it's just the way it's looking at you, it's very menacing in a way, it's kind of like very godly.
And we thought, well, we think this will be very special for Taifu.
So here's a little sneak peek and let's dive into it actually, how we actually started out and what are the tools and techniques we apply.
So first of all, we're talking about, we're going to talk about with Leech's spectacularism, I'll say spectacularity because I stumble constantly over the words, time remapping and Temtem battle shader effects.
So first up, Spectacularity.
So, you already heard us say a few times, 10x a turn-based battle game.
So, what we really try to focus on, we need to keep the players engaged, because we can have technique animations up to 9 seconds.
So we want to really encapture those hype moments because we create games for the players.
So every time they use a skill, they're like, yes, I want to maybe use that Temtem only because of the skill.
That's actually our goal.
And we want to make it really matter and fit the whole Temtem story itself.
So for Typhoon, that's the leeching part.
And also what really works the best for it is mostly anime because anime timing is really great.
It's very snappy and it's constantly engaging in a way, like the colors, everything's working.
And we can really put a more emphasis on the thematic.
We can give it much, much more power, really increased power of punches and everything together.
And we really think that works great for Leech and the technique animations.
Next up, we have time remapping.
And in this video over here, we'll show you the video actually without the tool applied.
We'll tell you what the tool actually does.
And then afterwards, we're going to take a look how it looks with it applied.
So what is time remapping?
So with time remapping, we're able to slow or speed up time with time curves that you can see on the left bottom over here.
This is actually a very artist-friendly way for us to efficiently try out different things.
Like maybe we kick in a very slow motion kind of feel, a very speed up kind of feel.
And we can give the technique 10 times more power with it.
So just imagine for yourself, you're looking at this technique GIF.
How would it look if it's very linear?
It would lose a lot of power, a lot of anticipation.
It kind of misses that hype moment and that anticipation moment for the players.
So by just really increasing those curves, we can really give that a very spectacular feel to it.
And we can say what gets affected by it.
We can say everything gets affected in the scene.
We can say the source animators, so the source temtem is getting affected, the targeted temtem, or we can say all the temtem in the area.
So we have lots of possibilities if you think of it.
So let's do a refresh for the mind how it looks without time remapping.
And these can be some pretty small details actually.
So the narrative is there, but it's kind of missing that juicy feel.
It's kind of like the oomph of it.
It's really like, oh, it's coming, it's coming.
And then, bam, it explodes.
So let's see how it looks with time remapping.
And it can be a slight detail that some of you might not really recognize in the beginning.
But for us, it's really adding on top of that extra animation feel.
So Typhoo casts its skill, it builds up, it goes in slow-mo and it rapidly increases over time to really show Typhoo leeching the life source out of the enemy Temtem.
And for the last tool of leech, let's talk about Temtem Battle Shader effects.
And you can already get a question actually yourself, or, hey, Kees, why are there two floating eyes and some swishy swooshies, solar coasters, curve meshes?
Yeah, you can name it what it is.
We call it solar coast for now.
Let me explain actually how that works, Temtem Battle Shader effects.
So here we show Taifu in the Unity editor scene.
And the cool thing we can do with Temtem Battle Shader effects is we can place Temtem clones.
And you heard me say clones, and Miguel will tell a bit more about clones eventually.
But what we can do is we can set custom parameters during the animation timing of the technique.
So during the eight seconds, we can say we want to increase the fresnel over time.
the texture speed, the power of the glow and everything.
We have lots of possibilities with this and we use it again with the curve meshes we showed you, the curve files.
But we can do other things only giving typhoon a nature godly feel.
We can give a tantum a digital feel that is a distorted hologram.
We can go more to nightmare field kind of effects like nightmare feet.
We can even glitch the temtem like it's stuck in the matrix and offsetting the vertices so much for digital type effects.
And we can send out an extra temtem clone with a battle shader on it, and we really portray the power of, okay, the temtem is getting punched, bonk, it goes backwards, and it's like an aura shader that we apply to it.
So again, what does it do for Typhoo?
Without the temtem battle shader effects, two floating eyes, some swishy-smooshy, solar coasters, it's missing something.
but with the Temtem Battle Shader effect.
It comes all together.
The narrative is there that we think will really try to give Temtem Typhoon a very nature-godly feel.
And it's a really cool tool, too.
We can do lots of things with it.
And let's see how it looks actually when we have all the tools combined and with some sound effects on it and see how it comes to a whole final product.
And you might also notice at the end of the effect, we let some particles linger so the player can already register for, okay, this tantrum just got attacked because sometimes there are maybe four of the same tantrum in the battle scene.
So with the first big technique out of the leech, Migo, can you tell us something about our next mental technique called Depress?
Yep, definitely.
Okay, so after leech, we are diving into Depress.
This one is a mental technique.
It's a damaging technique that requires the target to be asleep for it to work.
So given the name of this technique, we wanted to try and recreate those kinds of feelings and emotions that you may get when you're going through a bad time.
Our narrative idea for this technique was that if we were able to implement in some sort of way our own feelings into the game, then the technique would be more fitting inside the Temtem universe, but also outside of it, and the players would be able to relate more to it.
Ok, so that's why, let me show you a technique As you can see, the enemy temtem goes into some sort of personality disorder where it sees itself out of its own body and some particles that play with it and it gets pulled back together, but of course it's damaged
Okay, so in here we're going to talk about two main tools that we made to make this technique stand out, that are the extra tantrums or clones as Kees just said, and of course post-processing.
So for these extra tantrums or clones, what these are, they are copies of the tantrums that are within a technique and we can use several different animations for them.
We can use animations that they have in their Battlezone kit, that can be for example the gate hit animation or the
attacking animation, but also we can use some animations from the free-roam area.
This, in addition with, for example, some more basic animation that's just position, rotation, and scaling, we can create techniques that have sufficient narrative meaning just with that.
Like, for example, you can see a lot of running temtems.
That's the stampede scribble that I showed you earlier.
Also in the GIF, you can see this technique that's called Oshidashi, and you can definitely see the impact that being able to animate this temtem has.
Without it, well, the punch would feel powerful, okay, because we have the impact frame, we have the timbre mapping, but it will feel much less powerful if we didn't launch the temtem up into the sky.
It also helps us to give some comedic effect, because as you may have seen, temtem visual effects lean into some sort of comedic or funny effect.
And you can see that little star up in the sky, that's like, okay.
Okay, and next up, you can see the effect this one has on the press.
Without the extra temtem, you can see some particles floating around, but you don't understand why the temtem has disappeared, you don't really get where it is, and it has no narrative meaning.
On the other hand, when we put it back on, you can definitely see that something's happening to it.
We also use basic animation principles like this squat and stretch, so you can understand the violence of the pullback and the pullback together.
Okay, also post-processing, maybe for some of you that may not know what post-processing is, it consists of filters that are applied in the last stages of rendering and with it we can create some effects like vignetting or changes of contrast, bloom, etc.
So in Tantum we are able to modify the current post-processing that we have at any current time within the technique animation
and we can have two of them overlapping at the same time.
This means that we can have, for example, one handling a change of bloom and another one handling a LUT color swap of the full screen.
We can do this also with curving files that I showed you earlier in time remapping.
So this is a very artist-friendly way to do it.
For example, this would be some LUT textures that we created for post-processing.
And with this we can portray, for example, the violence of an explosion in this technique that's called knockback blast with these full black and white values, or color, sorry.
We can also portray, for example, an electrical field with these blue and dark blue values.
And also, we can create that feeling that you may have had if you had an electrifying massage, maybe.
But yeah, for example, here we get a full black and white color swap of the full screen, that in addition with an inverted fresnel on the enemy temtem.
We portrayed that thing that we may have seen in a lot of animes where the skeleton gets shown when you get electrocuted.
Okay, we've also created an Uber shader for post-processing.
because sometimes we want to handle more than one thing at the same time.
For example, if we have overlapping stuff in time, it's easier to do it in just one file and not have to move it around.
And you can see, for example, how we handle in the right part of the screen vignetting, in the middle part, there's kinetic lengths for some super fast techniques.
And up there is the LUT color swaps.
Okay, so getting back to the press, you can see the effect this one has.
So without post-processing,
you can definitely feel that something's missing, a transition feels a lot more bland, and we're missing something, yeah.
But when we put it back on, you can definitely understand that you are going into that sort of mental state where the damage could happen, and suddenly it gets a lot more narrative meaning.
Okay, so now let's show it with sound effects, of course.
So yeah, you can definitely see the projectile finding, then you get both copies or both personalities pulled back of the temtem.
The projectiles are the particles that are playing with both copies, and then the violins pull back.
So you can definitely understand that life will never be the same again for this temtem.
Okay, so next up, this is the app for the press, and we'll tell you about our next big technique that's called coaching it.
So, our third big technique is called CozNet and maybe the wording is a bit wrong because it doesn't look very cozy for little Mosu.
Yeah, we can all agree about that.
Fun fact, actually, if we show our work in progress videos, we cast all the different technique animations, all the different small temtem, because we have, we think that's the most impact and sells the idea a bit more.
And a lot of actually colleagues of us are like, no, the little temtem, so.
All right, so what is the narrative of CozyNet?
So with CozyNet, we really wanted to portray the feel of the temtem getting pulled into the lair of Arachnid, a spire temtem with the typings digital and nature, where Arachnid crawls down and eventually feasts on this little snack called Mosu.
And yeah, we treat them with love, don't worry.
So what are the things we're going to talk about?
We're going to talk about actually two very important things that we think are very special when it comes to Temtem.
It's camera movement and BZChain's Battlezone changes.
So you can already see in the video over here, it's not shippable.
The camera has an error or something.
So let me get you through it, how the camera movement works and what we actually can do by adding extra movement on already everything that's there.
So,
Yeah, it's quite unique being a visual effects art for Temtem because sometimes we have our own ownership that we come up with our own idea.
We create it from the beginning up until the end.
And it's really, we think it's really special that we can do that.
But also with this comes camera movements because camera movement is very important because we have the time for it with the turn-based battle system and everything.
So we can really create interesting camera shots and camera positioning or camera positions.
But how are we doing it?
So we do it again with the curve files.
It's a lifesaver for us.
We can do, for example, animate the field of view curve of the camera.
So instead of only doing screen shakes, we can create extra wobbles.
So think of, for example, a very climactic explosion.
It goes boop, boop, boop, boop, boop, boop, and then brrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrrr
it explodes.
Those are kind of like the things we can do with field of view curves and we can go all out and just have a lot of fun with it actually.
Next up we have curvings of different cameras so camera A and B and we have all kinds of freedom from how can we move camera A towards camera B so we can create shots of the cameras and how is it transitioning or when is camera B kicking in maybe camera C, D, E. We have lots of cameras sometimes.
And during this, actually approaching 1.0 of Temtem, it actually released last September, there was one colleague of ours, Adrie Dovonio-Andres, we call him the shader god, and he had one thing, like one sentence he constantly repeated to us, and we want to share it with you.
So, this is Adrie.
And Adrie always told us, let the camera follow the effect.
And why is this actually?
Well, this way it looks like the player is naturally getting guided by the visual effects instead of an almighty being controlling the camera.
What if typhoon?
So what do we mean by this?
Let's go, for example, through some examples.
So over here you have Unseen Blow and you can already see something and I'm letting the first run of GIF again.
Yeah.
And you can already maybe see some things that when a projectile starts, we first let the player register, okay, there's something happening with the projectile, but we only let the second camera kick in when a projectile is halfway through the trajectory.
So this way the player knows, okay,
I need to take a look at the projectile.
Okay, the projectile is going to do something.
It's going to damage the other temtem.
Because if we instantly let the camera move towards the target, the player doesn't know what to do.
And it's kind of, we're forcing the player in a way.
And the player is like, oh, I'm maybe not really together with the visual effects and the projectile movement of it.
Over here you have the coach net itself.
So you can see also with the line how the camera's moving.
So first camera moves down.
We do the anticipation also.
It's really building up to that hype moment.
It's like da-da-da-da-da-da-da.
And it goes back to the normal battle zone area.
And what I was talking about, building up to that climactic explosion with field of view curves.
So this is one technique called DG thread.
So the camera is zooming inwards.
We really increase the field of view power.
And it's like, we're holding a moment, tiny bit, and then it kicks in, it zooms very far actually inwards.
And we show that, yeah, the 10th time is damaged by quite a, quite an amount of damage.
So let's see again for coast net, how it looks without the camera movement, actually.
So Eric Knight is casting the skill, and of course, there's something wrong.
It doesn't look shippable at all.
But let's see actually how it looks with the camera movement.
So Eric Knight is casting the skill, crawls down like Spider-Man, and eventually feasting on his little snack called Mosu.
So with camera movement out of the way, let's talk about battle zone changes.
And you can already see, this is not the final battle zone, this is actually our visual effects test that you've seen.
It doesn't look that great, so let's see how we can make it even better.
So what are Battlezone changes?
Battlezone changes are custom unity scenes where we hand place all kinds of different assets that are actually at our disposal.
And we're doing it to really capture that because we do mostly Battlezones for signature moves that are special to one certain temtem.
So we can really give a temtem like Arachnid, a temtem like Leech, like Typhoon, much more meaning to the overall, the skill of it and what it does.
So what we did, for example, we created a giant spider web that's actually like the focus point, leading with the shape language, the lines to the middle, that little mouse.
So there's something going to happen with the enemy temtem.
And with that, we also added some environmental effects.
So we give the feeling of the players inside the spider cocoon, and there's something going wrong, and it's definitely going to go wrong with the enemy Temtem.
But also with this, if you think it yourself, we have lots of possibilities with this, because the Temtem universe for us is very big as visual effects artists.
So what are some other things we can actually do with this?
We can create a toxic wasteland, a stone dune and trench environment, a more martial arts melee environment.
And we can even summon a stormy sea where thunder and tornadoes appear.
Just a bit like in the Netherlands, where it's constantly raining.
And trust me, I am from the Netherlands.
It's constantly raining.
Actually, also in San Francisco this week.
So you can already see like we're having loads of fun also with this and we just kind of can go all out and just use all kinds of different things and the why's and the how of a meaning to the scene.
Because why are we doing it?
We're doing it to give again Eric Knight that special feel that maybe people want to play the Spire 10 because we can cast our enemy tantrums in a giant spider cocoon.
And how are we doing it?
We're using basically everything at our disposal that we can use.
So if, for example, some 3D artists create some very cool environment art assets, we think we can use it in a way, create some interesting composition and camera shots.
And if that works, yeah, we use that actually.
So a refresher for the mind.
How does it look without battlezone changes?
So again, you can remember the normal visual effects test scene, it's not fitting at all.
It misses the whole point of the technique.
But with the Battlezone change, there's already more meaning to it.
The narrative is there and just capture that moment of the spider tent and what could a spider tent be.
And lastly, let's see how it looks with some sound effects because we think adding sound effects, getting added to the facial effects makes it a whole picture and become a final product.
And there's also one thing I want to point out is that with certain techniques, we favor some cameras on the right side and the left side.
This is more because when a camera is favored on the left side, it could be the friendly team.
And when a camera favors the right side, it's the enemy team.
Because what I told you again, some temtem can be, there can be two of the same temtem in the battle zone.
So this is like a small cue for the players.
It's like, okay, the enemy is using this skill right now.
So with our third big technique out of the way, CozyNet, we have one more thing that's very important when it's getting applied to our technique animations, which is composition.
Can you tell us something more about that, Miguel?
Yep, okay, so as you've been seeing Temtem techniques are a little bit like small cinematics or like mini mini movies and we've tried to learn stuff like for example for animated series or movies and put what we've learned from them to use.
We of course tried to live up to those standards and we have tried to implement this like for example with a low angle shot to portray a Temtem as much much more powerful
or even just the opposite.
Like if we portray a shot from a super high position, and it's a small temtem in a super big environment, then that temtem suddenly feels super weak.
We've also tried to put two things together.
One thing was that what Keith said, that the camera has to follow the effect.
And the other thing is that the visual effects have to guide the eye.
This is really important for us.
So let me show you what I mean.
In this technique that's called Crystal Deluge, you can see that we try to, at first, the camera following the effects, because we don't start moving the camera up until the VFX have left the camera shot.
And also we have that triangular shape, so we make sure that the player is looking downwards.
Also that way the transition feels a lot more natural.
This is important because in composition in Temtem we don't want the player to miss any important information and we've tried to do it and it's been one of the hardest parts of developing VFX here.
This would be a sketch of the triangular shape I was talking about and you can see that the effect has already left the screen.
This next technique, that's called unseen blow.
You can see what Kees was telling about earlier, that we don't start moving the camera up until the projectile is like 50% on its way over the enemy.
In here, we put our higher values in the projectile, so we make sure that the player is looking, well, of course, at the projectile, and that they are looking at this action line.
And finally here, this is the signature move of Wasp Beam.
That's a Wasp Temtem.
and we do portray the temtem as more powerful with this slight low angle shot at the beginning and also with that conic shape that we do upwards we make sure that the player is looking above and behind the temtem because of course the first time they see the technique they are not going to know what's going to happen but at least they know where it's coming from so they are not surprised and they're like okay I wanted to look there but in a way we're making that look there
So this would be the action line that we want the player to look at.
And yeah, we are getting close to the end of the presentation, but not quite there.
Because, but wait, there is more.
So let's do a small recap of what we talked about with the three techniques, leech, depress, and cozy net.
We've talked about things such as time remapping, adding spectacularity.
Temtem battle shader effects, Temtem clones, and so on.
And we really think we have many more tools, but we think these are the most important tools that we can go actually all out and capture that narrative feeling of the technique animations.
We also think, even in the slightest, this could also work for you, because narrative visual effects meaning is very important, we think, and to give maybe the basic explosion a bit more meaning to it.
Of course, but wait, there is more.
Because we're all visual effects artists, there are lots of visual effects artists over here.
Imagine what we can do with this.
So, with that out of the way, can you tell us something about the divine god called Peak Epic?
Okay, so this is the signature move, this Piggy Tentum, that's called Piggy Pig.
And let me tell you the story for this one.
So since the game came out as an early access, there was a lot of interaction with the community.
And some Tentums in the beginning, they were super overpowered, like insane.
And it was the case for this Piggy Pig Tentum.
And of course, since it was so powerful, people started comparing it with a god.
and like shortly after this was all around in the discord okay and shortly after of course the pkip charge was born that was a thing and we wanted to give back to the community in a way and and try to put what well what they showed us and put it in the game so let me show you
Okay, so of course this is a meme for us, but we also wanted to make it look good for the players that weren't there in the beginning.
But yeah, I think it's been super fun developing VFX for this game.
You can also see that we've used all of the tools that we've been talking about, like for example, the time remapping, overlapping post-processing with that vignetting and chromatic aberration.
But yeah, next up we'll tell you a bit about another technique that's called horror.
So approaching 1.0, we kind of got like super comfortable with the Temtem IP.
I think we can speak for a lot of people that when you get at the end of like a stage from DLC or a game, you're really trying to push yourselves.
Okay, we got all this, let's create some crazy things actually.
So what we try to do with the mental technique, especially because fire is fire, electric is electric, but mental can be lots of things.
It can be depersonalization with the press, for example.
Or it can be something in your mind, like something affecting your amygdala.
Think of games such as Bloodborne, stories of H.P.
Lovecraft.
I'm myself a huge fan of those.
I was like, let's see how we can really put maybe Temtem in the Temtem universe and let's summon the depths of Cthulhu and put it in a Temtem jacket that fits the whole narrative of it.
So we summoned the giant tentacle eye floating, looks like a raid boss in a way to give that feeling of composition.
Oops.
Oh, sorry.
To give the feeling of composition and the menacing feel of the temtem that's in the mental realms.
Oh no, I'm not going to be the same after this anymore.
And what we did was we sent out a pulse of mental powers when upon impact tentacles burst out with toxic viscous goo splashing towards the player's screen.
The next technique is called outgrowth, or first when it started, drain climbing plant.
And this was actually a technique we came up with our own, like the whole idea was on our own.
And the designer also told us, okay, sure, you can do it.
Good luck.
And then afterwards, oh, okay, how are we going to do this?
So this technique is for one of our mythical tantrum called tyrannic.
which comes from the fire volcano environment and its typing is fire and nature.
And what we wanted to capture with this technique animation was the full force of nature ramping towards the enemy, creating a tree of life and eventually exploding in nature colors and nature schematic.
And a bit of flavor of Naruto wood style jutsu.
So for this technique, it was a real team collaborative thing.
And again, our shader god comes back, Adri de Voglio Andres, created a root shader because this was a very necessary thing for us that we needed.
So I'm going to explain to you actually how we set it up and how we made this possible, this effect.
So first, we needed some custom meshes that we created in Blender.
And you can see some red vertices painted on these meshes.
Maybe some of you already know how the root shader works or like how you let the roots grow in a way.
But these actually, these vertices determine the thickness of the root because again, shape language is very important and we want to get rid of the symmetrical shapes in the technique animation.
So it feels more natural and the roots really feel natural in a way.
Next up, we have a basic shader that actually Chromium made over here, together with Andri.
And these cover things such as fresnel, for example, texture panning, because that's a very important thing also, together with the roots.
And also, of course, the root growing in a point, actually, instead of being cut off, because then it feels more natural and believable to the players.
We painted our own personal roots tileable texture.
And you can see over here how we try to implement the roots hand placed again with the battle zone change that we think really fits the camera movement and the battle zone and the composition for the battle zone changes.
And it's also nice to see how it actually started, because this was the first color scheme.
But of course, the narrative is very important, but you can already guess it.
Tyrannic comes from a fire volcano there, and it's typings fires in nature.
So it leads more towards the orange colors, the more brighter colors.
So we changed it up totally.
And it took a while, of course, but these things, mistakes can happen in game dev.
And I think everybody makes sometimes these mistakes.
And let's see, let's also show you the first ever draft of outgrowth.
And there might, there are some important things I want to point out afterwards.
So you can already see the camera movement is there.
The composition, everything is there.
The roots are basically working, but it's very cluttered.
You don't really see where you have to look.
The color scheme is all wrong.
But this actually shows that camera movement is really a key into our visual effects animations.
And that, yeah, a lot of signature moves, we just even start with camera movement.
And on top of that, we add the visual effects layers.
So we make it easy for ourselves.
Next up, Migo is going to tell us more about Black Hole.
Okay, so as we've been saying, sometimes the ideas for the techniques came from the designer or our CEO, Enrique Paos, who was the one that created the techniques.
But other times, the ideas for the techniques came from either ourselves or more tech part of the company.
So this was the case for Black Hole.
In this one, we wanted to try and recreate the moment that you would feel, would think, inside a black hole, of course.
That's you hear nothing, you see nothing, there's nothing happening.
So let me show you.
Yeah, so that was that.
And yeah, we also did a custom post-processing here.
Let me show you, actually.
Swirling distortion in the middle to also portray that feeling that everything's been sucked inside the black hole.
You can see it right over there.
So yeah, that's also helped out a bit.
Okay, so this would be our last technique.
So Kees, will you do me the honors here?
I can.
I think we can speak for a lot of people and this technique will speak some volume actually.
And we've all experienced this like maybe every week, three, four times, five times.
And if not, well, we have a very special computer actually.
So let's just let this be a technique speak for itself.
Yay, blue screens.
Who doesn't love those?
Okay, so what we want you to take from this, of course we know that you have to be in this sort of position where putting this in your game makes sense, but if you are to take anything from this talk it's that in some cases less is more, okay?
Because you see that this is literally one big blue billboard and a sad face, and it has a lot of narrative and comedic meaning.
So we think that if you are able to implement, well, maybe any of that, even in the slightest in your own games, maybe you can benefit from that.
Great, so thank you all so much for coming.
This was the end of our talk, but we didn't want to leave before saying some shout outs and some thank yous.
So of course we didn't create Temtem on our own because yeah, that's just not possible.
And we want to thank the, just want to give some huge shout outs to the team back in Madrid.
Each and every person is super talented and just working with such a team that has so much passion for the Temtem IP is just great.
And that we can share our visual effects work with them is just an amazing opportunity.
Also, we want to thank our bosses, Enrique Paos and Guillermo Andradas, for believing in us, letting us give this talk and just having trust in us as representing Temtem, the IP.
Also Alex Munoz and our shader god, Adrie de Vognio-Andres, during 1.0 and just working on Temtem techniques, the feedback sessions were just super into detail with animation to time, shape, language, everything.
Shaders also helping out, and it's just, for us, really valuable.
People that really helped us out a lot.
And Jason, where are you sitting?
Jason, thank you so much for reaching out to us to give us the opportunity to give this talk about Temtem and creating narrative visual effects animations.
It's actually our first time going to GDC and our first time in America, so it can be quite overwhelming, but just sharing, because we're also quite new in the visual effects industry, and just sharing how much fun we have creating visual effects and how we can also do other kinds of visual effects and narrative visual effects, it's just amazing to share that.
And of course, lastly, regarding the GDC team giving out the important information about travel documents and everything, it really helped us out a lot.
And thank you especially Sam Warnke for replying so super fast.
So with that out of the way, actually, there is a little temtem that has actually a question.
And that is, are there any questions?
Yeah.
Yeah, if it's at the mic, that could be possible, yeah.
Yeah, I think that's best.
I'm a little short.
Excellent talk, thank you.
I wanted to check, what were the main points of collaboration you had with the wider team?
Like, what departments are you mainly collaborating with?
So, the main point with the wider team, like the collaboration.
So, I think especially with Adrie de Vogna Andres and the art director, we really wanted to capture that the Temtem style of the visual effects fits the universe.
But for example, also with the sound people that created the visual effects sounds,
They also sometimes ask us like, hey, what is actually your feeling with this technique animation?
Because sometimes the ideas come up ourselves.
And I can think also with game design, when we created Outgrowth with the routes moving forward, we had this idea and we showed a concept, but of course then the designer is going to ask, oh, how many targets does it have?
Is it one target, two targets?
How long is it?
Because if we make technique animations too long compared to 50 damage, then players will just be,
Come on, again, again, again.
Sometimes that happens.
I think, well, since it's a rather small company, in the end, we've had a lot of interaction with every department, mostly, because, for example, some techniques, I can think of the Shane Schmoyer's REC.
That one, the animation team did the animation for that one, and then we put on the visual effects.
Also, sometimes the 3D department created some of the environments, so in the end,
Actually a mix of every department almost.
Like for example a monkey getting animated jumping up with two giant rocks and smashing it downwards.
Those kind of things.
So it's really cool to create effects for that.
That's super cool.
Thank you.
No problem.
Hey there.
First, it's really impressive you built this game with 30 people.
Thank you.
Pass it off to you.
That's great.
So you guys obviously have so much creative freedom to build these effects for your TemTems.
So where did you checkpoint yourself in terms of budgeting or memory usage or time?
Because you could build environments, you can build shaders.
What kind of went on with that process?
So where do we build the budgeting, timing, everything?
Well, I think for optimization, the hardest thing was for, for example, Nintendo Switch, because we have lots of billboards that are just full on in screen.
So you can already imagine the overdraw.
So when we optimized for the Switch, it took a long time because we want to capture that feeling that it feels like very rich, the effects, but doesn't lose the glow and everything in the shapes.
And that was pretty difficult.
Yeah, we had to kill our uber shader that we had for PC and just build several super minor shaders that worked for that.
And also regarding time, I think we did every technique within 3 or 4 days.
Of course, it took more, it took less.
Outgrowth took two weeks because of the color change and everything and the slight colorblind values.
I was like, okay, these colors, oh no, again, again, back and forth, but that happens.
Yeah, and a follow-up.
Do you guys use the visual effects graph, or do you guys use particle systems, or do you guys use... Like, what's the core for what you build?
We use Shuriken, because it was built with a built-in render pipeline, a 2019.4 version.
Cool.
For example... Oh, sorry.
For example, like, the routes we animated by hand with the animator, because you just have control in the way the feeling control.
Like, you have to feel in this, okay, how can I really...
When the root grows, it goes like, it bursts upwards and you let it hang.
And then when it goes, it goes.
Yeah.
Kind of like how they do it in Naruto and like the animes.
That's like very timing feeling.
Yeah.
Cool.
Well, thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hi, guys.
I was curious about how you went about deciding when to trade off between keeping the animation as satisfying as possible and how much time the animation takes.
Because I realize that sometimes, take the animation as good as it can look, you need a certain amount of time.
But after a certain point, you're making a player wait a certain amount each time they play it.
So how did you go about deciding when it needed to be
So regarding timing and how long do you think a technique animation should take and how we decided.
So we have the holds for example.
So 0 holds is 2 to 3 seconds and 3 holds so how long the technique animation holds before getting cast.
possible to cast, it's nine seconds.
But we have, for example, the giant lava wall that you saw with like platypus standing there and then eventually lava will pour over the temtem.
First, the technique was 15 seconds or so, 13, because we had like a whole concept art that the lava walls are appearing, we have a camera pouring like over the lava wall, looking downwards, then we follow the lava, following downwards.
And then our shader guard, Adrieu Von Andres, he was like,
It's 15 seconds.
It's two holds, so it needs to be seven seconds.
So we had to just cut off like half of the technique animation and still make it work.
So sometimes it's also a try and error.
We have the, because we have lots and loads of fun, but sometimes you forget, ooh, okay, this takes too long.
Players are not gonna like this.
We got too excited with it.
Yeah.
And also if you think about it, like if it's a three hold technique,
it's gonna be seen much less.
Because you have to wait three turns to use it.
So in the end, we balance it out.
A technique that's three seconds, maybe you can use it three times, so in the end it's nine seconds.
And one technique that you can use it once every three turns, it's nine seconds.
So it kind of balances it out, yeah.
Thank you.
Oh, yes.
Thank you so much for doing this talk, it was really nice and really cool to learn about.
And I was wondering, for your concepting stuff, what are you guys trying to focus on with that?
Are you more like color theory stuff, or like, I guess just what's your focus with that?
I think when I start out at Tantum, I'm a huge advocate of overpaints for visual effects artists because
For example, when you're a smaller team, you don't have concept art.
And I think it's, uh, for example, kit bashing sometimes might take a bit longer and just drawing it out.
Even a little sketch or just full out sketch 15, maybe up 20 minutes.
It just shows in one shot.
This is what we want.
We don't do like some techniques.
We do the charge part, the impact part, and then the ending part.
And we concept it out, but we never go longer than 30 minutes in a way.
But this is just, uh,
Sorry, what was the question again?
Oh, just to get your focus for the concept.
Yeah.
So with the focus, it's like to capture that main impact moment, the highest part of the technique animation.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hello.
I have a question about your gradients and your gradient management system.
How do you iterate making new gradients?
Let's say you make a new like attack class or.
Damage type and then also how do you balance that against your very vibrant and colorful environments?
Like do you mean for example, how do we tackle our color gradients for example LUT textures?
The what, sorry?
The LUT textures
Well, we can, for example, with knockback blast that you saw with the very black and white flashing frames that you're really building up to the anticipation.
Sometimes we invert the colors by accident and it's like, oh, that's cool.
That's cool.
And then we use it for loads of other techniques.
but yeah with colors and everything and other other times we just like for example if it's an electrical field we think that we have to go for those blue or bluish dark blue values so in the end it's mostly going back to our color palettes and applying that to the to the technique also of course if it's something super particular like the electrocution thing we have to go for references outside of the game
So it can be anime references or other games, of course.
So yeah, I think that's it.
Thanks.
Awesome.
Thank you.
No more questions?
All right, cool.
Thank you so much, everybody.