All right, so we're running a little bit behind.
So let's get this one going.
Don't forget to silence your cell phones
and fill out that cute little questionnaire
when you're all done.
I'm Rob Ruppel, and this talk is going
to be on cinematography and concept art
and how they're related to one another.
As an artist, my expertise is in images and design.
So I'm going to focus on their appearance
and why that even matters in video games.
So where do we start?
Let's do a quick overview of the history of images.
Cave art.
Renaissance.
French salon, 1800s.
Perspectives getting better.
That's good.
Photography, cinematography, giggle, pixel photography.
All right, that covers about 40,000 years of image
evolution.
So all art is a translation of what our senses see.
It's a replication of the real world,
and we will never be able to match it
for its fidelity or complexity because
of the vastness of the experience of our own senses
perceiving the world.
That's going to be so much richer than anything we ever
put on a screen or on a frame.
So until we're actually able to record those perceptions from the mind and play them back,
which may be pretty soon, we still have to work within a frame of some kind.
So the mind is constantly selecting and focusing from a sea of information, okay?
This is what makes us different.
We have to make those same choices that our mind does when we're crafting an image.
So great artists and photographers all understand this implicit truth and work within the limitations
of their chosen art form.
This is an old book on photography from the 1950s.
What makes this book amazing was that the author completely understood the camera sees
the world differently than we do as human beings.
And by understanding that difference, we can make it work to say what we want to say.
Because today, we're still going to make images that go on some kind of screen.
Even though we move through them, and they're built in the third dimension,
and they're contained, they're still contained within a frame of some kind.
Now, they need to be readable.
And that is, they need to be visually understandable.
And this is an example of failing to do that, but they're failing to do it on purpose.
But it illustrates why readability is crucial
to surveying and understanding the setting and the intent behind it.
Now, the technical side is getting better and better at reproducing what our eye sees as an HDR photography.
And that begins to mimic the value range that we are able to perceive.
But I don't think the goal has ever been to merely record what we see.
Now this is a snapshot of Yosemite Valley.
And...
This is an image taken by an artist, Ansel Adams
in this case, of that same location.
Now one of these images is dramatic and tells a story
and has a point of view.
And one is merely a record of what it looked like that day.
So let's begin at looking at film
since most realistic games are trying to emulate a film look.
What does that mean?
In the beginning, films were not much more than
photographed plays.
The camera itself was the viewer in the audience,
fixed distance from the scene.
The subject was usually in the middle of the frame.
And the staging, that is the way the characters
related to one another, was generally pretty flat.
Now as the art form evolved, characters
were staged in depth.
We had stronger contrast from background to foreground.
Dramatic compositions added a dynamic element to the frame.
No longer is everything stuck in the middle, very evenly placed.
Liberties could be taken and then dramatic license used
to tell a more interesting story to the point
where we don't even know what's real anymore.
So when I started putting together this presentation,
I really noticed that film and art inspired each other
at the same time.
Illustrators in the 20s and 30s were the stars of their day
in terms of dynamic visual storytellers.
And these ideas and compositions quickly
found their way into the new visual medium film.
The way Dean Cornwell and Howard Pyle
grouped and organized their compositions
can be seen in Ivan the Terrible, which
is Eisenstein's masterpiece of Russian cinema.
The same with Roy Krinkle.
His unique play of shape and value,
particularly in his exotic world illustrations,
seemed to inspire the compositions of Ivan.
I can't help but think that Jack Cardiff was paying homage to Vermeer in this shot from Black Narcissus.
Now, the way cameramen photographed the stars paralleled to how the top illustrators painted their subjects.
The modeling of the form, the quality of the light, was due in no small part to the equipment available.
Fresnel units cast a very strong shadow which mimicked the effect of direct sunlight.
It also helped sculpt the form of the actor
to separate him from the background.
Early cameramen really understood
how flat the screen was.
And they used every visual trick that they could to add depth,
overlap, contrast, foreground, background, silhouette.
And this thinking carried through
to the early color films, too.
Color film, the early ones, needed a lot of light
to get proper exposure.
So they used the exact same principles
that they were accustomed to.
And the illustration of that period
still echoed the look of films and photography.
until new technology and faster cameras and equipment
came along, which led to a more natural, softer look,
mimicking the way the eye perceives the world.
But the good cinematographer still
knows it's about sculpting the form.
like these examples from The Last Emperor,
shot by Vittorio Storaro.
He still shapes the head with light,
but now he can use a soft light and a hard light source,
and he's got some more variety to it,
and it still has a very naturalistic feel,
but it's still very, very, very deliberate
and very, very designed.
So, more than most films,
the next one inspired a generation of artists
and concept designers to the point
where the look established in this film
still find its way into our visual vocabulary today,
even though the film is 30 years old.
I'm talking about Blade Runner.
So before that, science fiction films
were photographed rather conventionally
because the art of the time looked a certain way.
These are some paintings by Chesley Bonestell.
He was the leading science fiction artist from the 40s
all the way through the 60s.
His vision of the future shaped the look and feel
of the films of that time.
But also the way he lit his world
was very typical to the photographic style of his time.
He was a map painter as well as a futuristic illustrator.
Even the amazing 2001 was pretty reserved in its use of light.
Now, one could argue, though, that this film won't date
as quickly either, though.
And as groundbreaking as Star Wars was,
it still paid a huge homage to 2001
in terms of the look of the film and the effects.
Now, Blade Runner began with a unique director
and some great pre-production art by Sid Mead.
But it was the way the effects were photographed.
That approach is what began to set it apart.
So Dave Dreyer, the effects supervisor,
was watching how Ridley Scott was lighting his sets.
The director would layer in all his elements for the depth,
and he would strongly, strongly backlight it.
And then to match that technique for the effects,
they lit their miniatures the exact same way
so that the effects in the film would be consistent,
which of course led the way to a new and very unique look
to science fiction.
Here's a few of the effect shots.
And here's a few random contemporary concept
illustrations.
And so hopefully you can see the similarities, the use of
atmosphere, the strong silhouettes, that have all
become part of our vocabulary from this one film.
Concept art has become very photographic in its style now.
So let's look at some great examples of some classically
photographed films.
But first, I want to start with this quote from Roger Deakins,
which really sums up what's important about image making.
It is not the equipment.
It's what you're doing with the image and why.
It's their context, so to speak.
And here he's basically talking about, yeah, sure,
Citizen Kane, the film grain was all over the place.
Their lenses weren't as good.
But is it a great piece of cinematography?
Absolutely, it is.
And another quote by someone who knows his craft well.
And that's important.
That idea is so important.
Every good photographer alters reality.
They shape the light.
No professional just wanders out there and snaps away.
So why are we trying to dogmatically recreate
natural light when the professionals completely
shape and design it to suit their needs and their vision,
even though the final effect may be completely
natural looking?
Even on a set lit mostly by practicals,
there's still directed light sources to shape the actors
and to alter their values for a better read.
We'll start with Black Narcissus, which
was photographed by Jack Cardiff.
He definitely uses the direction of light and framing
to lead the eye into the picture.
His staging is always the very easiest to read,
dark against light or light against dark.
And I can guarantee you he kept that corner dark in order
to get the nuns to read better.
And look how high key this is.
It's for a reason.
High key is light, airy, angelic.
And the angle of light again leads the eye.
Seems like a really simple concept,
but it takes a very skilled hand to know what to emphasize
and how best to do it.
Notice the light on the door where the little boy enters.
There's a series of contracting rectangles
that surround the boy,
that compositionally forces our eye
to look where they want us to look.
And this is a great example too
of how a nun can be made to look sinister.
The underlining.
the lower key compared to the beginning of the film,
illustrates what's happened with the character.
She's gone through a big emotional change.
Same costume, same actress, different lighting though.
Totally drastically changes how we are now perceiving her.
Third Man, one of my favorites, shot by Robert Krasker.
Most of the compositions were known as Dutch tilt,
which means off horizon, which in this film
leads to the sense of unease that the character has
throughout his stay in Vienna.
He's trying to piece together a mystery,
and he isn't sure what is true and what is not.
Of course, the classic three-point lighting formula,
meaning key, fill, and rim.
This formula, particularly in the rim of the hair,
really helped etch out the character from the background.
And why is that important?
Because the early cameraman understood
that the screen was flat.
And they needed to do everything they can
to add dimension to it.
Especially in black and white, because you have one less tool
to deal with.
One less tool to work with, rather.
Very, very bold use of shape and silhouette throughout the film.
Amazing depth as well, which we'll get into right now when we talk about Orson Welles.
In Touch of Evil, Welles and Russell Metty composed nearly every shot in depth,
meaning a large distance from the front to the back.
Welles seems to have always favored a very wide-angle lens,
and most of his films have this very deep focus look.
Here's a great example of keeping the frame active,
even in a static shot.
The cinematographer has set up a dynamic triangle
to keep the eye moving throughout the frame.
Dark foreground, light midground,
and a lighter background behind the door
gives this shot its dimension.
And that's all designed.
Another nice triangle of faces.
Once you get used to this motif, you see it
used everywhere in the film.
And I love how dark the characters are to the right
and how well grouped they are.
This makes a great shape and a great composition.
You can see how interesting it is in the abstract form.
Here's a great shot.
Light background, dark foreground, which is an X and O.
I mean, how many cinematographers
would have thought they needed the main character
to be lit a lot more than that?
Gordon Willis, another master.
His lens choice, his light setups, his simplicity,
and sophistication are pretty much unequaled.
These are from The Godfather 2.
And while they seem naturalistic enough,
almost like they just sat down and started filming,
it's actually very, very well orchestrated.
All the characters have really good form.
They all stand out from the backgrounds.
There's always a good ratio of dark to light within the frame.
Now this is the rig that Willis developed to light Brando and the sets,
which everyone imitated after The Godfather came out.
They called it a coffin or a chicken coop, and it's that thing on the top of the frame.
It gives a soft, even, overhead light to the actor Brando,
who wanted the freedom to move around the set.
So it was done for a practical reason,
but in the hands of a master like Gordon Willis,
it becomes art.
And even though this lighting feels natural,
it's completely balanced and completely deliberate.
He also uses framing elements to trap and isolate
and silhouette Michael.
And in this shot, it's all about the intensity in Pacino's eyes.
That couch leads directly to them,
and nothing distracts on the wall.
A lesser artist wouldn't have been
aware of subtracting things in order
to emphasize something else.
And Stora, one of the greatest living cinematographers,
all these other guys can sort of be analyzed,
but this guy to me, just completely artful.
Simple, striking, powerful images.
You can analyze and say, well, it's naturalistic lighting,
it's shallow depth of field, it's harmonious color,
but it's his level of artistry, the gestalt,
and that means the sum is greater than the parts,
that for me makes his work so, so amazingly artful.
Every frame was a masterpiece because of its simplicity,
its design, balance, and the choices he makes.
Conrad Hall won Oscars for American Beauty
and Road to Production.
In this shot, look how he isolates Kevin Spacey
on purpose in the frame.
Kevin's afloat, lost in this bleak, gray reality.
The static composition of his dinner
to accentuate the static false nature
of the ceremony of dinner.
The marriage, his life are stuck and stagnant.
Now later, notice the harsh yellow light
in those prison-like bars that make the interior so alien
compared to Lester's change in attitude towards life.
The striking angle of light, too, points directly at them.
In this scene, he's caught off guard by the girl,
so Conrad traps him visually with framing devices.
This is another great scene.
put a lot more color into it. There's a lot more bright natural light
because Lester has changed his outlook on life
and this contrast to his grown-up world and his grown-up job
this one's more bright, more fun, more happy.
Very small spot on the face while the rest of the body goes completely black
strongly silhouetted against the wall.
Road to Perdition. Last film and he won the Oscar for it posthumously.
So this is really brave.
to put the lighter values near the bottom,
it forces us to squint more and pay attention to the face.
He did this in a lot of other films, too,
like Searching for Bobby Fisher.
He knows, as human beings, we're always
going to seek out the face.
And by placing it in an area of lesser contrast,
it forces our involvement.
Great shot of Daniel Craig.
Even the composition is stretched out horizontally
like he is.
Long lens, fog, rain, beautiful silhouettes.
So simple, but deliberate and designed, not accidental.
The window lighting hitting the cabinets
leads us to look directly at Tom Hanks.
Daniel Craig, isolated in the frame
for going against his father's wishes.
He's completely in trouble, and his father looms menacingly
in the foreground, all told with visuals.
Another great long shot of old Chicago.
It was probably shot this way to lessen
the amount of modern buildings around them,
but still incredibly effective.
What can you say?
Art.
Great shot of Stanley Tucci.
Now look how clearly he reads against that background.
In an amateur's hand, the background
would be cluttered and distracting.
Now in this shot, it does have a noisier background,
but it's all designed for a purpose.
The main character, framed against a red covered light,
most of the space taken up with his black and white
photographs in one image, the character and what he does
is introduced.
He's a crime scene photographer, and everything
draws us into what he's writing like a giant spiral.
Who thought Jude Law could be menacing?
Beautiful, beautiful pools of light.
Tom Hanks in the midground standing out,
but not competing with the dialogue in the foreground.
He's there, a presence, menacing, but in the distance.
These are not technical ideas.
These are storytelling, artful ideas.
Pools of light for Tom and his son.
And in this scene, so Paul Newman sits down.
Tom Hanks' head is down, so he blends in with the background.
But when we change focus, once he comes up and starts talking,
and Newman starts looking around surprised
but not wanting to show it, because he's
waiting for him in a church.
Sorry, there's spoilers.
Great shot, great shot, great sequence.
Very loose framing, no sound in this particular sequence.
Music.
We, the audience, do not know where
the bullets are coming from.
closer in, but Paul Newman knows.
The rest are still looking around,
but he's completely still.
Finally, he's accepted his fate with resignation.
It's all told with pictures and no sound.
So his son has been waiting up.
Tom Hanks' son has been waiting up all night,
not knowing if his father's dead or alive.
And that doorway separates him from what we know.
The doorway is a deliberate framing device.
Now, in Raise the Red Lantern, the director
wanted us to feel the same distance, the same disconnect,
that the latest wife feels as she enters her new life.
Her new husband, whom she rarely sees, is a mystery to her.
So the director mimics this with the visual idea
of never letting the audience see him either.
He's always shown in a far shot or from the back.
So we're kept in the dark as to his appearance.
Once film went digital, everything changed.
With a digital intermediate, whole scenes could be altered,
color schemes twisted, manipulated,
contrast ratios completely clamped,
white points completely shifted.
Creates a whole other visual reality,
and one that only exists in that particular film.
It's unique signature, as you were.
These are from Jean Junot's latest film called Mic Mac.
He has a definite color palette in mind,
one that lends a surreal edge to this film.
And if it were color time so that everything was normal,
I think it would really lessen the type of story
he's telling.
So let's see what happens when we take out that color shift.
Not as interesting.
It's pretty ordinary, actually.
So let's put it back.
So his films all have a rule set to themselves.
It's a slightly altered version of reality.
So it's natural the visuals reflect and support that.
His use of extreme wide angles and very theatrical lighting help sell that idea.
Same thing with Munich photographed by Janusz Kaminski.
Different rule set.
This film tends towards a higher contrast look
with lots of heavy filtration.
And these are just tools.
And they're used to create a style,
just as any artist would.
So what are some of the tools or choices, and why?
Each artist makes choices based on many factors.
But they should be choices, and deliberate artistic choices.
Hero, photographed by the Australian cinematographer Christopher Doyle, is one of the most stylized films in recent memory.
He and the director really pushed the idea of color for this film.
Each section had its own strong and very unique palette.
Gray and magenta.
Green and blue-gray.
Gray.
All blue.
Red-orange.
They're all for emotional reasons.
Sleepy Hollow is another good example,
but for shape, probably more than strong color.
Even though most of this is a matte painting,
it still has a very strong Tim Burton feel to it.
The film was photographed by Emanuel Lebesgue,
who's really known for his soft light.
But you can definitely see Tim's influence.
The shape and the sensibility are his alone.
All of these things we consider when we're making a game.
This is an overview of a color script
that we use to map out the emotional beats
as the story progresses.
More detailed section of the lighting change
that's going to take place within the game, in this case,
the cargo plane.
And a different overview of just color bars
we look at to map out where we want the visual design
to be over the entire game.
So where we go next is anyone's guess.
It's exciting, but it's unknown.
And for the time being, it still needs
to take place in a frame of some kind.
And it still needs to use the rules of picture making
we have developed as a species for the past 2,000 years.
Thanks.