Hello everybody, thanks for coming.
I know there's a lot of exciting things happening right now
outside of this talk and even outside of GDC,
so thanks for coming and hanging out.
Talk about fighting games for an hour.
This is kind of a dense talk,
so I'm gonna move a little bit quickly.
I'm going to start,
oop, my music is still going, sorry.
Yeah, so this talk is called 0929,
A Decade of Approachability in Fighting Games.
Real quick, kind of about myself,
I...
I've always been a casual Smash Brothers, Street Fighter player.
My first job, kind of adjacent to the gaming industry,
was at Major League Gaming.
After that, I got involved with a project called Sports Friends.
Worked on a game called Barabari Ball.
More recently, I've been working at the Mighty Iron Galaxy.
Kind of got hired on there to work on Killer Instinct.
There's my two favorite characters on the bottom.
Aganos and Cinder were really fun to work on.
Yeah, so we worked on seasons two and three of Killer Instinct.
A couple notes about terms.
I am using the terms approachability
and accessibility interchangeably.
I know like colloquially we talk about accessibility
in fighting games in terms of like,
oh, make them easier to play and so on.
I wanted to avoid suggesting this talk was about designing
for disabilities, which is important,
but that's not what we're talking about today.
Although if you are interested, there was some great work done
on the audio side of Killer Instinct,
and you can read about that.
I also recommend gameaccessibilityguidelines.com.
A few other notes.
I have like a big tense for fighting games.
So in my mind, like Street Fighter, Soul Calibur,
Smash Brothers, even like Nidhogg and Dive Kick,
they all have like enough in common that we can kind
of talk about them in the same breath.
I'm also kind of in the unusual position
of talking mostly about games I haven't worked on.
So, you know, if you see something you worked on here,
and maybe I say something critical of it today,
know that, you know, this is coming from a place of love
and respect, and like I spend a lot of time thinking
about these games and, you know,
thinking about how to make them better.
So I want to start by talking about a period of time
that's generally roughly between like 1999 and 2009.
If you read a lot about fighting games
or talk to a lot of people who play a lot of fighting games,
you can maybe hear this term like the Dark Ages, right?
So this is like the period of time
between roughly the final version of Street Fighter 3
and like the console release of Street Fighter 4 in the US.
It's a total misnomer.
There's actually a ton of interesting games released
during this period of time.
It's really more of a Street Fighter Dark Age,
but since Capcom was and kind of is still
like a symbolic genre leader,
the story that often gets told is that Street Fighter 3
was like a very demanding game with like a new mechanics,
like the difficult parry system and so on.
And it was inaccessible,
so it kind of didn't retain the massive
Street Fighter 2 audience that Capcom expected and desired.
And around that time,
fighters kind of like fell out of mainstream consciousness.
until 2009, Street Fighter 4 came along,
and that felt and still feels kind of significant,
like kind of the closing of one door
and the opening of another, like the beginning of a new era.
So if we call that time between Street Fighter 3 and 4
the Dark Age, I want to suggest that the time after it,
we call the Expansion Age.
So Street Fighter 4 is a perfect example of.
like how this was kind of kicked off right this is a game that had more approachable mechanics and
kind of online play for the first time and colorful colorful 3d graphics uh and you know highlighting
the original cast so this is all to me seems like a deliberate attempt at kind of appealing to a
larger audience like a broader audience uh not just people who had been playing and continued
to play fighting games but um people may be nostalgic for street fighter 2 or people who
maybe never played street fighter but just know like iconic characters like chun li and guile and
so on
So yeah, so this expansion age, that's like the period of time we're in now, and we've been in for a while.
The defining characteristic to me of this time is developers kind of putting priority on making their games easier to play,
easier to understand, more accessible, more approachable.
And you know, we see this through how developers communicate with players.
If you've read any interview with with almost any fighting game studio, you'll often hear things like,
oh, the game is as deep as ever, but it's easier to play.
Regardless though, this doesn't really seem
to have been as successful as many people might have hoped.
It's still common to even see players
talk about being intimidated.
Even players that play a lot of games,
players that consider themselves hardcore gamers.
It kind of reminds me, growing up,
something that a lot of people,
that you know, music fans would say,
oh I listen to everything, but not country and rap, right?
It's almost like fighting games
are kind of the country and rap.
It's maybe even worse, because there are people
who want to play these games and want to get into them,
but just can't figure out how.
Before we talk about why that is,
I want to kind of,
make something that's, make the case kind of against this process, like a case, a critique
maybe of the expansion age, which I think is a little unusual, especially from a developer,
but I think it's worth articulating.
I think the first thing is there's kind of like a romance of about difficult art, right?
There's a, in fighting specifically that kind of manifests itself in a fear of like diminishing
or like removing the value of skill, like feats of skill.
Tom Cannon, one of the founders of Evo, calls this the drama of humans under pressure.
And I can relate to this, like as a player and as a spectator,
I think part of what is so great about fighting games is how they're so expressive
and like allow for so much variety and reward skill.
Like they're games that don't come to you in the way that a lot of games now do.
And I don't think that's like invalidating.
I don't think that's bad.
I think difficult art is great.
I think composers like Schoenberg and Ornette Coleman and, you know,
performers like Lightning Bolt or Sonny Shyrock are all examples of kind of art
that you need to, you kind of need to work a little bit to appreciate it, right?
I don't think that's bad.
There's also a fear of kind of becoming too e-sports, which to me means a little too mainstream or like too dry and too commercial.
And I can relate to this also.
Like, I think there's this desire to emulate professional sports.
That's a little off-putting.
For one thing, like there's this emphasis on organizing around spectatorship versus participation, which just is a little less interesting to me personally.
Then there's the question, like, do we even know how to do this?
Like, so as a developer, I don't know that we actually know how
to make these games more accessible.
And there's a sense in which kind of tackling a problem
that you don't understand yet is like experimental surgery.
Like, it's unpredictable and weird.
My friend and collaborator, Richard Terrell, has a great example of this process
where he kind of likens it to attempting to like kind of squeeze a balloon in your hands.
And when you try to do that, like, you know, the air escapes between your fingers,
and then you kind of patch that up, and then it just moves and escapes somewhere else.
It's like not solvable.
And I think we'll see a running theme of this talk
is going to be unintended consequences
and weird side effects.
And then finally, well, maybe they're already accessible,
and people just don't like them, which we'll come back to.
There's also a case for accessibility, of course.
Most prominently, it's possible that design of fighting games
has just become overcomplicated and confusing over time.
Many modern fighting games are the result
of a very long tradition of building on existing work
and kind of piling on prior knowledge that
kind of makes it difficult for players and developers
who are steeped in this stuff to kind of understand
how complicated it is, how it looks to a newcomer.
There's also the fact that games are expensive.
If you make a fighting game and you
want to make another game afterward,
that game has to make money, right?
You have to recoup, especially as games become more online
and more games of a service model
kind of become more expected.
This just gets harder and harder.
Then there's the fact that games kind of are a little bit unique to me in that they kind
of need to be activated by their players in a sense.
There's a sense in which when more people play a game, they kind of reveal all the weird,
cool, fun aspects of it that are, you know, they're there in the code as like potentialities,
but you kind of need people to care about them and play them and kind of put pressure
on them to kind of...
help discover the cool truths about the games, right?
Like, seeing people do crazy things
like this tool-assisted combo is kind of just inspiring
and awesome because there's a value in that,
to me, just in and of itself.
And then finally, developers love fighting games.
Like, we do this stuff because we care about it
and we find something valuable in it.
And we actually do want to share them with the world,
so more access, more people is good just for that.
You want to see more of the stuff that you like.
So if it's not clear, I land on the for side
of this argument, but I think the concerns
on the against side are pretty serious.
And if this talk has a thesis, it's that I think
this is a more difficult, or at least a different process
than most people appreciate.
This talk is gonna try to help understand
what developers have tried, what works,
and what doesn't work.
And then at the end, I'm gonna try to offer some thoughts
about maybe what the next 10 years could look like.
We're going to talk about design, rules and features
in a game, and then input, specifically,
the stuff between the player and the characters.
So design.
There's a lot of stress around fighting games about how
to learn how to play or the right way to play, right?
So I want to start by asking, is there actually just something
inherently inaccessible about the design
or the nature of fighting games?
In other words, are these questions and stresses
actually really more intense than in other games?
And maybe they are.
Fighting games are head-to-head.
They're zero-sum, meaning if I'm going to lose, you win.
Actually, in Killer Instinct, there
was a brief period of time where there
was a bug where the people playing online,
their inputs would go out of sync.
So both players could win.
Killer Instinct was briefly the perfect fighting game.
But usually, it is zero-sum.
So when you do lose, there's no one to blame,
which can be stressful, obviously.
In order to improve, you have to interact with strangers,
which is even more stressful.
And then you also need to kind of examine your own behavior,
which is maybe supremely stressful.
But that's all true of all the most popular
enduring 1v1 games.
None of that is unique.
But fighting games do kind of have on top of this
what I consider a pretty unique set of features.
For the one thing, obviously, they're real-time.
So this is an action game where execution and strategy
are both important.
There's no randomness, generally.
We know that randomness kind of has the effects of softening
the effects of skill.
It kind of brings players closer together
at disparate skill levels.
And so fighting games don't have very much of this.
And maybe as a result, they're more stark and a little bit
tougher than a lot of people are used to.
Fighting games also have perfect information, meaning
there's nothing that one player has access to
that another player doesn't.
I can see everything on screen.
There's not really anything.
that you're hiding from me.
For pedantic people in the audience,
I'm gonna fix this a little bit.
Yes, there are characters like Game and Watch and Peach
that have random properties.
And you can think of charged characters like Guile
as having hidden information.
If you can't see what I'm doing with my stick,
maybe I'm charging, maybe I'm not.
So if we look again at like our top games, none of them really have this combination of properties right chess go all these classic games are not real time hearthstone magic also not real time and then they are on top of that heavily random with tons of hidden information clash royale is real time, but it's kind of random and there's a little bit of information and then weirdly to me Starcraft 2 is actually the closest we get it is real time. It's not random, but you know because they're separate screens and because there's fog of war. There is a lot of hidden information.
So I don't think this means the design of fighters
is inherently flawed or limited.
But maybe they cut a little closer to the bone
than a lot of other games.
So unless you're especially gifted,
you're going to lose a lot before you
become decent at these games.
And when you do lose, it can hurt quite a bit.
I think maybe this is the biggest impediment
towards mainstream embrace of these games now.
But at the same time, maybe the biggest gift
for these games to have and the reason why there's so much what
seems to me to be unique passion energy around people
who do play these games.
I know me personally, I kind of think of fighting games as a reality check, as opposed to a
power fantasy.
So many games now are about empowering the player and making them feel like something
maybe they're not, whereas fighting games will very quickly show you exactly what you
are and where you sit.
There was a couple other things I was going to say here, but Patrick Miller actually just
wrote a great article about what he gets out of these games, and I just suggest people
will read that instead because he's much more articulate than I am.
So first thing I want to talk about is training modes,
trial, story.
These are generally single-player activities
intended to help people learn how to play.
So training modes, for example, in theory,
these are like a safe space for players
to experiment and train, not have
to worry about what other people are thinking or doing.
And they're very, very good now.
We have replays, and save states, and AI settings,
and recording, and lag settings, and all sorts
of great features.
There's a couple issues, like learning
how to use a good training mode is actually
more involved than learning many other single-player games
entirely.
They're also entirely self-directed,
so there's no real motivation to use something like this
unless you already care about getting good at the game.
And they're also not very effective
unless you know how, why, when to train, and so on.
There's also an interesting unexpected side effect
of these modes in that in a game that has a good training mode,
the people who want to get good and know how to get good
can get good very, very quickly, which
can kind of separate the skills of the player base
in a surprising way, I think.
You know, we also have trials.
So these are more directed.
Classic examples, Street Fighter IV has combo challenges
for each character.
Dragon Ball FighterZ has a series of kind of tutorials
about mechanics on the extreme side of things.
Under Night In-Birth has this amazing,
massive interactive manual.
Then we have more interactive tutorials.
So Guilty Gear Xrd and Skullgirls did an excellent job
in this.
These kind of go beyond just telling you how the game works
and kind of start.
teaching you concepts.
So in this Skullgirls example, the player
needs to block a series of attacks from the computer.
And then when they block it successfully three times,
they can move on to the next lesson.
So this is cool because it's like it's actually
just teaching concepts, right?
It's kind of repeating and confirming knowledge
and can be very effective.
And then on the story mode, like single player side of things,
we have a lot of single player non-competitive modes.
Typically, these are kind of perfunctory,
like a series of fights against AI.
Traditionally, you go through the whole mode,
and at the end, you get a bit of dialogue or a bit of story.
Modern games have taken this to an extreme.
Obviously, Injustice series has lavish cut scenes
and amazing voice acting between each battle.
We've seen a lot of focus on kind of character customization,
character creation, lots of things for players
to unlock and purchase, kind of be creative with.
So there's a bit of a pragmatic problem here
in just that these are all costly to develop and maintain.
So it's easy to understand why like Mortal Kombat
or Injustice cut scenes are expensive,
but even just a training tutorial,
interactive tutorial mode,
they're not trivial features, right?
They take effort from the design team
and they also take sustained kind of repeated effort
because these are games that change, they get patched
and you can either leave it alone
and maybe teach people obsolete or bad information
or go back and actually touch it up.
Then you kind of have to question if these modes are actually effective at teaching or
even attracting people in the first place.
It's possible that it barely matters because most people don't actually do them.
You can kind of see a very similar curve in a lot of other games.
This is the dojo mode and killer instinct and people drop off very quickly.
It's also possible that, you know, games that kind of put pressure like in their, you know,
in their menus and in their feature set.
If they communicate to you that you need to research and study
to play this game, it's possible that this is actually
worse than doing nothing.
And it's intimidating.
If you look at some of the biggest fighters right now,
Smash Brothers, Mortal Kombat, Tekken, Street Fighter V,
these aren't simple games at all.
But they kind of put less emphasis on learning.
They don't tell you that you need
to train, which maybe makes them more appealing.
A lot of people don't like school.
I know anecdotally, I've seen people fall into a training
trap where they maybe feel like they can't play online
or can't play with their friends until they get through the combo
mode for their character.
And sometimes that can be very difficult.
on the Killer Instinct Dojo, one thing I really liked that we did was
actually encourage people to go away and stop using the Dojo after four lessons. You go play some matches and come back.
There's also, you know, a ton of resources for learning outside of the game now.
You don't need games to teach you necessarily because you can go to YouTube with a lot of very talented people, spend a lot of
time making information easy to digest.
Then as far as story modes go, I think there's a lot of room to disagree about how kind of
important and expected these kinds of features are, but it's not clear to me that they're
like actually appealing to people who don't already care about these games necessarily.
I don't know if they solve an accessibility problem beyond does this game have enough
bullet points on the side of the box to like seem like a good purchase, right?
Like I said, these are typically just a series of fights against AI, which is repetitive.
A common way people have been obscuring this recently is by putting players on a map so
they can kind of self-direct and move around and kind of feel like they have more agency
over what's happening.
But, you know, then it becomes harder to kind of create a difficulty curve that makes sense
or teach players because, you know, they can go where they want.
Encounters become either way too easy or way too difficult.
There's also a trend towards adding modifiers and RPG
mechanics to add variety to fight it, to the fights,
and maybe allow grinding to help players that are struggling.
Personally, this is always frustrating to me
because I end up spending a lot of time in menus
in this kind of game.
And when I pick up a Smash Brothers or a Marvelous Capcom,
I don't expect to be navigating menus for most of my time.
So as a design challenge, I think
there's something really alluring about the idea
of the great single-player fighting game
that maybe will ambiently teach people how the games work
by having them have fun while they're doing it.
I am still a little skeptical.
Unless you're working on a project
that already has a massive built-in fan base,
like a Smash Brothers brawl or Injustice,
if your solution to a design problem like this
is just make another game and put it in your game,
I think it's a difficult path.
That's a very expensive pursuit.
Next up is kind of pacing mechanics.
So this is kind of like mechanics and rules
that attempt to influence or color the flow of a game.
The thinking here is generally,
well, what do players hate?
They hate getting steamrolled and losing badly.
And what do players love?
They love tension.
They love close matches and kind of upsets.
Obviously, competitors would not prefer
close matches and upsets.
They'd prefer just to win.
But generally, players and spectators
actually do prefer uncertainty in their games, right?
None of these mechanics are especially new,
but they're kind of more ubiquitous.
Non-linear health bars, kind of deceptive health bars
is a classic example.
In Marvel vs. Capcom 3, for example,
the health bar kind of extends beyond the X there.
So there's hidden health that you can't actually see.
BlazBlue, Street Fighter V do something kind of similar,
where once your health is below a certain percentage,
all incoming damage is reduced.
This is kind of cool.
It kind of obscures the true game state
so that it appears that the players are closer to losing
than they actually are, which maybe
if you don't know what's happening,
it kind of creates tension.
So that's kind of cool.
There's also comeback mechanics.
Classic example of Marvel's Capcom 3's X-Factor.
Also, Dragon Ball FighterZ has sparking.
These are kind of mechanics that become more powerful
the longer you wait to use them.
Tekken 7 has something similar with Rage Art.
It's like a super move that becomes available
when you're low on health.
Killer Instinct.
Instinct mode, again, a meter that fills as you take damage.
And then once it's full, you can activate it and briefly
get access to new, exciting mechanics.
So yeah, so this is something I've been thinking about a lot recently, even just outside of the context of fighting games.
I think when done well, like these kinds of like rules on top of the game can give a game like a heartbeat or a pulse, like an arc that's really nice.
If done poorly though, it can be very predictable or, you know, even worse exploitable.
If it feels like a lot of gameplay kind of revolves around this mechanic, it's probably too impactful.
Like I think it's easy for these things to become a little too important.
And then, of course, there's an obvious cost
to just piling on meters and mechanics and extra rules
that are outside the basic gameplay.
For a lot of people, just the punches and kicks are enough.
It's easy to see why this might be
overcomplicated for some people.
So then finally, we have rewards.
So we live in a time where it feels like we are.
Most games are bending over backwards to reward players
for playing, right?
That's very much the time that we're in right now.
And a lot of fighting games are doing this as well.
There's a lot of mechanics kind of borrowed from mobile games.
You see in Street Fighter V, Killer Instinct,
you get a daily login bonus when you play the game.
You have in-game missions that you can use to win currency.
Here's me playing Final Fantasy Dissidia,
getting rewarded for jumping three times
and using a special move 10 times in Killer Instinct.
We also have unlocks.
So there's aesthetic unlocks, like the gacha.
There's a gacha game in Guilty Gear
where you can unlock costumes, and colors, and avatars,
and so on.
Then we have more mechanical unlocks.
So famously, Smash Brothers has you
unlock 70-some different characters.
And ARMS, for example, has you unlock ARMS
that you attach to your fighters to try
to change their properties.
Obviously, it's probably more exciting to unlock King Day
Today than color for a character you might not even use.
But there's a cost.
You delay the player having access to the full game.
You make your tournament organizers miserable.
That's definitely a balance there.
And then there's the most meaningful rewards.
So Cache and Clout, a lot of developers
have been organizing their own tours, their own tournaments.
And obviously, most people will never
get to stand on that stage.
But the idea that you could, or the idea
that it's rewarded to be that good
is definitely appealing to a certain type of player.
So I think if you believe complexity is a barrier to accessibility, these are not solutions
to the accessibility problem.
They may aid retention, but I think as these kind of mechanics become more and more ubiquitous,
and I think we're at that point now, basically, I think they probably will start to become
a lot less effective.
And, you know, there's kind of an air of pandering, and maybe it makes it feel like your game
isn't confident, like has a lack of confidence that's compelling on its own when you overdo
this.
Like, you can shower rewards on players.
And it can actually be quite risky.
This is a little outside of the scope of this talk,
but there's been a lot of talk at GDC
in the past of extrinsic versus intrinsic motivation.
And long story short, there's a lot
of research suggesting that when rewards are
contingent and expected, meaning you know how and when you'll
get them, they can actually damage players' motivation
pretty severely.
So next up is input.
This is notoriously the most intimidating aspect
of the genre.
The idea that execution is a barrier to entry,
that you might need to, if you can't throw a fireball,
you might need to practice before you can do that,
is a tough sell to a lot of people.
It's possible these games just ask for too much precision,
too much dexterity.
This is also not a new concern.
Like the original Street Fighter cabinets,
you can see on the right there, they
experimented with the six-button layout we know,
and also this kind of weird pressure-sensitive thing
where you kind of hit the button really hard to get a heavy kick
tap it to get a light kick.
A lot of mechanics that we consider mainstays of the genre
now, like cancels and input buffer windows and so on,
these all come out of early attempts
at making the games easier to play, moves more reliable.
So this is definitely not a new thing.
We also have hardware and cost as a barrier to entry.
What kind of controller should you use?
That can be a big question, especially
in a game like Smash Bros.
You have a lot of options.
Do I need a stick?
What kind of stick do I need?
Then we have experimental controllers and issues
around like, you know, like, you know,
modding hardware and measuring latency and input lag.
There's a lot of overhead to playing these games
the right way.
So it seems like an area where there's a lot that can
be done to help newcomers.
There's kind of two dominant approaches
that I've seen recently to helping players out that I
think are new and interesting.
Assist modes are a first example.
These are just simply control options that if you turn it on,
they kind of simplify the input requirements for various moves.
There's a lot of examples of this in a lot of games.
Guilty Gear, for example, stylish mode
will change the input system dramatically.
It's a dedicated special move button you get,
and simplified blocking and much more.
Then we have auto combos.
So these are like series of moves linked together
by a single button press that you press repeatedly.
So if a combo is a series of moves
that connect without the attacker having a chance
to react, this is literally an automatic combo.
You get a combo just by mashing.
So these are often reduced or non-optimal damage compared
to other combos in games.
And they often end in a super move
that uses a resource, a meter.
So yeah, so assist modes are like kind of generally
considered training wheels or like a crutch.
There's a lot of kind of stigma around these.
And it makes sense, like the idea of, you know,
on a bicycle using training wheels,
there's some stigma to that as well.
And as a result, like a lot of people avoid using them,
even people who actually should use them, you know,
and you can try to avoid this by naming them something nice,
like smart mode or stylish mode.
And I don't think it really helps.
I think people know what these are.
There's also, I call them perverse training wheels.
Like one reason is that they're very predictable, right?
You kind of limit your options so it's
easier for a more seasoned player
to kind of know what you're doing, which
kind of has the perverse effect of making you easier
to fight instead of the opposite, which
might be more desirable.
And you know, maybe they're even worse than training wheels.
Like they may make it easier to do stuff,
like stuff that looks cool, but because it's kind of cordoned
off for the rest of the game, there's
no graceful way to kind of grow into understanding
the rest of the game.
I think looking at Tekken 7 is kind of an interesting example
of this.
They have both assist modes and auto combos, in a sense.
So yeah, the typical Tekken 7 input control is simple.
Each arm has a button.
Each leg has a button.
There is a assist mode where, if you hold down
a new input, the shoulder button, each of those
kind of gets remapped to a predetermined special move.
So this is fine.
This is kind of just on top of the gameplay of Tekken 7.
I think it's harmless.
Then we have basic combos, which this is a toggle where you turn this on and it kind
of replaces two of the buttons with auto combos.
So you kind of lose access, obviously, to a lot of what your character is, a lot of
important options.
So this is, to me, is kind of perverse, right?
It kind of helps you do stuff, but like the stuff you're doing is not really playing the
game.
It's like being able to do short combos or even specific special moves isn't really playing
Tekken.
It's like...
Maybe even worse, because suggesting that it is
might actually make learning how to play Tekken harder,
not easier.
One thing that I actually like about the combo assist
mode in Killer Instinct is that it doesn't lock off
the normal ways to perform moves,
and actually you can kind of enable and disable
each component of it.
The combo system in KI is kind of baroque,
and I'm not really gonna get into it here,
but it is nice that you can kind of ease in
or out of this at any point.
Like assist modes, like the motivation behind implementing
something like auto combos can sometimes
feel like it's less about actually helping people
to understand or play the game, and more about wanting players
to kind of see cool stuff happen often and early.
So a common criticism that these systems kind of encourage
and reward mashing, kind of like the mindless pressing
of buttons.
And in some cases, I think this is true.
Like Marvel's Capcom 3, King of Fighters 14
have auto combos that are kind of just
a series of almost identical normal attacks.
If one hits, they all hit.
If one is blocked, they'll all kind of be blocked easily.
There's not a lot going on there.
But there's a couple nice examples, I think.
If we take a closer look at Linne in Under Night In-Birth,
you can see her first two hits are blocked.
The third hit gets through somehow.
That's because, no, that is a low,
so there's a very basic mix-up, right?
The defender would need to crouch block.
This is an AI, so it's not doing anything.
But you can kind of see how there's a little bit more
going on here than just kind of mindless mashing.
Another example is in Beerus in Dragon Ball FighterZ.
His auto combo kind of has a built-in gap and like a built-in left-right mix-up
You can see again his first two hits are blocked
He kind of skates underneath Frieza because this is a traditional 2d fighting game
You know, you need to hold away to block incoming attacks
But now he's on the other side so the the defender would have to change the direction they're blocking
So this kind of this is nice like they're not optional, right? These are a part of the game
They're not something you turn on or off. You can't
decide that you're opting out of this
because you're embarrassed by it or whatever.
They're also integrated into the game context.
They're made up of cancels and they use hit stun
and they kind of have mix-ups and gaps and so on.
They almost kind of become like a character balance tool
at low level play and maybe a teaching tool.
If you are just someone who's mashing
or you're playing against someone who's mashing,
you'll see kind of important concepts like this
over and over again just because they're built into
to your toolkit.
You'll start to understand, oh, why did I get hit there?
Why do I always get hit?
by that move and maybe you'll discover it's because you need to block certain moves below.
So next is the idea that fewer buttons is more friendly, like less intimidating.
A lot of new games have relatively simple controls.
Of course, the number of buttons that a game uses doesn't actually really tell you much
how a game is played.
There's longer games with fewer than six attack buttons.
For example, Virtua Fighter 5.
has very few buttons, right?
It's a three-button game, but it has a reputation
for being difficult to play.
And that's because they're used in complicated series
and they're kind of require memorization,
like the functionality of these moves is unclear.
And I don't want to overstate this.
I think everyone in this room could learn
to play Virtua Fighter 5 with a little effort.
But just from a kind of casual perspective,
it's easy to understand why you might look at this
and be more intimidated than looking at something
like Street Fighter 5, which, yeah,
it has twice as many buttons, but it has way less
kind of moves and rules, right?
Um, this is it looks like the Chicago train system. That's the CTA. It is actually persona for arena. Um, this is an interesting example because it kind of just demonstrates how complicated this all is. Like, there's a ton of combinations in this game, despite only having four buttons and a lot of contextual inputs, kind of overlapping inputs like.
ABC is an input and also ACD is an input,
which looks kind of miserable,
especially considering most people play this game on a pad.
But you know, actually, when you play on a pad,
those are mapped to, I think,
the shoulder buttons and the trigger buttons.
So maybe it makes more sense to think about this
as a six button game, it's unclear.
So I think number buttons is an incomplete metric.
It's really more of the beginning of a conversation,
not the end of one.
You need to consider how they're used,
how a combination of inputs and sequences,
special move commands and so on,
they kind of.
You need to take that all into account.
The number of buttons can actually
just obscure the real demands of a game's mechanics.
We also know learning a game is not as simple as just
memorizing what a button does and pressing it
at the right time.
There's a lot more going on there as well.
So if that's all true, I think it's
good to know when you actually should add more inputs.
Trust that the ease of use for mid-level players
should actually take priority over this questionable idea
that less is always more.
Guilty gear.
Great example, they added the dust button on the sequel to the original guilty or added this. It was formerly a combined inputs with a slash and heavy slash. I believe this isn't just an accessibility issue. I know in this case like.
This was a way to resolve certain like option selects kind of complexities that are like maybe undesirable and difficult to resolve when you have kind of combined inputs like that, but I think it's interesting for our purposes because it kind of.
calls out the functionality of the dust button to the player.
It's like, this is so important that it deserves its own button.
And it is important.
It's a big part of how Guilty Gear combos are built.
Smash Brothers Ultimate also did something great
with one of the aspects that was my least favorite part
of the game.
Tilts in Smash Brothers are a button combination
where instead of smashing the stick and pressing attack,
you gently nudge it halfway between neutral
and the direction.
A lot of people don't even know that these are moves
because they're kind of hard to discover
and they're small and fast,
and in the heat of battle it's really hard,
at least for me personally, to do these when I want to
and not mess them up 30% of the time or whatever.
In Smash Bros. Ultimate, they allowed you
to map the tilts to the right stick.
And this is great, this adds a whole new stick
for players maybe, but the game is genuinely easier
to play with this, so I think it's a win overall.
And then finally for input, there's this idea
that like...
A lot of the fun and depth in these games
comes from the way that the characters are different.
But what if they were less different?
Smash Brothers, again, is a classic example of this.
You don't have to learn different inputs
for every character.
Everyone, once you kind of internalize the fact
that there's a special button, an attack button,
you combine those directions, you
can kind of pick up most characters pretty easily.
More traditional fighters have been doing this as well.
A lot of the tougher special move inputs,
like 360s, half circles, even dragon punches,
are kind of starting to fade away in a lot of games.
Pocket Rumble has done some interesting stuff
with diagonal inputs and diagonal inputs with holds.
Rising Thunder and the upcoming Granblue Fantasy Versus
put special moves on individual buttons.
While it's on the screen, I just want to highlight,
Rising Thunder is actually an eight-button game.
But it's probably, as far as traditional fighters go,
easier to play than almost anything
we've talked about so far.
Every button has a very deliberate, distinct purpose.
And there's not a lot of overlap,
not a lot of combinations.
There's also kind of a trend towards what I'm calling
dedicated functionality.
We mentioned Phantom Strike Rise of Thunder.
They put specials on buttons.
But if we look at an abridged history of the Marvel vs. Capcom
series, I think it shows something interesting as well.
So all three of these games use six buttons.
Marvel vs. Capcom 2 started introducing two assist buttons
and made the medium attacks a little bit more
difficult to do as a result.
And then Marvel vs. Capcom 3 kind of
continued this, added a launcher button,
which just like we were talking about with Guilty Gear,
it's a great way to highlight that this is.
something important, something to pay attention to.
It kind of reveals it at the cost of another normal attack
button.
But there's so much else going on in these games
that I think that worked out fine for them.
Then finally, what if we did the same thing with combos?
So what if most characters could kind of string together
moves with the same inputs?
We see this in.
A lot of older games also, so X-Men, Children of the Atom,
and Darkstalkers kind of introduced this concept
as a magic series.
But a lot of more modern games are even more freeform.
Street Fighter, Cross Tech, and you
can go from any button to a higher strength button.
Dragon Ball FighterZ is very similar.
You can kind of end it with ki attacks or supers.
On Rainbirth, you can press pretty much any button
in any order as long as you don't repeat,
and you can mix in kind of crouching
to get even more variety there.
So.
These aren't the only combos available in these games,
obviously.
They're just combos that are available to most characters.
And they're usually very easy to perform.
So they have generous buffer windows and so on.
It's also interesting to note that Dragon Ball Fighters
and Undernight have auto combos in addition to this.
So you can start integrating magic series
into your auto combo or vice versa.
You can also mix in special moves.
It's a very open-ended system that
creates a lot of ways for players
to kind of.
optimize their combos at their own speed, right?
And so I think this can be really effective.
I think the best thing about these trends
is that they make it easier to try different characters.
They reduce the overhead of figuring out how to do stuff.
I think that's like a real underappreciated difficulty in appreciating these games for new players
Especially in a game that might have you know
20 40 60 characters finding and like learning a character that you like especially if you maybe you don't even know what you like yet
Can be really daunting and this may be one of the most powerful aspects of Smash Brothers success
I'm kind of calling this like knowledge portability and yeah, I really like it
I think it's a great way for low level players to kind of graduate to mid-level players
Flip side of this for me personally
is something like the Mortal Kombat series, where commands
can almost feel arbitrary and inconsistent.
They don't teach me really.
And it almost feels like the game is difficult to learn
for no reason.
Or it's like the part of the game that I dislike most,
this kind of memorization, just takes longer than maybe it
could.
And yes, so again, buttons can kind
of signpost important mechanics, as we talked about dust button
and launcher button.
It's just a great way to tell players that this part
of your game is important.
And then finally, just the idea that exceptions are OK,
I think is important.
So even if you have this broad outline,
like a skeleton of a rule set for your game,
if it's not always true, that's fine.
Some of my favorite characters in Dragon Ball Fighter
that I play as don't obey their Magic series rule.
And that's OK.
Maybe if that's your first character,
that's a little bit of a steeper learning curve
than it could have been.
But just having that kind of rule
that you can kind of point to, I think,
can be really helpful regardless.
So to conclude input, I think we can kind of like look at two kind of opposing motivations or ways of thinking about action game design in the expansion age.
And I think there's a lot of truth to both. The first is kind of trying to strip away the other stuff to like get to the strategy or mind games.
Right. And the other is that maybe players just want to see awesome things happen when they push buttons.
You know, I think there's truth there. Right. Like this is great trailer moments.
These are like fatalities and.
You know flashy super moves and environmental effects and destruction like this stuff is all really cool
Spectacle is awesome and like a lot a large part of kind of the day-to-day work
I think I'm making a game like this is actually making the stuff that the players doing feel really impactful and kind of feel good
Right and cool. I think it's a little more complicated
Obviously, I think seeing awesome stuff happen as a motivation for why players play games I think is
kind of patronizing and like oversimplified, obviously.
Like things like this are cool.
They're really cool the first time you see them.
They're pretty cool the 12th time you see them.
They're not that cool like the 120th time you see them.
And I think, you know, if we look at tennis, right,
like imagine tennis with cut scenes.
Like that's not obviously a better game to me.
That's probably a worse game.
And it's ridiculous.
And it's obviously ridiculous because we know
that sports kind of thrive on like more organic spectacle.
I'm not even gonna play this video,
because it's so ubiquitous,
but the official Evo Moment 37
probably did more to attract people to fighting games
than any individual cut scene did,
because you watch this and you can see,
you see the people, you see how they react,
you know the players, and you know the stakes,
you can kind of see the health bar.
The rules of the game kind of create the drama,
and that's why these games are cool.
Spectacle's awesome, but genuine tension
is maybe more awesome.
I mean, it is more awesome.
It's not maybe more awesome.
So then there's the idea of the real, there's like a real game, right?
Like if we could only get rid of all this unnecessary, redundant execution,
all this hard, unpleasant stuff, this learning, maybe there's like an idealized
version of Street Fighter where it's just like two minds at battle.
And if we can just take that and get it out of this hard stuff,
the masses will finally understand like what we love about these games.
We see this really explicitly in a lot of messaging
from developers, phrases like, we
want to get you to the fun decision-making part
as quickly as possible, or we want the game
to be out knowing what to do or when to do something,
rather than how you do it, ignoring the fact that doing
something at a specific when is not necessarily a trivial how.
We see a lot of games trying increasingly
radical and dramatic attempts at paring back their controls.
BlazBlue, Crosstag, TookAwayWalk, which actually worked out much better than I expected.
But, you know, we also see games like S&K Heroines, Fantasy Strike, Upcoming Metal Revolution
removing the crouch input, allegedly because it's unnecessary.
But, you know, crouching, like, isn't really an input I have to deal with.
Like, it's part of a stick or it's part of a d-pad.
Like, just from a raw kind of quantity of inputs perspective,
it doesn't really simplify much from that perspective.
And also I'm not convinced it's actually unnecessary.
Despite the fact that there's unexpected consequences,
like in Fantasy Strike, for example,
you can't crouch block, so you can't guard in place.
You need to be walking back if you're trying to guard,
which I'm perfectly willing to accept
that may be competitively viable in a balanced.
well, competitive game, but games themselves are kind of unnecessary.
They're not really all about function. They're not really all about results.
They're not really all about outcomes. There's a sense in which I think removing
something that's so fundamental kind of changes the experience, right?
It's just different. There's a cost and flow and engagement and familiarity.
I'm definitely not arguing against making these games more playable.
I think anyone who knows me knows I'm not someone who fetishizes execution at all, but...
I just want to push back a little bit against this idea
that there's a real game and that someone
gets to decide what it is.
I think another way to think about this,
like about what gets lost maybe when we reduce or remove
execution too much, Magic Re-Gathering, for example.
Would Magic be a better game if you
didn't have to remember what cards were in your deck?
Like if you had a spreadsheet and you could check them off
when you draw them so you know exactly what's coming
and how many lands are left?
Like we could do that.
We can make Magic easier to play.
Who's to say that it's not fair that I have to,
that it's fair that I should have to memorize that stuff?
Memorizing stuff is hard.
But people don't play Magic like that.
Magic is what it is.
The tension, the stresses, and the pressures are there.
Clash Royale, should that game show me
what cards my opponent could be playing
and what their current energy is?
I can derive that stuff if I pay attention and think about it.
But expending that mental energy is part of what the game is.
That's the cost of playing that game.
And removing it isn't obviously better, to me at least.
Finally, I just want to make the case for responsive real-time games.
There's a certain joy in motion control just for their own sake.
When I used to play a lot of Smash Brothers, I would close my eyes
and see the way the characters moved when I tried to sleep.
And that's because those arcs are beautiful.
There's just something cool about that.
This is what dance is.
Anyone who's played an instrument or a rhythm game
knows that there's just certain kinds of combos and actions
that just feel good to do on your hands.
And there's some other ones that just don't.
There's an aesthetic quality to this stuff that's really important.
then you know there's Divekick, right?
So it's hard to imagine a simpler game
that we recognize as a fighting game,
and in a lot of ways Divekick is supremely approachable.
But it's also true that playing someone
who's better at Divekick feels maybe less accessible
than many other games.
When you strip down things so thoroughly,
it almost becomes more likely that fewer options
leads to more oppressive gameplay,
like gameplay that's more dominated by skill,
less room for the kind of messy uncertainty
that we kind of get for free in real-time games
that are fast.
Another way to think about this is being able to hold
the whole game in your head, or hold it in your hands,
not being able to do that, I think is actually good.
That's not bad, that's kind of what's great about these.
We're kind of wrestling with something that's much bigger
than any of us, that none of us can ever master.
That's actually something to be valued, I think,
not tried to eliminate it.
Yeah, so this has been a look at several trends
we've seen develop over the course of the expansion era.
If the question is, are these games easier to play,
I think the answer in most cases is yes, absolutely.
But I think there's also this other question lurking
behind all of this, this whole pursuit for increased access
and increased ease of use is maybe as much about getting
more people to play these games and maybe more bluntly,
how to make more money off these games.
So in the beginning of the talk, I
mentioned how Street Fighter III kind of preceded
the Dark Ages because it was difficult to play and punishing.
You know, maybe that's true. There's another version of that story, though, that might be more true. And that's that story goes in the US at that time. Kind of arcades were declining and consoles were rising and is change in context. Right. This may be had as much to do with Capcom strategy at that time as anything else. And just like the context changed kind of.
In 1999, the context of the expansion era
has had its own unique set of pressures on developers.
We've had the rise of online gaming, the rise of e-sports,
and streaming.
This all means that there's a lot more money
and there's a lot more players in competitive gaming
now than there used to be.
It's a lot more visible.
At the same time, fighting games have fewer players
than a lot of other genres.
It can kind of feel like a niche sometimes.
Audience for games like League of Legends or Fortnite.
just kind of makes it feel like there's a big piece of pie
that fighting games don't get to eat,
like we're missing out on something.
So I think what developers a lot of the time are chasing
is not really just accessibility,
or maybe not accessibility at all,
but just this kind of broad mainstream appeal.
So one path for the next 10 years is this.
We just close the book on the expansion age,
and we start thinking about appeal
as much as we do accessibility.
We can take what we know and love about these games
and kind of experiment with new ways
of making them appealing to more different players.
I think it's very common to see developers more concerned that their game is easy to play
than concerned about who might want to play it or why they might want to play it in the first place.
And I think this is backwards.
You give people a reason to want to see and play your game, I think
you know, ideally you can trust that it's appealing enough to actually have them come to you and kind of put in that effort.
So I don't really know what this is going to look like.
I don't know what the experimental age will look like.
But it might include further attempts at bringing form and function together,
like making these games a little less abstract and more effective at
communicating the rules and their behavior.
It might include more attempts at kind of increasing access,
not just in terms of making sure people are able to play, but
making more people feel welcome.
Kind of reducing the stigma of being new and bad.
We know that no one wants to play a game if they feel like they're not welcome.
It can include working with players, right?
So initiatives like the XO Academy, a training program
that supports women competitors, started by longtime player
and commentator Persia.
It can also include just kind of rediscovering
the value of strange, unique settings, characters, concepts,
kind of the value of creating work
that is just unfamiliar and new.
Or continuing to explore new goals and win conditions
beyond simply reducing the player's health.
So to me, what the experimental age looks like
is devoting resources to features that are interesting,
new, or effective, while avoiding repeating mistakes
or leaning on ill-supported or unsupported truisms.
This absolutely is also not a call
for leaving traditional fighting games behind.
There's nothing wrong with developing games
for an existing audience or a niche audience,
and there's especially nothing wrong with making things
just because you like them and want to play them.
But I don't think our attempts
at kind of expanding our audience can be effective
unless they're a little bit more clear-eyed
and a little bit deliberate.
The expansion era produced a lot of excellent work
and made a lot of important progress.
But if our real goal is to kind of broaden the audience
and find new players, it's kind of a narrow perspective
on its own, it's incomplete,
and it might not be even the most important one.
So thank you very much.
So we're getting kicked out of here exactly at three,
but I guess we have time for a couple questions.
if anyone has any.
Yeah, thanks for the talk.
So you had mentioned that this experimental age potentially
coming up is involve a lot of risk-taking
and I feel like fighting games
as a genre more often than others value a lot of tradition,
you know, adding a new mechanic or new feature to a fighting
game tends to bring a lot of backlash with it.
But on top of that.
games, you know, the higher fidelity we're reaching as we're developing new titles,
the more expensive they're getting and adding these experimental features are,
you know, it's like you said, a risk.
Do you see the Titans, like, you know, Street Fires and the Tekken's
taking these types of risks or just going with the same formula
and not like now they have a working formula?
Yeah, I mean, I'm.
probably not the one to answer that question.
But games like Street Fighter and Tekken,
they're kind of in a tough spot, right?
Because they have a built-in fan base
that if you do make those kind of changes,
they'll understandably be upset.
And I don't, you know, but they're also in a great position
where they get to make more of these games, right?
So I think I wouldn't be, you know,
I'd be pretty surprised if the next Street Fighter game
played like Smash Brothers or something.
But I think there's definitely room for both,
you know, traditional stuff and kind of more attempts
at more experimental work.
All right, thanks.
Hi.
Hello.
Yeah.
So, I think that, you know, the root of sort of this problem is that important mechanics
that affect whether or not you win are difficult, right?
I mean, that's, this talk, and I think from what I've seen, most attempts have been to
try and reduce the difficulty rather than alter the importance.
Do you think there's any room for, like...
you know, okay, like combos, right?
Okay, you need combos, you're gonna get beat up
if someone can do them and you can't.
Do you think there's room and can you think of any example?
Do you know of any examples of people shifting
the significance of the mechanics
rather than their difficulty, if that makes sense?
That's an interesting question.
I mean.
I think there's long been games that aren't just about combos, right?
Like games like Samurai Shodown are much more high damage and not about really memorizing specific inputs.
And then you have games like KI which have a pretty unique combo system that, you know, it's got its own challenges,
but it's definitely very different than a lot of other games.
I mean, I think Smash Brothers is a good example of that,
right, like games that have a very different win condition
is maybe the most fruitful thing to explore in my opinion,
just because it totally changes the focus
of what players are looking at and what you even need
to make a game like that work.
So, yeah, I hope so.
I hope we see more interesting things like that.
Thank you.
Hi, you spoke about the difficulty graph
between trying to get new players into the game
and how RNG has helped doing that in other genres.
In fighting games, how much are fighting games looking towards that?
Or are they shifting towards that?
Or have you seen such things happen in fighting games
where they add RNGs to basic attacks or stuff like that?
Yeah, not really.
I mean, Smash Brothers is a classic example of this as well, right?
Like, that game, you can put on crazy items and crazy levels
and anything happens.
And I mean, I think it works really well for them in some cases.
Yeah.
I'm struggling to think of other recent examples.
I'm sure there are some, but nothing is springing to mind.
I don't know, timing-based, like you're just at the right time,
then you match.
Otherwise, it's an RNG based on your punch power or something.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't think we've seen the great kind of way
to add randomness to a more traditional fighting game yet.
I'd be very interested to see what that looks like.
I think SNK Heroines has random item drops or something.
Honestly, I'm not totally sure how that game works,
but you may see a little bit of it there.
Okay, sounds good, thank you.
Thanks.
How do you see the resurgence of the arcade?
Because I know it's like where I'm from, North Carolina,
I can just drive within like an hour
and be at four or five different arcades
and they keep on popping up.
How do you see arcades impacting the future
of fighting games in the future
as they tend to be a social game?
Well, you know, as part of Sports Friends,
actually like our big kind of motivating factor behind that
was kind of to kind of emphasize
how great it is to play local multiplayer games together,
right, like playing something in person with,
with someone else is way more exciting for a variety of reasons, maybe more stressful
too.
I think like we still, you know, Killer Queen is like another interesting example, right?
This is like a game that's kind of taken over a lot of arcades and kind of really is like
spread pretty far around the country.
So I mean, I think there's definitely like an opportunity.
I think again, like Killer Queen is a really unique case because it requires so many players,
like almost like a built-in spectacle for it to work.
So I think there's a lot that could be done there.
I don't know if we've.
Yeah, beyond that, I don't know if we've seen the great local fighting game yet either,
but that's something I personally would really look forward to.
Hey, I wanted to ask about non-fighting game franchises crossing over to fighting games.
How much of a factor do you think that would be for the future?
Because I got into fighting games because of Persona 4 Arena,
and then by extension Under Night In-Birth, and then Blaze Blue.
And I played Soul Calibur because 2B was in it,
but do you see that being like a very important thing for like sustainability of fighting games?
Oh yeah, definitely. I mean I have a whole section of the talk that I cut about that,
but like I think we're already there, right? Like you...
Basically, it's very difficult to find a fighting game that
has no guest characters in it right now.
So yeah, I mean, I think that's kind of been
something we've kind of seen in the last five, six years
kind of become almost ubiquitous.
I think it's great.
I mean, one of the great things about fighting games
is they're so character focused.
And you kind of are looking at beautiful animations
for most of the time you're playing the game.
So it's an obvious fit if you want
to see Persona characters in a whole new light.
Maybe there'll be a Fire Emblem fighting game sometime.
That would be kind of cool.
Yeah, I'm down for that.
That's a good point.
Patrick says it's called Smash.
Stand corrected.
Hey.
Hello.
Sorry, it's hard to see.
Even though games have been getting more and more
tutorials, I feel that people's most learning material is still
acquired outside the game.
You see a possibility of a trend of the.
the games themselves providing players the tools to create and share tutorials for other players?
We've seen some games that have kind of like in-game examples of ways to like share replays
and kind of like talk to people about them, but I mean it's just so expensive. Like to do this
stuff well it's really adding a lot to your development cost and that you know is of
questionable value in terms of...
making the game actually attractive to people.
So I wonder, I mean, there's an interesting company now
that's doing like Overwatch video analysis, right?
So you send them your gameplay and it has some tools
that'll like point out things you could be doing better.
And then you'll have people will kind of analyze it
and kind of report back and say,
here's the stuff you should focus on.
I'd love to see something like that.
A lot of people suggest a clippy for fighting games.
I've heard many developers say that something like that
would be really interesting.
I mean, personally I think something like that is,
you know, clippy doesn't really work,
so I don't know if a fighting game version of that
would work, but I'd love to see it.
Yeah, I just think it's tough to justify sometimes,
but that is definitely something I'd love to
kind of see developed further.
All right, thank you.
Hey, you talked a bit about how arcade games,
arcade fighting games has always been a big thing
and how losing to someone that you're sitting next to
is very different to losing to someone on the internet.
Do you think that online fighting games,
do you feel like that's changed the way people go
about designing fighting games?
Maybe it should have when it hasn't, things like that.
In terms of just how their sportsmanship
kind of comes into play?
Yeah, I mean there's another slide that got cut.
Like there's a kind of interesting thing I think that
Killer Instinct and I believe Marvel vs. Capcom 3
borrowed from League of Legends,
which is just like if you have a player
that's rage quitting a lot or maybe that gets reported,
they go into this like jail now
where they're only able to match make against other players
that are also kind of in that punishment zone,
which is kind of interesting.
I don't know, I mean a solution that kind of makes your,
like a lot of these games struggle
with having enough players
that you can even like get a good connection
against someone that's like roughly your skill level
in the first place.
So kind of like segmenting that.
even further is tricky, but yeah, we've seen a little bit.
I mean, you're always in the context of like an Xbox Live
or a PS4 where someone can just kind of send you
a nasty message anyway, so unless you disable that,
which I guess I recommend, then it's hard to say
how effective it can really be.
All right, thanks.
Cool, thank you for a great talk.
I know a lot of the examples you went through
and showed were console fighting games.
I was curious if you had any thoughts
on a lot of mobile fighting games,
especially major IPs that have brought their games to mobile
and touch inputs and things like that
in terms of more accessible ways for people to go through
and get into fighting games as a whole.
I don't really.
That's kind of an area where the kind of
input reduction stuff kind of gets.
so far that I kind of just as a player just lose interest.
Like I don't really want to play an action game on my phone,
much less a very simplified fighting game.
So it's just, yeah, I guess I don't have much to say,
because I don't know too much about them.
Thank you.
Hey, this is a great talk.
We as a genre and an industry really
need to kind of band together to kind of figure this stuff out.
So I really appreciate this talk.
My question is, so for Injustice 2 post-launch,
Kind of redid the whole tutorial and sorry which which game for injustice to
So for post launch for the game of the year edition ultimate edition, whatever we called it right like a year after launch
We redid everything and made it all like a la carte and let it make it be a lot less linear and trying to give
players what they want and kind of
break down that barrier a bit where players would be leaving the game to go to YouTube
to learn a little bit and just trying to make it a bit more accessible.
One thing that we really wanted to do was create all those tutorials within the context
of the game.
So something our designers were less interested in was the kind of Guilty Gear style of like,
here's these balloons popping out and you, you know, low, medium, high, that kind of
stuff.
I was just kind of curious on what your thoughts are
with teaching within context versus these kind of
mini game more fun-ish style of tutorials.
Yeah, when you say in the game,
you mean as part of the story mode,
like you kind of build it?
Well, no, I mean our tutorials aren't
in the story mode itself.
I just more mean within the context of the fight.
We're not adding these extra fun mini games
to help teach you what a mixup is versus,
no, here's a character that is blocking high,
like hit them low versus.
the more mini game aspect.
Right.
Do you think the mini games help?
Are they better?
I think they're probably better if you're actually genuinely
trying to learn, because you can repeat them and do them over.
And the Skullgirls example I like a lot,
because you're not going to get past that until you internalize
what you need to know to block that properly.
So I think from that perspective, maybe they're more effective.
But.
I mean, given that so few people use it,
then it makes me wonder, you know,
maybe it almost doesn't matter, right?
The answer you need is the one that gets people
to actually engage with it.
So I'd be interested to know if you,
do you have any metrics about how it went?
I mean, I'm sure our BI team does.
Maybe you should give a talk next year.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I don't know. It's just an interesting thing to be dealing with the context of like,
hey, you're in a fight. This is the more strategy component of it. It's not as simple and black and
white as like, do these things. You need to be in the context of the situation. And yeah, like I
said, our designers were a little bit less interested in the more mini game-ish aspect
to keep you grounded and teach you the actual situation that we're trying to put you in.
Yeah, I was actually just talking to my friend and co-worker Isaac Torres about this similar issue.
I think there's a lot of room for using what little we know about cognitive psychology to help people,
you know, help build these things in a way that actually reflects how people learn.
a lot of the problems, you go through these modes,
and okay, here's like 60 bits of information
that I kind of just swallow in an hour,
and then I play the game and I've forgotten it already,
so what do I do, go back and do it again?
It kind of sucks, there's probably a better way.
Yeah, and there's also, I guess,
a little bit of the added extra layer
of like creating these mini games is more assets,
it's more resources, it's more costly,
and it's certainly something I think we could have overcome
if our designers had chosen to go that route,
but it's also really hard to develop a tutorial for,
a game that's not complete yet, too.
That's a really good point.
We have to always do this at the end.
Yeah.
Thanks for the talk.
Thank you.
Three more questions?
What was that?
Three more questions.
So you talked about the obvious issue of great complexity
and a whole lot of decision depth being
unapproachable to newcomers.
But Divekick has the opposite problem,
where the decision space is small enough
that an expert can retain and think ahead much
more easily, do you think there's a happy medium on that, or that the solution has to be orthogonal
to that decision complexity? That's a good question. I think there's probably a happy medium,
I mean it's probably, but you know it's all aesthetic also, like there's games I like because
they make sense to me, and there's games that like I just don't play, you know they may be
great games, but they're just not for me, so it's like hard, there's no like objective answer, so I
kind of don't even want to try thinking about it.
Something I think about a lot that I had to cut, unfortunately, because this talk went
a little long, was this kind of property of having a real-time game creates uncertainty
in that it's so fast, right?
I'm pressing light punch, you're pressing light kick.
I can't react to your light kick because it moves so quickly that it's not random, but
it kind of has a lot of the same stuff that randomness gets us, which is meaning, like...
It's yeah, it's uncertainty, right which is yeah, there's a there's there's no we can point to exactly why you're like it came out
But I don't know that it was gonna come out
So we kind of get just by virtue of being like a complicated real-time game. We get a lot of that messiness
That's what I was trying to get out with like the dive kick example. Like it has a little bit less of that
And so that's why maybe playing that game against someone who's very good might be like more punishing, right?
It's just something to like be aware of as we like strip things away
So I get to this idealized point where it's like all mental
there's maybe an unexpected consequence, which is that we lose the mess.
And the mess does a job.
Thank you.
Thanks for the talk, it was excellent.
When it comes to fighting games, I'm always particularly interested in how they kind of tax the human brain.
And a lot of the stuff, you just mentioned it, right?
we know as experienced fighting game players,
we get to understand the limitations of our brain
by trying to do things and failing,
and then eventually realizing that this thing is actually
not possible to do on reaction.
It has to be a read, et cetera, et cetera.
And I'm wondering, have you encountered other activities,
like not fighting games, where you
see similar kinds of mental limitations,
essentially, that the players have
to learn how to negotiate?
That's interesting.
I mean.
I'm not much of a chess player, but I imagine playing chess on a clock is probably similar,
right?
Like, you don't have time to calculate everything, so you kind of have to find shortcuts.
I don't know.
Giving a talk can kind of be like that.
It would be easy to write an email and kind of respond to everything really thoughtfully,
but in the heat of the moment, you need to really kind of think on your feet, which is
obviously hard.
I think...
Sorry?
Yeah, I think, I mean, that just made me think of like,
oh shoot, I guess we're over time, but real quick,
it makes me think of, you know,
we kind of like valorize depth, right,
and there's a lot of players like,
this game is great because it's very deep,
but then it's like at the same time,
when you're actually engaging with it,
like so much of what playing these games well
is like finding shortcuts and workarounds,
like I don't want to do the hard thing,
like even if the hard thing gets me 10% more value,
like I'm not gonna do it because I might screw up,
and also like I don't really like doing things
that are hard when I'm playing a game.
So you kind of find your comfort zone,
whether it's mental or physical, I think.
It's kind of an interesting counterpoint to the idea
that these games are good because they're deep, which
is also true, but it's not the whole story.
Was that three?
One more?
I'll just talk after.
Is that cool?
Talk to you after?
Oh, yeah, sure.
OK, yeah, thanks so much, everybody.