Hello everyone, this feels very much like I'm back in school.
If you want to push up, please do.
So today I'm going to talk about my journey from a modder and a real non-gamer to being
creative director on PUBG.
This is not a technical track.
This is more kind of my personal story over the last
four years and how I ended up being here and
talking to you guys.
I was quite nervous about doing this because, as I said,
it's not a very technical track.
I'm not going to be able to tell you how to scale to 3
million CCU.
That's way out of my field of expertise.
We have wizards back in Korea to do that, and hopefully
they'll be able to come and talk someday to you guys.
So.
So I started in Brazil.
I was there for about six years total, living, working mainly
as a photographer, sometimes as a DJ.
And I really like photography in general,
because it captures an experience.
It captures a moment.
And it's something I've done most of my life.
I was also a designer doing flyers, photography for bands,
other graphic design work. This really helped me coming into gaming as well because as a modder
I had to do a lot of the stuff myself from the art for the game to how it was perceived by the
general public. Most of my photography was kind of rock event photography, candid photography.
As I said I loved capturing a moment, something in time that people can look back at and talk about
That's kind of why I like games like DayZ so much,
because they kind of create that water cooler moment.
Same with PUBG, that I meet fans and they
talk about the moment they had with their friends.
And in photography, I really like capturing moments
like that and then having friends look back at a photo
and go, oh, I remember this.
So speaking about DayZ, my
gaming history, so to speak, is not huge. As I said, I'm not a massive gamer. I was very much like I,
growing up, I gamed a little. My first experience in multiplayer was on Telnet using MUDs with a
friend in college. After that, I played, of course, some of the AAA titles like COD and Assassin's
Creed, but my first kind of...
love on multiplayer gaming and my first experience with sort of large-scale
multiplayer gaming was at Delta Force Blackhawk Down. I loved this game. It was,
you know, it was a realistic simulation. The single-player was good, but really it
was multiplayer that really pulled me in, you know.
There were so many different maps created by the community,
there were different game modes around those maps,
and there was such a depth of gameplay available.
And it had realistic ballistics,
and it simulated a real world, or so I thought.
And I loved that, and I played so many hours of this game.
And really, like looking back now and reflecting
when writing talks like this is...
you know, really heavily affected me as to what I like in games.
Then the servers kind of died in that and I found America's Army 2.
And again, at this stage I wasn't really gaming a whole lot.
I would be working on design or photography and coming home at night
and maybe playing a few hours.
And America's Army 2, it really, again, looking back,
I love that type of game.
It was your...
your mistakes had consequences.
If you did something stupid, you died.
And I like that.
I like when a game punishes you as a player,
because if you're not punished, you won't learn,
and you won't become better at the game.
The idea that you died at the middle of a round,
and then you couldn't play, and you
had to watch your teammates, I really liked that.
It was punishing me and making me learn.
So Battle Royale, why I'm here today.
I was sort of saving to come home in Brazil at the time, and I had sort of discovered
the DayZ mod.
I think I saw a Reddit thread on it or something, and found it, found Arma 2, and started playing
Again, talking about these kind of experiences in gaming,
I remember very clearly the first time one of our clan
got the helicopter on Stiliski Island and flew it to us.
And there was this real tension and nervousness
that some other squad would come and wipe us out
before we got in the helicopter.
And those kind of moments,
I fell in love with that sort of open world game.
It drew me back to gaming.
A lot of the AAA titles, and especially story-driven ones,
they didn't...
deliver what I wanted from a game, which was kind of freedom.
And DayZ really opened up that sort of idea that here's a world,
there's a set of rules, go and survive.
You know, there's no rules to it.
Well, there are rules, but you know what I mean.
It's the gameplay is invented by you rather than the game.
So this concept I fell in love with.
I ran a DayZ mod server for about six months, a year.
There's a guy called Devil Walker.
He offered me, he said, listen, I'll buy a server if you want to add some scripts in.
And we did and we kind of built up a community.
And, you know, we talked with the community and figured out what they wanted from the
DayZ server.
And it ended up being very much a PvP game rather than a survival game.
So we upped the loot rates.
We just experimented with, you know, how the gameplay.
happened on the server. As I said, it was centered around PvP and it was my first
kind of experience into game making and level design and you can see in the
background there there's some like of the locations I kind of put in to
increase where people got weapons, increase hot spots around the map and
try to differentiate our DayZ server from the many others.
I created this thing called the Arena, which was again an attempt at level design, an attempt
to create a space that we could put players against each other.
It wasn't hugely popular, but it was me trying to figure out ways to make every match unique,
every situation, and just pit players against each other.
So out of that came DayZ Battle Royale.
This was my first experience in trying to...
be the game master and trying to create this game.
I had seen the Survivor Games, an event by Brian Hicks and Jordan Thayer, hugely popular
and a wonderful riff on the Hunger Games but in the DayZ mod.
It was streamer only and I wanted to play and I wasn't a streamer so I saw some of the
stuff they were doing.
I thought I could do it better.
You know, the ever-decreasing circle,
instead of having a game master decide where the circle was,
you know, these kind of things that you
were fighting against the computer when it
came to the game mode itself.
I liked what they did, but as I said,
I thought I could do it a little bit better.
And Battle Royale was born out of that.
It was me making a game that I wanted to play with my friends.
I released it, some teaser images as you can see there, on Reddit.
It was kind of...
It was received quite well and when we launched the servers we
really had...
Oh, you know, a crazy influx of players.
I would see the game chat when we launched Battle Royale,
and people would be saying I was trying to get into these servers for two days.
Now, at the time we had six servers, you know, there weren't many games,
and I had to restart servers all by myself.
The first two or three days I didn't really sleep,
because there was no code there to shut down and restart the server.
Eventually, Bohemia did add it to the core code in ARMA,
so now you can do that, but at the time I had to...
you know, beg and borrow people to, you know, write systems that would do this,
because I'm not a technical person, I don't know how to do this.
Even the code for the original, you know, Daisy-Bout-Royale mod,
you know, I spent a month writing a timer, you know, just a timer that would just
time everything in the game. And this is like very basic code, but, you know, it
took me that time to figure out how to do it and get it to work
in the sort of the ecosystem of Arma.
So I believed that building up a lore behind the game
would also help people sort of buy into it.
These are kind of early kind of photographs
I'd publish on via my Twitter or post to social.
The one up on the top, you see one
of the very first airdrops, I guess, in Battle Royale
was when we were testing and getting these photos.
Originally, it was started like the Hunger Games.
You have the round circle of.
where everyone would start, and a cornucopia in the center.
You know, this was why in Battlegrounds,
the very first alpha test, we ran people out of a building
because it was harping back to what we'd done in Arma 2,
Battle Royale, just to see if it worked.
Eventually, we chucked people out of a plane,
and it's a much better way of doing things.
This was the original map for Battlegrounds,
or for Battle Royale.
You can see all the systems there, the blue zone, red zone,
and there's the start position where everyone ran from.
I was really, you know, we did Daisy Battle Royale
for about, I'd say about three months, four months total.
The Daisy standalone came out
and kind of tore players away from us.
But that really kind of gave us the chance
to move to Arma 3 and pair down to the Battle Royale game,
what everyone kind of knows today.
DayZ Battle Royale was fun for me though because we had zombies.
It was DayZ, right?
I had so much fun spawning, you know, we were coming up with ideas for hordes of zombies
and really like a PvE battle royale as well as PvP.
If you were outside the zone in those days, we just spawned zombies around you, so you'd
see people running into the zone with a trail of zombies, which was great fun.
But I added way too many, because I just, you know, I liked that intensity.
It's what I loved about DayZ in those early days was that the PvE was like really...
hard, you know, that you you it was a challenge and I like that in the game
I like dying in games because you know, you want to go back and beat it
So, I know it's a double slide sorry
So Arma 3 battle royale, this is again, so people had moved to Daisy
the standalone and I decided Arma had come out of alpha and
I wanted to pare it down, get rid of the PvE elements, well apart from the red zone,
and really pare down what Battle Royale was as a game mode.
over its life of about, it's still going today, you know, but at its peak we were getting
what about a hundred or a thousand CCU, which for a small mod was, was, we were happy with,
you know, we were getting tens of thousands of players every day and, and, you know,
we really had a very strong community.
You know, I've built a team over the last three years that now they handle pretty much everything
to do with the mod from adding new maps, to adding new content, to making changes and
you know they have the same passion for just making a really super simulated battle royale in Arma 3.
You know, over the years, the community, and it's something we continued into PUBG, was
we really wanted to, like, involve the community because they're the ones that play your game
and getting feedback from them is so important.
In the early days, when I first came to ARMA,
if you have never gone into the ARMA modding community,
I really strongly suggest you do.
There's such a wealth of content and ideas and scripts
and just people playing with the ARMA engine.
I say to anyone that wants to create a 3D shooter, e-game or anything with a realistic
world, try your idea in Arma, try your idea as a mod for something because there's a huge
player base out there.
There's still hundreds of thousands of people that play Arma on a daily basis.
there's people there to play your idea and it really allows you to iterate
quite quickly because the content is already there and
and trust me there is such a massive amount of content and armor
you know you'll be spoiled for ideas. So again
coming back to Battle Royale I was really trying to pare down the idea that
this was a random fight. It was
designed to
test a player in a moment rather than by a knowledge of a game.
I had moved back to Ireland. I was in my parents' house
in kind of an office. This was my battle station at the time,
which PC Gamer did a feature on which embarrassed the fuck out of me.
But at this time I was still making the mod.
I'd moved back to Ireland.
My parents were asking me what was I doing.
I was making a mod on Arma 3.
I wasn't making money from it, but I had belief that this
could be something great.
They didn't understand that.
They were like, would you not think?
Because I was in my mid-30s.
I didn't have a career.
I was a photographer and a designer, essentially out of
work, because as a freelance designer and photographer in
your 30s in Ireland, it's tough to enter a market.
I'd been out for six years.
So I was doing this in the hope that
something would happen.
There's some things I'm very proud of in the...
Why is this not playing?
Ah, there we go.
No? Ah.
So this is the loot system in Arma 3.
So this is showing you how high and low density loot
is spread around the map over the course of many rounds.
Obviously, you guys know this.
I'm really happy with how it works.
You know, we spent a long time trying to figure it out.
It's a very basic system.
You know, there's high tier and low tier loops.
Then there's high tier and low tier areas.
It just gives the feeling every time that it's a random game.
You know, I would watch Twitch streamers talking about the
loot system in Arma 3, about how we change stuff.
And I can tell you in about the two years that the Arma 3
model has been popular, we haven't really changed the
loot system all that much.
You know, we might change it maybe once every six months,
but really it doesn't change.
But the way it works, it delivers that kind of
feeling of newness every game.
Praise Orange Jesus.
You know this is something I very much espouse is like
I'm very careful I talk with our design team who are great and sometimes it's
a
It's hard for me because I really try to get the idea that you shouldn't design the game.
You should just create the system and let people play it.
With new modes, it's like, we just adapt the systems we have and make new modes, but let
the players come up with the actual gameplay because they're so inventive.
and some of the ways they choose to play a game is nothing you can plan.
And, you know, I'm very careful about designing the game too definitely.
So leaving it, like, I love that emergent gameplay. I know it's a buzzword, but, you know,
Daisy showed me, like, listen, any story can be the story you want, you know,
that you can tell your story and designing these...
open world survival PvP games.
It's having these games that generate these water cooler moments,
you know, is something I love that we're able to do these days.
In ARMA 3 I reiterate it a lot, I love our game modes.
With our event servers in PUBG it's kind of expanding on this idea that,
you know, we have many ideas for new game modes and
we have a lot of stuff internally.
I have history in ARMA 3 that, you know, it's just a great
thing to be able to play in and provide new experiences for our players and we
want to do that with with our event server. I did Street Fight which was
based you know Altus it's 20 kilometers by 20 kilometers it's a massive map in
Arma and it gave me so many different cities that you could just focus a battle
royale in that city with pistols you know so fun and just a different spin on
the battle royale game mode.
just using and abusing the arsenal in Arma.
They had tanks and rocket launchers and heavy artillery.
And why not have a battle royale like that?
Because it wasn't done at the time.
And I thought, OK, let's play with it.
So at the time, we were still getting 1,000 CCU in Arma
at this stage.
And I was quite happy.
But again, I was kind of looking for a way to make my own game.
there was nothing out there for me at the time.
I tried to look into Unreal.
I tried to look at making Battle Royale as a standalone game.
I'd reached out to Bohemia, and they were just
busy with DayZ and Arma that they didn't have time.
So at this stage, not I had given up,
but I was really kind of wondering what would happen.
Then H1 happened.
So I'm really, I say I'm the luckiest man in gaming.
And this is part of this, you know.
They had mentioned in some of their Dev Talks
that they liked what I'd done in Arma 3.
And I thought that was great.
Thanks for mentioning me.
You want to help?
And sure enough, John Smedley sent me a DM saying,
hi, I'm John.
Let's talk.
I didn't sleep that night, and the next day he rang me and he offered, let's come to San
Diego and talk about adding and licensing the Battle Royale game mode into H1.
And the rest, you know, kind of is history, right?
It sort of helped cement the Battle Royale game mode as a new sub-genre, right?
H1 really got it in front of a lot more eyeballs.
They did some great things.
I saw the first Invitational.
It really kind of showed off what
Battle Royale e-sports could be.
I was there in TwitchCon.
there were queues of people every day to try to qualify for the finals and we had I think about
2,000 people in the auditorium and a lot of people online watching and that for me was the first
sign okay it's what I always thought when I started this that battle royale could be an
amazing new e-sport and a spectator sport that has spectacle right and seeing this it was the
first kind of sign of that and I was really hopeful but
You know, they wanted to go a more kind of simpler route than the battle royale I wanted.
So you know, I let them do their own thing with H1 and I moved back to Arma 3.
So again, going on the idea that I wanted to create more and more spins on battle royale
because modding allows you to do that very, very easily.
I teamed up with the Ironfront team.
And this again, this is why I love modding, right?
It's so much fun.
Iron Front the game, you know, is an oldish game.
And the Arma 3 engine is a great engine.
And the two teams kind of synced up,
and the company gave the Arma 3 modding team
the assets to use, or permission to use the assets,
so they could spin up Iron Front inside Arma 3
with the, you know, advanced ballistics
and this kind of stuff.
So, you know, I love that about modding of this,
like this older game is now getting rebirth in,
So I teamed up with the Iron Front because who doesn't want a World War II Battle Royale?
And I decided, right, let's see if we could do it.
This was the trailer we made for...
So, yeah, so that's our In Front Battle Royale.
And this was all, the video was edited by me.
We, you know, we set up a server to record all this.
But, you know, all the stuff I had done from graphic design to, I was a video editor for
photography, it all kind of, you know, it was all helping create these mods and create
these mods with this kind of produced stuff.
So it looked like, okay, this is something serious.
So H1Z1 released King of the Kill,
or split the games into King of the Kill and Just Survive.
And I got an email from C.H. Kim.
Nope.
There we go.
Right.
So I got an email from C.H. Kim from Bluehole saying,
hi, I'm a Korean producer,
and I've wanted to make a Battle Royale game
for about 10 years now.
I've seen what you've done, I love what H1 have done, would you be interested in coming and talking to us about making a game with us?
I had looked into Bluehole and they were an MMO company so obviously I had reservations
but I flew to Korea.
I met Mr. Kim, or Dr. Kim should I say, and Sammy.
It was snowy February and it was wonderful.
I went to Bluehole and it was like a very big family.
They all have this passion for making well-made games and from the very start we went.
We drank with a big black bar.
I thought this was a glitch earlier.
But this is us drinking.
So we went drinking.
We went talking about what we wanted to accomplish together.
And the more I talked with
CH, the more I discovered that what he wanted for a game was very much what I wanted.
This platform for a great battle royale game and more than that, the idea of modding, the
idea of working with the community and being very open in development.
So I decided very quickly to work with Bluehole.
I moved out.
I think about two weeks later, the day before my 40th birthday, we started working on Battlegrounds.
You know, it was very, it was crazy in that sort of early days of development, because
we were pushing hard, you know, we initially wanted to release in about, I think about
nine months, and there was a lot of effort from the team, you know, there was a lot of
long days, and it wasn't because we wanted people to work, it was like we all believed
those early kind of playtests.
those early iterations on the idea,
it was already generating fun within the company.
I remember seeing...
when I went to H1, the first time we got a playable battle royale in the game,
you know, you had these old devs, you know, of like, you know, veteran devs
that were having fun and shouting and screaming at each other and just enjoying the game.
And it was the same when we came to Bluehole, those first iterations that we had,
you know, the team, they would gather behind each other, you know, they would,
you know,
look at, you know, cheer on the one winning. It was just a wonderful experience, and it's still to this day, you know,
if we're playing playtests internally, whoever's winning, there's a group of people watching them.
It's a real kind of family atmosphere in the company, and it's something I'm very, I feel very lucky to have found them.
So,
we worked hard that first year. Lots of meetings. The team started quite small, you know, we could fit in one room.
Now we need a very big room.
But this was my first view really into game development.
With H1, I was not stand-off, but I got to spend very little time in Santa Monica.
Here I was living and breathing with the dev team and figuring out and finding out how games are made,
which most of you guys know, I'm sure, but for me this was all new.
I didn't realize the complications, you know, that I would suggest stuff that we'd like
and sometimes the tech director would look at me quite maddeningly, but other times he
just slapped me down and go, no.
And it comes from my lack of understanding of the engine and lack of understanding of
what's actually possible.
So we had many, many meetings.
We, and again, you know, but it was, it was wonderful to see that someone would crack
something or someone would do something new and the team would just, you know, celebrate
it.
It's, it was a very kind of horizontal structure and it's a credit to.
the man there, Mr. Kim. He's built such an amazing team. When we started we were about
30 strong and these were people he had worked with for years, people he had built up great
friendships with.
They really, kind of that first six months,
there were, as I said, there were only about 30 of us
and we worked hard, you know?
It was, we really had this kind of very specific vision
for what we wanted for a game.
And there were lots of arguments about, you know,
how it could go forward or what we should add
and what we should not add.
And I was very, you know, hesitant to change
the core game mode because, you know, I thought,
okay, this has worked for so long in Arma.
I don't want to add too many things to it because I don't want to overcomplicate it.
It was one of the questions I got very much from the early days was, you know, what makes
Euro Battle Royale different?
I didn't want to be different, I just wanted to be good and the good version of what I
wanted to make.
So we had lots of disagreements and lots of arguments, but really it made the team stronger
and we grew very close and everyone understood the vision and it really helped me this year
you stick your name on a game, you have to do traveling to promote the game.
And I was all over the world at conventions, meeting fans and doing press.
So, you know, I don't get a lot of time to spend with the dev team.
And I'm very much, I like being there.
I like being in person and talking to people rather than writing long and complicated design documents.
Because, well, you know, who likes writing those?
So doing a lot of traveling and having that trust in the team that they could...
do the vision, you know, they could create the vision.
Again, it's a credit to CH for building that kind of team,
that just understand what we're doing,
rather than what I'm doing.
So, we had a very agile system of development.
It works great, especially the way that we set it up.
But CH is agile, not agile.
It worked really well.
We, you know, every day, every month,
we would have meetings to talk about,
you know, how...
you know, what new features were added, as I said, it was a horizontal structure, so we had,
you know, people suggested new things, they could take ownership of that, and
it just, you know, the revive system, jumping out of the, giving people the choice to jump out of
the plane, these were all things that came internally, and were sort of approved by the
team in general, so it was, it was great to see that the game mode grow with the input of, you
know, all these developers who, who just love making games.
We also did a lot of everything internally.
Again, we were a small team.
We didn't have AV teams to support us.
And we recorded dev blogs.
And it's something we did a lot last year of really being
open with the community.
And I encourage you all to really try to like, I've had
it since Arma 3.
If you really connect with the community and you get almost community ambassadors that
will tell you or tell the community what your plans are.
So someone's kicking up a stink in a forum, you've got someone that will step in and go,
well no, they're actually doing this, or it's not as bad as you might think.
We did a lot of that last year, really working closely with the community because they're
your voice to the larger player base and it's important to keep in contact with them.
The last few months we've had our heads down because we've been trying to come up with
a road map, but this year we want to get back to how we were last year, how we were so open
and very transparent about what we were doing.
It was also, I remember last year,
like, you know, we'd have these monthly meetings
where you would share what you've done this year,
or what you've done this month,
what you've learned and how you can improve.
And these were great meetings
because the whole team learned something
and they got to show off,
like this was our new water shader for terrain.
And, you know, this is the first time you'd see this
and people were just genuinely excited, you know,
because it just...
we're trying to create a realistic battle royale and, you know, Bluehole were used to making, you know, MMO or PG games,
so making a realistic game was a challenge, you know, because it was not something they had experience doing,
and they're really doing it so well. Tess Ock, our world design lead, he...
you know, he's such a passion for creating these worlds, and, you know, we're still learning and still improving,
but you'll see with the maps we have coming that we're really trying to upgrade and improve every time we release something.
our team keeps growing. This is us just before launch last year, when we were still about
40 people strong. We had at this stage kind of decided, you know, we really needed to
look into doing things a bit more seriously for the game. With our weapons, because it
was such a massive part of a PvP game, Pavel, our action and gunplay lead, you know, he
took the lead in coming to Prague and doing...
mocap for us, so we really got a good character system.
Picking a stance that we wanted to emulate across the whole
character system was very important.
It was great also for the team, because a lot of them
had no experience doing mocap.
It's not a big industry in Korea.
And actually, funnily, flying to Prague to do it, rather
than doing it in Korea, worked out cheaper.
It was a great learning experience for the team, because they had never seen it done before.
So, seeing how mocap and how hard it is, and especially as the director,
you know, you're on the floor and you're working with them,
the actors showing them exactly what you want,
because getting that vision across and getting those actions captured is so important.
So, Pavel worked his ass off.
But then we launched, and today is a special day, because...
This time last year, on the 23rd, we launched Entirely Access.
It was a big deal for us.
We had many long nights.
We had many long days also.
You know, I was worried about going into early access because, as I said before, you know,
it just feels that if you do early access, you have to answer X questions about, you know,
all these things. But again, it's a credit to the team that I shared this concern with CH and the
team and we ramped up like testing. So from a very early stage, we got a beta into people's hands,
like even a prototype, and let people test it from that early stage and really...
you know, work with them and let them know.
And even during the beta, like, there were times
we were there till 7, 8 o'clock in the morning
just because something on the server decided, no, not today.
Right?
And it just, I don't know, like, it's
running perfectly smoothly the other night.
And then today, no, no, it just, it breaks.
But the team, you know, they.
They just, they didn't give up.
There was no kind of like, okay, we'll fix this tomorrow.
It was like, okay, we have players waiting to play, let's get them on.
And by the time we launched into early access, we had a relatively stable build.
You know, it was working, people were having fun.
I was watching people play and, you know, I was, I was happy that
we were getting into early access with something stable.
So, you know, where we're now, you know, last year has been crazy, you know, it's been a year, only a year since launch and, you know, we've, I feel so proud of our team because we've accomplished so much, right?
You know, we broke 40 million copies worldwide across platforms, you know, we've, the number one played game on Steam and the only game to break 3 million.
When I started this four years ago, I never thought I'd be saying things like this, right?
I mean, three million players CCU is just nuts, right?
It's...
I, you know, I did this, which was bizarre, you know?
I was, you know, practicing for two or three days to make sure that, you know, I had my speech right,
and it was a crazy thing to be able to say,
Okay, my game's now on Xbox, right?
But, you know, I'm...
This year, looking back, you know, we've now got...
a much bigger team. I like my photography so when I'm back home in Korea I float around the office
with a camera. These are some photos I took that really show the scale of what the team is working
on now.
Some of these people are here today.
He'll be laughing at this.
But we've grown to be a global company now.
We have offices in Amsterdam.
We have offices with PUBG, MAG, Glory in New York.
We have offices in Madison.
in Santa Monica and in other small offices around the world.
And seeing the team grow, it hasn't been easy for us because
you know finding the right people, it really takes a lot of time you know
because
we're trying not only to find people but we're trying to create a
culture you know, and trying to create a company that can grow and be here for
you know five, ten years in the future and that takes time because
as I said you want to find the right people but
You know, this year it's been amazing for us.
You know, we handed 100 grand to Gamers Outreach.
We've done many more charity events.
And it's something I'm very proud to be able to say
I work with PUBG because they're committed to doing this.
Since Arma days, I've always wanted to give back
and wanted to help, you know, those less fortunate.
And having a company to go, yep, let's do that too,
is an amazing thing to have.
I signed a frying pan for Neymar.
Like.
And I get to look like a gangster boss.
So, you know, me traveling around the world,
it's tough on development because I'm not there.
But again, it's a credit to the team.
And, you know, there are some of the team here, right?
Can you stand up for a second, please?
Yeah, don't be shy.
Koreans are shy.
But this is our team.
Well, some of our team.
They're more floating about, but it's hard to take a company now that we're, what, 300 people strong, you know, everywhere.
So, but I really, you know, I'm honored to work with them, you know, and as well like other, like...
We did this at Starladder, you know this... well not we did this, Starladder did this.
But you know seeing now PUBG and the Battle Royales and eSport really starting to grow.
We have with PGL on this weekend and the way that they're using tech to offer you
different ways to spectate the game and...
You know, really seeing this starting to grow, it delights me.
It's where I've always imagined a battle royale as an eSport,
a spectacle in eSports where you have 100 people and the first person to lose
having to get up and walk off in front of a stadium of 25,000 people.
You know, it's that kind of stuff really excites me.
You know, as a game where we're going, you know, as I said we're really committed to creating these realistic worlds.
You know, Sergi, one of our terrain artists, he just loves terrain and he loves really trying to
make our terrains more and more realistic with our new 8x8 map coming out later this year.
He spent a long time working on it and it really shows it's a beautiful kind of...
upgrade to our previous maps.
And we want to go back to previous maps
and look at improving those and just continue to upgrade.
Again, we want to add more elements
to increase that sort of pull.
realism. I've always imagined Battlegrounds as you're playing a movie, right?
We want to expand on our custom games because that's where I really feel that
you know we let our players create games themselves and really give them...
we can't promise full modding, you know, because
there's security issues, we're trying to be a competitive game, so you know we have
to limit
what you can actually do but...
with custom games we really want to give you kind of fine-grained control over the game via UI but
still allow you to to mess and play with these battlegrounds to create your own game modes.
You know, as I said, we've got lots of new content coming out this year.
And as I keep saying, we really want to invest in eSports.
And last year, we had to sort of build the game.
And this year, we get to polish off the game,
really add the extra out game features we need,
and really kind of start to invest in eSports.
And as I said, like you have.
Things like Starladder, PGL, ESL, they all put on these wonderful
invitationals and it gives us so much knowledge to try to
improve what we do next. So, you know, this year we really want to focus on that.
And as I said,
we're growing globally now and, you know, it takes time to get these teams
in place but it really will help us sustain the game.
So, that's it for me. Before I go, just because it's GDC and I should show you something new,
I want to show you a small preview of our new map that we're releasing shortly.
This is going to be a 4x4 map, much more intense, 100 players, and I think it's going to be a lot of fun.
So, that's what it looks like. This may start playing.
There we go.
So yeah, it's a much smaller map, much more uniform,
and in a kind of a Southeast Asian feel.
Now, this is very early, right?
So forgive.
But I'm looking forward to it, because it's
going to be much more intense, right?
It's
it harks back to my days of creating these other game modes within Arma because you know
Battle Royale is a fun experience that that sort of ever-decreasing circle and that random game every time
So, you know, I just want to try lots and lots of more ideas. So that's it for me. If you've got questions
Please line up
Yeah, thank you very much
Hi.
Hello.
Well, took the whole thing off.
Just had a question for you.
How did you choose balancing stuff from sim games,
like Arma, and some of the more arcade-y stuff,
like H1Z1, so like you're driving and stuff?
Like how, where did you make those decisions
of to what to include and what not to?
It was more we looked at it always kind of as a split between Arma and H1.
You know, the body sim is quite simple.
You know, we've got pretty simple to hit boxes.
And, you know, we're still improving that.
But we really want to, you know, come somewhere in between.
Because I like that, really, I like the choice of weapons.
I like the choice of attachments in Arma.
And bringing that into our game was like sort of, you know, obvious to us.
Yeah, I don't know, it was just we always kind of went 50-50 between them.
It was because I like my MilSim, but you know, I like the ease.
And even in Arma, I really stripped back a lot of the the features of Arma,
like fatigue and stuff, because I wanted to be that little bit more arcadey.
Cool. Thank you.
Thanks for the question.
Hi. When you move to the Arma mod,
Why did you drop the PvE elements?
Was that kind of just because it wasn't easily available to you?
Yeah, pretty much. I mean, there were no zombie mods in...
Well, there were zombie mods in Arma 3, but nothing I would use.
And I wanted it to be a fresh start for the game mode.
That this was a differentiator from DayZ Battle Royale,
this was PlayerUnknown's Battle Royale.
So, again, just focusing on the PvP, because that's what I loved.
Okay, is that an element you think you might explore again?
Well, we now have like our zombies game mode.
So, you know, a Korean streamer came up with it on a stream and we put it into the game
and we have our zombie models and I swear to God, like, zombies that aren't AI and are
other players are so much more fun.
You know, I've seen videos where they're hiding in the grass and suddenly 40 zombies pop up.
So I really want to, we really want to kind of explore that a bit further and kind of
increase...
you know, how that kind of game mode can be played.
Given what you know now over the past year,
would you think about monetizing PUBG any differently
than what you ended up doing?
No, not really.
Like, I'm a big fan of the crate and skin system.
You know, I think in CS it works.
You know, it provides a sustainable economy.
I see it every day with players that meet me going,
oh, well, thank you, I sold this on,
I got this skin and I sold it
and now I don't need to buy games for the next year.
This kind of idea that it does work,
it's somehow, it's not fair a lot of the times,
but in order to have that economy,
it needs to be a certain way
and I think it's a great way to sustain the game.
Yeah, so I mean too with going free to play
instead of doing a box price at the beginning
to try to get a higher.
Oh no, I mean, we always wanted to have a box price.
That was the aim here.
We didn't think about going free to play.
It's a different model.
And we never thought, yeah, we always had a box price in mind.
Just shout.
So I guess just what are your thoughts on Fortnite?
What are you thinking about it?
I have many thoughts.
No, it's great.
Like, I mean, it's great that.
you know, the battle royale space is expanding and that like, you know, Fortnite is getting
battle royale game mode into hands of a lot more people. So you know, it grows the genre, right?
I mean, that's it really. I mean, I'm just happy that more and more people are getting to see
games and then getting to play games. And this year I think we're going to see a big expansion
in, you know, the amount of people that actually come and try games.
My partner played PUBG Mobile and messaged me like two hours after she was going to bed,
you know, saying, I finally killed someone. You know, that this just, she doesn't stop playing now.
But it's just great to see, like, I get asked these questions sometimes of like,
you know, what are you doing to combat this?
You know, I got it when we came out, you know, we were killing H1,
or, you know, when H1 came out, it was killing Arma 3.
And I never said it to kill other people's games.
You know, I don't understand this attitude.
Like, you're devs, you get it, you know?
Like, we're all relatively friendly here, you know?
We don't have a in-real-life GDC battle royale to see whose game comes out, right?
So, you know, this, we have to kind of, I've really tried to combat that perception that I want other people's games to die.
You know, it's like, it's great that more people are exploring the space and more people are getting to play games.
I was curious how you go about testing these large format game types, you know, 100 players,
do you start with 50, start with 25, does the number really matter because it's just
pockets of combat anyway?
Oh it does matter, I mean when we started off we did have very limited QA so you'd have
like 30 player or 20 player battle royales and they're fine to test the loot system to
test, you know, but you know for actual large scale combat it, you know, it does get tricky.
We started off very early.
We had a pre-alpha build where we invited maybe 600 to 1,000
players of H1, of Arma 3, and not just streamers, but just
players from the community to come and help us test.
And we ran these tests on a monthly basis, where we would
just improve something.
and run it again.
So we involved the community from a very early stage
because with a multiplayer game,
you have to have a lot of testing, right?
And involving your community from that stage.
You know, they shouldn't see the game.
The game doesn't look anything
like what you want it to look like.
But for a multiplayer game,
I strongly advocate getting that community in
and letting them play.
How did all that work before you had a large community?
So your earlier in mind?
Differently.
You know, now, like we had,
The server infrastructure was designed for like a million CCU because we thought that's
double dota, we're not hitting a million, and then we passed two million in six months.
So we had to rewrite everything, right?
going to that scale you have to be careful about things you roll out you know because
you know one thing or another some the community may not like it we rolled out a change to
to looting that the community just hated and we had to roll it back but you know having the
community to tell you very quickly if if they don't like your ideas and it's why this year we want to
go back to running an experimental test server,
getting community content much quicker so they can give us
feedback.
Because it's very easy to release something that you
think they want, but then the community will very quickly,
no, we don't want that.
Why are you doing this?
So at that scale, we really think iteration and a lot of
testing now at this scale will really help us get good
content out.
Thanks.
What are your thoughts on using bots and NPCs basically to populate servers early on in a game's life or to astroturf for a new player?
Is that something you guys do, especially with the mobile version?
And do you think there are pros and cons to that approach?
I mean, I know on the mobile version there's been talk of bots.
I don't actually know.
But, you know, what I've heard from a lot of people is that it eases them into the game a lot quicker.
You know, like, I mean...
I think as you play the game more, they get much, much less.
But I think it eases you in because it's a tough game.
Battle Royale is not easy.
I think the odds to win your first game are 1 in 6,000.
So I think it's like double the chance
to get struck by lightning.
So having systems like this, it just
helps you ease into the game.
So I don't necessarily see them as a super bad thing.
Thanks.
I wanted to ask about, what are your thoughts about when is a bug okay to go to production?
So as an example, I...
We believe always.
No, I mean, yeah, sorry.
I mean, as an example, I was driving in a Jeep,
and I collided with a grenade, which was stuck midair
and had this huge collision.
My friends and I all thought it was hilarious,
which was part of, actually, one of the things
that we enjoyed, which I think is interesting.
But I was just curious if that was sort of a part
of the intent, where, you know, like,
we're gonna ship this out early, it's intentionally buggy,
but you'll run into sort of these fun, random things
that you, will happen, or?
Yeah, I was just curious what your thoughts were.
I mean, I don't think any game dev wants the game to be a buggy mess when they release.
But there are bugs in Battle Royale.
There's issues because of what we have to do.
So there's like 100 players and 200 vehicles,
and simulating that amount of stuff, especially with server and client,
it can lead to all kinds of physics problems.
Game development is inherently buggy.
So we released a map with the Blue Zone very early in
development.
So you got to see all the bugs.
The bugs that maybe AAA companies would go, no, you
can't see this.
But I love it.
It creates content.
Bugs in games are funny.
We have the PUBG Rocket program.
It's provided many, many hours of entertainment online.
AUDIENCE MEMBER 3 Cool.
Thanks.
Thanks, man.
That is.
So I know that you mentioned the Hunger Games, but I was wondering if the original Battle Royale
Japanese film, I think 2000, 2001, was that part of the inspiration? Oh no, 100%.
I've never seen anybody mention that. Oh yeah, so Battle Royale came, like, so when I first
had the idea to make a mod, there was a guy that was friends with me, he was a designer,
and he was saying, oh we should do the Daisy Hunger Games, right?
and the Survivor Games existed, so I didn't really like that idea.
And during that week, we weren't talking, and I remember I'd seen something to do
about Royale, and I loved that movie.
I kind of looked at it and went, OK, this
can be a last man standing.
This doesn't have to be teams.
It doesn't have to be.
And I looked at the Battle Royale movie.
It's very loosely connected to the Battle Royale movie.
But I just love the name, right?
And even in the game, we have a frying pan
because I thought there's a frying pan in the Battle Royale
movie, and it's a nice tribute to add.
There is no frying pan in the Battle Royale movie.
There's a saucepan lid, but no frying pan.
So that's a mistake.
The frying pan being.
Bulletproof, again, is a mistake.
We were testing it internally.
I talked with the design team and went, listen,
can we try to do this and see if it works?
It worked.
Then we forgot to take it out of the build.
Build got pushed to live.
And now we have bulletproof fine vans.
So a lot of this stuff was beautiful mistakes.
But the Battle Royale movie, it really didn't inspire me.
The red zone is because I couldn't do a collar for people.
So I thought there's a way to.
you know, threatened death upon people by, you know, this red zone.
I couldn't do squares like they have in the movie because I wasn't a good enough
coder and circles are hard.
So, or no, squares are hard, so I did a circle shrinking
and that's why that exists. So a lot of this stuff came from
inspired by Battle Royale but having to do it my way because I didn't know
another way to do it.
Awesome, thank you.
Yeah, we done?
Nice, and before time, thank you guys.