Good morning, everybody.
Hello and welcome to our panel, Ripple Effect,
How Women in Games Initiatives Make a Difference.
My name's Stephanie Fisher and I'm the panel chair.
Just want to remind everyone,
please turn off your cell phones
and please fill out your speaker evaluations after this.
presentation. And before we start, I just want to let everyone know how we're actually going to run
the panel. So all of us up here got our start in games via a community run wig initiative. And
we're each going to give a short micro talk on, so you can get a sense of who we are, what we do,
and how we've gone, you know, from wig program participant to our current positions or
something generally like that.
After that, we'll have a conversation that's going to be focused on providing strategies
and resources on how to get more women into games, as well as how to work towards creating
a more diverse and inclusive industry.
Post-panel will be in the wrap-up room, but we're only going to do that for ten minutes,
and this is just for exchanging contact info and business cards, but please feel free to
connect via email and Twitter, too.
OK, so who am I?
I am a gender and games researcher
from York University in Toronto.
I'm a co-lead for a research project
called Refiguring Innovation in Games, or Refig for short.
I also belong to a lost generation of women
who played games growing up, but for a myriad of reasons
didn't think they could have a career in this industry.
Back then, when I was a child.
There were not a lot, or none, no game developing or coding
initiatives that specifically targeted women or girls.
Nowadays, this is clearly not the case.
There's a lot of programs where kids
can learn how to make games and how
they can learn how to code, both in person and online.
These are just a handful.
In 2011, I found myself managing one of these kids' game
development camps at my university.
And even though my role in this camp
was as a manager and a curriculum developer,
the kids would still ask me for programming
or code-related questions when they needed help in Game Maker.
And it sucked when I couldn't help them.
I had to admit that I couldn't help them with their code.
I felt like a poor role model for the girls in the camp who
looked up to female staff members.
I really wanted to learn how to make more games,
but I was just at the start of my PhD.
And between work and school and more work,
that really left me with little time or money
to do anything else.
So what was I going to do?
And what I can only describe as an incredibly stroke
of good luck, my research partner
forwarded me over information for a women in games program
that was accepting applications in Toronto.
This program is called the Difference Engine Initiative,
and it sought to bring more women into the Toronto game
scene by helping 12 aspiring game developers make
their first game in six weeks for free,
no experience required.
Perfect.
By the end of this program, I had made a game,
but I had left with so much more.
I was so inspired by the potential of this community
program and so impressed by the women who were a part of it
that I actually changed my dissertation topic
from educational games to exploring
the impact of WIG programs.
So I'm not going to bore you with five years of research
findings, because this is neither the time nor the place.
But if I could sum it up in one ultimate takeaway sentence.
It's that WIG initiatives that provides free support
and training for adult women who want to make games
not only gets more women into this industry,
but also contributes to creating a diverse and inclusive game
culture in the long run.
Oops, sorry.
So while that might be a really obvious statement to someone
who's already engaged in community organization work,
not everyone actually thinks this way
or sees the value in WIG initiatives.
Some people think that focusing on special interest groups,
like women in games, does not work
towards cultivating a fair and equitable industry for everyone.
And they actually say it's going to lead
to further discrimination and division among us.
So for example, in reference to the outcomes
of the Difference Initiative specifically,
these are some things that's been stated about it.
Initiatives like the DEIs don't do an adequate job
of addressing or actually treating
the systemic biases that have made the games industry
culture.
less diverse, and less healthy.
The DEI was designed as a creative space
where people could challenge themselves,
develop their abilities, and learn alongside each other
in a warm and encouraging environment.
Instead, it was viewed as a support group,
underscored and necessitated by a reaction
to an unequal social world where learning was secondary
to the formation of bonds and relationships.
That description of the Difference Engine Initiative
was very surprising to the people who were actually in it.
We certainly didn't feel that it was this failure in the way
it was being described, especially
when the second iteration of the Difference Engine Initiative
received almost universal praise for being a great success.
This visualization, which was created
by the talented Yuna Li, also a Difference Engine alum
and who's in the audience today, demonstrates
the impact of the program mere months after it ended.
It's a little small, but every node in here
represents the games, community initiatives, employment
opportunities, presentations, or exhibitions
that DEI participants were involved in.
And this included organizing monthly meetups,
running or participating in game jams, speaking at conferences,
applying for funding, exhibiting our games.
And in addition to that, we did this work in our own time,
and we made more games on top of that.
So that's what failure looked like.
It looks like maybe we should strive to fail more often.
So meaningful cultural change is a slow process.
It takes time.
A six-week WIG program cannot change the industry overnight,
but that really doesn't mean we should write off or give up
on WIG initiatives as a lost cause.
All too often, positive outcomes of initiatives like the DEI
are forgotten, or they're overshadowed
by this kind of thirst to tell and repeat bad news
stories about women in games or women in games groups.
And we all know these stories by heart now.
Women are too sensitive or emotional.
We need to grow thicker skin if we
want to be a part of this industry.
Diversity initiatives are negatively framed as handouts or special treatment.
My personal favorite is that we're all feminist bitches who can't get along, and we'd rather
tear each other down than build each other up.
I don't know about you, but I think we need some new stories, and that's why we're here
today.
As participants, organizers, and supporters of diversity initiatives, we stand before
you today as the best evidence that WIG programs can and do make a difference.
And so without further ado, I'm really honoured to introduce the panelists.
Sagan Yee is the Executive Director of the Hand Eye Society,
the Video Games Art Collective in Toronto.
Rebecca Cohen-Palacios is the co-founder and current director of Pixels.
which is a Montreal-based wig group.
She is also a dev at Ubisoft Montreal.
Zoe Quinn is an independent game developer
and the co-founder of Crash Override,
a support network and assistance group
for victims and targets of unique forms
of online harassment.
Oh.
Thank you.
And Gemma Thompson is an independent game designer.
chair of Diversity Sweden, co-founder of Ladycade,
and CheHack, two safe space communities
which promote the enjoyment and creation
of games, respectively.
And so as this panel's gonna demonstrate,
there's many paths to making WIG initiatives
and diversity initiatives work,
and they're not always straightforward or expected.
Thank you, I will turn it over to Sagan.
Hello, everyone.
So I'm going to blast right through this.
We don't have a lot of time.
So I'm Sagan Yee.
I'm executive director of the Hand Eye Society, which is a nonprofit arts organization dedicated
to supporting video games made as a form of creative expression rather than a commercial
product.
And they're the ones that sort of organized the difference engine to begin with.
So now that I'm actually running the show, it's kind of...
this again, this whole circle motif.
I didn't have time to put together an awesome ripple map,
but I did kind of put together some major milestones
in kind of my spiral-like journey to how I got here.
And I think this is kind of important
to show these professional and personal
artistic trajectories to demonstrate the impact
Difference Engine had on my life,
because if it hadn't happened,
none of the things I'm about to talk about
would have happened.
And I had a slide here with the poster
for the butterfly effect with Ashton Kutcher's face on it,
and then I decided.
to not do that.
So for some context, I just graduated.
In 2011, I just graduated from a four-year classical animation
program.
I moved to Toronto with no job prospects
and a lot of time on my hands.
And I stumbled upon the application for DEI
by randomly googling Toronto video games.
And the first thing that came up was this application.
And they were taking six women who had never made a game
before who were interested in it.
I signed up because it was free, there was going to be free food.
Reason number one, one reason to be, I enjoyed playing games but I never really tried making
one before and another thing I wasn't making was money and I had really nothing better
to do.
But also one major thing that I only realized later on was really important was that it
was aimed specifically at women.
Even though words like feminism and diversity weren't really on my radar at the time.
I don't think that, I'm not sure I would have applied if it hadn't been just for women.
That detail really caught my attention because it made me feel like my presence would be
expected and accounted for and it wouldn't be yet another situation where I'd walk into
the room and be the only woman there and have to navigate that situation socially by myself.
And I was also working on like this earthbound animation that I don't have time to talk about.
So, Difference Engine 1, I made my first game called Icarus, which you just saw.
And we were barely finished with first Difference Engine when the coordinators asked me if I
would like to be one of two Difference Engine 1 participants to lead the second version
of the program.
The second participant being Yuna Lee, who made the amazing Ripple graphics that you
saw in the beginning.
And I was like, I've only made one game in my life and it was the one I just made through
your program and it's not even over yet and you're asking me to lead the second workshop?
And they were like, yeah, yeah.
And this was such a bold move on their part that I assumed they knew what they were doing.
And so I don't necessarily think I was the most qualified person
to co-lead that workshop, but everyone
had a really positive time.
And as we will hear, all six participants
are still working in or around the games community
to some degree, whether working in a studio
or exhibiting their work at festivals or in Rebecca's case.
co-founding their own organizations,
and I've even collaborated with a few
former participants on game projects.
Again, I didn't make a Ripple tool.
This was a six-week workshop for animators.
I co-coordinated in 2014 with Matt Hamill,
who's the artist on Lovers in a Dangerous Space-Time,
and I bring this up briefly so I can mention Paloma Dawkins,
who made her first game, Dream Warriors,
through this program, and she later went on
to make Gardenarium, which was showcased
at GDC Mild Rumpus last year,
as well as many other festivals and arcades,
and that's like another,
example of how someone goes through a WIG program and then they start running non-WIG programs,
but it's still like women mentoring other women because you really want to like pay that forward.
And Game Curious is a really major milestone for a number of reasons. This is a program I
coordinated from 2013 to 2015 aimed at reaching out to communities outside of the traditional
gamer network and encouraging people to explore the medium on their own terms. And I like to
pitch it as a book club with buttons. And so...
Oddly enough, when you start making an active attempt to draw in people from outside the
group of people who self-identify as gamers, or actually going to different communities
rather than trying to make them come to you, things tend to get a lot less white male and
heteronormative.
So the impact of this was that Game Curious ended up attracting a very diverse pool of
participants and volunteers, many of whom continue to be involved with hand-eye activities.
Years after the first program, it led to an increase of women, people of color, and people
of non-binary genders in paid positions and leadership roles within hand-eye society.
And because of this, then that also in turn led to the inclusion of safer spaces policies.
conversations around anti-oppression frameworks for staff and volunteers.
And again, this is all because of the Difference Engine Initiative.
If I hadn't gone through that program, then I wouldn't have been asked to lead this program
and I wouldn't have led it in the way that I had if I hadn't done a WIG program in the first place.
And if you're interested in strategies for growing a diverse, inclusive community, we
have actually gotten funding from an organization called Refig to create a community toolkit
and that's going to contain strategies and programming for creating similar initiatives.
And that's, we're working with the Mount Royal Game Society in Montreal as well.
And these are some game projects that I've worked on.
And two of these games, Long Time Coming and Punk Prism Power,
which actually ended up being shown at Indiecade.
Night Games last year were both prototyped
at Dames Making Games Jams, which is another WIG program
in Toronto.
So these are some quick notes about just my trajectory and becoming ED.
So some important notes was that I was not only supported and encouraged to take on greater
leadership positions, but also given freedom to make programming decisions with very little
interference or pressure, and the result was that I never felt tokenized or that I was
just being used as a diversity figurehead.
I was, you know, really a leader in being accepted for my personal abilities.
I became involved with other organizations, some game related, some not.
For example, Allied Media Conference that focused on social justice issues, and I learned
a lot of valuable frameworks of equity and community building outside typical sort of
gaming spaces.
And my experiences as both a participant and coordinator of a WIG program has greatly influenced
how I make organizational programming decisions as director of a non-WIG organization that's
been around for longer than I have.
So I kind of inherited this non-WIG organization,
but it was sort of a WIG organization
that influenced how I ran it.
And although Difference Engine no longer exists,
they kind of ran out of funding.
They like did it twice and then kind of got forgotten
for a long time.
I continue to be supported by and draw inspiration
from other WIG programs to this day,
specifically Games Making Games, again in Toronto,
and Pixels, and I'm still learning.
So thank you very much.
Hey, good morning everybody.
You're all awake, and that is fantastic.
So I'm Rebecca, and I am a game developer in AAA Games
at Ubisoft Montreal.
I've been working as a UI developer artist for about 2
and 1 1â„2 years now, but I'm also the co-founder
and director of Pixels.
And if you don't know about Pixels,
it's a non-profit organization.
That's me.
A non-profit organization dedicated to empowering women to create games through self-discovery,
encouragement, community, and accessible learning.
We host a variety of free programs like workshops, mentorship, writers group, yearly incubator,
and my personal favorite, T-cade, which is a tea parlor arcade event.
Five years ago.
Five years ago, I was a programmer at a tech startup, Silicon Valley style.
And my only experience with games was playing big ones made by hundreds of people out of
renowned studios.
I couldn't even fathom how they were made or what they looked like.
were to even get started in this big amorphous cloud
that is called game development.
But one day, my friend told me about a video game incubator
for women called the Difference Engine Initiative.
And it helped six women make their first game.
There was no experience required.
And this just really reached out and spoke to me.
Somewhere in the back of my mind,
I had always, always, always wanted to make games.
But how do you even game dev anyway?
So over the course of six weeks.
I made my first game, and I was with five other really amazing women, and we supported
each other throughout this game-making process.
What was really important about this experience for me, aside from making a video game, was
this aspect of solidarity.
Coming from the tech scene, where you had to be one of the guys, it was really, really
refreshing to be able to meet other cool women who not only played games.
but shared the same gendered experiences as me.
It was a space where being a woman was okay,
and that in itself was really relevating.
It was this defining moment in my life
and encouraged me to examine the power
my identity had as a woman.
Women are powerful.
Women can make games and exist as women
in spaces that are predominantly made up of men.
And my journey continued on from there.
I moved back to Montreal and ended up staying there
when Feminists in Games approached me to run a difference engine in Montreal.
And at the time, despite the numerous amount of studios,
there was nothing dedicated to women in games.
So, in January 2013, my co-founder, Tanya Short,
and I ran the Pixels Game Incubator,
where we helped 10 women make their first game.
And for this program, we received over 65 applications.
And it was really, really clear that Montreal
needed some support structure for women
who wanted to be in games.
And from there, Pixels just expanded.
We started a mentorship program where game developers can
mentor aspiring women in games.
And that matched up with a current game designer
with an aspiring game designer.
So it was really kind of tailor-made
for this personal experience.
And I was still working for my tech startup at the time.
So I asked my mentor, sorry, I asked Tanya for a mentor,
Nicola, and he basically told me, like,
what are you doing?
You don't need to go back to school,
you don't need to, like, hone special skills,
you have the skills right now as a web designer
to do user interfaces in games, so go, apply.
And so I did.
And I got into Ubisoft Montreal,
and it was just like, whoa, it was kind of,
reflection back on this like starting experience in a wig program and I've been
I've shipped about two games now and I'm working on my third which is unannounced but it's really exciting
And what's important to take away from my life story
is that women in game initiatives
have these long-term effects.
They won't solve gender and diversity overnight,
but they have this incredible power to change lives.
And from pixels, we have a ripple effect,
which is also inspired by Yuna's fabulous work.
And it shows the activities participants from the Pixels
Game Incubator have done just one year later.
So they've made games, they've run workshops,
they've gone to game jams, they lead their own community
programs.
And it just creates a cycle of new makers
inspiring new makers.
And that is really, really exciting.
So what's important to take away is that women and other
diversity initiatives do work.
And if someone tells you otherwise,
then they clearly have no idea what they're talking about.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Zoe Quinn.
I'm going to be coming at this from a bit more
of a personal angle, so I don't have slides.
I'm just going to kind of talk at you.
Probably not surprising for anybody
that's familiar with my work.
I came to the Difference Engine Incubator
shortly after I had immigrated to Toronto
with about two suitcases and a cat
to try to make it as an artist in the big city,
because the biggest thing that scared me
was possibly getting to 40 and never having tried
to do the things I wanted to do.
Somehow this led to beekeeping, photography, fire spinning,
and eventually seeing a Facebook post on a friend's wall
that advertised, much like Sagan, free food
and live in that starving artist lifestyle
made it seem kind of appealing.
And I had been a huge nerd my entire life,
so I figured why not?
Six weeks later I had made my first game,
which was called Dame Game.
It was about a person that thought that she was a PI
and was basically being a terrible roommate
because an adventure game style,
because that basically means you're just
taking people's stuff and doing whatever with it.
So I wanted to lampshade that.
And from there, I got involved with the greater indie
community.
And since then, I'm going to sort of blip over any of the
community organization stuff that I've done, just because
Sagan and Rebecca have done such a good job at explaining
their experiences with there, and more focus on what I've
done with my career as a maker.
So it's not just starting initiatives that we tend to
pay forward from these.
I've also created things like Sorting Hat, which is
actually.
a twine game that's modified to be a conversation between the
player and the sort of like list of resources. So it would be
like, so you want to make your first game? Cool. Do you need
art? And you say yes or no. And it gives you a whole bunch of
resources based on that at the end. And sort of like I've
become an engineer, like automating those conversations
that I found myself having all the time. Similarly, I've made
games are for everyone.com, which is a sort of sister site
that has a lot more resources for beginning game developers,
including things like.
meetups, press outlets, anything you need to take it forward
beyond just making your first game.
I've also been in, and the cool thing about these initiatives
is that I'm not just a woman, so few of us are.
A lot of us contain multiple identities,
so that this woman in Games Incubator
actually brought a game developer into the space that
made a game about mental illness that sort of blew up.
Depression Quest, before we even got on Steam,
had close to 2 million players and was designed to sort of,
brings people who might not understand what living
with depression was like into my own personal experiences of it
to try to build that empathy and to make
people that were living with us feel less alone.
So in a way, this women and games incubator
had an probably unintended effect
of also furthering the discussion
around mental illness in our industry as well.
And it's important to remember when we talk about these
incubators, it's not the phrase women and minorities,
because so many of us are both and more than that.
Beyond that, I've also looked at ways
to try to make it more sustainable for people
once they're actually here.
A lot of women in games initiatives
do a lot to bring new people to this industry.
But in my current position, I'd like to figure out
how to help them stay.
I think at this point, I don't need
to explain how I've had an extraordinarily difficult time
to continue to make games in this industry.
I think that's fairly well publicized at this point.
But I was also one of the first developers to get on Patreon
and to look at and to try to advocate for that
and to look at sustainable production methods for people
might not make games that belong on Steam
to help support initiatives like itch.io
that help people distribute and be able to reach
their audience outside of going through
the mainstream kind of thing.
I also run, I like to experiment with the form
of games and game jams as well.
I ran a program called Anthology Jam
based off of a conversation I had
with a fingerstyle guitarist in Leeds
where we were discussing our love of short sci-fi anthologies
and wanting to be like, oh, it would be really cool
if we had a game version of that.
And actually, Gemma was one of our participants.
And I think it was about 15 games that shipped.
Some first-time game makers, everybody
made their games in one month.
We managed to publish it, and everybody got
paid, which was super cool.
The thing with these diversity initiatives
is that you have to look at it like planting seeds.
You might not see the benefit to it immediately,
because these things need to grow.
And as we grow these, it's important to remember
to try to tend our garden as we do it.
If there's one thing all of these diversity efforts could do, I would also ask to encourage
participants to make their own spaces if they enter the industry and still feel like they
might not belong here, because so many of us have.
And I feel like when independent projects like this happen and actively reach out to
communities and say, you can do this, we come from a place where we start with that level
of, oh, awesome, I can do this, that means other people can do this, let's help other
people do this.
And that's something that gets overlooked a little bit.
that this sort of cascading effect happens.
We start with the belief that it can be done,
that it's fine to be weird.
We are all fucking weirdos anyway.
And telling people that they can build things
for people that are their kind of weird
is a really empowering thing to do alongside game development.
But in the meantime, I'm focusing,
trying to figure out how to make more women
and basically make more people that
are dealing with any kind of oppression in the games
industry stay.
So going beyond just these starting conversations.
and trying to mentor people.
Mentorship should go beyond just the initial things,
because once you get here, it's very easy
to have so many questions, like, how do I negotiate a contract?
What does porting look like?
All these things to not just run and start these things,
but to continue forward.
And I'd like to see more women stay.
I'd like to see more women held up
as auteurs and leaders and visionaries
for their amazing work, and not just the bad shit that
happens to us.
I'd like to see them flourish, and not just survive.
I'd like to see them not have to fight the same battles we
already have or on other fronts of marginalization.
Because at the end of the day, despite the legendarily hard
time I've had in this industry, learning how to make games
is still the best thing that's ever happened to me.
Thank you.
Hey.
Yes, my name is Gemma Thompson.
I'm a game designer.
And as you could probably tell by my accent,
I'm not even from the same continent
as the rest of the panelists.
But I did find that my experiences
in games culture in the industry have actually strongly echoed
theirs.
My career began really with a game design degree course
in which there were four women to some 46 men.
But things took a more prominent turn
when I signed up to Europe's first all-female game jam
in 2012.
That experience instilled new confidence in my work,
it started lasting friendships within this profession,
and despite that gender segregated premise,
it reassured me that I could actually engage
in male dominated game culture,
or at least as it was perceived.
I stand now in 2016 as chair of Diversee,
an organization which works extensively
with companies, communities, and individuals,
primarily in the Nordic region,
to promote and support a broad range
of diversity efforts in and around games.
More relevant to this panel, however, I'm also the co-founder of three separate initiatives,
which, as I'm about to explain, have encouraged game creation and the celebration of games
amongst hundreds of new, shy, or disheartened female-identifying individuals across Northern
Europe.
So in my case, it all began in a 24-hour Game Jam event
in London.
It was supported by a number of bodies,
including the UK's Next Gen Skills campaign.
And it's called XX Game Jam.
It was an all-female event arranged
to coincide with Ada Lovelace Day in October 2012.
It led to the creation of six rather wonderfully varied
games, including the first one I could actually
claim to have been involved in from start to finish.
It was also the first game jam I'd ever attended.
And as I said, the friendships I forged here
had to reach well beyond the British shoreline.
I have worked with XS Game Jam alumni at other events,
including List Summit in Copenhagen and Helsinki,
and Anthology Jam.
XS Game Jam also led three of us
to found a women in games initiative of our own.
That initiative is called Ladycade,
and I've been running it since 2013
with Holly Pickering and Ennis McKendrick.
It's an event which has steadily gathered more pace as years have gone on,
and it's founded on the simple idea that women who make and enjoy games
deserve a hangout space where they can feel safe and comfortable,
but need not worry about being a woman in industry.
Nor will they have to spend the entire evening discussing how to get more women involved.
What we do is we hold social events and games showcases,
to which all genders are invited,
but where the attendee demographic is at least 50% female.
as in these snapshots of our first event in Nottingham
and later on in London, which is the one shown on the right.
Thus far, we've held seven gatherings,
either as stand-alones or alongside an existing event.
We've worked to create events for three years running
at Game City in Nottingham,
and we opened up last year's
Creative Coast Festival in Sweden.
Roughly 450 attendees have come to these,
enjoying an atmosphere which many have described
as disarmingly friendly.
And this tends to be a sentiment shared mostly
by the men in attendance, who we've
found to be just as tired as we are of nigh-on gender
homogenous events.
Many of these attendees have also partaken
of the games we showcase, indie titles being made by women,
some of whom have never demonstrated on a show floor
before, but have been encouraged to do so at a Lady Kade arcade.
And that particular initiative works towards two goals.
providing a platform so that more women can feel at ease
showcasing their games like that,
and tangibly proving that women are, of course,
in these local communities making excellent things.
It's this last point which I feel most strongly
harkens back to my experience of the XS Game Jam.
And it's hard for me to understate
the importance of this visibility on a personal level,
not least because, as I mentioned,
that was the first one I felt comfortable attending.
I knew jamming to be a challenging activity.
And having previously not felt comfortable dealing
with gross gender disparity at these events as well,
it added a bit of a relief, to be honest.
Well, I can proudly say that game jamming is now
one of the things I do.
It's a productive hobby, which has taken me
all over northern Europe.
And it's taught me much about rapid iteration
elemental game design.
As someone with very little coding ability,
it's also been an excellent way for me
to keep making games outside of work.
I overcame that initial confidence barrier after having embarrassment about my gender
removed from the equation.
But the same can't be said for everyone.
In the same way that Lady K draws exhibitors and creators out into a community which they
then realize can be inclusive, I resolve to do the same for Game Jams.
So as a sideways step, I am co-founder and vice chair of Game Jam Stockholm, a non-profit
which bears its purpose in its name.
We've run five events of various sizes so far, and although our actual demographics do vary between events,
the general format has been the same.
Positive outreach towards genders other than male,
assuaging the fears of those who haven't jammed before and feel their skills aren't up to the challenge,
and ensuring we have sufficiently safe spaces and the facilities to cater for vulnerable people from many walks of life.
These efforts are being played out long term, since one cannot conjure up a diverse community from nothing.
And in Game Jam Stockholm's case, we worked to ensure that the Swedish capital fosters a steadily more inclusive jamming scene.
To that end, here's a rough breakdown of the gender split at our larger events.
Women and non-binary people are represented by the orange and black sections at the top left of each graph.
After less than two years of operation, it is of course hard to project any sort of meaningful trends here.
But the bottom line is that we are bringing more women and girls into this hobby and the local game jam scene.
We find, for example, that word will spread amongst student bodies and local studios, encouraging more of the women there to join in.
A huge driver for this trend is also Game Jam Stockholm's collaboration with another outreach organization, which specifically supports girls and women in making games.
Myself and Game Jam Stockholm's Inger Ekman are also co-founders of Chehack, a nationwide
scheme in Sweden which runs regular game creation clubs and events for girls and women.
It began in 2014 with a free weekly after school club in a suburb outside of Stockholm's
city centre.
And this intentional move to bring game creation to families in the less social mobile paid
huge dividends, particularly for the girls we have involved, who are aged from generally
like 8 to 16.
It's a pattern we hope to repeat in the wake of our recently
completed nationwide tour, which took in seven towns and cities
across mid and southern Sweden.
Of those women we've involved in the club,
two have recently rejoined games-related education
on paths towards professional programming and art,
respectively.
We've also eased theirs and other members' paths
into local game jam events.
What began with a girls and women-only pajama jam
at the Royal College of Technology in Stockholm
became a 29-member strong mentor-led delegation
at Global Game Jam Stockholm 2016.
The Chehackers got stuck into all manner of games,
including the one I've got running on a hat,
running on a Gemma Arduino, which I'll be showing later.
And that's primarily the handwork of Inge Ekman
and Amandine Coget.
It's worth saying that with events like this
and Chehack's regular club meetings, our goal,
as with Ladycade, is not to train or push for more women
to enter the industry.
Nor are we really there to educate.
Instead, we promote the creation of games
as an interesting endeavor in and of itself,
and simply find that as a natural extension of that,
these girls and women in Sweden
are having their eyes open to vocations
in game development and other related fields.
This is the essence of the ripple effect for me,
which I've just represented as a transit map.
At XH Game Jam, I joined a practical and creative exercise
which had previously appeared hostile to my gender.
In the end, I was reassured both in my abilities
and in my right to create in all kinds of subtle ways.
And I've since spread that rather pure message to others.
In working with Diva C, I strive to pass that on for message,
strive to pass that message on
for folks from other walks of life,
and indeed get involved in explicitly bringing
more women into industry,
as with our GDC scholarship this year.
Ultimately though, it seems that a gentler splash and smaller outward ripples have managed
to travel quite far enough for me and the things I've been working on, given that Stockholm
is like 8,600 kilometers away now.
And that is basically me.
Thank you everybody.
I think everyone's eager to have us talk about strategies
and takeaway points.
So I guess my first question is, what are some strategies
that you guys can share from your experiences
that you want to share with the audience?
Who wants to go first?
I guess I can go first. So leading up to this panel and we were talking about, well, people will probably want to come away with some really concrete strategies for increasing women in their group or finding the women who are probably already there.
Um, and so some interesting kind of observations came up.
I'm going to name some of them and then maybe you guys can like chip in as well.
But, um, like I kind of noticed that, um, because I run a non-wig organization,
I'm suddenly facing.
like, a lot of the challenges of like,
because I've inherited this organization that's,
that was pretty homogenous in terms of gender,
like it's mostly male, mostly white males,
that come out to the events that we do.
So now that I'm in charge of the organization,
I just took over late last year,
so I'm wondering, you know, is my presence
and the way that I run things going to...
around in the long run because, you know, the whole reason I got
into this was because difference engine initiative was aimed at
women. But hand eye society is not a wig initiative. So a game
related event open to the general public with a wig
sounding name or theme.
seems to draw about 50% male-female ratio.
So a lot of the, whenever Dames Making Games
holds an event that's not just for women,
they just open it up to everyone.
It's always kind of like a 50-50 gender split.
Same with Ladycade, I think Jeremiah told me.
Coming from the opposite angle, we find,
yeah, it is called Ladycade, and yet,
because it's open to all genders, we.
It's kind of worst case we get 50-50 split.
It's mostly women, but yeah, we tend to get like a.
Yeah, so that's like one really, really obvious thing
is to just like name your thing something with women in it.
And obviously, I don't know.
It's, that was kind of just a interesting,
I'm not quite sure what to make of it,
but I thought that was really interesting.
And having events like.
I want to do a gamer knitting circle where we learn how to make a scarf and then play
Kirby's Epic Yarn or Little Big Planet or something and talk about textiles in games
or the tea party idea.
I was really interested in tea parties, so it came from this personal desire, but we
ran a tea parlor slash arcade party where we had tea and we just generally chilled in
the afternoon and just that kind of subversive feminine theme brought out this kind of excitement
in women and I saw a lot of new faces and equally men were excited about the tea party
theme.
It wasn't explicitly stated that it was geared towards women,
but it had this kind of fun femininity to it
that games usually don't have.
Something I found since I primarily run,
like I've done events for LGBT organizations
and other things like that is like having somebody visibly
in leadership that's a member of the group is a huge deal,
obviously.
For example, we had an event during GDC on Monday
where it's like we did not say anything
about any sort of diversity or gendering or anything like that.
I think since it was being run by me specifically,
like visibly run by a woman, as well as a very strict code
of conduct at the door, that seemed
to take into account things that might, like while writing it,
it was like, OK, how can we eliminate potential anxiety
that someone might feel walking into these spaces?
So we stated up front, you know, you
shouldn't have to drink here.
You don't like just saying that.
saying your wallet name does not have to match your RSVP name.
And the doorman have been assured of that
to try to be more inclusive to people that don't have that
going on for them.
As well as just being very upfront with what the rules are
and sort of reverse engineering it without saying,
we want this to be a safe space for these groups of people.
But just doing the pragmatic little practical things
like that seem to do really well for.
just the kinds of attendance that we saw.
I find that visibility also helps
with growing a community or an organization,
because being somebody who's visible
makes you a bit more trustworthy.
So the original people who identify that,
oh, this person is running this thing,
that seems good for me,
then that word of trust can then spread.
So as you make more events, then it, yeah, it develops.
That's what I found with things I've been doing.
And on the topic of safe spaces and code of conduct and stuff,
you shouldn't just name your event something
that will attract women and people
from other marginalized groups and then not have anything
to back it up in case something does go wrong
or if there is harassment or weird microaggressions going on.
And there's a lot of really small details that if you're
not.
If you're not a member of one of those groups that's affected by these seemingly small details,
then you'll probably overlook the fact that bars and alcohol do not necessarily result
in safe spaces for women.
And I found that Hand Eye Society, when they first started doing socials, they were always
in bars.
There was always alcohol involved.
And it was almost always just circles of dudes standing around.
talking and it was like, you know, we went to a couple,
after Difference Engine Initiative, we went to a couple
and we were kind of like, well, we did this thing
and, you know, the community's not exactly welcoming us
with open arms and soon after that,
they actually phased out the socials because.
They just weren't very effective at getting people to socialize or bringing in new people.
And I've actually taken it upon myself to bring that idea back, bringing back the monthly
socials, but now I'm having it in a space where there isn't alcohol and we have dedicated
volunteer greeters who are from diverse backgrounds.
and a lot of them are also involved with Game Curious.
And just things like low-pressure jams
with breastfeeding areas, having pronoun badges
is something that we utilize.
And just all of these things contribute
to a much more inclusive environment for everyone.
Definitely.
And we had a really good experience
with creating blanket forts.
at our events and these are just really dedicated
relaxing spaces where you can just go off to the side
and talk or take a break from the crowds.
And that is really helpful, especially as a new person
in the community because you don't know anyone
and you just might feel overwhelmed by going to these events
so like, as Zey can mention, all these small details
really do contribute to a healthier environment
for your organization.
We found that with, we put a focus at Game Jam Stockholm
on making sure all the attendees have enough food
and drink to get them through, but we have found as well
that having like dedicated food areas does mean
you can have that sort of breakout space.
And just like you say, if somebody's feeling
a little bit nervous or something, we try to make sure
that a mentor is always available there
to just like be a single point of contact
and help them through.
And the nice thing about this is like you see.
so much pushback to any sort of inclusivity efforts is like well
special treatment, blah, blah, blah.
But the thing about stuff like that
is that's just nice for everybody.
I mean, that's something, like having a quiet space
where you can actually have a conversation,
everybody stands to benefit from that.
And similarly, having mentorship and stuff like that,
that's good for all events.
So it's like that stuff should be an easier sell.
Similarly, if you do end up having events
with alcohol present, it's really good to have people
who are paying attention to what's going on
and the comfort level of the participants
that are willing to go in and just,
non-invasively go and be like, hey,
can I talk to you for a second?
And then bring the person who looks
like they're uncomfortable maybe out of that situation
and be like, is everything OK?
In a way that doesn't make them feel cornered or singled out,
just be like, give them the out.
A lot of us, I think, at conferences
do that for each other too.
Being able to be like, hey, fostering that,
looking out for each other thing, I think,
is super important as well.
I do want to mention that if you are thinking about starting an organization, you don't
need a ton of money to do it.
Pixels ran an entire year on zero dollars and we are still a low budget organization
and it's very nice actually.
You don't need to run off and incorporate as a non-profit right away because you have
to do taxes, you have to be liable to the government.
And there's also a lot of fees associated with incorporating as a non-profit.
So staying as this community grassroots organization is really a good thing.
And you can depend on, especially if you're in a city, I know smaller organizations in
like suburbs and what not might not have.
not be accessible to these things,
but a lot of like co-working spaces,
studios are willing to donate a space for you for free
and you just have to ask them.
And volunteers, a lot of people love to help out
and you need to, if you have them,
you need to appreciate them as well.
Similarly, actually, it's almost contrary to the point,
but at least in Sweden, a number of Chehak and Game Jam
Stockholm are both indebted to a nationwide organization
called Spherock, which it's another non-profit.
It helps support smaller games clubs.
And seeking out bodies like that can actually
be really beneficial because it's.
It keeps any potential running costs to zero, which then allows you to keep in members without having to put up a price point.
Because I think having free clubs is a huge part of keeping it socially mobile.
But also they then manage membership data securely and things like that.
All sorts of those kinds of things can be worth seeking out.
Yeah, just a point about what Rob was saying about if you are looking to start a similar
initiative.
When I meet people from other cities, a lot of times I hear, like, oh, man, I wish I had
a Dames Making Games.
I wish I had a Pixels.
And I like to remind them, like, what is the bare minimum of these initiatives?
You need a room with some people in it.
And they probably all have their own laptops.
So there you go.
Sometimes you don't even need a room.
You can do it in the park.
But it's basically just a bunch of people.
And, I mean, the difference engine initiatives were actually based on, like, that six-week
model is actually based on the artsy games incubators that the Hand Eye Society, even
before they were incorporated as an organization, the co-founders were running them, and it
was just...
a six week model for giving people space, time and accountability to get a small project
done.
So yeah, it was like, let's just find a bar or a library or whatever and once a week for
six weeks we'll meet up and keep each other accountable and show each other what we've
done.
And that was sort of basically it.
There was no organization.
It was just, yeah.
That was the sort of minimal thing.
And of course, you can build it from there
until you have larger organizations.
But then that's what people who, you can always come and ask us,
like people who have already done it,
ask for how to build that from that small seed.
The nice thing about that, too, is especially
if you look to any sort of maker space or something,
you'll often find people in that community that
want to get involved with games, that
are doing their own community organization.
And it just kind of spirals up from there.
I mean, every single jam or organization that I've founded
has just been asking for things and being surprised how
helpful people want to be.
Like, it's really people there.
I feel like this issue has hit the point where
I think enough people know that there's
a problem involving representation and in tech.
And there's a lot of people, the question I always hear
is, how can I help?
It sucks when you don't have anything to give those people.
And that's one of the easiest.
It's like, oh, give us some space.
Give us some support.
Or even just signal boosting is super important.
So you can actually reach the people that want to be involved.
And that's one of the biggest things
that I think you get out of that.
Yeah, it's great to feel like.
you know, you're no longer starting,
you no longer have to start from scratch or start from zero.
It's like now we are getting to the point
where we're laying that foundation
and it's like kind of historical and awesome.
Yeah, and it's also a thing where a lot of people
who are not necessarily part of the community,
like they're not part of the marginalized group
that's, that they want to help.
One of the big ways that they can help
is to support the people who are leaders in the,
and you know, looking to start these things in.
doing their own thing, to give them platforms or resources.
There's a lot of people doing this really good work already.
And another part of that, beyond starting it,
is seeing support from major institutions,
or game companies, or people that
do have the resources that we don't necessarily
have access to when we're building something from nothing.
On that note, what are some things
that game studios and companies can
implement when they get back to the office next week?
Well, you can always see what community organizations exist and support them.
You don't have to start from zero, you don't have to start your own thing because these
communities have already gone through lessons and mistakes and already know what their community
needs.
So, going and supporting them, either financially or with resources or with space, is something
really important.
Similarly, something that everybody can do, I think,
is to just start getting educated
about what the issues even are.
And the nice thing is, with things
like Twitter and social media, is
there's a very non-intrusive way to start learning these things,
like just quietly going and searching
for who the big voices are, like the people that
are talking about these issues that have done the work,
and just following their work, and seeing how
these communities help describe what their own needs are
in their own words.
And you can do this without like.
jumping on somebody and being like, hey, tell me what to do,
because that can also be really stressful,
especially if it's just a random person and not someone
who does this for a living.
So just quietly observing is a really good step
one if you're not even sure what the issues actually are
or what to do or how to help.
And it's a relatively easy thing to do at events like this.
One of the major things we do at Divacy at the moment
is outreach, because Divacy has a network, still building,
of, like I said, companies and individuals and organizations,
all working towards the same goal,
but not necessarily all as one package.
But when we do come to a conference or something
like that, then we tend to bring in people from these areas.
And so it's a matter of just seeking out and talking.
Just asking questions, I think, is basically it.
And similarly, there's a whole lot of community leaders.
Because I think one of the biggest things I hear
as an excuse for not seeing low representation,
whether it's panels or in hiring practices,
it's like, well, where do we find them?
Nobody's applying.
But to touch on something Sagan mentioned in her presentation,
you can go to them.
Like, you can go to these community leaders and be like,
hey, you know a lot of people.
Do you know anybody that is really good at this thing?
And you don't even need to make it a tokenization thing.
You can just ask who these people's friends are,
because they probably know somebody amazing.
Because I think there's a tendency in games
and a lot of places just hire people we know.
And I think that creates a very self-sustaining culture
of sameness.
And it's very easy with all these people
doing this really great work and doing this activism.
As you can see, one of the things with the ripple effect
is look how many of us actually talk to each other
and know each other.
So if you need recommendations, it's
not just look at all this cool work that's coming out.
It's look at all these people who
know who the talented people are that you might have not seen
because, you know.
social circles don't necessarily always overlap.
So taking the initiative to be like, hey,
who do you know that's really good at 3D animation
or programming that has time and is looking for contract work
or looking for full-time employment based in this location,
you'll see a better number of people
that don't necessarily look like you applying for those jobs.
And similarly, it's really good that there's
a lot of discussion talking about the problems right now,
but I've definitely seen and talked about this
with a lot of other people.
less so about how to actually support the people who are here,
how to talk about us as more than just a diversity
checkmark or somebody who has struggled.
Actually supporting the work that's
being done, like the games that are being made,
the cool initiatives, and make no problem.
Siri, my God, has no chill.
But actually getting us paid for our work
is really important and signal boosting that
because it's like cool to say,
oh, look at all these things that are being done
and all these people that are brought into the industry,
but then the path to sustainability there
is another core component
that not enough people are looking at.
And I would add to that, look in the long term.
I think if there's one.
constant thread through our experiences is that diversity initiatives of any kind are long-term reaching you're you're not going to get
suddenly a diverse community within a month or two
so investment on the years scale quite often because it is a slow process and
Similarly a beginning game developer is going to have different problems like breaking into the industry just getting the basic skill set
There's like a whole other arena of mentorship that
something I'm trying to step up with more like I'm actually people's agent now like I'm just
like a freelance princess Carolyn for yelling at you about why your contract sucks or why
you don't have a contract at all like even just teaching things like how to negotiate what to
ask for in a contract the fact that you can push back on a contract because oh my god the number
of starting independent developers especially people who don't look like the traditional
developer.
they don't know they can negotiate on these things. They are just so happy to be here in the
first place. That's something that experienced devs and veterans can do. Even if you write a
piece or put the stuff out there. Internet is awesome. We can say, hey, just so you know,
have you even thought about what your terms of your contract are or do you need or reaching
out to people in that middle range where they have made a couple games. They haven't had
their big hit or anything yet.
Maybe they don't have contacts at PlayStation or Nintendo
or sending an email even just for people like that.
Like that really minor mentorship,
that can do everything for someone
who's trying to build their own thing
and not just be able to make games,
but be able to do that full time and sustainably.
I'm very excited that we're getting to the point where, because we've done a number of
like first-time game maker type things, and now it's getting to the point where it's like,
well, we have, we've done so many of them that we have all these people that have gone
through that program, made their first game, and they're like, now what?
Now what do I do?
What's a contract?
how do I go from here? And now I'm excited to like start doing
those like more intermediate level support jams and stuff
like how do you go from there to like making a career or a
vocation out of this if that's the path that you want to go on.
So that's kind of like what I'm planning to work on next with
the Hand Eye Society. That's awesome.
We're definitely with Pexels we're definitely reaching that
point where we need to start offering like support to mid
level beginner.
developers because they needed to, they need to, like, not be part of the leaky pipeline
problem. They need support that is kind of away from the studios. They just need a place
to go to talk, as Zoe said. And it's really important that we start examining these needs
in our communities.
And I just want to say one quick thing about, like, experience and reminding
sort of everyone of, you know, how I came into this leadership role wasn't because I
already knew how to be a leader.
Like I had never done any of this stuff when they first asked me to run that workshop.
They asked me to run a game making workshop and I didn't know really how to make a game
still and it worked out amazingly.
And when they asked me to be executive director,
I had no nonprofit experience.
But they were like, you know what, it's more important
that you're in the community, that you know about,
you understand video games, and you understand
this community.
The other stuff we can teach you,
and we can mentor you through that.
And this was like a lot of men saying this to me,
a lot of men propping me up and supporting me,
and that was like, that meant an incredible lot.
Yeah, similarly, it goes beyond just like,
sustainable business stuff too, but also like,
how we talk about.
of games and what is getting visibility,
especially if you're an indie game maker,
you probably know that visibility is life or death
in terms of your business.
So making sure that, for instance, on award juries,
it's not just all people that look exactly the same.
That's people with a diverse range of not just backgrounds,
but ideally creative tastes as well.
It's not just five AAA guys, but a variety
of people from different backgrounds with different
you know.
views on things.
Because a lived experience is experience.
Exactly.
It's expertise, really.
And making sure that it's a holistic approach, not just
how do we get them to start their own business, but what
are we doing to highlight them and to support them.
We're actually out of time.
Quick.
So thank you, everyone, for coming.
If you appreciated what you heard today, please fill out
the speaker evaluations.
Thank you.