Good afternoon, UX Summit.
This is my first GDC talk, so whether you
think it was terrible or decent, please fill out your forms.
We want your feedback.
Also mute your phones, please.
My name is Marie Jassmin.
I've been in game UI design for 10 years now.
And last year, I joined a team at Bethesda Game Studios
with an interesting mandate.
to create an Elder Scrolls experience on your phone.
The vision for the Elder Scrolls Blades
was to create intricate role-playing game systems
with depth set in environments
that would push the edge of visual quality
on the small devices,
while fully embracing portability
and accessibility. Now it may not be apparent at a glance, but this vision for Blades contains a
dilemma. Should the game be built in the portrait mode or in the landscape mode?
Blades ended up being built for both.
And today we'll dig a little deeper into the vision that led us to choose dual orientation support.
Then we'll look at the UI design process and how we made it happen.
And finally we'll analyze the player response we have so far,
considering we're still in early access, closed beta actually.
But it's still interesting to look at today.
So we're building an Elder Scrolls game on mobile.
In essence, mobile gaming liberates the context of play
away from the living room or home PC
and takes it anywhere, on the couch, at the park.
on the bus, at the airport, on the toilet,
or during a meeting, or a GDC talk.
Notice a few things here.
In some of these contexts,
people only have one free hat.
So if gaming is to be made even possible there,
portrait is a must.
In fact, for some players, the one-hand situation is a little more persistent.
For others, it might be even permanent.
In other contexts, the public eye is upon our player.
And in those situations, portraits can act as some sort of a stealth mode,
where people may not necessarily appear to be playing a game.
Our creative director Todd Howard affectionately calls portrait mode
the meeting mode.
So looking at the context of play, we must conclude that if mobility is a
requirement,
then portrait orientation is the only way to go.
However, remember that for blades,
navigation in stunning environments is also a must.
External research done on the way we hold our devices reveals that while portrait holds
are relatively diverse, a lot of people hold their device with both hands or just one hand
depending on context, but the landscape hold is almost universal.
People have both thumbs firmly placed on each side of the screen towards the bottom.
The physiognomy of people, or the ergonomy of the landscape hold, enables us to separate
controls for camera and navigation in two. So, yeah, the alternative in portrait is the one
finger tap to move, but this inevitably binds camera to the eyes, effectively reproducing
the feeling of walking with a very stiff neck.
And perhaps more importantly, navigation options for humans,
and Khajiit, and Oregonians alike,
if you're familiar with the Yellow Scrolls,
are usually lateral.
Above is mostly ceiling and sky.
Below is mostly ground and floor.
Not very interesting for navigation
if you're a regular human, not Spider-Man.
As a result, so in this example, you see two doors, right?
So you could go left, you could go right,
you have choices, you have agency.
But when viewing the same environment in portrait,
you can only see one door.
So effectively what happens is that
your navigation options are hidden under the fold
to borrow a term from web design.
So basically what it means is you need to scroll.
to be able to see your options.
And this, combined with the stiff neck phenomenon,
creates feelings of claustrophobia
when navigating a 3D environment in portrait.
Hence, we come to the groundbreaking revelation
of this day at GDC.
Landscapes are better experienced in landscape.
So let's do a little experiment.
If you personally had to choose a device orientation
to build the Elder Scrolls Blades,
which one would you go for?
Those who vote for the portrait mode with better accessibility
and mobility, raise your hands.
Ooh, a few people.
And those who choose the more immersive.
mode. Oh, wow, that's interesting. A lot of immersive people here. Actually, this was an
endless debate at Bethesda, so we took the opportunity here to turn lack of consensus into
an opportunity for player agency, so we let people flip their phones whenever they please.
And yes, we knew it would be expensive and painful and we had never done this before.
What are we waiting for?
Let's get started!
To begin with, we make design documents and menu flows,
and we make only one set of them.
So to preserve our sanity, we go through the regular design
process, but trying to keep the information presented
to the players the exact same as much as possible,
just in two different layouts, so a bit like mirror layouts.
So what this means is that the UX or design team had minimal overhead for dual orientation support,
but the UI team needs to produce each mock-up or wireframe twice.
On Blades, this added about 20 to 60% time to UI conception.
It doesn't double the time
because most visual communication problems
have already been solved when you tackle the alternate mode.
But the extra time invested in conception
did yield some early benefits.
To provide an example, this is one of the earliest building menus.
we designed, and here I list all the materials people need to craft certain buildings, being
as generous with information as I can so that players can make their own crafting decisions.
And paper tests were relatively successful, so if I ask, can you craft a smithy, people
would say, um, no, because I'm missing lumber and potatoes.
Relatively successful.
But then came the time to adapt the layout to portrait,
and while our list now nicely held a large number of items,
and this was nice, we wanted to keep it this way,
but there was no way all the information
would ever fit the narrow space.
So it forced us to adapt, right?
So we started disclosing information depending on context,
So here in the repair section at the smithy I show the item condition
and in the crafting section I show information about the materials required
but notice here that the materials information has been distilled to a red X or green check mark.
And when we paper tested this again, the distilled version in portrait,
the responses were noticeably more confident.
So can you craft a steel dagger?
Sure, but it's not worth it.
It has bad stats.
So it was way better.
So we realized that the compromises we had made for portrait
were actually way more efficient.
So we adopted them for landscape as well.
The takeaway here.
is that the extra constraints on the UI team
allowed Blades to identify certain issues early on,
and it saved us a lot of time down the line.
Thank heavens it did, because down the line
is where time became excessively scarce.
The implementation was time-consuming.
First, dual orientation still means each of the two layouts
need to adapt to the various aspect ratios, notches,
and punch holes of the mobile market today.
So even if all our documents were produced in a 16 by 9
aspect ratio, they need to stretch vertically on iPads
and horizontally on larger, newer phones.
So our integration nodes got quite complex and our prefabs in Unity got even more so.
But the real dual orientation party happened in quality assurance.
Because remember that players not only own differently shaped and sizes of devices, they
are also free to rotate them whenever they damn well please.
So QA, to test this, needed to flip their phones in every possible game situation.
In the middle of a combat move, during a loading, during a server call, during animations,
between a button press and a button release. Yeah. Bug festival ensued.
In this instance, the UI disappeared entirely.
We fixed it, but fixing a dual in dual orientation is a tedious and delicate affair.
Our systems were sometimes redundant. It was the case of our animation system,
so keyframes are basically copy-pasted. That meant we needed to fix issues twice.
And most of the times they were instantiated, so the same widget would be used in both orientations,
but that was delicate because it means fixing a bug in one mode might break it in the other mode.
We did get the interface to work though and
We got a first playable demo in the hands of players
in dual orientation as early as we could.
Getting the game in human hands as early as possible
was crucial to the dev process of Blades.
Don't try to retrofit dual orientation.
Do it from the start.
You will uncover flaws in your designs
and you need to have enough time ahead of you
to course correct.
To provide an example, here we have a shield icon smack in the middle of the screen
in landscape and it's a critical combat mechanic allowing players to protect themselves with their
shield.
The icon was terribly positioned, and my punishment as a designer for not having noticed earlier
was to be forced to stand completely silent as I watched players struggle physically to
even reach it, and die.
One of the many ways I've killed people with UI.
We fixed it, of course, we moved the shield and we added a few player options in the process
so the left-handed could enjoy the game as much as anyone else.
But our first hands-on demo also opened our minds to an opportunity we had overlooked.
With the two different screen modes, we could cater to different play styles.
So as a design experiment, we began optimizing the landscape mode for immersion, allocating a good
portion of the screen real estate to 3D models, the player's avatar, etc. And in the portrait mode,
we got rid of all that. It became our gameplay first mode. We even cluttered the portrait
mode 3D model with
extra non-essential information that was nonetheless useful. This is a worst-case scenario by the way,
but the takeaway here is that the diverging layouts allowed us to be a lot bolder with
our design decisions since we were catering to a bit narrower subset of our players for each mode.
While it is still early to draw any conclusions as to whether this grand dual orientation
experiment was all worth it, the results we have so far are interesting.
First, if we take a look at the freeform comment
our closed beta players are sending us
through a generic feedback email,
so we give them a pop-up,
thank you for playing Blades,
send your feedback here, and they do.
And we witness something unprecedented in UI.
Apart from bugs, the majority of UI mentions are positive?
From my past experience, what typically happens is,
in freeform comment, is that UI doesn't even get noticed.
Or it gets noticed, but that's when people tell
the developer what's wrong with it and how to fix it.
What's interesting, though, is that landscape mode
gets the usual treatment.
People don't mention it.
It's the portrait mode that gets all the love.
Our players seem to perceive it as some sort of a bonus mode
that we've generously built for them,
and landscape appears to be considered default
or taken for granted.
Dinging a little further into our letters
of portrait mode appreciation,
we realized that the design assumptions we made about people with different play styles,
choosing a mode or the other to best suit them, were partly wrong. So we do have some players who
stick to one mode, but quite a few of our playtesters have gone to great lengths to describe
their use of the portrait mode, and it's all about the context of play.
So, more like what I talked about earlier, some of the associated keywords in the feedback
associated to portrait are going and walking. I know, walking. Don't play video games while
walking, people. And telemetry data sort of confirms this. For instance, and take this
with a grain of salt, we're still in closed beta.
But we clearly see, though, that the session length on average is much shorter in portraits,
so people play less long, and overall it's slightly shorter in the daytime when people
are going about their daily business versus longer sessions in landscape, mostly past 8pm local time.
Another curious finding from digging into device orientation telemetry data is the gradual adoption,
slow but gradual adoption of the landscape mode by the same players over time. So it's as if our
players kind of naturally realize that the experience is a bit better in landscape and
they kind of adopt it. However, the adoption is not
global. People play the quests, dungeons, more in landscape over time, but in menus it remains
around 65% portrait, 45% landscape, kind of consistently over time.
So globally, the trend we're observing is that many of our players will tend to go about their daily business in their town in short daytime sessions in portraits.
So they'll go get their gear repaired, temper a sword, brew a few potions, and then they'll come back later to the game in the evening for longer sessions to explore.
dungeons, fight dragons, or explore the abyss outside of town.
So in a way, dual-screen orientation support has positioned The Elder Scrolls Blades
in the best of both worlds.
It remains portable and accessible throughout the day,
while making no concessions on the stunning RPG experience it provides.
The grand takeaway here is that if well planned,
and I need to insist on this, if well planned
and if done from the beginning, both technically
and production-wise, the return on investment
of portioned mode support on a 3D mobile experience
is well worth the extra costs.
The extra design constraints actually
help improve the experience.
And our data shows our players appreciate it,
and they use it when it suits them.
If you'd like to try it for yourselves,
you can download the game.
It will be available this spring to all.
It's free.
Give it a run and send us your feedback.
This is a feedback address if you want to follow me,
I rant about UI.
And if you witness your colleagues playing Blades
in meetings, share your stories, I want to hear them.
Thank you.
We do have a bit of time for questions.
About how many, I guess, iterations did you go through for the UI when you started to realize,
hey, we can kind of put these things together, like we can use check marks instead of red numbers, etc.
So it depends on which parts of the UI.
Some were pretty good from the get-go.
Others were very much iterated on.
The game, actually, it's interesting
because it's a smaller team than I'm used to.
I come from AAA, and it changed radically
throughout the dev process.
I'll share this.
One of the things we discovered
in our first play tests last year
was that people were obsessed with cheese.
And we were like, oh my god, cheese is one of the Elder
Scrolls core pillars.
And people couldn't interact with cheese.
They were really sad.
So we added cheese.
And now you can eat cheese in the Elder Scrolls blade.
But yeah, some parts got actually really, really
changed radically.
It depends on the UI.
Crafting is one of the ones that changed a lot.
Thank you.
Hello Marie-Jasmin.
Hello Anouk.
Wonderful talk.
I have a bit of a question, sort of in the theme of one of our earlier talks.
In projects like this, one of the hardest things to do is to get buy-in.
So when you're starting a project like this, generally speaking, you need some data to
say,
we can invest all of this time because this is how our players are going to feel.
How did you tackle convincing your team and your company to be able to do this,
invest in the time to be able to do in portrait and landscape?
That's an excellent question.
And yes, it's true, you need buy-in.
We were lucky because it was the other way around on our project.
the creative director who believed in dual orientation support for blades,
and he needed to convince us because the doers were like,
but it's going to cost this much money.
And he convinced us. Amazing.
But that's easier than the other way around. Yes.
Hi.
So when you have your phone, normally it's in portrait,
like that's how all the apps are displayed.
Yes.
When you boot up the app and you have the splash screen,
that usually sets the precedent for whether they want
you to turn your phone or not.
How did you make the decision to make whatever the default,
whether it was portrait or landscape?
So the default is whatever the player is booting in.
And one of the things we're considering now
is maybe tutorializing the fact
that you can even flip your phone.
We have some hardcore portrait users.
You saw like about 65% of people are in menus in portrait.
And we think maybe it's because some people
don't even know they can.
flip their phone because it's not very common yet in North America. So we're considering it.
Hi, I have a question for smaller companies with smaller budget. For instance, is it an option to
play the game in landscape and the menu in portrait? Is this something that you already
have? Yes, it could be an option. Did you evaluate this approach?
Is it a valid approach?
That's interesting, but it would force users to flip their phones at certain times.
It's what they do.
I'm thinking, but I don't think I've ever seen this approach.
Me neither, but it's great to do both.
But let's say that, is it something that you analyze
doing playtest or asking players?
No, we wanted to give full control to the players.
Yeah.
And don't you think that it could be an option
or not at all?
I don't know, I think it might be frustrating
to be forced to rotate your phone
when you don't necessarily want to.
But that's just a hunch,
because I don't have an example of a case
where it's been done.
No, me neither.
Thank you.
Bonjour Marie. Just a quick question, because you talk about the old rotation scenario with your QA team,
and I'm just curious, what was the process with that or with them?
Because, I mean, it's, well, I think they might have lost their minds at some level,
because there were so many scenarios.
And the follow-up question on that is, how much data did you get from the QA on the UI and UX perspective?
A great question. Yes, they needed a hug at some point, but yeah, for QA it's, yeah, I said so,
they carry basically the heaviest part of the burden because they needed to test every possible
case. For localization it was twice, so every...
every language needed to be tested twice,
not all the possible aspect ratios
because you just need to test
your smallest possible aspect ratio
and test everything twice.
But for, yeah, testing, flipping their phones,
and they kind of liked it though
because they're sadistic.
Like, I flipped my phone in the middle of this,
yeah, button press and release was like,
why would you do that?
It goes QA.
So yeah, the buy-in, again, to come back to the buy-in,
needs to be global, right?
The QA needs to be aware, we're doing this,
we're in this together, and yes, they need support.
Merci.
Yes.
Hi, my name's David.
Do you have any data on whether it was harder to play in?
Portrait, you were talking about how you sort of have a tunnel vision effect.
Yeah, probably still get through the levels.
Does it take longer to get through them or more tries?
Do you know this?
That's a very good question.
It doesn't take longer to get through the same level, but.
Yeah, it's mostly a question of how you feel through it.
And we know also, it's actually really hard to get any data on this,
because people are in different contexts.
They don't have time.
They're kind of busy in portrait.
Usually they want to go faster.
I don't think you'd notice it's harder if you're playing.
But the landscape people will explore a bit more, go to the side path,
discover the hidden treasure.
So it's very different ways of playing the same game.
Actually, unfortunately we have not a lot of data
because we're still in closed beta,
but that's what we observe is people are a bit more
in a hurry and you saw the session length
is much shorter in portrait.
So it's just a different way to experience the same game.
Thank you.
Hi, I had a question.
You mentioned at the end you validated
that there was a good return on investment in doing both,
but I guess what were you looking at in terms of data
to kind of validate that?
Thank you. So was it a good return on investment?
What we are looking right now to say that is mostly the reception of the players and also the media.
It's interesting, I didn't put it on my slides, but we even have headlines in our reviews that are like,
wow, Elder Scrolls Blades is getting one thing right, the portrait mode.
And we're like, weird headline, like UI is not used to be.
so to get so much limelight, but that's also all the good press, the people are grateful for the
existence of the portrait mode, we think that's well worth it. It's hard to calculate isn't it,
because we also don't know exactly how much it costed us, it's hard to evaluate because we did it
from the get-go in both orientations, but yeah we believe it was worth it. Thank you.
That's all the time we have.
Thank you very much.