I'm Chris Wilson from Grinding Gear Games,
and today I'm going to talk about how we design
Path of Exile to be played forever.
I'd like to thank Jonathan, my co-founder,
for helping me extensively with this talk.
Half of it is him, I'm just presenting it.
I've been asked to make sure that everyone
mutes their phones so it's quiet,
and thank you very much for staying
to the last day of GDC to see this talk.
Hopefully it's worthwhile.
I'm going to talk very fast,
so there's a lot to get through.
It's like 90 plus slides and 45-ish minutes,
so we'll see how that goes.
Okay.
Thank you.
Early on in Path of Exile's history,
we discovered the truth here.
Player versus player games, like League of Legends,
are endlessly replayable.
You can play against different opponents every time,
different stuff happens, and they grow over time
because of that.
But a PvE game like Path of Exile is difficult
because it has a clearly marked set of content,
you know, a single player story you can play through.
And because of this, some players,
when they play the story,
they then don't play the game anymore.
And so it's very hard to get these PvE games
to grow over time.
And one could argue there aren't many good examples
of PvE games that have.
have grown.
And World of Warcraft is the type of game I'm talking about.
They threw a ton of content at it for a long time and they got some really good growth
out of that.
The tricky thing is how do you do that on a shoestring budget when you're a few guys
in New Zealand who haven't made a game before?
So, we found out the reality of this when we released Path of Exile back in 2013.
You can see here we had respectable user numbers, 150 million player hours that year, and less
in 2014, and less in 2015, and it just wasn't growing, right?
Like, you know, people were treating it as a PvE game, and we were doing the best we
could and we couldn't keep the player numbers up.
So we changed our strategy.
We had some hard learnings to do.
We changed what we were doing.
And that's what I want to talk about today.
How we managed to achieve the honestly ridiculous growth
that we've seen since then.
And there's a lot to cover.
It's also worth noting that the graph here
is showing only our PC Western English server.
This is meant to be an apples to apples comparison.
We're not cheating by throwing in like China and Xbox
to make the graphs bigger.
The other realms, the other platforms
are not included in this graph.
So I'm going to briefly show you some footage of Path of Exile.
This might be very loud, so we'll just turn it down if it is.
So, it's an online action RPG.
I'm sure you're all familiar with this game,
or at least this type of game.
It plays a lot like, you know, the Diablo series.
And it's all about deep character customization,
finding awesome items, leveling up.
It's got a lot of replayability in the league content
where you come back every 13 weeks
to play more Path of Exile.
And basically, it's a game that we're very proud of.
Entirely made in New Zealand.
It's the game with that skill tree,
the one that intimidates all the new users,
but we're keeping in there.
And so, anyway, that's Path of Exile.
You can Google it if you want more info.
So back in the mid-2000s, my co-founders and I had played a ton of Diablo II,
like thousands and thousands and thousands of hours.
And as we, over time, tired of the game, we looked at other action RPGs that we wanted to try out.
You know, we tried out Dungeon Siege series and Titan Quest and so on.
And we played those games too and enjoyed them,
but only for dozens of hours rather than thousands of hours.
And so this caused us to ask, why did we sink so much more time into Diablo II?
What was perfect?
What made that game the best action RPG that had ever existed?
And so we came up with a bunch of design pillars that we feel a perfect action RPG needs that some
of the other games hadn't quite hit in all cases. And so those design pillars are as follows.
The first one is visceral action combat.
This goes without saying, it's an action RPG.
You need to have immediacy.
You hit a monster, it dies.
Blood goes everywhere.
It falls back, and it's nice and fast and action-based.
And you have to remember, back in 2006,
the atmosphere of online games,
like the climate they were in was World of Warcraft clones.
The way combat worked is you walk up to a monster
and you target it,
and then your character starts hitting it on a timer
and you press your cooldowns occasionally,
and there's no real action.
You're not dodging out of the way when it attacks
because it's gonna hit you anyway.
And so nowadays, of course, everyone's doing a much better job at visceral action combat.
Even strict MMOs that come out have great combat in them.
Games like Black Desert Online, for example, feel really good to play.
So that's a pillar that everyone understands.
There's no particular secret that you need action in an action RPG.
Second, we have randomly generated levels.
Now this is secret sauce for sure.
There were games like Titan Quest that came out
where I played through it and said, this is amazing.
This is the new game I'm gonna play.
And I started my second play through
and didn't get a quarter of the way through it
because I played it before as far as I was concerned.
And so random levels dramatically help people
replay the game.
And when you want a game to be played
for 10 to 20,000 hours over the life cycle
of some of your longest users,
it needs to have the randomness that enables them
to play each individual tile set
two or three or 400 hours worth.
of gameplay.
And so I'll be talking a bunch more about random level generation later on in the talk.
I understand that procedural generation got a bit of a bashing in the last few years because
some games have not used it particularly well, but used carefully with a lot of good theming,
it can work really well.
So next we have randomly generated items.
Now I kind of wanted to just do an items talk,
like just focus on this one for an hour,
and I think I could do a good job of that,
but I'm gonna briefly say that if you get
your random item system good, it makes your game replayable.
And the reason why is because in these kind of games,
your items are your progress, right?
The character level number doesn't matter so much.
No one really cares if you got to level 97 or 94.
What they care about is the cool items you found out
that you got on the way.
And the other nice thing about randomly generated items
is it's not just a linear progression
where the player knows they've got three items left to go
and then they're finished.
We're dealing with ones where the stats are all over the place, who knows what the next best item is, how far it can be pushed.
And because of that you get this cool diminishing returns, so that players really appreciate the small upgrades they find.
Because it's a 1% power increase for their character, but it makes them so much better than more of their friends.
The next one is a secure online economy.
Now this is one of the things that sounds obvious, clearly games need a secure online economy.
But if it's obvious, why does everyone screw it up so badly?
Like, the first thing is, so many games these days just remove trade.
They're like, oh, there's gold sellers, we can't deal with that, we're just gonna get rid of trade.
This is not the right direction.
You need to have trade in your games that are about items, because that way the items have some value.
If you find an item, and you're the only person that can ever consume that,
it's not really something that you've achieved that you can actually, like...
feel good about having, it doesn't have any weight to it.
If you get a game where you get an item that you could give to your friends
if you wanted to, but you're not going to because it's your item, but you could give it to them,
that's something you feel good about having.
And the ability for the item to actually transact with other players
is a critical part in that item having worth in the economy and representing your accomplishment.
The second part of this is the secure part, which again sounds obvious, but so many games these days,
often from console developers who aren't used to proper secure client or server authoritative code,
write their games in such a way that it's really easy to exploit them, there's dupe methods,
there's various dumb stuff that goes on with the PC versions, you know, there's...
There's a lot of horror stories there, but the key takeaway is that there are very few games that actually respect items to the degree that we try to.
We want to make sure this is an online economy where the items are sacrosanct.
They are the progress of the players. They're going to matter.
We don't invalidate them too quickly with new releases of content.
It's a big rant that you can tell I feel passionately about, but needless to say, get your items right.
Anyway, the final one is deep character customization.
This is merely the fact that if you have thousands and thousands of ways of playing your game,
then when someone comes back to play it the second, third, fifth time,
they have a different way that they can play it.
And in some games where they just have a few simple character classes,
and it's pretty straightforward,
you'll play it with the first class, then you'll play it with the second one, then the third,
and eventually you run out of new classes you haven't tried.
Path of Exile tries very hard to make sure the class doesn't actually matter that much,
it's more about what you're doing with it.
Anyway, so there's the Preach E5 design pillars, and we felt that many of those other games that were released failed in a few areas, right?
They didn't have the secure servers, they didn't have the random levels, the items were bad, and so on and so on.
Very fun games to play through, totally worth their money, but not something you can actually sink your 20s into.
All right, so the next, yep, the next topic is,
we wanted to run this as a games as a service.
This is something we knew back in 2006,
though we didn't know the buzzwords for it,
but it was something where we looked at Diablo II
and they had tens of thousands of people
coming back per realm for each one of their ladder resets.
People were excited to jump back into that game
because of the fresh economy and keep playing,
even though the game was not being
substantially updated during that time.
There was a single expansion, a few tiny balance patches.
no real additions. So we felt if we update our game every week with new items, new
Keystone passives, new skills, and we keep Path of Exile updated incredibly fast. How can we not grow? This was the plan
I mean, this is you know, 12 years ago now that we're planning it
And this analysis also helped make us realize that we'd be economically viable at 10,000 average concurrent users
So that means if you sample a number of players online
And if there's 10,000 on average, we'd be totally fine.
We were running a skeleton crew out of New Zealand,
very few people on the team.
We paid for the game ourselves.
We didn't have any investors or publishers
and all that kind of stuff back then.
And we felt 10,000 people is enough to generate
from cosmetic microtransactions,
enough people to generate enough money
to pay for the game service, to pay for development,
to pay for the costs, and then have some money
left over for ourselves if the business goes well.
And so that was our target.
We were aiming low and we tried to hit it.
So, we scaled up from a team of three friends in my garage
to this motley crew of 18 guys.
This is a terrible photo I got on Google Image Search.
These are the initial part of Excel team
that launched the open beta.
We had like one person per department basically.
And we spent six years on it.
And so when we launched, it went really well.
We have two key stats there.
There was massive internet virality.
We had 70,000 peak concurrent users.
This is like pre-Apex Legends kind of numbers.
At 1.5 million signups, we're on top of the world, right?
Like our random garage game had just suddenly
like hit a.
And so we were very keen to see what happened with the player numbers.
So they declined. And it's not unexpected, right?
Like, you know, you release a game and everyone knows the numbers go down eventually.
And so they declined from 70,000 concurrence to 10,000.
Which is great, because we're happy with 10,000. That's where we want to be.
So this is still good news, you know. It was popular and had declined.
point out on the graph where the weekly patches were.
Well, they were every week all the way through there,
and they made no difference.
Like we never, and to this day,
have never seen a rise in player numbers
due to changing a small thing about the game.
It's all about the big changes.
So we switched to doing three weekly updates
because one week patches
just completely paralyze your studio.
You dream about the patch cycle every day, and it's bad.
Anyway, so at this point,
we'd declined from 70,000 to 10,000 users.
The business is still going well.
We're making some money for once,
and things are looking great.
But we need to get our user numbers back up.
We've tasted the sweet fruit of 70,000 concurrent users
and being at the top of the Steam charts
and all that kind of stuff,
and we need to get back up there.
And so we figured, well,
we know that economy resets are important.
They were critically important in Diablo II,
so let's release some leagues.
And the way leagues work in Path of Exile
is that they are basically economy resets.
In this case, it's the Anarchy and Onslaught League.
The Anarchy one adds some rogue exiles to the game,
which are some bad guys you get to find occasionally,
and Onslaught made the monsters attack
and move more quickly.
We also put some challenges in there, and this logo is from the challenge t-shirt that we gave out to the top 50 people.
And those t-shirts are like $1,500 on eBay now, I think? Anyway.
So we gave some t-shirts out to the top players at the start, and this motivated people to perform well in these leagues.
And so the result of this was a hefty 40% increase in player numbers.
We released this content, 40% extra players come back, it's validated.
Except when you look at it in the grand context, that's 40% of somewhere near the 10k mark, and then it declined below 10k.
So we learned to ourselves, we learned that challenge leagues are important, they bring players back, people care,
but we did a really terrible job at marketing these.
A lot of people don't even remember the release, we put them in, we just turned the leagues on basically with a thing on our website.
And so we learned that you have to bundle these economy resets with significantly marketable content,
like new characters, new acts, all that kind of stuff, because then the players and journalists will want to talk about it.
The good news is, since we entered open beta, we've been working on a new character and a new half of an act.
And so that's what Path of Exile 1.00 was.
This is the Scion character class, and that's the Act 3x, as we called it, second half of Act 3 in the background there.
And this is the official 1.00 launch.
And our goal was to get back up to 70,000 concurrent users and keep them.
And so we launched on Steam, we dropped all this content in.
And I have to note, you can't launch on Steam in 2013
when it actually works really well for marketing.
You can't do that every day.
And nor can you make this amount of content every day.
It took a long time.
Use the numbers.
Back up to 70K just like we wanted.
Holding steady, we're feeling really good.
This time we know what we're doing, got a lot of experience.
The numbers are staying up there.
It's awesome.
Okay, so they went down again, that's fine,
games do this, right?
Like everyone's game goes down.
And that bump there is Christmas, by the way.
I don't have a pointer, but the one on the right
is the effect of Christmas, if you're interested
to see what that looks like in a declining game.
So we realized here that we needed,
it's the only thing that causes player numbers
to ever go up, by the way, without releasing new content.
Anyway, so we realized we needed more content.
So we started work on our first Path of Exile expansion
called Sacrifice of the Vile.
Sacrifice of the Vaal introduced new endgame bosses
and introduced side areas and Vaal skill gems
and a couple of new leagues and all the things
a Path of Exile expansion needed roughly.
And how did it do?
Well, that's the bump on the right there.
It's reasonable, we got some more users,
we got some more money, things are good.
Like I have to stress, morale at the company is excellent.
We control our own destiny, everything's awesome,
people are having a good time,
it's great running this game as a service
for almost every team member.
It was their first released game.
We're on top of the world and we're finding
that releasing expansions bumps the player numbers up.
So now we have a button we can push
that makes the player numbers go up.
So let's push it a bunch more times.
We decided to scope out the second expansion to be bigger,
because the key question is, what is the cadence and size that we need to hit for these Path of Exile expansions?
Right? We're all scientists, we want to optimize this.
So, Forsaken Masters comes along.
This is an expansion that augmented the game thoroughly
all the way through with these master missions
and there's like customizable player housing
and that kind of stuff.
It was a good expansion.
And it took about five months to make.
And during which time the player numbers
were pretty flat down the bottom.
But the spike was bigger.
So bigger expansion, bigger spike.
This is looking good.
We have a bigger button we can press if we want to.
But this is tricky because it took longer to make.
So is it even worthwhile sitting at 10,000
concurrent users for so long?
So we decided that we would try an even bigger expansion
while interleaving some smaller updates in.
So we started work on,
well, started work isn't completely correct
because the ACT content guys have been working on this
since we finished ACT 3X,
but we formalized the Path of Exile The Awakening expansion,
which is Path of Exile 2.00.
It adds ACT 4 to the game.
It adds a whole bunch of cool new stuff.
There's socketable jewels that go in the passive tree.
We completely rewrote our networking code,
all sorts of cool stuff that players were gonna love.
And we didn't tell them about it yet
because we're waiting until we can show them
something impressive.
And so this is going on in the background, and we know it's going to be a big spike, or at least that's the theory according to this.
But let's try some stuff in the meantime.
Two more leagues. This is Torment and Bloodlines.
And we released these alongside some probably pretty misguided PvP stuff that we did in December of 2014.
And they were okay. Like, the numbers jumped up again.
Kind of proportional to the size of the content. In this case...
In this case, the Torment and Bloodlines leagues were worthy of a spike about that big.
Certainly not as important as the bigger spikes from the bigger updates.
So far this is validating the thing. Release bigger content, get bigger spikes.
But we're able to make them pretty easily while working on other stuff.
So we're pretty happy with this.
All right, next up is the one month league experiment,
called being really desperate to get your players back
and then calling it an experiment
five years later retroactively.
So we decided to try some one month leagues
to see what would happen.
The idea is we just put some cool game modes on there,
it doesn't take a lot of development work,
and we'll see what happens.
Maybe one month is the ideal cadence
for Path of Exile releases.
So there's the two one-month leagues at the end there.
It's hard to tell where the second one is.
And this is because your players quickly get inoculated to this kind of stuff.
One month is not enough time to play Path of Exile and enjoy all the stuff,
especially for the slower players.
There wasn't new content, there was no marketing.
A lot of people here probably don't know we did them.
The second one was Dark Shrine, by the way.
A fan favorite with like 10 people.
I mean, you can see it at the bump there.
Anyway, so...
This was kind of a failed experiment as far as we were concerned.
It was keeping the players somewhat entertained, like the core audience was good,
but you can see the graph there is trending downwards throughout 2014.
This is the point where we're getting a little bit concerned.
We're still over 10k, you know, we're still making money and it's profitable,
but it's not looking great.
Like, this is the point where we have to question,
do we just make another game instead?
Like, what's going on?
But we had the Awakening coming out.
That was Path of Exile 2.0.
So that was the saving grace.
We wanted to see how that performed.
So, we finished The Awakening, got it released,
and it had a big spike, exactly as we had expected
because it was a lot of content.
So this is like, everything on this graph says
that the more work you do, the better the results are,
which is great, that's a good moral to live by.
And the problem was, this just wasn't sustainable for us.
We had this awful situation where...
We'd work really hard to release some stuff, the player numbers would spike up briefly,
then they're back down to the borderline unprofitable mark, and we have to make more content.
And we just get to press the button really infrequently.
We wanted to change the whole paradigm.
So let's look at what we've learned so far.
Number one, economy resets. That's the key thing here for Action RPG.
If you start a fresh server, everyone rushes in, they take time off work, they want to
get to level 100 the fastest, they find all the good items.
Economy resets are amazing.
They're an opportunity to have a fresh start and a fair playing field for players.
If you've disengaged from the game, the economy restart is the perfect time to get back into
it because it lets you have an equal footing with other people who are much better than
you.
You believe you're better than them and everyone's happy until they're not.
So economy resets were great. The next note was about small content patches.
They never helped us in any way actually increase player numbers. Now don't get me wrong,
releasing content is always good for the game, right? At the beginning when we're doing one weekly updates and adding new items and skills,
that's vitally important to have the game actually have some content for people to play,
but it never moved the numbers up. And the reason why is there are two benefits to content.
The first one is it makes your game better,
and the second one is marketing.
And you want marketing when you're doing this kind of thing
and trying to get your graphs higher.
And so it's very important,
if you batch your content together,
you get both the marketing and making the game better.
So it's gotta be above a threshold
of people wanting to talk about it.
When we release Path of Exile expansions now,
people will message each other excitedly to say,
look at this cool stuff in Path of Exile.
It goes to the top of overall Reddit.
It does all that kind of good stuff.
Back then, no one was calling anyone
when you release a single new skill gem.
And journalists were not covering it, but they are now.
The next thing is balance changes during a league.
If you decide you want to fix something,
you know, to make the game better,
then the people who are doing that thing will be angry.
And if you make something more powerful
because it was too low,
the people not doing that thing are angry
because they missed out on choosing that character build.
And so basically making any kind of mid-season tweaks
is just a very negative experience
for a lot of players who care about fairness.
And so we learned to push these balance changes
to between the leagues,
because that's the point when players
are choosing what character to play.
They can see what's been reduced and what's been improved
and choose to play based on that.
The final story is one that I did not realize myself.
I wish I was smart enough to think of this,
but this actually came from Kriparian,
the awesome streamer who played a lot of
Path of Exile at the time.
And so Kriparian and I were chatting on Skype,
as I like to say that we did, occasionally,
and he said to me, you know what, Chris,
I've got a lesson for you that really helped me
with my streaming.
He said, every day, I will wake up
and I'll stream at a reliable time.
I'm there, right at that moment.
And I'm gonna stream until a predictable time.
And then I'm going to work on my highlights video,
and I'm going to post that at a predictable time.
And then I'm back tomorrow doing exactly the same thing.
And I'm going to try not to take days off.
I'm just going to stream at these times.
And the reason he explained was because that way,
when someone comes home from work
and they're wanting to watch Kripparian,
if that's the time of day that he's streaming,
then they'll be able to watch him.
And if they want to watch a video before they go to bed
or whatever the timing is, it will be there.
And the day that it's not there
is the day they look on the internet and say,
what will entertain me?
What else is there in the world?
And they'll find some other thing,
maybe another streamer, maybe a TV show.
And now that's the thing they're doing for entertainment.
and he felt that his numbers dropped significantly if he deviated from his very rigid schedule.
Now, you know, he's a powerhouse of streaming, right? He's amazing.
And he recommended that we do a similar schedule with Path of Exile.
Because he said, look at your graph of what you've actually done in 2014.
I made this graph, not him. But this is...
It was all over the place, right? We've got medium leagues at 20 weeks, big ones at 16,
they arbitrarily get small and close together. No Path of Exile player is going to think anything
other than, is that game dying? Like, what's going on with them getting smaller and what's
with the timing? No one can predict anything. And so he strongly suggested we have a rigid schedule
because that way it's more convenient for him because then he knows when to stream it,
but it's also convenient for everyone else. And so we tried this out.
So this was our new schedule, the new era of leagues,
as it's called.
And so they're every 13 weeks.
So this means exactly four of them fit into a year.
That means that we know that they're going to be
on the second weekend of the final month
in each quarter or whatever we do.
And this perfectly fits having one a few weeks
before Christmas and a week before GDC
and a week before E3.
It just matches everything and it's great.
So we started doing this and we were initially
doing some pipelining.
We work on a small one while working on a bigger one
in the background.
And then in the second part of the cycle,
we release the big one and then repeat this.
And that enabled us to experiment with scope and so on,
because at this point we still weren't 100% sure
how large these had to be to have the correct effect.
We were pretty sure 13 weeks,
which is roughly three months, was the right amount of time.
So, that was the new schedule.
Now the key philosophy here is players will stop playing your game.
That's unavoidable.
At some stage something's going to happen that makes them stop playing.
They get a new job or whatever, they get burned out, another game comes along.
But the key thing is to give them a lot of opportunity to re-engage.
And that means they have to really clearly know when the next coming back.
It is inexcusable for a player to be able to leave your game without knowing the date
that they are returning to it, as far as we're concerned with this.
And so that's why we want to make sure that users quit with a plan to come back.
Because before we clearly signaled when the next release was,
players would get horribly burnt out and then they would just never play again.
Whereas now, they can quit before they get burnt out.
They can say, you know what, I've finished this league, I've seen this stuff,
I'll just come back for the next one.
And that's amazing for us because then the users are fresh,
they get chances to play their AAA games or Fortnite or whatever they do,
and it works really well.
Also, we monetize very heavily towards the start of our leagues.
That's where we introduce new cosmetic microtransactions and supporter packs and so on.
So it honestly doesn't matter a lot if we lose users right at the end,
because they'll come back and monetize again at the beginning of the next league.
So let's have a look at some results.
So this tiny little bump at the bottom
is the same size as roughly Forsaken Masters was.
Just for, I've rescaled this because it's foreshadowing.
Anyway, so this was Talisman, right?
Talisman was a great league, it was a decent size.
If we could release Talisman every three weeks,
every three months, I'd be pretty happy.
And so Talisman went well.
And that was one of the small ones in our cycle.
All right, so the next one was the Ascendancy slash Parandas update.
This was a bigger one because as you saw, we're going small, big, small, big.
So, so far there's no unexpected results, right? Small, big, all good.
Next one is a small one again because it was Prophecy which wasn't as big.
But you'll notice it was actually a little bit bigger than Talisman.
So, this is how we rationalize. The numbers went down,
but in a good way, right? Because they're bigger than the previous small one.
And then sure enough, we released the next big one,
nothing surprising.
This is Atlas of Worlds and Essence League.
And at this point, we decided we hated pipelining
because we're getting so much attention split
between these two leagues.
We wanted to see what happens if we just focus
on one thing at a time and do it well.
So we said, if we could make one thing, what would it be?
So we made Breach, and Breach is very popular,
and it was our best release ever.
So then we said, well, what are we gonna make next?
What about Legacy?
So we made Legacy, best release ever.
And at this point, the background process of making a new act that trundles along all ways in Path of Exile's background had Act V almost ready.
That's the 3.0.0 expansion, the fall of Oriath, and that was sitting in our back pocket ready for release, so we did.
And that was huge. Definitely our best release ever.
We were feeling really good at this stage.
User numbers are big, we just launched in China,
we've just launched on Xbox.
This is just PC here and it's already very high,
dwarfing all our previous results.
And so the question is what would happen
with our 13-week cycle going forward?
Now we knew, and this happened,
we knew that the next release would not be as tall as 3.0
because it was just a regular 13-week cycle.
It wasn't an entire expansion
that took 18 months and 80 people to put together.
The war for the Atlas one was not as big as 3.0,
but it was bigger than the previous expansion before that.
And then Bestry, and then Incursion,
and it just keeps climbing.
The 13-week cycle is working really well.
Then we released Delve, which was great,
and actually down a little bit,
which we're not blaming on Delve,
because it's probably a lack of retention
during Incursion or something like that.
And we're a little bit disappointed it was down.
Like, this is the point we are questioning,
you know, is this parabola finally, like, hit the top?
But betrayal was really, really, really big.
And so when you look at it in the context
of all of the Path of Exile history,
you can see that we were clearly declining.
There's no argument about that for the first few years,
and then really clearly climbing.
And so this is the brunt of what I'm now gonna talk about
for the rest of the talk,
is what we do to actually make these,
and how we scope them out,
and how we deliver them fast enough.
Okay.
I'm gonna go through the marketing page
for Path of Exile Synthesis,
which is our most recent release.
And what I'm gonna focus on specifically here
is the way that we target specific groups
of Path of Exile users.
Because everyone likes something about the game,
that's why they're playing it.
And so we've identified a big set of categories
of things that people enjoy.
We've broken all the players into psychographics,
and we're gonna target each one with a specific slide.
And the goal here is when they're reading through the page,
they'll look at the features, they'll say, oh this is cool.
And then they'll find the thing that clicks for them.
They'll find the reason they're playing,
and they'll say, whoa, that's good.
Okay, time to tell all my friends.
So first of all we start setting the scene, the setting and the story and new characters and so on.
And there are players who really like discovering about the story in a league.
This is the thing that turns them on and makes them want to play, and so we lead with that.
And at this point some players are going to say,
OK, cool, this looks really nice. It's got this awesome blue portal and this dude and you can explore memories.
I'm going to go and get excited about it.
The next thing we do is we talk about a unique gameplay mechanic in combat that we've introduced.
In this case, it's the ability to explore these decaying memories and run away from this wall of decay.
And this is something that for many players, that changes completely how Path of Exile plays
because now they're running away from the decay wall, they've got to use movement skills differently.
And this is a thing which causes them to become excited
because that group of players loves the idea of combat being slightly different.
The next group of players don't necessarily care about the story, they don't necessarily
care about combat, they care about long-term meta progression within a league.
The concept of building something up over time.
And so we often implement kind of meta mechanics in Path of Exile which are like games unto
themselves.
And this really appeals to types of players who want a meta layer on top of the regular
gameplay.
And so for example, in Synthesis, you could get these puzzle pieces that you connect together
a bit like Carcassonne and explore the memory map with that.
And this is entirely a meta mechanic.
It doesn't have any impact on the actual moment-to-moment gameplay of the game.
This just dictates how you access the advanced content of the league.
And that really appeals to groups of players who want to make sure they're doing a different
meta thing with each league.
Next we have what I call endgame aspirational content.
So these are like final boss fights.
They're really hard to get to.
You've got to do a lot of meta progression to get there.
They're very difficult encounters.
They've got good rewards.
You have to learn the strategy of a fight.
They're big multi-stage ones.
And they take a lot of development time to make.
And they're only accessed by maybe 10% of our players,
the top players who can get through to the end of the game,
get a chance to see this content.
And you may ask yourself, why are you guys spending like 20% of your development effort on something that affects 10% of players?
And the reason why is there are groups of players in there who want to know that there is content that only they can get to.
Stuff that's actually hard and they're an exclusive club for being able to do it.
And so those players will work incredibly hard to identify the content, work out how to get there, rush there as quickly as possible, build characters custom made for it,
do time runs, try to do it in hardcore, try to do it without getting hit, all of these things, and then repeat it over and over to get all the good items.
And so...
we found that it's incredibly useful to have this end game content,
even if not everyone gets a chance to experience it themselves,
because there's a good strong overlap between streamers and these top 10% of players,
because streamers are generally the better players in the game,
and so they can consume this content on stream and everyone else can watch and think,
oh, I wish I was that good, I wish I could get characters that strong
and be able to play the top Path of Exile content.
And so we try to appeal to that group there,
which has a lot of overlap with the rest of the player base from an aspirational point of view.
Next, we talk about league rewards.
Everyone loves finding items,
that's why they're playing these games,
and so we introduce new rewards
that synergize with existing systems in the game.
And this is for players who want to improve their characters
and find out how they're going to be subtly different
in terms of what items they're getting.
In this case, it's the fractured and synthesized items.
We talk about crafting.
There are Path of Exile players who love crafting.
There are ones who will be really bored
looking at all the other stuff
until we talk about crafting,
and then the world opens up with possibilities
of what kind of stuff they can make using the new systems.
And this is also important from a gameplay point of view.
As any Path of Exile players know here,
if you can get a head start on the crafting in the League
and make the best stuff before other players,
you're kind of the source of the best items
and the exalts come rolling in.
And so this is actually one of the power game strategies
here is to care about the crafting for Path of Exile.
We like to do meta balance changes.
So for example, we did a spell casting rebalance
and synthesis.
And one of the reasons we do this
is because there are players who will play the best character
build and only the best character build.
And if that's the same for two leagues in a row,
they're playing the same character
for two leagues in a row, which might be fine.
But it probably is boring to play the same character
for two leagues in a row.
And so it's really important that we mix things up.
I mean, hopefully not completely arbitrarily.
We're trying to solve problems here.
We're trying to take the things that are overpowered
and make them a bit worse and take the things that
haven't been used for a while and make them really exciting.
But this is very important because it means that people will get a chance to see different aspects of Path of Exile from league to league.
Now, an important thing here is it doesn't require developing new content.
We're literally just rebalancing and so on.
And that means we get to leverage all of Path of Exile's hundreds of existing skills and systems when creating,
and kind of make pseudo content by bumping it up to be top tier.
Having said that, it's very important that we actually do introduce new skills
in order to appeal to players who are keen to play a new powerful character
and want to make sure they're doing something snazzy that hasn't been released before.
And so we shine a spotlight on various new skills and archetypes of players
so that they...
so that players who enjoy playing what's new and hot
get a chance to clearly see what it is on the marketing page.
Finally, I know I've talked about item rewards,
but the items we're talking about here are subtly different.
And you can tell this game's got a lot of items in it.
And this is referring to the items
that regular monsters in the game can drop.
Just the idea of playing normal Path of Exile content
and many people wanting to know
that regular monsters drop more interesting stuff
than before.
There's new divination cards, there's new unique items,
there's new mods available.
This is really important because for some people,
they kind of ignore the league.
We put a bunch of F in it,
and they just want to play Path of Exile,
and they kind of ignore it.
And it's fine.
We just have to make sure that those people understand
there is more regular Path of Exile for you as well.
Now there's plenty more sections in our marketing materials, obviously, we try to sell them some stuff as well,
but that's completely irrelevant for this talk.
Here's the checklist of all the things that, for Path of Exile, we find are important to push to the players.
And so that's basically the scope of what one of these updates is.
Now if you've been involved in game production, you may ask,
that's an awful lot of work to do in 13 weeks, how do we do that?
And so the remainder of the talk...
which we have about 20 minutes.
The remainder of the talk is about how we achieve this
in a 13-week cycle.
So I'm gonna give you a bunch of advice.
Some of it is going to be a bit weird, but bear with me.
Okay, so let's start with the easy stuff.
Fast prototyping.
Obviously, you should do fast prototyping, right?
Why do I even have the slide?
Because it's actually really hard
and we fail at it all the time.
Like the fast prototype for synthesis came in really late.
I was initially gonna say how late,
but that's really embarrassing.
So let's just say it was late.
And that reduced the amount of iteration we could do.
And potentially that affected the quality of the league.
We're having to do a lot of catch-up work at the moment,
changing some mechanics based on the fact that our prototype
was not ready early enough.
Thankfully, the fast prototype for 3.7.0 has already been completed
and thrown away once and completed again,
and that's a really good process.
Try to do this right, it's the easy part.
Now to get on to some harder stuff.
Okay, procedural level generation.
This is a multi-hour talk that I'm condensing
down to a few minutes.
Okay, procedural level generation is critical
because your leagues, or whatever is appropriate
for your game, need new content for players
to actually play through.
And that means making new areas,
because you've got to go to new places.
But the traditional way of making levels in games
can be slow and involves placing a bunch of things around
and involving artists and taking time.
Let's try to make a level in 60 seconds.
So, I load up the tool and I draw a line across horizontally, which is a river,
and then I draw a path going downwards, which is the white path there,
and then I put forest around it.
And I press the button to say go, and it makes a path of XL level out of tiles.
and there's a river and a path intersecting, and the engine knows it can put a bridge there and all this fancy stuff,
and I click go again and I get a completely different one, and go again and I get a different.
So, by default here, it's producing random levels.
Now, these are relatively similar, because it's just a relatively simple one, but I'll make it more complicated.
So, I can then play this in-game, and sure enough, there's a pretty bridge over the river,
and it works out the direction of the water flow, and does all the fancy foam generation.
All this cool stuff just happens, because we've got mature tools for that now.
And so I say, okay, so this is a forest.
I need some stuff to fill it with.
So I make a set of tiles that can go in there,
some trees and some fallen over trees and bandit camps
and tents and some rocks.
And it puts them throughout the level.
And then I generate again and get a different set of stuff
and again and get a different one.
And the player story is subtly different each time.
The crossing is at a different place.
The bandit camp is in a different place
if it's even there at all.
And you have to bear in mind that this was like
literally just a cross in the editor,
like the simplest possible graph that took seconds to do.
So here's a real level from Path of Exile.
This is the river crossing that's to the left of Act 2 town.
And the way that this all works is instead of doing levels like this,
where you just make one and hope it's random enough,
you make like 20 different variations.
You have two rivers, you have five rivers, you have no rivers.
You have it so that there's multiple roads or a fork in the road.
You have all of these crazy things.
And then when the game is generating the level,
it picks which topology to use first,
and then it does the random generation within it.
And so you've got two levels of randomness there.
And so this is an example topology from the river crossings, and here's some examples of what it can make.
So, there are many ways across the rivers.
There's paths, there's broken paths, there's little stones, there are fallen logs and so on.
You've got various boss encounters in here.
You've got different exits going off into different levels, waterfalls, that kind of stuff.
Here's a completely different variation of it that's generated.
In this case, there's like a different user story as they play through and get different bosses and so on.
This one here has like an island in the middle with a big like thick copse of trees there.
And so this area feels different every time you play
and did not take the artists very long to do.
For Synthesis, we said, oh, we need like 50 or 60
of these areas made that the players can play through.
And we kind of need them right now, like today preferably,
because we have to actually like use them
to put the monsters in and playtest.
And so they took minutes to make each one.
I think it was like 20 minutes.
But the point is they did it pretty fast.
And that's something we can do
because of a procedural level generation tool suite
that we've made.
And I should note all of Path of Exile's tools
and engine are entirely custom.
Not something I necessarily recommend,
but it's great when you've got it.
Okay, so I'm now going to show you why the level generation is good in another way.
It understands about your league mechanics.
So this is Abyss.
This is where when you're playing through the area, there's a crack that you can follow
and monsters come out of it.
And so when we're generating the level, the generator can place the Abyss cracks throughout
the level in an interesting way, aware of the context of where players can go.
So that's an outdoors one.
This is an indoors one.
It will follow the paths and go through the doorways and along the little narrow walkways
and all that kind of stuff because it understands about the walkability because it just generated
this maze for you.
And so because of this, Abyss is a fun mechanic.
It's different every time you play it
because of the level that it's present in.
It's a completely different story.
And this kind of leads on to the next topic.
And this is a topic about
multiple overlapping axes of randomness.
Now to give an example,
imagine you're a Path of Exile designer,
your job is to make encounters like fights.
So you're sitting at your desk and I come over and say,
we need lots of these.
We have a encounter that needs a ton of variety
because we expect the players to play it like 500 times.
And you say, wait, wow, I can't make 500 variations of this.
So you try and you have 10 encounter types to start with.
You've got the one where the monsters drop down from the ceiling.
You've got the one where they crawl up the walls.
You've got the one where they teleport in.
You've got the one where they're in a big sphere that breaks open.
You do as many encounters as you can do and you hit about 10.
And then I say, look, 10 isn't enough.
I said 500 retries of this.
So you make another 10 and now they're getting diminishing returns
and it's really hard to think of them.
So that's the point where we add another axis.
In this case it's like, okay, well all of that was with spiders, let's make zombie versions.
So you make it so it can spawn zombies, and then bats, and so on and so on.
So that's another axis.
And then we're like, okay, random bosses.
Randomly, some of these are going to be bosses.
So sure enough, the fight's no different because you get lucky or unlucky with how many bosses there are.
Then we're going to add some random mods to the fight, and so on and so on.
So each axis increases it, and it gets to the point where you've done five times the work,
but got ten thousand times the amount of randomness out, versus just making 50 encounters,
and then it gets boring once they've played all 50, which is the prophecy league.
Okay.
So, I'm going to show you a video of Breach, which is an example of a league with lots
of these axes.
So you tag this spooky hand, and it opens up a breach, which is kind of like a parallel
dimension where you fight these monsters, and if you kill them fast enough, the radius
keeps increasing, and it gets harder and harder to keep it open until it collapses.
Now there are good and bad things that can occur. This is a great breach because it's outdoors and
so you get a big circle you can kill a lot of monsters. This is an indoors one where you got
super unlucky and it's up against the side of the level and that's a bad breach because now
it's harder to fight all the monsters and that's okay because I'll look forward to the next good
one but there's way more axes. The monster density can vary, you can get these like special chests
that spawn.
very rarely within it, so you're lucky there's some chests up here that are like class pans that you can tag.
There are different varieties of flavour of Breach. You want to get the Chaos ones
rather than the Fire ones potentially because they've got better meta progression associated.
You can find Breach Lord bosses that maybe you do or don't want to spawn depending on how hard they are.
And so there's so many things that can happen inside of Breach,
you're always left feeling that the next one is going to be better
because you've never seen a perfect one on all axes.
All right, so let's talk about asset reuse.
This is another obvious thing.
If you're making a game like this,
as a games as a service model
where you want to make content really quickly,
then it's important to reuse your assets where you can.
It would be criminal to make entirely new assets.
The artist would be really, really,
really put to a lot of work.
So let's have a look at how we've done that in Path of Exile.
These are the same area.
On the right, we have like Kalm's lava cave,
and on the left, we have a plateau area.
Now, what we did is we removed the lava
and changed the environment lighting so it looks different,
but the tiles are the same.
I think many of the textures are the same as well.
That was really fast to do.
Now this is why you shouldn't add a day-night cycle to your game like this.
So many people make action RPGs and it's easy to add a day-night cycle.
So they do, because look at how awesome it is on the trailer to have to show off the
day-night cycle.
But that means you're throwing away the ability to hide versions of areas that use a different
environment elsewhere in the game.
As long as they're far enough away and look sufficiently different, then people will not
necessarily feel when they're playing through.
The players don't care in principle that you've reused content, they expect it.
But they care when they can notice it.
And so if you have a day-night cycle for each of your areas,
you've thrown away so many permutations
you could use to add actual meaningful extra content
elsewhere in the game.
Here's another area where we took the icy glacier area,
I think this is the ascent area,
and we made it yellow and took the snow away
and now we've got a desert.
And so we do this extensively throughout the game.
I think like acts six through 10 show a lot of examples
of both this and actual new assets mixed together
in a way that's very hard to tell,
but was actually very, very cost effective
at making content.
Here's another example with monsters.
So on the left here you can see a green flying monster, you can see a spiker and a bone wheel skeleton.
And at the top you can see a random portal frame made of metal.
Now we had a sudden and urgent need for a pile of synthesis monsters that looked cool.
So we said, that metal stuff looks cool, let's take that and let's put it on the rigs of the monsters on the left.
And so sure enough, we immediately have instantly animated and rigged monsters we can use.
And all we had to do was give them new names, give them new sounds, give them new effects,
and give them new skills so they have a meaningful different combat interaction with the player.
And then suddenly we had our synthesis monsters sorted out.
To make monsters on the left involves spooling up an asset creation pipeline that involves
concepting and high poly models and low poly models and texturing and all that UV stuff.
And I don't know any of this.
Animation rigging the whole works, you know getting effects. It takes months to make monsters
But if you do this like cheap approach here
You can make stuff that looks different than what you have in the game at the moment or relatively quickly and
We often have to make monsters with days of notice when we're putting these leaks together
So techniques like this really help and the best thing is these synthesis monsters don't feel like reskins
They've got their own new skills and stuff. It isn't just a blue version of the flying thing
It's like a cool metal version of the flying thing
Okay, so now we're going to talk about content reuse, which is different than asset reuse.
Because I'm talking about taking like a wholesale block of content and reusing it.
So this is Breach, which I just showed you.
And in the regular game, you'd find these hands and fight the monsters,
and players understood it and they liked it.
And then we...
We turned the Breach League off and had them relatively scarce within the game, but it
was available as a reward for later elsewhere.
So when we did Incursion, sure enough, the Vile have been researching Breaches in the
Temple of Atzoatl, and so you find Breaches in there.
And when the player sees that purple hand, they immediately notice.
They know exactly what it means in terms of the fact they're about to get a big fight
and lots of monsters, lots of experience, lots of items.
They understand the rewards.
They understand that if you find Splinters inside the Breach, it lets you create Breach
Stones, which lets you go and fight some endgame meta stuff entirely by seeing a purple hand
there.
This is a breach inside the Delve content.
So deep underground, there's Purple Hands,
and we just chuck it in there,
and it's really, like, it's entirely positive for players.
They hit a whole system
that they really enjoy engaging with.
Here we have some Harbinger fight in the regular game
when that was a main league,
and sure enough, you get the same fight
deep underground in Delve,
where there's a Harbinger portal
that the monsters come out of,
and it means you get access
to all of the rewards for that league.
This gentleman here is called Kadiro. He gives you bro deals for awesome items.
He's like a traveling salesman and we used him in the Parandus League and in very little since then.
But when we're designing betrayals rewards, of course one of the 200 or 300 outcomes has to be Kadiro's in a cage and he's very happy to do a deal with you.
And this is cute because of course, like, why is he in a cage in this area?
But it was something the players really liked because now when they want access to the Kadiro content,
they know they can go and find him in this outcome and all of that stuff is available.
So we found that wholesale content reuse has been incredibly useful at both bolstering the rewards in the game,
but also making sure that players immediately say,
oh, I know this, I know this, it's going to be great.
Okay, so now is the time for us to talk about some more controversial lessons.
This is the point where I get labeled crazy.
Alright, so this is the quality curve.
This is relatively obvious.
You have your work versus quality thing.
And this has an asymptote.
That means that you can never get to 100% quality.
It's going to take infinitely long in terms of work,
because people want more and more and more fixes.
But you can get pretty close.
The question is how far along the curve do you go?
And when you're left with 13 weeks, you can't apply the
when-it's-done philosophy, and you have to pick somewhere.
So for example here, for 50% of the effort,
you get 90% of the quality.
Now I'm not saying to release games that are only 90% quality,
but the way you do it is by putting the quality in the right places.
Polish the things that matter,
and don't care about the stuff that doesn't matter.
Now this means that you have to make some very difficult decisions about what things to pay attention to
and therefore the best skill for a developer to have on your team is the ability to know what actually matters.
Relatively few people on the Path of Exile team are able to actually gauge that as accurately as we would like
and so it's very important that we do focus everyone's efforts on the things that really, really pay benefits
for the actual content we're releasing.
And this is also why we hire our player base to be in the QA team and Dev team
because Path of Exile players will understand what's important because they've played through it a whole bunch.
and know how they interact with it.
All right, pipelining, we tried it, we really did.
We wanted to have two or three releases on the go at once
and it just really failed.
And we found several problems with this.
The first one was that when we're focusing
on too many releases at once,
we always have an excuse to go and look at the other one
when things got hard.
If you assign a developer, do all this stuff for release A
and then maybe do this stuff for release B later,
they'll work on A like they're meant to
until they get stuck.
And instead of then solving the hard problem,
they would often say,
oh, well, there's some easy stuff I can do on B,
so I'll just work on that for a few hours instead
to clear my mind.
And that's great, but then A is completely stalled.
And when you have precious few weeks
in order to get this stuff done,
you really can't handle those stalls.
The second thing is, if you pipeline releases,
you do not have time to react
to what the game actually needs.
By the time it's apparent that the game
needs a new end game, you're like three quarters
of the way through making a new beginning to it
or something like that, because Reddit will suddenly decide
there is a thing that needs fixing.
And if you have the ability to say, yes sir,
and get that done in 13 weeks,
that's not even good enough some of the time for them.
But having to spend like, you know, oh wait, wait, we've got the next two expansions almost finished, kind of,
we'll do this one next year, it's just not going to work.
The game is on fire until that thing is fixed.
It's also important not to stall content for later.
We get into a situation where we're like,
we finished all the skills we said we were gonna make,
and we've got two extra ones that got out of prototyping
and they're kind of finished.
Do we wait?
Do we leave them for the next expansion
so we have less to do?
No, put them in the game now.
The game needs to be in its best form now, all the time,
because you don't get second chances.
As much growth as possible every league,
otherwise you'll start to decline.
People express concern about creativity here.
They say, look, Chris, you've got this plan for like another 10 years of Path of Exile
with four releases per year.
That's 40 more leagues.
I can think of two good ones.
Where are we going to get 40 from?
And I always refer them back to Magic the Gathering.
They have released new sets, four per year or whatever,
for so many decades now, like 26 years in or something,
hundreds of these things, and there's always new ideas.
It's amazing the fact they can go back to the well
and find really cool, compelling stuff.
And so whenever I hear that we're not gonna come up
with another 10 or 20 or 30 of these,
I go, they did 100, you know,
and I'm certain we'll be able to, the well will refill.
Now if you're a project manager, you're probably asking how we can make all of this stuff in 13 weeks.
Because it's not just we start work and in 13 weeks later we release it.
Consider how the schedule actually works in reality.
So we release the content and now there's problems with it, right?
Right now there's a bit of a fire where we're fixing some stuff with synthesis that the community didn't like.
That's cool, we'll have that fixed early next week.
But this has taken the first two weeks of the schedule to do so.
So there's some time spent doing live ops work on the existing release you've done.
Then you've got to prototype the new stuff, right?
Ideally that's a bit pipelined in there, but still it takes time.
It's going to be another week before we really know for sure what 3.7.0 is.
So that's three weeks gone. Ten weeks left.
And coming from the other end, we like to renounce our content three weeks before the end.
We put our page up, we get the players hyped, they have time to tell their friends, there's a countdown.
You know, it makes sense for people to book time off work. So that's three weeks gone there.
We then have to actually do a press tour where we show all the journalist stuff.
It's very important to actually do real marketing and PR.
So we spend two weeks showing all the people stuff and preparing the marketing page.
But in order to do this, we have to actually have content ready to show them,
like a trailer and slides and this kind of stuff.
And that takes a week.
So now we've got this like four or five week window in the middle
to actually make all of the stuff.
And that's difficult.
And that's where the next counterintuitive advice comes in.
This is how you get your art so quickly.
Create content you have no plan for.
We have themed assets that we commission
because we know one day we're keen to use them.
And a great example of this is with the Betrayal League.
We decided we're gonna make this very complicated
evil organization with 19 members
who all have backstories and they all look different
and they feel different from any Path of Exile characters
we've had so far.
But where are we gonna get 19 fully modeled, rigged,
voice acted?
fleshed out characters like that in three or four weeks.
And the answer was, we go to our giant store of content
that we just have because we made it,
and we pick a bunch of characters.
We're like, this is a microtransaction armor set.
We were gonna sell it, but if I put it on a bandit
and sell it in two years, this is a new character.
And so, we found, we have just a catalog
of Path of Exile stuff that the team have made
because they can slot it into the art pipeline,
which is going to have a place in the world one day,
and we just pick some things for the league.
And I'll give you another example.
So this is not a real example.
We are never going to do a Path of Exile expansion
related to dragons,
because we don't want there to be dragons in our world.
However, if we decided one day that dragons were okay,
we'd say to the team,
hey guys, make some dragons,
and tell me in a year when they're finished.
And then there'll be dragons
sitting there in the library of stuff.
And when we're looking at league ideas,
we're like, could we do dragons this time?
Sure, how would that work?
And when we hit the prototyping,
the dragons are ready to go.
And so we have so much stuff being made for the future.
We have bits and pieces for expansions next year
where we don't know what that expansion is,
but we have an idea of a theme that we would like to do.
And maybe it's finished early.
Maybe we can use that this year.
Maybe we can take a few of those assets
for this current league, potentially.
And it's just so good to have that giant library of stuff.
Okay, so in conclusion.
We initially released Path of Exile,
kind of failed at getting any growth,
then we turned things around
with this aggressive 13 week schedule,
and I've talked a lot about how we actually manage that
and various takeaways that are a bit counterintuitive
to regular industry advice.
There's one last thing I'd like to end on.
People quit Path of Exile while they're playing the league and come back in the next one.
But what's fascinating is that the graph of people quitting accessing the community is a lot less steep.
So the yellow line there is people quitting the game.
It goes from 100% down to 20% by the end,
because there really isn't much point in playing in the last week,
because the new thing's coming out a few days later and you're about to essentially have your progress reset.
But people still use the website at no less than 50% of peak.
And these are players who are still engaged in reading the patch notes,
telling us we did it wrong, looking at all the changes, and buying stuff.
People who are not playing the game will come back and buy microtransactions
and supporter packs because they're available for when they next want to play.
And this is amazing because this is actually what we care about,
is keeping the community engaged.
And that community is never going below 50% during the quiet periods.
What's also interesting is the size of the community right at the end there, in terms of people accessing the website,
is a perfect predictor for server numbers for the next league.
So far, for like, you know, three years in a row, we've been able to predict server capacity for each launch
because of just looking at the website activity and using some ratios, and that's worked really well.
So anyway, the vindication we have with this whole plan is the fact that...
The fact that year after year we've managed to both grow our player numbers, but also get to the point where people never really leave Path of Exile.
They're still playing it, even if they say, I'm done with this league, I'll see you guys in a few months.
We know they're coming back, and they reliably do, they reliably keep spending and having a good time.
And this is the motivation we need to keep releasing quality content.
All right, so slight plug, we're hiring.
We're in New Zealand, so that's hard.
It's hard to get work visas,
and we don't pay as much as the Bay Area,
but if that's no problem,
and you wanna work on Path of Exile
and like everything you saw,
there's the contact details.
And also, please fill out the speaker survey.
It's very important to GDC
so they can get high-quality speakers.
And of course, I would love to answer any questions.
Timeline-wise, it looks like we have like five
or 10 minutes, so use the microphone
if you would like to ask something.
So first I just want to say thanks for making the game
I've been playing since open beta and every league since it's just incredible kind of inspired me to enter this industry
but my question is that
You talk about reusing content and Path of Exile now.
There's so many options in end game, right?
It used to be just grinding maps,
but now we have lots of these meta systems
that we can engage in.
And I'm curious, with player retention,
games like Warframe allow players to
very specifically choose what they go into, right?
They're like, I want to grind out this meta system
and make a lot of progress there,
but in Path of Exile it feels widespread.
Like you kind of progress in all things slowly
as you work through the end game map system.
So I'm wondering if you have any opinions on
Path of Exile going forward in regards to allowing more player choice in what types
of previous league content they engage in throughout their experience in the endgame?
Right.
Okay, to repeat the question just for the recording, so you're basically asking, in
Path of Exile there's a lot of content in the endgame and you get access to it as you
find it.
It's very hard to actually focus on narrowing down to specific content you want to engage
in.
So this is something we've been experimenting with in the last few leagues.
We introduced Scarabs in the Betrayal League, which is something that's a tradable way of
augmenting the amount of a specific type of content that you find.
This is something we are planning to work on more because we do think that someone being
able to specialize is an important thing.
It's kind of like a trade skill or profession in another game.
If you're just a really good person at playing delve content or synthesis content,
that's something that's good for you to have a specialization in.
So this is a direction I would like us to go further,
but we are very careful, because everything here is tradable.
If we go slightly over the line, suddenly everyone is doing exactly that
and farming the optimal thing, and it's hard to get items out of the economy
once you've put them there. So we're probably too cautious with addressing that.
Hey, thank you so much for the talk.
How do you keep your team engaged with working on a game this long?
So the question is how we keep our team engaged for working on a game this long.
It helps to be the only big game development company in New Zealand.
I'm kidding.
Our team have amazing, amazing staff retention.
We love working with them, we treat them as well as we can
and it really helps.
To them, we're not necessarily working on Path of Exile for this long, but we're working on these 13 week game jams
where we're releasing new things. Like last year we said, who likes Pokemon? We all like Pokemon, let's do Beastory.
And we made a league based on that. And the team we're engaging, they're drawing the art for the little book that you can tick them all off.
And everyone's having a great time. And it's the frequent release cycles which let us actually, like, kind of,
everyone, when you join the Path of Exile team, you get an experience of designing and working on and releasing and then maintaining
a complete game four times a year, basically.
Awesome, thank you.
All right, so you have told us about your numbers
and how did you manage them on your own efforts, right?
But I subjectively think that it's
because of yours, good decisions,
while your competition was not doing really well.
So I feel obligated to ask the question,
how did the out of season, April Fool joke, actually,
that happened in BlizzCon actually affected Path of Exile?
I have a graph.
You've seen it.
So that was the spike there at the end.
And I do think that the spike was larger
because of what you're referring to.
For the recording, he's referring to the...
Diablo Immortal announcement at Blizzcon last year.
This did drive traffic to Path of Exile.
Having said that, Betrayal was still our best release
from a content point of view, and we believe
it still would have been our best release,
even without the additional traffic.
We can tell who the new users are.
It was certainly helpful.
But yeah, it is useful when fortuitous events happen.
Having said that, it still means we have to stay vigilant.
There are gonna be a lot more competitors this year.
There are a lot of action RPGs that look really good
that are being developed.
Hey Chris, thank you for talking so fast
and covering so much.
My question is about one of the pillars
you talked about in the beginning
about a good RNG item system.
Could you talk about some common problems
or things not to do that maybe you've seen
in the industry or that you guys encountered
with these item systems?
So you're wanting to hear about some problems with item systems that other games do.
This is like, getting to know me in person is hearing about this stuff forever.
Um, okay, so...
In my opinion, the biggest mistake that games make with their item systems
is they have item mods that are individually hard to feel.
Like, the goal with Path of Exile is if you strip your character down to be pretty simple,
and you put an item on without looking at the mods,
you should be able to play and say what the mods do based on how the game feels.
Now this isn't something we always meet.
Obviously there's 11,000 stats in the game,
so it's hard to meet it with all of them.
But the core thing is we want them
to individually be impactful.
There's none of this like, plus one strength,
what does that even mean?
You know, we make sure the amount of strength
is actually meaningfully increasing your life,
meaningfully making at least 5% boost to damage
so you can feel the difference.
That's one example there.
Another example of what people do with their item systems
is they'll come up with a basically set of sequential items
where you can get this one, then you get this one, then you get this one.
And this is setting up a content train
that players, when they get the top item,
they're then saying, well, what is there to find now?
And you as the developer have to go and add more items on the end.
In Path of Exile, we go, yeah, there's random mods.
You'll get a top 10% item, you get a top 8%,
maybe a top 5%, but we believe that there are not,
like, the best items that were possible in 2013
have not necessarily been found yet
in any reasonable numbers,
just because of the harsh diminishing returns.
So to some extent, the initial levels
and mods that we set up six years ago are still working
and we haven't had to go and pile on additional higher mods
in Path of Exile, at least not to any large degree.
Thank you.
Hello, and thank you for the talk.
So you guys mentioned that your motivation for making this game was traditional boxed games like Diablo 2 and so on.
There the monetization model is well you like the game, you buy it and you enjoy it.
But for you guys it was not that sort of model.
It was mostly external visual updates and so on.
Moreover, a point of innovation I believe was your support packs.
Could you tell us a little bit about how you derived that business model?
That's a great question. So the question was, given that the other action RPGs were premium paid games,
why did we go free to play, have cosmetic microtransactions and supporter packs?
It was our plan to go free to play before that was a thing. We wanted to be the first free game.
It sounds silly, but that was 2006. We'd seen MapleStory, they were making a lot of money in Korea,
and we thought we'd revolutionize the Western gaming market.
Now I try not to say this because it's dumb because then if you spend seven years making the game
Everyone's free to play by the time you release in fact when we did release free to play was a bad phrase that you say
Free to play they assume bad monetization. We lost users by saying we were free
We tried very hard to make it seem you've got to pay for it anyway
So the ethical cosmetic microtransactions thing was because when we initially scoped the game out that was the only thing that made sense
We didn't realize that selling power was even this possible strategy, right? So
We scoped this out because it's a competitive game, people want to play a fair playing field,
and that was the way to design games. And thankfully this is now, you know, the tide
has turned on this to the point where most new games coming out these days are doing proper
ethical microtransactions in a good way if they're competitive. The Supporter Packs thing was we
needed to, we were about to start selling beta access in 2012 because we wanted to trickle a
few more people in and they were spamming us with threats if we didn't let them in,
so we figured we may as well take $10.
And so we made a page where you can spend $10 to get beta access.
And then we realized, considering Kickstarter was so big,
why not model it like what they were doing?
And so we added the $20 pack, and the $50 pack, and the $100 pack,
and we just kept going to $1,000.
And then that sold a lot of copies and gave us a lot of obligations
that we had to then fulfill for many years.
We've iterated now, I think we're on our 12th or 13th set of these supporter packs,
and it's something I also care a lot about, is supporter pack design.
So if you're doing anything on Kickstarter or other games where you're doing like a founder pack or supporter pack modeling,
and you want advice, I would love to give advice on that. I have opinions there.
Anyway, there's the summary of that.
Thank you.
Cool.
So, thanks again for making this game and this talk.
It's all amazing.
I play this game a lot, and I've been the guy
who is like, I'm done, but I'll play next league a lot.
And the question I have is,
how do you think about burnout burnout?
In this, like, you have these four releases a year,
you, people are ready to, like, come back,
and they're ready to come back,
but have you thought, like, what's the take on,
is, like, what if people run out of wanting to come back?
Like.
how do you deal with the, like, over time,
people getting bored of restarting over again,
even though it's something new, it's the same new thing?
Yeah.
So the question was how do we deal with meta burnout,
which is basically the next level above of, you know,
having to come back every league until eventually
you come back so many times.
This is partly what our big, big expansions are for.
That's the next meta level above there,
the 2.0.0, the 3.0.0, next year's 4.0.0 is gonna be nuts.
Anyway, those are the things that really drag people back.
And like, I mean, I was talking to a good friend of mine who works at Jinx,
and he actually started playing Path of Exile way back in the early alpha.
And he was saying he recently returned to it, has been having a blast.
And this is something where he took several years off, but now he's back,
spending money and playing characters, and it's all good.
Cool, thanks.
Thanks.
Hi, great talk. You mentioned that you generate content in the background so that it's just ready for use in expansion because that's the only way to do it.
What about tools engineering and things like that? How do you handle that?
The tools you were saying?
We have a tools team internally, so the question was what do we do about tools in terms of content generation and so on.
We have a tools team internally, probably not as large as we should have, it's obviously an evolution over many years,
and they're trying to stay abreast of the tools.
We made a decision a few years ago that instead of replacing our engine, we were just going to make it as modern as we can,
so we have a lot of advanced stuff there now which is beginning to be used in the game,
and therefore the tools team really got scaled up a bit.
It's kind of the heart of things like procedural generation.
When we do our, I don't know,
we revamp the Atlas of Worlds occasionally,
and that now has a complicated tool
that lets people move all the stuff around,
and it really is paying off in terms of time
and effort invested in the tool stuff.
It's kind of completely separate from the concept
of making art assets, though, for the most part.
I mean, the tool we're using to make this,
you know, endless supply of content is Maya,
for the most part, but all of the stuff we use
to actually hook it up into the game
is our ever-evolving set of tools,
which certainly pays off when we improve it.
One more question?
Hi, thanks for the talk.
Love the entertainment from it too.
So my question was for the economy part of it.
You said you reset the economy each time you do a release.
Yes.
How do you do that without upsetting users
who have spent for like all this effort and put into it?
This is a great question and something that I did gloss over.
So we reset the economy with a release,
but who wants to be reset?
That sounds really bad.
The way we do it is we make a new economy
and we say, you should play the release in that one.
and you've still got your old characters.
So we have what's called standard league,
where all the characters from the past economies get moved.
You're welcome to play there, maybe 15, 10% of players do play there.
And you've still got all the characters you've ever played in Path of Exile.
But the exciting place, where the economy isn't trashed with all the old items,
is the new league.
And so we make sure that the new league content is generally only available in the new economy.
So that's kind of your reward for starting a new character.
And this took a little while to train players,
but it really works well. It's the lifeblood.
I wouldn't be here if it wasn't for the fact that this works.
Well, thank you very much, everyone.