Welcome to Exploring Hidden Stories in the World of XCOM 2.
GDC's almost done, guys, so this should be good.
Just a couple more talks.
My name is Justin Rodriguez.
I'm a senior environment artist at Firaxis Games.
I've been at Firaxis for nine years.
And throughout that time, I've worked on all the XCOM titles
that Firaxis has shipped, from XCOM Enemy Unknown, which
you'll hear me today talking about as XCOM EU,
all the way till XCOM 2 War of the Chosen.
Before we get started, how many of you have played XCOM?
Very cool.
How about War of the Chosen?
Awesome.
Before we get started, I'm going to show a video so we can
get into the mood of XCOM.
So XCOM 2 is a tactical turn-based, cover-based strategy game.
It's safe to say that working on environments for this game is complex.
What you're seeing right now is basically just our pathing visualization,
and that's just not everything that we can look at.
It could be even more complex looking if we start adding collision to this.
And not only was the game complex just from a markup side,
but it also had multiple camera angles.
What you see right now is the default camera angle and the glam cam shot when
you're picking your shot and shooting at the aliens.
And most of our buildings and environments were destructible.
And all the levels were procedural.
This is one of the small town levels that you guys might have seen in the game.
And this is the exact same level with a supermarket.
And this snowy church level with a playground to the left is also the same level.
All of these factors...
led to extensive markup in all the levels
for both environment artists and the level designers.
So how do you weave narrative storytelling
into a procedural environment?
During XCOM 2 production,
I was responsible for creating props, textures, and world building
and decorating roughly 76 out of the 174 core levels.
If we were to count all the smaller levels in the game,
there was 508 level components in XCOM 2.
I had the help of, with Prop Create,
I had the help.
of two junior artists, interns, and one lighting artist.
Now before we go any further,
I'm going to do a quick explanation of just how these levels worked. So what you see here is the
same small town level
and this is how the levels were actually put together.
The whole entire level was called a
plot and we had holes so the actual levels could socket
into this and those we called parcels.
Most of these levels could also be rotated 360 degrees.
And many levels had to work in different biomes and weather
conditions, like we saw before.
A lot of time was spent marking up textures and adding weather
assets for biome swapping.
What you see right here is one of the two small town homes.
And there's icicles in the snow version of this level.
All of those were hand placed and hand filtered
in different layers in game.
With doing all this, we knew that larger narrative elements
would not work in procedural environments, at least for ours.
We could limit the map rotation and limit
the randomness of levels.
But it made the maps feel, look, and play too similar.
Uncertain how we would solve this issue,
we began art passes and world building on the levels.
During this time, we made an effort
to update levels with level design.
What you see here is actually a couple tests
to see how we could add a pop of color
within the interior spaces.
Because at the time.
We didn't know whether or not we wanted really colorful exteriors of the buildings,
because what if a very red building came in and procedurally plopped right next to a very blue building?
It would start to look rainbowy, and we didn't want that.
So working on each one of these levels, we wanted to make sure that they still felt distinct,
but worked in any random combination.
After a few levels, we became confident we could look, make the procedural levels work and look good.
But we thought we could do more than just a quick set dressing pass.
We wanted every level in XCOM to feel fun and interesting,
like the first game we shipped, XCOM EU.
Also, it's a tactical turn-based strategy game.
So that means that in between turns,
we know that the players are going to be looking at the environments.
So with limited concept support and hundreds of levels to work on,
a few of us were constantly brainstorming to find an identity for each level.
It was at this point that someone had proposed that we looked at old XCOM EU maps for inspiration.
We created new brands for stores and restaurants in the game for XCOM 2,
but we thought it would be cool to give an old nod to the XCOM EU businesses.
This is when I loaded up one of my favorite levels from the old game,
Office Paper.
The shop paper company was a funny detail that came from the in the path of XCOM 2's micro stories.
Jeremy was the lead graphics programmer on the project for XCOM EU,
and we thought it would be cool to put his name in the game with a couple of ours.
So, when I saw this, I was inspired enough to follow this story
of the Shup paper company into XCOM 2.
I wanted to explore what happened to it in the world of alien occupation.
I figured Shup, the company CEO, with his quick initiative,
would have diversified his company knowing that alien occupation
would bring a swift end to the paper industry on Earth.
So Shuff Paper Company became Shuff Material Industries in XCOM 2.
After doing this, finishing levels became easier and had better results when embracing the impression of smaller details.
The team loves seeing stories created from the inclusion of one or two extra story props in a level.
As you can see here, this is one of our small town levels.
We made it to make sure it fit into our feel of the small town, kind of run down, but at one point...
When working with one of the other artists, he said,
you know what would just really make this?
I said, what?
He said, just a little detail.
So I found a Frisbee and just put it on the roof.
He said, that's great.
I was now thinking up stories first too, before decorating.
And this was a great way to stay actively engaged
in world building for almost 80 levels.
It helped do away with generic deco passes.
The narrative details are small
and delicately placed around each level.
And all of these details are small enough
to work in any level layout or rotation.
I also began to add various ranges of micro stories to the levels.
What you see here on the screen, there's a blanket and a pillow on the ground.
I used to call those the sleepers when we were working on those.
And basically I had this idea that within the alien occupied Earth,
the Vaxcom-2, people were kind of misplaced.
They didn't have homes.
So you would just see somewhere where they shacked up for the night or
basically try to sleep somewhere and they would leave the next day or
maybe that was the last place that they spent.
Now also with that, that's a detail that I put all over the place.
I also had specific ones that were just in one level, like the pizza party.
Cowabunga.
So throughout production of XCOM 2 and expansion of War of the Chosen,
I actively worked to refine my process and establish a few techniques
that became helpful in creating the small-town narratives
decorated throughout the game.
I'll just share some of these with you right now.
So, first...
Be resourceful.
Not much time to create.
You don't have much time to create stories
with unique assets, especially in XCOM.
Getting in the mindset of creating unique from generic
is something really good that you can kind of adhere to.
And create characters and follow them.
I created anonymous characters for all the props
that I used to decorate within XCOM 2.
And you'll see that in a few minutes here.
and gather small deco to make landmarks.
There's no need for giant statues and set pieces.
Unique props take time and you don't have much reuse.
So try to make a story with just a few small assets.
Establish breadcrumbs and motifs.
Basically, whenever you use something
as small as a flower pot,
and you know if you're gonna use it somewhere else,
make sure that you think about why these assets
are being placed in multiple locations or multiple levels.
and flow with level design.
When you do deco your maps and your levels,
make sure that the player will see them,
or they enhance the story by, or enhance the player's
exploration.
I worked very hard with the level designers
to make sure everything that I did place in the game
was near cover points or specific locations
that we knew that the player would travel.
I knew I didn't have much time or space for large narrative set pieces, so small assets
became my go-to props in creating stories and leaving narrative hints.
These are just some of my favorite props to use, and if you play Dexxon 2, you'll see
them in a lot of places.
Now I'm going to take you through a few examples of my micro-stories.
Flowerpot Man.
Slums levels and buildings were some of the last levels to be designed by Level Design.
They were...
two-story buildings that had business on the bottom and an apartment up top.
So before I started decorating in the levels, I went through each level and assigned a business
to the first floor and a character who lived above. This apartment belongs to the flowerpot man.
Flowerpot man is a single male and he's extremely passionate about growing plants and living in a
better environment. You can basically see here that on the rooftop I reused some of the small
town assets and had a little water collection for him and just flowerpots. This guy was just
growing as much.
plants as he possibly could, hopefully to bring back the ozone of this alien occupied
Earth.
So whenever I placed the flowerpots in slums, I always thought about Flowerpot Mountain
and how they got there.
My hope was to use these flowerpots all over this house to landmark the level for the player.
This asset was made and primarily used in small town, like I said, and I hoped the cross-pollination
would help seat slums in the same world or universe of XCOM 2.
Since these flower pots were so small, it also helped me keep these slums levels feeling utilitarian.
The decision to follow Flowerpot Man also helped me make the rooftops of slums feel unique as well.
So when you're on top, as you know if you play XCOM, you do get bonuses for shooting
on rooftops. So I thought that would be kind of a cool place to put most of my deco.
So here's another story that I've
worked on is called the family in the shrine.
When I when
some of the concept paintings started
being finished for the paintings
that you find in the game.
There was one that one of our concept artists
made that was of a family.
And I almost went back to the concept artist
and said listen this is too
unique. I want to have something
that's generic enough that I can place in a lot of levels.
And before I went over I said you know what I'm going
to try to make a story out of this and I'm going to make sure
that I'm only going to put it in one or two
levels in the game.
So I decided to leverage this unique painting to make a story.
So as you can see, it's a family of three.
My whole idea was that the father and mother split because of the alien invasion.
And I left breadcrumbs trying to show that the aliens were attempting to kind of coerce the humans
to move through the alien-made city centers or our futuristic cities in XCOM 2.
As you can see here, this is kind of a culmination of not only the painting and slums that you would see in the small town building or the house, but there's also just other little details here.
So I figured that the mother would live in this slum's apartment, and there's a little, you know, pillow and a blanket here where she would basically think about her family or, you know, while looking at this kind of shrine that she made.
And you can also see that.
That was hard to see, but I actually have an XCOM symbol over the father's head.
She must have been cursed by the aliens, but the father actually was trying to support XCOM.
Actually, let me just go back here. You can also see right to the right, there's a propaganda center cross.
That was one of the alien symbols that the Advent had in their propaganda centers.
I had it here, kind of...
trying to create a breadcrumb to this small town level where we had a church
and the propaganda symbol is also on the back of the church wall.
So here's one of my last stories I'll share with you guys. The eye doctor. Really quick,
we'll get through this one. We only had so many futuristic assets for slums and there was one
asset that wasn't being used, just a set of 3D printers that we used for cover.
And I decided to kind of place these in the bottom of the business.
Now, like I said, the second story was always the apartment,
the first story was a restaurant or some sort of business.
But we didn't have any doctors' offices or anything,
so I decided to make an optometrist.
So I thought it would be cool that you would walk into his optometrist,
this futuristic one, and immediately get your eyes scanned,
and they would 3D print your glasses right there.
And when I was trying to figure out who would live above,
that the doctor that worked there was...
actually living in the apartment above. At around the same time I got a set of
children's toys to help deco the levels.
I thought it would be cool that if
that the doctor would after his, you know, after work day would
use the 3D printers to print out toy cars for
the children in the slums neighborhood. So you can see here there's actually a little
toy car there, and in his apartment on the deck
he's priming some of these toy cars or painting them.
And then I would start to try and decorate any other house
that I knew that I had children living in the apartment
with some of these toy cars.
So you can't see them here, but if you
look in the satellite dish, they're
actually kind of pushing them around and racing them
around there.
So real quick, let's just summarize the techniques
and tips that I used.
Try your best with props you have available to you.
You won't always have this ability to have unique assets,
but you can make something out of nothing.
Assign characters and create specific,
assign characters to specific props you use to decorate.
And don't rely on large set pieces
and unique assets to create landmarks for the player.
As you can see here, I just had a couple of folding chairs.
This is in our sewers level.
XCOM War of the Chosen. And I just kind of used these right next to the wall,
and I propagated some of them near cover pieces where the soldiers can take cover.
And my whole idea with this is that maybe there's a couple old men from New York City that were
still trying to play chess even though they had to live in the sewers.
And establish breadcrumbs and motifs.
Like I said, if I used the chess set,
I have used a chess set in the sewers,
I would always think it was kind of the same guys
that were finding these chess sets
and playing chess before the adjunct came in
and broke it up.
One other tip for you guys,
keep your Deco characters anonymous.
It just makes it easier to kind of move through
these levels faster and you don't have to worry about
doing a little too much with these stories
if you don't have time.
The deck of characters in the space don't need to be identified to be effective.
However, if one of your characters is received well by the team or fans,
maybe they can be identified.
This is the, I don't know if you can see it,
but this is the last resting place of our poor graphics programmer, Jeremy Shop.
It says on the wall, I was the paper king.
So he definitely regrets moving to material industries.
And trust yourself for inspiration.
Flowerpot man's silly, I know, but having these characters and stories helped me deco all these levels and give them the bespoke details they deserved.
Small details and little stories you create will be enough to fill these spaces.
And it's okay to be weird. In fact, try to be.
We only use mannequins in one of the abandoned city levels in War of the Chosen.
I thought it was a missed opportunity, and I wanted to use more of them, but I was working on the sewers.
So I decided to make a sewer fashion show.
And try to up the ante.
You know, when I did this and it received, you know, some interest from some of the other artists,
I said, what am I going to do next, you know, without making it too unique?
Now, all these stories and details are helpful because it reinforces emergent gameplay.
And XCOM thrives off that.
You know, from playing XCOM, you really start to have a connection with your soldiers,
especially if they're still living.
And it adds depth to player experience.
It helps fill in and reinforce XCOM 2's main story.
All of these stories that I was working on,
I always considered the fact of alien occupation
and that all these people were either coerced
and moved into the futuristic alien cities
or trying to make their way into smaller towns.
And most importantly, it inspires a player
to make their own.
And seeing these player stories,
I can be inspired to create new stories.
This process has been rewarding during development
of XCOM 2 and War of the Chosen,
and I hope to refine it in future products.
I hope to refine my cooperation with the level design team.
I hope earlier on in our next projects,
we can work on the mood and pacing of levels
with some of these deco pieces.
And it'll make it easier for me to hide these stories
or put these stories in the levels.
And the deco assets, I hope that we
can work to get the scale and color
complement the gameplay interactables,
like the cover assets.
And I would love to have heat maps in our future games.
I could decorate these levels using these heat pads
and inversely use them to hide cool details
and promote exploration somewhere the player wouldn't go.
I think it's important to note as well,
not every player will find or appreciate this work,
but the ones that do will enjoy more depth of the game that they love.
And it isn't wasted work.
It allows you to have a direction when decorating the space
and will make sure that the levels you create are full of life.
In fact, at the end of our slums production, we had a little bit of extra time.
And they said, is there any other assets that we can make for you, Justin?
And I said, you know, it'd be really cool if we could get some cool graffiti set pieces
that kind of reference what's happening in the story.
So one of our artists, Andrew, made these awesome graffiti pieces, and I hid them in
the kind of the alleyways of the slums, and it really helped kind of landmark some of
these other levels.
And don't be afraid to get time or try to make time to do this.
Having rough estimates of how long this deco pass takes
allows you to plan for it accurately with production.
Balancing cost and time to decorate
can be explored even by blocking out your deco assets
in a proxy gray box phase.
This also helps you establish a sense of scale in your level.
As you can see here, I'm actually
walking you through the process of making the sewers.
So what you're seeing is gray box.
But even earlier on when I got some base textures in here,
you can see that I'm already placing small deco down
on the level.
I wanted to make sure that everything
that I wanted to outline in this level
was there so we could plan for it accordingly.
You can even see gray box pictures on the walls,
so I knew that I had time to make these assets,
and I knew how they would fit into the space.
And let your sense of wonder drive you
when you decorate these environments in the game.
It makes a task more rewarding and inspiring
to those around you.
Let's go.
So guys, thank you so much for coming to the talk.
I'm always excited to talk about environment art
and environmental storytelling.
And feel free to contact me by email or Twitter.
I also started the Environment Art Podcast
with the talented Ryan Benno from Somniac.
And let me know what you think.
We just shipped the episode two
of the podcast earlier this week.
And if you haven't played XCOM, which most of you have,
or were the chosen, pick it up.
It's a blast.
Thank you guys.