There's a perception out there that the average game is mindless entertainment,
with at best a thin story, cardboard cutout characters, and stilted acting.
What is it you're after anyway?
But many companies have been working tirelessly against that stigma.
Here at Naughty Dog, we work hard to ensure our performances are believable,
emotionally relevant to the player,
and blend with our gameplay as seamlessly as possible.
Are you out of your goddamn mind?
Yep, probably!
Hi there, I'm Ryan James, Lead Editor at Naughty Dog, and this year at GDC, I'm going to be
sharing some of the methods our team employs when implementing realistic performances in
our games, both inside and especially outside our cutscenes.
You don't have to be a designer or an audio engineer for this one, it's open to all disciplines
who are interested in some nuts and bolts on the why and how of what we do.
So please join me for realistic performances in games.
I hope to see you there.