Round 1, Fight!
Come back here and let me stab you!
A command post is no longer under Empire control.
How do you feel about bullets?
What's that?
Now you are holding his head in your arms.
Now you are... kissing him.
What?
Yes, you are kissing him in your arms.
He's pulling your long hair, shoving his tongue deep inside your mouth.
Knife? Ha ha. Yeah, you'll get knifed.
Back again? Ha ha.
Let me kill you!
UAV recon standing by!
Our UAV is online!
God dammit, Jackson!
Weeeee! I win!
YES! YES!
I want to thank Robbie Cooper, who is a British photographer and video artist,
for the use of his short film, Immersion, to kind of open my talk with this year.
You might know Robbie Cooper for his work.
He made a series of photos a few years ago of people with their avatars,
mainly from MMOs, but also from various other kinds of games that were really beautiful and revealing.
So, good afternoon everyone and welcome to my talk.
Please silence your phones and other augmented reality devices.
And when you receive your electronic evaluations in the email, please, please, please fill
them out if you like the talk.
If you don't like it, don't bother.
And thanks to the awesome conference associates who, like every year, are helping us out,
being incredible, making GDC happen all the time.
So my talk today is the first kind of arty,
wannabe intellectual game design talk
that I've ever given at GDC.
So I'm pretty nervous, in case you think
it's a load of old bollocks.
But please bear with me.
It's also rather long.
And I might go over the hour, but GDC
have graciously given me an extra 10 minutes at the end.
So hopefully we'll have some time for questions.
My name is Richard Lemarchand and I'm lucky enough to be a lead game designer at a fantastic
studio called Naughty Dog. I've been a professional game designer for a little over 20 years now,
working mainly in character action games. And I've worked at Naughty Dog for nearly
eight years.
I was either the lead or the co-lead game designer on all three games in the Uncharted series.
Culminating, of course, in Uncharted 3 Drake's Deception, which we released last November.
We've had... oh, gosh.
Thanks. We've had terrific success with Uncharted 3,
and even though I'm not going to put too much focus on the Uncharted games today,
I'll tell you about some of the playtesting techniques later on
that we used to improve and polish this, our latest game.
But as well as leaving you with just a little bit of practical takeaway today,
I have two other goals for my talk.
Both of them to do with game design philosophy,
and both of which I hope will be useful to you in your game design practice.
One of them relates to my thoughts about the value and nature of what gets called experiential gameplay.
Now, we've used this kind of gameplay to powerful effect in the Uncharted series.
For example, in the peaceful village sequence in Uncharted 2.
But it's also being used in many different ways by many different kinds of games,
from the world of AAA to indie and art games.
So we'll get back to this towards the end of my talk.
But my first and biggest goal is kind of given away by the title of my talk.
In the grand tradition of Jesse Schell's game design lenses,
where Jesse gave us a big set of language for talking clearly
about many different aspects of the game experience,
I want to give us just one new lens.
That is the concept of player attention.
Now, attention in the way that psychologists talk about attention
is very important when we're discussing the core
of a good video game experience.
But it rarely gets discussed by designers here at GDC,
at least in my experience.
And I'd like to see if there's something that we can do about that.
Part of the reason that I'm interested in this
is because I'm hungry for knowledge about the human mind.
and not just the kind of knowledge that science gives us,
but the insight into what you might call the lived human experience
that we can get from art.
And what better art form to explore these questions with than
that of video games.
The other reason that I want us to start talking about attention
is my personal dislike, some might say my
unreasonable dislike, of a couple of innocent words.
Here they are.
poor, old, immersion, and immersive.
Their relatives, engaging and engagement, are a little bit better,
but I'm afraid not that much.
Now we use these words all the time when we're talking about what makes games
great,
but do we really understand what they mean?
their literal sense seems confusing.
When we're immersed in a game, what are we under the surface of?
Is it some kind of game design soup?
Are we inside the gameplay or inside the graphics like
James Woods making out with his creepy TV and video drone?
In their landmark 2003 book, Rules of Play,
Katie Salen and Eric Zimmerman talk about something that they call
the immersive fallacy.
They say that there's an idea prevalent among game designers and media theorists
that the pleasure of a media experience lies in its ability
to sensually transport the participant into an illusory, simulated reality.
one so complete that ideally the frame
falls away so that the player truly believes that he or she
is part of an imaginary world. And they go on to claim
that this conception is a mistake.
The use of the word immersion in this sense, which refers to our going
beyond the boundary between our day-to-day world of IRL
and into some machine-mediated consensual hallucination
to borrow a bit of poetry from William Gibson, it comes from the world of
virtual reality.
And it's an alluring idea.
Certainly, the level of identification that we have with the protagonists in a movie
or the hero of a game
would suggest that we get caught up in fantasies quite thoroughly.
And the amount of time that we at Naughty Dog spend grounding the reality of
Uncharted
in lots of different ways
is testament to the importance of helping an audience suspend their disbelief.
But the claim that you can make someone forget who they are
and start to believe that they're someone else,
just by enveloping them in pictures and sounds of another place and time,
has never seemed quite right to me.
It doesn't do justice to the game artisans who craft experiences
that get and hold our attention in many different, ingenious ways.
And even if we could pull off this trick
of making you believe that you're someone else,
would we really want to?
If I could reach into your mind, make you forget who you are while leaving all of your
skills and emotions intact, and have you literally believe that you and Nathan Drake hanging
out the back of a cargo plane with a desert floor a quarter of a mile below you and a
bunch of gun-wielding enemies up above you, you probably wouldn't be excited and entertained
in the way that everyone at Naughty Dog hopes for for the players of our games.
In fact, you'd almost certainly be scared shitless.
No disrespect, you understand. I know you're all very courageous.
Now, I do think that games, interactivity, and what you might call
overwhelming sensory inundation can change our identity
in interesting ways that are worthy of a lot more exploration.
The interactive theatrical production, Sleep No More, and Gaspar Noé's film
Enter the Void, are two great, entirely different demonstrations of that fact.
And here's some recent games that have played with this strange relationship
between a game's protagonist and its player.
Gerowin Stout's Dinner Date and Swery's Deadly Premonition.
Now, both of these games show us that things aren't quite as simple
as having some kind of one-to-one identification with a game's hero.
As do just about all the games by Belgium-based art game developer, Tale of Tales.
They too mess around with this idea.
Now, I don't really want to be that semantics-quibbling guy.
I actually think that the word immersion is fine when we use it casually
or when we're sure what we're talking about.
Virtual reality is very interesting and very important,
getting more important all the time.
And high-fidelity wraparound simulations
are immersive in the real sense of the word, I think.
But in the context of TV-based video games,
the word immersion is a bit of a buzzword,
and it can point us in the wrong direction
when we're trying to analyze the games that we love,
especially when we start talking about being immersed in gameplay.
So how do I want us to talk instead?
Well, it's really pretty simple.
Video games entrance us by getting our attention,
and then they give us what we call a compelling experience
by holding our attention.
Loosely defined as the cognitive process of paying attention to one aspect of the environment
while ignoring others, attention is one of the most widely studied and discussed subjects
in the whole of psychology.
So let's take a closer look at it just quickly.
For many years, scientists believed that the human mind could only pay attention to one
thing at a time.
And psychologists call this our attentional bottleneck.
The game designer Colin Northway has talked interestingly about this on his blog
in terms of attention splitting. For example, he talks about how Starcraft
players call
attention the third resource, and expert players
attempt to steal attention from their opponents with raids and harassment.
An attentional bottleneck is important for game designers to think about.
In many games, we have to keep track of lots of different pieces of information.
How much health we currently have, how much ammo we have left, where the enemies and other
immediate threats in the level are, and so on.
If the player only has so much attention to go around, we as designers have to stay aware
of this so that we don't overwhelm them.
Now we now know that it's not quite true that we can only attend to one thing at a time.
Our unconscious minds are always monitoring the world
for the arrival of important new information.
We call this vigilance and it's been studied quite a lot since the 1940s
because it's central to some very important jobs, things like
air traffic control, military surveillance, even lifeguarding.
It's totally relevant for game designers of course. We're betting on the fact that our
players are going to be able to be vigilant for hours on end. Whether you're keeping an
eye out for incoming aircraft in flight control or staring eyeball-dryingly vigilant for incoming
enemies in Action Button's awesome game Ziggurat, which you should check out on your iPhone.
But it's tough to be vigilant. We all suffer from something called vigilance fatigue,
which means that after the first 15 minutes, only 15 minutes of paying close
attention to something,
we become much more likely to miss new relevant information
if the sensory footprint of that information is somehow small or kind of
weak.
Now scientists used to think that the more boring a task, the quicker vigilance fatigue
kicks in.
But recent research shows that it's just as much of an issue for interesting vigilance-based
tasks like the ones in video games.
People focusing on the same task for a long time
and remaining vigilant
eventually become distracted, irritable and impatient.
Think about your mental state at the end of a six-hour online FPS jag
or a protracted raid in an MMO. If you're anything like me, it's probably
somewhat agitated.
But interestingly, switching to another activity,
especially one that is low-stress or even more interestingly, one that
contains
pastoral scenes of nature, almost immediately restores our ability to be
vigilant within a few minutes.
which I think probably explains the patterns of self-guided player activity
that we see in games like Skyrim, as we kind of cycle between exploration
and more intense combat and then less intense
and sometimes lengthy periods of just noodling around in our inventory.
Now, this need that we have to rotate between different tones and intensities of visual
activity probably explains why movie makers talk about pacing.
Here on the left is an intensity graph that the writer-producer Warren Skaran made for
the movie Top Gun, as well as Freytag's famous triangular graph of dramatic structure, and
Kurt Vonnegut talking with graphs about the shapes of stories.
I'd definitely check out this video on YouTube.
And we certainly think about pacing a lot when we're planning the Uncharted games.
And we space out intense periods of combat with less intensive exploration and problem-solving
and with experiential sequences like Uncharted 3's Lost in the Desert montage.
So to wrap this section up, I quickly want to tell you about the two different kinds of attention that we have.
The first kind is something that I've been exploiting every time I bring up a new slide,
using what's called your orienting reflex.
Now this big change in your visual field has almost certainly succeeded in attracting your
attention to the screen where I want it to be.
And it does so in a way that you don't have any real control over.
Sudden loud sounds and motion in our visual field also have the same effect,
as do the mention of your name, anything that threatens your survival,
and just plain novelty, anything kind of new and different in your sensory environment has a
tendency to attract your attention. Now this is called reflexive attention,
and broadly speaking it happens at the back and at the sides of the brain.
The other kind of attention that we have is executive or voluntary attention.
This is the attention that we are in charge of,
which we choose to direct, which we have what's known as
executive control over. Now executive attention
is one of a group of executive functions, which also include things like
problem-solving,
decision-making, and the way that we monitor our own
actions. And this takes place primarily in the front of the brain.
But executive attention can be tricked as it struggles to organize the world.
And it has a tendency to assume that the world is continuous and predictable.
You might be familiar with the brilliant person swap stunts
pulled by the British illusionist Derren Brown,
where a victim, the woman in the white shirt,
ends up giving directions to two different people
without even realizing that the person they're talking to has changed.
It's uncanny. She doesn't bat an eyelash.
Now, the whole spectrum of executive functioning,
where we make choices and take actions,
is right at the heart of our craft as video game developers.
This is what we're talking about whenever we talk about agency.
But it seems that we rarely talk about what the player is
choosing to pay attention to.
I wonder if that's because our executive attention is
kind of out of sight, out of mind.
In any case, I think we shouldn't forget that the players of the games that we design
have a freedom and a capacity to express themselves
simply by choosing what to pay attention to next,
before they even take an action.
And I don't know that the mainstream of video games
often take advantage of this in a thoughtful way.
And I'll admit to often being guilty, as a character action game designer,
of thinking of the player as pretty reflexive,
running from one shiny thing to the next that we've placed in their path.
Games like the contemplative Dear Esther and the atmospheric Proteus take a quite different
approach of course.
Proteus, which was developed by Ed Key with a reactive ambient score by David Kanaga,
is one of my favorite games of 2011.
And if you enjoy meditative, interactive experiences and you haven't yet played Proteus, I implore
you to seek it out.
So anyway, that's a 10 cent tour of what cognitive scientists know about attention.
If you're interested, there's lots more good stuff to learn about this on Wikipedia.
So attention is probably important for game designers, right?
Like other kinds of entertainment designers,
we have to guide our audience's attention
to the things that enrich their experience.
And we have to steer their attention away from the things in our game that don't or won't.
For example, game designers specializing in level layout
use the weenie technique that we borrowed from theme park design
to orient the audience's attention to these landmarks in the environment
that poke up over the nearby things.
And then we provide kind of sequences of cues and revelations
on the paths that guide the players where they choose to go,
having oriented themselves to these weenies.
So, if we're going to talk about the ways that video games get and hold our attention,
instead of talking about immersion, we'd better take a quick look at some of the ways they do it.
When I first sat down to think about this, I decided that most attention grabbers and
keepers in video games fall into one of these three categories.
Beauty, story, and gameplay.
Now, this list seemed like a pretty good starting point,
but it was going to change the more I thought about it.
So let's begin with beauty.
The simplest thing that I could think of that gets my attention in a video game
is great art.
You can talk about beauty in terms of symmetry, coherence,
harmony, and ideal forms.
You can also express it with logic and number.
We know about the complementarity of color,
the golden ratio, and the Fibonacci sequence.
But when I thought about it some more, beauty didn't seem to be quite the right word.
Not everything that gets our attention, like this, is traditionally beautiful.
Think about the striking work of H.R. Giger,
or how much of the art we love is cute or zany.
So I thought that maybe a better word than beauty was aesthetics.
That way we can include a wider range of tastes and philosophical ideas as well.
But then I started looking for a way to describe this in even more general terms
by talking about something that draws attention to itself
by virtue of its difference from those things around it.
So I decided to think like a graphic designer or an interface designer
and call this contrast.
That way, this category can include anything in our sensory field
that leaps out at us, that grabs our reflexive attention
in a way that is useful to our executive attention.
Now, things in this first category, beauty, aesthetics, contrast,
easily get our attention, I think.
They grab it quite powerfully in ways that we don't have that much resistance to.
However, these kinds of things don't hold our attention for that long.
Think about the way that people only spend an average of
30 seconds or so looking at even the most famous paintings in the world.
we easily tire of the contrast in the scene
and our attention needs to move on to something else.
So my second category starts out a story.
Now, of course, story is a hot button topic
for game developers, as you'll know
if you've been reading Gamasutra in the last few years.
My hope is that if we talk about it in terms of attention,
then we can make it less loaded as a subject.
Story and games are almost certainly the oldest human cultural traditions,
and both of them demand and occupy our attention.
Think about an early human shaman holding his village entranced around a fire
with his tales of the gods and the birth of the universe.
However, unlike the linear story that's woven into the playful space of the Uncharted games,
not many video games have a story in a traditional sense.
And so I pretty quickly changed the section to narrative,
to encompass many different kinds of games,
from Rockstar's brilliant systemic narratives,
all the way over to Daniel Ben-Mehri's new game, Storyteller.
I think even the fact that a rook is shaped like a castle
and a knight is shaped like a little horse
is narrative.
Thank you, sir.
But to generalize even more broadly,
this is all to do with social stuff.
A 2007 study at Florida State University
showed that we exhibit something called attentional adhesion
not only towards people that we are attracted to
but also towards people that we perceive as rivals for those
attractive people's affections.
Now suddenly it seems scientifically comprehensible
the interest that we all, men and women, gay and straight alike, have
in the attractive, noble, crafty cast of Downton Abbey.
So, opening the door to the social in this way
will also let us talk about how social games of all kinds
hold our attention. Whether it's the split-screen co-op games of
Uncharted 3, or the social aspects of
Facebook games and all of the other social games we've been playing recently.
The developmental psychologist Michael Tomasello
has written about something called the joint attentional scene
and he describes how a shared experience of a third thing
plays a fundamental role in our intellectual and social development
and it might even be what gives us our essential humanity.
Professor Janet Murray, author of course of Hamlet on the Holodeck,
has run with the idea of joint attention in the direction of games
and you should check out her work, you can find it online.
And thinking about the social also made me think
that this is why we've had so much success
with the character-driven stories in the Uncharted games.
By putting a focus on the people in the game,
their fears and hopes,
and the moment-to-moment nuances in the relationships between them,
We've been able to get and hold people's attention much more easily
than by trying to use kind of more abstract, dry,
plot-driven stories that many video games use and which focus on
the power structures or the history of a fictional world.
Now, I think it's averagely tough to get someone's attention with this story-narrative-social stuff.
Screenwriting books like Blake Snyder's Save the Cat are full of advice about the very challenging task of quickly establishing characters that are likeable or empathic, so that we'll want to follow them along their path.
and I think that narrative also has an averagely strong hold on people's
attention
uh... and in a way but in a way that's curious because
it doesn't decay very quickly over time
Episodic fiction, where we might have to wait days or even weeks between
chunks of a story, is testament to this weird fact.
There's an anecdote about people in the 1800s
lining the docks in New York City, waiting for the latest episode
of Charles Dickens' serialized story, The Old Curiosity Shop,
to come in on the boat. It was serialized in a pulpy magazine.
after he dropped a particularly spectacular cliffhanger on them
in the previous episode.
So my last category is gameplay.
Now, games are made of several parts.
They have rules, they're mechanics,
that interact in a systemic way with players and resources
to produce dynamics, which in turn yield
emotional responses, aesthetics, in a different sense
than I used earlier, for the players of the games.
Now, you'll recognize this as the MDA model proposed
by Robin Haneke, Marc LeBlanc, and Robert Zubek.
If you haven't read their paper about MDA, you must look it up on the web.
It acts as a great concise explanation
of how gameplay works to hold our attention and impact our emotions.
The philosopher Bernard Suits defines a game
as the voluntary attempt to overcome unnecessary
obstacles in pursuit of specific goals.
Now goals are what make a game different from a toy or a free play session.
We work towards long-term goals by means of attainable short-term goals
that we put together strategically to get to the long-term goal.
Things as simple as roll the dice or shoot the enemy,
even as simple as take cover.
Now these build into compulsion loops by way of letting us reach these satisfying points
of resolution.
The end of my turn, the dropping of the enemy, or the collapsing of three clumps of grass
into a bush in Spry Fox's brilliant Triple Town.
We string these loops and goals together into a gameplay experience potentially of many
many hours.
And I think this is also related to Jamie Griezmann's famous conception of the 30 seconds
of fun in Halo, where an underlying pattern of player activity is repeated with continual
variation but over and over again to create the long-term enjoyment of the game.
But there's a problem with calling this category gameplay.
Not all the video games we love even have goals, and so by some of our best definitions,
they're not very game-like, strictly speaking.
Minecraft, at least before the single-player game came along,
and SimCity are two video games that are very open-ended,
but which I've played compulsively for dozens, maybe hundreds of hours.
And they are clearly doing something right to hold my attention,
but quite how they're doing it has always been something of a mystery to me.
But I'll come back to this later on.
So I almost changed this category to interactivity to make it more general.
But let's call it lewdism instead, like ludic from the Latin ludus, as I'm sure you know,
which describes play of all kinds, not just games, and which acknowledges the playful
attitude that I think is necessary here.
And this scheme needed a bit of pretentious Latin, anyway.
So I think that when the human mind finds a system,
it loves to study it, if the moving parts of the system
are easily visible to us. This is Chris Burden's
art installation, Metropolis II, which I recently saw at the LA County
Museum of Art. And it's a system whose dynamics are plain to see.
And it's fascinating, isn't it? These are all Hot Wheels cars, by the way.
on an infinite loop.
They have a custodian to take care of them in the middle.
So we come for the regular structure and repetition in the system
which gives our minds something to grasp quickly.
Much like the way that we get fascinated by watching the waves
lap into the shore.
and similarly like the self-similarity in this Romanesco broccoli.
But then we stay for the variability in the system
like the ever-changing patterns in the flickering flames of a fire
or the variable schedule of reinforcement
in the payout of a slot machine. So to make things even more inclusive
I'll also call this category systems.
Now, when a rule of rules, resources, interactions and goals are well designed,
gameplay is like mental catnip to us.
I think that this gameplay lewdism systems category is the hardest to get a player's attention with.
For example, it can be tough to teach a board game to someone who hasn't played it before and isn't that interested.
And we have to work very hard to design video game opening sequences,
like the beginning of Uncharted 2,
which grab new players' attention very quickly.
Simple mechanics probably get your attention more quickly
since they're easier to understand and get behind.
But as Jason Rohr pointed out in his keynote at the Montreal International
Game Summit last year,
games are clearly the form that is best at keeping people's attention.
While a film struggles to keep you for longer than about three hours tops,
a great video game can hold your attention for dozens, hundreds,
even thousands of hours.
Now this is also where the depth of a game becomes important.
Game depth is a little hard to define, but let's say that a deep game
is one that produces a large number of interesting choices
in a comprehensible way from a compact,
elegant set of rules. The deeper the game,
the greater the opportunity it has to hold your attention for a long time
with its gameplay alone.
I think it's probably true to say that a game holds your attention best
when you feel that you haven't yet completely understood
its complexity. And I'd like to thank my colleague
Caitlin Burnell for that insight. Please check out her talk on Friday.
So, I hope you're at least somewhat agreeing with me by now
that we can cut through the confusion about what
immersion and engagement might mean simply by saying
good video games get and hold our attention
using a mix of the elements in these three categories.
Also, you can start to see how we could freely mix and match stuff from these
categories to make different styles and genres of game
drawing on them to serve each of our unique individual creative goals.
we can also keep them in mind to use them when we need to.
Just when we're losing the player's attention with one category,
maybe when they're succumbing to vigilance fatigue,
we could pull them back in by deploying another.
A very simple example of this would be the way that
back in the days of 16-bit platformers,
we would vary the graphics and add new mechanics into the mix
as the game progresses.
Now, we often get into difficult arguments, like the story arguments,
when we try to compare video games to other forms like movies.
And when you work on a game like Uncharted,
you end up hearing all about that stuff.
By using this concept of attention to look at other forms,
I hope we can get a clearer idea of what video games are and aren't like.
This kind of framework cuts us loose from subjective, ideological evaluations of the
value of different forms.
And it leaves us free to evaluate what does and doesn't work, both functionally and artistically.
So whether we're discussing games, films, sports, or even just some drunkard falling over at a party,
the kinds of statements we can now make are simple and to the point.
And we can more easily draw out the ways in which each of these things are similar to and different from one another.
So as we learned from Colin Northway and the StarCraft players, human attention is a limited resource.
There's only so much of it.
There's a cap on the rate at which it can be parceled out.
It diminishes and recharges over time.
But you can improve your attentive capacity.
In fact, the games we make are helping people do just that.
Ongoing research from Daphne Bavellier's group at the University of
Rochester,
one of whose experiments are shown here,
shows that people who play action video games
have better, faster visual attention skills than people who don't.
And the change takes place quite quickly, after quite short play sessions.
So, since attention is a resource, you'd think that it would be great subject matter for video games.
But there haven't been that many games that are explicitly about attention.
You can find some very simple attention training games on the web.
But there are a couple of interesting ones that I'm...
interesting attention-based games that I'm aware of.
Eric Zimmerman and the team at GameLab
made a game a few years ago called Arcadia,
where you had to play multiple action games at once.
It was very difficult.
And of course, Chris Hecker's game, Spy Party,
is specifically about using the player's attention
as a resource that they have to manage throughout the game.
In fact, I'd like to make the claim
that attention is the basic currency
in which video games trade,
and in which nearly every cultural form trades as well.
So I really wanted to talk about game addiction today,
which is a difficult and polarizing, but I think,
interesting subject.
And I can't help but feel that we should talk about it more
as a community of game designers.
I kept coming back to it over and over again while I was
writing this talk because of what seemed to me to be a
clear relationship between game addiction and attention.
What we call addictive games pull your attention back to them
over and over again and then hold it for a really long time.
Games that cause people addiction-related problems in their lives
are perhaps too good at getting and holding
that particular person's attention.
So unfortunately it would take me a lot more than an hour to do this subject
justice but I hope someone at another GDC
can come back to this subject and run with it.
So, the player has all this attention, which they're bringing to bear on our games.
How is that practically relevant for game designers?
Well, I don't have time to speak to every kind of game,
so I'll just tell you about our experiences from the development of Uncharted.
Often in our video games, we want to direct the player's visual attention
to an aspect of the environment. A ladder, a door, maybe an enemy, or even a simple ledge.
Now there are lots of things that impact the visibility of things in the environment.
The silhouette of the object and the background that it's against.
Its hue, saturation and value, all of which are affected by the lighting of the scene.
Then there's the composition of the view of the scene and the lines and shapes within
it and the density of detail and any animation that it contains.
Now if even one of these things is out of whack, then the player won't see what we need
them to see.
And every Uncharted game has presented literally thousands of these kinds of challenges for us to overcome, as you can imagine.
But there are a couple of simple tips for you to know about here, if you're working in character action games and maybe some other related kinds of games.
We found that players rarely look outside this central part of the screen, unless it's to look at the meta information like the HUD.
And that causes them to often miss things that might be in plain sight, but which are out in the corner.
Also, players are more attentive to things in the lower half of the screen
than in the upper half because of something called visual gravity.
Now, Bruce Block talks about these elements and many more
in his excellent book, The Visual Story,
which I think should be required reading for every video game
designer.
And I also like this book on the right,
Composition, from the excellent DK Eyewitness art series,
for just some simple tips about the way
that lines of force in a composition
drive your eye around the scene in useful ways to us.
The takeaway for game designers here is that subtle details in the art of your game don't
just make it more or less pretty, they make it possible for the player to play your game
at all.
Now my friend Robin Hunnecke, who works at that game company, told me that working on
Journey, their latest game, they created a new term for this.
They called it attentional design and you can see it at work in the opening moments
of their game.
The way that the player's attention is drawn first to the character that they will play
at the very beginning of the game by the character's isolation in the scene, and then the suggestion
that the character is now controllable because of the way that it's risen to its feet.
The establishment first of the hill as a short-term goal for the player through the use of attention
grabbing detail and animation.
and then the establishment of the mountain as a long-term goal for the player
by a change in camera position that frames the composition in such an impactful way.
All of these are subtle ways of designing to direct the player's attention in gameplay
towards the mechanics and the goals of the game.
Now Robin told me that even these simple seeming things took many, many hours of work to accomplish
and finesse.
And I know from our work on the Uncharted series just how hard we have to work to direct
the player's visual attention and their auditory attention in subtle ways like these.
Now, visual attention is a lot weirder than you might think.
We can only see a clear, sharp image with a tiny, tiny part of our retinas.
It's something called the fovea.
It's right in the middle of the retina. It's about a millimeter across
and it's responsible for a full half the signals that travel down your optic nerve.
If you hold your arm out at arm's length and look at your thumb,
that's about the size, the width of your thumb
is about the size of this tiny patch of visual acuity that you have.
So because of this, we can't look at a scene in fixed steadiness
the way that some other animals, like birds for instance, do.
Instead, we build up a 3D picture of the world
by zooming our eyes around it with these quick,
simultaneous movements of the eyes called saccades,
that's S-A-C-C-A-D-E-S,
which are punctuated by periods of rest called fixations.
And saccades are actually the fastest movements
that the human body can make.
and we tend to fixate on clusters of detail which explains
a lot of the stuff that's in that composition book. Thanks by the way to
Jerry for the use of his
graduate thesis project foveation movie here. I thought it was really
a clear way of explaining how this works.
So, knowing this, you'd think that we would want to set up eye-tracking equipment when
we playtest to be able to see exactly what our players are fixating on.
And boy, oh boy, would I like to!
I've always been fascinated by the kind of technology that can be used to see exactly
where on screen someone is looking.
For instance, web developers use it all the time.
and I'm itching to get my hands on some eye tracking kit.
But it's not something that we've done yet. Naughty Dog, if there's any eye tracking
companies out there who'd like to
hook us up with a freebie, please let me know.
Valve, though, have had some experience using eye tracking as part of their playtesting
process, as I think of people in the greater Sony organization.
Sony, oh, Naughty Dog, of course.
In fact, Valve even rigged Portal 2 so that you could play it using your gaze to aim the
portal gun around the level.
Now this kind of technology is an amazing boon for paralyzed people, of course,
and I think we'll be seeing a lot more of it in the future.
It's going to become cheaper and more usable,
and I think that eye-tracking technology could well become standard equipment
for game developers, maybe even game audiences,
over the course of the next 10 years.
However, right now, eye tracking technology is still very expensive.
Around $10,000 a seat, I believe.
And even if you could afford eye tracking, it might not be desirable.
In his excellent talk at GDC in 2009,
Valve's biometrics expert, Mike Ambinder,
mentioned a study that showed that when people know that their eyes are being tracked,
and you usually know because you have to like put your head in this weird equipment or
put these special glasses on, then people move their eyes around somewhat
differently. They become kind of self-conscious
about where their gaze is. So how else can we keep track of the players visual
attention
to make sure that the attentional design techniques that we're trying to use
are working? Well of course we study our players attention
all the time when we're using one of our most important game design tools
namely playtesting.
Now, I'm sure, I'm quite sure everyone here knows about the importance of playtesting.
Although, you'd be surprised to hear just how many game developers still make do without it.
Now we playtest our games all the time on each other, of course, as developers while
we're making them.
But the kind of playtest I'm talking about now is formal playtesting with groups of,
for us, ten at a time Kleenex playtesters from the general public who have never seen
our game before and who will only use to test it just once.
When I joined Naughty Dog to help finish Jack 3, we ran perhaps 4 or 5 playtests over the
course of the project.
For Uncharted 3, we ran 21 tests over the course of the last 6 months of development.
So you can tell how important it is to us.
And we run these tests in-house in a dedicated playtest room.
Each playtester's station has a networked PlayStation 3
with a build of the game that we're testing.
They have headphones.
And there's a networked DVR box that
will capture video of the gameplay to our network
as the players play.
Screens separate the stations from each other
so that the players can't see each other's games,
even accidentally.
And we ask them not to talk to each other
during the playtest.
And because we want to be as scientific as possible in this, we're ruthless about not giving them any help with what they're playing.
As the players play, the game records certain information about the gameplay session and posts it to a database on our network.
We call this our metric data.
Then, at the end of the playtest, we get the playtesters to fill out a questionnaire
about their experience and we conduct an exit interview
in quite small groups, three people at a time,
although one person at a time would probably be even better.
and we video record these.
And these are really useful.
The questionnaires are really useful to help us track the
improvement in the players' perceptions of our game
from test to test.
We've been lucky, maybe,
to always see a slow, gradual improvement.
and that is really valuable for helping us to stay sane
in the knowledge that the game is gradually getting better,
especially if we've recently made a big change somewhere in the gameplay.
And we also get some interesting, if kind of anecdotal, game design perspectives
that we can discuss
from the exit interviews.
Then immediately after the playtest, we take a look at the metric data, which lets us visualize
how playable the game is. One way we do this is by compiling a table of how many times
the players died in each small chunk of the game. And then I use the conditional formatting
in Excel to see where the average and maximum deaths for each little bit of the game exceeds
certain thresholds. And this is super useful to immediately alerting us to the parts of
the game that are still too hard, because they just jump right out at you, red and pink.
But back to attention.
One way that we can track a player's attention without this expensive
equipment is ridiculously simple. It's just by watching them play
or by watching their gameplay videos later.
In a game like ours, it's easy to see when someone isn't seeing something
or has forgotten their goal.
When players repeatedly run right past the object that they're meant to be
interacting with,
it's a pretty sure sign that they can't see it.
If they go up to it from time to time and try and use it, but then
leave it alone for a long time,
you know they can see it, but they don't think it's important.
This is one of our
playtest gameplay videos, by the way.
So we make notes about these situations as we observe them,
and then we make fixes between playtests,
and then we watch out for improvements in the next test.
And just by doing this, you can make an amazing difference
to the way that your players' attention moves
over the sensory surface of your game.
And you can seriously improve the amount of fun
that your players have with your game as a result.
But what about tougher problems, where the player's attention isn't so easy to observe?
Well, you can use your metric data in some clever ways to get a handle on these kinds
of issues.
The environments in Uncharted are visually very dense.
Thanks to our brilliant artists, there's a lot going on in the picture of any random
Uncharted screenshot.
And like we were just discussing, it's very easy for things that are important to gameplay
to get lost among all that visual information.
So because of this, we faced a nasty recurring problem in the development of the Uncharted games,
one that dated all the way back to the beginning of the series.
We found that players would often have a difficult time spotting the edge grabs in the environments.
Now this was usually a disaster for us, of course,
because it would stop them climbing onwards to the next part of the game.
There's a lot of climbing on edge grabs in Uncharted.
And the problem was compounded by the fact that players would also get distracted by things
that looked like they were climbable, but which weren't.
So the solution to this problem was quite brilliant,
and it came from these three handsome men.
Lead technical artist, Teagan Morrison, on the left.
Lead gameplay programmer, Travis McIntosh, in the middle.
And gameplay programmer, Jarosl Szynecki, on the right.
What we did was to set up a system that we only used during our formal playtests
that would record an XYZ coordinate every time the player pressed the jump button
and didn't end up jumping to a ledge, but instead jumped up and down on the spot.
And then we wrote those coordinates to the metrics database,
and then when the playtest was complete, we exported this data back into the game,
and we put a little red sphere where every thwarted jump had taken place
for every single player in that week's test.
And we called this our bad jumps system.
You could immediately see the bad jumps clustered beneath objects that looked like edge grabs,
but weren't.
And they told us immediately what we needed to fix.
So in the days after each playtest, the environment artists would go through their levels with
the bad jumps turned on. We'd have discussions about what needed fixing when we needed to.
And then the artists would make changes to the artwork of the things that our playtesters
thought had grabbable edges, but in fact didn't, to try and make them look less like handholds.
And we were able to make a huge difference in the game by doing this.
I wouldn't care to say that we fixed this issue completely,
but definitely we were really satisfied by the results that we got
just from setting up this simple system.
It only took a few hours to create.
And we invented some other similar attention tracking metrics for Uncharted 3.
How often did players pick up a new gun, hold it for a moment, and then drop it again in
favor of their old gun?
That was really easy to record in our metric data.
So was the data you can see here, the number of successful and failed attempts that players
made to throw back grenades, instead of ignoring the grenade throwback mechanic altogether.
And this technique seems like it could be applied to widely different styles of games.
I'm sure you are starting to be able to imagine them, hopefully,
for whatever kind of game you're working on, depending on its mechanics.
So before I wrap up this section, I want to assure you about something that always bothers me whenever I hear a talk about the psychological predictability of human beings,
and the way that we can use numerical measurements taken from our players to make decisions about the creative path that we should take with our games.
These are tools, just like any other.
And just like a knife, they can be used to peel a delicious apple or commit a horrible murder.
It's often good to be scientific in a technical art like ours,
but you shouldn't go any further with these techniques than your gut instincts
as a game designer and a creative person tell you that you should go.
What you're trying to do is to make sure that your game is landing with players
in the way that you intend it to land.
You're trying to get rid of all the daft oversights that stop your game from being fun and interesting,
while leaving in enough chewy stuff that players want to sink their teeth into your game over and over again.
And this also applies to my whole invocation of this concept of attention.
I'm not trying to be reductive and explain things away in terms of
psychology and brain science. I think that would be a terrible mistake.
This is just one more lens that we can use to look at what we're doing
when we're designing a video game.
So now let's get to the topic I want to close on.
The subject of experiential video games, what they have to do with attention,
and why I think they're important.
I'm sure that some of you have been wondering why I haven't yet mentioned a
concept
that seems obviously connected to the concept of attention
and the psychology of video games. Of course,
I'm talking about the concept of flow.
Now flow is, of course, the state of optimal experience described by the psychology professor
Mike Chixentmihalyi, and it's been much discussed here at GDC over the years for the strong
ties that it has to games.
When we're in a flow state, our attention is held and very highly focused,
whether we're doing needlepoint or speed typing or playing triple town.
Our attention is right where it needs to be, on the subject matter that we're engaged with,
helping us handle the tasks at hand, while our vigilance watches out for incoming tasks
that we're going to have to deal with.
We lose some awareness of ourselves, of our bodies in particular,
and we experience strange time distortion effects,
as hours seemingly pass in minutes,
but sometimes as moments stretch out,
allowing us to act more rapidly than we otherwise could.
When we're in a flow state, we're riding the boundary between mastery, where things are easy,
and challenge, where our abilities are being tested.
If the system's too hard, we'll get frustrated.
If it's too easy, we lose interest.
In either case, we drop out of the flow state, and the system has lost our attention.
When we are in a flow state, we're acting in a system as if it was a game,
manipulating the system towards certain goals.
However, we wouldn't always want to call the system a game.
Surgeons are often used as example cases of people who go into a flow state as
they work,
and we agreed earlier that video games like Minecraft don't even have explicit
goals, and yet millions of people, myself included, go straight into a flow state
when they pick Minecraft up.
So in trying to solve the puzzle of how we can go into a flow state in non-game systems,
I finally understood how Minecraft holds my attention so completely.
In the public debate about gamification, we've talked a lot about extrinsic and intrinsic
goals.
We know from educational and industrial psychology,
going all the way back to the 1930s,
that intrinsic goals are better motivators
than extrinsic goals.
It's the playing of a game for its own sake
that holds our attention,
not the promise of some eventual reward.
So I realized that I create my own intrinsic goals in Minecraft.
And this is what puts me into a flow state.
I make a game of Minecraft by imagining a backstory where I need to stay alive
to unlock the mysteries of my uniquely generated world.
And in order to stay alive, I have to engage with the system of the world around me,
exploring the environment and using the things I find in it
to make the tools that aid me in my quest.
However, the goals set for themselves by other people
who play inside this self-same system
that is Minecraft might be quite different,
like building a scale model of the USS Enterprise
or building a flipping working 16-bit processor.
But what's common for all of us is that we've had a profound experience of a flow state
that was only possible because of the goal-setting attitude
that we brought to an open system.
This is what Csikszentmihalyi calls the autotelic experience,
from the Latin auto, self, and telos, goal.
Autotelic people, he says, are internally driven,
and they exhibit a sense of purpose and curiosity.
Because of their nature, they're more autonomous and independent,
and they're less easily manipulated by threats or rewards.
They love to explore systems just for the sake of exploring.
Now, I think all human beings are autotelic to some extent,
but our generations, the ones that have grown up playing video games,
are very lucky because we've been trained to be more autotelic
than any other generation of humanity before us.
The games that we've played have cultivated our curiosity
and our independence and our ability to manipulate rich systems
in goal-setting ways.
I'm sure that you or people you know have had deep, rich gameplay experiences in Red Dead Redemption or Far Cry 2 or Skyrim without following the main storyline of the game at all.
Or maybe by running pacifist playthroughs.
This is testament to the power of the Autotelic experience.
Now, as far as I know, Daniel Ben-Mehi first coined the term
experiential games on his blog all the way back in 2007.
Broadly speaking, these are games that forego explicit goals and traditional
game compulsion loops
in favor of systematized, open-ended,
explorative experiences, often in pursuit
of an artistic impact.
Early attempts at these kinds of games and interactive art experiences
frequently struggled to hold people's attention for very long
compared to traditional video games,
maybe because they had a tendency to rely on aesthetics and narrative,
the categories that are the least effective at holding our attention.
However, as game aesthetics and narrative elements have become more systemically interesting,
new opportunities have opened up for experiential games because of this autotelic drive that
we all carry around with us.
In my IndieCade talk last year, I described the way that Tale of Tales game,
The Graveyard, which you can see in the slide, gave me the confidence
to push through the experiential, peaceful village sequence
in Uncharted 2, even when some of the people on our team
didn't think this was going to be a success.
The calm beauty of the scene...
And the pleasure of just the simple systemic narrative elements that we scattered through it
held people's attention for just long enough to create a powerful moment at an important point in the game.
Players who were curious and explorative found plenty to reward their curiosity.
And players oriented towards the ultimate goal of the game
were able to move through the scene very quickly,
while soaking up just enough of the calm atmosphere
to reset the intensity of the game
in preparation for its final act.
And you can find my IndieCade talk online
if you're interested to hear more about this. It's on YouTube and G4TV.
You'll hear my anecdote about people trying to punch the NPCs.
Video games are special
in their opportunities for non-linearity of meaning.
But they're not unique in this regard.
Philosophers have thought for years that so-called linear artistic forms
offer similar opportunities.
In his 1962 book, The Open Work,
the Italian author and scholar Umberto Eco,
most famous for his novel, The Name of the Rose,
argued, and I'm quoting from Wikipedia here, rather than from Eco himself,
literary texts are fields of meaning
rather than strings of meaning.
They are understood as open, internally dynamic, and psychologically engaged fields.
Literature, which limits one's potential understanding to a single, unequivocal line,
the closed text, remains the least rewarding,
while texts that are the most active between mind and society and life
are the most lively and best.
In other words, singularity of meaning is the enemy of art.
Great art in all its forms is multiplicitous, systemic,
and can have many meanings, even contradictory meanings,
which is why the same piece of art can speak to us in different ways
at different times in our lives.
If we expect to find new things each time we come back to a work,
then that in itself is a draw for our attention.
Amy Hennig, my dear friend and Naughty Dog's creative director and head writer on the Uncharted
series, talks about the very great value of leaving something to an audience's imagination
in terms of the storytelling in our games, so that the individual player fills in the
details for themselves and the experience of the game truly becomes their own even before
they've taken an action in our interactive system.
So to put it another way, if linear games are well-written, they're not truly linear.
We're learning more all the time about how to devise gameplay that expresses a broad
range of emotion.
That's crucially important for pushing games forward as an artistic form, as Jonathan Blow's
Braid has so ably demonstrated.
But I worry that we have a tendency to over-focus on compulsion loops and explicit goals in the games that we make.
And we tend to look past the emotional value, and hence the artistic value,
brought to a game by things like nuanced aesthetics, the narrative and the social,
and the space for autotelic self-determination created by open systems.
In his GDC talk last year, An Apology for Roger Ebert, Brian Moriarty gave us the definition,
Sublime art is the still evocation of the inexpressible.
When we're trying to make games that succeed artistically, our ultimate goal is to evoke
ideas and emotion from the player about subjects that are difficult to express.
But as Brian suggested in his talk, and as Csikszentmihalyi himself says,
the flow state that we enter when we're caught up in the formal parts of a game
is almost emotionless as an essential part of its character.
Our minds are just too busy when we're dealing with all of the rational tasks
that a game presents to allow in the subtlety of feeling that we're chasing as artists.
But I see room for both the flow of gameplay and reflective experience in our games.
If, from time to time in the progression of a game, we have the confidence to let the
player just drop out of their flow state.
As the player's attention begins to shift away from its laser focus on the goals of the game,
whether those goals are self-created or imposed by the designer,
then we have an opportunity to catch the player in just the right way
with an affecting piece of music, or a view of something wonderful,
or just a look from another character.
And in doing so, we can create one of those powerful moments that we cherish in our favorite games.
Have you ever stopped to watch the sunset in Minecraft or to admire a view in Uncharted?
Think about how you are in that moment as your responsible, logical, goal-oriented mind
gives way to the uncensored emotion of your innermost self.
For me, this boundary...
where the cool clarity of focused rationality
meets the chaos and immediacy of raw emotion,
creating in us a lived experience
that is uniquely ours in both its intellectual
and intimate qualities,
is the richest and most exciting aspect
of video games as an expressive medium.
Game designers are often terrified
to let gameplay's iron grip
on the player's attention drop.
for fear of losing that attention forever, I think.
But we can see from what we've looked at today that there's no need to panic.
If the player has come to trust you, then they'll stay with you,
for a while at least. And we have so many tools that we can use
to get the player's attention back again in a meaningful way
that the biggest challenge we face will be deciding which one to choose.
Artists from Shakespeare to David Lynch to Fermito Wader
have understood how to shape emotion by guiding attention
while leaving room for personal experience for years.
And in doing so, they've impacted our lives in countless ways.
The emotional results that Mark, Robin and Robert describe in MDA
are the point of games.
No matter how we get there.
And there's no one right path with this.
We developers are free to play in this domain
and make our own discoveries about what works for us.
We hope that we've shown with the Uncharted games
that the techniques of cinema can make a great mix with video
games.
But we mustn't lose sight of literary fiction, of poetry,
theater, and music as vital forms of self-expression
that we're only just beginning to synthesize effectively
with the creative opportunities that video games present.
There's one piece of knowledge that I'm certain we all share.
It's that all these things, new technologies and better development practices,
the mechanisms and mysteries of the human mind,
and the great powers of curiosity and self-determination that we all have,
are, in video games, making a new kind of cultural form possible.
One that is active between mind and society and life.
And that's my talk.
Thanks very much.