Okay, welcome to Black Games Interview and Afro Future Flyby. My name is Lindsay Grace. I'm the
chair of interactive media at the University of Miami and I'm vice president of the Higher
Education Video Game Alliance. I'm also professor, game designer, developer, artist, and author.
I currently work as Knight chair in interactive media at the University of Miami and I'm,
it's a position funded by the Knight Foundation.
I've created and directed two academic game studios, one at the American University and the other at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio.
I am a solo game designer, developer, and artist. I've produced 25 plus different games for mobile, web, and PC.
I've also done some commercial solo dev, a couple of my games.
I ended up in the App Store's top 100 for arcade games and puzzle games.
Some of the icons for those games are shown here on the left.
And I'm an awarded game designer for a variety of designs that I've done in collaboration
with students, in collaboration with other designers, and in collaboration or as part
of some of the studios that I've run.
Most notably, in 2019, I was selected as the Games for Change Vanguard Award winner at the Games for Change annual festival.
And I've been a lead curator and co-curator for a variety of exhibits around the world, from Scotland and Germany to the Smithsonian American Art Museum in Washington, D.C.
I've written more than 75 chapters, articles, and books,
most notably in those categories include
Doing Things with Games, Social Impact through Play,
which is a book on designing social impact games,
and Love and Electronic Affection,
which is a book about designing playful experiences
centering on affection and love within video games.
I've also done work with people like Susan Gold to help document the experience of game jammers.
We created a book called Global Game Jam Stories where we collected the stories and observations
of people who were central to the early generation of game jams, global game jam.
And I'm currently working on a book tentatively called Black Game Makers,
which is designed around helping document Black game makers and the games that they make.
So this work is supported by the Higher Education Video Games Alliance and the Black Game Makers
Association and the book will be published through Carnegie Mellon's ETC Press. It's also supported
by the Interactive Media School of Communication at the University of Miami.
And I just want to highlight, if you're unfamiliar with the Black Game Makers Association, it's
actually founded by a fellow named Lamont Harrell. And Lamont, as a former student,
has done a really great job of kind of trying to encourage people to collect, know, popularize,
and sell games made by black developers. So if you're unfamiliar with the BGMA,
I strongly suggest that you go ahead and look it up and find out more about it.
And so when I started this project, I began collecting games made by black game makers.
And I looked at both analog games, like Black Car Revoked here.
You notice for each game that I mention, I'll actually show you the URL so that you can get a good sense for where to find out more about them.
To games, digital games like Combat Corps, which I'll talk about again in a few minutes.
So I analyzed more than 50 games by black game makers, and my aim was to try and help people understand some of the fundamentals.
So, for example, you'll notice here that the games that I looked at, about 69 percent of them were digital and the other 31 percent were analog.
You'll also notice that I predominantly in the analog side looked at far more card games than board games.
I'm not sure if this is an indication of what's available and the way the market works,
but generally it was far easier to find board games than it was to find,
I'm sorry, far easier to find card games than it was board games.
And then in the digital game types category,
you can see that I looked at a variety of mobile games,
console games, VR, mixed reality games,
as well as web-only games.
But the dominant space was digital games, including PC.
So there were a lot of products being made for the PC
in comparison to some of these other categories.
Secondary would be console games and mobile games at 19% and 16%.
So team composition was also something that I looked at.
And generally, the whole idea was to only document things
that were either created by people
from the African-American diaspora
or from people who were
working as co-designers. So generally one of the kind of the neat things that I
did find out is that if you look at the Steam scores for these games you find
that 81% of them are that as a mean for the ones that were actually scored they
got an 81% which is a relatively high scoring. So I just want to highlight some
of these games and give you a sense for how they work and what they look like.
So one of the easiest places to start is BCFX, which is a is sort of known as the
black college football game is called black college football, BCFX.
And it's a kind of a version of playing football.
wholly focused on historically black colleges and universities, what we call HBCUs. So this
is a football simulator. It has some novel sort of additions to being a typical football simulator,
besides being focused on HBCUs. It's also got this really interesting halftime show mechanic
where you can play through the halftimes. And it's incorporated in HBCU Legacy Museum,
where you can see some of the history and historical figures within the HBCU football history.
Another good example that I have to mention right off the bat is University of Dope,
which is kind of describes itself as the first party game to celebrate hip-hop culture.
And you can see more at universityofdope.com. This particular game has gotten a lot of great
press. It's been featured in the Huffington Post, Esquire, etc. And it's really kind of a fun party
game.
Both of these games do something that I've seen in a number of the most successful Black games,
which is that they're affirming positive elements of the culture. So they're really about the
successes that HBCUs have had within on the football stage, as well as University of Dope
being sort of a playful experience around pop culture and African-American contributions to
pop culture.
So others play with what I would call in-group knowledge. So they're really looking for you to
understand some things about blackness or about being a member of the African-American community.
And so a good example of this is Passport to the Hood, which is self-described. It highlights
stereotypes of urban culture, says everything that you hear behind closed doors, and reflects
on how you grew up. And that you grew up is clearly a reference to in-group knowledge.
So there are other games that do a kind of a role play opportunity. So Rap Gods is a good example of that.
You can kind of guess by the description what you're doing there. And another one, Rap Quest 2,
which is a mobile game, is a hip-hop simulation for a rap career. And there are a number of games
that follow this model where it's sort of a day in the life of, you know, a rap star, hip-hop star.
And these games actually illustrate
common expectations of black games, which is that I think a lot of times people are going to assume
that there's hip-hop and urban culture, that there's some element of black history, and that
there's some element of in-group and out-group experience. You have to sort of be a part of
the African-American community in order to understand what's happening in the game or to
do well in the game. And generally sort of expectation is that games are these games
are about blackness and that they're featuring elements of black cultural space.
And so there's another sort of variety of these games that focus on imparting some elements of history.
The 1998 deck, which is really just a card deck, is a suite of playing cards that pay homage to the hip hop rivalries of the 1990s.
And Insecure, the come up game based on, produced by Glow Up Games, is based on the HBO show Insecure.
And as they describe it.
It's about hustling heart and hype as your tools to build your new life in LA.
And LaToya Peterson is one of the people who's contributing to my book, and so I wanted to
give kind of a shout out to her work, as well as just describing games like Far Rock Dodgeball.
which is largely focused on location. You play in Harlem, you play in other sections of New York,
but it is incorporating that urban culture expectation that I think some people would have,
as well as things like H-Town minis, where you've got these sort of characterizations
or like extreme characterizations, and it's generally a fighting game.
Or you have other games that focus on black history, like the Black Movie Guest Quiz, which is a mobile game.
I believe the developer is out of Cincinnati.
And it serves a sense of community through history.
But I want to emphasize that black games are more than this.
I think of the examples I've given you previously as part of the yes and.
And I want to emphasize the and.
So games like Swim Sanity,
it's an online multiplayer underwater shooter.
It's really quite a beautiful game.
It's really quite a fun game.
I think it's a good example of how broad the spectrum of black games can be.
Another really beautiful game is Ariel Knight's Never Yield, which just has this sort of really great aesthetic and really great feel.
It's just a really interesting game to play.
And you would, of course, in this context, talk about sort of well, well-known designers
like Mike Pondsmith and the Cyberpunk series, or another contributor to the book, Alan Turner's
work, where he created a tabletop role-playing game that takes inspiration from the myths
and folklore of tribal and indigenous cultures.
So reminding you of a kind of diaspora that exists.
And a lot of this work is actually in the book, so I'm going to kind of save it and couch it so I can tell you more about some of the digital games.
But if you do read, Aaron Tramiel has done a really great job of creating this comprehensive chapter on black analog game designers that will be a part of the book.
But I can also talk about another contributor, Boris Willis, who's mixing games and dance.
So again.
If you're thinking about all the ways that black games are created, there's
really quite a variety. So I want to take this opportunity to talk about black
game makers. And I basically started meeting with people and listening to
some of their observations, some of their experience, some of their motivation.
And there was one theme that seemed to be repeated every time.
And it was that not enough people tell our stories.
And I emphasize that in quotes because it was something that I heard often over and over again.
That the stories of black game makers just weren't being heard,
their experiences weren't being shared.
And so I've tried to make a space for their stories to be told both here in this talk
and also in this particular book.
And I'm going to give my story as a case study,
to kind of position and I hope you understand
who's giving this presentation and perspective
that I come from, but also because I think
it helps you understand some of the experiences
that I've shared with other developers.
So I'm a Cape Verdean American. If you're completely unfamiliar with Cape Verde,
there it is on the right hand side. It's a little tiny country off the west coast of Africa. Yes,
that's Africa on the right. And I grew up in Massachusetts, very kind of far from Cape Verde,
but nestled in one of the largest Cape Verdean populations in the country.
And I've been making digital games off and on for 20 plus years.
and I have a variety of experiences that have to do with the way that I've built games.
But when I started making games, I think one of the most important things to note is that
I was the only child in our subsidized housing project shown on the right with a computer.
So it's a good example of what I've seen several game developers mention, which is that
I, like the other game designers, and I'm refraining from giving their stories because I want you to read their stories and hear them directly from them,
but 90% of my childhood friends owned or played a console game, but very few of them made games.
They all played, but they didn't really make games.
And so if you look at some of the data according to Pew Research, African-Americans are the most
likely to play video games of any of the ethnic groups that they looked at, particularly amongst
teens at 83 percent. In comparison, those who self-identified as white were 71 percent likely
to play video games and Hispanic teens were 69 percent.
Take that in comparison to the IGDA statistic that basically says that less than 2% of all
game makers identify as black. That's a huge disparity and it's the thing I felt as a kid
and continue to feel as some of the other game designers and developers have mentioned.
Basically if 90% of my childhood friends owned or played a console game,
I was the only one actually making games.
And so there's this real sense of loneliness or sense of being different and outside of
a community that you'll see persists in a lot of the observations.
So my story in a lot of biographies, my story illustrates a common tale.
And that common tale is basically that the community of black game makers is much larger,
or game players, is much larger than the community of black game makers. There are far more black
people playing games than there are in people of the African-American diaspora and the African
diaspora. There are far more people playing, obviously, than there are in the community of
black game makers. And it's not even a question of proportion. It's actually, it's disproportionate,
exceptionally disproportionate.
even when compared to any other population. So I want to share with you some Black Game Maker
biographies to give you some context. And again, I don't want to attribute them to anyone
individually, so I'm just going to suss out some themes that persisted. So a few themes that seem
to come up over and over again as people share their stories. One was often feeling unique in
the industry.
And so you can see this also come through in blog posts and discussions.
So there's an article in Blacks in Technology that asks where are all the black game developers?
And there's discussion on Polycount that do black game developers even exist, which should be really scary to people.
And then there are collections that are trying to help people understand where the Black Game Devs are.
And so BlackGameDevs.com is a good example of such work.
Another theme was feeling no choice but to go solo.
And for context, there are people like Aerial Knights Never Yield that have created really successful properties by going solo.
And I remember more than a decade ago, I wrote an article for...
for Gamma Sutra and Computer Game Guide
that basically encouraged people to go solo.
I think that one of the ways that people solve this problem
of limited access to the industry
is to just do it all on their own,
which is tremendous amount of work,
but also I think echoes a lot of the things
that we've heard about the future of indie games
when we were talking about it five to eight years ago.
And then another, I'm just going to take this anonymized Facebook post for you and just share.
Another person on Facebook just volunteered that they said that being African American,
they've actually had investors say they love their company and love their game,
but they won't invest because I'm black. But they say they still keep striving towards my goal.
So there's a sort of sense of persistence, even in the face of some pretty obvious obstacles.
Another theme that kept coming up was this idea of being interested in making impact or doing what matters.
And a good example of that is Phi questions.
So this is basically a card deck that helps families, communities, people playing, normalized discussions of finances.
So it's kind of like a way to create community around talking and working through real important questions about finances.
Other activities like iThrives, the Runaround, were largely focused on co-design.
So the idea here is that they're going to make an impact by working with a community of African Americans
and then basically creating a game around whatever sort of product comes from a participatory or co-design approach.
And then you have other folks who are doing things around indigenous economic justice.
So this is EarthCypher from MediaBreeze.
And you also have this other theme of fostering community.
There was a lot of discussion from people who were making these games
talking about how they want to foster community.
So Spill It is an interesting one, and I like some of the artwork from their website.
These photographs you see on the left, they'll have a persistent appearance
because I shot them myself after I played the games.
But in short, they're sort of talking about the opportunity to let Spill It spice up your kickbacks.
and help you understand sort of like getting a little more casual with folks.
But there's a whole other space where other people are creating games for
Black people by Black people. It's sort of the
by Black movement. And for some, being a Black game maker
is central to the design itself. And for others, identity isn't actually
central. And I want to emphasize that not every Black game is about Black
identity.
So almost everyone noted that there is an expectation of making what folks would expect is a black game.
And so it's important to recognize, and people had mentioned this, recognize the diaspora,
that African-American is quite diverse and that there are a lot of different experiences
and sense of what it means to be a member of the black community.
So basically, being black doesn't require that the game actually incorporate what are
kind of stereotypical black culture elements. It can still be a black game if it doesn't
include hip hop. It can still be a black game if it doesn't include what other elements
someone might assume make it black. And so, examples of this, things like Sky Temple Stack,
a nice mobile game, quite pretty, are examples of that.
As is Tiny Bird Garden. Here's Tiny Bird Garden Deluxe being shown.
Really interesting game, very different.
Or Museum Multiverse to make sure I show you at least a few VR games.
Another VR game is basically Run, Die, Run Again, but it's a first-person parkour game.
Another really beautiful game by Retro Ninja.
And we've got other games on the independent side that focus on other
themes that are related to social impact. So operator is basically about a
journalist that has to use her police scanner to keep her sister out of harm's
way while an intense protest becomes increasingly unsafe. You can see the URL
there. I encourage you to play it, get that experience. And generally
I want to help people understand that Black Games are as wide and diverse as the people that actually make them.
And it seems so obvious to state this, it seems like I shouldn't need to state this,
but in talking to people, especially folks who weren't familiar with Black Games,
what I found is that this is a surprising observation and news to people, unfortunately.
So...
For example, black games include art themes.
So this is Artifacts 2 by Fizzaro,
which is self-described as a game
about the entanglement of trauma in the mind and body.
And this is an IndieCade finalist or IndieCade selection
back in 2018, a really interesting game.
Or religious themes.
So When I Get Free is a Christian Bible-themed playable
graphic novel that...
I think illustrates how these things can be integrated into gameplay.
And then we have a bunch of other games that are sort of new takes on old mechanics,
as I've done these analyses.
So Rageball, for example, I like its tagline.
Anything else is just Pong.
But you can see some familiar mechanics and then some changes there.
Or I think you'd kind of be under a rock if you hadn't heard about Treachery and Beatdown City at this point.
But, you know, really different set of experiences.
Or Combat Corps is another game I think I'd reference here that I think is really interesting and available.
And then there are even games that maybe not are just flirting with interesting new mechanics,
but also just fundamentally distinct experiences that may, and I want to emphasize this,
may incorporate themes of blackness, but not in the ways that we would, I think, people would
expect. So it's not about saying, oh look, I have a person of color as my main character,
but there are experiences like the entanglement of trauma that come through in really interesting
ways.
So, Hex Gambit's an interesting game I would encourage you to take a look at.
As is Chrono Ghost, really sort of pretty platformer.
Or, if you're looking for something really different, consider something like Galactic Bar Fight.
Weird Kid Studios produced this.
I just want to kind of wrap up with some closing thoughts and give some sense of sort of what's next and just kind of help you reflect on the situation of black games these days.
So I really did start this project to document the game makers in their games.
And I was really excited about doing that.
And as I did it, I realized that it's really important to tell black stories and to
recognize black cultural production in games.
It's not just this sort of horrible history in the U.S.
of really disrespecting the black community.
It's also just about recognizing the contributions that may not always be
amplified.
So from those stories, I've learned some things that I think are really worth sharing.
And one of them is this idea that in the absence of community, we build it ourselves. So there's a
lot of activity around saying...
It's really hard to get into the games industry.
People aren't really supportive.
It's really hard when you're the only person of color
or the only person in the black community.
And so a lot of people have made these efforts
to create their own spaces, websites,
Facebook groups, et cetera.
So in the absence of community, we build it ourselves,
seems to be a thing I've seen.
Likewise, in the absence of access,
you see people trying to create it.
So creating training programs, creating support,
creating social gatherings.
And again, it would be great if that absence of access didn't exist, but that the positive note is that people are creating those spaces.
And I think that's part of the future.
And then in the absence of support, we support ourselves, which is another sort of theme that kept coming through as I saw who was succeeding and how they were succeeding.
So I want to kind of remind people that games are actually part of a milieu of culture.
There's a wide array of cultural contributions that games make.
And so I strongly believe that games themselves, the games industry, the games practice, is
healthiest not as a monoculture, not rows and rows of the same work by the same people,
but instead as something that is born from diversity.
So much like a natural monoculture versus a diverse environment, a diverse environment can weather storms and monoculture can create some really bad situations.
So the game making community is stronger when it's diverse, in my humble opinion.
So I'd strongly encourage all of us to work towards cultivating that diversity, to cultivate diversity across the spectrum.
And of course, I have to remind you that Black Games matter,
which is why I did this research and why
I'm trying to share this work and put in front of you
a variety of work that others have created.
So thanks.
You can shoot me an email if you have any questions,
and I'll be happy to answer them.
Have a great day.