So my name is Elisabeth Mahler, and today I would like to talk to you about the process
of creating two social impact games that I've worked on, Normal Lost Phone and Another Lost
Phone Lower Story.
These two games are games where you find a phone, and you have to find out what happened
to the owner of the phone by looking through the different applications, reading the emails,
looking into the gallery.
They are presented as investigative games, but through storytelling, they make people
think about important themes such as homophobia or abusive relationships.
We sold more than 200,000 copies of these games.
And these games also had a real impact on a large number of people.
As you can see from different messages we have received.
This game helped me come out of the closet.
This game made me realize that I was homophobic and that I had to change.
This game has helped me accept my past.
This game made me realize I was too jealous and I had to work on it.
All these different reactions are what I call direct social impact.
Someone plays a game whose objective is to make them think about a subject,
and this game provokes a direct reaction.
I will give you some advice on how to design games with a direct social impact in a second
part of this talk, but first I would like to talk to you about indirect social impact.
Indirect social impact is the fact that any creation, whether we intend it or not, will
have a social impact on its audience.
To take a more personal example, when I was a teenager,
I read a lot of mangas.
On one side, I read a lot of shoujos, mangas for girls.
In these mangas, there were always
girls looking for prince charming
and also looking for the best way to satisfy prince charming.
At the same time, I was reading a lot of shōnen, mangas for boys.
And in the mangas I've read, all the boys were presented as sex maniacs, without exception.
I was quite young and I didn't have much perspective yet.
And these two parallel readings pushed me into the beginning of my love and sex life with two beliefs.
First, my role was to find Prince Charming and to satisfy him.
That's what I have learned from the Chojos.
But also, I had to accept all his sexual desires,
because all men were sex-obsessed,
without exception, including Prince Charming.
That's what I have learned from the Shonans.
If you want my opinion, it was really not the best way
to start young adult life.
What I'm trying to say here is not that mangas are evil,
and that I regret having read them.
Not at all.
What gets me thinking here is that I'm not sure
that the authors of this manga, while living in Japan,
were thinking about the influence
that their works could have on a French teenage girl.
And that's indirect social impact.
Every work we create has an impact, and as authors, we have a responsibility to think
about the creation we make.
Our responsibility as authors is not a choice.
It is a fact, and we cannot ignore it.
That's why we have to make at least inclusive games.
Making an inclusive game is an approach that consists in thinking about the impact that each creative decision could have,
and seeking to limit, as much as possible, any potential negative impact.
Making an inclusive game is essential, but it's not the same as making an activist game.
To make an activist game is to make a game for which you intentionally seek to express
active support for a cause.
It's not something that you should feel compelled to do, because it's risky, both commercially
and militantly.
Commercially risky because it will hinder some people and potentially generate lifestyle
sales.
and militantly risky, because it's really hard, actually,
to make a good game with real impact.
I will therefore give you some advice and tips
that we used for A Normal Lost Fawn
and Another Lost Fawn Lore Story.
The first particularity of these games
is that unlike other games,
you are not asked to play a character.
in which you do not recognize yourself and with whom you have difficulty identifying.
In this game, you play as yourself.
You are the one who found the phone.
You are not the owner of the phone.
You are playing yourself searching through a lost phone.
This means that at no time do you
find yourself playing a character that
doesn't look like you.
And you should never make them choose from proposals
that you don't like at all.
Here, the choices have already been made by the protagonist.
And you are just asked to try to understand
what prompted the protagonist to make those choices.
However, these mechanics had some failures,
especially in the first game.
In order to have more interactivity,
that is for gameplay reason,
we had set up an unsent draft mechanic.
That is, at times, you come across message
that has not been sent,
and you must send them to receive a response
that contains information that allows you
to move on to the next part of the game.
It's something that really caused a problem for a lot of players, and rightly so.
They didn't like interfering that much in the character's life, and they were disturbed
by the message that could be implied, that it was okay to search and interfere in someone's
life.
This is a negative impact that has not been considered when designing the game, nor had
it been brought up during playtests.
One of the reasons I don't think anyone gave us feedback about these problematic issues
is that all the people who tested the game were people who knew us directly or indirectly.
But most important, they knew our intentions.
Since those people knew that our intentions were good, they didn't perceive the possible
bad consequences of what we were doing.
This problem on the first game helped us better think the design of the second game,
and three major changes were made.
For starters, at the launch of the game, we added a message to remind people
that the game is a work of fiction and that in real life, we must not invade anyone's privacy.
It's interesting that we had to put this type of message in the game because in an FPS for
example, you rarely see messages saying actually killing is wrong, please don't do it in real
life. But since searching through a phone, it's something much more widespread. I'm sure some
people in this room have done that.
It becomes a necessary reminder
that it is not something to be done
in order to avoid tribalizing it.
The other change in Another Lost Phone
is that there are never any drafts to send.
When we thought about it,
we found other gameplay mechanics
to help the story move forward.
And we realized there are always other solutions.
The last change we made in Under the Law of the Throne was the end of the game.
There are three ways to end the game and one of them is actually a completely valid way,
but then the game is really, really short, is that you open the game and then you erase
the data from the phone and you don't look through anything.
And there's even an achievement for that because it's a noble way to play this game
to decide not to play it.
Another advice I would like to give to people
who want to develop games with a social impact
is to choose your battles.
Could you raise hands if you are planning
or if you worked on a game with a direct social impact
or if you want to do it one day?
Okay, that's a lot of people.
Good, I congratulate you.
You all want to change the world.
That's amazing.
I wanted to tell you that if you try to open the player's eyes on a lot of different topics
at the same time, it's a guaranteed disaster.
Think of it as glasses.
If you give glasses to someone who is not used to wear them, it will take them some
time to adjust.
If you give them glasses with very thick lenses,
it will give them a headache and they will remove them right away.
Activism is the same.
You can't expect that overnight, thanks to your game,
your audience will become super awake on all subjects.
I therefore advise you to focus on a subject that is close to your heart, to make this
the main theme, and for the other subjects that are important to see, instead of having
an activist angle, having an inclusive angle.
For example, in a normal law firm, we never talk about racism, because it's a heavy, complex
subject, and it cannot be approached as lightly.
However, we tried to at least have an inclusive angle on this issue.
We have very different characters and at no time do people use racist insults, for example.
Another example.
I like to talk about animal exploitation issues, which are important to me personally.
So in a normal Lost Phone, there's a secondary character
that talks about it.
But it's just a little anecdote in the background.
The protagonist has a friend who is vegan,
just like they have another one who likes board games.
In another Lost Phone, in Laura's note,
we find a recipe for stuffed zucchinis.
The recipe turns out to be vegan, but there is no mention of any time that it is specifically
a vegan recipe.
However, there are players who try to reproduce the recipe, and therefore they ate vegan that
day.
You want to make a social impact game?
I advise you also to avoid having a moralizing gameplay.
Avoid having rules in the game that do not allow the player to move forward
until they agree with the message you are trying to convey.
In the Lost Friends series, players are never told
that they are wrong to think as they do.
This allows them to continue and finish the game.
In Character Writing 2, we try not to be too mannequin.
characters who have a vision of the world that we do not share,
well, these characters, they have other qualities.
And this is important if we want the people who actually think like these people
to connect maybe with them and to not feel too attacked when after that we say that,
you know, maybe you shouldn't think that.
To make a good game,
In absolute terms, it's necessary to do playtests
to check if the game is understandable and pleasant
to use.
I'm a big fan of playtests.
When we make games with social impact,
we also need to do playtests to test this social impact.
And in order to do this, you have to playtest your game
with people who knows a lot about the topic
you are talking about, and also people playtesting
the game with people who don't know anything about it.
On a normal lost phone, what we did is that we ask people
to play the game, and after that to explain the story
of the protagonist from A to Z.
This made it possible to discover misunderstanding and the need to explain in detail certain
points that seem really obvious for us.
For example, it's really silly, but we realize that some people don't know what LGBT stands
for.
For us it was obvious but it made us realize that we had to add at some point in the game
someone explaining what it is because it's not obvious for everyone, especially people
outside the LGBT community.
Also testing the game with people from the LGBT community raised some other problematic
issues on the game in relation to the message we were trying to get across.
There was indeed a part of the game
where we talked about the suicide
and murder rates of LGBT people.
This information was not false,
but we were told that this could lead some teenagers
not to come out because of fear,
which was not our goal, so we removed this part.
A normal loss fund was first created during a game jam.
So a large part of the story was created in 48 hours.
This means that there were no pre-production process
with actual time to reflect
on the message we wanted to convey.
So a prototype was developed and then shown
to people from the LGBT community in order to improve it.
On another law firm, however,
We wanted to take the time to do some research before writing the script.
We knew we wanted to talk about toxic relationships.
So I spent several months reading a lot about it.
Essays, scientific articles, autobiographies, even some novels.
I then contacted the Victim Support Association to ask for their help.
It was difficult at first to convince them to work with us.
Like, what, you want to make a game about abusive relationships, about domestic violence?
We had to explain that games can be used for something else than just entertainment.
Finally, we managed to convince them by showing them videos made by famous YouTubers on a normal loss form.
And by showing them all the comment sections of these videos on YouTube,
and all the people saying that the game helped them,
that's what convinced the organization to say,
Oh, okay, interesting way to change the world.
We'll try to do that with you.
In terms of process of writing, we had made progress on the scenario in a gradual way.
Step one, we asked the organisation to think the subject, how it should be addressed.
On the issue of abusive relationships...
We were told that what was most misunderstood
by the majority of the population
was the way the cycle of violence works.
Google it after the presentation.
Which explains why so many victims do not leave
the person who abuses them.
The other thing that is often misunderstood by the majority of the population
is the importance of psychological violence and how it precedes physical violence.
Once we had these important elements, it allowed us to choose the approach to the story.
We had to write a story that would explain the cycle of violence and that would focus
maybe on psychological violence.
So then I wrote a one-page synopsis outlining Loa's stories.
This document was started by the organization that was helping them, and they corrected
some points to keep us from falling into clichés.
Once a new synopsis was written and approved,
we worked on a walkthrough of the game,
and we asked them to review it.
The walkthrough of the game, it was a Flora story,
the same as in the synopsis, but with more details,
and especially it was showing the order
in which the player would discover
the different parts of Flora's story.
Again, with this walkthrough,
we worked on the details together.
And it was only after that this walkthrough was written, proofread,
that we set about writing the entire story.
This method was very effective, because it allowed us to know exactly
where we were going, without having to write whole parts of the story
and then finally remove them, as we'd done for a normal loss form.
We have some time for questions, but I really hope that this talk has helped you to think
about the design of your games, whether you want them to have direct social impact or
whether you know it will have indirect social impact.
And there's a mic somewhere over there for the questions.
And if you could start by introducing yourself,
it would be great.
Hi, my name's Laura.
I'm working on a similar project
where I'm trying to create an AR experience,
but working with stakeholders
in Native American communities.
And I guess my question is,
if you had presented this idea to, say, victims
or people that are allies or working with those victims,
and they had said,
don't do this.
Would you have changed your course
or how would you have approached that?
I guess...
Well, that's what they did actually, first, the organization.
They say, oh, why do you want to make a game?
And then we ask them why they think it's not a good idea.
And by understanding why they were thinking it was a bad idea,
we realized that they were not understanding what we had in mind.
So, I guess, talking more, trying to understand why and...
It's difficult to answer.
No, I know.
Like, hypothetical things.
I'm in the same boat right now too.
We've gotten a lot of support from the community, but also we've sort of developed something,
and now we actually have to take it back to them.
And I'm a little apprehensive, because I'm like, what if they, you know, like it could
derail a lot of the work we've done.
But I mean, the goal has always been to work with communities to amplify their voice, not
necessarily to put our own spin on it.
At the same time, we have sort of the keys to the kingdom in terms of the technology,
you know.
Yeah.
So.
Well, you have to work with them from the A to Z anyway.
Thank you.
Hi there.
My name's Sam.
I'm a software developer, and I've done a lot of outreach activities with students in
schools from low-income families.
And one of the things I know from that experience is.
there's a difference between knowing the facts about like learning like hey like you know
Maybe I should do this or should not do this versus like changing behavior
And I was wondering like how your team worked on that like for your games like to actually
Did you address trying to change player behavior?
Or did you just really want to help them be exposed to what homophobia could be and what it means?
I'm not sure I understood the question, so if I don't answer correctly, please ask again.
No, please, just, could you ask again the end of the question?
No worries.
So, a lot of times when you're wanting to change behavior of people, especially like
in the case of like abusive relationships, a lot of times people will know that
hey, this isn't a good thing, and sometimes it's hard to identify.
But that doesn't necessarily change their behavior,
and that's certainly a very complex, difficult challenge.
So I was just wondering if you tried to address that in the game,
and if so, how did you approach that?
Okay, so now I understand it's a very interesting question.
On another Lost from Loa story, one of the first questions we were asking ourselves is
why do we do this game?
What impact do we want to have?
And we were thinking on are we making a game for the victims?
Are we making a game for the abusers?
And when we talked with the organizations that help victims,
we realized that it was more interesting to try
to make a game for the people who
might know other people who are in abusive relationships,
in order to teach them how to react.
Because that's the majority of the people.
Maybe some people here are in an abusive relationship, and I'm sorry for that, but that would be
a small portion of it.
But I guess all of you, you know someone, or maybe you don't realize it, who is in this
position.
So that was the goal, trying to teach people to spot abusive relationships.
give the right advice, understand them better, understand how the cycle of violence works,
remind them that there are organizations that can help with this kind of stuff.
All right, thank you so much.
Any other questions?
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I was just wondering, you said that one of the things that you were focusing on was allowing
people to make choices from perspectives that you didn't necessarily agree in or agree with
in the game, so kind of honouring the alternate perspective from what you're trying to teach.
I was just wondering if you could say a little bit more about that, like how do you kind
of encompass a divergent view from the message that you're trying to get, like how do people
that are making those choices kind of learn from the game?
I'm sorry, I'm still not sure I understood the question.
Sorry, I thought that in your talk you were saying that you
allowed players to play the game from different
perspectives, so there might be people that were making
choices that you wouldn't necessarily agree with.
No, we don't do that.
That's the opposite of what we're doing.
We're making a game where the player has no choices to make.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I misunderstood.
Sorry.
Hi, my name is Daniela and I'm studying game development
and I have like a very interesting project.
I'm from Mexico and there's a lot of like corruption there.
So my project was about corruption and it was really hard
because like you said, you can't force a player
to see like your perspective and agree with it.
But where do you cross like,
no, where do you draw the line, you know,
because.
I wanted to make the players feel the way, like, let me think about it, like when you're
in disadvantage with someone because of the corruption and the abuse of power and stuff,
but like, for example, we had to like force the players into that perspective, but because
without...
giving up without we giving them that like character,
they couldn't like see the issue, you know?
And I think there was an issue with the game because of that
because players didn't connect really with the character,
but like where do you draw the line between
like giving the perspective you want the players to see
and...
giving them the freedom to really connect with the game.
I think the answer would be playtest in order to find this line and also maybe use warnings
at the beginning of your game, content warnings, tariqa warnings.
I'm not sure if that helps.
Yeah.
I have time maybe for one last question and after that if people want to keep asking questions
we will do it inside because we have to clear the room for other people.
Cool, my name is Gabriel Adauto.
I make learning games for kids.
My question is about the mechanics that you use.
So you said in the initial game, you
didn't want to do the sending the drafts.
If you could just talk through a couple of categories
of mechanics that you used in the game to replace that,
or just how do we think about mechanics
in this style of game?
Okay, well the idea behind signing the draft was to be sure that the players have access
to different parts of the game at different moments.
It was inspired by a friend of us who had a bad experience with the game Her Story,
where they got to the end at the first minute and they didn't enjoy it.
So we wanted to have a system so that you
Even if you feel like you can read everything, in reality you have to read that part first
and do something about it and then you can access the rest of it.
The answer draft looks like a good idea at the time.
And what we did in the second game is instead
having more password protected apart.
And these passwords,
they were always,
you always had to have some information
that you have read somewhere else to find the password.
So that's how we did it.
Well, thanks a lot.