Hi, I am Tim Aituner, Assistant Professor in Kinesiology at California State University, San Marcos.
Before that, I was a professional dancer.
Well, I meant to say I was a neuroscientist who also danced professionally.
Both my research and extracurricular interest in human movement brought me to the kinesiology field.
Here, in the Mixer Lab.
We develop serious games and explore the effects of virtual environments on human movement.
At BRDC, I will be talking to you about a serious game called The Reaching Task.
We developed this game for both AR and VR environments to investigate which platform
would be more appropriate for rehabilitation uses of the game.
In this session, not only we will answer this question, but we will also discuss the challenges
we face.
in developing the same game with similar motor and cognitive demands for both platforms.
Hope to see you at GDC in March 2020.