Hello everyone. Sorry for the delay there.
Alright, so the year is 1993.
Let me set the mood. One sec. Alright, there we go.
The year is 1993. I'm 16 years old. I'm a junior in high school.
The world of graphic design is insane.
My father, who worked at IBM at the time,
was invited to take a tour of Citizen Hall
at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill,
which at that time was a leading institution in R&D
of a thing called virtual reality.
Here's what a poster looked like from around that era.
That is actually from UNC.
And that is pretty much what the 90s looked like.
Being a high schooler, I was at that time playing games every day,
like Castle Wolfenstein 3D, Syndicate.
And on this tour, I got to see a lot of neat applications for VR.
But the demo that I remember the most was of a molecule.
So you basically put on this, like, 14-pound helmet,
and you can look at the molecular structure of an organic compound.
And actually, if we look back at this poster here...
That right there is what I saw in VR.
And if you think that it looks like some colored spheres
with rudimentary lighting, you would be correct.
So I probably was not as impressed with this demo
as maybe I should have been at that time.
Last for a couple of years,
Nintendo brings us into the future in 1995.
It looks something like this.
And of course, inside it looks like this.
So, fighting giant robots, right?
Back in the mid-90s, we were all about
fighting giant robots.
Also, I was a little less than impressed
with this particular experience.
If we fast forward to GDC 2013,
this is where I had my first opportunity
to try out a device called the Oculus Rift.
It's an early generation version.
This is a DK1, I believe.
And it looks something like that.
It's fighting giant robots.
So back in the mid-2010s, we were all about fighting giant robots.
This game was Hawken.
And I remember when I put the headset on,
my first thought was, I really hope no one's
taking a picture of me right now.
It was a cool experience piloting a mech.
It's got guns.
It's got jump jets.
I thought I was going to be fairly clever and ambush some of my fellow demo players.
So I jumped up onto a roof and I did the thing that you would do if you're up on a roof going
to ambush people below you, which is I walked over to the edge and I looked down.
The reaction was immediate and sort of physical, visceral, fear of falling.
So my reaction was, of course, I wanted to back up.
And it was at that moment that I realized that something had changed,
and that 20 years of promises of VR were finally being made good,
and that VR had arrived.
Which sort of brings me to today and to this lecture,
which is Punch It Up! Writing for Star Trek in VR.
And by which I mean, of course, the Star Trek is in VR, not the writing part.
It probably would be cool to write in VR, but we're not quite there yet.
So, obligatory bio.
I am Jay Posey, I am an expert narrative designer at Ubisoft, at Red Storm Entertainment.
That is actually my title, that's not just something I put on LinkedIn.
I've been there for a little over 12 years.
Started in game development in 1998, so kind of old.
I'm also a traditionally published author.
My fifth novel will be out this summer.
And I actually got my start as a screenwriter,
doing script development for a Hollywood producer.
So all that is just to say,
I've had the opportunity to work in a lot of different media.
And I'm genuinely excited about VR
and about the opportunity that it is affording us,
that the technology is open for storytelling.
I think there's a lot of new experiences out there for us to discover.
And I'm really looking forward to doing some of that.
All right, so finally, Star Trek.
Has anybody in here actually gotten to try a demo
of Bridge Crew yet?
A couple people?
OK, good.
Yes, Mr. Dansky in the back, back there.
Very good.
So for those of you who haven't got a chance to check it out,
very quick primer.
You play as one of four officers on the bridge of the USS Aegis,
which is a brand new ship that we created in conjunction with CBS just for this game.
So you're up there.
And you're exploring sort of a poorly understood section of space called the trench.
And of course, awesome and exciting things happen.
Our four officers are the helm officer.
We have the pilot who pilots the ship and manages impulse and warp travel.
We have the tactical officer who operates weapons, shields, and scanners.
We have our trusty engineer who distributes and reroutes power
and then if it's ever necessary manages repairs.
And of course we have the captain who just tells everyone what to do.
And if playtesting is any indication, also constantly turns red alert on and off.
You can actually see in this image the red lighting is of course because red alert is on,
which is probably because it hadn't been on in like 30 seconds.
So I wanted to take a little bit of a different approach from usual with this talk,
so it's not going to be kind of the three bullet points of lessons learned.
It's really more of a high-level survey of some of the challenges that we ran into developing
and writing specifically for VR, and then some of the solutions that we came up with.
That being said, here are three bullet points to tie all these things together.
So I want to talk about presence, talk about franchise, and talk about cooperation.
So each of the topics that I cover in my remaining two and a half hours are going to touch on
one or more of these pillars.
So I'm just going to quickly define what I mean by them.
First off, presence.
How many people have tried VR at all of any of the current hardware?
Okay, good.
Most everybody.
If you haven't had a chance to, I definitely recommend.
Give it a try, take advantage of the expo floor.
I'm sure we'll have demos out there.
Primarily because the experience is very difficult
to describe if you haven't really seen it for yourself.
So I've got some screenshots up here that we'll go through.
But they really don't do justice to the VR experience.
We're talking about presence.
As game devs, we talk a lot about immersion,
which basically is just engaging our players enough
so that controllers and screens disappear,
and we're really engrossing our players in the created world.
It turns out with VR, that's practically free.
And it's much stronger in VR, so we call that presence.
That's why I had such a strong fear reaction in Hawken.
And you're really no longer just seeing and hearing things,
but you have this sense that you've brought your physical
body into the space with you.
So that's what I'm talking about when I talk about presence.
Secondly, franchise, Star Trek just celebrated its 50th
anniversary last year.
So that's 50 years of TV, movies, books, comic books,
video games, fan fiction.
And I don't know if you're all aware of it, but Star Trek has
several fans.
Sometimes they have opinions.
So that was really a mountain of content for us to kind of pour through and try to condense into this VR game.
So it presented some challenges, but it also turned out to be a source of a lot of our solutions.
So I'll touch on that too.
Franchise.
And finally, cooperation.
And I know this picture is a little bit creepy,
but this was literally the only one I could find
on the internet about cooperation
that wasn't just a bunch of hands on top of each other.
So, okay, fine, we'll use the hands.
That's fine.
So Star Trek Bridge Crew was really designed
as a social VR game first.
So you can play solo, but we intended it primarily
and we designed it primarily as a multiplayer game.
And it was really important for us to foster an environment
of cooperation, both for the gameplay but also
for the narrative and for the franchise.
It just seemed appropriate for this franchise.
So we'll touch on that.
And I'm going to use these sort of three images just
as keys going forward, mostly because I'm old
and pictures help me remember what I'm talking about.
All right, so first off, pacing.
It's not really new for narrative, obviously,
but I wanted to touch on it because this is one
of the big lessons that I learned working in VR.
Not because it was a surprise to us.
We obviously knew we had to consider it,
but we just didn't know how different
it was going to be in VR.
As game devs, we're always very concerned
about keeping our players engaged.
There are lots of different ways to do that.
There's sort of the call of duty model of spectacle.
As long as you continue moving forward,
you're going to see awesome things.
So it's kind of a thrill ride mechanic.
There's the more open world model
of a Far Cry or Assassin's Creed
where you have a wealth of choices to choose from.
So it's player directed, but they can always open up a menu
and see any number of things that they can do.
And obviously we never want our players to get bored.
So this is something that we brought a lot of our previous
experience of designing more traditional games.
And we're always very concerned about perceived downtime.
So things like traveling between objectives, we wanted
to make sure that players always felt like they were
kind of in the middle of the action.
But our main menu actually taught us a
really important lesson.
So I'm going to pop up some screenshots
here of our main menu.
And you can see just down there in the corner, that is
our main menu.
When you first load into Star Trek, bridge crew.
You start in an inspection shuttle.
You kind of come out around this space shuttle,
space shuttle, come around the space station
and do this lazy orbit around the ship.
And that will continue for as long as you want to sit in there.
And of course, being devs, we hop in there and we kind of
boop our way around real quick and we're into the next,
kind of on to the next thing.
But as we started taking this out to the public
and started giving demos,
we found that players were wanting to spend
three, five, seven, ten minutes
just sitting in the shuttle.
And one of our guys that ran a lot of these demos,
actually not once, but on two separate occasions,
had people who had to take their headsets off
to wipe tears from their eyes.
Because they were just so emotionally excited
and overwhelmed by this opportunity.
So, you know, and this is just our main menu, right?
So that really, really surprised us
at just the emotional impact that this,
you know, this franchise has on people.
And literally this is a dream come true for some people
when they put that headset on and they feel like
they are literally on the bridge of this starship.
And so that really opened our eyes
to how much we needed to respect
and give people breathing room to really fully experience
and appreciate the experience that they were having.
So we kind of had to resist some of our natural urges
to pressure, put pressure on players
or to kind of distract them with other things.
And that also impacted how many moments of kind of narrative
that we needed to push on people.
Because sometimes just sitting there on the bridge
and looking at space is apparently enough
to capture that experience.
Of course, that impacts storytelling.
And when I say storytelling, I mean the actual mechanics
that we use to deliver narrative information.
So there's this well-known
and generally accepted solution in games,
which is basically having some authority figure
somewhere far away telling you everything you need to know.
Good news is Star Trek franchise gave us a great solution for this.
And that was the Starfleet Admiral on the B-screen.
And sorry for the slight tilt.
I actually took this while I was in a headset.
And of course because the headset adjusts with you, I didn't realize my head was tilted slightly.
But anyway.
So the Starfleet Admiral, people talking to you on the view screen is across pretty much all Star Trek properties at some point.
So that was great for us. It was kind of a good way that we could use the franchise to do something that we always do in video games.
Bad news is, in a shared virtual environment, no one wants to listen to a talking head.
So, when you have multiple people in VR and that sense that you are all there together
in the shared virtual environment is so strong.
I think the contrast between natural human interaction and some guy on a screen talking
to you who's clearly not a human is just so stark that this method of delivering information
is just not as compelling or really as acceptable as it might have become in sort of traditional
media, other games.
So this is something that we had to really evaluate and think about.
And our Admiral does show up a couple of times, but it's something that we've used pretty sparingly.
And generally only for high-level information.
So it was kind of story information from back home that you couldn't really get any other way.
And it felt appropriate, the way we're using it,
but we just couldn't rely on it as much as we might have otherwise.
So that left us with a couple of needs.
One was to provide narrative context for missions and for moment-to-moment gameplay.
And then the other was just for directing player action.
The first point, the narrative context.
Again, the Star Trek franchise really came through for us
and gave us a gift, and that was the captain's log.
So each of our missions starts with a captain's log,
which is really just an establishing shot,
the voiceover from a captain.
This was great for us because it really roots
the experience of this game in something that's familiar
and iconic from the franchise.
So it was a good fit for us.
It also allows us to provide narrative context
from missions before.
So it can kind of serve as a reminder of, you know,
what you did earlier and also the results of those actions.
And then also, of course, sets up our coming mission.
So it kind of gives you a little idea of what you're in for.
From a traditional game writing standpoint, this isn't really a surprise, right?
This is kind of a cinematic.
We've been using these forever.
The thing that was interesting to me about this was that it works in VR.
And actually players seem to be more receptive to narrative information in this format than
they were from a guy on a screen talking to them.
And obviously this is anecdotal.
I think it's worth exploring though.
Maybe this is due to some sort of observer effect
where people have a natural sense
of whether they're inhabiting a camera versus an avatar.
Or if it's just this is a familiar framing device
and so people kind of go into the,
oh, I'm watching movie slash TV now.
So.
I'm kind of in a more passive mode.
I don't really know.
This is kind of a hypothesis right now, but this was a good solution for us for the narrative
context.
It still left for us the second challenge of directing player action, of making sure
that players had critical mission information.
And here we decided to take a little bit of a risk.
And that was entrusting our captains, actually, to help us as storytellers.
Which is of course meaning we're trusting a human player
to actually pull information and then share that with the crew
and do it in a way that contributes to the overall narrative experience.
So if you look here on the armrest of the captain's chair,
there's Captain Edwards, you can see some little buttons.
So the captain actually has a UI that they can bring up all these different screens
and get information.
And some of it is privileged information that no one else gets.
So not only do we have sort of outlining mission goals and requirements, there are also hints
or optional ways to complete objectives or things that you would really have no other
way to know, like the, you know, damage radius of a warp core breach, things like that.
Internally, we sort of couched this as the captain's experience.
And this was sort of our way of thinking, you know, if you're a captain in Starfleet
and you're responsible for an entire starship, you've probably been around for a while, you've
probably seen some stuff.
So this was really our way of letting new players kind
of benefit from those years of experience
that they don't actually have, kind of getting that from this UI.
That did mean for us that it was up to the captain to communicate
and coordinate with the crew.
And in some situations, there's not clearly a right answer
for solving a situation.
So it's sort of the classic, you know,
do you risk your own crew members
to rescue some civilians in harm's way?
And it's really up to the captain to make that sort of decision.
The good news is it seems to have paid off.
So from play testing and iterating on that stuff,
turns out that good captains,
people who are decisive and kind of know what they're doing,
make for great crews.
It's been really interesting to see when captains,
you know, we bring in four people who've never met before,
and you see somebody really embrace that captain's role,
and the other three players who don't know this guy
still seem to kind of come together under that authority.
and really buy into the experience.
And it's really, really cool to see that happen.
And as I said, of course, there was a bit of a risk
because when you get this guy,
you end up with a less than ideal experience.
So, that was one thing that we really had to work on
quite a bit.
A lot of this came down to, we went through a lot of iterations about what kind of information
do we present to the captain, how do we present it, how do we write it so that it's digestible
and then players can read from here and parrot that back and sound authoritative.
So some of that stuff has helped out.
And, again, you know, that was the interesting, another interesting thing about this is I
think we're requiring a lot from our captains to pull information to go find it and synthesize
it and share it.
And we as an industry have done a pretty great job of training players to be very passive
and just sort of like sit here and wait until we tell you exactly what to do.
You know, hey, the room you're in is on fire.
You should find a way to escape kind of thing.
So we had to go through a lot of iteration to figure out how do we train our captain players
to understand that, oh, wait, I'm responsible for making these calls
and for driving our gameplay.
So we're leaning pretty heavily on our captains.
But it's not all about captains, obviously.
Our entire player crew really participates in sort of that moment-to-moment story experience.
And so it was very important for us to...
Sorry about the ant picture there.
It was very important for us to continually bring our thinking back to the cooperation of the crew
and to really capture that proper experience of all of us working together.
In case you couldn't tell from the name, really the heart of Star Trek Bridge Crew is the crew.
Shocking.
And so we really wanted to create a narrative experience of sort of this trustworthy crew
off the leash.
Which just means that Starfleet has already checked you guys out and yep, we trust you
to go off into the reaches of space and represent us and do a good job.
So I also wanted to empower players with a sense of responsibility that they were out there to do the proper things.
And this is one of the reasons I think that the constant updates from Starfleet, the Starfleet Admiral, felt wrong.
Because it gave you the sense that Starfleet was always watching you and, you know, waiting for you to make a mistake or not trusting you completely.
So that was another thing we had to work on.
And spotlighting was something that we settled on.
Where our mission designs really provide challenges specifically designed
for one officer or more commonly for a pairing of officers to kind
of give them a chance to be the hero for a particular thing.
So instead of every player feeling like they are the hero of this story,
kind of everyone's taking it in turn to be the hero of this moment.
Which I think feels authentic to the franchise where you've got sort of the episode where it's,
you know, the science officer is figuring things out, or the engineer,
or people working together.
So, you know, a very simple example in our game, there's a mission where you start out,
the ship is damaged, and you are being pursued by enemy forces.
So it's really up to the helm officer to coordinate.
with the engineer to figure out sort of how much power they need, you know,
when they should make a run for it and when they should kind of hide out
and make repairs and that sort of thing.
So that mission is really built around that constant back and forth between the two of them.
Which of course leads us to overall campaign and mission design.
And when we sat down and did our sort of initial campaign design,
our campaign arc and narrative.
We really went with sort of a more typical structure,
similar to sort of a long movie plot.
You know, our A plot and our B plot, some twists
and some villainous heroes and some heroic villains
and that sort of thing.
And at the end of it, when we evaluated it,
I realized we had Tom Clancy's Star Trek bridge crew,
which it was a good story,
but obviously it was not the right story
for what we were looking for.
And we kind of threw that out and went back to the well.
And when we started as a narrative team talking about,
you know, well, what is Star Trek to each of us?
The things that kept coming up where people were like,
ah, well, there's this one episode where blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, or that one episode when hmm, you know, happened.
And it kept coming back to that sort of,
that episodic approach, right?
Which again, you think about the franchise,
it makes so much sense, it was rooted in television.
So this led us to take kind of a flipped approach
to mission design and narrative design,
which was kind of identifying these iconic
Star Trek experiences, exploration,
being chased by a strange entity,
searching for enemies in a nebula, that sort of thing.
And building these sort of,
Missions and narratives around that core experience,
both from a gameplay and a narrative standpoint.
And once we kind of had figured out
what those experiences were that we wanted,
then we went and arranged them in a way
that gave us a nice sort of long-term narrative arc
that felt more like a season.
And we really had to be comfortable with the idea
that not every mission had to have
every Star Trek thing in it.
And we really wanted to focus on sort of each,
each mission having a distinctive feeling.
And recognizing that we had to be comfortable with the idea that players were going to argue about which was the best mission based on kind of what they wanted their personal Star Trek experience to be.
From a mission framework standpoint, we kind of settled on this three-point thing of a concern, a complication, a crisis.
And that just means that we had kind of an initial setup for why you are where you are.
Sometimes it's something benign.
Oh, we're exploring this.
area or sometimes it's, oh, we're trying to help this ship in distress.
Inevitably, there's more to it than you first imagined, and usually that leads to some sort
of decision point for the captain.
So it wasn't really a formula that we followed
so much as one that we played with.
We kind of settled on this as feeling like Star Trek to us.
And then we kind of adjusted those weights.
But that was very helpful for us.
Obviously trying to define what makes Star Trek,
Star Trek is a bad idea because it's so many things
to so many different people.
But for us, one of the core ideas that we latched onto
was this idea of an interaction of experts.
So sort of the crew is the heart of every solution.
And again, giving each player an opportunity to shine at some point in the mission and over the campaign.
So we identified some iconic roles.
So we had our captain, our helm, our engineer, obviously,
but also communications, science officer, medical, you know,
any of those people that you've seen from across various properties.
And we selected the most that were compelling for gameplay.
which sometimes required us to collapse or combine roles.
This is one of the reasons that working with CBS was so great.
When we designed the ship that we made, it's smaller than the Enterprise.
It's not a flagship, obviously.
It's a smaller, different role.
And so we were able to kind of work with them to figure out
where it would make sense to combine roles that we see on the shows.
And then, for example, a tactical officer handles scanning, for example, which, you know,
typically we think of as more of a science officer role, but it made sense for us to do that.
And really it was important for us to make sure that players
who had never seen an episode of the show could still feel
like they were expert at their role.
So that helped, had to work a lot with making sure
that the stations were very learnable,
that each of the actions themselves were fairly
straightforward.
And then we got a lot of the sort of expertise
that we were looking for out of the combination of actions
or the coordination of actions with other people.
All of which required us to develop kind of a shared vocabulary.
So a major part of the Star Trek franchise, obviously,
is in its sort of particular use of language.
So helping people communicate authentically was something
that we really had to tackle, which was a challenge for us.
So there's sort of this feeling about Star Trek that, you know,
that sounds like science.
There's so much jargon and technical jargon that sounds...
plausible.
And we went through a lot of transcripts.
And I don't know if anybody's familiar with the Memory Alpha
website.
We use that quite a bit to try and capture that language
that we were after.
And we recognized that players are contributing
to each other's experiences.
So again, we had to make sure that new players could
sound expert, could use that language,
even when they weren't familiar with it from the shows.
So a lot of what we did was build the language
that we wanted people to use directly into the UI.
So phasers, detection range, shield level, that sort of thing.
It's people reporting on things.
It sounds like what you'd hear on the shows.
And for example, our warp core process is actually going to warp requires helm
and engineer to work together to go through these sort of protocol.
And what we found is after a couple of play throughs, people start to develop this cadence
and pattern as a crew of when they're hitting their marks.
Okay, I'm ready, I'm ready, this is ready.
Okay, hit it.
And that was really encouraging to us that we were kind of hitting our marks
with what we were going for there.
And again, that coordination of the team as to the authenticity
that we're looking for for the entire environment, right?
You start to feel like a crew because it sounds like a crew.
So that was great.
Sorry, I'm trying to blast through these because I know we got a late start, so.
Finally, filling out the bridge, obviously it's not enough just to have four people running
around, running a starship.
So to kind of fill out the rest of the crew, make sure this advances.
Ready, go ahead.
Sorry, I have a shot here.
Did we just lock up?
My slides aren't advancing.
There we go.
All right.
So, as I said, you can't play this solo,
so anytime you've got a partial crew,
if you don't have humans at one of the,
either helm, tactical, or engineer,
it'll be taken over by what we internally called a crew bot.
And from a writing standpoint,
we wrote the VO for crew bots.
Really in a way that we hoped would instruct players
on how they should communicate when they are in that role.
So a tactical officer only ever reports on tactical things
like when a new enemy appears.
Engineers reporting on things like subsystem health.
And we're really using those as a way
so that when players don't have a human there,
they're learning what it should,
when they play in that role, they should be reporting on.
Secondly, we had info shirts, which were our communications officer, who's back here,
and our camera-shy science officer.
We put them in because they were iconic roles.
We just couldn't find enough gameplay to support human players for that.
So what we did was we made them critical for narrative information and for gameplay information
and used them kind of to replace the talking head.
So now you've got somebody on the crew who's giving you this information
in a way that felt natural to the franchise.
And then finally we have these guys over here,
our red shirts, and they're actually all around
the outer ring of the bridge.
And this is really where we packed in a lot of that
technical and scientific jargon.
These are the guys that when everything's normal,
they're reporting on how Jeffrey 2.14 is,
and when things are bad that there's fire
on deck six or whatever.
So none of this is critical information,
but it does give you general game state information,
and that was really where we were able to kind of
pack in that jargon that we were looking for.
How are we doing for time?
Are we out?
Do people?
We're pretty much out.
All right, let me just go over the drama.
Turns out, interpersonal drama happens pretty naturally.
So if you take a skilled crew and you apply a little pressure
to them.
You start ending up with things like this where everybody is calling for things.
And, you know, anyway.
So we had to be very careful about, we found that we needed to be careful
about how much narrative information we were trying to push
because sometimes you get these high interaction moments between crew
and there wasn't any room for us to give more information into that.
So we had to balance that stuff out.
So we've come a very long way, all the way from here to now here.
I would say that, you know, this is sort of the known area of video games.
We on the Star Trek Bridge Crew team have very boldly gone forward into the future,
probably maybe roughly about here.
Which is to say, we really have no idea what's out there for VR.
And that's not to say anything about, you know, all these other places,
some of which aren't even on the map.
So, I'm really excited about a lot of the tools and techniques
that we're going to be discovering in VR.
I think we're just really, just now getting started on figuring
out some of the techniques for exploring this stuff.
And that is time.
And thank you all so much.
Appreciate it.
Contact information, hit me up on Twitter.
I'll take questions out there.