Yep, so let's start with some quick introductions.
So I'm Douglas Wilson.
I'm a lecturer at RMIT University in Melbourne, where I teach and research games.
I'm also the co-owner of Diguda Fabrique, a small studio based in Copenhagen, Denmark,
making indie games.
We're currently working on an adventure game called Mutassione.
This is not what this talk is about, but hopefully we'll have news about this game in the near
future.
So today I want to give a business talk about one of my previous projects called Sports
Friends.
I have a lot to share about this project, so I'm going to try to cram in as many slides
as I can into the next hour.
Just as a quick overview of the project, in case you've never heard of this before, Sports
Friends is a compendium of four different local multiplayer games, all by different
designers who were based in New York City at the time.
By local multiplayer, I mean multiplayer video games you
play together in the same room, like as opposed
to online.
The four games include Super Pole Riders, a physics-based
pole vaulting game by Bennett Foddy.
HOKRA, a minimalist 2v2 sports game by Ramiro Corbetta,
Barabariball, a mix of volleyball and Super Smash Brothers
by Noah Sasso, and JS Joust, a physical face-to-face motion
control game that I designed while living in Copenhagen
as a graduate student.
Actually, there are also a couple of secret games
by Bennett Foddy, but I'll let you discover those yourself.
And so when I say compendium, I mean that all four games were
bounded together in the same commercial product
as one executable glued together with the same main menu flow.
In May of 2014, we released Sports Friends
for PlayStation 3, PlayStation 4 on PlayStation Network.
And so that puts us very late in the PS3 lifecycle,
but quite early in the PS4 lifecycle.
Then in December of 2014, we released Sports Friends for PC, Mac, Linux via Steam and at
the Humble store.
The game received strong reviews, which we're really proud of, and the project was actually
profitable, which I'll talk more about later.
Today I want to give a business talk about how we marketed and made Sports Friends and
why that matters.
So, why talk about a project that's like four years old at this point?
You know, admittedly, the games industry has changed significantly since this game was
released.
But what's important about this talk, I think, is not Sports Friends itself, but more general
takeaways about video game compendiums and other possible forms of cross-game collaboration.
So this talk is not me suggesting do what we did,
but rather I think indies could take some of the lessons
and run with them in their own way in a manner
specific to their cultural context, time, period, genre, and so on.
Okay, so here's what I'm gonna cover today.
First, a review of how the project came about,
then how we raised funds to make the project
and built an audience,
how we made the thing once we were funded,
and then a whole bunch of our financials.
So the budget, the legal contracts that we signed,
our profit sharing mechanism, and some sales data.
And finally, and maybe more interesting, I want to think through a little bit about the future of sports friends like compendiums and what that could look like moving forward.
And then I'll crystallize some takeaways at the end of the talk.
I don't want this talk to just be like a post-mortem.
I mean, obviously, it is kind of a post-mortem of Sports Friends,
but I do want it to say something a little bit more.
One of the key points I'm going to emphasize is why a compendium like Sports Friends
is something more than just a bundle.
I want you to come away from this talk understanding why that distinction matters.
More generally, I want to convince you to consider broader cultural narratives
beyond just your one game.
So recently there have been a lot of articles about how to market your indie game and how
to design marketing-friendly moments into the very fabric of your game.
In this talk, I want to question the unit of analysis that's so often assumed by these
articles that the goal is just to market your one game singular.
The argument I want to make is that thinking about just your one game might not actually
be ambitious enough.
To this point, I hope Sports Friends can provide
one example of thinking more broadly.
Also before I get into it, I do want to mention one big caveat for this entire talk.
I don't mean to suggest that commercial success should be necessarily your goal.
It is 100% absolutely fine and great to make a video game as a hobby or artistic practice
beyond the demands of the market.
Actually on this topic I recommend Robert Yang's recent post on reassessing what success
means in independent games.
And anyway, I hope this talk will be relevant to anyone trying to build an audience for
their work, commercial or not.
OK, Project Origins.
I don't think I can talk about the business of Sports Friends without telling you about
the cultural context in which it was conceived.
So let's go back to 2011.
At the beginning of this decade, as new ideas about indie games were coalescing, there was
a growing wave of public video game exhibitions organized by festivals and game collectives.
Just to name a few examples, I'm thinking of events like Indiecade in Los Angeles,
the GAMMA showcases run by Montreal collective Cocoromi,
Babycastles, a games and DIY art collective in New York City,
and lots more I won't have time to talk about today.
These public events gave indie devs like me opportunities to show games to live audiences
and motivated us to make new exhibition-friendly work suited to spectatorship.
In some cases, these events directly commissioned and funded game prototypes.
An example here is NYU's annual No Quarter exhibition, which still continues today.
In fact, two of the games in Sports Friends, Hokura and Barabari Ball, were originally
commissioned by No Quarter.
Hokura was commissioned in 2011 and Barabari Ball was commissioned in 2012.
There's a much longer history I could tell here,
but what I do want to convey is that in
2011 it felt like local multiplayer was important, that
it was being recognized, that it was on the
rise.
So while all of this is happening, I was
living in Copenhagen as a grad student, making my
own local multiplayer games.
Inspired by my work with the Copenhagen Game Collective,
I went to the 2011 Nordic Game Jam and
prototyped what would become Johann Sebastian Jauss.
After showing the game in the streets of Copenhagen in June 2011, I knew I was on to something
really, really fun.
I submitted the game to festivals and was fortunate enough to be able to show it at
events like IndieCade, Wild Rumpus, and the Independent Games Festival.
But I had no idea how I could ever release this game commercially.
For one thing, it only ran on Mac and needed multiple PlayStation Move controllers.
Like this weird controller that not many people owned, let alone have like six of them.
Meanwhile, in spring of 2011, I playtested an early build of Hokura that Ramiro had emailed
to me.
I had met Ramiro the year before in my travels exhibiting my games in Baby Castles in New
York.
Immediately, I loved Hokura, like the minute I played it.
It was kind of like Nintendo ice hockey, but for the 21st century and with a nice 2v2 dynamic.
And despite the difficult path to market, indie designers we knew kept making weird
sports games.
In September of 2011, I met Bennett Foddy, the maker of QWOP, at an exhibition we curated
at Baby Castles in New York.
At the event, we debuted Bennett's new 1v1 pole vaulting game, Pole Riders, the game
that would go on to become Super Pole Riders.
We had this growing feeling that there might somehow be a commercial path for our games,
even if we didn't yet see how.
Also, we saw a commercial release as a way to reach new audiences.
And that was always the main goal, anyway, getting more people to enjoy our games.
In 2012, after a lot of brainstorming, we decided to take some inspiration from sports
games compendiums like Epic's Summer Games and Wii Sports.
The hope was that if we could combine a handful of games into one package, we'd have enough
critical mass to motivate a full commercial release.
Three games felt like too small a number, so eventually we recruited Noah Sasso and
his sports-like fighting game, Bar Bari Ball.
And that was that.
We had a team, we had an idea, and we'd eventually
call the project Sports Friends, inspired by the German word
sportsfreunde, which is a real word, which is kind of great.
Fundraising.
So I want to talk a bit about the project logistics
to give you an idea of what making this kind of compendium
might entail.
Early on, we decided it would be important to release
Sports Friends on console.
Getting controllers to work on home computers
is a real pain, especially the move controllers.
And anyway, getting on console would expose us
to a much larger audience.
Throughout 2011 and 2012, I had already been talking
to Sony America about JS Joust, my game, which
they had played at IndieCade 2011 and some
other events.
I took the idea of Sports Friends to my
contacts at Sony, and eventually we ended up signing
a pub fund deal with them.
The PubFund program, at least our deal back in 2012,
isn't really upfront publishing money from Sony.
It's more a guarantee on a certain number of sales.
So for example, let's say you get $150,000 PubFund grant
from Sony in the 2012 era of these grants.
That means you get $150,000 from Sony right when you finish the game.
Then, the first $150,000 you make goes straight to Sony.
That arrangement means, even if your game bombs and, like,
fails to sell a single copy, you still make $150,000 guaranteed,
and Sony eats the loss.
For us, that guarantee was enough to reduce the risk
of making the project for console.
Also, I think importantly, PubFund is a commitment from Sony to help market your game, both explicitly and implicitly.
This kind of deal gives them an incentive to earn their money back.
we still needed to raise funds up front to make the game.
So we went to Kickstarter in late 2012.
We eventually met our goal of $150,000 with over 4,000 backers.
Of course, that simple summary doesn't really tell the full story.
Both Kickstarter and social media...
I want to caveat, have changed a lot, like a lot, a lot over the last four years.
So I don't think I can give you specific crowdfunding advice that's still relevant in 2018.
What I can tell you, though, is that even in 2012, $150,000 was a big ask.
Why did we set it at $150,000?
Well, the four of us got together, spent a long time
figuring out what we needed to make the game, and we calculated
we could get by with a minimum of $150,000.
We asked for what we needed, because the only thing worse
than failing to hit your target is just barely hitting a target
that's actually too low for you to finish the game.
We actually barely made this target, squeaking by on the final day, as you can see from this
graph here.
In retrospect, we did, like, a lot of things wrong.
Despite significant effort, we had trouble explaining such a complex project with so
many moving parts.
But we did have a few key advantages going for us, advantages that would serve us well
not just during the Kickstarter, but also upon release.
First and foremost, we owned a strong narrative about reclaiming local multiplayer and ushering
in a new golden age of in-person play.
All four Sports Friends games, whether motion-controlled or screen-based, excel at getting people together
in the same room, facilitating an enjoyable social experience for both players and spectators.
This angle really resonated not just with players, but also the press.
The narrative capitalized on latent interest in local multiplayer experiences that people
had growing up in the arcade and in the home, like four-player games on the Nintendo 64.
In fact, we really doubled down on this narrative.
We made it clear that Sports Friends would be local multiplayer
and local multiplayer only.
We deliberately said we wouldn't be adding any single player mode
or network multiplayer or AI or anything.
Here's an editorial Bennett wrote for Polygon on the topic at the time.
This choice was partly for technical reasons.
Network multiplayer wouldn't have worked with most of the four games.
We also limited scope for budget reasons.
Writing four different AI systems would have been too expensive
and networked multiplayer would be even worse.
Mostly, though, we just weren't interested in those features.
We wanted to get to the heart of the genre,
playing with other people in the same room
and cut all the cruft.
One big advantage we had, or another big advantage we had, was that the four of us had accumulated
different fan bases while touring our games around in 2011 and 2012.
For example, I had generated a passionate fan base for JSJoust after having shown the
game at events like PAX.
Here's a clip of the special 18-player version I ran at PAX Prime 2012.
Noah, by contrast, was able to build some interest in the fighting games community and
had shown Baro-Bari Ball at events like EVO in Las Vegas.
By coming together, the four of us were able to attract audiences we couldn't have reached
on our own.
In a sense, then, this section title of fundraising is a little misleading.
What I'm really talking about here is something like cultural legitimation.
That's to say we didn't just raise money for a project we wanted to make, we also built
a fan base and reassured ourselves that there was indeed enough public interest to justify
investing our time and our money into such a project in the first place.
Also importantly, the project benefited greatly from the renown of Bennett's virally infamous
browser game, QWOP.
With our Kickstarter campaign sagging and just days to go, we tried doing a Reddit AMA
in a last-ditch effort, and Bennett, who understands Reddit pretty well, was clever enough to frame
the AMA in terms of QWOP, the game everyone loves to hate.
Thank you, Bennett.
The AMA was a big success, and in fact, you can see on this graph, you can actually see
the slope of the contributions to our Kickstarter changing that same day that we do the AMA.
Of course, this data doesn't, like, prove that correlation is causation, but my guess
is that the AMA helped drum up a significant amount of awareness.
The broader, more useful lesson here is that Sports Friends didn't just arrive out of nowhere.
It was a project that built on years of prior games, experience, and brand building.
OK, so the project was funded, and now we actually
had to make the thing.
In late 2012, right as the Kickstarter happened,
I moved from Copenhagen to New York.
That was partly for family reasons,
but I also wanted to be near the other sports
friends during the production.
Even though I was technically the lead producer, all four
of us were extremely involved throughout the entire process.
Each of us retained final say over our own games,
but when the entire product was concerned,
we tried to make all our decisions unanimous.
Of course, that meant a lot more discussion time,
but I think in the end it was almost always worth it.
In retrospect, I think Sports Friends only worked
because the four of us got along so well.
That meant working on the game was usually enjoyable,
like even the more bureaucratic meetings.
I don't think we could have achieved
such a coherent final product
if we all hadn't been so invested.
There's a huge potential for big disagreements to sink a project like Sports Friends.
I think knowing that we were each the king of our own little domain,
like our own component games,
made it easier to listen to each other when we were discussing the larger product.
The compendium brought with it a natural structure, which is, I think, a really key point.
We hired two full programmers, partly because console development was too much
for the four of us to handle.
Our lead programmer was Jonathan Whiting, based in Oxford, England.
Oxford made sense because that's where Bennett was living before he moved to New York in 2013.
Jonathan worked on the core PSN code, the menus, and was responsible for the PC, Mac,
and Linux ports.
He also did the Super Pole Riders and JSJoust.
Our second programmer, Ed, came recommended by Romero, who had worked with him at a previous
job.
Ed was based in New Jersey, which meant that we could take the train down to work with
him in person when we needed to.
Ed worked on the core PSN code alongside Jonathan and took the lead on the PS4 specific code.
He also did the ports of Hokra and Bar Baribol.
Now, one of our major tasks was porting the four games into the same code base.
Kind of hilariously, all four of our prototypes were made using different technologies, so
Flash, XNA, GameMaker, and Unity, which is a little brutal.
At the time, Unity didn't seem quite so ready for console ports, and anyway, we didn't know
when the Unity team would support PS4.
So we ended up going with a proprietary C++ engine licensed to us by our friends at Choice
Provisions.
Beyond Jonathan and Ed, we had a large team of contractors and collaborators helping us
with different aspects of the project in different capacities.
To start with, each of the four of us had our own small team helping us with our game,
which I won't detail fully here.
We did hire a visual artist, Florian Sanger, to lead the visual design of the menus and
the branding.
And we hired Guta Fabrique's composer, Alessandro Coronas, to do the sound and music for the
menus.
Here's a mock-up from Florian for a tournament mode that never made it into the game.
As I see it, the most important work we did during the production was the menus and the
branding, bringing together all the games into one cohesive package.
The menus took up a huge amount of our time and effort, way more than porting of the games
themselves.
It's one thing to make a local multiplayer game that's fun,
but it's another thing entirely to make the whole experience feel smooth and professional,
to make it easy for players to enter and exit games,
create their own arenas like they can in the final version of Pokera,
change settings, and all that other stuff.
We also felt like we needed to distinguish ourselves from the many bundles that have
flooded the marketplace.
Don't get me wrong, I really like the Humble store and I think their bundles serve an important
role in the marketplace.
In fact, Sports Friends has actually been in a few Humble bundles.
But often bundle themes are like loose at best.
We were worried about people thinking that the Sports Friends games were low value or
that the quantity was making up for low quality somehow.
So in contrast to bundles, we wanted to create a more coherent narrative about what Sports
Friends was as a single product.
To that end, we hoped that the menus would give the project both a visual identity and
a conceptual identity, a whole greater than the sum of its proverbial parts.
This isn't something we can easily measure, but I do think the new visual identity helped
address some of the problems we had explaining the game during our Kickstarter campaign.
Now, with the final menus, you could see visually
that Sports Friends was one product immediately.
It was tangible.
We also put in this great Danielle Buttonberry quote
in the startup sequence
to emphasize our local multiplayer narrative.
Here, we were basically arguing
that the absence of single-player or online play
isn't a bug, it's a feature.
Okay, so here's some of the gory financial details
about the project.
The project cost us approximately $200,000 to make.
Our Kickstarter budget calculations actually turned out to be pretty accurate.
But midway during production, we decided to take on some extra costs to add PS4 support.
So when we had originally budgeted the game, we thought we were only doing PS3.
So that explains the extra $50,000, roughly.
I do want to note that this 200,000 number is kind of artificially low, because none
of the four main sports brands took any money during the production, myself included.
We were only paid in profit share after the release.
All four of us worked on the game in some kind of part-time capacity.
I was the most full-time of the four of us, but even I took a couple of contract jobs
during the production.
Beyond that, I subsisted on savings for my previous job,
and the other three sports friends had their own contract work or day jobs.
Here's a budget visualization I spat out from Google Docs.
The text is a little too small.
But to summarize, about two-thirds of our budget
went to our hired programs, by far our biggest cost.
The second biggest cost was visual design and sound,
which also covered the new redesign of JSJoust,
which now features beautiful graphics by Dom2D, a Canadian artist.
For the legal entity behind the game, we used the studio I co-own, The Gouda Fabrique, and
specifically we used a New York LLC that's a branch of Gouda Fabrique.
Note that the other three sports friends are not actually part of Gouda Fabrique.
So because Gouda Fabrique took on the legal risk, and because I did so much production
work leading the project, we split the profit shares five ways, where me and the three sports
friends each took 20%, and the company Gouda Fabrique took the extra fifth share.
It was important for all of us to feel like equals,
while still recognizing all the additional work
me and Guta Fabrique did.
Actually, it's a little bit more complicated than that.
We also gave shares to our programmers, Jonathan and Ed.
Although we paid them for their work up front,
we thought it was only fair for them to have some share of the profits,
especially given how much time they'd be spending on the project.
They spent a lot of time on the project.
OK, contracts.
We knew there was a big potential for this kind of project
to go really wrong.
Thankfully, it didn't, but there was always that potential.
So we wrote up a lengthy contract and even paid lawyers
to look over it.
This is going to be a little oversimplified, obviously,
but here's an overview of some of the general terms
of our contract, just as a suggestion of what
it might look like to structure one
of these kinds of compendiums.
So Bennett, Ramiro, and Noah all retained the IP to their games, so Gudefribik does
not own Hokra or Super Bowl Riders or Barabaribol.
They did grant Gutaforbric a license to sell specific versions of their IP in perpetuity.
So Gutaforbric is allowed to keep sports friends on the marketplace as long as they want.
And they agreed to one year of exclusivity of their IP following the initial PSN release.
So a year after that 2014 release, for example, if Noah wanted to go on and make Barra Barriball
2, he could have done that.
They agreed to a pretty specific schedule and feature set.
We all agreed to that profit sharing scheme that we spelled
out in extensive detail in the contracts.
And they were also given a minor financial stake
in the Sports Friends brand.
So if Gouda Fabrique was ever to use it again
in some new project, like a Sports Friends 2,
or say I made Gun Friends or whatever,
they would have had a small stake.
That's a joke.
I'm absolutely not going to make Gun Friends.
to be really clear. The contract also covered some failure cases. So, like, what would it
mean for the designers, like the other sports friends, to breach the agreement? What would
it mean for Agouti Fabrique or me to breach the agreement? And what would happen to the
profit shares if the agreement was somehow terminated? Luckily, we haven't had to deal
with any of this stuff, but it was really important for us to set all this kind of stuff
in stone. And if you're going to do this kind of project, I think it is really important
to have.
So, we'll have a link to that in a
moment.
And, of course, you can see that we have
all the legal contracts set pretty cleanly.
By the way, if there's any interest, I can
look into releasing this contract someday.
So, feel free to email me.
I'll put some of my contact information at the
end of the talk.
OK, sales.
So, when we undertook Sports Friends, we didn't know
how much money we'd make.
And that's why the pub fund guarantee on sales
was so important for us.
Like, this was a weird and risky project.
It was quite possible in our minds that we
would make hardly any money.
So in the end, like to date, we've made roughly like $900,000 in net revenue.
Like that's the money that has come into our bank account, not gross revenue, which is
like a little bit more complicated for me to try to calculate, so I didn't.
This amount hugely exceeds our expectations, so we're obviously really kind of happy and
proud about that.
But so you think about the budget was $200,000.
So in reality, that's something like $700,000 in
profit so far.
So, figuring out, figuring like my, for example, 18.5% split over two years of unpaid work,
that's about like $65,000 per year before taxes, which is great.
I personally also took some of the Gouda Fabrique share and then put the rest back into our
future company projects.
Again, to be clear, we're like super happy with this amount, but you should note that
all four of us are still doing day jobs, right?
It's a lot of money, but split a whole
bunch of different ways.
By the way, this amount includes the Kickstarter money
we earned and a PS Plus deal that we
did. The vast majority of the sales were on
PS4 as opposed to on home computers. Like, the
vast majority of the sales. And we still enjoy
a pretty long tail of sales, which is, which
is great.
I think two things that probably helped us a lot was one, buy-in from Sony America, who
were invested in featuring our game, and two, we were pretty early in the PS4 life cycle,
which I think counted for quite a lot.
Okay, so making this compendium worked out pretty well for us, and clearly I'm a big
believer in the whole idea of compendiums as a way to do deep collaboration.
Sports Friends succeeded because it wasn't just a collection of random multiplayer games.
It was a project very visibly on the forefront of bringing back local multiplayer.
But thinking beyond Sports Friends itself, I want to offer a little provocation about
what the future of collaboration could look like in video games.
I've been talking about building something bigger than just your one game or even your
one studio, but in some ways that idea is kind of already well explored.
For example, I'm pretty inspired by the Rusty Lake studio.
It's a Dutch duo who make surrealistic adventure puzzle games,
all orbiting the same fictional universe.
I really recommend taking a look at these.
The series began in 2015 and already includes nine free-to-play games,
which are called the Cube Escape games,
and three larger premium games, the Rusty Lake games.
I also want to clarify these games are not the same things as episodes, like episodic
releases of one larger story arc.
Each game is playable on its own, apart from the rest of the series.
And yet, all the games connect in direct and indirect ways.
In an interview with the Itch.io blog, the series creators talk about the inspiration
behind the series.
And I want to read this one quote from that interview.
So they say, we were inspired by Twin Peaks and wanted to create a similar surreal world
where our games could take place and connect with each other.
It was back in April 2015 when we launched Cube Escape The Lake and Seasons, the first
two entries in the Rusty Lake universe.
Both games were connected and with a code you could use in one of the games that gave
a different ending.
It made people feel like these games were part of something bigger.
And so what I find so inspiring about this is that Rusty Lake isn't just a studio making
multiple games.
They're making games and servers of a larger, coherent experience with multiple entry points
such that each game leads players to all the other entries.
So the twist I'm suggesting in this talk
is that that kind of multiple entry points or larger
narrative can also be built more heterogeneously
across different studios, different designers,
different projects.
You see sports friends on the screen here.
For years, I've called myself an independent game developer,
but we might reassess how independent we really even want to be.
Barring a term from Bart Simon and the research he and his team have done
studying the economics of the indie megabooth,
maybe we could pivot from the more familiar indie game design label
to a kind of interdependy game design.
OK, like maybe not such a catchy term, but hopefully you get what I mean.
By the way, that research project about the Indie Megabooth called Indie Interfaces is
a really useful sociological look at collaboration and culture building in indie games.
It was one of the inspirations behind this talk, and you can check out their research
on their website, which I recommend.
Back to thinking about sports friends and what future sports friends-like projects might
look like, something I think about all the time is what are the record labels of video
games, and what could they be?
In music, one of my personal favorite labels is Warp Records.
In the 90s, warp became almost synonymous with a certain ilk
of electronic music.
If you bought a warp album back then,
you knew you'd get an album of heady, high quality
electronic music, even if you'd never heard
of the particular artist before.
Now, when I talk about this with colleagues, they often suggest that indie publishers like
Devolver are already providing the record labels of video games.
And I think this is partially right.
Clearly, Devolver has a coherent aesthetic identity, a really strong social media presence,
and a dedicated fan base.
But we might also imagine a more bottom-up structure,
where fellow creators come together
in more complicated artist-run arrangements,
as opposed to the more familiar top-down paradigm
of a publisher giving money and or marketing support.
So in that sense, maybe traditional record labels
like Warp aren't actually the best example here.
Maybe we can find more cooperative models.
One useful example that blurs the line between indie publisher and developer is Wadjet Eye
Games in New York, who make old school adventure games and also use their expertise and fan
base to publish similar games made by other developers.
Old school adventure games aren't so mainstream these days, sure, but they don't need to be
super trendy as long as Wadjet Eye can establish a niche and find their fans.
I'd also point to artist-owned studios and game collectives who bring together like-minded
work with similar aesthetics.
A good example here is Co-op in Montreal.
So they work on their own games like PS4 game Nog, but they also produce other people's
games like Gardenarium.
Check out their website, which I think does a nice job conveying the creative identity
that binds their games together.
So let's think about Sports Friends again.
I sometimes wonder what it would mean to give a project
like Sports Friends more life beyond just the initial release.
So imagine, if you will, turning Sports Friends
into its own platform, releasing a steady stream
of weird new sports games through the same application
over time, say one or two new games a year.
My ideas are still like a little half-baked, but let me at least propose two different
approaches we might take.
So the first approach is more ambitious and requires more coordination.
So we'd add new games to the existing Sports Friends executable and charge something like
in-app purchases or a yearly subscription.
The main menu would feature a news feed announcing new additions to Sports Friends.
So possibly maybe we'd even like help pay for the porting and console release and offer our
expertise working through certification. And depending on the business model, we'd have to
figure out some kind of new fair rev split between all the game's designers, acknowledging the value
that the new games are bringing to the project. And really importantly, I think all new inductees
would then become official sports friends and would get an equal say in deciding which games
were added in the future.
So, OK, a second approach, which is a little less coordinated,
so maybe also a bit more feasible.
All the new games would be separate downloads, separate purchases,
and whatever technology, so they wouldn't require any porting.
Maybe we'd specify some platform constraints, like all the games
must be for PS4 and or Steam or whatever.
All the Sports Friends games would include some kind of visual logo on their main menu
and link to the other Sports Friends games, like ideally in-app, maybe through some standardized
menu.
In this arrangement, maybe we don't even need to give funding or financial support at all.
The onus would be on the developer themselves to release their game, but the appeal is that
they'd still get to join a tightly curated collection with an existing fan base.
And of course, you'd still have the new inductees join the Sports Friends Council and help decide
which games get added in the future.
In either case, the strategic logic of that Sports Friends as platform idea is something
like this.
Importantly, we commit to a coherent, communicable idea.
So in this case, local multiplayer and weird alternative sports games.
We'd be pretty choosy about which games we'd add and release only, say, one game a year at a regular time.
The hope here is that we would be able to set regular expectations.
You'd want the fanbase to look forward to the new Sports Friends game of the calendar year.
And of course, we develop a coherent online and social media presence, a place for fans
to stay updated about the platform.
Finally, as I suggested in approach number two, a cooperative might not even need liquid
financial capital to make this idea work.
All you really need is a group of friends and colleagues coordinating their different
releases in a smart, branded, well-planned way.
I'm not sure if this is a good idea, by the way, for Sports Friends specifically, and
to be clear, none of the four of us were interested in pursuing such a project.
But I suspect that other compendiums could really make this general idea work.
Cross-promotion is certainly not a new idea, but I'd love to see more indies running with
it, taking it in new, more tightly coordinated directions.
Actually, maybe promotion is too limited of a noun here.
What I'm talking about is creating a narrative,
becoming part of something larger than yourself.
In the current attention economy,
I think there's something really valuable
to be gained by thinking bigger
than trying to build just one great game.
I know this sounds like a little over the top,
but it's worth considering how you might build
a larger cultural movement.
The question here is, how can your one isolated game
be connected to something larger?
For us making sports friends, this was pushing the zeitgeist of local multiplayer.
For you, this will almost certainly be something totally different.
Now, I wish I could give you, like, a recipe for how to build that movement or collaboration,
but the power in this idea is precisely in charting new terrain and trying new arrangements.
I do think sports friends offers some valuable hints and inspirations, but any structure
you try to build will need to be tailored to your context, moment, and genre.
Finally, beyond business concerns, there are also political reasons to pursue radical
collaborations.
One thing that's a little obvious from all the photos I've been showing is how all four
of us sports friends and all of our main collaborators were men.
It doesn't have to be that way.
Just like how Sports Friends gave the four of us access to a commercial platform, we
couldn't have feasibly reached on our own, I think these kinds of collaborative structures
could also be used to give professional opportunities and visibility to more marginalized voices.
Just as one small, recent example, local to me, I'd point to the all-women Australian
collective Blushbox, who make and promote games about sex and romance.
It isn't easy to get your game on console, especially for newcomers to the industry,
but as we learned making Sports Friends, there is definitely a power in numbers.
For example, I don't think I would have been able to launch JS Joust by itself on PS4,
even with one-fourth of the Sports Friends budget.
It was the larger scale of the Sports Friends project,
the four games together, that made the funding and logistics
possible.
Applying collaborative structures more broadly,
we might wonder what other non-traditional games
and whose games might we be able to get
onto highly visible platforms.
OK, so let's end this thing.
Some final takeaways I want to emphasize.
Take away one, Sports Friends wasn't just an idea
that we pulled out of thin air. It tapped into
particular trends. So, right place, right time. Sports Friends
was very much a product of its, like I
just said, of its place in time. It was
conceived somewhat organically, gradually, over a period of two
years.
Again, I think the trick here is to shift the unit of your thinking from just your one
video game to broader cultural narratives.
I don't think anyone can force a cultural movement.
A zeitgeist is something you identify, feed off of, and amplify.
That takes time and isn't the same thing as just trying to cash in on a hot new trend.
Takeaway number two.
As much as possible, we try to go all in on our central narrative.
Again, think about the Danielle Buttonberry quote in our boot sequence.
Rather than shy away from the shortcoming of having no single player or online play,
we fully embraced that identity.
Take away three, narratives aren't just for the public and your potential consumers, they're
also for publishers and platform holders.
So here's a photo of me and Nick Suttner, who was then one of the main indie dev outreach
guys at Sony America.
Sports Friends could not have happened without his enthusiasm or without the help of other
Sony folks like Brian Silva or Adam Boyes.
The fact that Nick so enthusiastically bought into the idea of local multiplayer
was a good sign that we were on to something and that the project was worth pursuing on console.
Takeaway number four, crafting new narratives is actually really hard and describing complex
projects like this is pretty tricky.
Again, think about our Kickstarter campaign and the trouble we had packaging the idea
of the project.
So it's easy for me to stand here and sing the praises of radically collaborative projects,
but they often come with a huge amount of work nailing your narrative and explaining
the project to the public.
This takes time.
Sometimes the public just has to sit with the concept for a while before they really
get it.
That said, it's precisely that difficulty that makes such an idea worth pursuing.
If the narrative were easy, someone probably would have done it before.
Takeaway five, team chemistry is everything.
I've been talking a lot about the narrative
of local multiplayer and how sports friends
with the right project at the right time,
but all of that was only possible
because the four of us got along so well
and we're so excited to work with each other.
And that's not just true of the core team, but also of our programmers, Jonathan and Ed, and all of our other collaborators.
All that is to say, I'd be careful not to force a collaboration.
But if you can find a great group of people who are all hungry to work together, you're definitely on the right path.
Takeaway number six, get involved.
Put yourself out there.
These kinds of collaborations don't happen overnight.
They happen gradually.
Here's a screenshot, actually, from the time
we video called Ramiro right after trying
Hochra for the first time.
Thank you, Brandon Boyer, for the screenshot.
If I hadn't exhibited my games at Baby Castles in New York
in 2010, I don't think I would have ever met Ramiro,
and Sports Friends probably would never have happened.
And it's not like we came up with the idea
for Sports Friends the first time I met Ramiro.
That happened slowly over time as I got to
know him and his work and, and the other
Sports Friends.
OK, so, final caveat.
Yeah, listen, this game is pretty old at this
point.
So this, this talk is not a how-to guide.
2018 is a very different climate for local multiplayer,
and this is not a project that we could
easily do today, at least not in the same
form.
Still, if you're feeling alone in the world
of game dev or intimidated by the torrent of
new releases on Steam or whatever platform, I might
suggest consider finding new forms of collaborations, collaborations that make
sense for you, and try to build something bigger
than just your one studio or your one game.
Yeah, that's about it.
Thank you.
I thought I'd go longer, but so we do have time for questions.
So if you do have any questions, great.
If not, that's okay too.
Hey, thanks for the talk.
I just wanted to know, like, because everything seemed to come together quite organically.
How did you manage, once you sort of kicked it into a gear and realized what you were trying to do,
how did you manage everybody's time and the differences of where people were up to with their projects and deadlines
and just communication in general between the team?
I think we were lucky in that all the games were already really playable, and we knew
all four games were good, they were playable when we started the project.
So in that sense, managing...
We all had to polish our games, but it wasn't that much polish.
So managing the four main sports friends finishing their games was never really a big concern.
It was more just the like...
polish and the porting details, which is kind of them like managing a regular project.
So I think this would be much harder if the games were in like various different states
of completion.
So in that sense, we were already had the momentum of four games that were like showable
and playable.
That answers your question.
Yeah, cool.
You may have been asked this before, but why were the secret games kept secret?
And did that have any sort of effect on like the profit sharing conversations?
It did. So actually, the profit sharing slide I showed you is a little bit of a lie.
We gave Bennett a few more profit sharing percentages for the Secret Games.
I think this is, in fact, Bennett's in the audience, so he could probably tell you.
For us, I think it was like a labor of love.
Like, it was never even planned.
Like, one day, Bennett was like,
you know, I want to make this secret game.
And so I think that spoke to the kind of, like,
enthusiasm in the project,
like people just doing stuff for fun
because they were geeked about local multiplayer.
So those two secret games kind of came about,
like, weirdly and surprisingly.
But, yeah, we did.
I didn't want to get into the extra detail.
But, yeah, the profit-sharing scheme
is a little bit more complicated.
And we did compensate Bennett a little bit more for that.
Okay, cool. Thanks.
Hi, that was great.
Can you just talk a little bit more about,
you mentioned that 2018 is really different right now.
So can you talk a little bit more about how
local multiplayer, how you think about that right now
versus when you started working on the project?
So I've had this discussion a lot,
actually with the House House guys
who are here in the audience
who made a great local multiplayer game, Push Me Pull You.
I think local multiplayer is a tricky beast because people find their one local multiplayer
game that they love playing with their friends, and there are other ones out there of the
same era, right?
Like Tower Fall, Samurai Gun, Gang Beasts, whatever.
And it's something about the replayability of those games where you'll keep coming back
to them, so you might have less space in your social time for new things to try.
So that potentially, I worry, crowds out the ecosystem of local multiplayer.
So to some extent, I think.
Now, in terms of co-located play and video games, more generally, in 2018, I'm really
excited by cooperative games.
So Overcooked is a super good example of this, and that is a deeply underserved genre.
Someone should absolutely go make cooperative friends, or whatever you want to call it.
They would slam it out of the park, for sure.
So I think...
Not that like...
I don't know.
I don't mean to glorify cooperation over competition in games.
That's often a false binary that's evoked.
But right now, I think that particular mode of co-located couch play is a little underrepresented.
So I would absolutely love to see cooperation friends or whatever it is.
Yeah, for sure.
It's great you say that because a bunch of friends of mine are working on a bunch of
similar co-op games.
Yes.
And I floated to them a similar kind of compendium idea.
And a lot of us have a couple irons in the fire, very few of us have released games before,
so it's pretty difficult to, as much as everyone loves the idea, to commit to giving up your
potential to one quarter or one fraction of a potential.
So when you guys were putting this together, it's gone organically, but where was that
moment where everybody kind of got...
the full sort of like, OK, this is the way this will take,
rather than me continuing to develop and releasing on my own.
Was it a difficult conversation?
No.
And almost the opposite, where me and Ramiro had no idea.
We were just like, we're never going
to be able to sell our games.
It's going to be impossible.
Hooker requires four controllers.
You can't sell that.
So for us, it was more like, uh.
Even convincing ourselves that we could sell it in the first place.
I'm trying to think of what else I would say.
I think it helped a lot that all four of us had showed our games at festivals.
And so, like, you mentioned, you know, being somewhat more of an unknown.
And that gets to my point where this took time.
It wasn't like we had our games and then just did it overnight.
We were lucky enough to get our games into smaller, large festivals.
And so to someone, for example, making co-op or friends or whatever, like, if those individual
games can speak for themselves at whatever local or global events, I think that's the
kind of sign, OK, we're onto something.
This is worth pursuing further.
So that's, I think, maybe.
And also, there was maybe some amount of equitable attention
on the four games.
All four of them had kind of made it to cool festivals.
So we didn't feel like necessarily one of the games
was way less popular than the other three,
and that wasn't fair to the four of us.
It was also, and I guess that's also what I mean
by don't force collaborations.
We found four people who were kind of in the same place
in their career.
and that made it feel really fair to split the profits equally.
And you said that you don't think you could have released The Origin of Chess on its own.
No.
So it seems like you found that right balance almost by happenstance with the four of you.
You all believed in your projects, but also believed you couldn't sell them on their own.
Yeah, but I think that's a special case.
I think even if you believed you could sell your, let's just say, cooperative game...
over cooked, like whatever, undercooked. I don't know.
You maybe could sell it on your own. I still think there's something to be said to momentum scale.
And that, like, unless your game is as right time right place is overcooked I...
there's probably some other conceptual addition there that you would
have to work out. So not just like,
yep, we made four co-op games, I guess you can
get them, and like what is, there's like some
other special spice, like whether that's all games for romantic
pairs, right. Like that's suddenly like a more coherent.
So, you know, all weird 3D, some aesthetic style that binds things together.
So I don't know, but I think all four people have to kind of sniff out that, like, the
momentum we can generate together is going to outweigh my game just being lost in the
bajillion games that are released on Steam every single minute or whatever.
Next.
Yeah.
We have one more question.
Hey.
Just a historical question.
Like, were any of the Sports Friends
sold separately at any point, like in their lifetimes,
either before or after the game?
And two, did the release of Sports Friends
end their festival circuits?
Like, was that kind of the cap on showing them publicly?
Great questions.
The games were never sold, but it's a little bit more complicated than that.
So JS Joust was part, in 2011, of a Kickstarter reward for Brandon Boyer's Venus Patrol Kickstarter,
which actually ended up working pretty well because it was like a little bit of guerrilla
marketing.
There was this like crew, this select crew of people, enthusiasts who had funded Brandon's
Kickstarter, who then got the build of JS Joust.
So there was...
Some of these games were leaking out into indie circles, which I think helped start
that buzz.
So it was kind of like an organic lifting-off process.
But no, we weren't selling them.
Bennett's game, the original version of Pole Riders, which is a little different than Super
Pole Riders, was available in Flash free on his website.
So that, again, is this kind of leaking out into the world.
But again, Super Pole Riders totally changes the graphics, adds four players, and makes
the game quite different.
The second question is, so you're saying when we were funding on Kickstarter or when we
released the game?
OK, so the question is, do we still show at festivals
now we've released the game?
Kind of.
JS Joust will still appear.
For example, at MagFest in DC, they show it every winter.
I try to go when I can to run it.
I've heard of some of these other games being played.
Like, not in the same way.
And we're not paying, for example, for a PAX booth
anymore.
If we were to do Sports Friends the platform, I think we probably actually still could be running
like Barabari ball tournaments at a booth at PAX along with whatever the new Sports Friends game is of the year.
So I think if we were to do that platform, we could keep digging back into our back catalog
in interesting ways in concert with the new games, I think in a very productive relationship.
But all four of us have day jobs that I think we like, so that's...
That's why it hasn't happened, but I do think we could have done something like that.
In that case, we would be still going to PAX every year to show both the new games and
the old games.
It's not a specific question, but I was wondering if you could talk more towards this idea of
using the compendium to boost more marginalized voices?
Yeah.
Because it's incredibly interesting and I think sort of necessary.
Right.
Do you have anything more to say on that?
of a leading question. Thank you. Yeah, no, I'm not sure how much there is to say, but
there's definitely, for example, I live in Melbourne and there's a crew of us who are
interested in exploring some of these ideas. So what does it mean to get a whole local
community making games together? And I think there's something powerful.
In fact, I was just answering another question.
In the case of Sports Friends, all four of us
were in a similar stage in our professional careers.
But I think you could also do it some way where
you were mixing old experienced voices with less experienced
voices, whether that was on different games
or potentially working together on the same game.
So that kind of knowledge transferred,
social capital transfers.
I think there are totally different ways to do it.
And that could be everything from a community art project
to a really commercially focused title that's funded by an indie publisher or whatever.
But it's something I personally am looking to continue working on in the future when I'm kind of done with my current projects.
What is that next version of Sports Friends that's appropriate for 2019 or 20 or whatever the year it is?
Unlike Sports Friends, how can we bring in more people in interesting ways?
So put people on PS4 who have never been on PS4 before.
Get an artist who's never, you know, worked on a video game before.
And I think there's something also about the compendium structure, too,
where it's easy to slot in heterogeneously.
different minigames of different visual styles.
So that, like, the structure itself of the compendium
or the metagame or the party game is kind of naturally,
I feel like, is a kind of plurality of heterogeneous voices in and of itself.
So I think it almost naturally lends itself to that kind of...
political art project.
So fingers crossed that we'll see more of this,
whether that's from me or somebody else.
But yeah, for sure, this still remains
one of my main interests, which is
why I'm talking about it so many years later.
I think we're wrapping up.
But thank you, everyone, for attending.
I'll be out in the hall if you want to talk more.
Thank you.