Welcome everyone. We'd like to get started on our talk today. This is our How to Run Your Own
Career Fair on a Tiny Budget. We are the IGDA Los Angeles chapter. For context here, of course,
IGDA is a non-profit. We know we're coming from a big city, but our focus here today isn't just
telling you about what we did in LA. It's trying to figure out how we can adapt this so it can
work for more places. We'd like to help you run a career fair, whether it's at your college,
whether it's at your local IGDA chapter.
Or maybe you run your own meetups, jams,
other kinds of events.
We'd like you to be able to add this to your repertoire
of things you can do to serve your community.
And so where possible,
try to acknowledge some differences of LA
compared to some other spaces.
The one other note is that the context
we were inspired to do this by was the mass layoffs
about a year, year and a half ago in Los Angeles.
And so that colored a few of our decisions.
We'll kind of mention where that's relevant
in a few places.
At our high level, you can see here our agenda.
We're gonna talk about, we're gonna introduce ourselves.
We're going to kind of give an overview of the event.
We'll talk about some of the challenges or constraints
that came from our our venue and other factors, our time frame.
Talk about what worked, what didn't, major challenges, feedback.
And of course, we're hoping we'd have this as a live discussion at GDC.
We'll find some way to receive your inputs and share your stories.
Some discussion questions like to talk about as a group and closing remarks.
And here's where you can find our chapter online.
We are on all of the medias.
You can find us on Facebook, Twitter, YouTube, Twitch and LinkedIn.
I'm the chair of IGLA this year.
I'm Chris DeLeon.
I'm the founder of Home Team Game Dev,
a worldwide group where people build games together
for practice.
If they have questions, they work with me
or one of my trainers for help.
Outside of that, I'm also our alumni chair for IndieCade.
And I'm David Mullick.
I'm secretary on the LA chapter.
And currently, I am an adjunct professor
of game design at the Art Center College of Design.
And I'm also director of development at C Design.
And I'm Drew Erich. I run a small work for hire and consulting shop that's focused on online games called Game Breaking Studios.
My name is Tiffany Otto. I work full time with Indiecade and I'm IGDA LA's treasurer.
I work from the business side of things, not the development side of things.
Our event was a career fair.
We have a video we'll share for it to kind of a little highlight walkthrough just so you can see and visualize what we're talking about for the rest of the talk.
We'll switch to that video.
We're here at Industrious Century City where we'll be hosting our recruiting event today.
First we're going to check in here with our lovely Drew and our volunteer Quasar.
Coming through, over here on our left, we're going to have a lovely snack assortment
and Spatial And, Walmart's experimental virtual reality unit.
As you can see, we have areas where our members can hang out, chat,
and see if they want to start something together.
Moving down this way, we can see that we have individual tables for recruiters to sit at
and see if there's candidates that match up with them.
To our left, we have the Indie Matching area, also known as the Indie Jumble Room, where
candidates who have an interest in indie games or creating a new property can see where their
skills can interact.
We have representatives from WB Games, Acapara Games, and Servios down this hallway.
You'll see that we have a ton of lines, and that's actually because we had a really long waitlist for this event.
And if you follow me back this way, we can head over to the other side of the beautiful Industrious space.
Industrious is an amazing co-working space that tends to skew a little older and a little more diverse,
which matches up with our pillars of inclusivity and diversity for IGDA corporate.
We have a lovely backdrop for taking photos later.
And if you follow us through the elevator bank,
we'll get to the main conference rooms
where recruiters who brought three or more representatives
have been assigned spaces.
These two tables are listed as conversation nooks
for some of our more indie studios.
We have Fox Next Games in this room
as well as Network in this one.
In addition, we have TBA Games Inc.
and this is our war room for IGDA LA
where our board members can hang out
and sort of handle everything.
This room is a soundproof phone room where Java from DeWitt Street Accounting is giving one-on-one personal accounting consultations.
In addition, we have other conference rooms and conversation nooks where bigger studios such as PlayStation and Respawn can have a more casual situation.
So that's basically what we've done with the Industrious Faith, and we're hoping we can continue this partnership with them because they have several locations in the LA area and they're all amazing.
Yeah, so I was the events chair at the time that we
Started this event planned it and executed it which means I was the point person
So when you're making your own event, you need to have a point person. Let's start with that
But what I learned in that process was there's a lot of requirements as dictated by the event,
and every event space you find will have these kind of constraints. They might not look identical
to ours, but they are going to be there. For example, we could not come in early to prepare.
This was okay for us because we didn't need too much setup. But as you'll see later in our
challenges, there actually were a couple issues that came from not being able to come in too early.
I, as the chair, visited twice and I had a 20-chain email before I actually... I mean
a 20-email chain before I actually got a signed contract out of it. And the paperwork was
extensive because we did have HQ involved. And by that, I mean IGDA HQ because we're
an international organization.
So Industrious got 10 minutes to speak to the attendees ahead of time. We gave them
a mic in a shared space when we had the first...
50 or 60 people in. And it's a pretty standard thank you for hosting the event. It's a chance
to advertise. So we got our event for free, but free is free. And what that means is we
had to have several agreements with them, such as a credit agreement and a social media agreement.
Often, your space, if they're donating it regardless of your nonprofit status,
they'll want their collateral in the major space.
Industrial signage had to be prominent in all of our marketing materials,
as well as things such as name tags, signage.
And when we put the video together later, we had to show their logo quite a bit.
In addition,
Industrious offered five days of free co-working on a postcard, and everyone was going to receive
that in their gift at the end. They did end up distributing that via email later.
We ended up not printing out the collateral because we just didn't have time. There was
enough bandwidth on our team at that time. But physical stuff is important. Digital stuff is
hard to redeem. No one actually redeems the digital. We highly recommend physical envelopes
that people can take home later.
Gifts help our partners, the people that partner with you, whether you get a big sponsor such
as Amazon or if you get a local sponsor such as a catering place, having them put small
gift certificates as a form of PR and marketing so you can add value to your non-paying sponsors
and get them to give you in-kind donations even without a 501c3 or 501c6 space.
So thank you.
For example, Jaga, the accountant who runs DeWitt Street, LLC, he does the accounting
consultations.
I hate to say this phrase, but exposure was his main value add there.
He actually ended up getting multiple people calling him from that event.
He used specialty business cards that were printed in a different style so that when
he asked people how they heard of him, they actually referenced our event.
He got paying work out of it and, to quote him, that paid for me getting the cards printed
and coming to the event.
Talk to your sponsors and your partners about what their goals and values are,
because that'll help you craft something that's necessary for them as opposed to you.
Part of why a co-working space was such a great fit as to appeal is that IGDA necessarily
is bringing in a bunch of people, many of whom are freelance people who do development
and might use a co-working space, new companies getting started who might use that as a stepping
stone towards an office, and very much that we could potentially say, hey, we're going
to bring you dozens of people who will get to know your space, your parking, your environment,
your location in the city, help make that a value add to them to offer the space for
free.
It was a good match.
And if you want to make it even more polished and professional,
one thing we actually did is on our entry survey
when people signed up to attend the career fair,
there was a yes no question.
I'm interested in hearing more about coworking.
And everyone who clicked yes on that.
We curated it into a list and gave to Industrious as part of our agreement.
We'll talk more about privacy agreements later, but everyone knew exactly what
they were signing up for when they checked that box.
That was a real value add for Industrious because for them, it was warm leads of
people who already were interested in coworking.
A customized value add.
This is how you look more professional, even if you can't pay for things.
Going on to the venue budget, one of my coworkers will talk about that.
I think the general theme here is working with the venue.
There's a lot of different things that we did.
to try and make sure that we were meeting their needs, meeting our attendees needs.
So some of the constraints that I think we mentioned some of them already, they wanted
to make sure that they didn't have too many people in the space.
They're obviously for venues like that, especially in LA, they can get a lot of money to have
an event of a certain size.
So there's a bunch of different things that we had to consider and ended up needing to
cap the amount of people that we let in, things like that.
And we ended up with a wait list.
There are a lot of other options that we could have taken here, though, that I
definitely would think about next time about rolling people in over time.
Could we potentially have two different start times for different groups of
people so that we can keep the event to have under fire code and all of these
things, just different ways to kind of work with within different strengths
like that. A great framing exercise to use is this is a free career fair. All
you have to pay is this one email that you're going to get from our venue. Is
that okay with you? And I think
Nobody likes to get spam, but if you look about the cost value
trade off there of one email versus getting to have a
potential career opportunity, that feels pretty strong to
people. And then there's a number of other constraints in
there as well, like the timing and like at what time can we be
in the venue and for how long. All these things, you know, we
just kind of looked at and tried to do our best with LA traffic.
How do we start the venue late enough, but not too late so that
there's still staff on site at the at the venue and things like
that.
I think the thing to keep in mind, right, is especially for a game industry career fair,
a lot of people who are going to game industry career fairs, it's not that they don't have
a job, it's that they're trying to shift into a game industry job.
And so because of that, it's not like, oh, I can do it the middle of the day, their time
is necessarily flexible.
We were trying to account for enough time, they could get out of their work, they could
get home, they could change into their nice clothes, get their business cards, still make
it out.
And one of our concerns we're always on the lookout for, well, you don't want your event to skew too late.
At the same time, if you do it too close to the end of the workday, people will look at that and say,
I would miss the whole first 45 minutes or I would only get the tail end of it.
I'm just going to skip it. And so those kind of logistics are part of our factoring in there,
alongside, of course, the venues constraints of when we could be allowed in.
As the treasurer, one thing I don't know if we've made clear yet is
we ran this off an impact grant from headquarters.
IGDA HQ has a program where if you're doing something that positively impacts the local game dev community,
and they have a list on their website that's very clear, it's very simple,
we have to positively impact the community with this money.
And that's how we got the money to run this. This was not a free event to run.
A lot of people told us, well, it should be easy to run a free event, get people to donate stuff.
And you'd be surprised at how difficult that was. We did have to take on exterior funding.
It can still be a low budget, but a no budget seems unlikely to really, for that matter,
meet people's needs of pulling off a professional seeming event.
Some things that did work great for us.
I was really curious, David, your takes on the ways that...
Your connection to a lot of the studios who showed up in terms of
the people you reached out to, how they were able to make it.
Can you speak a bit to that process, what those communications were like?
One thing that's really helpful is to have a lot of connections in the game industry.
Even before you think about...
Thinking about running a game fair, just for you personally, it helps to know as many people as
possible. And one thing that I've always done is try to make contact with all the recruiters in
the game industry, with all the executive recruiters that work independently, as well
as with all the recruiters that work on each of the different studios.
So when we started talking about having a job fair, what I did was go through all my contacts
that I had already made long ago and gone to each of them to find out if they were
interested in participating. So that sort of preparation that I had done just in case
I'd ever come a time where I was employed, I already had people to reach out to,
that gave me preparation for this career fair.
being able to reach out to people that we can invite to appear and be vendors at our
game period to help out other people.
I went and started contacting them a few weeks ahead of the event, and one thing that I discovered
that would have worked better is if we had established a date even sooner.
As different venues we looked at became available, and then it turns out we couldn't use that
the date kept switching. So that made it hard to arrange recruiters to come in and studios to come
in. We were able to give like four weeks notice. Most of the people I talked to were actually very
interested in showing up. I think recruiters do like having opportunities to go and meet people
because that's really what they're in the business for, to go to find out possible people to
to join their companies. So they do look forward to having events like this.
A couple things I think we maybe didn't even organize until afterwards, realizing each of us
in the IGDLA board have different connections to industry, and we kind of built out a spreadsheet
of who knows people at which places in the area. And even that's become a useful resource to us
for future kind of things to realize, okay, well, we need some people who are
VR in the area or AAA or indie or otherwise in the area.
kind of realizing just how useful it is.
And that's the thing where if some people who are watching this talk are like,
well, I don't have those connections.
This sounds like an easy cop out for IGD people to say, go to your IGDA events.
There are chapters all over the place,
and there's necessarily a congregation of people who have different connections.
The Venn diagram of which might surprise you of just how many different places
someone can find somebody who, again, these recruiters,
when you can invite them to these kind of events,
it's doing their companies a favor in terms of they want to find people
who are looking for work or a good match for them.
And you're helping make that match happen.
really helpful for making connections is LinkedIn. You can
go in on LinkedIn and find the in-house recruiters working at
just about every given studio. And I've not met one recruiter
online that wasn't more than willing to accept my LinkedIn
connection. So that's that's part of how I build up my own
network.
Yeah, their job is almost accepting LinkedIn connections
every time.
Which is actually so building off of what David said, we did
have a bit of a chicken and egg problem. People and companies
only wanted to show up.
if there were people they expected to have a positive impact or that they wanted to impress
on the thing. So what we were like, Hey, studio name, do you want to be at our career fair?
Like, well, how many mid-grade engineers do you have? And I'm like,
I can get back to you with that. And then when we started advertising a career fair,
we didn't really hit the high end of that curve of signups until we started putting
known entities and like names people had heard of.
whether that was a local, you know, local Indies that everyone had heard of, or
AAA studios on the list. As soon as we dropped two AAA names on the list,
like our Eventbrite just got loaded out. So that's a chicken and egg problem.
And this is where we say like collab with the local IGDA chapter.
If I can speak to, there's a point in there too,
and maybe it sounds obvious and said out loud,
is basically if you have some friends,
some places that you're more connected to
that you can ask first and get some yeses first,
it's very tough to get people
to be the first person to a party.
If you have a little bit of traction,
we have three other students who've said yes,
we have four other students who've said yes,
it's that much easier for someone to see like,
oh, this is a legitimate thing, people will be there,
it's happening.
So it's before you approach the strangers
who just, you only met on LinkedIn yet,
it's useful to first try to leverage what you can
from your in-persons.
Connections through however you're finding a yeah and david made a really good point about being able to parse the data of early attendees to invite companies of different sizes if you realize you're getting like.
A bunch of mid level audio guys responding then you start targeting your studios appropriately we're very fortunate when i you know la new york.
Any of the nordics you can grab your local industry so you'll be surprised who you can pull in.
Depending on where you are.
And I will speak to I think some folks probably who are in this area knows I
grew up so I grew up in the Midwest and one of the things that happens out there
is that the few meetups and events and cities and hubs that would hold events
people would drive from three hours in every direction to be at that thing to
find the other people who are in their region now granted they might also be
driving three hours of LA traffic but it's outside LA but it's like just
because you're not in where there's a major city hub you might surprise
yourself on the people who will fly out to your thing etc to make it happen
All the things that we've talked about at this point are just like, what are the value adds for
different groups? We don't have a lot of money to bring to the table to just pay people for this.
So what's in it for the venue? What's in it for the attendees? What's in it for the candidates,
the recruiters? So those three sides of it. And a lot of this stuff is around... Yeah.
So we know that our recruiters are looking for candidates.
One of the ways we can answer some of those questions,
even from our early signups, is making sure
that whatever signup sheet we have,
we're collecting as much information as we can,
as long as it feels relevant to people.
So we did go ahead and put in
as much information as we could about,
like, please tell us what sort of job you're looking for.
What do you consider yourself?
How many years have you been in the industry?
So we can start to answer these questions
when we ask a AAA studio,
hey, would you like to come to our event?
And they ask, well, how many mid-level artists
do you have or hire?
And we're like, okay, we have five artists on our signup sheet already.
And we expect it to grow as we put more studios on there.
This is kind of always a thing when you're talking to any kind of other
organization, but if you can start the conversation, asking them what it is
that they're looking for, before you start asking them for things, it gives
you lots of opportunity to be like, okay, well, we want this and I think we can
give you X, Y, and Z of the things that you already mentioned.
My favorite phrase and the most polite way to say this is,
so what does success look like for you?
How can we facilitate your goals?
Absolutely.
Yeah, use those exact words.
Use those exact words, like steal them.
And then, David, I think you were, you had some information about
how the social spaces worked and sort of that sort of thing.
Yeah, well, what really worked in the social spaces were snacks.
Especially, gamers love food.
So yes, snacks are really helpful.
But the key thing is without serving alcohol,
which would have been a really bad fit
for a professional interview setting.
So we were lucky that our host,
Industrious, provided the beverages.
Also chose non-alcoholic to keep the insurance costs down,
which would have been $10,000 for the event space.
So you have to account for event insurance, especially whenever alcohol is served.
And co-working spaces do come with their own liability insurance already.
So that's great if you're holding at a co-working space.
If you're holding it at a game studio, you have to make sure that they have
liability insurance as well. IGDA HQ insurance doesn't cover your event.
because their stuff covers only things like E3 and such.
So you have to make sure that all of your insurance is covered.
Anyway, getting back to snacks.
As much as gamers like snacks, they were good to have,
they do provide good opportunities for social interaction.
You know, people go and gather around the snack bowl and such,
and it really make it easier for those people
that don't normally socialize well.
especially since we didn't have alcohol there.
So even though they didn't eat a lot of snacks,
the snacks were still a good way
to get people talking together.
And we also found that the recruiters
hung around the snack tables.
And by doing so, they were able to initiate conversations
with the various attendees
and start building up those important social contacts.
There was one company,
they brought six people, I believe,
to represent their company.
They had three people in the room
looking through resumes.
While people did their one-on-one like,
Hi, my name is Jenny Job Hunter and I like visual effects.
And they actually had three people sort of incognito, for lack of a better term,
hanging out by the snack table and the fizzy water dispenser, just making connections.
And they actually told me during their exit, because I did an exit chat with each of them,
they're like, Yeah, we took every resume that came in.
And then we hunted down some people that didn't come in by talking outside.
Because it was... They were doing the professional thing, as well as the casual thing.
Speaking of the professional thing,
adding a professional veneer or sheen to your event is a major key for getting those high-impact AAA or AAAI
studios to take you seriously next time.
And by next time, I mean the next time you do this because you're going to be so successful.
You're going to have like 4 of these.
We found that making the staff wear the same shirt, ideally with a logo, is a major key.
I know everybody hates uniforms in our industry and everyone hates suits, and I totally understand that.
But it made it super easy for people to say,
go find Tiffany. She's the girl in all black with the name tag on.
I wish I had an IGDA-branded shirt so that I could wear that and say,
go find one of the people in an IGDA shirt. That's a major thing. It makes it more comfortable for
people, easier to find out who to ask questions of. And you got to remember, especially for your
venue staff, they don't know who you are. They don't hang out with you.
We didn't have shirts printed, so we all wore black t-shirts and blazers. Considering it's
gaming, the blazer was a major delineator. And I highly recommend it, even though we're in gaming
and we all...
natively dislike blazers as part of our career choices. It makes your staff stand out and that's
what you want. Looking legitimate during your meetings, having your point person wear a blazer
even if you don't wear a blazer in life, or a black long sleeve that's not faded out and doesn't
have a weird game logo on it is a great way to work with people who don't normally work
in the gaming space such as co-working spaces, beverage vendors, etc.
It's a non-endemic brands like that veneer of professionalism, because when you're in
non-gaming spaces, you're competing with companies like Pepsi or Coke or Uber or like tech companies
and people who have a lot more budget and finance than you.
And then Chris, you had some points about documentation, right?
Documenting the space was one of my focuses.
I'm always trying to document our events to help not just show that we're doing things,
but really make a case for next year, being able to visualize it really clearly.
That's why we made that short video about kind of capturing what happened there.
Help secure the venue next year.
The recruiters.
attendees helping them see what they're getting themselves into. We had a couple companies who
sent recruiters and were kind of confused because they misunderstood the nature of the event.
Even having a two minute long video showing this is what it is, here's what's going on here,
will help you get a right fit between people who what they're looking for and showing up.
They were still happy they were there, but they were kind of caught off guard.
Legally, by the way, at least this comes from our headquarters,
it is important to explicitly tell people that they will be videoed or photoed or otherwise documented.
It's required to document things, at least in the state of California. Your laws may vary.
Depending on your venue or who you're partnering with, that may already be covered as part of their agreement using that space.
That's something where I went up doing that this time.
I've got some equipment for other professional uses.
We did unfortunately learn the hard way that you should not go into a photography
community if you do not have a photographer to advise you on the rate you should try
to suggest to try to get help from someone who's professional in that space.
Obviously, good photography is an expensive thing in a budget.
And when you're running a low cost event, it might be what equipment you and your
other volunteers can scramble with.
I would encourage not just using a smartphone. That said, smartphones are not terrible and use both hands if you do.
Yes, or you can find a relatively cheap gimbal online. All the streamers have them these days.
Or borrow them from your friend who has way too much photo gear. That's what I do.
Speaking of specialized things like photo gear,
so we did something a little unique with our career fair and this is because we had
people who are coming in from a layoff. So we looked at it more like a layoff workshop
instead of just a career fair. We got Jaga, who's somebody I know. He runs Dewitt Street, LLC. It's
an accounting consultancy firm to come and give one-to-one advice for anyone who signed up for
completely confidential accounting advice for free. A couple people talked to him. One person
seriously talked to him, but no one took advantage of his services on site, which
means our attendees were a little bit foolish, in my opinion.
Because a lot of them ended up calling him and he's like, yeah, now you've got to pay
its tax season.
What we learned from that is that that was a miscommunication on our part, mine as the
event chair and us as a chapter.
We should have explained more of what he was offering.
You need to sell the good stuff.
We fall into this trap of good things will sell themselves.
They don't.
Good marketing sells all sorts of things.
So moving forward and for next time, we would definitely highlight.
the value add of this kind of thing that you wouldn't expect at a career fair.
So how do you staff an event like this? Obviously, you're going to work with what you have.
And the more the merrier with volunteers. But specifically, the things that we found
were, obviously, there's going to be a huge rush of people at registration,
you can never have enough people checking folks in. And that's a great place to have volunteers.
But pretty much anywhere you're assigning volunteers,
you want to make sure that one of the coordinators,
one of the people who was there organizing the event
is nearby so they have someone to kind of escalate to.
Because obviously they're not going to have the answer
to all the questions.
They just kind of showed up as an extra pair of hands.
The other thing was there tends to need to be somebody
that's floating around,
checking in with each of these groups of people
and making sure all of their needs are being met.
So checking in with the venue, like,
hey, everything's looking good, et cetera, et cetera.
Checking with different recruiters.
we get you anything, etc, etc. Especially the recruiters are kind of locked down at tables
sometimes. So if you can help them out as someone who's a little more mobile, then that can be great.
And just checking in with attendees and making sure somebody is getting a feel for
if people are having any troubles that you can get something, even if it's too hot in here,
you can go ask the venue to turn the AC on or whatever it is.
Having people floating around in different capacities is really helpful.
One of the things we found is
We have a venue that was really actually well set up for this where we could put people into
these phone booths. But a venue like that is really distributed. And how do we tell people
to get around? So as soon as they come in, again, lack of signage, but as soon as they come in,
they're like, what do I do now? And we're like, well, there are companies in all of these rooms
there and all of these rooms there. So having a person to basically air traffic control the humans
around the room and into different places. The other thing that we could have done there is
if we really knew the venue ahead of time.
a little bit more printed materials as you walk in, here's a map, you know, like you'd
see at a conference or something like that.
And some of that was, of course, since we were at a co-working space,
where if we didn't tell people that some of them might have been worried about,
like, is that just other people who are having a meeting in that room that
aren't related to this event?
Part of what's neat about that same dynamic of you're not taking over a
hundred percent of a space makes it potentially like, okay, so you're a
college organization running it on a campus.
You know, you can't lock down that whole building.
You're going to get maybe a few classrooms or whatever.
You can still have people there kind of direct people like, oh, don't go to
this hallway.
We're all up and down this wall over here.
And so you can have a space without having the whole space and opens up your options for where you could be and how flexible your growth can be as well.
And on the note that Chris was just talking about, when we have lots of people in sort of a mixed use space, making sure that everyone had a name tag was important beyond just sort of the facilitation piece.
It's really kind of a security thing, making sure you know who's a part of your event, making sure that they know who's a part of your event so that they're not reaching out to people who are actively working at a desk when we're in a co-work space or something like that.
And I will say as well as those name tags are also potentially part of it's
valuable to have an anti harassment policy or similar types of things
documented that can be up on little trifolds around tables or whatnot.
Something we did not do this year, want to improve for future events.
But basically, sometimes we get resistance from someone saying,
oh, I don't feel like wearing a name tag.
It is important for being able to hold people accountable
for someone's misbehaving, someone's doing something they shouldn't do
to be able to at least have some way to tell who was who.
And that's an important part of that policy.
Yeah, that was all our kind of prep stuff.
But there's actually a bunch of prep that you want your attendees and recruiters to
be doing as well.
It's obvious things like reminding people to bring their resumes and their business
cards.
And it seems very obvious.
But the better prepared people that come in are, the better your event is going to seem.
Because your audience, especially we've talked about this, your audience is your value here
too.
Because this is kind of like recruiters looking for attendees, attendees and venues looking
for people to work there.
So if everyone's professionalism is higher, your event looks better.
So help prep them.
I think David was going to talk about some of the other lessons
learned for the next time we run an event like this.
Some stuff that didn't work.
Yeah.
One thing I think we wish we had done
was request from each studio a high res logo
so that we could put it on our signage.
Would have made a lot better looking signage
than what we had.
One thing that we thought would have worked out well
is that we had an interview room that we called the phone booth.
It had soundproofing in it and that way it allowed people to have private interviews.
But it's turned out that nobody really took us up on it because it wasn't well communicated
that we had that. And then what we should have done is for our survey,
we should have used the survey in Eventbrite rather than having a separate Google link.
Things we could improve upon and that didn't work
We had some individuals, some sort of career coach types,
offer to come and do resume reviews.
And so there's a question on the sign-up form that was,
would you like your resume reviewed by a professional
resume reviewer?
About 40% of people said, yeah, we would like that.
That sounds like an exceptional thing.
I just got laid off.
That vendor didn't show up.
We haven't heard from them since.
I hope nothing terrible happened to them,
but they just didn't come through.
They didn't come to the event.
Fortunately, I was running points on this event. So when the people got here to sign
up for resume review, as you could see on their name tag, which had 1000 stickers on it,
I apologized to them and said, our resume reviewer didn't arrive. Can I interest you in one of our
other specialty products? And they didn't remember signing up that they wanted resume review.
People often say they want things and not actually know what that means or not actually
want it at the end of the day.
How you can account for that, I'm not sure.
Just remember that not everything people say they want is what they want.
And sometimes things they don't say they want, they decide they want when they get there.
I'll say to that point, if one thing that can be done to mitigate is essentially that if it's something feels like a key value add for our event is really relying on, we're really pointing out like come get VR work or come get your resume reviewed or whatever, to basically try to build in some redundancy, thinking of it more as a panel approach, less as a single point of failure.
Just because what we figured out is just as much as not every
attendee who says they're going to come shows up, not every
studio or service who says they're going to come show up
either. And so building around that as an assumption from the
beginning of like, if this is a key value to what we're doing,
how can we make sure we have three lawyers present or
whatever? I mean, if we can't, then not wanting to over
emphasize that in the messaging as to why people should be here
or they show up and they're upset if, if the only AAA
company that was supposed to be there doesn't show up, you get
mad people if you don't have any other sort of backup plan in
that risk mitigation sort of strategy.
Yes.
Speaking of people who didn't show up, Chris can talk about our LinkedIn coaching.
Yeah, we were also hoping to have some LinkedIn critiques for the same reason as our resume
reviews and like the resume reviews, the LinkedIn coach did not show up.
Fortunately, we scrambled a little bit and created the Indie Scramble,
realizing that some of the people there are really, you know, they're open to exploring
studio work, they're exploring jobs out there, but also they're open to the idea of finding
collaborators, getting their own thing rolling out here, maybe meeting with our accountant,
get some financial advice, we would hope next year.
But what we did was we created that space, we set aside if it was an hour or two, and basically
tried to invite people to be like, hey, if you want to meet other potential collaborators,
other indies in the area, go be in this room 2pm to 3pm or whatever we made it.
And during that time, we tried to encourage them to go around and introduce themselves,
really trying to structure it to be that it's less about what happens in that one
event and more about trying to forward some connections so they might follow up after the
fact of like, oh you're also in mobile. We should touch base on is there some way we can connect
each other, is there some way we can collaborate, have you learned some lessons that can apply to
our marketing and vice versa. We did have some people who kind of took over the room in sort
of a show-and-tell format. It would have been probably useful to have had a facilitator had
we planned this event from the beginning and not been a last-minute improvisation.
to help kind of coordinate, make sure the time is evenly fairly distributed or
some people who are a little more talkative might kind of take things over.
That said, for a last minute shift,
it kind of worked out alright as an improvised thing.
So if you do wind up with some empty space, not sure what to do,
if you create kind of a structured conversation, say,
audio room, freelancers room, whatever,
you can at least make some of those connections and create a space for them to feel like
it's okay to hand out their business cards there if that's what they do.
And it's kind of a decent way to improvise when you have vendors not necessarily coming through for you.
Yeah. Speaking of vendors, we had a little bit of difficulty getting them to do exit interviews
afterwards. I did minor ones with each company that I caught, but I'd say about a third of the
companies snuck out the back without saying goodbye. But I wish I had scheduled straight
up like one-hour video calls with a rep from each studio for the week after.
to get more qualitative data. I also wish we'd done that for attendees to get better numbers on,
did you get paired with a studio that ended up with a job? Because the best metric for a career
fair is how many jobs did people get out of it. And we only have soft data, not hard data on that.
Having said that, several vendors dropped out last second. So our numbers are
a little skewed in that space.
And I think part of that's due to the way we handle the Eventbrite.
And I believe, David, you have more info on that, right?
Yeah.
One thing we had, which we had done is we'd use the corporate version instead
of our, our, our personal Eventbrite.
Cause obviously one thing is that we wouldn't have had to reinvent
the wheel if we had done that.
We also missed out on the opportunity for collecting donations.
Also using IGDA HQs.
event prep would have reduced, if we had decided to charge for tickets, it would have reduced
any additional fees that would have been charged to attendees.
And so that's like on the digital prep, as David was saying, but on the physical prep side, which
Drew's covered a little bit before, it ended up being very heavy manual prep the day of, which
I did not account for as the chair on this event.
The big thing was stickers on name tags.
I know this sounds absolutely ridiculous,
but we blew hours manually sticking stickers on name tags
to indicate the disciplines a candidate was working in.
I'd like to point out,
the reason we're talking so much about stickers
is the value add of the stickers
to both the attendees and the vendors.
A lot of the vendors said like,
You know the studios they were like, oh it was great. I could you know stare around the room and see oh
They're here for vr. They're here for audio and they could start up conversations based on the info on the name tags
What that told us is like, okay, we do need to do these stickers
Do we have them do it at the door when they sign in that was already a bottleneck where we want our bottleneck prepping on
the front end or prepping day of
We used an avery tempera template because it was free
which is our favorite word. We bought the name tags at a local office supplies chain
and downloaded the Avery template and just plug and chugged everything in from Eventbrite.
There's an extension that Eventbrite uses to make it quite easy to do that.
Applying your own stickers was an option for next year, but the professionalism would have
been less because we actually had set spots on the tags that each sticker could go almost
gridded out and it's a bottleneck.
all over the place. There were a lot of bottlenecks with sign-in and we're concerned about adding to that
because it was kind of, we didn't plan for that bottleneck at sign-in and I think,
Chris, you have more information about unplanned bottlenecks?
Yeah, again, we kind of spoke earlier about some of our improv events.
In general, organic, unplanned, if you just kind of leave like,
oh, there's couches open, it'll go okay. Maybe, maybe not.
There are some people who sort of professionally are charismatic,
your producers, your professional socializers, your recruiters,
people who just are comfortable with conversations.
For a lot of other folks, and this is true across, we find some of our IGD meetups too,
it can be helpful to have some sort of other focal point, structure, topic.
topic card, we've run some other events where we just put cards on tables of things to discuss for a certain time and swap those out, or
we've had board games sometimes at our events where people are able to use those
as just something to do, maybe not the right thing for a professional career fair,
but figure out some way to structure the conversation, I think that's part of why we had
a little more success in the indie scramble room than maybe some of our other
improvised, open-ended spaces.
Some of that might be part of the industry, although I think our stickers actually did probably help us there too,
where as an easy conversation starter to be like,
oh, you're also an audio person, or, oh, oh, good, I actually need an artist.
in a cup save the kind of moment of introduction.
Run it like people don't know how to socialize as well as you
think they do. Because our industry can be a little awkward
sometimes.
They're stressed out and nervous and they're not used to wearing
a suit and
and it's awkward to try and sell yourself. It's much easier to
sell somebody else like oh, my friend Jenny is amazing at 3d
modeling. You need to see her portfolio is way easier than
being like, I make really good pitch decks, I swear. Like it's
it's helpful that way.
And then David, you had more information on our major challenges, if I remember correctly.
Yeah, big challenges. You don't only have to consider the job seekers to make your event
attractive for, but you also have to make it attractive for hiring companies. So if they
really want to come to your event and getting the big studios to show up proved to be a challenge.
I thought it'd be a lot easier because
I had a lot of connections that I knew personally that I could invite. By the way, if you don't know
connections to invite, what you should do is partner with your local IGDA chapter,
and that's the sort of thing they love to do. They love sharing their connections,
and they can help you put in touch. But even though that we personally knew a lot of connections,
and we contacted AAA studios, and a lot of them had confirmed that they would show up.
None of them actually did.
And there might've been reasons for that.
Maybe we didn't give them enough notice.
Maybe it was because a lot of them were personal connections.
And unfortunately I was traveling at the time we had the event.
So I wasn't able to follow up with them.
It might've been that they realized they didn't have positions they
really needed to seek at the time.
Maybe they had other things coming up.
We don't know exactly why they didn't, but it unfortunately was a little bit embarrassing for us because
we wanted to be able to promote that we had these great studios that would be there and
we weren't able to fulfill on that.
So it was a little bit embarrassing that we booked and set up rooms for them and they didn't appear.
But anyway, lesson learned that
we need to follow up better. We should have
had them sign a form
stay in contact with them and really keep on top of everyone who had RSVP to make sure they were
going to show up.
I would add on the other side of that, from the giant studios, the small to medium sized studios, a few I was impressed, who basically, you know, a giant studio like you said, they might not need a specific type of job right now that they see us bringing out in the demographic.
The small, medium sized studios, a number of them kind of came out and said, we just want to get to know who's in our area.
Because sometimes they'll add, they're small enough, they're flexible enough, they're adaptable enough, they might realize that once they find someone who's really good at a certain type of talent,
can change what they're doing in a way that the bigger company might have kind of already,
its plans are pretty locked in place. That was actually a neat dynamic. We have a couple of
studios, I think TV games might have one of them who are there basically to, let's talk about your
resume. We're not trying to waste anybody's time, but we're not specifically hiring for this
particular role. But we get on our radar because any given time, we don't know what contract work
we're spinning up. And then they want to have access to those people in their community.
And I think it was actually surprising flexibility from the small studios that
kind of I hadn't expected going into it.
So don't discount smaller midsize studios.
Everyone wants to work at Epic or Sony or Nintendo,
but don't forget the medium or little guys,
the studios that have less than 15 employees,
because there's a lot of opportunity there.
Yeah, I mean, from that angle,
I run a work-for-hire shop,
and we have that exact problem all the time.
It's like, I have no idea
what the next contract is going to be.
I might need nine contractors
across the entire spectrum of game development.
get moving. And so just having those contacts and knowing that there's people out there looking or
freelancing or what have you, extremely, extremely valuable for me as a small business owner.
Speaking of value, funding, money. Yay, I'm a treasurer. That's what I talk about.
Funding the event is part of why you're here. We've talked about our pitfalls.
Now I got to talk about our fiscal pitfalls.
A career fair charges tables
Charges companies at a table rate generally between one and five thousand us dollars
For a you know, three by six costco table, but to be fair
You got to fund these things somehow
That's how they make money. That's how these things like pay for stuff like insurance and snacks and name tags
We used an impact grant
an impact grant
it's from
IGDA headquarters and every chapter can use up to a thousand of it a year. It has to impact the community
You know on screen you'll see the requirements headquarters has for it
It could cover everything from printing name tags
to snacks to possibly subsidizing parking
As long as it's part of something that positively impacts the community
The vast majority of IGDA chapters don't use theirs and that includes SIGs. So it's not just like LA or Norway
it can be like
Latinx in gaming
Esports like whatever
Um, it's use it or lose it money. And so this isn't supposed to be an ad for the IGDA, by the way
This is not what this is
but what we found is our infrastructure that we've had as being part of IGDA
Has really underpinned a lot of the stuff we could have done as opposed to four people trying to make this happen
In a corner
So pair with your chapter. There's one basically everywhere.
Finding a venue that would take us for free was an exercise in cold calling.
I personally really actively dislike cold calling.
It's uncomfortable. I'm bad at socializing. I don't like it.
I got one response out of 65 calls.
I thought co-working spaces would be useful.
I thought that public libraries would be useful.
Both of those wanted to charge me $3,000 to $5,000 for the space.
And maybe the library thing is just an LA thing, but I didn't realize you had to rent your library.
I thought my taxes paid for that. Apparently, that's not true. I tried with friends in nice
work buildings. They had security issues and stuff. They couldn't handle it.
Restaurants needed a buyout. I was like, can we just use your space when no one's in here?
You can keep serving food to everyone else, but can we just take like 10 tables in the corner?
And they were like, no, you need to buy us out for 5k plus the cost of food. And I was like,
well, that's not happening.
The local women's club had a venue.
They also wanted to buy out.
The LGBTYMCA wanted to buy out as well.
Every community center wanted to buy out.
I understand everyone's got to make money somehow.
But it was really surprising to me how many
venues required a buyout.
I had to call individual locations.
So a lot of things, whether it's your WeWorks, your Spaces,
your Industrious, or your The Wings.
They have an HQ and they also have individual chapters.
HQ for every single organization I called said no.
Bar none, every single one of them said no.
I actually ended up using Google Maps to find the local phone numbers of my local
co-working branches.
Two of Industrious' branches said yes, specific to location.
I went to a local chamber of commerce meeting with the city of Santa Monica, and I met someone
who's the head of programming for the local Santa Monica WeWork chapter.
Now, I know WeWork's not everyone's favorite right now, but they do have big spaces.
That gentleman was shocked.
He's like, what do you mean we said no?
And I'm like, I called you.
You said no.
And he's like, are you kidding me?
This is exactly the kind of event we want to host in our big communal spaces.
And I'm still in contact with them for another event with another organization I work with.
So.
HQ saying no doesn't always mean no, because the local chapters have more flexibility in certain
things. Also, think outside of your game dev network. You don't have to use the canteen at
a studio. Speaking of things we need to run the career fair, Drew, do you want to talk more about
actual logistics once you find the space? Yeah, I mean, there's a bunch of equipment
concerns about obtaining venues and obtaining equipment at venues. Obviously, for a lot of
career fairs, it's tables. It might be signage. It might be a variety of things.
I think this is one of those things where you got to understand which things you're
most constrained by. If you have a budget, there are a lot of places that are set up
with facilities to handle this. If you go ask a hotel, they will tell you what their
rental prices are. They'll give you a sheet this long. If you go ask a college, they have
a facilities department, they'll give you a rental sheet of things that are this long.
Usually, they're pretty expensive, but know which things are your constraints.
If you are trying to find a venue that you're trying to save money, etc., etc.
Again, it comes down to like, how can I help those people?
Or who can I partner with that's sort of on the inside?
At a college, this is usually like,
I need a professor to sponsor me,
or I need a student group who's really invested,
because those people are usually able to obtain
classrooms or gymnasiums or whatever for free.
We had tried to do this thing three, four years ago.
There used to be a startup out here on the west side of LA
that they had monthly meetups from meetup.org out there.
They loved, basically.
They wanted people to know where they were, their brand, what they did to know their people.
And again, that would have been great.
They're unfortunately no longer out there.
But that really does come from figuring out, okay, who wants to be on that map?
Who wants those kind of connections?
Somebody potentially.
But this is something where you have to have a high expected failure rate.
This is a thing, obviously, it's equally true for the people out there applying
for jobs, it's part of the discouraging process if they are applying for 10 or
20 to get maybe one or two or three options to hopefully consider in that,
uh, you know, this is something where a lot of our people that we work with are
coming from maybe engineering disciplines or some other field where if you do the
right steps, the algorithm computes, you get the end result, or you ace the math
assignment.
this is a fundamentally a business operation. So it's going to be low yield. And that if you're
doing 65 calls and getting a few yeses, that's great. And there's no shortcut to that besides
getting really used to the rejection. And to point out like again, that doesn't mean you're
failing at it doesn't mean you need to, you're doing everything wrong. That's part of the
process. If you're trying to operate a low budget of that budget translating to legwork instead of
capital, you're able to invest in a known quantity like a hotel establishment or
paying for college space you don't have a direct in at.
Mm-hmm. And speaking of business, because I do, I come in from the business,
people doing business side of things.
Here's some tips that I know from my space that might help people who aren't
from that space. Don't use words like unemployment or laid off when you're
trying to get a space. People don't really like hearing that.
It's not an appealing demographic.
You have to sell the venue on yourself and your organization before your thing.
The venue wants to know our demographics.
What percentage of your people are,
well, they didn't know to use the word engineers,
but they literally say,
can you give us a demographic breakdown
of the people in your organization?
You know, make sure you can define it before you go in
and talk about your target demographics.
It's not just people who make games.
Frame it as a business
and use business language for product market fit.
Creative entrepreneurs is a good word for indies.
Lean Startups is a great name for two-man studios.
It's not about what the things are.
It's about how they're presented that count.
An example we use and why industrious liked us is like, oh, we skew high mail, but compared
to our industry average, we're actually quite diverse.
You show a state of comparison between two things.
People love that.
Early mid-twenties.
has college degrees, like the way you can slice and dice your people, the more ways you can slice
and dice it and the way you can present said slicing and dicing will really assist you in
getting what you need. And then David, you were talking more about, you know, trying to get free
stuff and how to market it and all that. Yeah, well, particularly getting the venues because
Only until you actually have a place you're going to hold the event, can you really get people to
agree to actually come to it. So the venue is probably the most important thing of all.
And you know, everyone says they know somebody, they know some place. It's real easy. I have a
place I know I can get a free venue at, but when it really comes down to it, it's really tough.
As Tiffany just said, she made over 60 calls and nobody wanted to do it.
Even despite dangling a little carrot of because we're a non-profit they might save as much as like
$3,000 hot beer taxes that that still wasn't able to do it. I went and uh,
I looked at a number of different restaurants that we could hold it at but
The noise level was too high. I thought for for holding meetings and holding interviews
And some of the foot traffic was really poor
People getting in and out that's that's something you really have to consider the flow of the people within the place
A lot of people say that uh, oh, let's we can hold it at a university or a college
Easier said than done turns out universities book their spaces way in advance
And we tried a number of them and we weren't lucky. Also, there's tremendous parking problems
often at universities
you really have to consider your venue first consider such things as
Who you know who you can contact?
Give them a lot get a lot of advance notice because places get booked booked up
Very early
no matter what type of place you're holding it at,
as much advance notice for booking things in
is really helpful. Consider how people are going to move, where you're going to
set up stations, and parking. Yeah, two quick notes on
that are, for one thing, one of the reasons why the university is so
important to have that connection, like was said earlier, kind of a
professor's pet project.
is that anytime companies are coming onto a college campus,
that college campus wants to charge those companies.
That's part of how they operate on.
They're accessing their students
and they're essentially clients and so on.
And so that's where it needs to be.
It's like we said, sort of an in over there.
In terms of snacks, another thing to keep in mind,
and we did not do this in this case,
but I remember a few years back,
some small, I think it was a game jam or whatever,
hit up my small company at the time I was just getting started out
to sponsor their snacks, which like,
uh, okay, the thing is, if you try to hit up a giant company, they're not gonna hand you snack money.
A small company was like, yeah, I can spare 50 or 100 bucks on snacks, which is
not a bunch of money to even a beginning company,
but it felt cool to get my name on there, you might be surprised, again, it's like, the people who show up sometimes,
the small companies, the approval is the only person you're talking to, and they're like,
yeah, I can do that, here's a check.
And so you might be surprised that here and there
might be able to add up on funding some snacks
that's not coming out of your pocket
or your tiny budget you're already working from.
In terms of our parking barrier bottleneck,
again, we kind of knew this was an LA challenge.
It was expensive parking.
And so much so that we did receive some hate mail,
some people were frustrated at the cost,
especially knowing it was for people
who are in a laid off situation.
When you're doing things,
it's going to attract some opinions of it.
And that's gonna always come with you doing anything.
There's gonna be a range of people.
Some people like it.
Some people wish it was done differently.
kind of having to kind of accept that part of it is absorbing some blame and that's hopefully still
the positives that way the negatives of the good that you're doing and so it's also being just
simply empathetic to the fact that when you're trying to help people who are necessarily laid
off between work still trying to find the first footing and maybe people who are coming from
they're in stressful situations they are counting on certain things so being patient with that as
you're trying to to help people and do all you can to help the community.
that that's part of the process and the cost kind of factor into what goes into doing it.
In terms of printing, we were very fortunate once again, here's a place where our host
Industrious was able to deliver. They actually offered to do our printing for us that included
like a massive Kinko's like banner. But as long as you know, those things early on of like,
potentially our venue might be able to account for some of those services. If you can sort
those things out sooner rather than later might be able to better take advantage of those kind
of opportunities. I think Drew some PR marketing thoughts. Yeah. Generally, I thought
We were really happy. The event seemed to be successful for our size. But we needed to leverage
our presence online and all of these things better. We needed to get the messaging out in
more different ways. Something that I think people don't often think about. You obviously
have Facebook and Instagram or whatever people are Twitter, if people are following you on.
But for professional events, LinkedIn is huge. If you're a job seeker, you're on LinkedIn. If
you're a recruiter, you're on LinkedIn. So we didn't have our LinkedIn presence.
up to date at that time. And we didn't really grow it as much as we could have. And if we
were to leverage that for our next event, which I hope we can, I think that'll be really powerful.
On top of that, there's a lot more data we could have been gathering.
That Eventbrite, we funneled things in from Facebook and from Twitter and things like that.
If we were to just use backlinks or shorten URLs with data attached to them, we'd absolutely be
able to know, okay, most of our traffic is coming from Twitter. So maybe we should spend more effort
there.
it's coming from our mailing list. Let's see how we can grow our mailing list." That kind of thing,
just to focus our efforts. Because anytime you're working with non-profits or small companies or
whatever, you get into this space where you're doing a shotgun approach to marketing. And it's
a very high effort operation. But if you're able to know which pieces are giving you the value,
you could save yourself a lot of time and honestly, you can be a lot more successful
investing in the one thing that's giving you the most outcomes.
On the other side of getting people to show up, we kind of knew building into the plans.
Like any event, not everyone who says they're going to RSVP on Facebook or Eventbrite is
actually going to be there.
And first off, we just kind of Googled average rate of people who don't show up for Eventbrite.
We found about 40 to 50 percent, which is also consistent with our casual meetups as
a chapter we hold anyway, in terms of we might have 20 to 30 shows for an event that 50 people
respond yes to.
So it seemed to kind of live up to our expectations.
And so, you know, going off of that, the attendees getting specific data in advance from the people who say they're coming
Is really important. We sent out a pre-vetting survey
But the problem is people didn't want to fill it in or they just put in gibberish or made stuff up
Borking our data like it would say like what do you do for work?
You know artist engineer audio other and they put like
Unicorns and i'm like that is not a sticker. I have
In front of me to put on your name tag
And it wasn't until we started parsing that data and looking at some of the charts that Eventbrite generates, I was just like, oh, no.
Speaking of, oh, no, you got to be ready to hold your ground politely and appropriately as people try to push or bully you into comping things that you shouldn't.
I'm going to say this right now.
It is not industry standard to comp anything at a career fair.
Do not let anyone tell you otherwise, whether it's parking or their parking ticket or whatever.
There is a clear management of expectations in terms of I think our page might even be
probably all capitals like parking is X amount which is a double digit expensive amount.
We encourage ride shares or public transit etc.
Giving them a heads up helps make it easy if you have to afterwards to point to the
thing and be like you opted to do the thing we let you know.
just kind of helps prevent or reduce and manage as many of those conversations you can have.
We did have, in terms of feedback we received, some positive feedback.
So we had mentioned earlier our friend, the financial advisor, who did not get as many
interactions as we were hoping for him during the event, but we did have people hit him
up after the event to do their taxes for their company this year.
So it's still a worthwhile thing for him to be out there.
sharing those business cards, making those connections.
We're trying to figure out a better way to get follow up from
our different organizations that were there.
We know it was valuable for some of them, but we would love to.
This is where we would share some quotes if we had them.
Like we said, a lot of them kind of ghosted us on the surveys after the fact.
They kind of felt like they built up for an event.
They were done. They were exhausted.
Granted, they got other priorities to go to next.
But working out a way to get that sort of notes from them,
just like it's valuable for us to document the event on video and show,
look, this is a real thing that happens.
Getting those sort of quotes and feedback, we might be trying to find still ways
yet to get a hold of them, to get some notes of how valuable it was in retrospect.
Those help you land new venues next time.
Those help you sell the event to other people who might come out.
Those are important and worth finding ways to figure out.
We have not cracked that puzzle, but we acknowledge that's a thing
we are trying to improve at.
There were some studios that were unhappy.
with the clientele we brought in,
we might handwave and say to an extent
there's only so much we can control about that.
There was one who wanted some very high level people,
but here's a case where even there,
we could have managed expectations better
if we had been able to get that company
to fill out their pre-survey,
where they did not let us know
that's who they're looking for
until it was sort of already too late.
Managing expectations and stuff is important.
And on that note, we actually had a midsize studio
who really loved us.
They were incredibly happy with their experience
and they didn't expect to be so happy with their experience.
They not only found who they wanted,
but also people they didn't realize they wanted.
And they added it to their database later
for when they got back to HQ,
because they knew they'd be hiring
in a couple months for those roles.
Right on. In terms of getting our logistics out, again, we hit up basically every channel we could.
We also, we had our town hall a couple months prior, and we really tried to drill in there that this was an important event coming up on the calendar.
So it can be an opportunity to kind of basically build up to that event.
So by the time it's coming up, people are asking about when's that going on?
I heard that's a thing that's happening.
And we did see some of that response on our Facebook event, which I think was helpful to us.
We didn't charge people. Again, our context here was this, we're mostly large, trying to create this to help people relate off.
That said, there is some sort of trade-offs between if you charge even a nominal amount, maybe $3, maybe $5.
We have some internal dialogues about if it makes sense for us to do it for our next one.
Obviously, you're going to get fewer respondents, but you might have a much higher rate of people who feel like,
I paid for this, I'm going to show up.
and you might have a much better therefore hit rate on promising your attendee or your company's coming
who's going to be there based on they paid for it, they're probably going to be here
even if it's not a huge amount.
For volunteers, it's good to ask them at least a month in advance
even if they're people who are not necessarily specialists with a camera
or other kinds of certain work
it's still the case even if it's something you could be doing but a volunteer could do it instead
that frees you up to do work that they might not be able to take care of based on
who they know there, who they invited there
stuff that you have the authority as the person facilitating or administering it.
to take care of. I've got a couple notes from I think David on pre pre recording some email
correspondences. Yeah, it's important to have a good communications plan when you're holding an
event like this. And so it helps to to write out plan out what emails you're going to send and
write them out well ahead of time because you find when you're.
When you're preparing for an event like this, you don't have time to think about these things.
So plan out your emails ahead of time, like write an email to send out to thank people when they signed up,
then maybe another one five days or a week before,
10 or 14 days before, and then 24 hours before the event.
Just continue reminders so that people don't forget about it and to build up the anticipation for the event.
A note I want to add about those pre-scheduling the emails is so important because you'll
be exhausted. You'll be scrambling just before it. You'll be tired right after it. If you've
written them a few weeks in advance, it may not seem fun or easy to do, but it lets you
not stress out about it at the time and the emails will still go out.
Yeah, and the same way that you want to schedule stuff beforehand and send out emails to prep
people, it's really helpful to send one out afterwards just to thank you to people, make
sure the last interaction is positive.
kind of keep up that relationship for the next time.
If it's a recruiter or whatever,
the next time you're hosting an event,
we need to contact them again.
And that's also a great opportunity
to kind of share some of the data
that you've gathered at this point
and provide extra value back to these people,
whether it's a venue and telling them who showed up
or recruiters giving them a list of the candidates, et cetera.
And there's some sort of nuts and bolts technical stuff as well in terms of verbiage, strategy,
timing, all that. Make sure you fit your venue. We've said it over and over and over again,
the venue is going to be the most important thing.
Right on. Well, and for closing, I want to encourage we'll put
our email addresses up how to contact us in the chapter for
IGDA. If you have questions about it, we'd love to discuss
them with you. If you have tips, opportunities, better ways to
fund things, better kind of things to look for. We are as
much as anything, not just trying to say this is how it's
done. We're trying to create that conversation and learn from
you as well and your experiences. It would really
benefit us as we are continuing to try to run career fairs as
well. I thank you for taking the time to join us today. And
also thank you, of course, David, Drew and Tiffany. I'm
Chris. Thank you everyone for being here.
Thank you.
Bye everyone.
Bye.