On GDC Podcast Episode 5, we got a special guest, Hannah Flynn.
Hannah Flynn with Sunless Skies developer Failbetter Games,
and she'll talk about marketing your indie game so people might actually buy it, maybe?
Also stay tuned for the latest GDC 2020 news and hear opinions about 2019's best games.
Back in a sec.
Hey everybody, we're back. This is Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra,
and I'm here with my co-host Alyssa McAloon. Hey Alyssa!
Hi, I'm Melissa McAloon. I am a news editor,
and a social media producer.
Producer? No, what is my job?
Publisher of policytru.com.
Do you want to be a producer?
No.
You got it.
Just add it to your title.
So let's go right into some GDC news
real quick before we bring on our very special guest.
So GDC 2020 is coming up in March still, right?
We haven't shifted the dates.
Near months away.
Yeah.
Mere months.
I can't take it.
This is like a, it's like three podcasts away.
Oh, don't change.
I've changed.
Yeah.
My perception of time into podcasts.
So I hope that's a acceptable unit of measurement.
Uh, yeah, uh, it's coming up March 16th through 20th, 2020.
Get that year right, 2020.
Registration is open at gdconf.com and we would love to see you there.
I, we would, it would be nice.
Wouldn't it?
We actually have, it is a lovely atmosphere.
I mean, it has been for the past what?
31 years.
It's been nice.
Five, something like that.
Yeah.
100? The century?
This is the 100th GDC?
Dog years, yeah.
Yeah.
We have some honestly really exciting, we're finally starting to talk about the talks that
are going to be there.
So have, Alyssa, have you heard of this game called Death Stranding?
The walking simulator, yes, I'm familiar.
Is it?
I thought it was a stepping and falling simulator.
dropping your packages all over the place simulator.
But there's going to be a talk, deconstructing the AI of Death Stranding.
That's going to be there. It's going to be great.
There's also a little app called Apex Legends,
known around Gamasutra's hallways as Apelegs, but more formally as Respawn's Apex Legends.
So yeah, there's a post-mortem on that.
Come on down for that.
And, uh, last one I'm going to mention, although there are so many others that
are live on the site right now, uh, on GDC's website right now, there is going
to be one on the, uh, the ashtray maze.
In control.
What do you think of that, Alyssa?
I haven't beaten control yet, but that I probably watched someone play that part
and it is visually stunning, so I can only imagine the making of that has to be wild.
Yeah, I mean, watching games nowadays, it counts as playing, I think.
So, you have played the Ashtray Maze.
Dang, dang.
Yeah.
And then lastly, there are a bunch of alt control GDC.
This is, these are games that have these really wacky
alternative controls.
This includes a, this year there's
going to be a cow milking, competitive cow milking
simulator there.
I've seen, uh, I've seen it in pictures and it's exactly what you would think.
It would look like kind of like rubbery udders there.
And you, uh, go up against your friends and you mug a cow.
Alyssa and I are actually, we were raised in the Midwest, so I
think we would be pretty good.
It'll be a nice little sense of home.
I think in the middle of a chronic convention floor is just
a, some udders and a pail.
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
And then last of all, you can, for our potential GDC guests
who need some financial help, we also have a,
what we call a low income pass lottery,
which you can apply for.
So check that out on the gdconf.com website.
So, on to our guest.
She is director of comms, that is short for communications,
I think, at Fail Better Games,
where she's worked on Fallen London, Sunless Sea,
that is singular, not sunless seas,
sunless sea, as well as sunless skies, plural.
She also came up with a really cool campaign last year,
the hashtag LoveIndies campaign, which we'll talk about.
She is a marketing guru in the game industry.
And in her past life, in a past life,
she worked in book publishing, art, and charitable causes.
She is a past and future GDC speaker.
And she's spoken at a bunch of other places
sharing her knowledge.
It is.
Hannah Flynn.
Hey, Hannah.
Hello.
Thank you.
That was the warmest introduction I've ever had on a podcast.
You know that I F I feel like it was the warmest one that I've given.
And extremely accurate.
We pride ourselves in the facts here.
Finding research was worth it.
And it's funny to think I am previously a speaker at GDC as well, because I spoke at GDC next.
You did yeah, I watched it. I'm really thinking of this one as my first go
I don't know. Yeah, this is this is a big show
This is the big show. Yeah
Yeah, one of my favorite parts about your GDC Next talk back in 2014, I think, was that you were
a little under the weather, and every time you coughed, you asked the audience to applaud.
Yeah.
It was the most applause that I've seen during the entirety of a GDC talk.
I think it was the last talk at GDC Next, maybe, ever.
I think I closed it out with a lot of applause,
but yeah, I was quite sick.
And I'd been in the industry for a total of five weeks
or something at the time.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
And you already knew so much that you had to tell everybody.
I came in on a high.
Yeah.
I had a baby in the middle, and now I'm back.
You're back.
All right.
So give us a little bit of your background.
You actually came to Fail Better Games
from a non-games background.
Yeah, I don't even have game-based qualifications.
I don't know what I'm doing. Me neither.
I don't know what I'm doing here.
I worked previously in film,
then in publishing for one of the biggest publishers
in the world, if not the biggest,
and then for museums and galleries.
digital team making games and interactivities for children and young people and that's the biggest gallery in the UK and
Then the biggest children's charity in the UK and after a while of not really knowing any of my colleagues names
I thought I quite like to work somewhere very very small and I joined fail better. I think I was employee number eight
number eight
yeah, at the time there were only eight of us.
And that was much more my tempo, much more comfortable for me,
no longer having to try and curry favour with people on a different continent
who you sort of have to guess at their email
and you need them to do something for you in short order.
Just, it was very stressful.
Very stressful. And gaming was less stressful than that.
Weirdly enough, I joined in 2014, right on the tail end of the first bit of Gamergate.
It was less stressful than working for a children's charity.
Good lord!
Okay, I guess counting my blessings there
Yeah, so
It's I always like stories where?
People come into the game industry
after not being in it because I know that a lot of people kind of are on the outside looking in and maybe think that
They can't get in
or that their background won't benefit
or is not transferable to a career in the games industry.
So what informed, how did your non-games work inform
your current work in marketing and communications and games?
Well, I've always worked across marketing and comms.
So the beautiful part of that discipline
is it's completely transferable.
I could go and market Kitchen Cleaner
if I felt strongly enough about it.
Do you feel strongly enough about it?
No.
I'm looking at my kitchen right now and it is not clean.
So I don't think I'd be a good ambassador for that industry
at all.
Let the record show.
Yeah.
Because comms and marketing is basically
about the audience and platform.
It's about finding the one through the other.
So when I arrived in games, I didn't really
understand, say, live streaming.
I hadn't used tools like that before but because I'd built audiences before
and I understood a bit about human behaviour and what people are looking for out of community,
it's something that you can really apply. So because getting into games is extremely competitive
and because roles like mine are really very rare even within the small industry that we're in.
It is slightly heartening, I think, for people to think,
I could do this for another business and learn,
and then take those skills plus my personal knowledge of games,
which I had,
and turn that into a role for myself somewhere,
you know, working on something that I love,
which is what I did.
Do you feel like that kind of like accessibility has changed from like 2014-ish when you got
started to like the current state of the industry or is it about kind of the same?
I think it is getting better partially because I've done a number of talks where I just have
big letters on that said hire a marketer.
You're a marketer, Jesus Christ!
Oh, how can I, can I curse?
Yeah.
Never stopped us.
I don't think Jesus Christ is a curse word.
I stopped myself halfway through Jesus Christ
because I was thinking of something else.
Because people, I think,
marketing is becoming something
more and more studios need in order to get any traction.
and people are really having to consider what is possible within what they have
in terms of resources and money, obviously,
but also their ambition and how they can make something happen that matches the ambition they have for their games.
That's very much changing.
The need for what I do has definitely increased,
but as Felbetter have been ahead of the curve on a few things
and lucked out on a few things,
and one of them, I think, was hiring a fully-fledged full-time marketer in 2014.
Yeah. Can you, uh, before we go on more about, uh, the, the marketing, uh,
details, uh, can you tell us a little bit about what fail better does and, uh,
the kinds of games that, that you all make there?
Yeah, we make really beautifully, exquisitely written, story-driven narrative RPGs that are heavily text-based.
The most recent has more than 800,000 words in it, but primarily about giving...
extremely memorable, strange, oblique stories that you don't get anywhere else in games
through a setting that we've been developing for 10 years that's called Fall in London.
And all of our major games so far take place in this alternate history, Victorian Gothic
universe that we created ourselves and is now absolutely massive.
And in these games they've been quite successful too because of you.
Well, yeah, and because they're really good.
Which helps.
You sort of have to have both.
You have to have an exquisite product
and then you have to sell the crap out of it.
There's no sort of getting away from
you needing to do both of those things.
Part of the reason that we're able to
maintain and sustain our success is
Fallen London, the original game,
is a browser game that's still going.
It's going to be 10 in January.
and has a subscription model that supports it, it's free to play.
And we have, you know, x-thousand subscribers still,
that enables us to take a few more chances
and to have something to fall back on
if one of the premium games that we make alongside Fallen London doesn't go so well.
So that is the bedrock of our business,
is this ongoing sort of game-as-service.
which enabled us to do a kickstart of Sunless Sea,
which succeeded brilliantly in a different age on Steam.
When we launched Sunless Sea, we were on the front page of Steam for all Steam users for about four days.
Which is a big piece of pie. And you don't get pie that big these days.
Certainly not a game of our size.
And then that in turn enabled us to keep going, do another Kickstarter,
create another Early Access title, which we launched this year, Sunless Skies.
which for the glory of everything has been even more wonderfully warmly received
and I would say has sold sustainably well and we're very happy.
But yeah, the time, the difference between when we launched on the sea and when we launched on the skies
is quite marked in terms of what you are, the audience you're able to reach.
Yeah. How about we just cut to the chase and I'll just ask you,
I'll just ask you, how do you market an indie game?
Like where do you even start forming a marketing plan?
Some people don't have one at all and don't know where to begin.
With conviction, Chris,
you have to, you have to believe that.
marketing your game is something that you need to do. You have to start there.
And I guess the answer to this question comes differently if you are a person or two people or three people in a micro studio
versus a team of 10, 15, you know, 25 people.
If you have 25 people, you don't have a marketer. I'm afraid you've already made a few errors.
But if you're marketing something by yourself, the way that you start...
is with a really good store page, with a really good Twitter, and with a press list and a
press information.
You commit to doing those things, you nurture them and you, what's the word, where you grow
something and you cultivate it.
You cultivate those things.
Start making a press list.
Start day one by...
looking up a game that is a bit like what you want to make,
googling the reviews of that game,
looking at the journalists who wrote those reviews,
finding those journalists on Twitter,
and saying, hey, I saw you liked X, I'm making Y,
can I put you on the press list, could I send you a key?
And do that until you have a list of people
who are warmly interested in the sort of stuff that you make.
And do a little bit of that every day.
The big mistake is feeling like marketing is a big.
homogenous, single activity thing that you can spend lots of money on,
and if you don't have any money, you can't do marketing.
You can, you just need to account for marketing time within your development time.
It is part of development, it starts at the beginning of development,
um, but it's people who...
ignore it because it is daunting
that we'll miss out.
So you say it starts day one with development. How do
a developer who's like, here's my project, here's my idea, here's a game we're
gonna make, we're starting today,
what would be the actionable things that a marketer would do in that
situation?
I would ask them who it's for.
That gives you almost everything you need to know about what to do next.
We know our audience super well because a lot of the core people who are with us now
have been with us for 10 years, 8 years, since Fallen London was launched.
So we know where they live, not in a creepy way.
We know that they love to read, they love to feel clever,
they love mystery, they love representative characters, diversity.
We, as far as we know, were the first commercial RPG to have a third gender option at all.
So we know that a lot of people are with us for that stuff.
And we do quite deep research with them.
We sort of exist alongside them in our Discord and in our various community forum spaces.
But if you don't have that, then the first thing you need is to...
figure out if that audience exists, doing research on similar titles, establishing what
you think the ambition for sales could reasonably be, and pitching yourself a sort of sufficient
level of activity, of marketing activity, to grow a community that could support that
type of sales level.
And being realistic about that stuff.
And finding a niche and being happy to be niche is kind of the modern way.
Find an audience who will love it.
10 people who will love it is better than 50 people who think, meh.
So like, uh, you're kind of, I mean, you were talking about market research here.
Uh, and you mentioned discord.
uh how do you collect uh this information how do you quantify it how do you use all that data and
information and apply it to development and marketing of a game well cunningly this is
kind of what i'm covering in my gdc talk oh yes so i'm doing a talk called um next level
indie game marketing um which goes into things like
How do you use player data research and understanding and knowledge of your audience to inspire
ideas that will work for your specific game?
A big deal is being specific.
to your thing. People oftentimes will look around and see these kind of big flashy, splashy
marketing ideas or they think the first things that come to mind when you think of video game
marketing is like massive announcements attached to big award ceremonies or huge side of bus or
side of building advertising. But being very specific to the tone of your thing.
and the information that you know about your audience is what enables you to narrow down
and then you sort of put that through your mill
and what comes out the other end is the idea that will meet those...
those wants and limitations that you have.
A good example is the launch campaign for Sunless Skies.
We had minimal advertising budget and we don't do a lot of advertising
so we wanted to use that money in as a constructive way as we possibly could
and we knew all these different things about what we wanted to achieve.
We knew that the launch window
was extremely short in which we could get enough public conversational and algorithmic interest in
the game in order to really when they say launch they mean you know punch through the atmosphere
launch the thing
and get that attention.
So we kind of narrowed absolutely everything into a 24-hour period.
We also knew from our understanding of our community
that they are very charitably minded.
And we knew about our games, from having already made Sunless Sea,
that we weren't probably going to get a lot of attraction with streamers.
We get some streamers, but it's...
It's about specificity again. The people who really want to stream it are very, very few, but they will really go for it.
They want to read all the words, they want to wear a top hat and have a little train whistle and just go completely hard for it, which is amazing.
But we wanted to combine all of these things and kind of bake them and construct them into something that would give us that launch velocity.
We did the Sunless Skies 10k challenge, for which in the first 24 hours after we launched,
we gave a pound per minute of streamed content to the gaming charity SpecialEffect,
aiming to get 10,000 minutes, hence the 10k challenge.
And because it was charitable, original...
It convinced people to stream it who might not otherwise have done so.
And we actually ended up with about 28,000 minutes of stream content in the first 24 hours,
which was fantastic and was a big part of the reason why we were able to chart on Steam in that initial period.
Stuff like that's so creative.
Um, do you feel like, uh, some developers who are kind of new to this are, uh,
you know, ma maybe they're, you know, they can come up with a good idea, but
are standoffish about trying something new like that
I think it's really intimidating to do something like that.
And I also think, if you can't afford to hire a marketer, then absolutely don't because
it will cost.
But if you can afford consultancy...
Talking about your game in great depth with someone who doesn't understand it very well is a great way to find
the points at which you can like
Convey exactly what it is and and a good marketer will be able to reflect back to you like oh you have something there
You know, what do you mean? People don't really want to stream your game
Oh, well, it's a load of setup and you get really breathless. They get people get tired of streaming it. Well, what if you know
It is really intimidating
But
This is not to say that everybody should go away and do exactly what I did,
because it won't necessarily work for another type of game.
But it is about mashing those things together and getting something new,
or even involving creative idea generation tools,
like rolling a dice or something,
to throw in some random elements until you get something that you think might work.
Yeah. And you also last year, uh,
formulated the hashtag love Indies campaign.
Can you explain what that was all about? That was a success.
Yes, it's been great. We've done it twice now.
Love Indies is a campaign that goes across players, developers and platforms
to basically encourage everyone to rate, recommend and review indie games.
Because we all play games and we all sort of fail to review them,
even if we really like them, it's a chore.
So we turned that part of...
you know, you can't just keep tweeting,
please review our games,
please leave me a review, I really like it.
It would be really nice if you,
like if you just keep saying the same thing
over and over again, it doesn't get you anywhere.
So I chewed on that for a little while
and it came to me that every developer has this problem.
So we reached out to a load of developers who we knew
and we put together a participation guide
that was extremely low friction,
really easy for people to pick up.
It had...
all the little social media things that people needed, all the links, example tweets to do
and just sent it out into the world and then we had you know thousands and thousands of users of the
the hashtag during the Love Indies campaign period which was a week the first year,
two weeks the second year.
And it had some really amazing effects like a permanent change to Itch,
where Leif from Itch had seen the campaign and created a tool
which surfaced any games in your library that you'd interacted with
but never left a review with.
So it made it really, really simple for people.
Everybody got a glut of these reviews and all that developers were so happy to see people reviewing their stuff
It just gives you such a boost. Honestly, we've just reached a thousand reviews on Sunless Skies and we practically had a party
That's yeah, those are great numbers. And can you can you explain for?
listeners who might not understand
Like why is the number of reviews so significant for game developers?
It's more it's significant for morale
We slave away. We slave and we just want to know what you think.
But it feeds into what I would call the health metrics of your store page.
I say when you start marketing your game, you should start with the store page.
No amount of stuff that you do to drive people to your store page will sell your game if your store page sucks.
So when you put it up, go back to it every two weeks, review it, change things, tweak stuff.
We were named a game of the year recently by a couple of wonderful outlets,
so I've put that on a bit of artwork and slapped it on the store page.
Your store page has to look healthy and alive.
And a contributing thing to that is review numbers.
On Steam particularly, it's the sort of...
I don't know what they would call it, the review descriptor, like overwhelmingly positive
or very positive or mixed.
Heaven forbid mixed.
Oh, thank you, Your Majesty.
Kiss of death mixed.
Just give me a negative.
At least that's what's in my interest.
Maybe mixed makes people read the page a bit more like, ooh, maybe.
But what you really want is overwhelmingly positive, which is extremely hard to get.
You have to have something like 100 reviews in the last three months and it has to be
95% or more positive, which we have at the moment, which is really nice, on Sunless Skies
at least.
But the rest of the health of your page is like, can people understand your capsule image?
When they look at it, do they understand the vibe of what they're getting?
Do they get the genre of your game from what you're putting on there?
Genre is so important to convey.
It's not...
People think about, like, oh, I want to put something on telly,
I want to watch something, I want to watch a comedy,
I want to watch a thriller or something, a crime drama,
and you can tell from the pictures of these TV shows on Netflix
what they are, what type of show they are, you know?
But people, I don't think, recognise that when it comes to
pitching their games on platforms.
So selling the genre and getting, like, the actual verbs
that the player is doing and using every bit of the page, like...
I do Steam store page reviews or store page reviews every Wednesday when I'm on the train to London
and I do looking at other people's pages and just going through all these things and
so many times people have not been specific enough to describe their own game in their own tone of voice
they haven't given enough imagery, they haven't given enough sense of genre
and just a few changes of word brings the like the health rating of the page up.
And it just raises people's confidence to buy. People look at your page every day and they decide right then,
is this something I want to buy or not? And if you're like, oh, I just haven't updated my page in like a month,
then people are going to look at it and think that it's crap.
Hard truths with Flynn today.
But you have to kind of give yourself a recurring task to look at that and treat it as like, it's the shop front.
It's the book jacket for your game. It's so important.
How often do you update pages for Fail Better Games?
Yeah, for Skies I do every couple of weeks, or every time I have a new bit of news, like any Game of the Year placements or stuff like that.
For Sunless Sea a little bit less now, because it's five years old.
But I will definitely be reviewing that for the fifth birthday, which is coming up in February.
Wow. For Steam page and like kind of see what works and what graphics you want up there and stuff like that,
is that somewhere we're having in established community or like a discord you have regular
interactions with kind of comes into play where you can bounce ideas off of them or solicit
feedback directly from the community? A little. It's a bit of a curse of knowledge type thing,
double-edged sword.
The closer they are to you, the more they want to be kind to you.
So they probably would not tell you if there were lots of problems with your page.
But we have done, for example, we use Survey Monkey, we make surveys.
We had some capsule art for Sunless Skies that really wasn't doing the job for us.
So we made a survey where we put together four different variants
and we sent that out both to people who knew what we were doing
and people who never heard of our stuff.
and it really helped us figure out that what we had was too complicated
and we had some options that were like a lamp post in space, a Victorian lamp post in space
and all the people who knew our work was like, yeah, fall in London, I get it, nice
and all the people who didn't know what we did, we had way too much percentage of those people say
I don't know what I would be doing in this game.
I don't know what it is.
So now it's literally a whacking great train in space.
It's a steam train in space, and it's flying, it's coming right at you, and it's got a beautiful
serif font that says sunless skies, and it says literary, and it says fucking space train.
And it's the best-sounding space train image on Steam, I made sure of it.
So that was the answer, was, oh, I know what I'd be doing in that game.
I'd be driving a train around in space. That's cool.
Because trains are cool.
Trains are cool.
I imagine it's kind of...
a similar issue for like, when you're writing something, you're too close to the topic,
and you hand this to someone who's never interacted with games before maybe, and they're like,
I don't know what any of these words mean.
Is there a similar trap for game development and game marketing, where you have to have
these fresh eyes, or make sure you're not using the terminology too much to have a wider
appeal?
Oh, yeah.
There's, I mean...
This is something that kind of comes to me often because of my past doing marketing for other stuff.
We have quite an insular situation, certainly with PC gaming and the way that we put together our pages for these games,
where you can say things like...
Can you just say this game is a turn-based RTS and people who've already played that kind of game and like it will go cool
I'll have that that looks great, but if
There are people out there who would enjoy playing whatever that is
But would not know what that meant at all
And that jargon wall is so hard in games, and I'm never sure where my job ends.
Is my job going to be to sell these games to people who right now don't even have a
Steam account?
Is that...
it or am I selling to the Steam user?
And I think part of that conflict comes from the fact that Fallen London
is the most accessible game possible.
You play it in a web browser, you can play it with a screen reader.
So the makeup of people who play Fallen London is extremely broad.
Ages, you know, 10 to 80.
all manner of gender types, all manner of everything.
And that is not the Steam audience.
So I'm always pulled one way or the other
because we have these people who really love what we do,
but they've never played a real-time game
where you have to control something using WASAD.
And they don't want to really play that,
but they really want to get more of our stories.
So that's just like, yeah, that's a point of challenge for me all the time.
Is there a kind of similar conflict where you have your, when you've been working in the same IP for
like a decade now, trying to make things and market in a way that appeals to the people you already
have in your ecosystem versus the people who are out there and trying to get new players in?
Yeah, it's hard that.
It's hard. And Sunless Skies is a sequel, you know what I'm saying? Like, it's a sequel.
We did a lot of work to make Sunless Skies much easier to get into than Sunless Sea,
which was extraordinarily punishing to the point of being completely obfuscated
in the first couple of hours to a lot of players.
It was too difficult, just immediate nope.
So Sunless Skies has way better onboarding, and we've definitely done a lot of work
that translates to more sales of Sunless Sea.
After people have tried Skies, they're ready to go get more of the stories
and kind of put up with the fact that Skies, the sea is harder.
But I'm looking forward to doing stuff that is not a sequel in the near future.
In the medium to near future, that's going to be pretty cool.
Cool.
The way that you talk about, you know,
your career at Fail Better and just talking to us right now,
so much of it is injected with this knowledge
of your community.
It just makes me feel like you are so in tune
with the kind of audience that you wanna reach.
So my question is, you know, how do you even begin to build a community around a game and
how do you nurture that community and help it grow as time goes on?
I think with a strong perspective and what you might call a super objective, so it comes
back again to being specific.
We recently launched our own Discord, having kind of crouched on the shoulder of a community
Discord for a while, and we invited people over, and we had set it up in a way that was
very surprising to them.
in a lot of ways because that's our specific way of doing things and that's the vibe that
you get when you come to us.
And a couple of examples, we have a channel where you can self-assign pronoun roles, really
important to our community that they are able to be recognised for the gender that they
are.
So you can assign roles that are sort of laced loosely on the ones you get in Fallen London
and it's cute.
We also banned memes.
I feel like really good about it.
But people were aghast.
I mean it took about 24 hours for people to sort of go,
Oh, okay, you know, whatever.
But the fact that we've banned memes...
Which sets us apart, I think from literally every other discord I've ever looked at and I did lots of research
it
That is a statement of intent and it is specific to fail better
It encourages people to have conversations about other stuff without pulling on
You know, just the latest meme that it might be something that half of the other people in the channel get and you get to feel smart by sharing it, but not that smart really because you're sort of alienating people.
It's brought people back in from the community who'd left other spaces because they felt just excluded, that they didn't understand what was happening because they weren't like deep into meme culture.
and instead we've been talking up we were retelling Norse myths and we've
gone through a whole big recommendation thread about webcomics and about Russian
literature and all these things that are so idiosyncratic and true to what Felbeta
offer people who have literary interests people who have a huge amount of
interest outside of games and they're still happy to be in our discord what
was it the thing I said specificity and something else I was very clever when I
said it I'm sure
Yeah, we'll just, you know, our listeners can just rewind it.
And that other thing, do that as well.
Yeah, the other thing it's but yeah, I mean, I'm just talking
about the, you know, cultivating your community. And, you know,
how do you feel people end up entering your community? Like,
why does somebody come to your discord channel? Or why does
somebody want to be a part of it?
That's a really good question.
I think because it is safe and because it is different.
You can be yourself there in a way that a lot of other...
not high toxicity necessarily, but really highly online meme literate, fast velocity kind of
communities can be quite off-putting, to the extent where I think a lot of people just feel
like Discord as a general thing isn't for them. Or the way I feel when I'm watching like a live
stream with a lot of people just going kek kek kek kek kek face face face face face on Twitch,
like oh my god this isn't, this is not for me.
And in terms of people, how people find us, there's a really interesting phenomenon with Fallen London that
Ascendancy obviously brought in a lot of players to Fallen London as a persistent game.
but we still have people being referred in from TV tropes or people discover it via browsing TV
tropes or really once every six months there'll be like a free games you can play on your lunch
break thread on Reddit and Fallen London will get voted to the top and then we'll get a few
thousand people join from that um which is just extraordinary when I think of the longevity of
Fallen London but it's formed like a huge part of people's lives it's
for a small number of people, like they check in every day.
You spend actions in the game to read stories and
some people are planning a year ahead of what they're going to play,
they are grinding out a vial of Hesperidion Cider,
which is sort of an immortality juice,
which people, it's something you spend every action on for a year.
So they join the community for something to do while they're doing that.
Yeah, that's and that's one of the obviously one of the big challenges today is, you know,
there's so many games out there. And people are talking about discoverability. So, you know,
what's what's your view on today's marketplace? And how do you
You know you've talked to you've talked some ways that you've done it
But what's your view on discoverability and and being effective at getting your game in front of potential customers?
Yeah, it's much harder than it used to be and yeah
I think that's the entry-level thing to say about it isn't it really but it bears repeating
Choosing the space that you want to be in is probably
the toughest decision like making sure you have the product that will succeed in the place
you know and and then being lucky or or fortunate or timely enough to get an exclusive somewhere
that someone will pay you for that could set you up for a long time apple arcade this year has
secured the next year's development for tons of studios yeah out of nowhere um or an epic exclusive
or I think the tightening up of discoverability means that people just need to have commensurate
ambition for what they're trying to do. Being able to sustain what you're doing.
making it sustainable as as as like your first point of business
is much more important than it used to be
and it all ties into these ideas of
of crunch
and one big hit
and
being like a one big hit
you you can't look at one big hits and then do anything to
to make another one
so you have to kind of
look at your life, like it's really serious stuff, look at your life and what do you want it to be
like and can you work another job and make your indie game and you know in two evenings a week
around caring for your children and is that what you want to do and does it really make you happy?
I think that's the questioning that the democratization of the tools and platforms has led to.
Not that I want to put anyone off doing it, but just to be real.
Be real with yourself and don't hurt yourself.
We are so...
We won the Best Places to Work Award this year and in 2017 and we are sort of more proud
of that than we are even of our games.
We want people who are healthy and happy to come in and they don't dread work on a Sunday
night.
and the work works for their life.
That's what we really want.
And to keep doing it, that's the key.
Yeah, absolutely.
Do something that makes you happy.
Seems like this weird novel idea
when you frame it that way,
but there's a lot of just kind of chugging away
and making yourself miserable for this thing
that you think is gonna be this hit
or make you happy or whatever,
but you have to think day to day
rather than like the grand picture kind of.
Yeah, basically, you've only got so many hours on the planet.
Like what do you want to spend them doing?
I'll offer a podcast, get kind of existential at some point.
It's about the 40 minute mark every time.
We've cleared all the chaff now, gang.
Here's the wheat.
Well, we are starting to get to the end of our time here.
I do want to ask, because I think
this is kind of a practical question, what have you
found that have been some of the most effective tools for you
as a marketer of games?
Is it like?
email, is it trying to get featured on a storefront,
discounting games so that people see it?
Like what are some of the things that really work
that people should pay attention to?
Collaboration and strategic discounting, I would say.
The biggest things this year that have moved the needle
on selling Sunless Skies since it came out have all been
big sales, targeted sales, and digital collaboration slash events with other developers.
As an example, the publisher Fellow Traveller put together an event on Steam, within Steam, called Ludo Naracon.
Ludo, you know, narrative game con.
And it was a bunch of their games that they publish and a handful of other people who applied for it.
I saw it on Twitter and I applied for it.
Another important reason to be on Twitter because you find these things.
And that was like a three-day sale where we committed to streaming a live stream of our game on our page.
and that was on the front page of Steam in the carousel with other stuff,
but it had live features, it had live streaming features, and it had discounts,
and we were I think one of like 16 featured games.
But we were giving something to get that really fantastic placement
and really like targeted specific niche.
And we also have done like...
similar things with a slightly more altruistic bent like we were part of a steam um sale
around the charity War Child who help children in conflict do a big thing around Armistice Day in
November. So we created content within Summer Skies of an urchin, a young person who had lost
her parents in conflict and was the star-worn urchin who'd seen too much of the skies and just
wanted to hide away on your ship and she could become your ship's mascot. And because we
generated that and came up with that, again in line with the kind of stuff I'm talking about,
charitable.
And despite having a game set in Victorian times, we do not just let children get tortured and messed around in our games.
It's one of the content tenets that we had. So she's a really optimistic character.
She's not in a workhouse or something, which you'd often get in these slightly more bleak
Victorian based games.
And that enabled us to get some visibility around that sale, and then we also raised money for charity.
And I realize I'm saying all these things and it is contingent on having someone at
Steam who listens to you.
Not everyone has that.
But collaborating with other people who are at a similar level to you, or a slightly more
aspirational level than you, is a really good way to reach new audiences.
We're in a couple of bundles now, across different publishers, which makes our game appear on
the Steam pages of other games in a way that we control.
and not just algorithmically, which is pretty cool.
So those are the big successes for us.
Well, I mean, you talk about, um, I mean, you just mentioned, of course, like you
have these relationships, but I mean, fail better was at one point, you know,
you said you were employee number eight, um, and you got to start somewhere.
So, uh, yeah, it's, it's not like it's unattainable to gain these important
relationships with platform holders and whatnot.
No.
And I think you just have to.
I think a big part of what makes us look legit in the eyes of these platform holders is how
much we care about our presence on their platform.
For Steam particularly, we are sort of Steam first, you know, we're porting Sunless Skies
next year.
but we developed it with Steam audiences in mind and started there.
And we play the game, you know, our page is gorgeous, it looks great,
it's literary, it's a quality prestige sort of a game.
That's what people want to see,
it matches up with their kind of aspirations for the platform,
I feel.
It's something that you could put on itch with a really interesting indie aesthetic
and like, you know, some really traditional interactive fiction with no walking or anything.
Like, that's perfect for that platform and that will really energize that audience.
So set it all up over there and see how you get on there.
Like, tailor what you're doing to the space.
Yeah, yeah, it seems like a theme there, being specific and tailoring it for the space.
So is there any parting thoughts before we let you go? You're in the UK.
Yes, my bedtime.
Yeah, it's bedtime.
It's not even late, I'm just a parent.
Oh yeah, I mean, me too, I get it.
Yeah.
Yeah, is there any parting thoughts, you know, tips for indies who are kind of trying to get their bearings
marketing in this really tumultuous and difficult marketplace?
just do something now, do something now
because it's the same thing as prototyping, you don't know
what the finished product will look like and how it will behave until you've tried something
and there's a lot of paralysis in the face of
oh god, I don't even know, what should I tweet?
what did you work on today that would make a funny or interesting gif
that is in reasonable shape but you don't mind showing to people
tweet it, target IndieDevHour
show it to someone, you know, begin by doing, begin by doing and don't sit on your laurels
because you need that, you need that cultivation time ahead of you.
All right, that sounds like a great place to stop and thank you so much for joining
us Hannah and...
Thank you for having me.
Yeah, of course, and best of luck with all your future endeavors.
Thank you.
And we're back. That was a great conversation.
Oh yeah, that was. Marketing's wild.
Yeah, I know. It's difficult just the attention span of people, uh, you know, and it's, I mean,
it's me too. I'm not criticizing people for having the attention span of a, of a butterfly
these days. I'm the same way. It's just we're, we all get pulled in so many directions now.
Even when I'm playing a game, I noticed that I get distracted by other games
and then I go and start playing another game. Do you do that?
yeah especially the last like month of the year when i'm like oh i want to do my godi list stuff
oh uh but this game looks really cool oh but what if i play red dead online
for five hours every day instead and like it's
Yeah, yeah, I know. I keep getting distracted by these, these older games and it, you know,
it like Destiny 2. I'm randomly decide to get back into Destiny 2 when I need to be catching up.
Well, it was good before, but like they did a lot of good changes recently,
so you're going to be hooked.
Yeah, I know. I like it.
Yeah, but that's not a 2019 game.
Shadowkeep came out, I guess.
I guess that you can kind of, that's
why it's difficult with these end of year lists.
Like press outlets, we kind of, I
think we should keep on doing it to recognize the new things
that come out every year.
But we do it as a kind of tradition, and a tradition
that.
You know, I as an editor, I sometimes question the value of it because people do play, you
know, there's so many live games now.
Like what's a 2019 game?
And is the game disqualified for this reason or that or the other?
I always found like, I think every year I've written a game of the year list for Gamasutra,
I've gotten Hitman on there.
I don't think it's going to be on there this year, but I'll figure it out.
You'll find a way to get Hitman on there.
But it's because of live games and like, oh, I will.
And there's just like, yeah, games are, they aren't this like one-time event anymore.
The entire landscape has changed.
Yeah.
Yeah, and a game that might have launched this year that stinks might be good next year.
It might be great next year.
And what, they just missed the boat on the accomplishments that they got?
Ubisoft's Rainbow Six Siege was like, when it launched in 2014, I don't go out and battle
with years, when it launched several years ago, it was like a shadow of what it is now.
It wasn't that great, and now that game is doing really well, it's got a solid community,
it was up for an award at the Game Awards because they recognized in that way that games
are kind of like this process that evolves beyond a launch, especially when you take
as good care of it as Ubisoft has, and they're really good at that.
Yeah. And to segue this back into marketing discussion with Hannah.
Marketing.
Yeah. I mean, that is marketing. Live games, like it's like, there's so much
marketing involved with these games that are updated constantly and, you know,
feel better. Um, they also update their games regularly. Uh, they're living, if
you will. And.
Well, and while the games are living the steam pages for them are kind of like evolving in a similar way as well
Or that process never really stops. It just changes. Yeah
Yeah, and you know
It's been like this forever. I feel like with indie games in particular
People don't you know, they just don't market their their games enough or they don't
You know
do it with the same kind of intention that Hannah does.
I mean, she clearly does her research,
like deep research on the audience, on what they want,
how to better serve them, how to expand your audience.
She talks about, you know, the store page,
which seems like an obvious.
thing. People know that they should have a store page and they're going to have a store page,
but what makes a good store page? You know, when you Google a game's name, its title,
that's what you come across. The, you know, the Steam page or the main page.
Not just a placeholder, it is an advertisement for the product you're trying to release and
yeah, it's easy to forget that. Yeah. And like there were
Oh, go ahead.
Sorry.
I was just going to say that the people who are Googling
the game in particular, they're already aware of it,
or else they wouldn't be Googling the name of the game.
So they're finding that they're already
close to being part of your community,
to being converted into a customer.
They're that close.
And then they get to the page, and then they
might just be like, oh.
As we said during the broadcast interview.
There were a lot of takeaways that I didn't write down fast enough because my keyboard
is loud.
But the fact that marketing should be a day one part of the development process is something
that like...
I think it's not the easiest thing to wrap your head around, because what am I going
to do day one?
But she had some very good advice for what you should do in those early stages.
But otherwise it can be too easy to kind of be like, okay, well, I'm going to work on
my game.
And then now that I have something shippable, I'm going to start, now that it's ready to go,
I'm going to start getting attention on it. And like, you can't segment the process like that.
No.
She had a lot of really good advice on how to kind of bring that process together and
weave marketing throughout every step of the development process, which was nice.
Yeah. And I hear similar stuff from other people who market games, particularly.
indie games, you know
it's funny because you know, I keep an eye on the Steam charts and
Sometimes it'll be like this number one game just came out of nowhere. It's like then you Google it
It's like oh it didn't come out of nowhere. They've been
Doing like they've they've been cultivating this community on reddit
for the past two years, three years. So there is like this perception among some developers that
oh this game just came out of nowhere, like they must have you know gotten linked somewhere,
got lucky, or just... They had a good idea and it took off on its own. Yeah, it took off on its own, which...
I can't think of a case.
I guess if I thought hard enough, I could think of an exception.
But it's usually like when you see that, quote unquote,
out of nowhere hit on Steam, number one.
Do yourself a favor and Google the name and then find the reddit page
like that's been there for like three years that has crap loads of followers and
And then you'll see that and learn from that. Yeah. Yeah, absolutely
So, yeah, let's talk about like the end of end of year stuff real quick end of year stuff
Yeah, we're planning things earlier than we did last year. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
For Gamasutra, we do, uh, uh, our end of year lists and, uh, yeah, we, I'm also
pushing back a little bit when we're going to publish these, we're gonna do
it, some of the big ones properly.
We're going to wait until the end of the year, just in case something comes right
before the stroke of midnight on New Year's Eve, if a game comes out and it's
just like mind blowing, and then we can laugh at everybody who published their
list too early.
Someone did that last year where everyone was like, all right, I got my list ready to go.
And then the next day, some really cool indie dev published some really cool game.
And I'm like, ah, yeah, that'd be, uh, that's what I would do.
If I was an indie developer, like a really talented one.
People's gaming your list.
Yeah.
Just like release my amazing game right before the stroke of midnight on New Year's Eve.
That'll really get those journalists.
That'll show them.
We've got best trends coming up in comics future best events best devs. Yeah of the year and then best games
That's not all of the categories we hit. Yeah, we're all gonna do games
Apple arcade games. Yeah. Yeah, I don't really like a lot of Apple arcade games this year. There's some good stuff
It's my Grindstone subscription, but sometimes I remember to branch out a little bit.
I like having narrative games on my phone, so that's really nice.
Yeah, Grindstone is great.
Bleak Sword is incredible.
I will sing Neocab's praises.
It's so good.
Yeah.
Dear Reader is another one that is very good, that doesn't have a lot of, like, cool...
characters or attention or anything on it, I think, but it's just a really cool literary
puzzle.
It's really great.
It's a lot of fun.
I stayed up until 4am playing it.
Yeah.
It's been interesting seeing the kinds of games that are being recognized.
Some of them are kind of what you would expect on other publications' top 10 lists, like
you got Outer Wilds.
That's being really talked about, that's a great game.
I know, right?
Yeah.
The first 10 minutes are great.
I don't have any free time.
Hey, you got plenty of time.
You got, I'll get it to it after my list is written before the end of the year,
unfortunately, but yeah.
Just make sure to play it before the stroke of midnight.
Years, even it can make, make your list.
So yeah, I think that that's all for this week for the GDC podcast.
two more podcasts away from GDC itself.
Yeah, we are officially two podcasts away from GDC,
which I don't know what our podcast plans are exactly,
but might get a torrent of,
like a torrential downpour of podcasts
out of GDC during GDC week.
But that's not a promise.
All that good content.
There'll be good content no matter what.
Yeah, there'll be some kind of hashtag content.
Yeah, so check us out on iTunes, Google Play, Spotify,
and we're at YouTube where you can stare at a static picture
and listen to us or just change tabs on us
and just listen to us out of your computer speakers.
We'll never know either way.
Yeah, you could play a video game
that we are talking about on the podcast on your computer
while listening to it.
I'm not sure. I think my brain is melting.
It's the last month of the year.
It's the last couple of weeks of the year.
Yeah, it's just, it melted.
It's gone.
Yeah.
All right, everyone.
Thanks again.
Thank you.
If you enjoy us, if you love us,
leave us a good review, give us a thumbs up on YouTube,
give us a five star review on iTunes.
I mean, this is what we have to do, right?
That's what Hannah was talking about.
Reviews are important for podcasts too.
Yeah, that's right.
They really are.
Please like.
Yeah, please like.
Be kind.
All right, thanks everyone and we'll see you next time.
Bye.
you