Hello, hello.
Wow, a lot of people in for 9 o'clock.
I didn't expect that.
Thank you.
I got 30 minutes.
So I'm going to begin now.
It's a lot to cover.
Basically, I'm going to talk about, and I kind of did this
presentation for people not wanting to get into the games
business.
That's not what I'm going to focus on.
I'm focusing on once you get there, how to survive.
How many people are working for R&Ds?
OK.
How many people are working for game companies?
Good old mix.
I started out as an indie with a group of guys in our early 20s.
We formed a studio, lasted for about five years.
And then after that, I started working for game companies.
Now I'm back at an indie.
I'm kind of circular here.
I've created three studios from the ground up
in Austin, Texas.
Vioware Austin, Sony Austin, and Battlecry Studios now,
Bethesda Game Studios, from scratch.
And it's been a lot of fun.
And I learned a lot by doing that.
And so what I learned is kind of like what
I look for in the games industry and how to survive.
Because one of the things that you're going to notice
There's a 90% chance of the demon, I call it,
the layoff demon, will hit you.
And by the way, don't feel bad about that,
it's kind of a rite of passage in the games business.
It will happen probably within the first five years
of your career, if you're with a game company
or even with an indie.
Average lifespan in the company is about four years,
I found, just kind of looking around.
Change is inevitable.
Our industry changes so much.
You look at all the disruptions that
have happened in the past 10 years in our game industry
and what's coming with streaming.
and other things like that VR, AR, it's a new,
this particularly I think in the next 10 years
will be totally different than what you see today
as far as entertainment or as far as what we develop.
And one of the things I noticed too,
and every game company I've worked for,
is there really isn't any onboarding to say.
There are some at places.
Training is non-existent in a lot of places.
And mentoring and career growth, secondary.
And that's unfortunate.
And a lot of things I've done for training
has just gone on on my own or come here to GDC.
One of the observations too is there's a delicate balance,
and it's actually getting better now,
but when I started it wasn't, between work life.
This industry can chew you up.
You work long hours, a lot of times with no rest.
Again, it has gotten a lot better today
than it was 10 years ago.
But something to, you know,
these are things you need to be aware of.
There's a hierarchy in our business.
And these are just kind of observations right now
I'm going over to you and then I'll tell you,
get into the meat of this.
Programmers are king, secondary design,
third is artist, fourth is QA on the ladder.
And it's bizarre because if a game isn't fun,
it's not gonna do anything.
And designers are, in my opinion,
are not as high as programmers are.
And I think that in our industry is just screwed up.
And QA is not respected, which I totally are against.
And by the way, a lot of really good people
came out of QA in gaming.
One thing I'm going to talk about is culture.
So wherever you go, whether you're an indie studio,
you're going to have a culture.
Whether you're going for a game company,
they're going to have a culture.
And it's really important to learn what that culture is.
And if you're looking for a job,
to make sure you see if you're compatible with that culture.
A lot of cultures are top-down.
When you see a top-down culture,
you see you walk into the place and it's very quiet.
Easily an indicator.
And groups are separated.
And then there's bottoms up.
And how you fit on that will be something you need to learn.
So in a top-down, you're taking orders.
In a bottom-up, it's kind of a more collaborative type
of development.
So if people don't like the top-down approach,
then maybe that's not a good cultural fit for you.
There is places I've seen, and even indies are like this,
they're either design-heavy or tech-heavy.
And so you need to see how you fit in in that kind of place.
Because it all goes into how, what kind of voice you'll have.
And again, it's like DNA matching.
So as you're forming your indie studios,
make sure that you form something
that you all will appreciate and like,
and as you grow, can bring people into it.
I always had, when I started a studio,
any size studio is my core values
and what our mission statement is.
If you're indie, that's the first thing you should do,
is figure that out.
And that's something you abide by as you grow and as you are
successful and as you hire people.
Because when you're hiring when everyone goes for an interview
for a job they're looking at number one your hard skills
what you're good at.
Number two is can you be a cultural fit.
That's what a lot of people use because if you're not you're
going to be swimming upstream.
And sometimes that happens.
And it's not all against you,
you just don't fit within that culture,
don't take it personally.
And what I'm gonna talk about is soft skills now.
Because soft skills is something
that people don't really talk a lot about in our industry.
But it really is,
important. In fact, I think it's more important than your hard skills, because you can learn
hard skills really easily. There's so many great gaming schools out there today teaching
stuff you can go learn on or come here. You're going to be working with a variety of different
weird people in our industry, and you're going to have tons of personalities to deal with
here. I see it all the time, and I just accept it.
Artists have their personalities, designers have their personalities,
programmers have their personalities.
And so you're going to have to learn how to adjust and fit to that.
And that's where soft skills come in.
One of the most important soft skills is what I call emotional intelligence.
And some people are not self-aware on that front.
Self-awareness is really critical.
If I had to say anything about one of the biggest things about emotional
intelligence,
Egos have got to be left aside in our industry.
I've seen so many people not be self-aware.
If you're not self-aware, you're not gonna learn,
and you're not gonna grow,
and you're not gonna be able to succeed
in an entertainment-type company.
So being self-aware is really at all this,
and that's why it's on the top.
It's the most important thing.
and self-management too.
Understanding how to deal with your time,
how to deal with others, and social awareness.
Social awareness is really, really important.
Where, and when you go to work for a company,
you kind of like see, what I always do
is I don't say anything.
And when I came to my last job, which I work out today,
I only knew one person.
That was terrifying to me.
Because I've always started up studios and formed them,
and grew it, and went with the people I know to start them.
So this was really important for me
to figure out how the social structure exists in a studio.
And relationship management is another one.
These people you work with a lot.
And it's really important to make sure, and by the way,
there's a one degree separation in our gains business.
So if you piss someone off, likelihood you'll maybe be
seeing them again and they may be your hiring manager.
And that goes for anybody in this room that are really
young and starting too.
Because one day, I may be looking for a job, right?
Another skill I think is really important in this
business is called adaptability.
You really have to learn how to be adaptable.
You can't be rigid in our business.
Our business changes way too fast, way too much,
versus any other business.
By the way, it's chaotic.
And I'll tell you what, I like chaos.
And I think anybody that does games
and thinks games are easy to make,
they ought to not be in gaming.
Games are probably one of the hardest things to build,
in my opinion.
They require so much multidisciplinary talent.
Lots of people working together to make it happen.
And it's magic.
It's lightning in a bottle whether you hit it or not.
Another one, in my opinion, is being collaborative.
You have to learn to work well with each other.
I told, someone asked me, well, what did you learn?
What are the skills you learned to manage a studio?
Well, I said, I learned everything
when I went to first grade.
And I said, draw between the lines, play well with others.
These are things that are really, really important
as you grow, even if you're indie.
Collaboration is sometimes hard,
because as a smaller studio you are,
sometimes you have bigger conflicts, believe it or not,
because they're amplified because of your size.
Learning how to get people to be collaborative is an art.
And it comes with this.
Ego doesn't really work well in our business.
There are a lot of egos in our business.
I'll tell you that right now.
And I'll tell you what.
Some of them are very good at damping that down and not
exposing it to a lot of people.
Some are not.
And ego in our business can lead to bad decisions.
And you need a little humility mixed into that.
So humility, in my opinion, is one of the best things
to have as a soft skill.
You need to be confident.
This is real important.
If you're an indie, if you're going to a publisher
or going to get finance, you need
to show them that you can do the job that you
said you're going to do.
that I'm going to give you money and the likelihood of me getting my investment back is high.
If you go in there not confident, you're not going to get anything from a publisher or
an investor.
As a developer, people look at you and you say, yes, I can do this.
Confidence, being insecure, is something you don't want.
If you are, a lot of people are.
I've been insecure at times, but I don't show it.
I try to have a persona of confidence.
That's really important as you're successful.
But another side of that,
if you don't know how to do something,
there's nothing wrong with saying,
I don't know how to do that, help me.
Ask for help.
This is another one I think that in our industry is hard.
Some people are really good at it, and I've seen,
and some people are really, really bad at it.
Learn how to listen.
Understand, look through the lens of other people, their perspective,
and then communicate concisely, not a thesis.
I think one of the biggest things I've seen people do
in communications is write a thesis.
Get to the point.
But be delicate if it's something that is a delicate situation, but get to the point.
One of the things that I think there's the other side of this
is called a nonverbal communications.
The way you stand up, the way you act,
this is very important in a game company
as well as an indie company.
Because again, indies, if you go for a publisher or investment
and you have bad body language, you're not going to get it.
Make sure that you look at the way you're acting.
Because even when you're in a meeting,
you put your head down when someone's saying that,
that's not a good thing all the time.
It's learn how to have both verbal and nonverbal
communication skills are really important.
There are many types of people you're gonna deal with
in the games business.
Even in small teams, it's really there.
You have the rational people.
I call them the engineers.
They're the rational people.
The producers are trying to be rational as well.
You have the extroverts and you have the introverts.
And I'm kind of like an introvert myself a little bit,
more so than extrovert.
And it's hard to push yourself out of that.
And some people are extremely emotional.
And I will tell you, you're going to have bosses
that cover this spectrum.
I had an emotional boss once, and he
was a very abusive person.
And it was an awful situation to be in.
It's really hard to deal with.
And so.
Having soft skills is why I think it's important.
You have to deal with all these three or four different types.
And sometimes when you're an introvert,
the best way as a producer I am to get an introvert to talk
is I ask them specific questions in a meeting.
Extroverts you don't have to worry about.
Emotional people, you just talk to facts.
You don't get emotional yourself.
You talk about facts, and if it's not working, you just say,
OK, I think we need to take a break for a minute.
Rational people are a lot easier to deal with,
a lot easier to deal with.
But sometimes they can get too rational about things,
and you say, well, look, take a leap of faith.
So those are things about, again,
what I saw about building confidence.
Why are these important?
Because I will tell you, if you do get reviews.
The people who have the best soft skills by the way and hard
skills get the outstanding or the excellent people who don't
get satisfactory or below satisfactory a game company.
So if you want to advance your careers go out and look for
good books on soft skills.
There are many times in our game industry
that you're going to have these moments.
We're all familiar with them.
And they happen.
And the way that I deal with those moments
is I take a breath.
I go outside and walk around.
I don't respond in email.
Please don't do that.
Take time.
Walk around outside or do something different.
Get away.
think about it, come back, and then deal with it at that particular moment.
But I will tell you, I've seen people respond very quickly to those moments that they regret later.
And so I always kind of like, I say, I need a pause, and I need to go think for a minute.
A lot of times when you do that, you can look through the lens of whatever's happening and
figure out how to get around it. But our game industry is full of these moments, by the way.
Stress is something that we deal with a lot.
It's very stressful to do games.
I have not been in a situation that hasn't been stressful.
It always comes down to you have this passionate thing
you worked on, this baby, and someone says it's ugly.
And that's the worst thing you can hear,
is your baby is ugly.
And you have to sit down and go, I'm going to kill that guy.
And you get very passionate about it.
All the reviewers say, your baby's baby.
Your baby's ugly.
No.
And so you have this fear when you launch that things
aren't going to go right.
You have this fear that you're not
going to get money from your publisher
because you're missing deadlines and they're
going to cancel your project.
We have a fear of losing our jobs.
That's stressful.
And the way I deal with stress is yoga and workout.
But seriously, one of the things I do
is I always kind of look forward.
I don't look back.
I look at the situation I have on hand.
It's not life and death.
here. There are many moments in your lives that be a much
dealing with much force worse things than this. But it's
about everyone's passionate about it. So what I learned is
to kind of like deal with stress is to kind of put it in
perspective and immediately try to look for ways of dealing
with the stress to look for solutions or the way out.
Look forward, not look back.
Don't sit down and just go into a loop, what I call it,
of always saying, and I call this the abused puppy syndrome.
Some people may come from a very bad place
and they start working in a new place,
but they got that abused puppy syndrome.
So anything you do, they're gonna look at it
from their lens of where they were, not where they are.
It's real important to know that you're here.
It's not like where you are.
Leave your luggage behind, your baggage behind.
Leave it.
That's my advice.
Always look forward.
One of the things I do is even when I schedule or everything,
I don't look in front of me.
I look where I'm going.
Everyone should look where they're going.
And for that, for advice to everyone here,
and this is kind of harsh a little bit,
but what I've learned is no one's going
to stand up for you but you.
And in our, and it goes for any business,
but in particularly our business,
you could get laid off any day, they don't care.
Loyalty in my opinion is something that I have not seen
or earned from any game company yet.
Because if things go bad, they'll get rid of you.
If you have a great opportunity,
if you love the people you work with
and you love your job, fantastic.
If things don't work, or if you get a greater opportunity,
always look for the greater opportunity at times.
Because you never know what that opportunity is,
and it may be something that the place
that you currently have doesn't offer you.
Or you think you're worth more than what you're getting.
Always look out for yourself.
But be careful about being careful what to ask for.
You always have to look at the situation
that you're currently in.
The company may not be doing well,
or the average salaries of that company
are a little lower than most.
But if you like, my opinion is,
my most important criteria is,
do I like the people I work with?
Is the company culture something I enjoy and like?
And is there a work-life balance?
And that what we're working on is cool.
And if I meet those criteria, I'm fine.
I am fine.
So, I have some time.
Like 10 minutes for questions.
Anybody want to ask questions?
Yes.
Go to the mic.
Sorry.
Go up to the mics, please.
Thank you.
That way we can hear the recordings.
Testing.
OK.
Do you have any soft skill books that come to mind?
What do you recommend?
Yeah.
I'm trying to think about some good ones out there.
that I've seen.
You know what there is?
There's nothing on the gaming industry.
I wish there was.
I'll tell you what.
You email me.
I'll give you some books.
Thank you.
That'll do.
I have some at home, and I can just pick out.
Yeah, go ahead.
Hi, so you mentioned that you had an abusive boss that was emotional at times.
When you're asked the question of what was the context of the problem and how did you
manage it, how do you talk about that experience?
When you get an emotional boss, the best thing to do is to ask questions versus anything
else because that makes them respond.
And don't be defensive.
Ask questions at why, why do you see this, or what do you think are the issues that you're
upset about, right?
Always ask questions.
Don't make statements because they always end to be bad.
Because when you ask questions, you actually can get the viewpoint or the lens that person
is looking for.
I also kind of like if he's really hot right now or very emotional, I wait.
Come back later.
Also be careful about the group thing.
If you're going to ask something that's kind of, should you ask that with a group of people
or should you do that one on one?
That's a really important one, because a person one-on-one
will talk to you a lot differently
than a person in a group, right?
And trust me, there are certain things you ask in a group,
and there are certain things you don't ask in a group.
And I've been there where I had some of my people
in my studio go up to a CEO of a company
and ask this question.
I said, oh my God, I can't believe he just asked
that question in front of the company.
But yeah, that's the other criteria.
Yes.
So you mentioned having both humility and confidence.
How do you sort of balance those,
and I guess in an outward way to be a bit of both?
Yeah, I mean, I like confidence, right?
Confidence doesn't mean,
if you're confident in what you're doing,
you believe what you're doing.
Now, sometimes a good game designer
is stubborn a little bit.
and confident that's OK if they believe in what they believe in and they have a good
rationale for it and the data is showing that they're moving in the right direction.
Yeah.
I'm on.
There's nothing wrong with a good argument but if you're wrong and the data showing you're
wrong you need to have humility to recognize that right.
OK.
Thank you.
Yeah.
In one slide you mentioned that programmers are on top and designers are below.
So I'm a programmer myself and I'm thinking, OK, how does that affect, in your view, the situation?
What can I do as a programmer to remedy this?
You know what? This is just a hierarchy I've seen.
A lot of companies value technical people over design, which is crazy.
And I don't get it.
Every studio I have, I balance that. I don't do that.
And I have pressure from above telling me,
no, you need to give this person this amount
for bonuses and this person.
I said, no, this person is the reason
this game got an 87 Metacritic, right?
Or these people are.
And to me, that's messed up in our industry.
I've just seen it so much.
And to me, designers are king,
because a game isn't fun, it's not gonna be played.
And fun, by the way, so here's another thing.
Programming is measurable.
Design is this magic black box.
It really is.
It's hard to test for.
It's hard to hire for, because you
don't know if someone's a walker or a talker
when they're a designer.
We do have tests.
They help call it out.
But tests don't catch everything.
So it is and I think design and art are not the black boxes as well as I think QA is also
that way but design is this little, it's magic.
It really is what design skills are.
There's several different versions of what designers are and there's several types of
designers, but it is and I think that's the reason because they don't know how to quantify
a good designer, right?
They only quantify a good designer by what they've worked on, right?
Go ahead. Is that. I hope that answers your question. I don't know how to deal with that. It's really the culture. Right.
Whatever company you have has a good culture where design is king. That's that's awesome. That's a culture that I like because
usually a culture that we're design is really appreciated and respected. Blizzard. It's that's where you get good games.
Yeah, so with those problems that you mentioned before,
like the top-down culture and the weird sort of hierarchy
that he just brought up, what do you
think about unions and co-ops helping with that a little bit
with the culture?
So I'm not a big fan of unions.
I don't know.
I heard all this going on.
Do you know how the film and I came out of,
I went to USC film school.
I came out of the film business to go into games.
You're hired freelancers.
That's all you are.
And basically, they make a, they have,
the studios have staff, right?
And they have executive producers and things like that.
But directors, DPs, all that's hired to make a film.
So if we go to that model,
that's exactly what may happen is we're all freelancers.
So we're getting paycheck to paycheck on games.
And by the way, getting in clicks
of where the good people are in Hollywood is hard, real hard.
So if they're making a blockbuster AAA movie,
they know the group they're going to get.
They know the group of people they're going to hire.
And if you're not on that group, you may not get hired.
So there may be a lot of content that
needs to be done in the games business, but I don't know.
In my opinion, yes, there are good positive things about unions, about work-life balance
and things like that, that forces that.
But again, how is the publisher going to deal with that, I don't know.
I really don't.
pushing publishers to do good work like balance by having by
companies that promote that and get the good talent there I
think is a good indicator about how to push that forward where I
seen work like balance happen to be honest with you just as a
long answer your question.
I see crunch happen because schedules are top down not
bottoms up.
That's the number one cause of crunch in my opinion.
in our industry that I've seen in the past 20 years is top down schedules versus bottom
up.
And the realities, by the way, of a business, meaning you have to get a title done by a
certain time, but there are casualties with that too if it's not successful due to an
unrealistic schedule.
But again, I don't know how the industry is going to handle
unions or anything.
But I know how it happened in the film business is it just
basically, it's all freelancers.
So I don't know if that's going to happen or not.
But that's what happened in the film and
video industry.
Yes, go ahead.
So on your hierarchy, it was very interesting.
But I did not notice writers anywhere.
Are they so low value that they wouldn't even be on the
people?
No.
No, writers are, where I worked at Bioware,
writers are designers, right?
We call them narrative designers.
That's what writers are in that field.
They're not anywhere off the charts,
just because you're a writer, you know what I'm saying?
They're narrative designers, that's what we call writers.
Cool, thanks.
So don't worry about that.
I love writers.
Story's important.
So you talked a lot about culture and sort of the work life balance at a company can vary from company to company.
Do you have any tips or suggestions on how best to assess that before you're in the position of like during the interview or something to ask for something like that?
I always ask to go to the bathroom and then get lost.
There's a reason I do that, because I want to see how people are interacting.
I watch a lot.
I watch the people's faces.
I watch the people, the way they communicate with each other.
I see how they're working around their desk.
It's that kind of thing.
How quiet it is, is another one.
And then, the second thing I do is, there's a time you take a break.
There's always a smokers area.
That's a great area to kind of walk to.
Usually you can find it and just ask questions.
You know, that's my other tip for that.
But yeah, just look, watch, and listen.
And I also would go to LinkedIn
and look for other people who work there
and maybe ask directly, hey, I'm looking at there,
what's it like?
That's another, that's second degree versus first degree
trying to get that information because the people are gonna
interview you, are gonna give you a different perspective
than going out and trying to get it yourself, right?
Yeah.
And I would also, at LinkedIn, look for people
who worked there before.
Maybe they don't work there now.
That's another one.
That's good.
Go, we'll have one over here sometime.
Go ahead.
Hi, my name's Anna.
So you kind of covered like many things
that are kind of like.
issues in the game industry.
You talked about how it's come far along since, like you said,
10 years.
What are some things that, what's
some advice you can give to us that we
can help to move along in improving the things
that we still have issues with?
Yeah, I mean, basically, if you see work-life balance problems,
make a big issue out of that, talk about it, and bring it up.
And if it's that way, and you're not liking it,
look for another job.
Look for another place in the industry.
Because it's not worth it that way.
And if you see chaos in a game, games are chaotic.
I'll tell you that right now.
No matter where you go, they're always chaotic.
And no matter where you go, I will tell you, you always put in a little extra effort.
It's a matter of what the duration of that extra effort is.
A lot of times when I ask, when we go into deadlines, I ask people to move, put some
extra effort in.
I ask, I first of all give them goals so they know what they need to do.
It's all voluntary and there are guidelines for it, meaning duration, other things like
that.
And I don't continue it.
It's like a basically accelerate release,
accelerate release, it's not constant.
But anything entertainment wise,
and even in film and video,
everyone puts in extra effort when the release comes in.
It always happens.
I'd be honest with you, no matter where you go on that,
that's always the case in the entertainment industry, right?
Yeah, sounds about right.
So I mean just that's what I'd say just push it forward and be
a voice in it right. Yeah. You look at E.A. E.A. had the E.A.
wives got a huge issue with them right along 10 years ago I think
it was and they they changed the way he operated for a while. So
that was good. I actually have a spouse I think he a spouse. Yes.
Was that.
Sorry I didn't mean to interrupt.
That's all right.
I kind of have another question, actually.
Do they advocate for certain issues?
Do they have any, I don't know, I don't want to say social
justice kind of?
You know, any company, the problem is just
bringing awareness.
If people start leaving, that builds awareness, OK?
Next question and then I think I have.
Yes.
For someone who is a programmer who also has interest in being a designer, what do you
say about programmers who also have design skills?
Oh, that's awesome.
No, that's where I came from.
So I was a programmer, then I became a designer, and then I became a producer.
But yes, and when I started, by the way,
most producers were designers.
And sorry, most programmers were designers, by the way.
So in the 90s, when I was started,
you would not see a lot of designers.
You'd see programmers that were designers.
that are designers and that's the way the industry was for a long time in the 90s and
the 80s too, but from what I heard, but in the 90s for sure and then probably in around
2000 and beyond it started, you started fractioning off the different disciplines.
But nothing wrong with being a, going to design track, being a pro, in fact that's a good
thing.
It's good to have programming and design skills together in that case.
Yes, it is.
It's very, very good.
Yes.
Thank you.
Is it time?
No, thank you.
Thank you, everyone.