Good afternoon, everyone.
Thanks for coming by at the very, very end of GDC.
Happy to see so many people here.
This is Legal Battle Royale, Not Boring Edition.
And put bluntly, the idea is to go
through hot and interesting topics in the game industry
from a legal perspective, but in a way that's going
to be useful to non-lawyers.
So can I get a sense of who in the audience,
how many lawyers do we have here?
Okay, oh, uh-oh.
Uh-oh, sleeper agents.
But for those of you who are non-lawyers,
I assume that most of you are here
because you have either some questions
or you want to get a better sense
of how legal issues are going to impact decisions
you make as developers or publishers.
I think what we're going to do is maybe take about half the time to go through a couple
of topics that we consider pretty interesting and that are currently kind of hot legal topics
that we think there's something important to say about, and then about halfway through
we'll switch over to audience questions.
And I've got a million things we could talk about, so if there aren't a lot of burning
questions we can always go back to that.
So, I think I'm going to go through and allow everyone to introduce themselves.
I'll start.
My name is Chris Reed.
I'm in-house counsel for Tilting Point, who is a mobile game publisher and growth marketing
company in New York.
And then we have Stephen.
Right.
I'm Stephen MacArthur.
I will stand up just one time so that everyone on that side of the room can see me.
Hello.
I'm Stephen MacArthur.
I'm a developer.
My name is Stephen MacArthur.
I run a small law firm of four or five attorneys in Los
Angeles, and we work with video game developers.
I'll also stand up and wave to the other people with crazy
colored hair.
I'm Mona Ibrahim.
I'm with Interactive Entertainment Law Group.
We are based in El Segundo, California,
which is in Los Angeles.
And we represent about 300 companies, publishers, and
developers, all exclusively in the game space.
My name is Greg Boyd.
I am partner at Frankfurt Kernet, Klein & Selz.
We have office in New York and in Los Angeles.
We're a media and entertainment firm in general.
But my group is mainly interactive entertainment.
And I do about the other half of my time in advertising.
So I think before we get started,
there's two things I want to do.
And the first is that in the interests
of helping bridge the gap between lawyers and humans,
I've gotten some visual signifiers.
A lot of times people say,
hey, can you give me that contract
in like human readable format?
Which I've always taken a little bit of offense to
because it implies that lawyers aren't humans.
But-
We're not.
Yeah, not fully human.
We're more human than human.
Totally cyborgs, by the way.
Yeah.
So, the idea is going to be that a lot of questions we're going to answer from a legal
perspective, giving sort of an angle from our legal knowledge, but then there may also
be cultural or non-legal aspects to the question.
And I want to be really distinct as when we're talking as lawyers and when we're speaking
as humans.
So to that end, we've got two sets of hats so that you can, we can literally wear our
lawyer hats when we're being lawyers and wear our human hats when we're pretending to be
human.
So.
Wait, pretending?
Yeah, emulating.
You're giving away the gifts.
Do I get to keep this?
Because this is awesome.
Oh, absolutely.
Oh, this is badass.
That's the gift.
There you go.
Best swag, best swag of GDC.
I know, I'm sorry.
It's okay.
I'm sorry.
You can hold it up.
I'll still wear it.
You don't have to wear it.
All right, I'm going to start as lawyer.
What are you going to be?
I'm going to be human.
And the second thing I want to point out is,
and you've of course heard this if you've ever
dealt with lawyers, but we do not represent any of you.
Our firms are not representing you.
When we speak, we're giving generalized information
about legal issues and not specific legal advice
that you should go home and act on.
So I know that there will be questions where it's like,
well, my friend has this really specific scenario.
We can tell you generally about it,
but it's not legal advice.
And I think it also is important to state
that we all work for firms or for companies,
and the opinions we're gonna give
do not reflect those of the companies we work for
or any of the clients.
And there'll be certain issues
upon which some of the panelists cannot speak
because they may be working
with people involved in those issues.
So if someone is, yeah.
The human hats will be helpful there, but even then it's,
so if someone gets a little cagey,
it's probably because they're working,
you know, we're talking about one of their clients.
Okay, so with that, I'm just gonna jump around
to a couple of issues that I think probably
are top on people's minds that they've heard about.
And I think we kind of have to start with dancing.
I think everyone's aware that there's been a series of,
a series of lawsuits leveled at Epic for dances
that you can buy as emotes in Fortnite.
And they're not the only company that has emotes
that may be based on identifiable real-world dances.
But I think I wanted to throw it open to the panel.
From a legal perspective, how...
how likely are any of these suits to succeed?
And can we maybe just give a quick primer
on why you think that and how the law in this area works
and what the implications may be for any games using emotes
since mocap is becoming more and more common in games?
Sure, so I'll start and I'll let you both of course jump in and interrupt me as you
please.
So this issue is very, and I will be wearing my lawyer hat for this, for sure.
Okay, so the issue here is what is protectable?
So what happened for those that don't know is
there are these dances that have been popularized
and sometimes created by certain people.
They're often simple dance steps, two or three moves,
and these people become known for them.
And Fortnite, you can buy emotes in Fortnite
such that you can make your character do that certain dance.
And in every situation,
situation, they've renamed the dance. So, for example, this rapper 2 Millie created
something called the Millie Rock in 2014 and popularized it.
Can you show us?
I don't know it.
You didn't pay for the emote.
I did not pay for the emote.
But, so he popularizes this,
and it becomes known as the Milly Rock.
So in Fortnite, they rename it to,
I don't remember, something else.
The Fresh is what they call it, I think.
But they don't call it the Milly Rock.
And they don't use 2Milly's name,
they don't use his likeness.
All they're using is his dance moves.
So this begs the question,
if they steal his creation from him,
and they use it to make money.
What cause of action does 2MILLI have? How can he be reimbursed for this?
Cause of action means right to sue someone.
Yes, yes. When you sue someone, when you file a lawsuit, you have causes of action such as breach of contract.
It has to fit in a certain bucket. You can't just sue someone because.
So...
Wow.
So the interesting thing with...
That's not true.
So one of the first things they went to is copyright law, because copyright law is supposed
to be there to cover creative works and creative expressions, such as music and books and poetry.
Source code even, when you draft your source code, that is covered by copyright law.
And copyright law, the statute specifically says it covers choreography.
So it would seem at a first glance that perhaps they can sue for copyright infringement.
The problem is, the short answer is, no they can't.
And even though they can sue for it, but they will not win.
And the long answer is because the copyright office
and the federal courts have been very, very clear
that you cannot get copyright protection
for a simple dance step.
So.
So you need like a ballet.
Yes, you need the actual legislative history talks about a 22-minute ballet, and that is
what you can get copyright protection dance over.
It's awfully specific.
Yes, it is.
It's pointlessly specific.
It is.
Like 22 minutes.
Why not like 15?
Because they gave an example of a particular ballet that happened to be 22 minutes long
is I think the issue.
And so there have been other lawsuits in the past.
There was a lawsuit in the early 80s over the electric slide,
which was this 18-step dance move.
And the creator of the electric slide
started suing people who were doing the electric slide
because they were doing it wrong.
And that pissed him off that they were doing it wrong.
So he started suing them and lost.
And so we have this, and as you know,
the law looks at what's called precedent in case history,
you know, what happened in the past,
because it's very important that we are consistent.
It's often more important than being right,
it's just being consistent,
so that people know what they can do
and whether they're gonna get sued or not.
This is called precedent.
Precedent, yes. So the answer is that they will probably lose their copyright lawsuits,
although they have a couple of other interesting causes of action around right of publicity.
Trademark, things like that.
Right of publicity being your right to not have people put your face on a cereal box without your permission.
Right.
Essentially.
Unfair competition would be more accurate than trademark.
So it's a right of publicity issue which differs state by state.
So the issue with right of publicity is, and this is a huge issue in video games,
is you cannot use someone's, and we'll probably talk more about this later,
you cannot use someone's likeness without paying them, generally speaking,
because it's an economic right.
And what is your likeness?
Your likeness is your image, your name.
And some voices, someone has, I think Barbara Streisand won
that her voice was her likeness.
But
So to win these cases based off likeness, it is very difficult because they have to argue that the floss, for example,
the kid that does the floss, if you see anyone do the floss...
I want to see the floss first.
You have volunteered.
Chris.
I don't know, something like this?
Yes! You can't see it, it's behind the thing.
My niece was teaching me that one. It's the one that goes like, one, two...
Yeah, I think you have to go in front and behind.
Yes. It's very complicated.
My nine-year-old niece was teaching me this at Disney World.
We have some volunteers in the back flossing, it's amazing.
Nice! There we go! Perfect.
So the long story short is this is going to be an uphill battle for them to win because
they have to establish that when you see this dance, it has become merged with their likeness.
It's basically a photograph of them.
And it's going to be really difficult for them to win that argument, I think.
point out though on that particular right of publicity issue is that, so for example,
the Carleton, the only dance I actually know out of all of these different cases, the Carleton
dance is actually owned by the studio that did the Fresh Prince of Bel Air.
So the issue is more about preemption because the copyright law would preempt the right
of publicity that Carleton has.
Yeah, there's a lot of issues and preemption is another one.
These guys have a lot of reasons they're probably not going to win their cases, but that pulls
up another issue.
So speaking as a human now.
What does this mean if I'm a publisher or I'm a developer?
Practically speaking, given that there's a lot of cultural
artifacts like dance moves that sort of blow up, become
viral, and that a lot of times people want to reference in
their games in one way or another.
What does this mean for developers in how they're
going to?
How they're going to approach thinking about the risk of doing things?
Does that, you know, what you just said, does that mean, sure, fair game?
Should we just jump in and grab whatever we want?
You know, practically speaking, does it make sense to approach people who are creators of these?
And how do you even determine who gets credit for that?
Just ask your lawyer.
Right, so...
I mean, at the end of the day, it's a case-by-case basis, right?
We're not talking about something that you can just give a blanket answer to on this one.
Because it's going to come down to how much are you using, who are you taking it from,
how big, like how much of a mark are you going to be on the radar in terms of liability.
Go ahead.
I want to, I'm going to do the, I'm going to do the human hat for a second.
This is the way I explain it to people when they come to me.
So the more successful your game is, the worse cases people will bring against you.
And … ... ... ... ... ... ... ...
The less people play your game, the more you can do anything you want.
Okay, now you can come to me and I can tell you what the law is and here's the thing and I'm not talking about
In fact, I can't discuss this particular game
Let's be a hundred percent clear because we do an enormous amount of that particular game
But in general if your game makes a hundred million dollars a year
You are going to have to be beyond spotless or else and you're just gonna have a ton of things that have nuisance suits
now at the same time if you have a browser based game
that your grandmom and your aunt will play and your second grade teacher
put Kim Kardashian in it. You know, put
a Buy Now for heroin in it. I mean
the thing that I'm not actually... You might want to remove the human hat for that one.
And obviously not
connected to real Buy Now for that. But I'm just saying you can take a
tremendous amount more risk when you have a small audience but by the time
that you become very successful and think about a top 20 publisher
Things have to be ultra-buttoned up and things have to be conservative necessarily.
And you're going to, there's nothing you can do, you're going to draw crappy cases
and you're just going to have to have a budget for that.
Yeah, this is, I think being extremely successful, there is just a tax and people suing you is
just a tax on success and there is no way around it.
I have clients asking me, how can we avoid getting sued by patent trolls?
How can we avoid patent infringement?
Don't make money.
Exactly.
The answer is you can't.
At a certain point of success, you will be sued and you will be sued for patent infringement
and there is literally nothing you can do to stop it.
That's all I had to say, like don't make money.
That's pretty much the only way to not get sued.
And the interesting thing is there were many other video games doing this exact same thing,
yet they weren't sued.
Only Fortnite was sued, even though many other companies were doing this.
So, I have a question about, I'm going to put on my human hat,
because this is a legitimate question about World of Warcraft.
And I say this as somebody who played World of Warcraft for years.
There are all sorts of dances.
They were all sourced from fairly popular dances.
On top of that, just blanket theft of general IP like Dark Crystal.
There's an entire race of creatures in World of Warcraft,
which is a straight rip off from the Dark Crystal.
So you kind of have to wonder, how is it that a company like Activision
can borrow this material without?
the liability that, for example, Fortnite is seeing?
Well I think one issue that is going on is that, I think a lot of it is actually driven
by this law firm.
So there's been a lot of these lawsuits against Epic.
And they're all based on the same thing,
and they're all brought by the exact same law firm.
And there's this new law firm.
And I think it's a little bit of a disservice
because I think Fortnite or Epic
is at the wrong place at the wrong time
because this law firm wants to get their name out there,
and they're using these lawsuits and these celebrities
as a way to almost market themselves.
They're not going to be very popular with other lawyers in this space.
I'm just going to put that out there.
They are very unpopular with lawyers in this space right now.
So let's, speaking of being careful as you get more successful, and I think the message
here has been that, yeah, you can't stop people from suing you.
The best you can do is anticipate which things might be an issue and make sure that your
house is in order.
So another area where people have to be very careful,
and it's also garnered a lot of attention
the last couple years, is loot boxes.
People love to have opinions about it,
both as would-be game designers
and as would-be legislators.
So there's been, I think, a lot of discussion about it,
but also a lot of potential and actual regulation
in different countries and in different states.
Where do we see this shaking out?
I mean, if I'm a company that wants to use loot boxes,
or let's just open it up to gambling in general,
I think we need to be very careful about that line.
Please, let's be very careful about walking that line.
Let's start with the question of where on the line
do loot boxes fall?
And that comes in two questions.
One, looking at current legislation,
is it clear whether they may be defined as one or the other?
And then if you dare to opine on where that line should be,
I'd be happy to hear that too.
Gambling requires, under almost every single state's law, at least three things.
Consideration, prize, and chance.
And consideration is something that you give, usually in the form of cash or currency, in
order for the right to participate in this chance to receive a prize.
real simple way of explaining what gambling is from a legislative perspective.
And that more or less reflects what we see in the U.S. and what we see abroad for what
gambling is. Now, where loot boxes become tricky is, well,
a few things. First, let's look at the question of consideration.
What are you paying for it? If you're actually paying a cash price for
it, that's one thing, and, yes, that's pretty clearly well defined.
But then you look at a game like PUBG where you're not actually paying cash for it.
the currency you're generating is from time played, right?
At least that was my experience playing
or getting loot boxes from PUBG.
If that's the case, then what is your consideration?
Does it qualify as actual consideration
under the particular statute or whatever in question?
Then there's the question of chance.
Generally speaking, loop boxes are going to incorporate
an element of chance unless you're guaranteed
to get certain things in that loop box
that you're purchasing.
So it may, like whether or not there are odds
associated with the loop box or not
are going to be an issue.
And the final thing is obviously a prize.
And the issue with a prize is that the law isn't always really clear on whether or not
a prize needs to have cash value or not.
So if the prize that you receive isn't convertible to currency in some form or can't be sold,
then does it actually have value enough to qualify as a prize?
So we really actually do have to be very careful about whether we call loot boxes gambling
or not.
And honestly, the biggest issue with loot boxes from a regulatory standpoint, at least
as far as the FTC is concerned, has more to do with consumer protection and keeping kids
from spending like 3K on their parents' credit card.
And it's really just about informing the public if there are odds and stuff like that.
And this reason she's talking about being able to sell it is one of the reasons that when you read a Terms of Use,
I'm sure you always read the Terms of Use of every video game you play and download.
I do.
I draft them, I don't think I've ever read one.
The Terms of Use...
I read them because I draft them.
I copy paste ones, man. I think they're cool.
Like, ooh, this one's interesting.
I'll save that for later.
You never have time to play anything if you're reading them all.
But there's terms of use in the ULA.
Barrett and everyone will say things such as,
you know, you don't own any of this.
This software is all owned by the company.
We can revoke it anytime.
Importantly, you cannot sell this, right?
So even though technically,
even if you maybe could go out to a third-party marketplace,
the terms of use in the ULA says you cannot.
We disallied from selling and said, we figured out you've sold this, we'll ban you.
And this actually became very relevant in a case where the judge said,
there was no cash value to these loot boxes.
Because even though they theoretically could go out on these third party websites
and sell them, I think this was the big fish case.
It's against the rules and they don't encourage it.
There's no official way to sell these.
And it's against the rules in the terms of use.
And so they got that case dismissed.
So where do we think
So that's a good explanation of sort of where we are right now with loop boxes.
But given that this mechanic is something that seems to be, you know, it.
It's useful in a lot of games, and people can debate
whether they like it as a game design thing,
but where do we see, if we had to predict,
legislation and regulation on this going?
Because obviously right now, yeah, it's quite complicated.
We're trying to fit a new phenomenon into existing laws
that were designed for casinos and slot machines
and that sort of thing, and it's not clear
always where it fits, but if you had to guess,
is it gonna continue to be a patchwork and a mess,
different states, different countries?
Yeah, so I have a few, well, I don't know which one this is.
This is kind of lawyer thoughts.
So, okay, I think there are two paths on this decision tree.
So one is less regulation of the status quo, right?
Like I would like it if, and it sure would be nice if,
and I mean it for all of us, the home team,
the game developers, and it's not bad
for the consumers either, is if the rule was,
and the rule,
pretty much is now, pretty much is,
it's like with some exceptions,
if you don't have a cash out mechanism, you're okay.
Right?
But then to the extent that it becomes more regulated,
I hope it's not more regulated
than we do sweepstakes contest and promotion.
So, and look, I know that sucks too,
but the thing is sweepstakes contest promotion
has state laws, but we have a consensus.
A lot of it's about disclosure.
I'm not wishing for it.
You know, what I wish is something like we have right now,
but I hope it doesn't get.
I hope that's the far right boundary, right?
I hope that it doesn't go beyond that and cross over into gambling regulatory, which
is much worse.
But to me, right now, if it's not harming children, if there's a special disclosure
for under 13 games, then I think it's in a pretty good spot, especially if you as game
companies—this is one of the things I say to people.
Just quickly in closing on this is that you can solve a lot of this in a customer service level if a mom calls you
And says 17 year old boy girl, whatever
Spent $3,000 on my credit card
You you make it right there on the customer service level and you don't eat that money and maybe you put a stop in there
Like they can't spend more than $100 a month or something, right?
There's something you can do on a customer service level and that's gonna save us
from some regulatory intervention because then that mom or dad's story doesn't become
a news story, which is what a politician reads in an election year and decides this is some
new kind of, you know, save the kids, mom and apple pie legislation that would be really
easy to be elected on.
So that would be the ideal for me.
Following on that, and we see this in copyright too,
we see this in censorship in general,
with violence in games.
Generally the best way the industry can insulate itself
from regulation is to be responsible,
like to actually exercise some level of social responsibility
with how you engage with your customers.
And that is as much true for gambling and loot boxes
as it is for violence in games or anything else.
The more we try to say, well, freedom of speech,
let's do whatever we want.
We can say and do however we want.
We don't need to be responsible for it.
The higher the likelihood that eventually some government
is going to come in and say, oh, yes, you do.
You need to be responsible for this,
because obviously you are incapable of regulating
yourselves.
One of the things that the video game industry has really
benefited from are programs like the ESRB and the ESA
that help us self-regulate.
The more we get to self-regulate, the better off we are in terms of being able to service
our customers and give them what they want without government interference, because governments
are really terrible at economics and customer support in general.
I'll just end this, maybe the one time I put on my human hat for tonight.
The two things I will say that may not be technically required, but generally make loot
box type experiences less evil is when...
When game companies, one, show you the odds, right?
So if there is some chase item out there that everyone wants,
and there's a 1 in 10,000 chance of you getting it,
so people are spending $1 or $2 to buy these loot boxes that
look for this awesome chase object,
if the consumers know there's only 1 in 10,000
chance of getting it, that is important.
And I think that's something people should know, right?
When they're spending money on loot boxes,
they should know what the odds are.
And the second thing is, usually give them,
if they're gonna spend a dollar on your loot box,
give them a dollar's worth of product in there,
not 10 cents worth of product.
Also, just to put that in, if you're distributing in Japan,
you have to do that one way or the other
due to gotcha regulation.
Right, many countries do require that already.
So I want to move over to another area that I think has kind of exploded in the last five
years in the game industry, and that's streaming and the rise of sort of influencers as a very
dominant force.
So, you know, Apex Legends dropped with almost no fanfare and basically rode to five million
plus, you know, installs.
on the back of A, being a good game, but B, a lot of prominent streamers playing it.
And it then came out.
Why it came out makes it sound like it was a big secret, but no surprise,
some of these streamers were paid quite substantial sums
in order to stream it at a specific time all on the same...
on the launch date.
I think Ninja was paid a million dollars
or something like that to play it for like eight hours.
So I wanna ask a little bit about
what we think developers and publishers,
if they're the ones handling the marketing,
need to understand when they're interacting
with influencers, any kind of marketing or advertising,
what kind of pitfalls are there?
Can I just hand over a bunch of money
and say, hey, play my game, say X, Y, Z?
What do I have to do?
So I'll start this off and go real quick.
So the current guidelines for influencers are the same thing
for people in video games as there are for people that are
selling shoes, right?
The Federal Trade Commission has come out and said, if
there's a material connection between your company
and the influencer, then that influencer needs to disclose the material connection.
This is where you see hashtag ad or hashtag sponsored or hashtag, you know, your game ambassador.
Or the streamer says, I'd like to thank game company for their support, etc.
The disclosure has to be clear and conspicuous,
and the disclosure has to fit the medium and travel with the medium.
So there's a lot of complexity to unpack there. We don't have to do it right now.
but they are supposed to say something and they are supposed to disclose.
And here's the question or here's the way that you should think about it to the extent
that you're asking the question, you're making games and you're asking the question, or to
the extent that you're an attorney and people are asking you the question.
If your creative folks come to you and say,
Hey, you know, is such and such sufficient in the tiny little mouse voice?
The answer is no.
The answer is no because that's not clear and conspicuous, right?
So that doesn't meet the FTC guide.
Anyway, we can chat more about this.
We now have hundreds of FTC letters saying what's sufficient, what's not sufficient.
So you know, two years ago, we were guessing.
We don't have to guess anymore.
if I screw this up as a developer or a publisher,
who, what's the result going to be?
Who's going to sue me or fine me
and who should be worried?
Should it be the influencer?
Should it be the developer?
You know, how should they think about this in terms of risk?
This hat, okay.
So what would likely happen.
if what's happened in the past continues to happen is the brand, the publisher, the video
game publisher or the developer would get a letter from the FTC that they would be published
and it would be embarrassing, the influencer would also likely get one.
Now, the fear is at this point that there would be some combined regulatory business
that would occur and what's been letters in the past will now become fines.
Because they could look at us and say, we gave you guys hundreds of examples.
We have FTC cases on disclosure.
There was a Machinima case was a case on disclosure.
The Sony Vita case with the hashtag game changer was.
AstroTurfing, which is like fake grassroots, which that was essentially also a place on
disclosure because if they had properly disclosed, it wouldn't have been AstroTurfing.
So they could say now that, you know, you guys have had years of warning and years of
understanding.
The, you know, the stakes are going to be higher.
The thing I do want to point out that's a really big deal that should be unambiguously
described is if you are the party paying the money, meaning you're the ultimate brand,
you're the developer, you're the publisher, you cannot...
absolve yourself of responsibility by putting it on the influencers or putting it on your marketing agency.
The regulators have said outright it has to be you that is responsible for policing,
even if it's in the contract.
This is going to be a little bit of both.
The reason for that is because ultimately the party paying the money is the one benefiting the most from the advertisement,
from the endorsement.
Another thing that, because I actually did a talk on this with Online Performers Group
and some other people at PAX last year.
One of the other things that I hear from a lot from influencers is, well, they gave me
this for free, but it's not money.
Like, they didn't pay me to do the ad.
Or you know, they gave me, you know, this headset to test on, to test so I can talk
about it.
Do I have to disclose that?
And the answer is yes.
You still have to disclose it, because unless you actually
paid for it yourself, you are receiving some kind of benefit,
whether it's financial or otherwise.
And you still have to disclose that you received this.
Now how you do that in a stream, like we have that
hashtag ad and whatnot.
We have the 30, okay.
So the hashtag thing is great for Twitter and whatnot,
but when you're running a stream,
how do you do these disclosures?
And generally I think like the FTC
has written guidelines on this as well,
and it's generally like, you know,
if you're doing a super long stream,
maybe once every couple of hours.
If you're doing like a short one hour stream,
maybe at the beginning and maybe have a card at the end,
disclosing the fact, so.
I'll see.
I'll say one other quick thing about streaming.
Another thing I'm seeing more of now are transparent badges,
especially if you are paying a streamer to stream for two
hours, early access to your game.
They come up and they say, thanks, game company, for
giving me early access to this level.
Really excited to be playing it tonight.
And then there might be some kind of transparent badge or
something like that.
The key is not one click away.
If you're one click away, you're hosed.
Don't do that.
Could you explain that?
Sure. So one click away is like people used to ask or were curious,
well what if I go to more and then at the bottom of more there's some disclosure
or what if it's in the about page for the streamer? And in fact,
I'm, I don't want to name.
You guys can look into this or talk to me after.
There's one particularly embarrassing case that all the way at the bottom of a whole
lot of lines of more, it actually wrote something like, I can't believe that you read this far.
You know, this is so embarrassing and unlikely, but this video was sponsored by such and such.
And that was reprinted in the FTC opinion against.
this party. It's like how could you allow your influencer to sort of mock the process
like this? Yeah, so don't be that person.
So, human hat for this, because this is a general rule for streamers, for game developers,
for everyone, don't be a dick.
That's actually a general rule for everyone, I would hope.
Audience, audience.
Yeah, so I wanted to move to audience questions, though I do feel like...
What do you think?
Should we dive into privacy GDPR?
Do we want to do privacy transactions?
Well, I think it's important to talk about privacy
because I think it's connected to a lot of things,
but I don't want us to take like 20 minutes
because I want to get to audience questions.
So the last like sort of preceded topic
that I'm gonna talk about is privacy.
Privacy you may recall around May last year you got approximately
400 emails that said we've updated our privacy policy and you may have scratched your head and said why am I getting these all in
The same week and the answer is that the EU
The answer is Mona. She drafted motion
Because the clients all came within the same like three-week period right before me 31st 2018
So what happened was the EU finally put into effect a
sweeping privacy regulation that sort of altered the
responsibilities of anyone on the internet collecting
personal data from people in the EU, which is a lot of
people, and so everyone scrambled to kind of figure
out, oh, what do we have to do to become compliant, because
some of the potential fines were huge.
Now the problem is this is a sort of a government
regulation where they said, here's what might happen, but
of course nobody knew.
whether they were going to be mean about it,
whether they were going to be chill about it,
for lack of a better term.
And so it has a lot of far-reaching implications.
For instance, Tilting Point does free-to-play mobile.
We spend a lot of effort making sure
that our technology is on point to separate out personal data
and do all of that.
And in games in general, even if it's a single-player game,
you're generally collecting quite a bit of data.
And that data can be useful.
Some of it is.
a name for an account or things that can identify a person.
And this is especially interesting because just earlier this week, Google announced Stadia,
which is their...
Is it Stadia or Stadia?
I don't know what they're called.
Stadia.
Stadia, yeah.
That's what I thought.
And this is going to be interesting because Google is known for having quite a bit of
information about you.
So it raises some interesting questions as to how they might, you know...
Combine that data with the data they're gonna have of your every move within games as you stream it
so I think you know if anyone wants to take sort of a very top-level explanation of
Correct is not
Of why anyone should care about it and just very very generally
What are the new obligations that developers and anyone that's using data, which is everyone?
What new obligations do we have?
So as to why you should care, I will put out a number for you,
$57 million.
That's what Google was fined by the GDPR Commission
for violating GDPR.
Chances are this is going to continue to be litigated.
They're going to fight it back and forth.
But that's $57 million most of us don't have.
So just to put that out there, GDPR Commission
is not afraid of fining as much as they want.
They have some.
some benchmarks for that, but they are taking it very seriously.
A couple of high-level points on this. The entire point of GDPR and the
easiest way to explain it
is private, like what they are trying to accomplish is they want to make
the internet as an industry, privacy by design.
They want companies to sell privacy as a service. They want this to be
incorporated
in how they service their customer base.
So they don't want data to be the selling point for the business unless their clients
are very, very, unless their customers are very aware of that fact.
One of the biggest issues for this and one of the reasons as to why Google was fined
$57 million, which probably isn't actually that big a number when we talk about Google.
The reason why Google got into so much trouble,
or one of the many reasons as to why Google
got in so much trouble is this idea of consent,
and when you need to ask people for permission
in order to collect their data.
your privacy policy is no longer a contract and that is something that you
need to be very aware of at this point in time. If at any point you thought,
like, if at any point you had an accept or do not accept at the end of
your privacy policy, get rid of it now.
Because blanket consents are not allowed. You have to ask consent at the time of
collection for that specific point of data.
And to clarify, GDPR is talking primarily about what we call personal information.
So, you know, totally anonymized data is not so much the issue as any type of data that
would let me figure out who you are in the really real world.
But their definition of personal data is extremely...
It's not just your email address, date of birth, it can be your IP address.
So the tricky part about it is that it's not just any information you collect,
it's any information when taken with anybody else that you work with
could possibly identify that individual in some context.
That is considered bullshit. It's huge.
I stopped myself, I said, well...
Oh, the cursing wasn't my issue.
No, no, I was just like, one day you might find yourself in front of a regulator and they play this back.
I would say that maybe the argument is that the execution and the way that it was drafted is perhaps not clear or helpful, but...
perhaps they are aiming at very valid goals.
So I was just going to put the human head on and just say this entirely non-legal thing.
The statute has its own website.
If you print it out, it is 500 pages.
It is the modern Necronomicon.
So if there's something in your life that you think you should get some help with, it
is GDPR.
Okay.
Fair.
All right, so I think at this point,
because I think GDPR, no matter how user friendly we make it,
is going to make people's eyes glaze over.
I'm going to throw it open to questions,
because I think maybe that will be a great way to sort of see
what people in the industry are actually concerned about.
And hopefully we can provide some clarity on how
you should be approaching it.
So, yeah.
Hi.
Thanks very much.
This is a very interesting panel.
I wanted to circle back to the loot box conversation,
but use it in the context of blockchain.
Okay.
So, blockchain technology,
especially non-fungible tokens in blockchain.
CryptoKitties is what you're talking about.
I'm actually legal counsel for CryptoKitties.
That would explain it.
Okay, hello, nice to meet you.
So, one of the questions that I have had
is how to manage the gaming mechanic question
when by its very nature, non-fungible tokens,
you were saying, look, the way to solve the problem
of loot boxes is make sure you can't cash out.
Guess what?
NFTs are based on being able
to have secondary market sources.
So, how would you handle it?
Well.
That's a very specific legal question.
I would say.
Yeah.
Well, I would say, to a certain extent,
again, it comes down to those three questions, right?
consideration, chance, and prize.
So the question is really that chance, I think,
when it comes to non-fungible tokens.
because you are effectively guaranteed to get an entirely unique token.
Basically, from my understanding of CryptoKitties,
whenever you create one of those non-fungible tokens,
which is basically the kitten, right?
It's the cat you actually get from the game.
Those are each unique and those are each special.
So, by virtue of the fact that they are all distinctly unique
and distinctly special and therefore non-fungible
in the sense that they cannot be exchanged for something.
identical, then they all share effectively the same value at base
because they are all essentially unique.
This is me over-lawyering the crap out of this question, by the way.
But that would be the argument.
That would be the position I would take if I were counsel for CryptoKitties.
So I will also say, and maybe this is the human hat, I'm not sure.
To a certain extent, there's a lot of things out there that already meet all three of those definitions, or clearly each of those, yet are not illegal.
Magic cards.
Magic cards would be my example.
You pay, oh god, I've not bought magic cards since like 1999.
It was like $3 for a pack of magic cards, I don't know what it is now.
Five, okay.
Get into it, man.
Inflation.
I played a lot of Artifact recently.
But these are all, yeah, I know, it died very quickly.
Anyway, you are paying money for something and there's a completely random chance of what you take out of there.
It is directly exchangeable for cash.
I mean, magic cards are just directly exchangeable for cash.
So this meets the entire definition, why aren't these illegal?
Isn't this a loot box?
And yet they've been around for 20, 25 years and no one's ever gone after them.
So just because you're doing something that meets the criteria does not mean anyone's ever come to come after you.
Yeah, because that really comes down to the gambling question, right?
It comes down to how are consumers using your product?
How are consumers actually like playing your game?
Are they spending a dangerous amount of income in order to get that specific kitten?
And if not, then you're probably not going to be getting on anybody's radar on anybody's bad side.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you.
But the magic is so huge, I don't know, I can't explain it.
Magic is magic.
Maybe the regulators are, maybe they play.
Yeah.
And Nick Mitchell is excellent.
What's that?
Oh gosh, we have two, sorry, I didn't realize there were two whole things.
I'm sorry to this side of the room, by the way, that they put this in the middle.
There was no way to...
Yeah, so.
Great panel.
I have a question about historically accurate games,
especially if you're trying to preserve history
of like our present.
Is that mic on?
It sounds like.
I don't think so.
Oh, can we make sure that that mic is live as well
just for recording?
Yes, the question's about historically accurate video games.
Video games.
Yes.
Taking place in like.
Just get closer to it taking place in
2019 and you want to use maybe like trademarks like logos sure of real corporations real countries real people
Yeah, like it sounds totally illegal, but like not this I think all three of us may have a lot to say about this
But it really depends. It's extremely it's extremely context
of that. It depends. Actually, Mona, why don't you tell us about Red Dead Redemption and Pinkerton?
No, I'm not touching that. But no, oh god, that was silly. That was really silly.
Oh yeah, well so this is an example. I guess this was not modern day, but there's a lawsuit ongoing right now,
you guys may have heard of this, of Pinkerton versus Red Dead Redemption.
That's not the name of the company, so it's essentially the IP's issue.
And Red Dead Redemption is a sort of historically accurate Old West game.
Oh wow.
And they have Pinkerton agents in them, and Pinkerton sent them a threatening letter and said,
you need to pay us, you need a license.
By the way, Pinkerton, in case anybody hasn't played
Pinkertons were this bounty hunter company or agency that used to go around and pick people.
It's also the best Weezer album.
Yes, it is. Thank you.
Union busting, there's like photographs of them with Abraham Lincoln.
They're real historical figures.
I actually just gave a talk on this last week with the GC of Riot Games
and it turns out he used to be a Pinkerton agent before he went to law school.
It was really random.
So the point is that a Pinkerton's going to lose this, because you can, to a certain extent,
there's something called nominative trademark fair use, and that is just one of many considerations to use.
If you want to use a modern-day game and you're getting coat caps, and on every single coat cap is a Coca-Cola logo,
you're going to get sued and you're going to lose.
If you use...
photographs in your game or even architecture of modern day buildings,
that could be covered by copyright and if that's on the cover of the games, maybe that's not okay.
If it's just incorporated in the game, like in Spider-Man, maybe that is okay.
It's so context-dependent.
And I just want, for fun, to just describe how this actually works in real life.
So you have...
You're going to make a game, let's say there's a thousand art assets in it that could be
something else.
It's not just generic whatever.
Let's say there's 10,000.
Let's say there's 100,000.
What those folks do are they send a spreadsheet to our firm, these guys' firms, and it has
little miniature links to the art asset.
and it has multiple columns about it,
including where it was sourced from
and whether or not it was modified.
And then this one particular company
that I'm thinking about,
but a lot of them do a variation of this,
we color code a column red, yellow, and green
based on how it's used
and what we think the relative risk is.
Another thing we haven't discussed
that goes into this analysis,
that takes, I mean, it takes months of attorney time
to go through all of the assets.
is how litigious is the party.
So, you know, like those little tree air fresheners,
those are some dangerous bastards.
I'm just letting you know.
Lindsay Lohan will sue you.
Yeah.
Anything Disney.
I mean, I think to summarize on a practical level, though,
you never know who's going to sue you.
There are risks, and it depends on if you're a tiny indie,
where you don't make any money, so no one cares.
And it depends on who you're using and how.
So there are no blanket rules for this.
So there's a lot of questions, so for the next couple,
I'm going to ask that we try and keep it
to a nice pithy response, so everyone can
get to ask their questions.
And I'm sorry in advance, because somebody like that question, we could have a whole one hour talk on.
It will all be available outside afterwards, by the way.
So, well, at least I won't. Are you guys?
Yes.
Stick around?
For like 15 minutes. I got a client meeting.
Okay, cool.
Okay, yes.
Okay, so this goes back to the issue of privacy.
It kind of goes beyond just the GDPR.
Companies like Facebook and Fitbit and Google and so on,
they've been dealing with sort of personally identifiable information for a long time.
and they have formed, typically have formed,
an in-house review board of some sort,
which is not just lawyers,
but also user advocates and technical people and so on,
who basically review the issues here
and give a thumbs up or down
as to whether this process should be implemented.
This is sort of analogous to institutional review boards that you get in universities doing human subject testing.
I'm wondering is there any kind of structure or standard way of dealing with this within the games industry?
No.
There's nothing standardized yet.
To keep in mind, a lot of these companies came into this
pretty late, in games in particular.
As I said, most of my clients didn't come to me, even though
I gave them notice on GDPR about a year ago, or a year
before.
they didn't start even thinking about implementing any kind of consumer-facing documentation
or their own back-end process until like a month before it went, until a month before
GDPR went into effect.
So do they, like, they are in the process of trying to establish a process right now.
They haven't, most of the companies that I've worked with and even some of the bigger companies,
with the exception of a few who, you know, are owned by Google or Hasbro, for example,
because it's a very well-defined process.
You know, some companies have gotten there, usually the bigger ones, Microsoft, you know,
Wizards, whatever, but the smaller studios and the smaller publishers and the indies,
no, they're still trying to figure this out.
Seems like it'd be good scope for an industry-wide sort of thing.
It costs a lot. I'm sorry. I have to, like, seriously censor myself. I apologize.
Thank you.
Oh, a quick reminder, by the way.
After the talk, please do fill out the evaluations.
They're very, very helpful to let us know how we did.
So, you know, any comments, concerns, et cetera.
And they should send you an email about it.
Yes?
So I kind of have a loaded question.
Get really close to that mic, man. It's not good.
I kind of have a...
a loaded question away. So recently Civilization VI updated their EULA. And one of the paragraphs,
I don't have it on me so I can't quote anything, but essentially allowed them to access and
read any information whatsoever, not necessarily restricted to their product on our computers.
and they updated that and with the,
expands into the question with a lot of games,
games only actually provide you the EULA
after you purchase the game.
And if they update at any time, you're not able,
unless you agree to it, you're not able to play the game
that you purchased and spent money on.
If we take an example of Stellaris, that's $300 worth of game right there.
Yeah, that's two entirely different questions.
The second one is like a huge issue we actually discuss.
It's like one of these few kind of issues we discuss in law schools,
these shrink wrap agreements.
You've already bought a game, and then you've already bought some software product.
You get home and open it, and it says,
great, you have now agreed to these terms of use.
And essentially, if you can return it,
If there's a method, I think, of returning it,
then you are deemed, because you have not returned it,
to have agreed to it.
So I think as long as there's a method of returning it
or refunding your money, then you are out of luck.
And they said, well, sure, you paid $300 for it, opened it,
but you could have returned it.
You had, like in Steam, when you buy something,
you got like two hours or something to play it and return it.
So you're SOL.
Well, and just really quickly on that.
So in my experience,
If you contact the publisher and it means a lot to you, you can get your money back.
That's what I always advise them to do.
Try it.
See if it works.
They may ask you to send the game back or not.
The second thing is the reason it has to say something that looks like that is because
the best cheat programs run entirely outside of the software.
They're not looking at your Facebook photos.
They shouldn't be.
Thank you.
Yes.
So my question has almost nothing to do with anything you've spoken about, which...
Excellent.
I mean, yes, I really enjoyed what you spoke about,
because I have a consumer viewpoint about a lot of those topics that you mentioned.
But my question is, I'm an indie,
and we are a team that just came together as friends,
wanting to make something really cool.
We all care about, oh, I see an expression.
We all care about the product and we all want to make it happen, but there has been almost
no conversation as to how we're going to actually make this a business.
And while I think everyone would agree that having legal protections and bylaws and all
that would be amazing and would be helpful in the long run.
I am concerned about bringing it up because we haven't had this conversation at all, and
I don't even know if other people in the team have even thought about it.
So, I have a quick question just to kind of elaborate.
Is this a hobby project or are you actually planning on selling it?
We're actually planning on selling it.
Then you need to incorporate or otherwise form a business entity because this is not
a hobby?
Well, my question is more not do we need to do this?
More of.
How do we broach this subject between a group of friends
who, you know, we trust each other,
but this is still contentious and difficult?
Yeah, I agree.
That's very well said.
You need to be able to have that conversation.
So, and also just, this is a situation I've seen quite a few times is,
you guys don't incorporate or you guys have just some kind of loose agreement,
maybe some handshake agreement.
There's four of you, each on a fourth of the company,
you're going to go forward.
This is great.
Well, in six months, one of you takes a job at Epic,
and now they're out of the picture.
Two years later, your game releases.
It's a huge success.
Well, guess what?
That guy that never really worked on the game,
that took the job at Epic and never input anything else,
still owns a fourth of your game.
So he owns a fourth year game.
We were opposite counsel on this.
You better have an agreement in place.
Yeah, and I too have been on, I've been on, I think we ended up settling this case, so it's not public,
but for almost $100 million on a mega, mega game that just nobody decided to talk to each other for a long time.
Somebody just went away and they thought they weren't ever going to hear from him again
until that game started to make some real, real money.
I just realized that we actually had, that we were, the first time I ever worked against you on a case.
This is the exact thing you did.
Yeah, Zorna and I were opposite each other on a very contentious deal where this is literally what happened.
And, but the thing I will say real quick is it's super common, but don't let it be common.
If you guys are in here, I mean, get it done right, you'll be so happy you got it done right, even if the game doesn't work out.
To be honest, I can say this, I think for both of us,
it sucked for both of our clients.
There was no happiness in that situation.
So go ahead and have that conversation.
If you're a team, if this is something you all care about,
they should acknowledge that you are not selling out
by actually creating a business
if you plan on selling a product.
You are always selling out if you're selling a product.
selling out means you're selling something, right?
Right?
A good way to broach it in a way that won't be awkward if you feel awkward is to say,
look, this is about protecting our friendship.
Because, no, seriously, because I would say that the more you trust and like someone,
the more important it is to have a contract.
And the reason is that when you trust and like someone,
many things will go unsaid because you trust each other.
That's what trust is.
And if you're dealing with a random stranger,
you're gonna know to ask a lot of questions,
say, well, how exactly do the percentages work?
But you're not gonna know this.
And by having this conversation in this contract,
you have the confidence that your friendship
isn't gonna be destroyed if someone has a change of heart.
So yeah, I would do it and you'll feel better about it.
And they're gonna breathe a sigh of relief
when you bring it up and say, oh yeah, great.
We were thinking this too, let's get this.
So there's a reason as to why
I'm probably perpetually single.
But one of my.
One of the things that we do is...
Yes, my contract.
Is it the lawyer hat?
No, I treat...
I...
True.
But I treat all relationships like they are...
I treat business relationships the same way.
I treat my romantic relationships and vice versa.
And that is, you go through stages, right?
Yeah, see, this is why I'm single.
You go through these stages.
It's not a zero-sum game, right?
It's not about winning and losing.
And anybody who says otherwise is full of it and does not know
anything about contracts, and that means you, Donald Trump.
When it comes down to it, you are creating a relationship,
right?
You are courting each other to find out if you have similar
goals in mind.
You are negotiating your values to determine what boundaries you establish in the relationship.
And you have like a term sheet phase, which is kind of the honeymoon phase.
And then you have the long term or the long form agreement, which is effectively like,
you know, your prenup.
So at the end of the day, I mean, you the business relationship is still a relationship
and the conversation isn't going to be that different.
So we've got about five minutes left, so now we're going to go to lightning round,
because I really want to make sure everyone gets their question.
Yes.
Thanks.
I'll try to make this brief.
My question is related to personalization, and it connects with both the gotcha loot
box question as well as GDPR and privacy.
When I think about monetization and mobile and sort of random-based monetization,
We're entering a place where as Google and more players have more data,
they're able to generate offers on a very individual level, right?
And the bigger that the data sets get, the more personalized the offers become.
What risks do you see for either publishers or developers from a legal perspective,
in terms of like, how deep can you cut or?
Can you change the odds based on consumers?
What could you do and what pitfalls would you see
as more players that deal with personalization
enter the space?
Yeah, I think, I mean, at a top level,
the use of the personal data, the sort of GDPR,
and it's not just that regulation,
but is sort of about either consent
or having what they call a legitimate business interest.
So that frames how you,
what it is you're allowed to use someone's data for.
And if they're not aware that,
they say, yeah, sure, of course,
you can have my email and this,
and you can track my clicks because I'm playing the game,
and that's how the game works,
and yeah, I wanna get special offers, that's fine.
And if they agree to that,
or if it's clear that that's what you're doing, that's fine.
If you start doing this, but they think,
oh, it's just everyone gets the same ads, that's an issue.
I think as far as the changing of the odds,
I would assume that it has to do with.
disclosure and that that they need there needs to be a way for them to
understand and I don't know if if the fact that it's based on an algorithm and
it could fluctuate ten times a day how do we disclose that I think if you find
out that someone is is is vulnerable or not very smart or likely make rash
decisions so you start offering them deals where they have terrible chances
of winning that seems really like predatory that's bad that's with my
lawyer hat and my human hat that seems like that seems like it's gonna go
what do you think
Lightning round.
Yeah, lightning round.
All right.
Yes.
Okay.
So yeah, so on the disclosure and promotion type things, I work with educational institutions,
I work with festivals, and we're talking about, okay, a click away doesn't count.
If a university wants to retweet stuff that's a student project being shown someplace, if
a festival wants to retweet something that's by creators, are there concerns there of like
they paid tuition, they pay submission fees for access to those PR machines, or is that
not a concern at all?
That's not what they're paying for.
OK.
Thank you so much.
Easy.
Yes.
So when it comes to, this is more also about Tyson
to communicating with the superiors.
So for Rainbow Six Siege, what happened
was there was a scandal of them censoring violence to, I
believe, fit into the Chinese market.
And what happened was there was a lot of controversy surrounding that.
And basically, there are different...
What I'm trying to say is that there are different costs
to just being legally compliant,
whether that be financial or reputational.
How do you...
How would you suggest communicating that to a superior
who might be from a different culture or, you know, all that,
to convince them that it is important to stay legal?
I mean, it's the price of entry.
Specifically with China, it's the price of entry.
Well that and, never mind, I'm not going to say it, that would be offensive.
Yeah, like with China in particular, things are extremely regulatory.
Generally, you're working with the Chinese publisher anyway, so...
Very few, I don't know of any companies that can get Chinese distribution without working for a company actually based in China.
As a Chinese person, I give you full permission to say that.
Like, you are so right.
So the additional cost also goes to who you need to bribe to get it through the regulatory and licensing channels.
Though the US has laws against Foreign Practices Act, so.
Well, we do, but...
Okay, I think we've hit time.
What an ending.
Everyone who's still in line, we're happy to talk to you outside and take your questions
off the air.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Fill out your surveys, please.