Thanks for being here.
I appreciate you all.
I appreciate you wanting to.
Develop and improve your skills as producers.
And I will do my best to pay some justice to this topic.
Communication is a huge, huge, huge topic.
And it's important to me.
It should be important to all of us.
So I was happy to come and be able to participate.
But I don't know if anybody could really do it full
justice, so we'll give it our best shot.
Just a couple points of order here.
One, please make sure that your phones are on vibrate.
I'm sure you've already done that.
Uh, two, uh, we, we take the reviews,
uh, all the speaker reviews very seriously.
So, um, please fill that out at, at the end of the talk.
Um, or you can take a guess what it'll be and do it now.
Uh, either way, just please make sure
that you, that you turn those in.
Um, and, uh, and thanks very much.
to you guys for being here.
So Producer Boot Camp.
Boy, I remember, um,
I used to come to producer talks here at GDC,
uh, actually when it was down, uh,
about, uh, what, 40 miles south of here,
um, years ago when we would all get together
in the Fairmont ballroom.
And, uh...
and be kind of naughty.
It was a much smaller industry then,
and we had, uh, we had smaller teams,
and communication was a problem then,
and, uh, it's still a problem now,
but sometimes we get it right,
and when we do, great things happen.
I'm head of production
and executive producer at Gearbox Software.
My name's Aaron Thibault.
I also teach from time to time.
I'm teaching this semester a capstone class at Baylor.
I've been in education for a while,
so I love, uh, talking about things
that I get to learn more about.
So first on communication,
game development's hard, right.
We know, or we're learning, that game development
is really, really, really hard.
One of the hardest things about it
is communication.
Now, I like to learn, I read books, I find material on communication so I can improve
my skills in communication with the teams that I work with and the people that I interact
with.
I do that all the time, and hopefully you're doing that all the time also.
One of the books that has held up for a long time for me, and he's written more material
than this on things having to do with trust and truths, is this one, Seven Habits of Highly
Effective People.
In it, one of those habits that he points out is communication.
Seek first to understand, then be understood.
And he makes the point that our whole lives...
We're spending time speaking and writing,
and in our classes in school,
we learn how to communicate outward.
We're broadcasting.
We learn a lot about broadcasting messages,
things that we care about,
because we assume a lot of people care about
what we care about,
so we want to tell them all about it.
But we don't spend a lot of time listening.
And most of what we do as producers,
or what we should be doing as producers,
is listening and observing
and gaining situational awareness.
really cluing in to what's happening with our projects and our teams and
if you're on the development side with the publisher and vice versa
if you're a publisher.
We don't spend nearly enough time really synthesizing the information that's
coming to us.
So we really have to develop our skills in listening.
And it's a practice.
So since this is sort of an overview of communication,
I'll just cover a couple of basic topics,
things that you've probably heard many times in school,
but it doesn't hurt to refresh our memory.
Here are some things that are barriers to communication,
just generally, just broadly.
These are broad principles,
things that can impede good communication between people.
So physical barriers.
Nowadays, it's not uncommon at all to work with
teams who are on the other side of the world.
Very often, we work in buildings where we may
not see other people who are in the building
with us for days, weeks, months. I was talking
to one of our producers last night who said
he got to meet one of our animators
for the first time. He said, how long have
you been here? He assumed it was maybe a
month or two. Two years.
So, it's funny how long...
time can go by for that we don't interact with others who
are actually working on the same project with us,
or on other projects near us.
Choice of the wrong medium.
We do this all the time.
What's one of the,
what's one of those mediums that we use all the time
where we probably should have chosen some other medium?
Hmm?
Email, for sure.
That's a, that's like low-hanging fruit, right?
All the time we use email for things that we shouldn't be using email for.
Semantic barriers are language.
We use a word that somebody else takes an exception to.
That sort of stops their, the flow of communication,
they're listening.
Might stop you from talking.
Cultural barriers, some of these are pretty obvious,
I won't go too deep into these,
just, it's good to be aware of these things.
Psychological barriers is one of the biggest ones, actually,
because you can only ever control...
yourself, the communication that you're providing and the listening that you're doing,
you can never control anyone else, right?
So, psychological and attitudinal barriers, while they might frustrate us,
they might be things that we're aware we have to pay attention to,
it's one of those things that makes communication hard,
because we can't force the other person to really hear our message.
All we can do is a better job on our end of conveying it
and being aware if they're getting it or not.
in varying perceptions of reality,
which are caused by levels of understanding and comprehension.
So everybody has a different view, a different filter
that they use to see the world and to see projects.
And some people might think game development's easy
or should be easy, and some people think it's hard.
And it should be hard if you want to do a good job.
There's a lot of different ideas
of what game development is and what it's not.
Nobody shares one.
People don't share one idea of that.
It's important to know where the other person's coming from.
And it's really easy for us just to assume it's the other person.
We have to get through that.
And it comes up all the time.
And at Gearbox, with the people that we work with,
our partners inside the company,
you always have to kind of just pause for a second.
And think about, is this quality issue
something that this person...
You know, did they do this on purpose?
Was it a timing issue?
Am I saying something where
they already have built up a wall to it
and I wasn't aware of that?
What's going on there?
And you must encounter these things all the time,
I would guess, if you're making games.
So, the description of the talk...
is about communication being the bane of all postmortems.
Well, I'm, I'm really sad that Game Developer Magazine's
not still published in the way it used to be,
although we still see great articles on Gamasutra.
But one of the articles that, as producers,
we always enjoyed looking for were these postmortems.
And the reason I say communication's the bane
of all postmortems is because you just waited for it.
You waited for that team, the person who's writing that article,
that postmortem, to say communication was one of the top problems.
Every time. And if they didn't, you called them a liar.
Especially because you were probably having those problems.
Well,
in this particular issue, which was
at the beginning of 09, I think,
Brandon Sheffield.
wrote up just a quick recap of some things
that he'd run into, or he'd come across in postmortems.
And it kind of sets the tone, I think,
just that over and over again,
we come across these same issues.
So Penny Arcade.
They simply fail to employ best practices,
which are things that you agree in communication
amongst each other,
are things that you should be doing
so that you don't have to have
more formal rules. They're, they're guidelines for you to
follow. And you set these in agreement with the
team, because these are the things that are gonna
keep your project from going off the rails.
They, they knew better. They simply failed to employ
best practices. How often does it happen? I know
it happens pretty often. Happens at Gearbox. I know
from developer friends I've talked to, it happens throughout
the industry. We just forget.
At Harmonix.
On Guitar Hero.
Well...
they created an early schedule.
They had a communication plan for how they would go
about making the game.
And then what happened?
As things went along, they forgot to keep up-to-date
with specification of what they were doing.
So if you're aware of the PMBOK,
or the Project Management Institute's guide
on how to do project management...
PMI tends to avoid talking about Agile development.
At least, I don't see PMI talking a lot about Agile.
They use other language to talk about
more traditional approaches to project management,
which still fit within an Agile structure.
One of those, they talk about a rolling wave.
And that's a common theme.
And in communication as a producer,
you have to be ready to catch the project as it moves along,
the idea of the sort of rolling wave in development,
to stay on top of the wave and to continue
to bring ideas and specifications back
into the project so that it can be tasked properly
and be broken down.
If you're running an agile project,
then you're breaking down epic stories into smaller stories.
The smaller that you get in the story, the better spec,
the better it can be estimated.
They just sort of forgot to do that.
Max Hoberman, great developer, developed multiplayer for Halo.
Went off and made his own studio, Certain Affinity.
He was used to open pit environments, open communication.
Had a passion project.
Age of Booty was their original IP.
Even in that environment, they forgot that their teams
had to communicate with each other.
They didn't have a formal tasking plan.
for how they would ensure that dependencies worked out
between those teams.
It ended up costing them a lot of time and money.
And I won't, I won't go on and on on each of these for now.
But Brandon says, a lot of these issues have to do
with scheduling and communication,
which in turn has to do with the quality of producers.
And I'm really heartened to see you all here
because I know you want to be quality producers.
Not everyone can be here right now.
It just shows your interest, though,
in furthering your careers.
And these have to be things that we remind ourselves of
all the time, to be quality producers.
But we just run into these.
Thanks, Brandon.
in postmortems all the time.
So what are the kinds of things that we can do
to make sure that we're learning from these mistakes?
And how do we use communication
to reinforce with the team that we have learned something
and that we're going to get better?
And that it won't happen again.
Well, sprint retrospectives.
How many of you here are employing an agile methodology
in your studio or in your development environment?
many of you. How many of you are not? Specifically not? Okay. So for those of you who, one or
two, but for the most part, for those of you who didn't raise your hand, either you're
not sure or you're looking to get into development, you've heard maybe a lot about Agile and you've
heard about other methodologies. Sprint retrospectives are a great way to make sure that you're actually
absorbing these best practices and that you are culturally building up, up
a good way of talking to each other on your teams
so that you avoid wasting effort and having angry developers around you.
And in those sprint retrospectives, you have to talk about
things that you need to start doing, things that you need to stop doing,
and things that are going pretty good, continue, will observe, good so far.
That's a really useful team discussion.
Now there's also a thing called an AAR.
This comes from military training.
We use it, some people call it a mid-mortem.
It's really similar to a mid-mortem.
Okay.
Difference here, though, is where a sprint retrospective
tends to be, at least in my experience,
I'm sure many of you probably have different experiences,
but my experience usually is a big discussion.
And if you as the producer are there,
you may be sort of guiding people through it
if you've collected topics,
or guiding your way through those topics.
An AAR tends to be more of a coaching moment
for you as a producer,
or someone who's senior in your organization
to ensure that, in fact...
learning really, this is your moment to say,
have you really got it?
The person who's on your team when you're talking to them
and you can be in a group environment,
you can break up your teams into smaller groups
to really focus that conversation.
But that after action review.
That's about performance in the team context.
How is your performance as a developer,
this is a tool for you to use,
how is your performance as a developer,
how is that with what we were trying
to accomplish on the team?
It's not coaching like performance review coaching.
It's not the kind of thing,
so one of the problems is we don't always coach people
at the right moments.
We wait until they're way off the deep end,
and they've sunk morale of everybody around them,
and we waited until that moment to coach them.
in good behaviors. Don't wait. Do this all the time.
I drop into offices around the studio all the time
to see how things are going, but also I've heard
something about the possibility of a problem, and I just
want to go see what's up.
Or I've heard something where someone's performance is starting
to lag, and I ask that person's lead to go
follow up. Just spend more time with them.
If you guys are familiar with the Hawthorne effect.
There was a social science experiment years ago where in time series studies they wanted
to see if there was a way to have more productivity in factories.
And they set up a test in a factory and they had a survey set up where the scientists would
walk around and ask questions.
It was a survey of people who were working on the floor.
They wanted to see if lighting conditions would change productivity in that factory.
Well, productivity increased.
And at first they believed that the correlation was directly to these new conditions in the factory.
And later they realized that it probably had a lot to do with,
in fact they discovered it did have a lot to do with just that interaction of people,
of those scientists walking around asking questions on the floor.
The Hawthorne effect has to do with changing the outcome of an experiment
simply by holding it and getting involved in the subjects of that experiment.
So we know that interaction with people who are around us
is gonna improve their performance
because they know that you care.
What you have to do is then turn that into data
and turn that into specification,
turn that into things that you're actually tracking
to know the health of your project.
Maintaining best practices is hard.
This is part of why communication's hard.
Maintenance is a hard thing.
You gotta roll up your sleeves, you have to go do it.
It's hard, so a lot of times it just doesn't get done.
But if you want to have a great postmortem and a great AAR,
if you want to be aware of what's happening in your project,
you have to develop situational awareness and keep it.
You can't let it go,
because your project and your team changes all the time.
Dynamics change, your project's changing,
what's the status of it?
Don't just go asking people for status updates.
You have to know.
And if you don't know,
if you don't know, you're not doing your job.
Frequency has to be high,
and you have to be vigilant about it.
Eons ago, I was working on a project,
and the producer on that project realized
that there weren't enough touch points with the team
and wanted to improve processes,
wanted to do things differently
from how this particular studio I was working at
was doing things at the time.
So that person wanted to institute mid-mortems,
very reasonable,
told the leads that...
Now we were going to have updates regularly.
And these were going to be built around
essentially sprints.
We didn't call them sprints.
We knew that it was time to crunch a little bit.
And we didn't want to use the word crunch.
And we came up with a different word.
I'm saying we generously.
But a different word was used.
And that word was surge.
So we're going to surge ahead.
This period of time, we're going to surge ahead.
And then at the end of this surge,
we're going to get together and talk about how it went.
And then we're going to improve.
So at the end of the surge, people have been crunching a bit.
They had some goals that they'd started with.
They got together.
The whole team, the leads had been tasked
with gathering up information from their team members
about how things went.
They got together, big room like this,
and the leads came up one by one,
and they wrote on a board what their top items were,
and they all agreed on what the number one thing
was that they could fix for the next time.
Well, guess what?
First one, number one thing, communication.
Big letters on the board.
Cool, we'll fix it.
It went away.
Another surge.
Took goals from that first one, went into the next one,
had that next AAR.
Same thing.
Communication.
Big letters.
Number one thing.
At this point, I was starting to worry a little bit, just
that, you know, I don't know how the team's thinking about
this, but.
you know, let it go. See, see how that works out.
At that point, I wasn't in the same role
that I'm in now. Although, I did speak with
that producer a bit about some concerns that I
had.
Third time. What do you suppose happened? Well, here's
what. As the lead started coming up, that producer
said, but this time you can't say communication.
So the leads looked around and said,
we're good.
Everything's great.
Let's go back.
That project shut down two weeks later.
Communication's hard, and if you don't do something
about it, you're gonna fail.
And this is how we felt.
So you can't ignore it.
Here's a good best practice.
By the way, I tend to like to bounce around a bit.
So, for those of you who were in the talk I did last year,
thank you for coming back this year.
And for those who weren't, I'm just letting you know ahead of time,
I like to move around a bit.
So, saying I don't know is a best practice. I love that.
This is how I'm looking for, when I look for new producers to work with.
And I listen for how much experience people have
when they say, I don't know,
because I say, I don't know all the time.
You can't possibly, this industry's moving so fast,
and the things that we do are so complex.
You have to say, I don't know sometimes.
I don't know why anyone would try to fool us
by saying that they do know
or by indicating they know more than they do.
But this is also how you gather up information
to improve and to schedule and to work with your team.
So look for that.
You should value those simple words.
Especially so we can avoid a death march.
You guys recognize this graph? It's pretty well-known.
Okay. Well,
this is considered to be, at least Tufte,
who, whose opinion I, I trust,
says this is probably the best infographic ever made
by Charles Menard.
And this is an infographic about Napoleon's army's march
into Russia, into Moscow.
And what you see is the line that starts out
quite broad on top and gets progressively narrower
to the right as it approaches Moscow
is the number of troops still in Napoleon's campaign.
And then that black line on the way back
is the continued death march home.
And the graphics that you see here are about distance.
They're about temperature.
You can see temperature charted in the bottom.
They're about latitude and longitude.
And they tell a pretty stark story.
Well, if Napoleon knew in advance that this is what the
outcome would be, would he have still engaged his troops?
I don't know.
If he thought he'd won, maybe.
Hard to say.
This cost him his future in France
to become the great emperor that he was looking to be.
And as an infographic,
it's very interesting.
I want to make the point that, as producers,
we use graphs all the time
to communicate things.
We use Gantt charts and burndowns and build fancy things in Excel to show the relationship.
You know, we try to break things down to make them as simple as we can be.
I think we probably still haven't gotten quite as elegant as what we see here,
but I'd encourage you to think about...
breaking away from a rigid practice
of how you display information,
especially quantitative information,
to the teams that you work with.
They're looking for something that distills
the essence of where the project is.
That's all we really care about at any time
is where is the project, where is it going to be,
especially at the executive level.
Is this project going to be worth more than it costs
by whatever number the P&L says it should be?
you can convey that in ways that
show the attitude of your project
and the quality of the game that you're making.
So just think about ways that you can visualize that data
that will really come across to the audience you have
in a way that conveys the heart of what makes your game special.
Discipline, organization, and maturity are not things
that we always found in the game industry.
But I think we're doing a lot better job of that now,
broadly, as game developers have gotten
really experienced and mature over the years.
And we should value the wisdom of those that have been around.
But discipline is hard.
Organization can be hard,
especially for it to not feel overly bureaucratic,
an environment that's looking for creativity.
And maturity.
I don't know much to say about maturity other than we value it.
In this postmortem,
this was a good game that came out last year,
Lords of the Fallen.
This team looks back and thinks,
we're not really sure how we made that game,
given the problems we had going into it.
And they make the point that something they were really looking for,
when they realized they needed it,
was a person.
They were looking for a person
to come in and ask the tough questions
and make the production decisions that needed to be made
because they as a team
had a very difficult time
pulling things out of the game,
cutting things out.
And this really caught my eye.
I don't know what happens on a project to get to the point where the publisher is now
coming in heavily and creative.
They talk about the publisher at this point is actually doing level design, is doing map
design and mission design.
Something's happened in that crazy, chaotic environment where those tough questions aren't
being asked, where the publisher now is having a creative role.
certainly beyond whatever they thought they were signing up to in the beginning,
and not enough communication has been happening.
So somebody needed to come in and create some structure.
And every studio environment, you need structure to give people the trust
that things are going the way they should, to be making a good game.
So I say basically they had not thought about establishing those guidelines for communication.
And once they got the right person in the environment,
that stopped crazy communication happening
between the publisher and the developer
and employing channel people.
Now, every good organization,
it's clear who has responsibility and authority for what.
So...
you should know who in your team is talking with the person on the other side,
if you're working in that developer-publisher relationship.
If you're self-funded, cool.
At least then, though, you should be understanding more about who the customer is,
where are you going to market,
if you're having that sort of direct interaction with customers.
And in that sense, I mean customers who are buying the game.
You have to really understand the structure though, and if you don't,
go make sure that you do.
Start asking hard questions about who's responsible for
which parts of communication with finance, with publishing, with marketing.
But information's not going to move by itself.
You have to do things.
The problem that I've seen time and time again
is simply people not getting out of their chairs.
So you can lead by example to get up, walk around.
As I said, I do that all the time.
Just by you getting up and walking around,
you can show you don't have to be stuck in your chair all day.
But also, some people need some prodding.
You want to do that if the information that they have
is vital to others.
For example, there may be a rendering programmer,
a graphics programmer,
who's working on things that are really important.
to the technical artists and artists and, you know,
level designers and your lighting artists on the team.
And for some reason, that communication hasn't happened
in a way where they know what to expect
at their next big milestone.
Something has to happen,
and you have to be the one to do it
to cause that communication to happen
for those specifications to be written down.
But there are a lot of kinds of, you know,
different people are different.
And they get into this rut of.
not sharing information.
So you have to get it from people into a format that's usable.
And it's hard.
But reminding people what they're doing is awesome really helps.
That encourages them to get up and walk.
It encourages the kind of specificity that you need
to move forward, because they get passionate,
they feel good about what they're doing,
and then you give them a structure in which to work.
And you can funnel that passion into something.
Those who are checked out are not actually going to provide
you the kind of data that you need, the kind of specificity,
for others to understand what they should be doing, or how
to use this tool that's being developed, or this tech that's
being developed, or when does level art come into what your
mappers are doing.
Those who feel good about what they're doing are going to be
more vocal in a positive way.
You guys play Shadows of Mordor?
It's a good game.
Well, in their post-mortem,
it's funny, the thing everybody talks about with that game
is the nemesis system.
And they talk about how they didn't do a very good job
of communicating the promise of it,
internally or externally,
for a long time.
And it created them some issues
as far as spending extra cycles on things
that they could have cut out much sooner than they did.
And they needed somebody in that team,
and you as a producer can do this,
to evangelize a system like that,
the thing that's going to make your game special,
whatever it is, to promote that all around.
When I was at Origin, we would do that.
We would make posters of things,
and I saw other teams inside EA do it,
to really promote what they were doing inside of the system,
to really gain buzz and favor for their projects.
And that's a good thing, to let people know what is special about what you're doing.
And then to connect the people who are working on that special thing with others.
It fuels the passion for making it.
This is a post-mortem from 1999.
It's one of the ones that I used a lot when I was teaching at the Guild Hall still.
Ken Birdwell here talks about the cabal process,
how that evolved on the first Half-Life.
And what it evolved in response to.
And now we call, you know, this is pretty common now.
Strike teams, tiger teams, some people just call them cabals.
We just, we like to group people around features,
things where you can have efficient communication.
But there's a couple of interesting points here
that I still like to look to.
So one of them is, during that process,
they realized that even though level designers
knew about some feature that was made,
in this case, he's talking about a Beam tech
that, um, Code had worked on.
Nobody was using it. They didn't know what it was for.
Hadn't been communicated to them what was special about it.
All those points that were just made,
they weren't doing that.
And their solution was,
well, the Beam tech's made.
It'd be cool if it was used.
So...
The solution is, tell them they need to integrate it,
train them on how to do it,
and then follow through to make sure they really do it.
Now, smart and creative people
don't usually like to be told they have to do a thing
unless they think, especially if you're a level designer
in this kind of environment.
You want to know, I mean, you basically own that level,
right, as that LD.
So you want it to be cool enough where you want to use it.
Not, not that you're told you have to.
But sometimes as producers we have to ride that line.
So you have to make sure you know, and that everybody else knows,
who the customer and the provider of everything that's being done are.
And in your tasks, if you use Jira, let's say, or Hansoft, or whatever you're using,
make sure that it's really clear who's responsible,
who had the vision for a thing, who...
should the implementer go to for more information.
And then if you're in a system like ours,
a lot of times what we do is we essentially hand off
ownership to a person who says they really get the intent.
But for questions, they know how to follow up.
In the past, on Borderlands 1, for example, we saw this.
Some feature request would go in.
It would sit in our task management system for a while.
Wouldn't get a lot of love.
Eventually it'd get picked up, and then it'd be implemented
in essentially a vacuum.
Until we realized in a playable build,
maybe a month later, what had gone wrong
and seeing if we could catch up to fix it.
Well, that's not a best practice,
so I hope that you're doing something better than that.
And one of the things that we do now
is we always make sure we know
who the customer is for a feature.
Now, in this case, I mean customer on the team.
Who's the person on the team that needs a thing?
And out of that, also we developed, we, we built our,
our tools programming team,
who always know who their customers are
around, around the studio.
We see, we don't see this as often anymore,
but, man, it's always frustrating.
You, you must have been in a meeting at some point
where you realized the thing that everybody's arguing about
is something nobody really knows about.
And then you start making calls, hopefully.
Or you do something, or you postpone that meeting.
But if it's a decision that has to be made right then,
you shouldn't probably have gotten to that point.
You should be more careful about how your meetings are structured
so that prior discussion happens before you get to that point.
So think about actually a...
a plan for your meetings that stages them in a way
that the right information gets to the point where
that eventual decision-making meeting happens.
Or allow decisions to be made in those meetings
by the people who are actually doing the work.
You have to decide, but you don't want to get
to this point.
We still see that, but not as often, like I said.
So again, communication's hard.
Some of the harder things that we have to do in production
are these three.
Hiring. Hiring is one of the most difficult and important things
that we can do and get it right.
And it costs us so much when we get it wrong.
And it costs us so much just to do it.
Right now we're going through thousands of resumes
in the studio, where I am, at Gearbox.
And it's a huge process.
And all of you know this, too.
If you've hired anybody, you know how,
unless it was your buddy, you know,
which, then at least you have trust for your buddy.
But it's hard when you get it wrong.
Assessing, assessing a situation
when you have two different points of view
is enormously difficult.
There are tactics that you can employ.
when talking to different, people with different points of view.
And sometimes one of those people isn't wrong.
Sometimes they're both right.
Or they could both be wrong.
But you have to be able to assess that for yourself.
And if you don't have the technical or domain expertise,
and it's not a technical issue, and you're trying to solve it,
either you're making a mistake,
or you just need to bring others into that discussion to help you,
or you're just really comfortable kind of playing it from the hip,
and maybe you'll get it right.
maybe it doesn't matter. Maybe you just need to make a decision so you can move on.
Which is sometimes the best answer.
Sometimes you just need to make a decision so that you can move forward.
But hopefully you're being diligent about that.
Because if you make a technical decision on a topic you don't really know about,
but maybe you think you do, and you're kind of fudging it,
the people that you're talking to know you don't know it.
So watch out.
And resolving disputes.
Similar topic, but in this one, a little more aggressive.
Now, on the topic of hiring,
have you heard of behavioral descriptive questioning before?
A few of us, a couple.
It's something that's really good for you to understand.
It's really simple.
It's no magic to it.
It's just asking people questions
that gets to the specifics of what they actually did.
New hiring managers or people who are involved in hiring
sometimes just make assumptions.
Maybe not so much that the person is, you know,
always has actually done the things that they're talking about,
but more, maybe they're, maybe the person that you're talking to,
that, that candidate, really means well.
Maybe they did things like what they're saying,
so we'll kind of give them a pass.
And I don't do this, really, anymore.
especially after some training and specific methods of questioning
that get at what that person really did.
And I highly recommend that you follow up
and learn more about.
how behavioral descriptive questions are structured,
and more so how to follow up once you get an answer.
Um, you've probably been asked questions like these,
or the, tell me about a time, just like you see here,
give me an example of those kinds of things.
But you, again, if you don't have the domain expertise,
and it's an area where you need that domain expertise,
you need to take another step back,
uh, and bring in a bit of help.
Behavioral descriptives really help with this.
Now, since this is a communication talk, I figured
I'd better make sure I at least cover this.
You need to know what questions are legal and what
questions are not legal.
Make sure you don't ask illegal questions.
It's going to be really bad for you and your
organization if you do.
and in line with that, you should have a formal hiring process.
It's going to help the candidate to know that you have a formal hiring process.
It'll make you look more professional if you're at a smaller studio now
or if you're in a larger organization.
you should go around and ask questions of other hiring managers
of what their approaches have been.
If you're not sharing that kind of information already,
you should start,
especially because you're all working on the same projects
or you might be at some point.
You want to know that the people that they hired under them
are going to fit into the team structure
and be as good as the people that you hire.
So hopefully you've kind of congealed all of you
in your leadership structures.
or you will be in terms of how you actually hire people.
At Gearbox, I like our hiring process quite a lot.
And in fact, we've done that where our code team
built a formal hiring process that the other teams,
once they saw it, loved it so much they began bringing in.
And I can't get into the specifics of what that is too much
other than to say it's kind of industry standard now.
And it goes back to behavioral descriptive.
questioning.
We really want to know
both what you did in the past experience,
and we're going to throw things at you
that give us some clue
of how you will perform in the future
based on what you say about what you did in the past,
not based on guesses.
Do not ask about personal identifiers, affiliations, religion, disability.
I'm just gonna say it, right?
And get professional HR training if you can.
You should.
From that notion of questioning,
and the way that questions are structured,
I'll say this. This is a,
kind of my strategy, I guess, for
how I find out things when I'm talking to people.
And also, it's a tool that I use
to motivate developers to focus in on what's important
and for them to convey back to me
they are, in fact, actually focused
or they've actually done the diligence
of the thing that they need to do.
It may be difficult to read, so I'll read some of these.
Do we know how performance is impacted by these changes?
That could be about a lot of different things, right?
But in asking the question, you find out very quickly,
is cross-team collaboration discussion happening or not?
And have we done the instrumentation that we need to do?
And are we aware of what the deadlines are,
what the build requirements are,
of the release that is coming up for evaluation?
Is somebody about to do something
that's gonna tank this build that's going to be evaluated
for an important milestone without even realizing
that that change they made is going to do that?
Well, you need to know.
Do we know how, you know, obviously for say animation
or something that maybe is being built in movers,
we use Unreal.
Do we know how it's going to be rigged?
Have we considered the impact of co-op?
That's a big one.
That was huge for us on Borderlands 1
as we decided co-op was gonna be an important thing.
We were all, we continue to be surprised actually
by some of the things that impact co-op
in ways that we hadn't considered.
Is there another way to accomplish the same thing?
How will we know if it's good?
These are all focused.
on the, on the actual issue in development.
Not on the person. Right. You want to
be really careful. Especially, especially cause you're now
being seen as someone in a position of authority.
You never want to be seen as a person
who's attacking the developers, just doing their job. Right.
Fortunately, I haven't had too many managers who've made
me feel like I was.
the focus of broader development issues.
But this does happen.
And I know it still happens.
You guys remember Team Bondi?
So in summary on this,
questions are powerful.
You have to practice listening, practice getting conversations moving.
You have to do that, you have to practice it.
You can use humor as a tool, you can use different things as tools.
Not sarcasm, but humor.
Well, I use sarcasm a lot, but only with people who I'm friends with.
You have to really know who the people are that you're talking to.
Stay on topic because you'll be seen as more professional,
and then you can move on from whatever that topic is from there.
But make sure you get to the heart of what the thing was
that you came in to talk to people about
or that you're in the meeting about.
And if you can end the meeting early, do it.
Speak with intent. Know your audience.
You have to know what their filters are.
December 2008.
This was another kind of post-mortem recap.
So in this one...
on Final Fantasy XII,
I thought this was pretty interesting.
Um, here, uh,
Taku talks about, talks on, talks about, um,
what, what happened with the team,
given the freedom to make changes at various stages of development.
So they, they, they're expressing that they had
some freedom to make changes
at some stages of development, um,
but...
That freedom led to miscommunication, confusion, disorder.
I thought this was sort of an odd thing
that freedom would lead to that,
unless in the freedom that they had,
they didn't communicate any of those changes
that were being made.
They didn't, they failed to set the expectation.
That's very dangerous.
We have to be constantly setting expectations
with people around us, don't we?
And then it said right here,
how work was to be distributed was also often ambiguous,
which contributed to the problem.
So that really speaks to the problem
of there not being a producer.
And of course, I'm, you know, I'm.
basing this on what I've read in this post-mortem.
That's the best we can do sometimes.
At least when we're reading these,
we're making guesses, right?
So that being ambiguous means that there wasn't
a producer making sure that as things were being defined
as goals for the project, those turned in specifications.
They didn't stay on top of that rolling wave
as they moved through in development.
Things just happened.
And, um...
I mean, it's an older article.
Things aren't exactly the same.
You know, cultural things happen, be aware of them.
I think that's a good summary.
Recently, and again, this feature actually
is just wrapped up.
I think they're done with the series now.
This is the Games Outcomes Project.
Has anybody been tracking this?
It's a great project.
I love this project.
Paul Tesor, who I respect a lot,
is a great AI programmer and designer.
So he talks here about.
as one of the few things they discovered had real correlation
in the questions that were used.
In the structure of this study,
used a few approaches, theories,
on why things fail with teams,
why things succeed.
And here they realized that this one,
team members would often work for weeks at a time
without receiving feedback from project leads or managers,
led directly to those projects which were assessed
as being some of the failure projects
or lower in the success scale.
And we've seen that.
People who go for a long time without feedback...
First of all, just like we talked before
with the Hawthorne effect, right?
Like, if you're not getting interaction and feedback,
you don't have the context for what you're doing,
you don't know where you stand
in the work that you're doing,
you start to feel a little bad, maybe, about it,
or you don't feel as good.
You're just not as connected.
And we hear that all the time around every studio,
that people don't always feel as connected
as they used to with smaller teams.
And that will impact the quality of their work.
And also, now you're starting to fail expectations.
You can build up an expectation gap
with those people who are the product owners, the EPs,
whoever's going to be ultimately deciding
if the quality of what's been built is good enough or not
and releasable or not.
You've built up debt.
Also, since this is a topic of communication,
I thought I should make sure to point out,
because we were talking about humor and sarcasm a second ago,
you have the responsibility of making sure
that your workplace is a safe environment
and that feels good for people.
You have that responsibility.
And you have the authority to make it so.
I don't care who in your environment...
is creating issues with coworkers,
you have a responsibility to do something about it.
So first, please, no sarcasm that puts down coworkers.
That's not acceptable.
Okay?
No condescension.
No backhanded task comments.
You really have to watch out for this one.
Historically, in some parts of the industry,
there was always a divide.
You know, not so much now.
especially not in our studio, I don't think.
But there was a divide where, um,
those who were considering themselves developers,
uh, saw there being sort of a gulf
between themselves and those who were in QA.
Now we have a lot of great producers and executives
and people who came up through QA,
and we really appreciate the close collaboration,
uh, between all the departments.
And now I just see QA as another
one of those development departments.
Um...
But occasionally you see really shitty comments
from people in development to people who are reporting bugs.
You have to watch for that.
Don't let that happen.
It will make your product worse.
Condescension as well.
Not that long ago, it was called to my attention
that someone who was in a, call it a technical,
creative discipline, was making comments in tasks
about a tool that they were developing.
Which, by the way, it's a tool.
It implies that there are customers on the creative side
who are gonna be using that tool.
And sort of calling out some of the comments
about why people thought that tool
or that approach that person was using wasn't the best.
And then I saw this kind of back and forth,
very thinly veiled passive-aggressive
back and forth happen that we had to put the kibosh on.
And we did.
And then it's funny, once we talked to the people involved,
you know, whether or not they really knew
what they were doing,
they kind of expressed they didn't.
They were just kind of trying to get their point across.
And you as a producer have to be the adult there.
No name-calling.
And at the same time, though...
If you're hearing those kind of things, so and so is stupid.
Now, that's different from this thing that we're doing is stupid, right?
Don't tolerate low performance, because if you let people stay around your environment
who are low performers, that's gonna tank the performance and the morale of everybody
else, right?
So if you have a low performer, you have to get rid of them.
Don't let them just sit there in the environment and get kicked around a lot.
They have to go.
You can't have saccharine cows there.
And you have to get rid of bad processes.
So if somebody says this process is stupid,
well, talk it through.
It's possible the process is stupid.
But at the same time, unless you've really understood
where that person's coming from,
you can't assess.
Just same as what we were saying before.
If you don't have the technical expertise and domain,
you can't really know if you don't get more help.
So...
Going back to communications hard.
I was talking to a project producer a few years ago
who had a kind of a monumental set of tasks on top of them.
They had a really hard job to do
based on the nature of what they were trying to ship.
And then they had more and more things heaped on top of them.
And so that person kind of delegated a bit,
a very small amount,
some production responsibility of some of those other things.
And that producer came to me and just completely befuddled,
totally befuddled, said this.
They had the same information as me.
How could they possibly have come to a different conclusion?
Something's wrong with that person.
You should fire them.
After sitting down with the person in question and this
producer, realized all the decisions that had been made
were great decisions for these things that had been
delegated.
They were actually great decisions.
They made the product better.
but there had been a failure to communicate and set expectations
as changes happened.
Kind of like staying on top of that rolling wave.
And so, because the end result of those decisions was so different
from what the producer thought was going to happen in the beginning,
all they could see what the result was
and immediately see it as all bad.
And it took a long time, actually.
In this case, I mean, every hour is expensive.
It took a couple of days to work it out
and see that actually it was okay.
But that communication goes both ways.
It's why it's important for you to communicate up well
to your leads and set those expectations
and do the same with the team that you're working with,
your peers, collaborators, and your teams.
You have to be constantly setting those expectations,
or people will see a thing that happens later
and react to it very differently
than if they understood the expectation up front.
Communication's hard. Some cats are going to sneak by you.
It's impossible to get them all.
You could be patient. You could learn about people more.
You can find out that you can do things to bring them to you.
Even the most belligerent people up front getting to know you.
Understanding not just your intent, because everybody can have good intent.
But if they see that you're trying hard and that you're learning,
and you're learning about what they do.
and that you appreciate and respect them,
and you don't allow yourself to fall into bad habits.
If you're really setting the standard,
people will flock to you.
They'll talk about you like,
well,
God, I was going to say the cat's meow,
but I can't help it.
Free association.
They will always want to work with you.
Okay.
Let them come to you.
Perfect communication, guys, is not possible. It's why,
in the description for the talk, I said, it's
hard, might as well give up now. OK.
And I'm giving us some hyperbole. It's, it isn't
possible to have perfect communication, because again, you only
control what you do. Right. So if you want
perfect, if you're always going to be frustrated because
things you say are going to be mistaken, all
you can do is improve your side of it.
You have to practice your communication skills.
The way that you break down tasks, what you learn,
the domains of the people around you, the wave of what's happening
in technology around you.
This industry is changing so fast.
You have to stay on top of it.
And I want to see you all, as you succeed, or not,
whatever's happening on your projects, keep learning.
Help us as a community learn.
Share what you've learned.
And write new postmortems.
And that's it.
Thank you.
applause
So I think we got a little bit of Q&A time,
if anybody wants to ask any questions,
or else, uh,
I know we have a great panel coming up pretty soon.
Anybody have any questions?
Okay.
Q So you were mentioning before about visualizations.
A Yes.
Q And I was wondering if you could give examples
of some of the visualizations that you've used very effectively in the past.
A Thank you.
So some, some visualizations I think I've used effectively.
Some of them have been things that...
were in fact kind of time series between,
basically showing dependencies between departments.
I don't have them to show you here.
Maybe I could follow up with a few that I'd show,
but I can describe a couple.
One is, I was working on a project
that was new IP.
It was seeking to innovate.
And it had an uncertain budget.
It was a large budget, but it was uncertain.
And between ourselves and the publisher,
we wanted to understand...
the, uh, kind of the difference between
our perceived value of what we'd built
and, um, uh, and the true value of where it was.
Um, so I built a graph that showed
the value of other projects, um, that had just shipped,
that had some of those innovations,
and, um, the entropy of, uh,
basically in people's minds.
how fresh would those ideas still be when they came together as one?
And how long would it take us actually to finish,
depending on how many of those innovations we finished?
In this case, we were doing some very heavy physics stuff.
We were doing some brand new animation tech.
We were doing destruction.
This is all long before this generation of platforms launched.
and it was going to be a last-gen project.
So basically, sketching all those things out
and also showing what the gap was to when we thought
the next-gen platforms would be.
Basically, all the costs involved
and what the market expectation would be
and what it would cost to get us there
versus basically cutting those things
and shipping what still would have been a good game
without all those innovations.
And doing it in a way that didn't take those people
who had been working on them...
and not pay respect to the effort that they put in, and their feelings about it.
So, in that, showing not just the work that they've done, say,
a couple programmers and a designer, or animation tech,
and a few animators and a programmer, but...
all the other people in that dependency chain
who also would have to work on it,
so that if we decided to cut that feature,
that all the people who'd been working on it
really understood what the larger risk was and cost was,
as opposed to just what they'd done.
And also how we could, um...
Well, that's basically what the graph focused on.
From there, though, it was used in communication
to talk about how we could recycle those things
for future projects.
Any time you're gonna deliver some...
something that could be bad news, I want to see if we can refocus that to show how something
will be better in the future.
A few other things would be, I had a great AP on a project
who helped me with, if you guys have tried to use
JIRA and Project together, you know how much of a bear
that is, but helped me with a near real-time flow
of data between JIRA and Project so that we could
visualize the impact of tasks that were being created.
on a regular basis.
Once we had to sequence those out into our project plan,
and we could visualize at a much more micro level
than we typically would in project.
Actually, in that Gantt view, which can be helpful
because it gives you...
It gives you the brackets within which things are going to happen.
It can be used as a helpful tool
because it's a bit of information overload.
It's like there's all this stuff suddenly,
this work that's suddenly been created.
Could we please just finish the work that we already committed to?
Because we know that those bars are really going to grow
for the polish of every one of those things.
It was just a handy tool.
Those are a couple.
Thank you very much.
Sure. Any other questions?
No time? Okay. Thanks, guys.