Okay, all right, we'll kick it off. So this is about an hour. We might have some time for some Q&A.
We'll go through at a high level.
how we took Tomb Raider, started it, looked at reinventing it and all the way through
the last four years to what we have released March the 5th just recently.
My name is Darryl Gallagher, I'm the studio head for Crystal Dynamics and to my right
here is Noah Hughes, creative director at Crystal Dynamics and on Tomb Raider.
So we're just off the back of a very successful launch of Tomb Raider.
How many here have actually played it or seen it?
Some hands? Good. Awesome. Nice. That's a good start.
Thank you.
How many here have got a hangover from last night?
That's why I'm here.
So excuse any stumbles.
Okay, so thankfully we had a great launch in March for this game
and we had this talk prepped prior to launching the game on the reinvention and reboot of Tomb Raider.
And it was successful, so we didn't have to rewrite the talk, which we're very happy about.
It could have been a what went wrong. Thankfully, it's not that.
So it really is a broad case of here are some things that we thought went well,
some pro tips around the project,
and some experiences we had from start to finish that we hope that we can share with you today.
So we're going to go through a quick outline here from a franchise perspective, how we
went about reinventing an icon such as Lara Croft and Tomb Raider.
Goals and methodology, in terms of our high level goals at the beginning of the project,
some of the things we look to want to achieve.
Some production techniques in terms of how we made the project and how we went through
each phase of the project at a high level.
creative techniques with Noah in terms of how we went about making a very narrative driven production
and it involved changing major parts of how we did things at Crystal and last but not least
some pro tips that we hope we can leave you with today and maybe take back to your studios and learn from.
So at a high level it was roughly a four year period from start to finish on this project
and it wasn't always perfect. So while this PowerPoint is nice and slick and we've rehearsed
and we'll go through it in an hour, the actual production of four years you're going to have
bumps along the way. So I just wanted to say that these are some of the good things we've learned
but any project you do that is special and we wanted this to be special is going to be tough.
and it had bumps along the way so this is a consolidated version of that.
Digging into the project, it's the biggest game we've ever done at Crystal.
It's two teams that have worked on this.
We did the single player here, close to here, 25 miles away in Redwood City.
And the multiplayer was done with our sister studio, Eidos Montreal, in Canada.
We were lucky enough to get a huge amount of recognition along the way as we were making this game.
We had over 50 magazine covers and two E3 stage demos and over 150 awards and nominations along the way,
which on a long development of three or four years is very encouraging and definitely put some fuel in the fire that we were doing something right.
It's been the biggest week one sales in franchise history.
We're only a few weeks into that launch right now and it's been the biggest opening so far of 2013.
So we're happy with the outcome.
We're certainly in a place where we feel like we're on our road to achieving everything we wanted to.
I'm going to play a quick video right now which is just a short 60 second recap of where we landed.
Every survivor has a story.
You've got great instincts, girl.
You just have to trust them.
Every mystery has its truth.
What the hell is happening on this island?
Every saga has its beginning.
Alright, there it is.
So we're going to talk about how we got there from beginning, middle to end.
It was an epic adventure, much like one of Lara's.
And we're going to walk you through that at a very high level.
Some of our challenges, you know, it's great to be working on a franchise like Tomb Raider
with the recognition and the popularity it has, but it came with challenges.
And with 17 years of history since 1996...
It left us in a position as we finished up three games at Crystal feeling like we had to make some changes.
And that's natural when you're dealing with a long-running franchise, but we were really encountering this for the first time.
As a result of the ups and downs of that long history, you have sort of mixed feelings and loyalty around sort of a fan base.
We had new contenders at that time in 2008, 2009 when we were starting this in the likes of...
Assassin's Creed or Uncharted or God of War 3, there was a new generation of hardware
and there were new contenders to the Action-Adventure crown that were bringing their new angles
and really doing some great stuff around Action-Adventure too.
Also we had a generational change, not only in hardware, but it was also in terms of our
fan base and our audience as well.
Obviously, 17 years later, the people that may have started playing Tomb Raider in 96
may be different people today.
They may have never played it before.
Some people would have and some people won't.
So we also had to think about how we spanned from one generation to another, and that was
some of the challenges we were dealing with going into this project.
So, these were some of the things we did coming off the back of a trilogy we created in Legend,
Anniversary and Underworld.
And as we finished that up, that was very much based on a formula very much from Core
Design and we were successful with that formula.
But going into this new phase of Tomb Raider, these were some of the challenges we felt
like we had to deal with.
From a goals perspective...
Ultimately, we wanted people to fall in love with Tomb Raider once again, with this next game.
And this is what we started with way back when.
We had a real goal to make Lara somebody you could get to know again, to humanise her,
for her to be less of this superhero that you knew because you played N number of games and seen the movies,
but somebody that we actually got to know once again and fall in love with over again, like it happened in 1996.
So therefore we had to challenge the expectations around Lara and the brand.
We had to make sure that we were embracing this new audience that maybe hadn't played Tomb Raider before,
or maybe they were old fans that were revisiting that we had lost along the way.
And to do that we really felt like we had to make some big changes.
Quality and innovation was synonymous with Tomb Raider in 1996 and along the way it was
one of the pioneers in action adventure.
So we wanted to put that stamp back into this game, we wanted to be right up there as the
best of the best.
So these were high goals that we had at the beginning of this project.
And ultimately we still had to thread the needle because it's a tightrope to walk between old and new.
That we had this franchise with this fanbase and all this rich history, but we wanted to take it to a new place.
And that tightrope is a very, very narrow one to walk because too much old and it feels like it's...
the old game, and it may as well be a sequel, too much new, and maybe it wouldn't be Tomb Raider anymore.
And whilst we sort of approached this with a blank canvas, the actual reality was it was a very, very narrow razor that we had to walk.
So it's tough doing these types of games as reboots.
Originally, it actually didn't start as a reboot, it was almost a pseudo-sequel.
And as ideas were being kicked around in the early stages of development in concept and in pre-production,
it became clear that to achieve the goals we just set out in slides before,
that we ultimately had to wipe the slate clean.
And we needed to make a fresh start with this character, and a fresh start with no preconceptions built in for the audience.
So ultimately it became an origin story and we were buoyed and encouraged by other franchises
around us outside video games where we looked and we felt that they had actually taken a
similar approach.
So here we have Bond and Batman that are two amazing examples outside games where Bond
has been around 50 years this year and has just done a billion dollars at the box office.
So it's as fresh as it was 50 years ago today and Batman is in a similar place as well.
And I think the key thing about this and why we looked here is because in games having 17 years of history,
ultimately we were one of the first to have to go through this.
You know, it's a shorter time scale in games in terms of people having franchises
because game space is much narrower and obviously younger than things like movies.
So we looked outside and what we felt was these franchises have done such a great job
in retaining the DNA of their characters and their franchises but bringing it to new generations
and really making it feel fresh.
And they've managed to span generation to generation but retain their franchise integrity.
So we were very much inspired by this and this origin story, but we really had to find our own slant on that.
And ultimately, we knew we wanted to make an origin story, we knew that we had these high goals,
but we were looking in early stages around how we could hang our hooks on something that made it feel fresh.
for Tomb Raider and also fresh in the industry.
So many ideas were thrown around and explored in the early stages of development
and ultimately we landed in a spot where we found something we felt that we could hang our hooks on,
which I'll hand over to Noah to discuss.
Yeah, it was important to understand that in humanizing Lara by rolling her back to an origin story,
we were making her closer to you or I and hopefully a more relatable character.
But the most exciting part about it was that we could then take her on that journey,
we could take the players on that journey to becoming the Tomb Raider.
But...
We needed a sense of identity beyond just origin story.
So we looked at a lot of different things,
but ultimately we came upon the idea of survival stories.
And for us, we were really inspired
by the real world tales of survival.
We have Aaron Ralston here, who featured in 127 Hours,
ultimately had to cut off his own arm in order to survive.
Or the rugby players in the Andes
who resorted to cannibalism in order to survive.
These are.
at the surface, very dark stories.
But what was interesting to us is
there was a sense of inspiration to these stories,
that there was a memorable journey here
that showcased the human capacity to overcome.
And ultimately, through that journey,
these people were changed as well.
So that idea that we could.
take Lara's origin story and tell it through the lens of survival was very compelling to
us and we felt would help humanize her as a character.
But we had to zoom in a little bit and understand what that meant.
I think what we found was that
Survival can be many different things to many different people.
So we tried to clarify what it would mean to us in this game.
So first of all, survival action.
And that's to sort of balance out this sense
that there's a simulation version of survival as well.
But because pace was incredibly important to our game
experience, we really wanted to capture that survival action.
But it would still be brutal, perilous, raw.
This would be the harsh environment
that would forge Lara.
And it would ultimately ask her.
to fight to survive, that we wanted to showcase
her determination as a character, her endurance, her will to live in the face
of death,
but also as a character who's sort of an intellectual hero.
We love that aspect of resourcefulness that we saw in these stories. Here's
people who
had nothing and they had to make do with what they had and it was really
that ability to adapt to their situation
that let them survive. So these are all things that very much resonated with
the franchise for us. So just to capture some in a sentence, the idea of the
determination to go beyond human endurance, taking the moment of raw
instinct and stretching it. It's about overcoming that near-death experiences
time and time again.
So we had now an inspiration in survival.
And at the end of this concept phase,
we sort of summed that up with a survivor is born.
And ultimately, that became our tagline.
But internally, it was also a guiding vision.
It captured that idea of Lara's origin story seen
through the lens of survival.
So with that, we felt we had a very clear sense
of a high-level vision for the game.
So I'll turn it over to Daryl to get back
into production a little bit.
Thanks, Noah.
So now we had our identity, at least a hook we felt we could work with, and a high level of what we wanted to do with the game.
And ultimately going into the high level in production, I guess I wanted to sort of carve out what we use, which is a rule of thirds.
This at a high level is what we've done on the last couple of projects at Crystal.
including Lara Croft and the Guardian of Light.
And essentially it's just breaking your production from a high level into
one third for pre-production and what we call vertical slice,
which is the end of pre-production for us,
one third for production, and one third for post-production.
Some commentary around that, I mean typically what we've seen, you know we've all made a lot of games here,
is that that first third and that last third tend to get squished and shortchanged in lots of ways.
And we felt that it was important that we actually maintained sort of an uncompromising view on what we wanted in each third,
and therefore shape the production around this rule of thirds.
We wanted to give as much time as we could in post-production to polish and refine.
what we had and we wanted to make sure that every step of the way in pre-production and
vertical slice it was clear what game we were making.
So there's always a lot of pressures in each one of these phases and even though it was
a four year period essentially once we found our hook of survival in early exploration
really that pre-production to vertical slice phase was one year, production was one year
and post-production was one year and we're going to walk through each one of those phases
at a high level and show some videos of where we were at each stage.
So some quick stats around it. We made a 12 hour plus experience. 10 to 12 hours is what we were aiming for.
We actually found that once people played the game, we saw them play for 14, 18, 20, 25 and more.
So we've been very pleased with the feedback.
absolutely built a very, very big production in this game because it was a complex, big game to make.
So we had to focus very much on our tools and pipeline.
I know Jason has given a talk this week around our tools.
Also there's some other talks around our process today as well from some other folks at Crystal, so please go see those.
But tools and pipeline, because we weren't going to be able to...
an army of hundreds making this game,
we were gonna be under a hundred ultimately
making this game happen on the single player side.
So we wanted tools and pipelines
to really be that driving force
to help us iterate quickly,
to help designers and artists
really have the power in their hands.
So it was a big investment in the tools that we made
to make a level editor that really put the power in
the content creator's hands with live editing,
live updating, and a very flexible,
powerful system to create content.
We totally turned our production methodology on its head.
In many ways in this production, we did things very, very differently.
And because we were building such an important origin story,
we actually made a beat-driven development process.
Now we'll actually go into a little bit more detail there.
But essentially, in previous games, it was saying we wanted to do 10 or 12 hours.
What's the footprint for that? It's about this big, let's fill it with stuff.
And this one, it was, we still wanted 10 to 12 hours, but we wanted every moment to feel like it fitted into a larger picture.
So the scheduling and production was built around beats and moments that we wanted to deliver from an experiential standpoint.
And that's how we costed things, that's how we produced things, and that's how we scheduled out the whole production.
So the actual footprint from the game was built from beats.
which we'll go into again a little later with Noah.
We also had a very modular level design process,
especially on the art side,
that ultimately we had to build big worlds,
biggest worlds we've ever built for Tomb Raider,
and we had to do it in a way where we kept the fidelity,
but we kept flexibility in building them too.
So we had a very instance-driven art approach with the art team and the design team where
there was a lot of repetition, a lot of clicking together Lego pieces to really build an organic
world.
And that was a complete 180 on how we built things before at Crystal, and still do have
a very crafted look.
But ultimately we wanted that crafted look, but we wanted flexibility with it.
So it was really about embracing this modular development process and pipeline as well.
And that allowed us to ultimately get to the point where we could bring our partners to
work with us.
And we had a robust outsourcing pipeline that by the end of production we were able to actually
send out a rough version of a level in Graybox that had been designed with modules.
over to partners overseas in Shanghai and we would get back an alpha quality level at the end.
It required some touch-up and finishing but ultimately was produced with external partners
which was an amazing feat when we have a very high bar for our game.
We had multiple cinematic production companies through production as well, so we worked externally
with a number of partners on over 90 minutes of story content for cinematics.
So it was a very big production overall.
I think one of the key things that we did in the last couple of games, including this
one, is this philosophy is know as you go, as I put it.
And essentially we put quality as the premium, which makes it very difficult to schedule.
So ultimately we put...
The emphasis on knowing every step of the way whether we were actually achieving what we wanted to achieve from a quality perspective.
And this allowed us to scope along the way when we were off in time or off in targets and shape and change our production in order to maintain quality and deliver against our high goals.
Ultimately, one of the problems we've seen in the past is if you deliver things at 50%
or 60% at alpha and don't take it all the way up, it can be difficult to schedule that
post-production part of the project.
Quite often we see, and I've seen, projects really get to the point...
where they've actually taken too much time in production,
they haven't really understood how long it takes to get to the quality bar they're aiming for,
and ultimately there's a block of time, which is your alpha to bug fixing to shipping,
and that is relatively immovable at that point, because it's very late in the production process.
So what we wanted to do on this was essentially not wait to find out exactly what game we were making, but be sure every step of the way.
So it had to be great at every milestone.
And that was really our philosophy on the last few games at Crystal, that ultimately...
If you're not great every step of the way, then don't expect to be great at the end.
So we wanted every milestone to be great and we wanted to know whether we were on or off.
And ultimately, even though we use production schedules to drive our metrics
and we use production to really calibrate what we're doing and how fast we're going,
the sticks...
and the screen really are our ultimate production schedule.
And it's about picking up the controller, playing the game, and saying,
is it great? And if not, scope accordingly, change, fix it,
and do whatever we can to get that right.
So we were iterating to make sure that we held up that bar every step of the way.
It's important you don't drink your own Kool-Aid and you're not the one saying it's great, but other people are too.
Ultimately, we're making this for an audience.
So it was important that we also brought that audience into Crystal and we got validation along the way that what we thought was great was actually working for them too.
So we have a focus testing lab at Crystal.
We had focus testing from pre-production all the way through to the end of the production,
roughly every two weeks early on in pre-production, through production,
going down to every week and almost every day as we got through to the end of the project.
And that was key in terms of understanding whether our choices from a design standpoint
were actually working when people got their hands on the sticks.
I think one of the other biggest things we did was build our game as episodic chunks.
And this was a very different way of building.
We had built our game in contiguous chunks of content that were almost products in themselves
within a larger production cycle.
So they were developed to an alpha quality before we moved on.
And ultimately, if we didn't hit what we felt from a quality standpoint within these chunks,
they were roughly about three hours each.
Then we would iterate until we did and we would scope the remainder of the project to make sure that we still hit our timelines that we needed to.
And this allowed, if we were productizing along the way and essentially making nuggets of product that were three hour chunks,
what we could do is really very clearly see where we were on or we were off and make...
choices along the way. And as we said, it's game development, so it's never perfect and
you're always making choices. So the more knowledge you have and the more data you have
about whether you're on or off from a quality standpoint, if you're putting that as a premium,
it allows for better choices down the line.
So we made many scoping decisions along the way around the content at the end of each one of these chunks,
which we're actually going to show shortly some videos of.
We could review it, we could refine at the end of every episode,
and we could come back to the next episodic chunk that the whole team was on at any one point
and say, how do we do it better next time?
And through that process, it really did get faster and quicker to produce the game.
So moving into pre-production, again, that sense of it being a product really existed
in our first playable.
And ultimately, even though we spent quite a long time looking at different flavors of
the game, and before hanging our hooks on survival, ultimately when we came to doing
our first playable demo, we wanted to make that feel like a product in itself.
And ultimately that had a beginning, middle, and end.
It was a 30-minute experience, and we wanted it to feel like you could put it in somebody's
hands, and it was as close to a shipping game as we could make.
So we started that in 2010. It took about five months to develop our first playable demo.
And I think a testament to that is, out of that first playable, it was taken to, as I said, a 30-minute chunk of shippable game almost.
We actually presented that to Game Informer and they were...
We were lucky enough that they put it on the front cover and really embraced what we were
doing because they could see very clearly at that stage what we were making.
So it was definitely one of those things internally, it was a great calibration tool for us to
work with.
In terms of approaching it, Noah's going to take a look at the pillars and then we'll
show some short videos as well around it.
Yeah, so as we step through each of these phases of production, I'm just going to give you a few glimpses of some of the key documents we used to capture the creative intent, and also give some snapshots of actually what we were putting on screen.
So, we had this idea of the survival informed origin story, but it was also a Tomb Raider game, so as we, obviously, as we start to set out to make the game itself, understanding how that applies to the gameplay experience is important.
So we've always had the sense of our core pillars in the Tomb Raider franchise.
So traversal, combat, and smart puzzle solving are really our core gameplay mechanics.
And as we discussed before, we were going to infuse them with this flavor of survival action.
So in the case of traversal, that meant treacherous, dangerous world,
and ultimately less canned controls, less canned jumps, so you really felt at any moment.
you could fail and you were in connection with the character.
In terms of combat, we moved from a lock-based system
to a full third-person aim system, but also really tried to capture that sense of desperation.
We were rolling Lara back to a point where she was far less confident
and far less competent than people knew her as, and we wanted that to show in her animation and in her mechanics.
And in the case of puzzles, we really
embraced the idea of physics, both for its simulation aspect,
but also the idea that it helped players
with an understanding of cause and effect,
that by using fire and water and mass and pulleys,
we could create environmental challenges that really asked
the player to, like we saw in the survival stories,
use what was at hand in order to overcome their obstacles.
So this is very simple.
And you'll see with a lot of these,
it is important to be able to boil things down.
to a very simple view and sort of guide your vision
with very clear and precise concepts.
This is a little more complex, but it's really just
speaking to a philosophy we had, which
was the idea that these gameplay, the spikes
of different colors, really are different gameplay flavors.
But the dotted line represents this experience.
So in a lot of ways, what we were creating
was not a sequence of game design challenges,
But really, an experience made up of those challenges.
So that's a philosophy, this idea of variety and intensity
as a function of pacing is something
you'll see through all of our docs here.
We're going to take a quick look at actually some of the content that we were putting on
screen at this time.
So this was in mid-2010.
This was cut from probably about 30 minutes of gameplay, and this, we cut it together
at the time, so this was sort of our trailer packaged up, and this helped us both internally
see our concepts in practice, but also, as Darrell mentioned, starting to generate support
externally both within the organization and within the press.
You think you know me?
Think you've seen me before?
The Brit Princess.
Rich girl with a pretty face.
and a flair for gymnastics.
I think you've got me mixed up with someone else.
I'm not perfect.
I'm not bulletproof.
I struggle.
I bleed.
I get lost.
I know pain.
I know fear.
One day, I will become a legend.
A warrior.
A raider.
But first, I will be a survivor.
Still think you know me?
philosophy really actually showed us very early in production that we were going to
struggle to meet that. So it meant that we could actually communicate to Square and to
the wider group that based on what we wanted to achieve, we did actually have to move the
date. And it wasn't a surprise. It wasn't like it came at alpha. It came fairly early
in production. So even though the date was changed, there was no surprises with that,
which I think is sort of the good moral of that one.
So this wasn't the end of pre-production for us, that was first playable.
But it really had that identity that we wanted.
It was absolutely playable on the sticks as a 30-minute experience.
Going into our next phase is what we call vertical slice, which is the last phase before production.
This was a seven month period where the team worked on really taking that skeleton and
fleshing it out and putting the meat on the bones to make playable, full playable expressions
of all the pillars.
This amounted to about one and a half to two hours of content at alpha quality.
all the base mechanics were in and implemented.
We didn't think it was going to be, it needed to be two hours, that wasn't really the aim.
The aim was to make sure we had full playable expressions
of all the gameplay patterns that we needed to go on and replicate in production.
So it was a case of making sure we had one of everything.
And because experience was really what we were aiming for, rather than components,
it had to be strung together as a complete narrative start to finish.
So it was contiguous.
It represented every part of what we needed to build in production and it ultimately came
as a 1.5 to 2 hour experience which was larger than I guess we planned originally.
I guess the good thing from that, again putting quality as a premium and not moving on until
we actually achieved it, is when it came to doing things like demos and actually getting
the word out there, we didn't have to do very much which was a good by-product.
One, the team knew internally what they needed to build,
but two, when we got asked to be on stage in 2011
from Microsoft, we said, let's take five minutes or so
of our vertical slice and put that on stage.
So literally, the work involved to do a demo
for a Microsoft keynote was a small team of a few people
for a few days to really just cut down the content
and say, here you go.
So it was not custom crafted.
So that was a great by-product of taking quality and pushing it hard early.
Another aspect of vertical slice is one of the common challenges in game development,
which is sort of planning at the same time you're putting that hour and a half on screen,
that's a demonstration of your vision, you're planning the whole game.
So for us, it was important for us to come out of that pre-production phase,
knowing exactly what we were going to build.
And in some ways that's a challenge just from a documenting perspective.
So I think one of the ways we approached...
this game was to look at it as an experience driven game,
which meant it wasn't really purely a story driven game,
it wasn't purely a gameplay driven game,
it was really all of these things coming together
to create an experience,
because the players really don't experience them
independent of each other.
So this document, it's not necessarily important
to see the details,
but the horizontal separators are levels,
so between that would represent about 20 minutes of gameplay,
so each segment was about two minute granularity
at this point.
But looking at the columns, the center column was story beats.
So that was much like just a treatment that you'd have for a game story.
But then as you sort of expanded on that with gameplay concepts,
on the right-hand column you have Lara's character arc,
because obviously that was very important to us in an origin story.
And then to the right of that, her gameplay progression, so where gear and
abilities came in.
And on the left-hand side, you can see the colored bands.
And the one colored band represents the different
flavors of gameplay.
And then the grayscale represents the
intensity of that.
So through this documentation process, we were able to
visualize a little bit more richly than just a level
document or a story document might do.
And so we were able to map out and create a framework for the
entire game.
In our case, we were also trying to tell a fairly linear story in a fairly non-linear world.
So this is just an example of then mapping that experience to our spatial layout.
So we chose a hub-based system, which ultimately uses gear for the player to unlock new spaces.
So down the bottom of the page here, you can see the gear that's acquired over time,
and each of those is a key for one of the locked areas.
So by getting new gear, you can see you can progress through the various areas of the game.
So it was just tools like this that allowed us to sort of zoom out and visualize the whole game experience.
But one of the great things about having that sense of a full framework,
all of the disciplines can work within that.
So in a lot of cases you might have art understanding what the region is
and being able to concept against the basic themes.
But because we knew Lara's journey,
Art could do exercises like this,
doing a great job of really capturing
not only the physical requirements of the space,
but really the emotional context of where
it is in Lara's journey.
So having that sense of an entire framework
and coming out of pre-production with a fairly clear vision
of the whole game was important to us.
But as Joel mentioned, we also had to put it on screen.
So what we'll show you now is probably a five-minute video
cut together of.
an hour and a half of gameplay content.
This was done probably at the beginning of 2011.
So this is still two years before we shipped,
but it represents the first shippable,
essentially shippable content if we had to.
I thought you were alive.
God's got nothing to do with it.
It's good to see you two go.
Sorry, you did a real number on your leg.
No, it looks worse than it is.
Something to pry this open.
R.I.P.
Okay.
So what was great about that, and it's even amazing to look back on in some ways, that
that was two years before our game shipped, and before we even started production.
But we had one of everything, we had an hour and a half to two hours in the can, and the
key thing about making a product every step of the way, this was going to ship.
and it had to be treated like that.
So we then had to just move on and make more.
So that was the next phase of production, which was a year.
So there was 12 months in production.
We had about 9 hours of content to be produced in that period.
We had sort of an hour and a half to two hours in the can from what you've just seen.
And we were making them in episodes, as I mentioned earlier.
So that represented one episode.
Holistically, the team worked on each episode start to finish,
including all the sound, the effects, the usual finishing things.
And each episode, or vertical slice chunk as we called it internally,
really comprised of that same sort of pre-production, production,
alpha, bug fixing, sort of almost a product in itself from start to finish.
I think it's the most important thing is to look at the ratio of time per episode
and know that practice makes perfect.
So if we said that we spent seven months on that first chunk of an hour and a half
and then we had twelve months to do the next nine hours,
that doesn't add up on paper.
as we knew internally. But what we do know is we get better with practice, and what we
had to find out was how quick we could go and how much practice would make perfect.
And ultimately going into production, really we did. And one of the key things to that
was building expertise around each discipline and around each pillar. So we had these pillars
of traversal, combat, puzzles, and some other ones outside that, such as hubs and effects.
music, but ultimately the key pillars, we actually built teams around that were multidisciplinary
that had their own leads and they had their own ownership over a piece of the experience
that was mapped to that larger, broader strokes in the documentation Noah was going through.
And ultimately as each team worked on a pillar, they became better and better and faster and
faster.
So, over the course of production, the first hour and a half to two hours was about seven
months.
The second one was around six months, five to six months of that year.
The third, and these are all three hour increments moving into production, the third one was
around three and a half months and the last one was about two and a half months.
So by the end of production of that year, the team, along with all the external partners
we had brought on to help us through production, was moving at
3 hours of content in around 2-3 months versus 7 months for an hour and a half of content
in vertical slice.
So what it allowed us to do, as I said earlier, at the end of each episodic chunk was actually
make decisions and scope and really learn how much gain we could produce in the time
whilst maintaining quality.
And ultimately production was comprised of what you just saw 4 times over.
We had 250 cinematic moments and 90 minutes of custom storytelling cinematics.
So it was a large cinematic pipeline that we produced in that year as well.
And ultimately we had teams around the world working for that year, producing content for the production phase.
So teams in San Francisco, obviously with our sister studio in Montreal, Shanghai, India, L.A. and a number of other places.
But you name it.
we brought them on board and said let's get this done.
So it was done in a year period and that really brought us to Alpha.
So quick docs, I'm just going to flick through them.
in terms of scheduling, because we were building in patterns,
ultimately we could actually schedule out
what are the patterns and what do we need to repeat.
And each level was comprised of those patterns
that we could then take from vertical slice
and almost sort of map to production and say
it's kind of like this, but with a different wrapper.
And ultimately those patterns we could then cost against.
So, I'm not going to go in detail through this,
but again, similar to Noah's document,
from a production standpoint,
we added up the costs.
associated to each beat or each moment we produced
and we broke down each beat and moment throughout the whole game
and then applied a cost to it.
Ultimately, you're never right with documentation when you start out
and we refined it over time and became more and more accurate
about what we could produce in the time we had.
The other key thing is understanding where you're at at any one period in time and having a team all understand it too.
And one of the things when you've got a lot of people with their heads down producing content,
just saying, here's what we need to be done and being clear about it is very, very important.
So we actually lined the internal team up all around the same milestones rather than have a lot of...
I guess cross-hatching if you say in a schedule where people are finishing things at different
times.
We really tried to finish everybody at the same time on the end of each vertical slice
chunk of content so everybody knew when done was and what done looked like.
It had to look like our first vertical slice repeated.
Yeah, and as Darrell mentioned, working with those patterns was important.
So from a creative perspective, we had the Uber doc, which mapped out the whole game,
but it was a higher level of detail than you would want to actually produce the content.
So as we zoomed in, this represents a beat doc.
So for every level we would do, we would do a beat doc for about.
20 minutes of gameplay, you'd have about 10 plus pages.
So the first page is something you'd find in a lot of docs,
probably the setting, premise.
We're tracking Lara's emotional arc as well,
because that was important to us.
Gameplay mechanics, enemies that you'd find in the level.
So a fairly standard overview.
But then on the lower right-hand side of the screen,
you can see sort of the first beat laid out.
And it was important for us to actually.
from on a moment to moment basis describe what the player was doing rather than just
frame the high level goals.
And that was a bit of a culture shift for us as well because in a lot of ways developers
like having a bit of a blank canvas but the good news with putting something in place
is that you know you have an answer and that answer can always get better.
So in the beats we'd also put.
goals or conditions of satisfaction. So not only did we have sort of our starting point,
but we understood what this beat was trying to achieve so that as we iterated and as we
improved upon it, we could make sure that we were still achieving those goals.
We had to map out levels spatially, so obviously paper maps are fairly standard, but really
pairing design with art as well. And Darrell talked about those cross-disciplinary teams.
it's great to get in and really think about the same thing at the same time.
So something on the left is an example of a key art image that would really help capture
the person, a moment of the level, but also the personality so that as we're talking about
what's going on we can all visual, visualize ourselves in that space.
And then on the right hand side you see sort of our beat boards,
which any moment where we had heavy character performance, scripted action, cameras, that
we tended to get much better results when we took the time
to go through the process of doing these beat boards.
Sometimes it feels, especially when you've only got two months
left to do three hours of gameplay,
that skipping some of these steps is an efficiency.
But in the end, for us, it really wasn't.
Speaking of cinematics, just a quick glimpse
at our cinematic pipeline, because that
was slightly different from the in-game performance moments,
that we did motion capture.
So.
Once we had that full uber doc describing the game,
we could write the script.
So that looks like any TV or movie script.
In our case, we had to extract any props, any set design
elements.
So in this case, we're looking at a scene that
takes place in Himiko's tomb.
This is the first tomb that Lara raids.
We would build that out, measure it out, because when we got down to LA, this is the capture volume,
there's actually a grid on the floor and all that junk around Lara really represents elements in the 3D world,
so she could be aware of that environment.
You'll also notice that she has...
cameras mounted in front of her on her helmet.
So we didn't actually capture face data,
but we got frame by frame reference for the animators.
So we were capturing full body data,
and then we were using that face information
for animation reference.
You can see in the background, there's some monitors.
So as Lara's acting out a scene, we
can see something like this on the monitors.
It's extremely rough.
But the other great thing about this is it becomes a previs for that scene.
So even out of our rehearsal shoots, we would get something like this and then could plug it into the game.
And then now that story element is starting to be represented in the game experience.
Once we get effects, lighting, sound, face, hands, all of the additional layers we put on,
our cinematic should look something like this.
I hate tombs.
So as Darryl mentioned, we went through basically three
versions of that production.
And we really did hit our stride.
But part of being able to hit our stride was sticking to
those patterns, that when we visualized a new scene, we
needed to see it through the lens of something we had
already done.
Okay, so that brings us into our final third.
We're gonna run through that very, very quickly here.
So we had a 12 month period where we had
those four chunks of content in the can
and we could play it start to finish
and it was already at a very good quality level.
But we knew that we wanted to edit what we had on paper
and make it better once we actually saw it in the flesh.
So we built time in for that.
And that 12 month period was basically split
six months into editing and six months into bug fixing.
And ultimately that six month period of editing is gold, right?
I guess I would just say that, that without that we would not be able to realize the game
that we wanted to because going from your idea of what a game is at 10 to 12 hours to
reality it's always going to be slightly off when you actually see it and play it through.
So it gave us a chance to actually go through, play it ourselves, use usability to actually
give us feedback.
and essentially go through and edit that content.
And then the last six months really were polish, polish,
polish, and heavy playtesting, heavy fixing of bugs
to make it a polished gem that we wanted it to be.
And it was a great opportunity to have that time.
A lot of times, it's all we can do to just fix the bugs.
So to have some time to actually sculpt the experience.
And I would say that even though we
tried to make each vertical slice as finished as possible,
There's certain things that you can only sort of identify, like overall pacing and character arc, once it's all in place.
So inherently there's some improvements that can be made on any game at this phase if you leave yourself the time.
But we wanted to, I guess, make the best use of that time.
So here's just another quick document, and this should look familiar because it's very similar to the Uber document,
but whereas the first document we looked at represented our intent.
This is actually our actuals.
So every square is a minute of gameplay.
And again, it's color coded by the type of gameplay
and the experience.
This was valuable because games are fairly intangible,
and the script doesn't really represent the game.
So when you're sitting there and you're
talking about how do we sculpt this experience,
it's really nice to have something,
a tangible representation of that experience.
So this is zoomed way out.
You can see that's our 10-hour experience,
or our 10-hour core experience, laid left to right
with all of the.
I guess, progression along the bottom there.
Now, that was just basically assessing where we were at.
But in terms of informing iteration,
we really relied heavily on play testing
throughout this whole process.
So qualitatively asking questions about, do you enjoy
this?
Is this too difficult?
Or in this case, story comprehension.
So we'd have multiple people come in,
play through the entire game, ask them
questions at various points.
And in this case, we identified some issues.
Lower comprehension in the beginning is fine because Lara is thrust into a crazy situation
and she doesn't even know what's going on.
But that dip at the end was a problem, that we didn't want people to not understand what
was going on at the end of the story.
So ultimately we did a lot of rewrites at the outset of our post-production process,
but then we would validate those changes.
So a subsequent play test gave us this graph, and we're like, excellent.
We definitely made some improvements.
And there's still a couple points that we could then identify and say,
all right, now let's go address that.
And so the idea of informing your refinements through playtesting
and validating your changes through playtesting was essential.
And just one other component with that process,
which is in addition to asking them questions,
we were also capturing data over the network.
regardless of what they said about a level,
we could see things like how much damage they were taking
in a space or how many deaths.
And that really helped us with the tuning and balancing
aspect of it.
So I guess the key is leave yourself that time
to iterate and make your game really
what it wants to be in the end.
So finally just wrapping up, I guess it's great to give you a broad view. There's some more detailed talks as I said around Tomb Raider today.
So please go see those. I want to leave you with some pro tips but one of which is that it really is a team effort and Noah and I get to represent the team up here.
But ultimately it was a team that made this happen and the team really had the drive and passion to go through all the different challenges you get in development to produce the game we produced.
So it is not as effortless as what you see in this PowerPoint, as I'm sure you all know.
But the pro tips really to leave you with, really that know as you go, I'm going to show you one last video just after this to wrap up.
But knowing at every step of the way what game you are making and whether it's good or not, whether you're hitting your goals, your quality bar, was critical.
And it's been critical for the last couple of projects at Crystal in the way that we've produced them.
So being great at every step is critical.
Knowing that you're great at every step.
knowing you're getting what you want and not waiting until alpha to find out and find out you haven't got enough time to make it great.
The cross-discipline teams around pillars was a key change that we made in terms of how we produced the content,
fitting into a larger macro map of the narrative and gameplay experience.
And with this ownership and this expertise, it really gave us the quality but also the speed to produce content that we need to in that production phase.
Lastly, we went through the post-production phase, but you can't shortchange that.
You're never going to get the game you want when you see it at alpha.
So build time in to get the game you want post-alpha.
Don't just bug fix and put it out the door.
So that's really a key tip for us.
And ultimately that bug fixing and play testing all the way through to the end,
I mean it really is what makes a polished, refined experience.
So don't shortchange that as well.
Lastly, I'll just leave you with a short video which is really the culmination of all the work,
which is a trailer we put out just before Christmas.
But I think the key thing to look at with that know-as-you-go mentality is at the end,
it's very close to what we had three years ago.
And I hope you can see that through this too.
and through the production of this game that every step of the way it really wasn't too
far off. You could squint a little bit at the beginning in the first playable but from
then on it was the real deal and ultimately that really allowed us to scope and manage
our project as we went. It wasn't on rails but it gave us the feedback and the input
we needed to make the right choices in order to hit our dates and our quality. So I'll
leave you with that and say thank you for joining us.
And I don't know if we have time for full audience questions, but Daryl and I will hang out.
So if anybody has questions about the process or Crystal or anything.
Thank you.
So much has happened.
I have no response.
Our captain is injured.
Have you heard from any of the others?
Nothing.
Our crew is scattered.
I have a bad feeling about this.
were hunted by the island's inhabitants.
Kara!
Please don't get locked up!
Sam!
Listen!
I'm gonna get you out of there!
You're a croft.
I don't think I'm that kind of croft.
Sure you are.
You just don't know it yet.
Alright, let's do this.
Sometimes you've got to make sacrifices, Lara.
You can't save everyone.
There's no other choice.
I've got to do this.
If I don't survive...
None of us will.
Thank you.