Yeah sure, hello everyone. So, my name is Radek Ratusznik, I am game director of Ghostrunner.
Relax, your implants are still adjusting to the software. I'm in a prison.
Oh, so everything is muted except you, I believe.
You'll have to suffice for now.
A trespasser spotted at metro station.
This is bad. You'll have to fight your way out of here.
The air ducts lead to another sector.
God, your software is a mess.
I've rebooted your acceler-
Hi there.
I've rebooted your acceleration module.
The trespasser is in the air duct.
Yeah, yeah, sure. 1, 2, 3, 4.
Guys, can you hear me?
Or not?
I'm talking.
Initiating the sensory boost.
Focus.
Oh, I see. I was still muted because I'm still getting used to my new setup.
Oh my god. Okay. I'm gonna restart the- that was all me. That was all user error. Okay.
Uh, hi everyone. Back to the start of the demo. Let's pretend that didn't happen.
My name is Brian Francis. I work at GDC and a little website called Gamasutra.
Um, let's start the introduction again. Raddick, take us from the top. How you doing?
Thank you. Hi everyone. My name is Radek Ratusznik. I am game director of Ghostrunner.
Yeah, and together with me we've got a couple of developers.
So yeah, I'm Damian or Damian and I work as a 3D lead artist at One More Level.
Hello, my name is Marcin and I am lead of the designer at One More Level.
Hello there, my name is Jan and I'm the narrative designer and writer for Ghostrunner.
Looks like we have a pretty active chat today. Chat, I can see your stuff.
I did turn down the audio levels for you for the game.
We're gonna be taking your questions and asking them for the folks on Ghostrunner.
No, we are not doing speed tech.
You are about to watch someone who was playing the game for the first time is gonna die about precisely 17 times.
I know that number because it shows up at the end of the demo.
But yeah, if you have any questions, we're happy to pass them on to the team and we're here to talk about the making of Ghostrunner, which comes out very soon.
Alright, Radek, what are we looking at here? Like, why did you and your team want to make Ghostrunner?
And how did this game sort of get started?
Sure, so...
Obviously we are looking at you dying a lot of times.
Oh yeah, get ready for that.
Besides that...
Yeah, so our previous title called God's Trigger, it was a game which we developed in Unity,
and it was a top-down action co-op game, heavily inspired by Hotline Miami, so it was also one hit,
one kill, that mechanic which is also here, like in Ghostrunner. This is like the core mechanic
of our game. So we decided to, you know, to push to a little bit, to something new, that we wanted
to make.
take this one-hit-one-kill mechanic and deliver the game
which will be kind of different.
So we put it to another perspective, to the first-person perspective,
which is something new for us because we haven't done any first-person game before.
We've also switched to the Unreal Engine 4, which was also totally new for us
because it was the first game for many of us on this engine.
We are lucky that Damian, our 3D artist who is today with us, he's amazing in Unreal.
And that was also our main decision, that we wanted to push that visuals to the next level.
To one more level, let's say. But yeah, so what we wanted to do is to, you know, bring the new
quality to that, to our team, that we wanted to have like...
A nice, very nice looking game with this kind of indie creative vision that we are, you know,
it's not like a AAA game in terms of gameplay, in terms of what you are doing actually in the game.
We are free to do what we want to do.
We wanted to make that one-hit-one-kill mechanic something unique to that mechanic.
That was our main goal, I think, at least at the very beginning.
But at the very, very beginning, it was just,
let's make a first-person game on Unreal Engine in a cyberpunk theme.
So that was our premise, let's say, at the very beginning.
Yeah, right on. We can talk more about Ghostrunner's cyberpunk vibe and world in a bit.
Damian, I want to spin to you as a level designer.
Something I said before this meeting started, and you're seeing me horribly reflect it,
what I think is interesting about 1 hit 1 kill is it means that even combat...
I wouldn't say there's combat in this game, there's just platforming.
And every one that you kill is just sort of like...
They're just a little platform that you have to reach in order to achieve your goal.
They just have to be positioned a certain way, and they're trying to kill you.
Um, uh, what was your, like, experience making levels for this game?
Because I've played a little bit more of it.
I won't be able to discuss much more of what I've played.
But I wanted to, uh, hear from you, like, what was your experience making levels
where, you know, like, like I said, where it fits the platforming and where enemies
are positioned in such a way that they guide players through these pretty high
velocity situations without, uh, losing track of the situation.
As you will see me lose track of the situation, but that's not your fault.
That's mine.
Yes, that's the... sorry, that's the question for Marcin.
Marcin, I'm so sorry Damien, I'm so sorry.
Yeah, it's okay, actually the topic is connected actually.
Damien can elaborate on the visual side and guide you later.
More on that side, but...
Designing the levels, yes. So as Radek said, our previous game was Sleeker and also was 1v1 kill.
So as designers we had plenty of experience designing that kind of game.
To be fair, to guide the player in the right way.
So, actually to the details maybe, you know.
We made sure that everything that is of interest to the player, like where to go and what to do, is mostly in front of you.
You don't have to look around that much and you make split-second, moment-to-moment decisions
seeing those things, like you see the next enemy, you see the next highlighted platforms,
like highlighted here in yellow, as you can see.
Like this is one of the main colors that guides, you know, the wallruns are yellow.
And how much time passes before the enemy shoots is indicated by the particle.
So maybe I'm elaborating on that.
Also, when thinking about the space, I was thinking, and every designer is thinking about the movement.
This is one jump, this is one slide, this is one dodge.
Thinking about what's the moveset to pass through this space.
It's like this specific space requires this and this.
Instinctively, we connect those spaces with the tutorials,
so we don't stop the player too much.
Everything is, I think, fluid in that regard.
Yeah, and basically also taking inspirations from other games like Doom, Titanfall, Windows Edge,
you know, all the good stuff that works and mixing it in with the things we know.
Yeah, so basically that's the gist of it.
Yeah, this space is interesting that I'm running through right now, as you can see in this footage.
This is where the game starts to open up and give players more choices.
As you can see the curved wall I'm about to run on.
Like you said, players have some tunnel vision in this game that keeps them pushing forward.
How do you still help them move?
They're essentially doing this in a bunch of cubes, maybe they're long rectangles.
But how do you help players get that comfort in that motion?
How do we place...
In the vision of the player, there are points of interest.
You see the yellow signs.
You see the highlighted spaces.
Here you can see the grapples. You look for the next grapple.
You look for the next enemy. You hear the sounds.
And it's just, you know, a lot of testing too, actually.
It's not just that you think it through and make a level and that's it.
Actually, this particular level, we were making many, many iterations before you were playing what we see here.
A lot of iterations.
A lot of iterations, actually.
I lost count, actually.
So, getting a lot of playtests, listening to feedback and looking at the players, what they actually do and where they look.
As you can see, I know that they are not lost and do what's supposed to be done here and go where they are.
supposed to go and to be fair in the game so it's not vanishing for you when you die
you replace a lot of checkpoints that comes from the experience from making previous games
a lot of checkpoints between obstacles in between combat spaces
makes you not regret dying.
Dying is a part of the main loop of the game.
So you have the enemy placement, if you don't see them,
you know, ah, there's a guy, ok, next time I know he's there.
You see, it's in the first time.
If the level is more open, we tend to use objective markers, as you saw in the previous arena.
That's extra help for guiding the player.
That's like the easy way to go.
Yeah, that's the cheap way out, but mostly trying to funnel in the most important information.
Yeah, but you know, it's also important that we have those instant restarts,
which is like, you can immediately...
come back to the action right after dying. So we are not breaking the loop. It's like the part of
the loop as mentioned, as Marcin mentioned before, that you are dying but it's we are not punishing
the player. It's like a part of the learning how to play this game and you are getting better and
better. So that was our our design for this.
It's the same as we did on God's Trigger.
It's inspired by Hotline Miami, of course.
You are with this tension.
We are not breaking the music, for example, in the background.
It's playing constantly.
So you feel that it's like...
Sometimes you can...
If you are fast enough, you can just press R for restart
without even seeing this dev screen, for example.
So, yeah.
Right on. Before, I would love to ping Damian and Jan for some questions, but I do want to get a question from chat.
All I want to hear in chat is praising Kevin. I don't know who Kevin is. I haven't met Kevin yet.
LucholanGD would like to ask, what were some of the challenges creating the game?
And I'd like to invite each of you to share one specific challenge you remember that you would like to talk about with folks.
So, like, that represent each of your fields.
So I can start I think.
So for me, as I'm also leading the whole team of 1MoreLevel,
it was the process of switching to the new engine.
That was easier than I thought, but it was hard.
It was like...
Not everyone were...
you know, sure that it's the right move, that maybe we should make another game in Unity,
maybe we shouldn't jump to Unreal Engine 4 right away, but it was a good decision for us because
it really works well for us, so that was a hard decision, but we had to make it.
Um, uh, who's next? Uh, Damian, what was your biggest challenge?
Yeah, so yeah, I guess the whole game is something new for us.
It's totally different from our previous title.
It's a totally new perspective, totally new art style,
totally different set of the tools that everyone on the team needed to learn, obviously.
We are a fairly small team and the game for that kind of a small team is very ambitious
and there is plenty of locations and interesting environments.
Also different sets of assets for different areas.
So it was very challenging for us to get through the design process
and the process of creation of all the art assets,
all the set dressing.
Like I said, we are a very small team.
I guess we did pretty good on that front and even to this day we're still tweaking stuff.
Obviously, like Marcin said, we put a lot of, as a team, a lot of work to make sure the gameplay is well.
And this is definitely a gameplay-first title, so all the visuals serve to improve the gameplay.
to make all the action very well readable,
so you never get stuck in the levels.
So this is definitely a challenge.
You have to consider all the lighting in the scene,
all the assets you place around the path of the player.
And yeah, we still also...
This is not my part,
but as a team of people focusing on the visuals,
we still want to...
So this is also a challenge in this kind of a game where you definitely don't want to
stop the player.
Marcin, let's start with you. What was one of your biggest challenges?
I totally agree with the previous points that Guy said.
I can elaborate on the story part a bit.
When designing the levels we were keeping in mind what was the dialogue there.
Basically, as we talked about before the stream,
is fluid, so there's time for combat, there's time for parkour, there's time for exposition,
so you can breathe, it's not just frantic action all the time, and making the game fair,
as we were talking, fluid where to go, so it's easy and fun to play where it has to be,
where it has to be, and
Well, that was maybe the hard part, to my field of more specifics.
Designing maybe boss fights was a bit challenging, because one hit mechanic makes it a bit challenging to design, but I think they turned out pretty well.
That's one thing. Maybe the other thing would be to...
You know, to make the game as fun as possible, as cool as possible, you know, and keeping
everything fresh, you know, because as you play the game, something pops up.
So that was the challenge, to make it all, you know, come together as maybe...
Right on.
And also upgrading system, that was something which we have, like, you know, how can you
upgrade your character when you've got only one health point.
That was also some kind of design challenge for our gameplay designers.
Maybe if I can add, because there are no programmers with us, I could say that making the game snappy, as Radik said, like the respawn is instant.
To those of them for making it fluid, what you can see is the effect of the hard work, the whole team.
Right on. I want to give Yon a chance to weigh in.
Yon, obviously we haven't even gotten to talk about that ghost runner.
It takes place in a pretty unique world.
You've got this tower that's like the last bastion of humanity.
What was your sort of...
We're in a very narrative set piece right now actually.
So what was your biggest challenge?
Basically, Damian already named my biggest challenge because the game is very much about
gameplay first.
So how to implement a story into the game that's all about staying in motion and rushing
ahead.
So in a way there's a limited amount of tools you can use to deliver a story in games such
as this.
Because there's not really time to stand around, to listen to people talk, to read things.
Basically, you want to focus on delivering a story that's, you know, engaging in a way
that will grip you even during a fight, during traversing the levels.
So Martin mentioned the pacing, that there is some place for the fighting, some place
for platforming, some place for delivery of the exposition, and I think it came together.
really well, if I do say so myself, and I definitely can praise Martin and other level designers for delivering the great pacing.
But for me, it was, you know, the overall shape of the story, for it to stand on its own legs and to be able to be delivered in this fashion during the running, basically.
Because most of the interactions you have with the characters is not face-to-face. Basically, they are just voices in your head.
So also writing the dialogue in a way that it's engaging and it's, you know, it delivers the
exposition in a way that feels natural and it feels fun and complements the action instead of
getting in the way of the action. I think that's the best way to put it. How to make the story,
you know, stand on its own merit but complement the action instead of getting in the way.
Uh, guys, I just want to say, by the way, chat is incredibly hype for this game.
Whenever we get to, you know, have a games community in the chat, you know, it's always fun and exciting,
you know, when they're, when folks who love the game pop in, but these, these folks who are watching with us today are,
uh, just talking about how excited for they are when this thing, when it comes out.
They're actually also talking about, um, speedrunning, which is a really fun conversation we can move to,
which, uh, kind of affects all of your work.
Um...
Speedrunning is a different kind of way to play a game.
It's about efficiency, it's about skips, it's about runs and percentages.
And I'm curious what your experience was prepping this game and sort of going,
oh, hey, this might appeal to the speedrunning community,
but we don't want to make them the only people who can play our game.
Do you have any thoughts about building games that are popular with that crowd?
So, yeah, so it was like...
We knew that this game had potential for speedrunners.
Just like our previous one, God's Trigger,
there was also some potential in terms of speedrunning.
Whereas Ghostrunner, when we first showed it up on last Gamescom,
last year, it was Gamescom 2019,
that was the place where we showed the game for the first time.
And there were a few guys who were just...
Over all the time they were just you know coming by and playing the levels and they were starting to you know
putting their own phones and
recording their times and stuff like that
And when we were looking at them when they in like they were playing like five or six times
In a row through the game and we we saw that oh my god
They are starting to be better players than we are of our own game
That was the moment when we knew oh my god
This is the potential for this game.
And after releasing the demo on Steam,
where the community of speedrunners showed up
and they really enjoyed the game,
they gave us very valuable feedback,
we knew that this is something we should work with.
They found their own tactics on how to move our character
and we didn't want to remove it from the game or fix it
because they really enjoyed it and at the same time we were trying to use
their own techniques when we were playing, when we were testing the game
and we at the same time we were really enjoying it too so that was a new way
of playing the game. Right now we are also pretty good at speed running this game.
Oh that's fun!
Yeah.
Uh, Damien and Marcin, okay, so real quick guys, so the demo, uh, I've got, uh, we're just gonna look at the menu here for a couple seconds, it's a beautiful menu,
and then you know what, we're having a good conversation, I'm gonna run the demo back to the start,
folks like Cube Zero in chat are asking who plays the demo five or six times in a row, guess what, it's gonna be us today!
Except, I'm not playing it, this is pre-recorded footage, cause it's really hard to play games and talk to people at the same time.
Um, Damien and Marcin, after, after experiencing that, you know, watching people speedrun just your demo...
Oh my god, MetaLive says they're sitting here with 70 hours in the demo.
So I hope y'all are excited about that.
But yeah, what's your experience?
Like, okay, now you know this is sort of how some people might play your game,
and it's a very high level, very different from the average play.
How did that impact your work as you got ready to finish this game?
Yeah, so maybe I'll start.
So yeah, definitely there was a lot of unexpected ways to complete the game, at least demo,
that I noticed when watching people playing the game.
So it definitely changed the way we're thinking about addressing the levels, how we approach.
approach, thinking about the paths the player may take.
We definitely try to waterproof kind of the level,
so the player can not, or can, but it's more in a designed way,
go through different route for example.
Yeah, so we obviously pay more attention to details like that.
I'm not really sure, it's kind of a...
affected the way we construct the visuals.
I guess when someone tries to get the best time on a particular level,
they're not really interested about the visuals when they replay the level for a hundred times.
So yeah, we still try to make the game appealing to every player.
So you don't have to worry about that if you're not speedrunning.
But I'm sure that there's not much that will get in your way if you try to get the best score.
Like we said before, this is a gameplay-first game, so you don't find stuff that constantly blocks you.
So yeah, I would say it's a very speedrun-friendly game, definitely.
Yeah, we are trying to fix some out of bounds bugs, but not like something on the main road.
But, you know, we won't manage to close it all. It's like, it's impossible.
People are always trying to find a way.
So maybe I can elaborate more about that.
As Alex said, we were in contact with the planning community actually.
When we were designing the levels, we were thinking about ways you can play them faster.
It's not just about being a speedrunner, it's just about you can figure out a bit of shortcuts,
it's not like a major shortcut, but you can do this.
And yeah, we were thinking about it.
And also, as Damian said, this is a game...
Not only for speedrunners, if you are not running around doing out of bounds stuff,
I think you will enjoy it too.
And yeah, we were very surprised and very happy about the result the demo gave us.
Plenty of feedback, also plenty of things to think about.
So yeah, we were thinking about making the levels appealing to many people, actually.
Not just speedrunners.
I saw him and in my head I said,
Hi Kevin, I just had to let you finish your thought.
So what is a skip that you obviously want to patch out?
And what is a skip that you think,
Oh, we should let that stay in.
There's actually a little skip that I developed for myself.
You'll see it later on now that we're running back through the footage again.
There's a point where you're supposed to grapple
and I just accidentally kept dashing through this spot.
Um, but I'm curious, like what's a sk- so what's a skip that you need, you go,
okay, that's good, that's high skill, and what's a skip where you go,
that's not fun, we need to get that out, or it's going to,
like, we don't consider that something we want in the game.
Yeah, that's a very good question.
You know, it depends on the situation, actually.
There are plenty of out-of-bounds situations or missing collisions, stuff like that.
It's like, you know, it depends on the situation.
Mostly you fix that, but you don't have to, like, patch every hole.
The main thing is to keep the game fun.
If you are having fun and you are not breaking it, like going crazy and making bugs...
We don't want to stop the player, as Jan said, and the guys.
There are not plenty of cats here, so...
It depends on the situation, actually.
Yeah, it's more like when someone is trying to break the collision,
where we have a wall and a floor,
and let's say that they are pushing into the collision.
doing that they are out of bounds.
So this is something that we are fixing.
But for example, when we have a normal gameplay situation
but you can, for example, skip some enemies
or you know, when you don't have to use, for example, that grapple
but because you can jump using the ledge boost jumping
you can jump on the really, you know, big distances
this is something which we are not patching.
So you are...
You are able to do it using all the speedrunner's techniques.
You are able to move pretty fast and you don't have to use all the walls, for example, which are indicated to you.
You can skip some gaps, some walls, etc.
So this is what we are living as it is.
Chat would like to know if you guys are getting rid of the triangle skip?
Each guard has a built-in lockdown.
Yeah, we wish to fix it, to be honest.
Actually, you know, it's not that simple.
Yeah, yeah, because...
So maybe not for the release.
But we will see.
Gotcha.
The out-of-bounds situation into the elevator, yeah, I get it.
Yeah, yeah, we saw it, like, 17 seconds or 16 seconds in the first level.
It was so easy to fix, actually.
Not so fun.
Well hey, maybe it just gets too hard, you know? Maybe it just gets put off for another day.
Uh, um, Chad's got some great fun. I'm so, like, it's so much fun to see players just like,
it's so exciting about something. It's like, like something from a small team that's not out yet.
Um, you know, like, it's like Ubisoft, you know, like big companies, your Ubisoft, your Activision,
they, they, you know, can spend thousands of dollars on marketing and these guys, this chat
is full of people who are just like, oh wow, like, y'all have played this demo for hours and it's
like, their enthusiasm is infectious.
But I so as much as I want to answer other questions from chat
I do need to get through some dev focus questions because like I said, we're kind of a dev focus channel
Though they do want to know about merch
So I'm gonna suggest that for any questions about merch you take that full if you guys have a discord for social media
I suggest that question
For my, uh, Damien, I want to talk about a 3D art thing.
So I was shocked by, um, uh, um...
Uh, I am only running an i5 processor on a GT970,
uh, which is not a powerhouse machine.
I'm working on, I'm gonna do an upgrade soon.
Um, but I was, I got, I got this game demo running,
and I, you saw me futz with the settings at the beginning,
and I went, oh, this is running great.
Like, the footage we have is really smooth, um...
It's thankfully, like, my CPU's even handling all the stuff we're doing right now okay,
and it's giving me some trouble on other stuff lately.
What, um, when you're making art like this, I know one challenge is making, you know,
for these vibrant, beautiful 3D settings, is making sure that they can still, you know,
uh, making environment assets that also don't, you know,
especially when speed is involved, especially when the frame rate, you know, is something to be managed.
Like, what is sort of your...
What was your practice as this game's 3D artist for a first-person high-speed game to make sure that like,
stuff could be beautiful, but also not be a memory hog or not be a...
Yeah, not be a hog on resources and not be too expensive, you know,
so that players can play this game on cheaper machines.
There's no simple answer to that question, but there are a couple of main areas where we focus.
Obviously texture density and the amount of texture we put into the game, the amount of triangles.
And I guess overall level complexity, also the lighting is very important.
We use Unreal, which is using kind of a mixed way of lighting stuff, so it's not all real-time lighting.
Lights that are not that important are baked, and it's pretty cool because with that you can get very nice looking global illumination.
which is very cheap for your hardware.
Basically you're taking out lightmaps and it's all stored like a static texture.
Yeah, so that's something that really well is optimizing the lighting.
We make sure that we don't go overboard with level geometry.
However, modern hardware can handle a lot of that stuff and we have really complex scenes
in the editor.
We kind of made like basic guidelines how many draw calls and how many triangles we
want to put in a scene.
Some things are more demanding on your hardware definitely.
We test the game on a wide array of the target hardware and try to get the best possible results with that.
We also optimize the game for the consoles, so that gives us a lot of performance stats and profiling.
Obviously, there is a lot of stuff that our programmers are constantly working on when
it comes to optimizing AI, optimizing a lot of in-engine tick times.
and stuff like that, more complex stuff that I don't really understand.
So we basically play the game all the time.
We have a lot of performance stats, we have a lot of feedback from the players that play the game.
Thanks to that we can really...
We put a lot of work into optimization and making sure the game runs the best as we can.
It's also very important due to the fact that we also support ray tracing.
So obviously ray tracing, when you turn it on, it's an additional cost for your hardware.
So you want the base game to run as well as possible.
before adding that additional performance hit.
That's another reason why we put a lot of hard work into optimizing the game.
We don't have... maybe I will go back to the...
We give people a lot of freedom.
This is also the reason why we were able to create this amount of level art and art assets in such a short time.
We have very experienced people working, basically.
We made already a gods trigger together, so we're kind of a small team.
We can communicate very fast, so if there's something wrong in the game,
we can directly communicate and basically in a matter of hours we can fix stuff.
So there's not much overhead in communications.
So yeah, I guess that's the reason.
That's the reason as well.
Right on.
Yon, I'm gonna pivot to you because I have a question.
I've played a little bit more of this game, so I've gotten to see where some of the narrative goes.
And like we were- I was about to tell you before the call, I'm...
Uh, there's things that hooked me as a- as a story lover in games already.
I- I have- I have this thing- there's just these games that come along every few years.
They're like these really great first-person, like, motion games.
Um, god, I'm forgetting the name of the other one I have, but it's on Steam.
Uh, uh, and it was one of the first games we streamed on this channel.
I'm like, wow, these games like actually like do a lot to...
hook me in and pull me in.
But one of the challenges I do find in this genre is...
Obviously like we discussed before.
When you're gameplay first, one HP,
there's not much opportunity to stop, sit and stare, and just story.
Though we're going to see a narrative sequence that happens later again.
And we've already seen it earlier in the stream.
My experience was I was impressed by how some pretty impactful dialogue was coming through later on.
And it was timed well enough that it still, like, I got through, you know, I was rushing through a section of a level pretty confidently.
And the dialogue didn't rush past, like, I didn't rush past the dialogue, it didn't get cut off.
So I'm curious what some of, like, how you can still, what are your thoughts on getting character and getting important story bits through.
without sacrificing in those short amounts of time.
What are your thoughts as a narrative designer about accomplishing that?
Well, basically that's the main challenge.
You have to play and replay and replay the level over and over
and tweak and tweak and cut stuff out
and move stuff around and shuffle it
until you're pretty confident that it works.
When it works, you can feel it
I think, well, it also has to do with the pacing that Martin mentioned, because if you
don't have any moments that you are able to say for 100% that, alright, I do have some
time here to tell something important that won't be missed by the player.
It's important to have points like that.
So for example, what we're seeing right now is the cybervoid section.
And in there, there's less stuff happening.
You're not in immediate danger, so it's a pretty safe bet to assume that the player will be able to concentrate on the dialogue more.
And that's how we use it many times throughout the game.
As a sort of section that is able to deliver exposition and deliver the story in a more safe manner.
You know, because it's... depending on how fast you're going and depending on how much attention you're paying,
it's easy to, you know, just skip or overlook some finer points of the plot.
And those sections, without any fighting, they are a platform that we use to deliver the story in a more laid-back manner.
But as I said, it's all about going back in there and tweaking it and seeing if it works and reworking it.
While coming up with a sequence of dialogue and putting everything in a place that guarantees you, or at least gives you the best possible chance of working.
You know, you've made a world for your game, you've made characters, like we were finding out here about the relationships between some of them.
What's kind of your interest? Like, why go for Cyberpunk? What kind of characters were you hoping to explore with this?
Like, sort of what... you know, you've made a really cool...
Like, again, great mechanics, great levels, like, there's a lot of cool stuff happening there,
but what kind of excited you? Like, why even tack on a story at all?
And, which is to say, like, what kind of story were you interested in telling,
and what were you all really passionate about in this space?
Because I could also see this game succeeding as just kind of an arcadey experience with a good, like, visual,
but instead you've, you know, layered on some pretty, uh, uh, functional narrative stuff,
and I'm curious what we were passionate about on that front.
Yes, so for the, let's say, cyberpunk world, I think the reason that we decided to do it,
it was just because we are huge fans of that cyberpunk genre, let's say, that renaissance
which is going on right now.
We have a CDPR game, Cyberpunk 2077, we had a new Blade Runner movie, that was something
that we...
We wanted to be a part of it, to be honest.
Just by being gamers and fans of this genre, this is why we wanted to make a game in this setting.
But the other thing is that it really corresponds well with the gameplay which we had.
That we had this kind of cyborg ninja character who can run through walls, who can dodge the bullets, slow down time, let's say, because he's so agile, he's so fast that he can dodge the bullet or deflect the bullet.
So...
That was the first reason and in terms of building the world, why we even add a narration to this game, because we just...
We wanted it to be, for Ghost Hunters, it's supposed to be like something more than just arcade game.
We wanted it to be something like, not a AAA experience, but that kind of indie premium experience,
that you can also enjoy the visuals, that there you can...
also enjoy the story of this game. So it's not like that it's not an important part of this game.
It's like it's also an important part but of course our, you know, premise is gameplay first
so it's like it serves to the gameplay. That's what I think Jan mentioned before.
Jan, you can also add anything about the world itself, because it's also pretty interesting what we have here.
It's not something like a usual, like a generic cyberpunk stuff.
Oh yeah, if I might add something, I'd say that I'm pretty sure that we came up with a very particular kind of cyberpunk because of the setting.
The Dharma Tower is, you know, when you...
If you place the entirety of the game inside one megastructure, you already are drawing a pretty powerful picture.
This is a megastructure. This is one very particular place.
It's got its history. It's not somewhere in the world. It's this place.
And this place has history and it...
came from some beginnings and already you know the story begins to write itself really
when you come up with the visuals, when you build this world
the questions ask themselves and then you try to explore them and you learn more and more about this world
and it begins to unfold in a way.
So yeah, I wasn't with the project from day one
so I can't really speak for the first decisions being made
but I was very happy to be able to join the project.
And well, yeah, for me it was very appealing from the start, this vision of this giant
structure, this mega structure that's the whole world really.
And the stories that come to mind immediately when you think of a place like that, well,
there's abundance of that.
We're nearing the end of our time with y'all, so I'm going to get one more question in from chat, which I think is a good design question.
Before we go, and we let this question play us out, if they have more questions about this game, where can they ask them? Where should they ask them?
Totally our Discord channel. I mean, it's right now very popular, but...
You should join it, of course.
Right on.
Um, okay.
Uh, for our part, uh, we are Game Developers Conference.
We are a place where people who make games get together and talk about making games.
Um, if you'd like to learn, hear more from us, uh, our Facebook and Twitter info is at the bullet bottom.
If you want to see more streams from more cool game developers, just hit the follow button on this channel.
For our part, if you yourself are a game developer, um, uh, like, say, these folks from Stardust DevZero,
who I kind of want to get their question in too, so we'll see if we can squeeze it in.
Um, uh, uh, you might be interested in our master classes. That is a new thing we're trying out this December.
Um, it's really cool. You can take a class, have some one-on-one time with great instructors like Jonah Loeb,
who's a great character, who's a character artist who worked on games like Skyrim and Fallout.
Um, you can get narrative tips from people like Susan O'Connor. Um, so that's kind of, oops, uh,
we're just gonna, we're just gonna leave this menu up for the last part of our stream if it would.
Yeah, there we go. Nope, did it again. Okay.
Here, we'll just leave the menu right there.
Yeah, so we're going to get two more questions in, like I said.
If you want to check out those masterclasses, you can check those out on our website.
4JanusSG would like to know,
what was the decision behind removing the dash ability from the Cybervoid level,
which you just saw a couple seconds ago when I was in Cybervoid?
Yeah.
The question is quite good, because we decided that we don't want to...
give people as players as much speedrunning mechanics there.
Because we wanted them to chill out a little bit on that section where you can listen to
the story, where you can think about it a little bit.
It's mainly the pacing reason, I think.
That's why we delete this dash ability.
And also, wall running is not present in cyber void levels.
So that's the first thing.
I think the second thing is that.
We wanted to keep it consistent because we've got many types of VR levels.
VR, sorry, that's our code name for it, but for cybervoid levels in our game.
And you are doing many different things over there during the gameplay.
And we wanted to keep it consistent that you are not able to dash and you are not able to wallrun over there.
I think that's the main two reasons. I don't know if Marcin, if you want to add something?
Yeah, basically you got the point straight. So yeah, so that's the way it was designed,
to shield out the player and make it a bit different so the play style of the Cybervoid
is not the same. Yeah, so it's not so rushed, you know, that you don't have to...
be in such a hurry as in normal gameplay.
They seem to be a newer game developer.
They would like to say that they're making a 2D puzzle platformer and they've never designed
a full level before.
What do they do and how do they tell when that level is fun?
What's your guys' advice for Stardust?
Just give it to your friends and watch them playing.
That's our main...
I think advice, right, Marcin? This is what we are doing.
Yeah, so basically my advice and Asterodix's, the main thing is to give it to somebody who
doesn't know the game and actually is not an expert, you know, and see what they do.
If they do and go where you want them to go and they are having fun, you know, you can see it.
They will say things, but you don't have to talk to them to know this.
You see what hands they are using, where they go, what do they listen to.
What's their emotions?
Think about the player movement.
The level is good when those things click in.
One thing comes from the other.
So when you show the dash, then you use the dash in a different context.
So one thing comes from the other and the pacing, you know, so there's not too much stuff and too convoluted, you know, or too much action, you know, you know, basically playtest it, playtest it, playtest it and then tweak it, tweak it and then playtest it more and tweak it more.
Maybe it's basic advice but I don't know if it's that common that you know you should start
testing your game on something who is not involved into the development like from very early days of
development. That's our main advice. You know we were in like six months in the development and we
had like first open play test I think.
Yeah, this is something like that, because we were starting at the beginning of the year
and in August we had a demo on Gamescom, so pretty fast.
Oh wow, congrats.
Yeah, also if I may add one thing, don't be attached to your design ideas, you know.
If it works, it works. If it doesn't, try something new.
Also something you might watch for is to not try to make levels look good at the design stage
because you probably have to scrap everything and start from the beginning.
Yeah, just some white boxes are fine, right?
Yeah, you don't need graphics or anything. You can playtest like 15 minutes.
If it's fun without the graphic, without the art, it is good, yeah.
Right on. Well, folks in chat, thank you so much for hanging out with us.
Tronjavolta, Tronvolta, GNSSG, MetaLive, it's been great hanging out with you.
The game is Ghostrunner. It's out on the 27th. That's correct, right? 27th? Sweet.
Yeah, that's correct. Yeah.
Yeah, and it's a neat game. And like I said, I hope that some of you join us in the future when we check out other neat games here on the GDC Twitch channel with the people who make them.
That's one of our, that's always what it comes back to at GDC is it's the people who make games. We want to give you the opportunity to hear from them.
With that, have a good day, everyone. For y'all in Poland, have a good night. Thank you for joining us so late. And that'll be it. Bye, everyone.
Bye.