Wonderful glad to see everyone here.
I know it's early 930 first session of Tuesday, but we're super super excited to have you here with us.
So First of all, we're gonna start our panel and you're gonna have a blast We had a blast preparing it and I'm very sure that you're gonna enjoy it as well remember to silence or at least turn off your phones just so you don't get distracted by it and
If you did scan your badge at the entrance, later after the session, and I'm going to remind this at the end as well, you're going to get a evaluation form.
And it means a lot if you could take the time to evaluate this talk and share your thoughts.
And just, yeah, that feedback is always valuable.
So just a quick reminder for that.
And with that said, I think we're ready to get started.
Okay.
Officially now, good morning and welcome to our panel.
As you can see, a decade unveiled the Brazilian indie game scene's transformative journey.
I'm Arthur Portazio, and you may be surprised to learn that this sequel is actually, sorry, this talk is actually a sequel to a talk that we gave, Bruno and I, ten years ago here at GDC.
That was actually at the localization summit back in 2014.
And at that talk, we explored the state of the Brazilian game industry as an emerging and budding game development scene.
Today, of course, we're back, 10 years later, to show how things have changed.
Why?
Because, just a quick show of hands here, how many Brazilians we have in the house?
Amazing.
Which is also super cool that we have a lot of people who are not necessarily from Brazil.
So our focus here is to talk about developing countries, to talk about Latin America, and to talk about what has changed.
We are at a turning point.
And over the past decade, the Brazilian game development community has grown from around 100 studios to over 1,000 companies, employing about 10,000 individuals.
But it's not just about the numbers.
This reflects a significant cultural and global shift, with 57% of sales now targeting international markets.
And behind those numbers and changes, there are people.
Look at us.
People make Brazil a diverse country, and at the same time, play a significant role in the industry by forging different, unconventional paths.
That's why we've assembled an amazing range of speakers with unique and instrumental experiences.
From developers to scholars, each will share their stories and lessons learned, highlighting collective and individual actions that have shaped the Brazilian game development scene in recent years.
So join us as we explore the transformative journey of the Brazilian indie game scene, reviewing the past, shaping the present, and envisioning the future.
Now, to kick us off and to get us started, let's welcome first speaker, Bruno Campagnolo.
Thank you, Arthur.
Okay.
Hi, I'm Bruno Campagnolo de Paula, and I lead the gaming course at PUC Paraná.
I'm from Curitiba, the land of capybaras.
And I also organize the global game jam Curitiba.
I love to organize jams and play parties, and I think these kind of events are really important for us in Brazil to get better at making games.
They make our community unique and I think others can benefit from that too.
And I'm sure of that mainly because of what happened the first professional job I had at the industry, at Continuum Entertainment.
But before explaining this, I want to tell you a little what Global Game Jam Curitiba is.
In the last 15 years, our jam has become one of the world's biggest and most productive game jams, attracting around 500 regular jammers in nearly 100 games each year.
I'm proud that our jam inspired many new developers to start in the industry.
And I began organizing this jam because I was sad.
Really sad.
OK, my mission is to talk a bit about Brazil over the last 10 years, since our last talk, OK?
But I also want to tell you a little about my personal journey, my personal journey first.
I've been making games as a hobby since the 90s, OK?
But my professional journey began at Continuum Entertainment, one of Brazil's pioneering international companies.
Sadly, after two years of hard work and a superb game,
We had Inferno, a unique health simulator with advanced AI and lots of humor.
The company shut down, because it ran out of money, leaving me sad and deeply disappointed with game development.
And I did not want anyone else to face the same kind of disappointment as me.
Large and non-competitive gems like ours inspire and teach how developers enjoy helping each other, and also make it clear in practice that we need more thematic diversity in games, and small games can help us to be better.
But I have to make it clear, very clear.
Gems should be used as an opportunity to elevate people, more than creating games.
In our gems we place the jammer in the center and he receives full support.
Play parties are more than a celebration of the created games, it is a celebration of the bonds between the people who produced the games.
In these 10 years since our last presentation, I've seen gems like ours establish themselves in Brazil as talent incubators, as part of the Brazilian game development culture, and I am very proud to be part of this context.
So when the continuum broke down, I naturally shifted to a career in academia as a professor at the Games Program at PUC Paraná, one of the top private universities in Brazil.
My goal was to show others how to avoid such disappointments or, at the very least, how to handle these situations better.
Well, but I was still sad, very sad, when I saw my students fail, imagining and even trying to create big, big, large games, but doomed to failure.
Then I direct my work to more experimental, small-like games and games that welcome failure, like Game Jam games, like Game Jam games, like the games we produced during Global Game Jam.
So, ten years ago, when I took over the coordination of our gaming course and brought this jam vibe to our program, always focusing on prototyping, publishing, implementing a constant feedback culture, and preparing the students to make small games before trying a big one.
Then we grew from 70 students to almost 300 now, and I feel very gratified when I see a student succeed with a game, but even more so when I see a student fail and continue to be motivated, to stay in the field, keeping creating games.
That was my story.
Okay, I'm very happy now.
Yes, okay.
But I have the mission now to provide an overview of the Brazilian market before my friends here, okay, present their stories.
So now I need to draw attention to some numbers, numbers about our market.
Firstly, we are an emerging market, probably the 10th largest in the world, probably.
And most of the population place and considers themselves
gamers.
Half people prefer mobile gaming, and games like Genshin Impact, Chinese games like Genshin Impact, are a strong part of the pop culture here.
Unfortunately, we still have some problems, like many countries.
Just to give an idea, a PS5 here in Brazil costs five times the normal price.
Top Apple products are almost impossible to have for most people.
because of taxes.
The language barrier is still there.
We speak Portuguese and many Brazilians do not speak English well and it doesn't look like it's getting better in the last ten years.
But even with these issues, our industry grows with a focus on external market and mainly producing entertainment games.
We have grown from 200 to over 1,000 developer groups and from 2,000 people to about 13,000 professionals since our last presentation.
And these groups, as mentioned, in our most recent research on Brazilian industry, are very different, very heterogeneous.
From unicorns like Wildlife, companies focused on earth-sourcing like Cocoo, large companies with international operations like Aquiris, now Epic Games Brazil, from Sandro, medium devs like BitCake, indie devs like Thais from JoyMasher,
and even groups of students who grow stronger in gems, like our gem, like Manalith Studios from Dungeon Drafters.
And of course, we have Brazilians in global teams bringing our creativity and adaptability to another level.
I'm very proud to have followed, for example, part of the Celeste team since the beginning of their international career.
For me, it's a great emotion to have their presence in our first Gems.
By the way, we have here Ana from Árvore, which made a very interesting partnership with Atari in her latest game.
And to conclude about our ecosystem, we Brazilians love events and associations.
We love to socialize, and we are good at it.
Some of the world's largest gaming events, such as Big Festival, which is now Gamescom Latin America, and BGS, are huge.
And there is a strong role played by the national association, ABRA Games, and our 17 regional associations.
And of course, gems like Game Jam Plus and Women Game Jam and even Global Game Jam Curitiba started in our domestic market.
Ten years ago,
this image summarized most of our Brazilian indie production.
Today, it's impossible to represent our production in just one image.
So we'll close my presentation now and reuse here the image from the latest Brazilian bundles, which we have more than 500 games, and call on my friends to continue talking about their personal experience as game developers.
Before calling my neighbor, Thais Weiler, she's my neighbor, really, to the stage, I want to remember my main takeaway for you, okay?
Creating small games is the key to developing better game creators.
Thank you very much, Thais.
Hello, everyone.
Can you hear me okay?
Great.
So I'm Thais, that's a weird name, I know, but that's what I'm called.
I'm in the industry for almost 15 years now, and when I talk about that, that sounds really exciting and really professional, and as if I know exactly what I was doing since the beginning.
But the truth is, I started as a creator, a writer, a painter, and
I sucked at it.
And then I tried to work as a stylist.
I was kind of good, but kind of shit also.
And I had to get out of this field.
But yeah, sure, let's do something else.
So I started doing headgear.
I'm fascinated for headgear, as you can see, obviously.
And this is a Japanese technique called kanzashi.
I used to make a rice paste to do that.
It also failed.
So that's how I felt at 22 years old.
I felt like that character in Undertale that I think we all can relate a little bit.
Everything I tried was shit and nothing ever ends nowhere until I entered in the game industry.
And for the first time, I really felt like I was part of something.
So, I'm going to continue talking about community as Bruno already started.
But my point of view is that without community, people like me and a lot of the developers Brazil has now, some of our best developers, wouldn't be here.
And I want to give some small tips of what worked for us.
Maybe it worked for you too.
In your own countries on your own situations, maybe not, but let's see.
I will just start then When I first joined the industry, I don't I never even thought it was a possibility something you could do as a professional you see games were made by rich people from other countries like Europe the country Europe or the country USA and I
It's impossible to do in Brazil, of course, but when I started I saw, no, there are a lot of people that already do that here.
It was felt like it was an impossible thing to do and still I was there And when I enter I discovered actually games were made in Brazil since the 80s They're just not very talked about in anywhere else.
That is not the industry So you need to get into it to start hearing about it, which is not very good, right?
There were many, many dev groups already and many companies, but mostly there are people trying to create companies and not many people just doing games for the fun of it.
There were people doing that, but there were smaller groups or they weren't very talked about.
And people really didn't talk to each other.
There were people that talked to each other, but small groups, not everybody.
And I don't know if you noticed, but Brazil is really big.
It's almost as big as America.
So it is hard for people from all over to talk.
And then happened something very small, very little, I don't know if you guys heard of it, called Indie Game the Movie.
Yeah.
Almost no one knows about that movie, silly.
But anyway, that movie had a great impact on our place, too.
Because even though it was a completely different reality from Brazil, it made indie developers feel empowered for the first time.
They felt like they were seen.
They felt like people cared about their games.
And they started talking to each other.
So that beautiful image Bruno showed us with the main characters of our games in 2013, that's a result of that.
People start talking, creating communities.
And the difference in Brazil at the time, filming the game, the movie, Brazil was completely different.
There was no funding from the government.
Everything was done as a hobby, as a side job, as a hustle.
Me, in particular, I had
two jobs at the same time just to keep making my games.
It was very, very hard to get dev kits.
It's still hard, but it was almost impossible.
You had to smuggle them, literally, almost as if they were drugs.
There weren't many companies present there.
It was very hard to talk with a game publisher, for instance.
There was almost no publisher presence.
So people start talking and creating groups and creating communities.
As Bruno told, I don't know if that's a Brazilian thing, but we just like to be around people.
It's crazy.
So students started creating small groups.
We also had some artists creating some small groups.
What started with small Discord servers for artists now, they are huge and they are creating their homes, their hosting bundles now.
But some junior developers started getting together, and of course the weirdos, that's my part, that's where I come in, and what we started doing.
That's what, in my opinion, is different from most countries, or at least most first-world countries.
we started doing more informal gatherings.
So bars, expositions, small expositions.
I remember a friend of mine made an exposition of Atari cartridges that were labels created by developers of imaginary games and games that they dreamed about making.
And some people even did the game afterwards.
Jams, especially global game jam,
It was one of the biggest of the world, right?
It's amazing.
Especially hangouts.
A lot of hangouts that generally happen at bars, but sometimes they happen elsewhere.
Online forums start also being a big thing.
We had a small community called Boteco Gamer.
No one knows about that.
But especially, the most important thing was the informal part of it.
Because people started talking and got to know each other, and to understand each other, and making connections.
And that was the most important thing, at least at that moment for us, because it made our
our
workshop
that shouldn't happen, and starting doing collabs and other games.
And when people work together in bigger projects, they can make even greater games with more ambitious ideas and more interesting concepts.
And also, when we are together, we have bigger bargaining power.
We can even be a bit louder and talk a little bit stronger and higher so people in higher places can hear us.
And also, very important, it's so nice to be part of something, to be part of a community and feel like you belong somewhere.
So, sometimes not everybody plays nice, right?
Because I'm talking about how it's cool to have a community, everybody works together.
Sometimes people don't work together in the community, right?
And that's okay too, because that's what the community is about.
When someone is not working very well with everybody or is not behaving well, as a community, we stand strong to make them change or to make them leave.
So how things changed since people started organizing in Brazil.
There is more government funding now, that was something that didn't exist.
It's not like a fixed thing, it doesn't happen every year, but it happens, so better than nothing.
We do have some very big companies.
In Brazil, we already had presence of Ubisoft, of EA Games, and they always left.
But now we have stronger presence of them, which is very good for, I don't know, all devs that want a little bit of stability.
Before, we didn't have any stability, and people started working in games and they have to leave after a while.
Now we can actually have people that work for 10 years and keep working in it.
People know each other from all over the country, which is amazing.
We have even laws being discussed in the Congress about making game developing better and easier for everybody.
We have communities that are organized around state interests of developers of that state and city interest.
And people from all around the world have people that discuss things that are important for genders in the industry, which is amazing.
We finally have people fighting together about things that they believe.
There are so many small studios now that it's impossible to count them.
We just know they exist because they are in the discord.
And hello to them.
I can't name you, but you know who you are.
And thanks for asking.
I'm doing great now.
I don't feel like a failure anymore.
And that's the end of it.
Please remember that we can change ourselves when we work alone.
But if we are together, we can change our whole reality.
Thank you.
That was amazing, Thais.
All right, so I'm back.
And I'm back, which means I get to share a little bit about my story as well.
So thrilled to share my journey as not just a creative professional, but also my insights into the Brazilian game industry.
I was born in Rio.
You probably know Rio from the Land of Beaches or maybe the Christ the Redeemer or the Sugarloaf, but I guess that's also why my passion has always been storytelling.
To make sense of the world and life through stories is my drive, and that's what, after quite a long journey, but it led me to become
and Emmy-nominated writer-director with over a decade of experience in digital entertainment.
What I really like is that from games to VR, TV, film, comics, and even telenovelas, I was able to journey through different franchises.
That went all the way from Asimov's Foundation to Disney's Mickey Mouse, Netflix's Cobra Kai, DreamWorks' Trolls, even Destruction All-Stars, and I got the chance to explore a bunch of different narrative formats.
Each project I tackle and I work on is an opportunity to craft a modern-day fable with the intention of blending culture and sharing meaningful messages.
But it's been a long road, as I mentioned, to get here, and that's why I want to share how these adventures that I've faced have connected Brazil with the world, plus the lessons along the way.
To talk about my journey, I have to contextualize the market and industry in Brazil.
While the market is massive and consumers play AAA games, the industry isn't on the same scale.
Yes, it has grown.
Obviously, as you've seen, it's amazing.
But it's a little bit different, because this creates a gap for those who aspire to get into game making and make a career out of games.
The same games that inspire the medium also can many times feel like a distant dream, especially in developing countries.
And at the same time, which is interesting, you see here the logo for TV Globo, that is the equivalent to Brazil's Hollywood, let's put it this way.
It's the second largest commercial TV network in the world, and it's synonymous with high-profile, large-scale productions that reach millions of viewers, not just in Brazil, but also with that content exported worldwide.
What that means is, within Brazil, working for and with TV Globo is huge.
It's a massive achievement.
And I'm one that I'm very proud of to have worked and worked on different productions in there.
But imagine my surprise when I realized that being a screenwriter at TV Globo didn't mean much to people outside of the country, despite the network's numbers.
It was only usually in conversations when I mentioned, oh, we worked on an Emmy-nominated show, that people would start paying attention.
So this is just a simple example of how navigating from a developing country to the global stage is especially challenging.
The gap between underrepresented talent and global recognition is real, because if you can't acquire industry-valued references nationally, achieving recognition becomes much harder, requiring many years to build trust and develop that career.
Of course, this struggle isn't unique to me or to Brazilians because it's shared by creatives from all over the world from different communities.
However, this was what fueled my determination to amplify Latin American stories globally and ensuring that Brazilian voices are heard and acknowledged for their achievements.
That's why my career has been a journey of self-realization, filled with gratitude for the wild opportunities that allow me to connect with diverse fields.
I started actually as a Bachelor of Laws, because again, it's very hard to figure out if you're going to get into game development at an early age.
But being in the academia, I got the chance to explore the intersection of digital media, art, culture, free speech, and intellectual property.
This led me to work on unique projects, and many of them international, but for example, Creative Commons, which was super relevant in the realm of copyright and getting people to share knowledge and access to content, but also researching game censorship across the world.
We had a series of cases of games that were banned, not just in Brazil, but across the world.
This was also connected to the Supreme Court case in the US, and that was part of my field of my research, understanding games as art and culture as well.
And of course, in a very creative and different way that also led to putting together a performance, as you can see here, where cosplayers were criticizing absurd judicial decisions.
So that's something that we were very proud of to put together in the sense of how can we communicate the value of games as a medium, how we can communicate the relevance of it in Brazil, but through different means and tackling different issues that are of social relevance.
So motivated to bridge the gap between academia and the game development community, I also created Ludobardo, which is what you can see here in the GIF in the middle.
This was a YouTube channel where I presented my academic insights as video essays and explored the rich narratives in games while discussing the cultural and legal aspects surrounding them.
Eventually, I also founded the Rio de Janeiro chapter of the International Game Developers Association, and specifically Rio, of course.
And that was done with the intention of helping people connect.
It's very much related to what Thais said, to what Bruno said, the idea that we needed people to get together.
People needed to get to know each other.
And it showed me, of course, that even if we had games made in Brazil since the 1980s, aspiring professionals had no clear way of becoming, they had no path to becoming an intern or a junior at a AAA studio.
That wasn't a possibility.
So, of course, many people considered leaving the country to pursue an international career.
Fortunately, and this is super cool, because Thais mentions Indie Game the Movie as well.
So fortunately, Indie Game the Movie, as said, was a huge impact.
Specifically in Rio, I got the chance to translate the movie to Brazilian Portuguese.
So we got it subtitled to Brazil, and then I hosted a Brazilian premiere.
It was wonderful in the sense that we had the theater sold out, and everyone was inspired by, of course, this potential new path in career, in the game development career.
But, of course, it wasn't as simple.
The reality in the movie was different than the Brazilian reality.
And I felt that as well, because when I decided to transition from academia or from screenwriting, etc., to games, I noticed that there weren't any jobs for a writer or a narrative designer.
So of course, because I was already involved with the building of communities in the games I've seen, and already had the narrative experience from writing for TV and film, I was able to, as soon as I wrapped up my master's degree in design, out of necessity and passion, start my storytelling studio, Fableware.
I applied for and was selected by Rio Criativo, this was the creative economy business incubator of Rio, and this marked our beginning as a service provider, since there was no studio that had the budget for an in-house narrative professional, but it opened my eyes to the business model of contractors, consultants, and co-developers, which are crucial in game development, and was also very important specifically in the Brazilian scenario, and still is.
Not by chance, one of our narrative consultations evolved to a full co-development partnership.
We joined forces with a local studio in Rio to develop the tactical RPG Sword Legacy Omen, and then taking on the role of the creative director, I was able to pitch the game to Team17, and it became, and we're very proud to say, the first Latin American game as part of their portfolio.
As we won awards and nominations in both Brazil and abroad, we would always proudly announce the game as a Brazilian production, and that even led it to being featured on national TV, which is the image you can see on the left.
It wasn't an easy feat, but the point is, Fableware's journey showed me that the company wasn't just about crafting our original projects, it was also about empowering other creators who face the same struggle, either because we could provide narrative development opportunities, or helping them with showcasing their talent.
In 2018, which is the GIF you can see on the right, I curated and organized a three-day event in one of Rio's most prestigious museums to celebrate Brazilian digital culture.
Digifestival was the name of the event, and it featured over 50 Brazilian games, films, and VR experiences for thousands of people to play, watch, and connect with.
And the journey continued throughout the past decade.
Each year has brought new adventures and achievements.
But my primary focus has been on expanding our business internationally and fostering collaborations to highlight Latin American and Brazilian projects and visions.
In 2019, I relocated from Rio to Vancouver in Canada.
and to expand Fableware's global reach.
It was a tough decision because I didn't want to contribute to the exodus of talent, but then on the other hand there was this unique opportunity to represent, support and spotlight Brazilian voices from that international setting.
This includes, of course, working on diverse projects, as I mentioned before, Destruction All-Stars, which was developed in the UK, and has characters from all over the world, including Brazil and Argentina, but also collaborating with remote-first studios such as Good Dog and Pixano.
Narrative development and cultural authenticity are closely connected with one another, and this is a great example of how we champion our voices and support other developers.
We dive deep into cultural heritage and lore to ensure the narrative is consistent and the representation is accurate.
all the way from a management sim game about a Brazilian jiu-jitsu gym in Rio, to an RPG with ties of Mesoamerican-inspired tales and themes.
All of this points out how valuable, in fact, remote work has been for these cultural collaborations.
It helps connect countries, build partnerships, and generate jobs for Latin American talent, be it from Brazil, Mexico, any other country from Latin America, or even Latins in North America.
Looking ahead, the Brazilian game industry finds itself as a pivotal moment of both opportunity and challenge.
Over the past decade, it has evolved significantly, with the emergence of larger, successful studios along vibrant indie communities.
Remote work has been a game changer, enabling talented developers from Brazil to contribute to a wider way of projects, from AAA to indies, as employees or co-developers.
I've worked on fostering not just games, as I mentioned, but building communities that facilitate this network of inclusivity.
In Vancouver, we've organized panels featuring local developers and pitching competitions, all dedicated to diversity and career development.
I've collaborated with other BIPOC-focused events, including the Brazilian Consulate and the Brazil-Canada Chamber of Commerce, discussing the challenges immigrant entrepreneurs face.
Through Fableware, we've helped Brazilian developers connect with the global industry and provided opportunities for them to work on high-profile international projects.
However, of course, we can't ignore the impact of the industry's layoffs, which have affected Brazil and beyond.
We've seen closely that stability is not guaranteed, but that's why I also believe these collaborations between talent in developing countries and established industries are vital to generate jobs.
The indie scene, with its capacity for experimentation and community support, provides a strong path for us to build a new standard of sustainable careers, redefine what success means, and shape the future of our medium, not just in Brazil, but across the world.
And that's it for me.
Thank you so much.
Now, let's have Ana.
Hi, everyone.
I am the creator of Pixel Ripped.
It's a VR series.
And I also love cosplaying.
That's why I'm dressed like this.
I try my best to promote this game.
I'm with Arvory Immersive Experience.
We are in Brazil.
And we focus in VR, AR.
I have been working with XR.
All the R's, right?
We call AR VR.
Nowadays, it's just so many things.
But just say XR.
It's fine.
I've been working with this for 10 years now.
Actually, more than 10 years.
But how did I get here, right?
Everyone's sharing their stories.
I'm going to share my story.
It also took a long time to find myself.
Like Thais said, I didn't see games as a way of work.
I always loved playing games.
But then I got a degree in psychology, and I ended up working at the Justice Council, making divorces and paperwork.
It was weird.
People like asking for the divorce and I was typing the documents, listening to Mario tunes and it was just weird.
And at some point, I think in a way to escape from that bureaucracy, I start like making pies and bringing pies for my friends.
This is the picture to prove it.
I wish I had the pies.
Actually, I thought I'd bring the pies for you guys to eat, but there was no oven in the hotel.
So I started selling pies, and in a moment, it was like in a couple of months, six months, I ended up selling like 4,000 pies a month.
It grew really quick.
And at some point, it was super weird.
People were asking for a divorce paper.
Where is my divorce?
Give me a chicken pie.
And then I ended up, people were like, OK, we need a pie shop.
All right, and I entered this entrepreneur's course where you learn how to, where you're going to be, your business, and I was like, OK, I'm going to open the pie shop.
And in this course, I realized I was in the wrong business.
And I found myself, and I'm like, wait a minute, I don't want to be making pies for 10, 15 years.
I love playing games.
This is me, actually, in the corner on the left playing Counter-Strike.
I had a female Counter-Strike 1.6 professional team.
This is a long time ago.
And then I took the leap.
I was like, OK, I'm going to change my life.
Everyone thought I was crazy.
My family is just like a big thing going on.
I changed career, but I also changed country.
I always wanted to live in Europe, the country Europe.
I decided, OK, I'm going to start games and I'm going to learn this.
I don't know nothing about anything, how to make this.
And then I joined the SAE in London.
And it was one year of games programming course, C++, hardcore.
And then I realized, OK, I'm more of a game designer.
Then I managed to enter a master's degree at the NFTS.
It's not NFT.
It's the National Film and Television School.
But nowadays, every time I say it, it's NFTs.
No, it's not NFTs.
It's NFTS.
And this is me trying VR for the first time.
This was a two-year degree course.
And in the first year, I had the opportunity to meet a student from the previous year, Albert, that showed me VR.
And this is me using the Oculus DK1.
So I fell in love, and I was like, oh my god, I want to make a game in VR.
And I was really into it.
And then the final year of this course, you could make anything.
It was your final project.
You could make a project the whole year.
So I had this dream.
And I was playing this game on the TV.
And this game was involving from 16-bit, 32.
And it was involving from 2D graphics, 3D graphics.
And the whole living room around me was changing.
And I woke up with that idea.
Oh my god, I want to build a time machine.
make people go back in time and play video games the way it used to be, how it was in the 80s and the 90s.
So that's how the inspiration came, and I knew I wanted to make a VR game.
So that's how the creation of Pixel Ripped came, the game I'm still with this game, 10 years now since I created.
This is 2014, the picture on the left.
And then I put this game online.
At the time, there wasn't a store, or a VR store like we have nowadays.
There was an Oculus Open
I forgot the name now.
But anyways, there was a website where you could share.
It was from Oculus.
You could just share.
Everyone was just sharing their games.
And the new one was selling.
And there was a lot of roller coasters.
So I put my game there.
And I was really lucky to put a student game and get some annotation.
Because of the roller coasters, I ended up being in the first place.
And I got YouTubers, investors looking.
And I was like, oh my god, OK, maybe I have to release this game.
So I finished.
The university ended up in this journey, VR journey.
a lot of
in Silicon Valley.
I lived in San Mateo for like three years.
Got some investment in BoostVC.
And then 2016, my whole money was gone.
It was like really hard.
Friends were helping.
And then in 2017, I found Arvory, the company I am with.
And it was like really good to have this long journey and find the perfect partner.
When I joined, Arvory was like eight people in the room.
There's actually some people from Arvory here today.
And yeah.
Actually, this picture, the lead artist of Picture of 1995.
And now we're going to be, to the end of the year, 100 people working at Arvory.
This is like the picture from last year's celebration.
So when I joined Arvory, we put one more year.
I had already worked for three years on this first episode.
It's a series.
And we put one more year together, working, release Pixel Rift 1989.
And then the work was good.
We keep working and we start from scratch Pixel Rift 1995, released during pandemic.
And last year we released Pixel Rift 1978 with Atari publishing.
It is, today, Arvory is actually the largest XR company in South America.
And we released many other projects, apart from Pixel Ripped Series, which was the first game we released.
We released Yuki, it's a bullet hell in VR.
The Lion, which ended up winning an Emmy Award during pandemic.
And we have today like around five projects going on in the house.
Many projects, I cannot say, big projects coming.
And yeah, it's...
Everything going good, we are big in our industry.
But unfortunately, we are more well-known outside Brazil than inside Brazil.
It's just crazy.
But all the games we sell, this is the numbers we got.
Less than 1% is the public of our games from Brazil.
Less than 1% buy our games from Brazil.
And 70% is America.
So America today is dominating the market, but it's also 31%
growing fastest, growing industries are also in Asia.
So Pacific Asia, it's also growing really quick.
But why Brazil is not on this graph as one of the growing markets?
It's small today and it's also not growing as fast as the other ones.
I blame the price.
This is actually real prices of the headsets in Brazil.
We don't have officially released.
When you're here in America, you enter Best Buy, you can try a headset, put it in your head, and you can buy it on the go and try it.
In Brazil, you have to go online and buy from people that are basically reselling.
Like, this is the Quest 3, the major headset today.
In Brazil, it's $958.
All of them, you can see, is like double the price.
Basically, VR is for rich people in Brazil and really enthusiastic people that are selling their souls to have VR.
So, for XR industry to go mainstream, we in the world and everyone in the industry actually become like something common on a daily basis for everyone.
We need VR and XR industry to leave the boundaries of USA and China.
So, yeah, that's my take.
I'm gonna pass the word to Sandra, my friend.
Hello.
Good morning, everyone.
I think it's hard to keep up with a story like Anna.
I think Anna is the perfect representation of the passion and talent that Brazil has in our country.
And despite every difficulty, we're going to find our way.
So I think congratulations, Anna.
It's great to hear your story again.
Well, good morning.
My name is Sandro Manfredini.
I'm the co-founder of Aquiris.
Nowadays, I'm a business development director at Epic.
Epic acquired my studio last year, in May last year.
And as of background, I also volunteered at Abra Games for 10 years, from 2011 to 2021.
And I was president from 2018 to 2021.
And my whole background, my whole career in games was basically developing my own studio in Brazil.
Before that I was working on advertising agencies and marketing, but also on the business side of it.
So today I'm going to tell a story of Kyrris, very briefly, as another example of what was going on in Brazil and how we got here.
I will divide the story in some milestones to make it shorter, as we have just five minutes to go.
So let's jump right in.
In 2007, we started Aquiris.
Actually, it was three of my co-founders that started the company before.
I jumped in a little bit after.
And so we didn't start the company dreaming about doing any specific kind of game, like a shooting game or racing game, et cetera.
Basically, our business mantra was stay in business first, basically doing a lot of work for hire and everything that was necessary to stay in the business.
Part of that is because all the founders, we came from a very humble background, so economic stability was very important for us, not only for the company.
Moving forward, I think I can say that the first years of the company, the most important power of us was the tech ability.
We were fortunate to start working with Unity since the very beginning of Unity as an engine.
And that gave us a lot of experience while Unity was growing.
And it's licensing business across the world.
And they liked so much what we were doing in the first years that they invited us to do the tech demo for Unity 3.0, which gave us a lot of visibility internationally.
We gave speeches.
We were able to call ourselves as one of the most specialists in Unity and help us to make business and deals here in Europe with Cartoon Network, DreamWorks, and some other publishers.
2014 was one of the most important milestones for us, as we were able to secure one of
venture capital round for the company that allow us to start developing our own IPs and also save us from a big layoff as in the same year, later in the same year, we got a business publishing contract cancelled and so we were able to save the jobs and also start our own IP.
And here it is.
So Horizon Chase, our first game, was launched in August 2015.
Horizon Chase is an arcade race pretty much inspired by Top Gear and Cruising USA kind of games.
And the game was released in August with huge support from Apple.
Actually, the game was the best of the week for one week worldwide, and that gave us a lot of visibility and revenue.
We were able to recoup our investment in the first couple of weeks.
Moving forward and brick after brick, actually the success of Horizon Chase brought us the opportunity to work with Scopely on the mobile, on the Looney Tunes World of Mayhem to mobile.
It was a very big and ambitious project.
We never had 50 people on the same team work together for one title only.
So that gave us a lot of new experiences and muscles to keep growing and also being recognized by the industry.
And again, one thing caused the other.
So Apple knew our work on Horizon Chase and some other titles, and they invited us to do a new game that would be part of the Apple Arcade portfolio down the road.
So we decided to do Wonder Box and Adventure Maker.
That was our first game when we migrated from Unity to Unreal.
And again, that will play an important role in our future.
Moving forward, also Horizon Chase 2 was a game that we did in partnership with Apple.
Continue and following up on the real development until Epic decided to invest in our studio in 2021.
And last year, they acquired the whole studio.
So here is the part that I want to connect some of my takeaways with Akira's history.
So international relationship is quite difficult for us in Brazil.
We are far from the main markets like here, like the country Europe, or Asia, or Canada, for example.
So I want to give a big shout out to two institutions here, Abra Games that have been mentioned before, but also to Apex, the Brazilian Trade Investment Promotions Agency, that together, for more than 10 years, they created this program called Brazil Games that actually invites investors and publishers to go down to Brazil to visit the studios and to participate on the business rounds at big festival events.
As an example of how important was that for Aquiris, I think the relationship that we built with Apple wouldn't be possible if we didn't have this kind of program.
Because we do have meetings with Apple here at GDC or Gamescom in Europe, et cetera.
But having the chance that a half day coming down to Brazil, visit our studios, have a closer relationship was key to the success of Horizon Chase and some other projects in our history.
No funding, I think we have mentioned that here as well, but basically we have immense difficulty to find private funding and also public funding.
In this recent study, only 70% of the studios mentioned that they had the opportunity to have a VC round in Brazil.
So basically, again, how important is the Brazil Games program to help us to have access to funding?
Last but not least, world class talents.
I think you guys have seen with the stories that we shared here, but also I think in all disciplines we have the talent in Brazil.
And I think what you guys can expect is more great and great games coming from us.
This is it for my part.
Thank you.
Amazing.
Thank you so much, Sandro.
All right, so as you can see, whoops, that went away, now it's back.
I'm back, and I'm back because that means we're very close to our end.
Have you seen, over the past decade, the Brazilian game development community has made tremendous strides forward.
We've witnessed the effectiveness of low-cost internationalization strategies, the transformative impact of community-building initiatives, and the significant role of educational programs and fostering the Seed Grove.
Additionally, of course, there's a rise of outsourcing, co-development studios, Brazilian publishers that have further propelled the industry forward.
Our speakers, as you saw, have shared inspiring stories of not just resilience, but innovation through different forms of success, showcasing the Brazilian game industry as a model of possibility for developers worldwide.
And I think it's super important to emphasize what Sandra just said about also the fact that having this world-class talent access the international stage is a challenge.
And it is a challenge, and at the same time, it's amazing for us to have this opportunity to have this conversation with all of you right here.
But it also shows that it's a step forward, a step in the right direction.
So instead of
don't go alone, because you're not.
Take these nuggets of wisdom that we are sharing with you from our experiences.
So coming from Bruno, make small games.
From Thais, together we can change the world.
From myself, don't hesitate to embrace your voice and experiment.
From Ana, XR is here to stay and it's not too late to dive in.
And from Sandro, any industry relationship can be helpful in the future.
So as we look to the next decade, keep these lessons in mind.
We learned them in Brazil, but we know that many other regions and communities face similar struggles and can benefit from these insights as well.
Thank you for joining us on this reflective journey and inspiring experience.
We look forward to connecting and building the future with you.
Now, before we move on to questions, though, just a reminder that, again, please fill out your evaluation forms once you get the chance.
It means a lot to us.
And thank you so much.
We're ready for questions if anyone has one.
Just let us know if it's a question for the whole panel or for a specific person.
Yes, I have a question for the whole panel.
As a game development student, I see lots of my friends talking about how difficult it is to enter the game industry there in Brazil, and talking about leaving to other countries to start a career.
And I saw you talking about this too.
Does the companies there in Brazil see this as a problem and are addressing this in some ways, or they don't care, or I don't know?
OK, I'm just going to repeat it so we have it for the recording.
So the question is, with the challenge of getting into the games industry from a student perspective, how do local companies or national companies see that issue of the exodus of talent and what is being done to deal with that?
Wonderful.
Anyone want to take it?
Okay.
I was going to say that the first thing I would do, I would just start doing projects.
I think you're having a good portfolio where you have a bunch of stuff that actually done it, that do a lot of game jams.
It's really important.
When we're hiring people, we want to see what they've done.
It's important to have the course, of course, or degrees, but then most importantly, what you've done.
When I finished the university, my best, the best thing I had wasn't my degree, my master's degree in the game industry.
It was the game I created in the demo.
Like, make a demo, make it short, and have, like, a good pitch.
I think if you have stuff you've done and you create it, and it's going to be much, much more important than anything to get a job.
I think you have to show you've done and you have experience.
So do game jams and, yeah, start doing stuff.
Yeah, in addition to that, yes, go to Game Jams.
This is super important.
You've got to obviously develop this report.
But I also think that it taps into a little bit of what I said.
Even though, for example, Fableware is based in Canada, we're always looking for opportunities to collaborate with Brazilian studios.
So that means that we're looking into co-development possibilities.
And in many ways, because, again, of remote work,
I'm
And I think that that's one of the ways in which we can still leverage the world-class talent in Brazil without necessarily having a full mass exodus of people.
Thank you and congratulations for the talk.
It was amazing.
Thank you so much.
Hello.
Thank you, guys, so much for the talk.
I loved it.
This question is for Arthur.
So you mentioned the importance of remote work in helping Brazilians kind of connect with studios abroad and create jobs locally.
As someone who's also from a developing country, I noticed that it can be hard to build trust with foreign studios when people from your country haven't worked abroad that much.
So how do Brazilians kind of create that trust in order to solve the chicken and egg problem and get the job in the first place?
Excellent question and as I mentioned with when it comes specifically to my story, it's oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Sorry So just to repeat what you're asking and let me know if I got it, right?
What you're saying is also coming from a developing country How do you build that trust or how do you build that?
Possibility to tap into the international market when you're in a place where you don't have access to already those opportunities Exactly.
Okay, perfect.
Yeah, as you saw, I mean there's a challenge which is
What are the references from specifically the country you're in or the region you're in?
As I mentioned, that's why I use TV Globe as an example.
It's massive, it's huge, it has big numbers, but lots of people don't know it, right?
I think that thankfully, though, unlike, for example, TV and film, where there is this very strong regional element of even the live action factor, with games and animation, there is a bigger possibility of exporting that content more easily.
So, connected to what has been said about going to game jams and making games, I think the most important part is there are lots of places, not just game festivals that are in person, but also opportunities online for you to showcase your work.
Not just, and then of course that extends all the way to the discords and servers and communities, of course, and this has been, this is actually good timing, because this has been enhanced
by the necessity of remote work and remote connection that took place because of the pandemic, because of COVID, right?
So it's not that, for example, Faberware, I have been working remotely since 2015, but at the same time, that factor allowed us to start working more easily with people across the globe.
Even based, for example, in Canada, there are lots of connections with Asia, where I've worked with the country of Europe.
So it's, there's this connection of how can we tap into
world connections, but from where we are.
The thing is, exposure is a necessity.
And that's why I highly encourage you, depending on the factor, to go to these, even if they're remote events, right?
Connect with people.
There are several events that are even more active now here at GDC that weren't before the pandemic.
So the fact that it is remote, there are events that take place in different time zones for people to be able to make those connections.
Sure, thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Hi, this is for everyone.
Great talk.
I was wondering, and I thought the statistics were really interesting, so I was wondering if you see any trends as for types of games or genres that are really booming in Brazil.
I'm thinking stylized art realism.
Anything that you see is growing really rapidly in the next year or two.
And for context, I'm thinking from a small indie studio, what might be a great match for a limited marketing budget to go after Brazil?
OK.
So repeating the question, just what are the most relevant genres and trends that we identify in the Brazilian market?
And also from an indie studio that is not based in Brazil, how can you also make that connection with the Brazilian market, right?
The answer is Free Fire.
Free Fire is everywhere.
I know everywhere else is Fortnite and other games, but mobile has a much bigger penetration in Brazil.
Anything you can do mobile, it's going to work much better there.
And right now, I can see children that are seven years old playing Free Fire and being very well ranked.
Okay, perfect.
Xiaoma, thank you.
No problem.
Welcome.
This question is for everybody, but maybe mostly Thais.
You had talked about how prior to Indie Game the movie coming out, the community was really sort of spread apart and hadn't come together.
Was there anything specific you all did to like find each other or like kind of create the community and bring folks in?
Nothing really specific.
Oh, sorry.
So just to confirm, repeating the question, what are the best ways to get the community to connect, right?
As in like before, everyone knowing each other, right?
Yeah, 100%.
To find each other.
Not specifically, but at the time Facebook was getting big in Brazil, so most people started connecting in Facebook.
I don't know if you noticed I mentioned a name, Botaco Gamer.
It was a community in Facebook that was very toxic, but everybody was there.
So people started knowing each other, and actually it was bad, but it was good because you could see how people behaved even when they weren't behaving very well.
Right now.
I'm not sure which way is the best but one way I did when I started it I move I move it a lot for jobs and for money and whatever but after the past six years or so I'm Kurichiba and when I Started living there.
I started looking for indie hangouts there and no one had organized one yet So I decided to start organizing one and we started meeting monthly every first
for Saturday of the month in a specific place.
And in the beginning, only two or three people appeared, but we kept on.
And after a year, like 10 people always came.
And sometimes five new people appeared.
Sometimes no one appeared.
But that's part of it.
That is my strategy.
I don't know if it's going to work with you.
I like bars.
I like drinking.
and that helps but maybe get together in a board game place or a coffee just to get to know each other.
That makes a lot of difference.
I like bars too, so that works.
Thank you.
Just to give an addition, I think another strategy is thinking game jams not only as game producing events, but as events for making people work together and making relationships.
I think there's another way to make this kind of connection.
without alcohol, yes.
But there is Game Jams with alcohol and pizza, so... Of course.
You just get all together, you can stop at every break in the bar, is where the best ideas come for the Game Jams.
And another addition to that, if you have access to any, this was mentioned before, like either national associations or regional associations, look for those.
That's why at the time I started the IGDA chapter, because it was a name that people could identify and recognize, but it doesn't even have to be an existing association.
You can start, as Taiz mentioned, start a meetup, be consistent.
That's super important, because then people will know that this is the spot for other indie devs or other developers to meet.
call.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Alright, we are unfortunately out of time.
We're unfortunately out of time, so we're going to wrap it up.
But speaking of wrapping it up, we are also going to, if anyone's interested, we can talk more at the wrap-up room here after the session.
And again, just a friendly reminder, please fill out your evaluation sessions.
And a big thank you to Bruno, Thais, Ana, Sandro.
We're very proud to be Brazilians and we're very proud to have shared our stories with you.
Thank you and have a great GDC.