So I think it's about two minutes in already,
and I'm going to start.
Yes.
Woo!
All right.
Now I'm hyped up.
Okay, so designing Journey.
Journey took us three years to make,
but the company, that game company, was started in 2006.
In the first three year, we were making other games.
You know, so far, we've made three games
on PlayStation console, Flow, Flower, and Journey.
This is the journey team at the end of the development.
Here's a celebration.
And we've made sky for every team member.
And it's a small team, there's 12 people here.
When we started making Journey,
it was seven guys after the finishing flower.
And over the course, various people come and leave,
and most of them were on the stage last night.
We, actually before Journey, we've already kind of made
quite a few awards, which I'm proud of,
and now with Journey, it's kind of going crazy.
But what I'm most proud of is actually these kind of
association of video game with museum and art,
and some other industry giving our game nominations
and awards.
Because deep down I always wanted games to be accepted by,
I guess, the mass.
So a lot of people ask us, you know,
how did you guys do it?
You know, you don't even have a PR department,
but we see you in the news all the time.
I'm like, well, I guess maybe the difference is
like we view game development
from a very different perspective.
I remember when I was at GDC in 2004, 2005,
we were talking about innovating games
around gameplay mechanics.
And there are various ways you can innovate games.
You can make a new technology
and build a new game around it.
You can create a unique art style
and build a game around it.
But when we approach innovation,
we like to look at it from the perspective of emotion.
I kind of see games as an entertainment,
and when I think about entertainment as a whole,
I see it as a kind of industry to fulfill human desire.
Just like food and water,
when a human have a craving for emotion,
there's various ways you can get it through various medium.
It just happened to be interactive medium
can provide entertainment,
can provide various emotions.
People often compel games to film,
and if you look at film, which has grown quite mature,
and the genres of the film are often divided
based on the feeling, and from negative to positive.
But when I look at video game genres,
and particularly the early video games,
These are what I consider the arcade era, even though Angry Birds and Bejeweled are here.
I mean, I consider they are the type of game which was very popular in early days.
And these games are about the sense of...
accomplishment, you know, you're really getting better at performing certain skills. The feeling of
achievement is really a powerful emotion that is often not achievable in cinema. And I think that
is why in early age this emotion has been explored a lot. And over the past 20 years, games have
become bigger and bigger, particularly the console game.
with the teenagers and younger male and and and if you look at the games that appear into this particular age group
a lot of them are about empowerment.
And particularly when you think about
what this age group people need emotionally,
most of them are in school,
they were told not to do certain things,
and in the home, they can't drive, they can't drink,
they can't leave school,
there's a lot of limitation about the freedom.
So in a way, a feeling of freedom
is something that really appeal to this age group.
But as I grow older, I have the freedom.
I have a job, I have the money,
I can go anywhere I want to.
I start to find it's less appealing to me,
and I start to play less and less games.
And if you look at the innovation on emotion
in the history of video game,
I can recall a couple.
Like, for example, Sims.
Sims is the first game that gives me a feeling of socializing with someone.
And that is huge.
That's like, you know, before multiplayer even existed, this single-player game can
give me the feeling of connection and relationship.
And I think that's why it has a huge hit and has a very different appeal to different demographics.
So when we started that game company,
we wanted to push the boundary of what kind of emotion
can games communicate to the players.
And we thought, you know, if there is a variety of feelings
that's available in the entertainment,
it is going to be a healthy media.
In gaming, it will be making the gaming
a more healthy medium.
And for player, if all they play is the empowerment,
if they have new feelings,
it will also be healthy for them.
And so now I'm just gonna talk about Journey.
This is why you're here.
So in early 2006, this is before
That Game Company was created.
I already have this idea for Journey.
At the time, it was about the third year
I've been playing Warcraft, a lot of Warcraft.
You know, I started since early alpha
because my friends works in Blizzard.
I feel super privileged to be able to play this game
before everybody.
But there is also the time I started getting
really sick of World of Warcraft.
And the reason for that is that, you know,
most of the time I'm really busy working at school,
and I almost have no social life.
So being online, being with other people,
the real people, they are on the internet,
is something that makes me feel close
and makes me feel less lonely.
So when I'm playing game online,
I wanted to have emotional exchange with the other player.
So.
you know, kind of wanted to have romance or friendship.
But most of the time,
the player doesn't care about those things.
They like to talk about a strategy,
how you're supposed to kill this boss,
move over to the left, you know, and you're slow.
And all they will say, you know,
no, I wanted this loot, and this is my turn,
you're not supposed to get it.
And so I was kind of disappointed
because the more I play this game,
the more people I encounter.
the more I realize I have no connection with any of these people.
They just remind me that I'm a lonely person.
And so it's kind of sad. So I was hoping that there would be a different type of game out there
that will
satisfy my desire, I guess, to have a connection with people.
And so, you know, as you can tell I'm an introvert. I don't like to go to parties or bars.
So I was imagining this online world where
there's no longer the difference between,
first of all, there's no enemies you can kill,
and there's no armor sets, like,
oh, I'm platinum, and you're only bronze, right?
I want everybody to forget about those material things
and just focusing on the fact that we are all human.
And so, I, um, the other thing I got, you know, quite annoyed is a lot of people will
check to see if you're a guy or a girl in these online games, and it's always a sad
ending.
Uh, so.
And so I really want to see a game where there's no difference of gender and age.
And yeah, sometimes I realize this guy I really have a connection to during playing certain raids
is actually 12 years boy and I just suddenly feel like such a disappointment.
So I want to see a world where everybody is the same.
You can't tell how they are, what their gender is.
They are all on their paths searching for something.
You know, it's something... I don't know what that is.
And so I have this scene here where one person is just simply standing on a bridge,
looking down in the waterfall, and I'm just imagining a scenario where I can just walk up to him
without words, and he's just staring at the waterfall, and I decided to stop and look into
the waterfall and thinking, why is he looking at there? And the very action of stopping and
being next to someone and not keep moving on.
gave me a feeling that that moment we are together,
we're together for this.
But back then I was thinking about MMO
because all I play is World of Warcraft.
So there's supposed to be lots of players
and this scene is something I really liked,
I want to see in a game one day.
It's basically, I also just finished Shadow of the Colossus.
How ridiculous that is.
So in the scene, there are these dark pillars.
They are actually the legs of the giants.
And they are walking through the snow field,
kicking up all the dust.
So it's very foggy and dusty,
and you can't see it in the front.
You guys have to keep silent because if you make noise the giants will notice you.
So you have to slowly contract through this plane and rely on the guy in front of you
to lead you away from danger and at the same time being relied upon by the person behind
you.
And that feeling is something I really want to experience in this game.
But we had no money and there's no that game company back then
So we were very very lucky to be able to find a funded deal to work with Sony
So, you know, they helped us to build the previous two game
flow took us a year flower two years and
so when we finish flower we say, okay, finally, let's make our third game and
I
Feel like we're finally ready to tackle an online gameplay
So we want to take what we learned from Fuller and Flower and try to induce a new emotion between two strangers online.
And when thinking about the emotion,
you know, we're going back to this pie chart here,
and I mentioned early on there's social games like Sims,
but this is also the era 2009 when Facebook gets big, right?
The social game become big.
People are talking about social games,
but I look at the social games,
I look at the mechanics, the interactions,
they're not really about socializing.
It's more like exchanging numbers and resource management,
which reminds me more of the earliest games.
And when I think about social emotions,
Sims was one of them.
And when I play Guitar Hero,
I have a great social bonding with people playing with me.
And even playing Minecraft, well Minecraft is recent,
but I'm just trying to say that there are interactions
that actually make you social.
So.
you know, my habit, you know, with previous games
is trying to make an emotion that's stronger
and that's different.
So I really know that, you know,
it's some emotion there that's gonna bind people.
They're gonna have a deeper connection
after they finish the game.
But I have no idea what is the emotion.
So it take us quite a while to search for exactly
what is the emotion behind social interactivity.
So I first look around at the online games
that's popular on the console.
There's a lot of team fights or team survival, co-op.
It was very interesting for me to look at
kind of like what is the average noise,
if you think about online games.
People keep telling me how they hated online players,
and then people are mean online,
they don't want to know who they are.
I really want to make something that makes them feel differently
or make people trust each other better.
And I was very lucky that I have met quite a few astronauts
in my life and talked to them about experience
in space.
they talk about how there's this weird myth
between all the astronauts who went to the moon,
that after they came back,
they all become very, very spiritual and religious.
I mean, that's kind of like a joke
I heard from a lunch table, right?
And they say there must be something mysterious
about the moon that really transformed
these people who went there.
And later on I met the guy who drove the first moon buggy and I asked him,
so what is so special about the moon that makes these people feel different after they come back?
And he said, you know, on the moon there's nothing.
There's no sound because there's no air. It's utterly quiet.
And the Earth is so small, it's like your thumbnail, you can just cover it up, you know.
And you're on this strange place where there's nothing and there's no sound and you just can't stop but thinking
Why?
You know, why are we here? You know, what about the rest of the universe, you know, because everything you know, these these these
Astronauts, they're mostly scientists. They know a lot about Earth's but and all of a sudden
they're facing with a lot of unknown.
And I learned psychology, I know that the sense of awe
and unknown is directly tied to a lot of religious meanings.
And so it's kind of an inspiration.
It might not directly connect to what the game is,
but it kind of inspired me looking at our life today.
We are kind of super empowered by technology today.
We can move really, really fast.
We can live and work above the clouds.
We can talk to anybody, talk to anybody
at anywhere, at any time.
and in our pocket or our bag, we carry the entire knowledge that human has ever gathered.
It makes me feel powerful because if I get to bring the gadgets today to 10 years ago,
they will think I'm a god. I know everything, I can do anything. But it also kind of makes me feel
like we are living a life where we're trapped by these empowerment. We can't simply live without
them anymore.
And when you look at video games,
and particularly the popular commercial games,
you know, most of these characters are kind of,
you know, carrying something, symbolize power.
And the gameplay, you know, I mentioned earlier,
is mostly about empowerment.
And when you have empowerment,
when you put a bunch of people in that environment,
their first reaction is,
how am I gonna apply my power on someone else, right?
If you give me a gun,
and you lock me up with another guy in a room,
I think I'm gonna use it someday.
So, the problem is, you know, when you have a lot of power,
even though the game is supposed to be about survival
and bonding and collaboration,
most of the time you're applying your power,
like let's say I'm shooting Left 4 Dead,
and if my teammates block me, I'm like, ugh.
Get away, you know, I'm gonna shoot this zombie.
And the only time I felt a connection
while playing Left 4 Dead is when someone was
patching me up, and I really feel something,
but too bad it's so rare.
Most of the time, majority of the time,
I'm still applying power.
So when I think about redesigning a social experience,
that's something that will connect people together,
I think the very first important thing is to reverse the power relationship between
the players and the world.
The player needs to be less powerful and the monster needs to be more powerful.
And then you will think about collaborating with other people.
And in a lot of games today, it's mostly about achievements, you know, and challenge about
conquering the monster.
And too bad the monster logo looks like the Android logo.
It has no indication here.
So what I'm trying to see is that in an online game,
you know, most people think about getting items
and getting power and think less about the other player.
And particularly in World of Warcraft,
most of the time I don't think about the player,
only when I'm like, this guy is too difficult to beat.
I need another guy to help me to beat this boss.
And I kind of think of them as a tool to get the treasure afterwards.
And I want to see a reverse.
I want to see the treasure and the monsters only being a means to make me realize how
awesome the other players are.
In most of the online games, it's about shooting,
but I wanted to see online game where the skills
the player gain and improve over time
is actually about communicating emotions
and really feel each other rather than just,
you know, like how accurate your gunshot is.
So, the problem, you know, trying to create that word
is very difficult because in a lot of modern day games,
the theme of war is just too noisy.
You just don't have time to look at the other friend
when a tank and a helicopter is attacking you.
So I thought, well, it's easy.
The first thing is we should get rid of the noise,
and we just keep a game to focus on people.
And then we have that problem where, you know,
if I have a gun, I'm gonna use it,
so we have to ditch that.
And then, you know, it started to get interesting, you know, a bunch of people in a lobby kind of like waiting before the raid starts.
They start to talk to each other.
But I kind of wanted to have more structure.
So I thought, well, what if we have less people?
You know, it's easier to design when you have less people.
Let's say we are in a very hazardous environment.
Not many people can survive.
And there's only two people left.
And then, you know, all of a sudden,
this guy in the distance become very, very interesting
compared to, you know, a constant warfare of action.
So that's kind of the very beginning of Journey.
We wanted to have a game which make you feel
somewhat lonely, somewhat small,
but you have a great sense of awe
and the feeling of unknown towards
the mystery behind this game world.
But that's just a kind of emotion we identified,
but to actually execute that emotion,
we have to do a lot of prototyping,
because we have not seen a lot of games
that's trying to achieve that.
Maybe Myst or Shadow of the Colossus is the only two
I can see that is actually having similar feeling.
So when we prototype,
I actually always start prototyping music.
it's not the interactivity because music is the most effective and powerful medium
that can create emotion. So I work with Austin Wintory, by the way he's Grammy nominated.
I was really really lucky to have a music that he made pretty much like right beginning of the
development. So four months into Journey's development, our artist made this mock-up
trailer with Austin's music and I'm just going to play it here.
And you can see in the early days, our character looks like a ninja.
And he still has like a human shape, he has arms, you know, it's very much the early stage.
But we know the world needs to make you feel big and inspiring, and you need to feel small.
So, it's kind of various landscape, but you can hear the music, that's the music we used
in the endgame.
It's the music you would hear on a cross-media buy before you launch the journey.
It has not changed, it just hits something strong and I really feel there's something
there.
And we kind of start to build the game around this music.
And the mountain used to be a...
crevice of a canyon rather than a hill.
All right.
And so...
So...
Then we start to enter all kinds of RAM problems.
You know, like, I think the trailer is the only thing successful in the early day.
So, okay, let me show you something we learned, right?
We started prototyping with co-op
because we know we wanted people to work with each other.
So we started this prototype called Rope.
So basically it's a one button game, you just press space.
And rope is the action, you know, in the chat bubble
it's the action, and you can see a long legged guy
can't break rock because he doesn't have arm.
But the fat guy, he has strength, so he can break a rock.
But still the chance is not always 100%, right?
And so as they collaborate, here's a rope
so they can climb up.
So the long-legged guy runs fast and he can jump through gaps.
And so, well, he didn't do it that time.
But with a rope, because anybody can lower a rope at any time,
eventually, with the chance, they can collaborate.
And we thought this is a great game, you know, you help each other,
but then, you know, the problem is like, what if you're playing alone?
You can't play this game.
And, you know, Sony keep telling us that this game could have a great multiplayer,
but it needs to have a single player.
Otherwise, you will not sell your game, right?
And so we're like, okay, well, this doesn't work.
And here's an example where...
Two people are collaborating and they're pushing a heavy rock.
I mean, this is a very common co-op feature I think most co-op games have.
But if you're alone, you can't even finish this level.
Even though there's a great feeling of collaboration, it becomes quite a trouble for us when we
wanted to design a game where it's possible to play alone.
And the other thing, you know, as you can see,
most of the prototype early on is like Java and Flash.
They're 2D prototypes.
And stuff we thought was brilliant.
didn't walk in 3D at all.
So we started this idea about trail.
So if you walk in a desert,
you can only see so far and from the top down,
how would you know there's other player?
And even if the other player exists,
if they're moving towards one direction,
how are you ever gonna catch up
if you all have the same speed?
So if you walk on other people's trail,
you will speed up.
And so eventually, you know, as you explore,
you will run into other player,
and you can see the shout has been, you know,
very early prototype, I think that was a success.
But in here, I'm trying to show you
that if the player can be next to each other,
they become more strengthful, and they can climb up rocks.
And, you know, but these mechanics,
eventually when you transfer into 3D,
it's almost impossible to actually pull it off
because cameras.
and other things.
So here's another prototype we thought was smart
is when the two people are traveling,
they get to go faster
because they can leapfrog from each other
and they can increase the speed.
Another great idea we had, we thought it was smart,
is the idea of calling to distracting the monster.
In Journey, you see the monster, right?
But if you shout at them,
then the monster will not attack you.
So between the two players,
you might be able to collaborate and distract the monster
and to get through.
But when we actually try to execute this idea in 3D,
it's almost impossible to tell the distance
between you and the monster and coordinate.
It's just way too hard.
And it tells me that a top-down view is great
for strategical maneuver and collaboration,
but it's almost impossible in 3D.
So here's another scenario which we really saw
was a great idea which also got killed.
You know, we thought about desert,
of course there's sandstorm.
So sandstorm is coming and people need to find a shelter.
The shelter is kind of a gray color.
And you can see the sandstorm keep going.
If they stay in the shelter too intimately,
the color of them will change to pink.
I don't know what that means, maybe they're shy.
And so,
this very scene of the sandstorm wiping the entire world
was a very powerful emotional experience,
but in the end, when we bring it to 3D,
we realize how difficult it is to actually do a sandstorm,
and we just couldn't do it.
And there's also this idea about graphics as gameplay.
This is something very unique in TGC.
Internally, we call it a gameplay,
We are more of a gameplay company than than gameplay mechanics company. What do I mean? So
Imagine you're in the desert and you're walking towards a mountain in the distance and you've been walking
And the mountain is so far, there's almost nothing changing on screen.
And this is kind of how it feels early on in the journey, where we have to keep dropping
breadcrumbs to keep the player feel like, oh, am I actually making some progress?
The world is so big, you know, we want it to feel epic, but then it's really boring
to traverse through the land.
And for quite a long time, we were like, this game is not fun at all.
So in order to create feedback for simple traversal,
like walking, we added the sand trail
so at least you're enjoying something.
You can sense how long you've been walked.
And we wanted to have a lot more dunes and things
that would be passing by so when you walk,
the entire screen is giving you feedback
rather than just staring at an image.
So we went out to a real kind of desert beach.
This is the Pismo Beach.
And here's a video of our lead engineer, John Edwards,
climbing the sand.
And I'm like, if you jump off the sand,
can you actually slide down, you know, like sand slide?
And so here I'm telling him, hey, you know, let's try this.
Let's try, just jump off, see what's gonna happen.
So here he jumps down,
and then just stopped.
Right? And how terrible is that?
And so, I wish in the ideal world he would just be sliding down, right?
And that's what we did exactly in Journey, which is like,
you climb up kind of slowly, and then eventually you kind of like slide down on the other side.
You know, it's kind of weird, it's like we're trying to capture realism,
but we're trying to capture the realism that we wished.
So, you know, then walking becomes interesting because every dune you climb up, you have
this anticipation of what's behind it, and you also have a reward.
So there's a lot more engagement in the basic movement.
And there's no mechanics here, really, just the feedback.
So as we work on this game, we run into a lot of distractions.
As a good designer, you need to be very clear
about the experience you want and stay the hell away
from the experience you don't want.
So Journey is a very simple.
Interface game because we wanted to make it for everybody, you know
We want a kid to be able to pick up the game to play
We want to give this to my dad or my mom and they should be able to just enjoy it rather than learning a lot
about gaming
So when I think about online game, the first thing I think about is the online interface, you know
This is Journey's online interface. There's another guy. So, you know, it's online game, right?
And then when I think about online games,
before we made this game, it was like this, right?
You have to figure out a lobby, check out a room,
and check everybody's pin number,
and make sure it's all green, and then you start the game,
and you have to say, you know, ready.
And I just don't know how I'm gonna explain
what is a pin number to my mom.
So we say, well, we have to hide all these interfaces.
And the next problem is just the user IDs, right?
You know, like, because player has been playing
the aggressive competitive games,
and their name tend to be very aggressive.
This name is actually not too bad.
they actually take me out of the game.
Even with Paris, well, Harris Hilton,
but I'm seeing Paris Hilton, I'm seeing real world.
It takes so much effort for us to transport
the player from their living room into a magical realm.
And these names, these texts just bring them back.
And I really think in order to have them collaborate
and connect, they have to forget these real life things.
And the next thing is people will say,
oh, online game, I get to talk to my friends, right?
I need to have voice chat, or at least I can type.
And knowing console games,
I just really don't want to hear the voice
of the 12-years-old boy.
And who knows who's playing the games on the other side, right?
And...
But Sony was talking to us that, you know,
if you have friends invite, you know,
you can have a viral marketing, right?
Because it's fun to play with friends,
they will tell other player to buy the game.
And we thought this is good idea,
but when you implement that,
if you have two stranger on the internet,
and they can't chat, they can accept that.
But if I'm playing with my best friend,
and he's on the internet, and we can't chat,
it's kind of frustrating.
And because of that, we actually decided
to not even support friends invites,
because it would break the integrity of the word.
So the only way we allow players to connect
with each other is at the very end of the game,
after all the critics rose up,
the very end, we show you the ID of the other player.
And so that way we can protect the feeling between the strangers.
And the other distraction is in the early days when we tried 4-player co-op,
we realized there are a lot of weird situations, like
after they play for a while, they start to talk about us versus them.
They suck, you know, we are great.
And I'm thinking, well, sure,
having competition is great for online games,
but that's not the emotional connection I'm thinking about.
And the worst case is when there are three players,
they're a bigger group.
And this single player is isolated.
I remember talking to my professor, Tracy Fullerton,
who's sitting here, and she told me she hated this game
because she's an explorer, she wants to explore the game,
but all the other testers wanted to move on.
And she felt forced, she has to conform herself
towards others.
And so in the end we start to focus on
one-on-one interaction.
But also based on that particular problem
with the three versus one,
I wanna bring this idea of collaboration and flow.
So, Flow, originally, I learned it through making
the single-player game, because, you know,
as a psychology theory, Flow is about the balance
between the player's ability and the challenge of the game.
And you want to make sure, no matter where the player
evolves in the game, they're in this nice balance.
But also, there's this concept of the flow for collaboration.
or in Bernie DeKoven's word, collaboration,
which is like in any group co-op,
there's a balance between the individualism
and the group conformity.
You can't just be too much about yourself,
then the group will abandon you.
And you can't just always do what the group wants you to do,
then you lose yourself.
And the player needs to have the choice
to actually navigate through the experience,
to stay in the flow,
and also to stay in the flow of collaboration.
And that's really why we try really hard to create Journey's seamless online lobby system,
where, you know, we will match you up with all kinds of players,
but some of them might not match with you.
They might be explore, but you wanted to finish the game as quick as possible.
But we believe if you have the choice to walk away from a player,
eventually you will run into someone who wants to do the same thing,
who is a similar type of player, and then you would love to be next to the player.
When they have the choice to leave, the co-op is actually more real and sincere,
and I think it's possible to have a stronger emotional connection.
And so in the end, Journey's online matching system is based on the physical distance.
You know, if someone's close to you, we will match you up.
But if you don't like them, you start to kind of walk away.
The system will disconnect them and find someone else.
Another type of distraction, resource, right?
In Journey, you go through, pick up those cloth strands,
and you fly, and you love them.
And when two people who love strands, they meet,
and one guy take the resource, and he fly,
then the other guys hate you.
And in fact, in our early days of playtesting,
people were saying like,
I really don't want to be with the other player.
They don't belong here because they're going to steal my resource.
So for quite a while, in order to compensate,
we thought we have a great idea.
We have the player who drops the resource
after they use them,
so they don't actually consume resource.
So maybe that way the player will love them.
So this is an early stage kind of 3D prototype.
And you can see if the player flies,
he drops all these kind of strands right behind them.
So for the other player,
he can just pick them up and fly up for free.
It's kind of like a communism thing, you know, you share all the resources.
But the problem is that even though mathematically you share it,
psychologically you don't.
A lot of players complain about how I picked up all these resources
and I carried all the way to the other guy
and he got to use my resources to fly.
He takes advantage of my labor,
even though most of them are not intentional.
And a lot of people feel kind of very weird
where there's a guy stalking you
and stay behind you and just pick up your stuff.
And so they just think this is, you know, they still feel like there's some kind of stealing happening.
So in order to really eliminate that,
so at least people don't hate each other,
we decided to drop the idea of possession, like resource.
We just have infinite resource,
except the player have limited pocket size.
You can only carry this much money, right?
So, and people go to resource,
they all pick up their money, and they can all fly,
and they don't hate each other.
And then, at some point,
we have another distraction from physics.
In most online games, there's no collision,
so people can't just walk through each other
because collision online is very difficult to do
and it causes all kinds of problem.
And at some point, we talk about the two people
helping each other to go through a rock.
You can see in a 2D prototype, it's very easy,
but to do this in 3D, you need to be able to
carry the guy, push him up, and the other guy
have to pull you up, so there's a lot of collision
we have to, physics have to be implemented.
So we thought, well, but this is gonna make people
trust and help each other even more.
Let's do this, this is gonna make this emotion deeper.
So we added the physics so the player can actually push each other, you know, they feel the existence of each other.
This is great.
But instead of helping each other to push them onto the rock, they'd like to push them onto something more exotic.
So, and for quite a while I thought it was just,
you know, those playtests,
they play too much Call of Duties,
they're just mean, right?
And then we were doing playtests at our own office.
You know, our lead engineer, John Edwards,
who was the guy who jumped off the sand,
killed me.
And multiple times.
I'm like, wait, you know this game is about
helping each other and having a connection, right?
Why do you keep doing this?
And he just stared at me laughing because we are just right across the office.
I'm like, come on, revive me.
Right.
And then I realized for quite a while I was disappointed about humanity.
So so.
I was so disappointed and one day,
Kylie told me to meet her brother's girlfriend.
She is a spiritual psychologist.
So I talked to her about this very, very dilemma
about humanity, right?
And she said, oh, you know, it's because your players,
they're babies.
What do I mean by that?
You know, like when you transport yourself
from the real world to a virtual space,
particularly when character looks like dots.
they don't carry the morality from our real life, right?
It's like a new baby.
And baby only seek for feedback.
And pushing a guy to a rock has almost no feedback, right?
But pushing a guy to kill them,
there's animation, there's blood,
there's a sound of crying,
and there's social anxiety of waiting you to revive them.
It's so much more rewarding.
Of course, the player wants to do that.
So what I learned is that the morality
doesn't necessarily carry over,
and in order to shape players' behavior,
you have to control the input and output.
So in order to prevent this happen,
we actually get rid of collision in the end.
So what happens is instead of pushing each other
when you're next to each other,
you start to give each other money.
And so people love to be next to each other because there's a lot of feedback
But there's no feedback by pushing them to a cliff or kill them
And now they can both fly just being next to each other. They love each other, you know, and just these little tweaks about
Features can can go a long way and there's so many small things about journey. That's kind of like
Constantly play testing and realize it's not working
And now I'm gonna talk about,
I think the most important thing for journey
is once you figure out the mechanics,
you really need to push for emotional catharsis.
And catharsis is kind of like,
you know what people would say,
a climax of a great story, you know.
But what's important for catharsis is,
it's not emotion, it's just intensity.
I think no matter what emotion you're pushing for,
whether it's joy or sadness or sarcasm,
you know, all kinds of emotion,
you need to push to a certain depth, a certain intensity,
because otherwise, adults, you know,
myself as a gamer, I'm too jaded.
You know, I need to be really shaken
and to be surprised to actually feel something.
And so this is a typical three-act structure from Hollywood,
you know, how you would structure the intensity of emotion in a story,
hoping that at the very end, there's a huge rise.
And that rise is the change of intensity,
and that's the cassathes of emotion.
So, you know, for journey, the feeling is awe and mystery,
and we wanted to kind of be able to control that.
And this is when I start to look into Joseph Campbell's work.
He's a master about myth and awe.
And this is where I actually get to learn
the hero's journey in depth,
because I keep hearing it,
but never really pay attention to it.
And the hero's journey,
is essentially a structure of storytelling about a transformation of human being.
It can be something like a transformation of a farm boy into a galaxy saver or, you know,
some hacker guy turning into, you know, you know, the one.
And it could also be used for more abstract stories, like the transformation of a little
lion into the king.
So when I actually line up the transformation of the hero's journey, which is called the Monomyth,
with the intensity of the 3X structure, and I'm thinking about like doing a transformation
of a character's life from the birth to death, it's surprisingly aligned. It's almost like
perfectly aligned. It's such a great 3X story about a hero's journey, which is also a human's life.
And I'm just at that point. I'm so geeked out
I'm like this is so perfect people all figure it out a long time before we look into cinema and all these things
We have to try it out as a game
So we create an arc of journey,
and then based on the arc, we create the landscape,
the world of journey, which you can see from the altitude,
it's almost like based on the arc.
And then we figure out the character's growth
from young to old, and they eventually transcend.
And based on the storyline, we create the mood
and the colors and the detail of each area in the world.
And then based on that, we have a more detailed emotional arc
with gameplay elements specified in this chart,
and divide these larger into smaller levels.
So this is all done in the first year,
the first half year.
So basically, we break all these nodes down
into small scenarios of gameplay elements,
storytelling elements, and
um, um, you know, the history elements.
There's actually two starry lines for journey.
Um, but you can see based on this arc, we have this, this intensity, uh, curve here.
Um, if I map it out onto, uh, uh, axis, uh, you can see basically.
We can use that as a guide to direct what we want
in terms of gameplay.
So on the positive side of the intensity,
we want to make the player feel free.
We want them to have lots of movement.
We want them to feel energetic
and feel connection with each other.
And on the opposite end,
and you can imagine what kind of emotion that is.
When we work with artists,
it's very easy to tell an artist to paint something
that's...
you know, very intense or very low.
And it's easy to work with composers
to get a music that feels sad or happy,
but it's very hard to work on controls and gameplays
because what is a sad gameplay?
You know, there's almost no reference.
And we as game designer we have a lot of vocabularies to refer from all the games in the past
About how to create a sense of fun a sense of achievement and a sense of accomplishment and empowerment
But you know my knowledge about other emotions only through the games. I've done you know flow and flower which is
Zen like game and a love giving a peaceful game
so
it takes a lot of effort to explore these mechanics to follow the arc.
At the end of the first year of the journey development,
the game is supposed to look like this.
This is the concept art. Matt Nauba has Jewel.
But this is what the game kind of looked like.
You know, we kind of blocked it out.
And this is the second bridge area, which is supposed to look like this.
We have some basic foundation of it.
we actually blocked out the entire game
before the first year.
So we have the final mountain level
and underground level,
except this is the target of the emotion.
This is how it feels.
Nothing really kind of makes me feel anything.
The game sucks.
Nobody have any confidence it's gonna do well, right?
And so we keep pushing it,
at the end of the second year.
This is the trailer we made
And you can see this is very similar to the final trailer,
except the sand is not as sparkling
and some of the model is not very polished.
But you can see mostly the character is there,
the scene is there, and the storyline is almost there.
I'm gonna save some time now.
So this is the curve we measured at the end of the second year.
It's basically there.
You know, like, we have the first four levels basically there.
And we have a lot of people coming to playtest.
And the result is not good.
And they say this game is really bad.
Some people told me, you know, before the final Heaven level,
when the player died, you should just cut it there.
Because the later part is making the game worse.
I'm like, what, really?
So I looked at the game, and what happened is that
if you look at the green curve, right,
this is the final emotional rise.
And that is not even bigger than the level
where the water is kind of floating.
And that's not even higher than the sand surfing level.
It's not exciting, it's not satisfying.
But the guy was saying like when he died
and accidentally the game crashed,
he was staring at the white screen for about two minutes
without nobody noticing.
And he was in a deep thinking, he was like,
this is very serious tragedy.
And he really liked it, you know, and I started to look at why.
I'm like, actually, if you jump from that level to the very bottom where you just died,
it's the biggest emotional change.
And it's actually, you reverse it, it's actually a catharsis of tragedy.
But that's not what we intended.
You know, we're not trying to make a sad story here.
So we actually took another year just to fix that problem.
So what did we do to increase this Cassathes?
So first we have to make sure the mountain,
the level before the final rise, is low enough.
So what we changed is the mountain kind of feel long and shallow and tedious
because it's just a lot of wind blowing at you and it takes forever to walk over it.
But we actually wanted to make it feel more struggling.
So we create a completely new animation set.
You know, animation sets is hundreds of animations.
And we just make it for this level
where you kind of feel weak walking against the wind.
And climb slowly, and jump slowly, and shout weakly.
And we actually change the physics
of the scarf and the clothes,
so they actually, when they're frozen,
they become heavy, they become lifeless.
In the middle of the scene, the guardians, the serpents,
usually just kind of stay above.
They just kill other Klaus creatures, being scary,
but they never attack you.
We actually make you to be attacked,
and we make this shelter actually crushable,
so it's no longer safe.
And to extend the amount of struggling,
we also need the player to spend longer time in the level.
So we added two new areas just to extend how long it is.
There's a sanctuary, which gives you a brief rest.
And then there's this fortress area you have to go through.
And then eventually you go to the final walk of death.
And to make this error even work better,
we have to figure out a way to continuously
slow down the player's input.
And we actually dim the light,
because the light is a symbol of hope and goal.
So when you actually die, there's no hope.
you know, we spent so much time tweaking the timing, right?
A lot of times I walk, I thought three minutes is about
the good time to walk to your desk.
But then,
and then our team member were like, this is too long, right?
And they want it to be 30 seconds.
I'm like, 30 seconds is not enough.
I'm not even in the right mood yet.
So it's just constantly back and forth tweaking
the exact right number where everybody's happy
and you know, for you to fall down.
And then when we move to the summit we have to make sure the summit is a lot more exciting a lot more
Climatic and a lot more free right you know what is the emotion of?
The intensity right originally summit actually looks like this
At the end of the second year, but the whole game is on rail
So you just kind of like follow the rail going through and seeing everything
But you don't have a lot of control you can kind of like Star Fox a little bit. You know
but
Because of that, I think that's why the game was not climatic,
because even though visually it's the same as the final game,
gameplay-wise, it's not.
You have no freedom, you can't move anywhere you want,
and it's just not right.
So what we did.
is we break free the rail, we end up opening up the entire area, you can go anywhere you want,
and we actually added a surfing area as well because surf is actually the most fun
out of the entire game. We know it, the flying is not fun, so we actually have to bring the
surf back just to give you a feeling of excitement again.
all the way until you walk into the light,
we kept it free, so you can do it.
You can walk anywhere, even walking into the light,
it's your decision until the very end.
And I think this freedom is super important of journey
because if you think about all the highs of the journey,
you know, whether it's the surfing part
or the water temple, or eventually the summit,
it's always about movement and freedom.
So eventually we executed at the end of the third year
in a playtest of 25 players.
Three of them actually have tears in the end,
which is kind of amazing,
because that's when we know the emotion is actually working.
Before that, all the playtests is just like,
people get lost, people don't know what to do here,
or people get stuck.
And I think while we do playtests mostly for usability,
Testing for emotion is super crucial,
but unfortunately you won't get it until the very end.
I really wish there's a better way to test those things.
So when we launched the journey,
I was very nervous because
we spent way too much time to build this game.
We extended the project for two times,
and in the end we had to put our own money in
just to make sure we could finish the game.
is all this thing gonna be worthwhile?
You know, we just don't know.
You've been close with this game forever.
And it was really relieving,
the first day we launched the game,
people started to post on our forum
to apologize to each other
for not being able to play through the whole game
because they had to leave.
But they couldn't tell the other person,
so they started to leave in post on our forum.
And I can never imagine a Call of Duty player do that,
but they are the same person.
Right?
And so as you play the game,
you slowly build up your scarf and cape,
and you become one more veteran player.
And I have a bunch of fan art here,
because I think fan art is a great way
to see what the player remembered about your game.
And they usually would remember the most intense emotion,
and this is what they remembered.
They draw hearts at the end of the game.
They remember the awe and the sublime beauty of the world.
They remember being scared and afraid of the danger.
And they also remember struggling together with each other
and helping each other to push all the way to the end.
And so, before all these awards season,
I still question whether it's worth it
to push a game to its extreme.
Up to today, we have 896 emails from our fans
who tell us very personal stories
about how they interact with the game.
A while back at DICE, I've shared this letter.
I'm just going to read it.
Your game practically changed my life.
It was the most fun I had with him
since he had been diagnosed.
My father passed in the spring of 2012,
only a few months after his diagnosis.
Weeks after his death, I could finally return myself
to play video games.
I tried to play Journey,
and I could barely get past the title screen
without breaking down into tears.
In my dad's and in my own experience with Journey,
it was about him.
and his journey to the ultimate end.
And I believe we encountered your game
at the most perfect time.
I want to thank you for the game that changed my life,
the game whose beauty bring tears to my eyes.
Journey is quite possible the best game I've ever played.
I continue to play it and always remembering
what joys it brought and the joy it continues to bring.
I'm Sophia, I'm 15, and your game changed my life for better.
And, and, and...
And seeing this letter, somehow it brought back to me about this fan art.
I think, you know, it is what life is about.
We are only here for such a short amount of time.
We happen to be all living in the same era, and let's help each other.
Let's make each other's life better.
And that's why I think, as a game developer, you know, that's the best thing we could do.
And that's why I love making games, you know.
And that's why, you know.
So.