Hello everyone, welcome to the GDC twitch channel, my name is Brian Francis your regular
Your regular host just hanging out here with you today on this fine Wednesday afternoon. Good afternoon
If you are somewhere east of me, good morning
If you're west of me and just happy high noon if you're here in California or on the west coast
We are here today playing a really cool game from when I was 12 years old.
The game is Jedi Knight 2 Jedi Outcast. I'm letting the old logos fly by on the screen for a bit of nostalgia for everyone.
Here we go. Here's the Raven Software logo.
I'm excited today. Jedi Knight 2 Jedi Outcast was a game I played so much of in 2002, 2003, 2004.
It was announced earlier this month that the game would be re-released on Nintendo Switch and PS4.
Today, down in the left-hand corner of the screen, we are joined by four developers who worked on the original game.
Going from nearest to furthest, I've got your names on standby here, but why don't you guys just introduce yourselves while I load up Nar Shaddaa.
I'm Chris Foster, I was the lead designer on the project.
Michael, game programmer.
I'm James Monroe, a tech programmer.
Eric Biesman, a story from things like that.
Right on. Chris, I'm gonna ask you to take the lead on my first question here.
For everyone in chat, for folks like Adrenalinke, I do want you to know that you can ask questions too if you ask them in Twitch chat.
There are two kinds of questions. If you ask a question and we pull it for the stream.
We've also got Chris from Raven is hanging out in chat. He'll be grabbing some questions that you can ask as well.
For folks who are fans of Raven Software, we would advise...
We're here today to talk about Jedi Knight.
We would love to answer questions about Call of Duty, but unfortunately we can't do that
because we have to stay focused on Jedi Knight.
So if you have Call of Duty questions, feel free to drop them in chat
and maybe we can get you an answer.
But for the stream itself, we're going to be focusing on Jedi Knight.
Chris, I'm going to toss my first question to you as the design lead.
And as I enter this Nar Shaddaa bar that I remember so well.
What was the origins of Jedi Knight 2? Because I believe this was Raven taking over development of the Dark Forces series, correct?
I'm going to toss this right at Eric.
Eric was our commander in chief on the whole thing, so he's best suited to answer the background.
Yeah, so Steve Raffel was actually the project lead, and he and Kevin Schilder did a great job. Unfortunately, I couldn't be here today.
So when we first started, we had just come off of working on Star Trek Voyager Elite Force,
and we worked with Paramount, and we had put a lot of love and passion into that game as well.
And I think that that was something that helped us take a step towards LucasArts.
You know, they saw what we had done, they'd seen all the stuff we'd worked on before,
so just kind of like magic happened, and suddenly I'm working on...
the game that I've always wanted to work on in my life. I grew up on Star Wars and it made a huge
thing. So, huge dent in what I did with my life. So really it was, I think it was more fate than
anything. It just kind of happened. We had a lot of really good upfront meetings. We spent a lot of
coming back and forth. LucasArts people came out and visited us. We live in the middle of
frigid, frosty Wisconsin. They're in beautiful
sunny lovely California so we visited them more than they visited us.
But yeah just kind of I don't know if that answers your question it just you know I feel like it just
kind of happened after what we've already done. I mean our work it was an example of our work
I guess speaking for us.
No, not at all.
Just to follow up on that question, what was the lay-up, what was kind of the first blueprint
for what this game would look like?
Obviously following up on Jedi Knight meant you were, as following Kyle here, you would
be taking up a lightsaber again, but you're also, you know, you guys were coming from
a shooter background.
What were the first steps taken to lay out the programming and design for this game?
It's kind of like our prototype that we worked on.
Yeah, but I think, well, we started building a level of just test features, functionality
and things out, reflective surfaces, rebounding surfaces, how stormtroopers would walk around
AI and stuff like that.
So I built a little playground to help Mike and everybody feature all their stuff and
then they took it from there and made it like crazy.
Yeah, if I remember...
That's the same level that we released, that we showed at E3.
Right? And you built it.
And it was also what we released eventually as the demo for the game.
But if I remember correctly, we were originally going to do Dark Forces 3.
And we, and they, like, just a shooter. No Force powers, no Jedi.
I don't know if it's because they thought we were an FPS studio or whatever, but we were like,
we can do Force powers, we can do lightsaber.
We've done Heretic 2, which is a third-person action game.
So we brought over some of that animation stuff.
and we took the Elite Force engine we'd done, we put them together, and the Ghoul technology.
Yeah, from Soldier Fortune.
Yeah, that allows dismemberment and stuff.
We put all that together, and hit location, like really...
Yeah, skeletal animation.
Yeah, all that stuff.
We put it all together and made a demo in about three weeks, I think it was.
It was quick.
It was very, very fast.
Yeah, and that was...
Brian Rathel took that to LucasArts and they're like,
oh, okay, I guess you're gonna do a Jedi game now.
Yeah.
Well, I think part of it was that we had the...
Kyle Katarn is Dark Forces, and at the end of Jedi Knight, he's a Jedi.
Yeah, he's a full-on Jedi.
And so to bring him back to Dark Forces was a challenge, and that's actually a challenge
we had to follow through in this game too.
That's why we started him without his lightsaber.
We just didn't want to start him as some uber-powered Jedi.
We also didn't want to create a new character for this one, because it had been a while
and we really wanted to make sure Kyle, who was a really cool guy, like I really like
his character and Janors and all the...
all those people that surround him.
We wanted to make sure that the game was about him.
So it was kind of questionable at the beginning,
like do we just start full on super powers,
force user, or do we bring him back to his roots?
And at the end of the day,
we decided to bring him back to his roots.
And I actually really think that turned out well.
Using that same hero's journey again.
Yeah.
And I think the design philosophy was
like the first few levels were like dark forces.
Yeah, totally.
And then it becomes.
Right on. We've actually got a solid question in chat. I'm gonna...
There's a... I'm gonna get to that question later.
Adrena, Lin-C, I may actually remember the cheat you're talking about,
but I'm gonna follow up on that.
What do you think, as game makers, was sort of the...
What was sort of the guiding limitation of your original tools
that you had to make this game?
Because obviously, it's much easier to sort of pop things into a prototype now,
but in 2001, 2002, that was not the case.
What do you think your team did well in getting this idea,
like from concept to execution?
But for some tech things, I think something we really did well was packing a lot of texture
detail in on the characters.
We had some advanced texture mapping tools that helped us pack them efficiently.
So for not a lot of memory, we got really high details on that.
And looking at it now, yeah, it's low poly, but for the time, we were maximizing everything
we could out of those.
And using skeletal animations, because the previous tech was using mesh animation.
this is much less memory so we had a lot more variety of animations so we could do all the flips
and saber attacks. Didn't we do a lot of large texture map like texture pages that had a whole
bunch of that because with that way we could just use the drawing on the wall we could cut stuff
out as well we're like we're gonna put this on the window we're gonna put this piece on the
right underside of the bar we just took the textures off on the same page and just tried
to use them for everything we could.
One of the best part. Oh, go ahead.
Yep. What was, um, let me push this guy.
Okay, I can't push him off the edge and I'm getting shot by a disrupted rifle.
This guy's going great.
Um, uh, I was gonna say, well, what, what was you, you know, with, with having Star Trek and,
um, uh, Soldier of Fortune, uh, games under your belt, what was different about,
like, getting this texture pack together compared to those games?
It had to be realistic.
But it also had to look like the reference from all the movies and everything.
That's where I was going to go.
Star Wars was pretty...
We had our own environments that we were making up for some of the things.
But we knew we wanted Stormtroopers.
There's like the classic Star Wars characters that we wanted.
And so, from a prototype standpoint, we didn't have to do a bunch of concepts.
We didn't have to do...
We could just sit down and work.
I think that, at least from...
The Star Wars side of things really made it go a lot quicker.
We already knew the world that we wanted to make.
But as far as technology and stuff, it was really just building off of that technology that we already used.
We just, we had that in our pocket and we had it ready to go.
The, a fun little note, when we were doing the demo,
we were starting so quickly and coming right off of the Elite Force,
that for Stormtroopers, I just took the Klingons from...
Oh, I forgot about that.
We painted them white, put black around their eyes and those were our stormtroopers.
I forgot about that.
But they made the models really quick.
They were in for the demo by the time it was finished.
Yeah, they did.
They built this super fast.
Let's talk about lightsabers.
This game, I think, sticks in a lot of people's minds because it's one of the first Star Wars games that does third-person lightsaber action in a way that would be compared to for games when The Force Unleashed came out,
when The Force Awakens came out.
This is the big challenge of streaming and talking is, A, this game is already old school challenging.
That's a very difficult level.
That's a really hard level to do.
Guys, I'm going to be honest, your first two levels were really hard too.
Yeah, that was stupid.
I remember when I got to that level, I always got sniped.
Good job, Stu.
The thing about Nar Shaddaa, if I remember correctly, that was supposed to be before you get your lightsaber.
But at some point we were like, it takes too long to get your lightsaber, we're going to move those after you get your lightsaber.
But the design for the levels...
was still mostly for shooters.
So it's kind of weird you get your lightsaber and then don't get to use it a lot.
Because they're snipers.
Yeah.
But we ended up working on some of those puzzles to let you into the top of things.
We just had to retroactively work on some of that to make sure that the saber was still
really fun to actually use in here.
Yeah, like this bar fight in the beginning.
Yeah, once you get past all the snipers.
You can't avoid the snipers.
It's a little, it's actually, the bar fight is so great.
It feels so great because it feels like the Noir Jedi thing
you guys put together.
I really like that sequence, especially with
I was replaying it and I was so impressed
I'll get back to my question in a second, but
I was so impressed with the scene
what your cutscene and animation scene
were able to do with these low poly stuff
because even though
even though the models may look a little
old, sorry.
Um, the camera choices and the way the model, like the animations are pretty pose-driven,
does, you get that cinematic sense in a way that I don't, that I think a lot of newer games have
to do so much work to get with so many more effects. Alright, let's try sniping.
We definitely storyboarded on pretty much everything.
That was you?
Yeah.
That was me.
We had a lot of fun with that.
Um, okay, no scoping, no scoping. Um, uh, yeah, let's talk, like I said, we were talking about
the lightsaber and the reason I wanted to talk about the lightsaber, like I said, because,
um, everything from the, uh, the limbs that get chopped off to the marks that get left on the
wall, um, it's a very, like, free-flowing nature of it, where I can move right and swing,
moving left and swing. These are things that don't...
Like, if you think about KOTOR, if you think about the classics like side-scrolling games,
like the level of immediateness to this lightsaber usage wouldn't be met again for a while.
What do you, what was the core design and programming logic that made that possible
if you're able to share that?
For the lightsaber combat stuff, well for the effects, it was mostly Jeff Dishler.
I recall. He spent a lot of time on that, making it look really good, the lightsaber
blur, the glow itself, the marks on the walls and stuff. That was all him. The combat was,
we brought over the third person combat logic that we did for Heretic 2, and then expanded
it for this and put in a lot of transitions and try to keep it smooth. My goal was to
make it so that...
you could be moving in any direction and attack in any direction. I worked with the animators on that.
And tried to keep it as freeform as possible, to give you control in every direction.
And I wanted it to be quick, I wanted it to be responsive, I wanted it to be fairly lethal.
My actual inspiration for the combat was Bushido Blade.
It was old, I don't know, PlayStation 1 was it? PlayStation 1 game called Bushido Blade.
where you have these samurai fighting,
facing off with these different samurai weapons,
swords, naginata, stuff like that.
And you'd like fly through the air
and like slash at each other.
One hit could kill you if you timed it just right.
And that's kind of what I was aiming for.
Right on, I'm gonna go into the question pile real quick, so sorry I have to pause the gameplay for a sec.
Um...
Duh-duh-duh, um...
Uh, yeah, let's talk about first and third person views.
Like you talked about, you were borrowing some of your third person tech, um...
This is again one of those things that I think from a player's side...
At the time, it must have seemed like an easy thing to just say,
Oh, the game is in first and third person.
Um, nowadays you would still say, Oh, of course you can just...
set your camera to wherever it is. In 2001 and 2002, I'm sure that wasn't true, even though you had working tech.
Um, what was the... the secret to making... what techniques did you use to get a game that could switch between first and third on the fly like this,
and make sure that that didn't create any weirdness?
Oh, there was some weirdness.
Oh, hey, yeah!
We went through a lot of weirdness to get there, but yeah, we took the... I think we took the basic...
The engine already had a rudimentary third person to just set the camera back, and we
added in a bunch of scripting and traces to manipulate the camera to make it feel more
natural to do some cinematography type thing where if you back up into the wall it moves
the camera up.
Yeah, we did a lot of testing with that when we were building everything, especially those
little elevator shafts everywhere to make sure there's enough room for the camera.
Yep, and it would slide and move around.
And the little camera...
I'm trying to remember, did we do it in here when you got some of the kills in slow motion?
Yeah, we made a target around the death.
Those were very cool.
But yeah, designing it we just had to make sure that you could do it either way.
And I'm trying to remember, you can switch on the fly.
You can switch on the fly.
There was a menu I can pop into here.
I think it's P.
By default?
Well, we're on PS4 now. We're playing the new release version.
I played it recently on the PC.
So you could shoot your guns in third person.
I remember I would charge up the Breyer pistol,
do a roll, and then come out of it and like
blast the guy right in the head when you stood up.
And then the...
Do you remember the first bug when we did first person saber?
There was first person lightsaber.
And you would do a roll and your saber would just hover.
Yeah.
It didn't work.
It can't roll.
It's not really attached to your body.
So yeah, we did do first person lightsaber and it was, we felt like because Jedi Knight
was first person lightsaber that we had to do a first person lightsaber but we kind of
preferred the third person.
Right.
So we did it and the trick was like, I tried all sorts of different things of attaching
the players.
view to the actual model but then it was like moved around too much. I tried not doing that
and yeah and then your arms are moving around over here while you're back here.
So I blended the two and then I faded out the arms. I just put some alpha right from the arms
so they fade out and we went up to the shoulders. We used the actual third person arms though. Yes
and then so that would uh it would a little bit hide the the connects that you're not totally
connected. I'm not sure how many people played that way but we we uh put it in there but I don't
think we kept that for
Jedi Academy because there were just the saber staffs and dual sabers and all the acrobatics
and stuff just didn't really work.
Swiss Army Knife Sabers.
Look, Delphi!
Oh, face shot!
I would recommend Vespen.
Again, PS4, we're stuck, like I said, get ready to allot me dying.
This is not pro-play Jedi Knight 2.
This is someone who hasn't played Jedi Knight since...
This is as far as you were able to get.
It took me six hours to get this far, guys.
When I was playing through it again, I realized that nowadays, when we're making any game,
we're doing serious talks about onboarding and steps-driven.
We did no onboarding for the most part.
Hey, you've got a gun. Do this stuff. Go figure it out.
Hey, you found a secret area. Good job. We didn't tell you.
And when you get your lightsaber, I was running around in one part of Bespin going,
why did I make this puzzle so hard? This is so painful. I keep having to heal.
And I was like, oh, that's right. We can wall run.
Oh, yeah. We never tell the player you can wall run.
I'm like,
Yep, that's how we got past that puzzle.
You were supposed to just know that from...
Yes, you were just supposed to realize that.
That was a different time.
It was. There were things called manuals that we expected people to read.
Oh, right. It was in the manual, you're right.
Yeah, exactly.
Man, I do want to, I need to take a minute.
I'm going to pause from trying to get past this sniper brigade.
I need to get to some of these great questions in chat.
We are going to go back to Adrena Linkta's question.
In the PC version of Jedi Outcast, there's a cheat where you can activate over-the-top dismemberment,
where you can cut off limbs and even whole torsos. I remember this cheat.
It was gruesome.
They heard that the game used the Ghoul 2 animation system, which was used in Soldier of Fortune.
Did the functionality of Ghoul 2 in Soldier in Fortune, was that also used in Jedi Outcast,
and did that lead to the existence of the Heavy Gore cheat?
Basically, yes.
The Ghoul was the skeletal animation system I was talking about earlier, where...
That gave us the ability to pretty much zero out any limb just by zeroing the scale so we could cut off at any joint.
So with that in mind, I think Mr. Gummel here added the realistic saber where as soon as it touches you, it severs you.
Just readings wise.
This was a debugging tool.
This was debugging the joints so we could make sure every one of them looked correct when they got severed.
I wanted to make sure if I cut off more than one part it would work correctly.
I wanted to make sure the lightsaber was doing, you know, I could try out making the lightsaber more deadly by increasing the damage or making it do damage when it's not in the middle of an attack, like if it's in a transition or anything like that.
That was the deadly one I remember.
I just actually tested out someone in chat pointed out if you click R3 on the PS4 version
You can switch between those first and third person view. So here's that first person view we were talking about
Yeah, that's the first person view.
Yeah, I see your arms.
See how they're kind of faded out there at the bottom.
Now can you do a forward roll?
Yeah. Did Aspyr do the forward for this?
Yeah.
Yeah, it's Aspyr. Aspyr Media.
So you can...
You can do the forward roll in first person, but your view just goes forward.
Yeah, roll. Because when it was actually attached to the body, it was too disorienting.
Right on.
Oh, Chris Graft, Mysterious Interloper Chris Graft, who is also Gamma Sutra Editor-in-Chief,
would like to know, are there any aspects of Back in the Day Game Dev that you look on fondly that don't exist today?
Oh god, yes.
Yeah.
How long did it take to finish this thing?
Being able to make a game in 10 months for 24 people.
Yeah, that was nice.
One of the things with fast development,
we do talk about is back then
we wore a lot of hats.
Like, I built levels, I was in
charge of the design team, but I also
had the light levels, I was scripting,
and we were doing all the continuity
of everything, and we were helping Eric
make sure that
when the dialogue went in that it all made sense given what we had to change around.
So we were doing tons of things.
A lot of times now we're a little more segmented like we build the levels and we do whatever
but somebody else is doing a Hollywood level layer and somebody else is you know a scripter
that has you know 20 years of experience doing it.
So we kind of spread.
a lot of those tasks out, so it means a lot more communication has to happen.
Yeah, I think for me it really comes down to, when I started I think there was 13 people
at Raven, and now there's two-something.
And that's a portion of what goes into making a game.
Like you have four or five hundred people that could be out making a game.
And I still love it.
I still love the people I work with.
And I got to meet a lot of really cool people at different studios.
But there was just something about, like Chris said, I would be working on the narrative.
I'd be working on ketchup base.
I would be retexturing and talk to our artists.
I'd help with art, like.
it was there was just more for you to do and I personally have not really been in an editor
and I don't know how long and it's it's it's something that you really miss and I miss
I need a minute to work on yeah yeah I'm just running away from you guys
oh look grenades oh these guys love throwing grenades
exactly in a PC game on a PC, but it's been harder on console.
Yeah, how does it feel with the DualShock?
Uh, so I played this on GameCube back in the day, so this is already like, it feels better
than it did back then because the GameCube controller was a proto-FPS controller.
Right.
It feels, the looseness of the camera is the only challenge, but it's also just, I had
this realization yesterday, if I go back and play Halo, I know exactly what I'm doing,
like the shooter controls for Halo have defined most of the shooters I've played since then.
This game feels like kind of the end of the doom era like like with key hunting like kind of a floating gun
I'm gonna walk around with the gun for a minute, but like this kind of like there's no aiming down the sights
There's no snapping behind cover like the most effective way to murder a bunch of stormtroopers is to effectively do this
To just juke back and forth with blasters
I made it through that part. So I'm gonna save real quick
There's an interesting challenge with the ps4 version of this game where I may accidentally fill up all my saves and I may have to
Go delete some if that happens, but we'll cross that bridge if we come to it
May I? Just gonna go back to the chat real quick. There's a bunch of great people expressing
their love for the game. Quick shout out to Mace Maddenis who's still modding Jedi Academy
after 10 years. Wow! Dark Shadow Rage bought the Switch version. They love Outcast.
10 years of modding Academy.
That's really awesome.
Yeah. I'm going to dive into my
question pool again.
So you talked about going to
fly out to work with LucasArts and some
of LucasArts working with LucasFilm.
I'm gonna ask a two-part question on this. One, what did it mean to work with an external partner
like that back then in GameDev? Because back in the day, licensed games were a lot less riskier.
They feel a lot more riskier these days, given the financial partnerships that have to take place.
I got shot. I hate that guy.
And the second part of the question is, what kind of resources do they have for making
this Star Wars game feel like Star Wars?
Because the Battlefront devs talk about how they get to go out to old Star Wars locations
and record audio from those locations and pick up textures from the audio.
Sorry, I was rushing through my question there, but what resources do they provide to make
a Star Wars game look like Star Wars?
Well, they have the library.
They had a massive text library and the reference library where you got a lot of shots and things
when you were out there.
So when we started, I would say that we still had to paint all of our own textures, but
most of the stuff that we had, consider this was only the first three movies.
This was before Jar Jar was introduced.
And it was, there was just a ton of, they had their library and they had, they had,
they still do I think, they still have a division of people that are just there to, you know,
tell you if it's usable or canon or not.
So we had to have a lot of yes or no conversations and there was a lot of times where actually
I could find.
be like, no, they have to say yes to this.
Why do they say no?
I will go find reference in a comic book
to show them that it's already out there.
Yes, it is canon.
Yeah, and then they'd be like, all right, fine.
You can have a gold protocol droid.
That's not, you know, stuff like that.
And it was, it was, it was cool,
but at the same time, it can get pretty frustrating.
I would say like, as far as like what we came into,
they sent us books.
movies, comics, like they had a lot of physical material that we could look at and look through.
And then, like I mentioned earlier, I think, I can't speak for all of us, but Star Wars nerd
would pretty much define me growing up especially. So I had all this, you know, Star Wars role-playing
game stuff, I had all these different things. So I already had like this really, like this was a
dream come true. Like this was seriously, never in a million years did I think I'd get to work
on a Star Wars title.
And so I was lucky enough to get to go out and work on the story and they took me to Lucas Ranch.
I got to have lunch right next to George Lucas. I couldn't look at him or talk to him
because they warned us about that when we got there. But you know as a nerd boy growing up
in Wisconsin this was like the most amazingly cool thing I'd ever done in my entire life.
I kind of a weird follow-up question on that. I like I like
I am endlessly fascinated by how story and experience emerges from tools and shapes.
What do you think was the biggest contribution you guys did for Star Wars in terms of something
that could only happen in a video game?
Because it's easy, big air quotes, to make up story ideas and say, oh, it would be cool
if this happened in Star Wars.
It's another thing to say, because our game could only do this, this is kind of the only
thing that could happen in this moment in this way.
Now if you'll excuse me, I'm going to snipe these Rodians because I hate them.
Well, we fostered hatred of Rodians.
Oh, I like Rodians! I hate to take these ones!
Okay, these Rodians, yes, exactly.
That's a really good question. I mean, there was the Reborn, the Remnant, all those things that kind of came out together.
I mean the whole expanded universe actually was pretty cool and how everything tied together.
Obviously since we worked on it I was disappointed when Disney mixed it all.
I kept expecting to see Kyle in Rogue One.
Kyle would have been great in Rogue One.
Cassian Endurance.
I thought he was going to be in Disney at one point.
Kyle Katarn.
Let's put him back.
Yeah.
But you know again I think Star Wars was huge but it wasn't as...
Huge as it is now like now there's almost like everywhere you go there's Star Wars
And and well we made it accessible through the game because you can actually then jump into Star Wars in this case and actually feel
Like you were in the world. I mean getting killed by Rodian
Yeah, exactly
What's funny is I killed them and then I accidentally loaded the game to where I hadn't killed them
Oh, I was like, why did I do that?
Huh?
I want to say too about the modding, the person you mentioned modding before.
Modding was really important to this game.
When this game came out and we saw how many people were making content for it, making
character models for it, lightsaber models for it, James and I tried our best to make
Jedi Academy as mod-friendly as possible, externalizing a lot of the data, putting it
in text files, making it easy to mod.
The first external data, most of it was scripted back then, but we moved it to text files so
that you could change the values.
Right, and that was really important to me personally too because I started as a modder.
When I applied at Raven, it was sending Doom and Quake mods to them.
I wanted to see it make the game really easy to mod, so for me it's really awesome to see
that people are still modding it all these years later.
To go on mods real quick, I'm actually going to build off of that.
I saw a great tweet from Radiator Yang, his handle is Radiator Yang, I believe it's Robert
Yang is his full name, talking about how much level design tools that are available to the
public have changed.
On the one hand, anyone can license Unity or Unreal, on the other hand, there isn't
quite that Doom or Quake mod for people to just play around in.
How do you feel...
I guess you guys obviously have made a very moddable game, but how do you feel that games like Doom and Quake were at the time for modders, and do you feel like people still have those opportunities to show off their own skills?
They can in certain games. I mean, Valve's got their stuff for Team Fortress, and obviously the Black Ops tools are out for...
They're out for 4.
I don't know if they did for 4.
Okay, but they were out for 3, and I mean, people can go out there and make all kinds of mods and all kinds of...
Changes I mean, I think the world sorry. No, I was gonna say it's a it's a little
Different I suppose because you have a few more options
But I guess you have to be really invested in the game to really want to do that
I think the world quote-unquote the game world changed when consoles became
Yeah, the king like back when this kid like this was built for PC
We we only were a PC studio and that's why you know, the other company imported it
And so it's a lot easier to use a keyboard and a mouse and be able to modify stuff and
Offer tools that are supported that way than it is to do it for like a console game
So I think like that's that's part of it is just as we've gone along
It's just we we've focused more on console games, just the entire industry in general
Really quick
Instigator007 points out that Halo Forge is an excellent resource still available to people.
I was using GTK Radiant and I expanded the ladder map that you made.
We used to test AI, like I just scripted it to spawn increasingly difficult waves of enemies and we released that.
But I was using GTK Radiant.
earlier this year to expand that and modify it.
So you can still modulate tools.
The Sames tools still work.
And we released pretty much all the tools for this, the
Simulate and ModView and all that other stuff.
Simulate.
That's your new track.
I'm going to dive into the question pool again.
One of the things that I was fascinated on revisiting this was the, not only is this,
I feel like a lot of people working in Star Wars outside of the movies have wanted to
see that grittier side of Star Wars.
I could dive, I'm a Star Wars history nerd, so I could dive into like the crime show that
was supposed to be made before the Disney buy.
But the idea of gritty Star Wars is not in and of itself fascinating, but at the same time you guys are the you know
You took a brand that the time was if anything getting more kid friendly and released a a version where which we discussed before
People's limbs were getting dismembered extremely you are literally showing that just we just watched a bunch of people get disintegrated
what was kind of the
The feel at the time for that kind of storytelling and that or in that kind of visual design in your in your Star Wars world
You got something else you want to say?
Well, I was going to say something I remember specifically from that era.
We've just come from Elite Force where all the weapons and ships were super clean and shiny.
And here, I remember having a conversation about how the whole world is different now.
Things are gritty and grimy and scratched up and dirty.
And it was a very stark contrast switch to this world.
It's high tech beat up.
It's all well used industrially.
I think, too, like, well that's not totally related, but I think one of the things that,
I think one of the reasons we did, you know, licensed games well is because we were fans
of every license we got.
That's right, we had a lot.
Like, we knew, we knew Star Trek and Star Wars, you know, Wolverine and X-Men.
To be fair, like, to be fair, I know I keep saying that, it's my new words apparently.
Back then, licensed games were the king.
If you had a movie title, you were the king.
You were walking on water.
To get a new game up and off the ground
with a brand new license was not an easy thing to do.
And working with Activision too,
I know that they were very much about trying to find
co-marketing and getting people connected that way.
So it wasn't until probably right when we started,
we just finished up Wolverine, right?
X-Men Origin Wolverine.
It was sort of the downfall of movie games almost, I felt like, where movie games...
Because they had to be so connected to an actual movie, they became really hard to make.
And they didn't give the returns that they used to.
And on top of the licensing fees, it feels like, just went up.
And so the returns you'd have to make to keep your company doors open...
Are you behind me too? Seriously?
There's one above you, one behind you, and one in front of you.
So... go left.
Go left.
As far as the dismemberment stuff goes, I remember there was a debate in rules about
what you can dismember and what you can't dismember, how much...
That was in Cavitation.
And then you go see... and then Episode 3 comes out and Anakin cuts off both of Dooku's hands
and his head.
It's like, oh, okay.
And they're like, really?
And he's chopped in half, right?
Yeah.
Well, they said that was okay because it wasn't...
Anakin gets arms and legs and burns his wrists and is like, holy crap.
Well, that was...
We had a hot patch right there at the end where we had to dial down the chance of dismemberment
per location and the neck was something like 10% but we had to take it down to, did we
make it actual zero?
We made it actually zero.
Unless it was a droid, you couldn't make it.
That's right, we made it actually zero.
We were like, it's a really low chance and they were like, no, that's too much chance.
So you're right, yeah, zero.
So you had to go up and jump down onto that thing, I think.
I did have a game facts guide open.
Yeah, I'm just going to get shot a lot, aren't I?
Alright, how do I get up on this?
Um, it is back at that front area, isn't it?
Yeah, there's a little window.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Do I have to shoot this, right? Nope.
You have to go up a level and jump down onto the roof.
Jump down onto the roof.
Got it. Oh.
Yeah.
Well, you know, some of the other things that I noticed when I played through was
You don't always get the best clue of which glass is breakable.
We try to have the most breakable have either cracks in it or a pattern in it that it's unbreakable.
But if it's clear, it's breakable.
Yeah, but there are some clear glasses here and there that we had that were not breakable.
It just happens sometimes that they became bulletproof.
Yeah, exactly. It just happens.
I think in the past, especially, there was sort of the designer mantra of...
Harder is better. Yeah, you still see games that are really hard and they thrive on those dark souls. Yeah
Consider this the dark souls. Yeah
Everyone at home you are being introduced to my kitten Ellie. She decided to join us and is squeaking into the microphone
So if you hear her say hi to her she loves video games and she loves Star Wars she likes eating Star Wars Legos
Um, so we only have 20 minutes left in our chat.
Unfortunately, I could go all day.
I could, but unfortunately these folks in the room need to go back to making video
games.
I'm told that I'm told that you can't just talk about video games, although you
need to actually make video games.
Um, yeah, we can just hang out.
Production does not approve.
By the way, this is my current lightsaber.
Oh.
I will pause for a minute just to admire this.
So I, uh, modified it to, uh, have the sound, the actual sounds from the game.
Uh-huh. Ooh!
And that's just, that's just a, um, that's not one of the new, um, hilts from Disney, right?
That's, that's like a...
No, this is a help that I think Saberforge made and then I modified it a bit to make it look more like Kyle's lightsaber.
Nice. I do my best on the stream to keep things related to game development, but I, as a Star Wars nerd, need to stop and admire my craftsmanship.
Um... um... okay.
Moving on from the greater thing, let's dive into the- we've danced around the topic of tools this whole time, but I'm curious,
what were the tool- you already mentioned the names of some of the tools, but what were the tools like that you used to make this game,
and what do you think worked well about those tools, and what do you think that helped you iterate quickly,
and what do you think they could have- like, what were the things you were trying to improve as you were making them?
Radiant was our editor for the levels.
By this time, at least, Radiant had more than a top-down view.
Because when we first started working in the Quake editor, it was only top-down.
You had the Z-checker, and that was the only way you could tell floor above floor or anything.
So as soon as we were able to actually have multiple views, it was like a godsend.
It was a game changer.
But really, I mean, Radian is Radian, and at its core, building brushes, surface, all
of those things.
It's pretty solid.
Patches have changed quite a bit from the way they used to have to be implemented.
I mean, they were a lot more like a nerd back then, but we also had bending mode, so we
couldn't just grab points.
We had to hit a tool to take a pipe and actually bend it on a specific angle, then save it
and make sure it didn't crash, because we put too many parts in it.
We're like, hey, it's saved.
This was before normal maps.
This was before specular.
So we didn't, you know, textures were just painted.
We added normal maps.
the game you put in.
Did we?
It's at the very end, yeah.
That's cool.
It was in the first ports.
I know we had to write a lot of tools for ourselves.
We did.
For like the model viewer and the editing note tracks
in the model viewer, I think we did that.
And stripping out the script, we did that for Elite Force.
Stripping out the dialogue out of the script
to turn it into subtitles and that sort of thing
and sound files.
Oh, gosh.
I had to hand, my friend, I had to hand
go through.
for voice modulation for head down.
I had to mark which vowel forms people had to use for their mouth.
We didn't have lip sync tech.
So we did animations for this one, right?
The previous one we did texture pages, but this one was animation.
And you tagged it, which you had to put in brackets, which phoneme.
Yeah, which phoneme so that it would pick a matching vowel.
I remember I wrote a little...
I guess procedural kind of head bobbing as they would talk based on the volume of the file they're saying.
We would use the average volume to drive the animation.
Oh really? Wait, wait, wait. No, I need to nerd out about that.
I'll nerd out about the figure in a minute, but how did using the volume to drive the animation work?
Well, so...
Well, I was talking about the saved memory.
We don't store all the animations.
Like, the upper animations are completely separate from the
lower legs so that we could do all those left, right attacks
and running.
The facial animations are the same way.
We just stored, what was it, seven phonemes?
Different mouth shapes.
That was to drive all the animations and then to make it seem more realistic, we added some head motion.
Yes, they're not just puppets.
So they're not just puppets, right?
Trying to keep the interest, like they're nodding and bobbing.
And so we just basically made it random, but as an input to the random number generator with the volume,
so that if they're speaking more emphatically, their head will move more.
Right.
And that was just a free way to make on-the-fly animations.
I'm sure that's a trick that's still used today to some extent, but I just haven't heard of it being
of such a programmatic solution being implemented with animation.
You did that in Elite Force and carried it over to this.
Yeah, there's a lot of programmatic solutions back then just because the memory was so tight.
I mean, look how many textures we have in this world. It's not a...
Not a large set.
I'm just trying to get some breathing room here. Okay, cool.
back to tanks.
Oh wow, is that with a Yu Zhong Vong?
Yeah, so I had to get that.
So it's called comic, but yeah, like the way I could, like I said, I could talk too much about how the Old Eagle worked, the logic of it.
I could spend too much time there. I'm going to check chat to make sure there's any questions.
Oh, Bucky21659 has a great question.
Is there anything you can talk about as far as cut concepts or content?
or things that changed during development. For instance, they heard Tavion was going to be male
and was supposed to be encountered again near the end of the game.
That's right.
So, do you remember this?
Do you remember anything? Go ahead.
You know you were first to ask.
You start.
Are we those chipmunks?
I have to look something up, so you start.
Well, I just, I mean there's a ton of stuff that
hit the cutting room floor.
I don't know how many stories
I put together, I don't know how many different
locations, like again, this was like
Nerd Eric's dream. So I was pulling in like everything that I could possibly get character wise.
You know, we were lucky we got Lando. And that was just like, holy cow, just to be able to have
Lando in the game was amazing. And it's kind of it's, it's something we always joke about,
but we were actually running a Star Wars RPG game. And so a lot of the characters in that game,
that's Tavion, that's Ardis, that's D'Sonn, those are those are characters that we had.
different things like that, but I couldn't, I don't even know where to start with things that were in and went away or never even made it to the day.
So, change the opening level.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, we'll change the opening level.
So I was going to say, the bad guy, Tavian, the story behind that was, I had suggested that we make a...
a bad guy based on Bruce Lee, but the specific Bruce Lee no one ever saw.
That was an audition he had done for Shaw Brothers films.
So he had a very kind of Shaw Brothers look to him.
So it was kind of like, I don't know if this is going to show up.
It's showing up. It's good.
Yeah. So it's that look right, like that.
Yeah.
And we originally were going to do that.
And I think then it became a woman, like the story changed everything.
But we did end up using something like that.
For this guy, you'll see sometimes he's a Jedi trainer.
Yeah.
That's what it became.
But that was something I remember that was a cut concept.
So we still use them somewhere else?
Yeah.
I think coming up with D'San, even being his own race, was coming up with a new type of
creature for Star Wars at the time was hard to get passed through.
It had to go to Lucas.
We had all these things we had to jump through.
What got cut for technical reasons?
I wanted to, oh no that was for Jedi Academy.
Yeah, flying.
No, well okay.
The ships.
So the flying we did that in, I did that as a mod after Jedi Academy, being able to fly
the ships.
But for Jedi Academy I wanted you to be able to build your own lightsaber.
That's right.
Yeah, that's right.
Although for Outcast I do remember, like we could only have a certain amount of lights,
and like in the Doomgiver levels, like I went through and I started putting colored lights
everywhere like every point in the world where there was a light I really wanted to make it feel
like a real place and it we ran out of
It ran out of entities essentially, and those all got torn out in order for it just to run.
It was so depressing.
Didn't some of the levels have to be split in half when they were ported to the console?
We had to split a lot of them, yeah.
We had to chop a whole bunch of them in pieces and we were like, where's the logical point?
We were just playing through, like, here?
It was because of something you had to go back and forth.
Yeah, we had to chop some of those spots where we were like, this isn't optimal but it's
going to work.
But that was just for consoles.
Yeah, exactly.
For PC we were just like, yep.
Well.
Art Salad actually asked a smart question.
Couldn't you use shader lights instead of entity lights?
They didn't cast light, right?
Yeah, they were shadow casting and some of them were scripted to blink and stuff.
So they were not baked.
And we didn't have shaders, like GPU shaders back then.
Answer. The tech didn't exist yet.
Right. This game is entirely on the CPU. The GPU is just the fixed function triangle rasterizer.
To springboard off that chat while I deal with another pair of annoying Rodians,
um, this is so- I do, I do actually- weirdly I've like, as an adult now, I've picked up on so many subtle design things
that help make this game make sense, like um, the concept of a kneeling Stormtrooper and how dangerous they are versus the standing ones.
Um, uh, the- the fact that each- you've separated the species, like it's easy to tell which species and what kind of gun you're facing based on that.
Um.
Which I guess technically is anaphobic, but whatever, who cares, it's Star Wars.
They're just story tells.
Yeah.
I'm going to...
I guess I can ask this question from DarkShadowRage.
Did you guys spend any time playing fan maps, like one called Atlantica from JKA?
And I'm going to follow up as a dev question on that.
What was the difference...
Oh no, another one.
What was the difference from interacting with your community then versus interacting with
your community now?
He said, as Chris, the wonderful community manager, sits in the room and has been very
helpful today.
What's changed about interacting with your community in that way?
You want to start with the mod question?
Did you guys play that mod?
Yes.
I don't remember that map in particular, but I played a ton of mods.
Maps, multiplayer mods, multiplayer.
Mods, content, player models, all the extra dual maps, those are really cool.
Played on modded servers and stuff like that.
I remember one was so cool, it wasn't really Jedi related because it was a total conversion to a Roman Colosseum.
And so there would be this cheering and you would come out and you'd have a short sword and rose petals were falling and everything.
and they had music from Gladiator or something.
And you go out and fight, and he was using all of our...
Sabers.
Yeah, all of our...
Animation.
But he was using, not lightsabers, it was swords.
And it was so well done.
I was like, this guy's amazing.
This guy should get hired.
And I think he ended up working at Respawn.
Yeah, and he ended up going to...
But anyway, I remember just being super impressed with a lot of the mods that were out there.
So as far as the second part, with how we interacted with people, like...
We came from, I don't know, probably all of you guys said Finger Files.
Plane Files?
Yeah.
We lived in a world where Plane Files ruled the earth where we could, every day we would,
I mean it was a totally different place.
I would come into work and I would write, hey today I'm working on this level with
this character and this gameplay and now everything is a tightly held secret.
I'd get fired if I, you know, we put screenshots out on our own.
What was the instant messaging thing we had back then?
We have AIM, we have ICQ.
I used to get ICQ messages from...
Oh, random ICQs all the time.
I'd get them from people working at magazines or interviewers,
and they're like, hey, can I ask you a quick question?
I'm like, sure, and I answer the question.
Nowadays, we're like, we actually have to make sure.
Legally, we're allowed to answer certain things,
and we don't want to give away things
because we don't want to screw up marketing.
But sometimes back then, it was like, oh, here's the info.
We're like, wait, should I told somebody?
Well, it's probably okay.
I went and looked and you can still find them on Blue's News.
Yeah.
The last time I checked it was on Blue's News.
It was on Blue's News.
One of those two.
I'm pretty sure it was on Blue's News.
But it was cool.
It was cool and at the same time it was pretty weird where one time I have a brother who
lives kind of near me and he was wearing a Jedi, I don't know if it was a Jedi, it was
a raven shirt and a UPS driver came up and...
And like had to have him sign for something. He said Beastman would you work at Raven software?
And that's when i'm like, all right, I am not going to be posted online anymore
They're outside the window
Yeah, I still have a uh mail posted on my door that we got like a few years ago
I think from a group of people who still play
multiplayer and they were just thinking
us for how amazing it was and for making the game and I was like, oh man, it makes me feel really good.
So it's now pasted in my door in my office.
Yeah, I think the biggest thing with that is and
Mace kind of hits on it in the chat is I wish studios were more open with communication like that still.
It's not that we don't want to be. Everybody's very very, even projects we have right now,
everybody's very very passionate about it. It's just it's a different culture now of the info sharing, you know, we're all
Once the game comes out, you can certainly talk to us.
There's certainly ways that we want to reach out with even newer titles and stuff like that,
with Twitch and Twitter and all that type of stuff.
It's not that we've lost interest.
It's about the reveal. Everything's bigger.
I remember when we released development screenshots, like you were saying,
like the lightsaber. We showed some pictures of the lightsabers and stuff.
I don't know if that was for E3 or whatever.
We released them and then I would go on to the forums and I'd see people were talking about the lightsaber effects and how it didn't look right.
And I remember reading that and I'm like, oh, they're right. They're totally right.
It's like it's got the wrong blend mode or whatever.
And so, you know, they just changed the blend mode and it looked more, you know, movie-like.
And I'm like, oh, that's great. Like that's something we wouldn't have known if, you know.
We wouldn't have thought of that as quickly without the...
I'd say it's been, it was 90% positive.
Like, there's always those people online that are not.
They just don't like anything. They dislike you for some reason, but I love...
I mean, I'm a gamer at heart. I'm a Star Wars fan at heart.
Like, I want to geek out with people and I want to share stories and, you know, talk about this stuff.
You must be playing on Jedi Knight difficulty.
I am. I am. And I regret it.
So, for this game, for difficulty, like I...
My personal philosophy on difficulty was that...
I didn't like it when they just threw more enemies at you, or they did some of that,
or like they just have more health.
Like I didn't want the Jedi you fight to have more health.
So what I did for difficulty was, at higher difficulties, they had better tactics.
Like they would dodge, they would start rolling, they would start jumping, they'd force grip
you, or they'd push and they'd have better reflexes and that sort of thing, and reaction
times.
Maybe that's why the snipers are killing you guys.
They are the best aiming snipers I've played.
I play a lot of Apex Legends and I swear, like, player snipers aren't this good.
I mean, it's the computer, duh. It's allowed to be good.
They're sitting there all day, just waiting at that one spot.
And when snipers are going to come by, this is their job.
You do a few of them.
Yeah.
Folks, we only have a, we literally, on paper we were supposed to be wrapping up in the
next three minutes.
We got a little bit of a late start, so we can make sure we, if you have questions, get
them in chat now and I will ask them.
If you repeated, if you had a question earlier and I missed it, I apologize.
I'm like a one man band over here at the moment.
I'm going to ask my last question. I'm actually kind of impressed. You guys are such efficient
answerers that I've gotten to all of the topics I wanted to hit. My last question is, most
games in the era that this was released had to ship with a single player campaign and
a multiplayer in order to be marketable. That's changed a lot.
There's a lot of talk about the death of single player experiences.
There's a lot of talk of multiplayer only games.
Y'all are in an interesting place where because you still work on Call of Duty,
you're working on a franchise that sometimes does both and sometimes does recently just did one.
What do you think has changed about the era of single and multiplayer design versus the era we live in today?
Ooh, that's a good question.
I remember it wasn't that long ago that we still had to...
Like you couldn't ship them a single player game, right?
You'd have to have multiplayer.
Yeah, for a long time in the development of our Wolfenstein title, we didn't work in that way with multiplayer.
Right.
I think the biggest, I mean, speaking as a gamer, the biggest thing difference is the progression systems.
You know, back in this time, I mean, I landed this game in college.
It was an arena you got into and you played.
Now it needs to...
multiplayer always needs that stickiness, at least the multiplayer we're working on
need that stickiness of progression, unlocking things, feeling like you're invested within
the game in some form.
Let's be fair, technology has allowed us to connect everywhere all the time, so that online
presence, that community, that's something that all the games are interested in, bringing
people together.
That's grown a lot.
Yeah.
I think too, we got kind of lucky in that the engines we were using, like the N engine,
It was a King of the Universe.
It was actually Quake 3, right?
This is the predecessor. This is of all multiplayer games.
So Quake 3 was still in development while we were working on Elite Force, which is a game right before this one.
And that didn't have any single player at all. We had to add the concept of single player to that.
It may have something to do with the routines and things like that you guys were playing around with for all the different AI.
But I mean, we were always going to do multiplayer.
Yeah.
We had a lot of fun working on multiplayer.
Oh, man.
That's where we got to kind of let things go.
And then everybody's like, oh, force push
is really powerful multiplayer.
And we're like, yep.
Let's make more places where you can push each other.
Yeah.
More playable.
All I'm hearing is extra life, LAN party.
I'm going to pause the game and get into these questions
in chat, because it's more important than me
getting to the level.
I'm getting somewhere. Hi, Ellie, you back again?
Um, DarkShadowRave wants to say thank you again, Raven Software, for making such great games.
Uh, um, and they- and poke Asper to update the PC version for 16x9.
Asper, if you're tuning into this, folks in chat have had some comments for you.
There are folks at Raven Software who cannot help with this port.
Um, uh...
Other questions before we leave today?
Oh! Yeah, Chris Graft is back again. I'm gonna get this question in.
What were the key parts of the game's design that were points of contention
among the team during the game's development?
I don't know if I'd order that.
You said we were all fans, but we all had the same vision.
The only thing I think that people were, you're going to laugh at this, that had issues with
were some of the jumps, because some of our guys were insanely good at making jumps.
Oh yeah.
And people were like, tone it down.
They're like, that doesn't make it fun.
Poor the snipers.
This level is...
Especially, but later on in Academy as well, we had one jump in the rift where nobody could
make it.
And our designer said, what?
I can do it just fine. He does it at his desk for like, nobody else could do it. He tried
it at somebody else's desk and he couldn't do it and it had to do with a combination
of I think his keyboard and mouse settings or his keyboard and mouse.
It was because most of the other computers we had, if you held the control key along
with one of the others, it didn't register the interrupt and you couldn't hit both keys
simultaneously except on his. He had a HP or something.
He was allowed to make these crazy strafe jumps.
But yeah, the only other thing that I think ever came up was people having a grumpy time
with some of the AT-ST combat back and forth.
There's like, come on, you're in the AT-ST, you're doing worse stuff.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but honestly I think we had more disagreements with LucasArts than ourselves.
And none of those were...
LucasArts was great to work with.
Very talented guys.
Michael Stemmle wrote the dialogue.
Dan Pennett and Brent Toskey, like all the people that were there were...
And they had a composer that would take the John Williams pieces and put them together for us the way that we needed.
Like he would mix and match them and we wrote a dynamic music system that would...
That's right.
Go between, yeah, go between like kind of the mellow exploration music and action music.
Trying to blend in and match tempo with the...
the two different genres.
We had a whole dynamic music action.
Look at that, you're going down memory lane here.
Most of the disagreements we had that I can remember were just me trying to get other
Star Wars movie references into the game.
I remember there wasn't a lot of time for these games.
We didn't have enough time for you.
Yeah, that's true.
We didn't have time to disagree.
But I think the thing is that Star Wars is such a clear vision.
Star Wars is such a...
a visionary concept to begin with. We all knew what we were making.
Right? We all have the same vision. That's the hardest part of making any game is
make sure everyone's got the same vision for the end. And if you don't, then you uh...
Poor speed!
Every time I remember how a puzzle works in this game that I solved in childhood,
as I solved as a teenager, I'm just like, I knew this. I knew how to do this.
Anyway, I'm going to ask one last question for you guys from my end.
Work-life balance is a huge topic among game developers.
Was I supposed to go over here?
I really hope I was.
Um...
It's a huge topic among game developers these days.
It has been a long time since this game was in production.
When working on this game, did you have to pull crazy hours in order to make it work?
And do you think, was it necessary?
Do you think your team's improved by then?
Did you learn anything from working that hard that you now are able to work more efficiently?
What are your thoughts on how hard you worked on this game then versus how hard you work on games now?
For me, this was a passion product.
So there was a lot of self-defined extra time.
It made it a lot easier.
My wife, I guess I'm trying to remember if I was married then, yes.
My wife at the time, she was, or she still is my wife,
was very caring and very understanding about it.
But yeah, definitely there are times when it is not.
This was a product where I actually
Did not mind it.
Well I had a futon in my office that I used to kind of live on when we were doing Star
Trek and when we got into Star Wars I got myself a new pillow because I knew I was going
to be spending so much time because it was so much fun to work on everything.
And I'm just going to say this out here, Kelly if you're listening, thanks for putting up
with all that, because I spent so much time at work and it was a labor of love.
I'm like, this level isn't quite where we wanted it to be.
I'm going to spend the evening just trying to rework it.
And then we'd rework it, and then we'd say,
what do you think?
And then somebody would give us feedback,
and then we'd spend the next night at work again,
and then stumble off the couch in the morning
and hope that we actually were coherent the rest of the day.
Did that a lot.
I'd say the same thing.
It was a passion project for me.
I think you can jump down to that room.
Yeah, I'm trying to figure out, I
think I need to jump down to a room,
but I don't know which room it is.
And I have three heads.
That console thing you were trying to get into before
that has all the glass.
That's really, really far below you.
Good luck.
Save, save, save.
I think I did work a lot.
I honestly don't remember.
I do remember I would take the game home with me on weekends.
And come back with a stack of notes.
Yeah, I would play it over the weekend.
I'd take a bunch of notes, and then I'd
come into work on Monday and do it all.
So I think, like everyone said, it's a passion project.
And yeah, I think we've all gotten probably more efficient.
As we've gotten older, we work smarter, not harder.
We've also gotten a lot more time.
I mean, this game, we did it really fast.
The thing I remember, because it was sort of the end, was spending crazy long hours
just doing the final burn.
We had to burn it to CD, drive it out to FedEx to get it on the last plane out of here to
get it over to California for review.
Those are some crazy long nights that we don't have to do that anymore because now we have
blazing fast internet.
So that's a giant time saver.
JustOneMoreGamer has actually a really good question that I really should get to before we go.
What was the thinking behind creating a completely unique demo for the game? How much extra time did that add to development?
None.
None really.
Because that was a lot of prototype work.
Yeah, that was a lot of work that we took to LucasArts to prove that we could do it.
It was the pilot, yeah.
It was also our E3 demo.
Yep.
That's where we were playing around with, like, hey,
You can use the lightsaber to break something.
There was some extra work that we had to pause it up and get it ready for public consumption.
We had to go back to it and put the proper file on it.
We said we wanted to do it and they went, okay, sure.
Yeah.
But yeah, that was something we wanted to make sure would happen.
That also has nothing to do with the actual story.
Right.
It's a fixed scenario.
not having the reflective floors.
Because we used to have the...
At the beginning we tested out the reflective floors so you could see
the stormtroopers walking.
And it was all reflective with the shots too.
But I think in the demo it just turned out just being reflecting shots.
Like all the surfaces.
I can't remember how it finally shipped, but I know that
when we first did it, it was reflective.
Because we built that one hanger just to show it off
and show the guys moving information.
The glossy floor.
Alright, I would love to. I guess there's a secret place back on this 45 degree ledge.
Uh, I guess I'll try getting to it, but then I'll probably die.
Nope, didn't die.
Um, uh, wow.
Whoa, he made it.
You gotta get-
I did not know about that.
Uh, this is Stu's level.
It's his-
Oh, yeah, it's their life secrets.
Yeah.
Oh man, oh my god, Endar, you just made this, when I get back to playing this game, you just made this so much easier for me with those extra shields.
Thank you.
With that, I'm going to bring our stream to a close.
Thank you so much to the folks from Raven Software for joining us.
Thank you for everyone for watching. Thank you for your good questions.
As a former member of the Jedi Academy community, thank you all for showing up.
Here on the GDC Twitch channel, we talk to developers about how games get made.
We are mostly talking about newer games.
Occasionally, we have the opportunity to go back and revisit a classic game,
and I'm so thankful we got to do that today.
It seems weird that 2002 is now an era of classic games, but...
It is. I'm thankful for to Asper Media for porting this game to new consoles so that new folks have a chance to check it out.
If you enjoyed the stream, please click the follow button down below.
We have some other great streams with some other great devs throughout next month and throughout the end of the year.
If you're a developer yourself or a developer adjacent,
we invite you to come out and join us at GDC.
If you are an active developer talking right now,
we are still taking submissions for the GDC summits.
Those close September 30th, so we would invite you to supply.
Go to our website to check all that out.
Yeah, hey, pitch to the people in the room.
If you have a good talk for the summits, submit it.
We'd love to hear it.
From there, for folks in the room at Raven, if people have more questions about Jedi Knight, where can they ask them?
They can ask them at our Twitter, at Raven Software. They can ask them at my personal Twitter, raven underscore lin, L-I-N-N, and I can get them to the right people.
Right on. With that, I wish everyone have a good day, and of course, may the Force be with you. Bye, everyone.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks.
What? Is that the wrong one?