Okay. Hi everyone, thanks for coming to this talk. Before we start I'd like to gently remind you to
switch off your cell phones and to evaluate this session at the end. This is my first talk at GDC
Europe and your feedback will be very valuable for me so please do that at the end.
I'm Paweł, I'm Director of Research and Development Technology at Techland.
And I came to you from Wroclaw, which is located in Poland.
And I'm going to give you some insights about Dying Light game.
So the title for the session is 4 and 1
half million players within 100 days.
There are two important takeaways for this talk.
So you'll learn what are the most important aspects
of successful game before the release.
What have we done before the release to make it successful.
and then how to increase the game virality and visibility to make a great commercial success.
So things we've done after the game is being released to the market, to the platforms.
So the agenda for this talk is as follows.
I'll give you some very brief background about myself
and Dying Light game.
And then we'll jump into the meat of the presentation.
So we'll be talking about things before and after release.
And hopefully, at the end, we'll have some time for questions.
So please stay tuned.
About me, I'm a director of research and technology development, which means I'm doing pretty much everything in the company.
Which means I'm responsible for stuff like defining vision and goals for technology development, advising the business development and supporting internal teams in terms of technology decisions.
I'm also conducting research and conducting scientific and technological centers like hardware manufacturers and so on.
and also managing internal teams, running inter-program,
hiring people, and all stuff connected with game development.
At last, but not least, I'm working very closely
to game teams.
So I try to provide the best technology for game teams
that they could take benefit from.
Yeah, a lot of stuff, but I believe strongly
in synergy between business, art, science, and technology.
That's why I really enjoy my work.
OK, so first question, have you played Dying Light?
Please raise your hand.
OK.
And who hasn't heard about the game at all,
like for the first time here?
OK, three people.
So I'm going to show you a very short, like 60-second video
clip about the game.
So it will remind you what the game is about.
But first, why video clips are good for the presentations
like this?
So there is a Chinese proverb which says that word is worth 10,000 words.
So if we have a 60 seconds trailer at 25 frames per second, it gives us one and a half thousand
pictures.
That is 15 million words, right?
I'm speaking to you right now at 180 words per minute, approximately.
So I would need almost one and a half thousand hours to talk about this video clip.
So let's save some time and see the trailer.
Okay, so this was something we've done before the release, of course.
Yeah, and now is a very good time to jump into that part of the presentation.
So we'll start with the things that we've done before.
we try to do the clear communication of the game
features.
So there are certain game features
in the game which are really like the face of the game.
For example, one of our first major feature
was the melee combat.
So in the game, you can kill zombies
in many different ways, like using weapons, traps,
environment, world objects.
You can kill zombies by kicking zombies, jumping out of them.
And we put a lot of effort to make killing fun.
So that was our first feature.
The second feature of the game is that you don't have to use the first feature. So you don't have to fight zombies, you don't have to kill zombies if they don't like you.
Instead you can use plier parkour style of moving across the world. And we call this feature the natural movement. It means that you can jump over the zombies.
You can push them, kick them, you can climb the building smartly away from the zombies.
You can use grappling hook to very fast and quickly and efficiently move around the world.
So the second feature is something that you can use the first feature or you can combine
them together.
So it worked really, really great.
The third one is the night.
So during the night, gameplay changes.
Zombies are more scary, more powerful, much more dangerous than during the day.
And you should really avoid the night if you want to survive.
There are new types of zombies, for example, like Volatiles,
which are chasing you always when you are looking back.
You need to use your flashlight, which limits your field of view,
which is even more scary.
And we call the feature Hunter by Day, Prey at Night.
And really, we try to make the game feature strong and visible for everyone.
And the last feature I'd like to mention about is the co-op play.
So you can explore the world of Koran, which is the main location in the game, with other
players, up to four players.
And people really love that.
Apart from the co-op play, you can play in player versus player mode, which we called
be the zombie mode, when you can be a hunter chasing human controlled by other players.
And that was one of the major things that we did before the release.
So, apart from the feature, we were showing the features.
We were not afraid to show, like, the one minute of the gameplay.
It's not a trailer, it's a gameplay, right? The video that you have seen, it's a gameplay video.
It's not a, like, trailer for marketing purposes.
It's the gameplay, and we were showing each week new game feature.
or the features that can be combined together
to create the new gameplay for the game.
And we call those features dying highlights.
So to keep it interesting, we weren't afraid to show.
a bit of humor as well. And one of the clips that was in Dying Highlights was the clip that you saw
two minutes ago. And also I'd like to demonstrate you another clip which is very popular and a
little bit humorous. And it's a clip about traps you can use to kill the zombies in many different
ways.
Oh
So as you can see, it's not only the melee fighting and the natural movement.
You can also kill zombies using the environment and different objects in the world.
The next thing I want to mention is that our in-house technology really worked for us.
So apart from those four game pillars I've mentioned, we're having our own tech.
And it's a really great advantage for us.
We have been developing the tech for 15 years right now,
and it gives us great flexibility and advantage.
Like, we decide which platform we are targeting,
which game features we would like to bring
to the higher level to support games,
and really, that's great, right?
So we have physically-based shading,
advanced post-processing,
as the photorealism is really important for us.
So we decide which features should support the game,
and how.
Of course, based on our engine, so the rendering stuff,
the physics stuff, and so on, we have also in-house made tools.
And this is something that gave us extra advantage, right?
So we can create the city like you
see in this picture quite easily by using
this special feature which is called hierarchical selections.
Unfortunately, I don't have time to go through that.
But if we have some time for questions,
you can ask me about that, and I'll
try to explain it in a few words.
But in general, it's some kind of a way to build a world in a hierarchical way, and in a semi-procedural way.
So we can just clone some groups of objects, which can vary a little bit, to build the city, which looks like this.
Okay, so this is something we've done before the release, and it's release day, so everyone is exhausted.
But it seems that the real fun is just about to start.
So we really wanted to take care of...
things such as keep the player engaged in our game,
so it's not only a one-shot game,
keep the product fresh and viable in full price,
and stick to our goal like long-term investment
and player support, and what we did to achieve that.
First, we have used the PLS system,
it's post-launch system, we call the system like that.
So we wanted to gather data from users, like the telemetry.
But it's only a 50% of the success.
We've provided the system, this system provides the ability
to do the real-time patches, game patches.
So if we gather the data from users,
we can tweak on a daily basis game balance,
like game scripts, for example.
So we can.
we have the whole loop so we can see how the changes progresses by changing the
scripts, getting data, and then it's a closed loop and we can just make the
game better and better on a daily basis or a few times a day even.
It also allowed us to use some event type,
event based actions like new achievements,
challenges or for example, first of April power up
when we just increase the power of fists and kicks
and you can just kick the zombie like
for a few kilometers away from the player.
So it really worked for us.
Of course we have implemented the PLS system before,
but we use that after the game is being released.
This is the example stats from the screenshots from the tool that we've used for telemetry.
So as we can see for PC players, there is something between 35 and 40 percent of retention.
So the people really completed the game with returning to the game and completed the game
after the whole gameplay.
And it's really unlikely to have an open world game.
So it was a good sign for us.
Here are some other stats that you can take a look, like for example, distance traveled.
It's something like 700 ways from Earth to Moon.
But also we can see from the stats, like marked in green, that lock picking is quite well
balanced.
So still there are more players who were able to pick the locks.
Maybe we can see from the stats that zombies dissolved in acid is quite low,
so maybe we should teach the players to do so,
or maybe there are two little places where you can kill the zombies that way.
So we know that from our telemetry and we can balance it in real time.
Okay, so that was the wide aspect of telemetry.
So we were gathering like statistic data from the users.
But then we decided to go very pro-player company.
So we were reading feedback on forums, on each forum.
We were talking to community via Steam chat
and on the Facebook.
We were present in social media everywhere.
We were really listening to our gamers
and tried to change the game,
taking...
like the feedback into account, so it was very important for us.
And the example for that is that we are always pushing hardware to the limits of our technology.
So we have experienced a lot of issues, like hardware issues for the PC version
after the game is being released.
And really working with community was a great experience for us
because we're contacting individual people who had problems.
we were providing the beta branches on Steam.
They were downloaded, the branches, they were tested,
said everything is okay, you can go live.
We made the patch live.
So it really worked for us,
and we received great feedback from community
that we're really working with people,
not only from telemetry point of view,
but also from individual player point of view.
And it's a great way of getting to know about your issues
getting better feedback from community.
Worked fantastic.
Another thing we've done was releasing the developer tools.
So after two months, two months after release,
we have released our world editor.
And people just were able to create the mods for our games,
for Dying Light games.
So we've got right now, after four months of release,
like 150.
maps for example, so you can extend your gameplay into 30 hours just by playing mods.
And yeah, so it was really, really good direction.
So you can see the different mods on Steam Workshop.
So we've done the Steam Workshop integration.
There is a lot of stuff going on in the forum.
Here are some stats.
So we have something like 150k downloads, which is quite good in terms of game visibility and virality.
And one of the stats for here, which is I guess the most important, is the return of investments for generated marketing value.
So we put the X amount of money for making the tools available, and we got 10X.
back in the marketing value bar, but generated links, YouTube views, and Facebook views, and so on.
So, yeah, it was really a long-term investment, and it was something that you should really consider doing also.
Apart from that, so apart from the very wide perspective,
like the telemetry, and talking to individual users,
we also wanted to reach all potential players.
And I really do mean all of them,
like even those who buy the game once or twice a year.
So we reached to Ampisound, a parkour collective,
to create a real-time, real-life Dying Light video.
The video they created for us attracted
over 12 million players.
and views both on the YouTube and Facebook, so
really we started to propagate the zombie culture
in the mainstream media, and it
worked also just fantastic. So
you were just able to read about Dying Light in
really every review and every
journal, so it was great.
The next step we've done was that once the game came out,
our focus shifted from just presenting the gameplay
into keep the fans engaged.
So we just don't want to show the gameplay,
because the players were able to play the game.
But we tried to do something like the customer word
of mouth.
But we wanted the users to create the content
and to share the content.
So we decided to create something like the community hub
when we asked our fans to participate in gameplay community challenges.
So first, for example, we asked our fans to submit a maximum
30 second long gameplay clip that make feel them like a badass.
The process was very simple. Upload your clip to the YouTube,
tag it with the hashtag badass dying light,
and send a tweet with the link in the hashtag.
we gave people a week to send the clips in.
And the result was really staggering.
So we received hundreds of entries populating YouTube.
As a result, Badass Time Flight Tag
had over one million impressions over Twitter alone.
So the best part was that our fans were sending out.
like the gameplay from the best possible angle,
that they were really proud of it,
and it really, like, it was the marketing
which go viral and great.
So digital word of mouth at its best, really.
We did some other campaigns, like Drink for DLC,
and it also go viral.
We had also ideas like, and we've done the ideas,
like the Horan emergency line.
So.
to give a world of dying light a nod to the real life,
we set up a real phone number which is located in the game.
So it's linked to the Skype account
with pre-recorded message and people were able
to find the number and call real Skype
to Horan emergency hotline.
And before we publicized the number, we had thousands of messages left on Skype,
account and Reddit threads talking about the number.
So we decided to listen to the messages through,
and after a week of listening and digging through,
we choose the best, most funniest one and create a compilation of that.
It's on YouTube as well.
And once we released the video, our social channels, the fans went nuts.
Over 100,000 people watched the video, and it seemed just as many people called the number
right after.
So it was really, really great move.
And the amount of positive feedback and community support was really staggering.
OK, so we don't have much time, so...
I'll try to make a wrap-up of all the features that we've done, all the things that we've done.
clear communication of game pillars, game features.
You need to stick to them and work on them
for the whole production process.
Having our own tech was really great advantage for us.
And we are not afraid to show the gameplay footage.
So we were showing the gameplay features just
on a weekly basis.
And just for three or four months before the release,
you can see, you were able to see the game actually
how it looks.
We use the post launching system. So both telemetry and
patching on on a daily basis
And of course, working with community was one of the best shots in like the marketing and PR of Dying Light.
So it helped us solving hardware issues, making challenges, releasing developer tools,
community hub for sharing the best gameplay videos from our users.
And of course, a lot of crazy and creative ideas like Drink for DLC or Skype emergency hotline was working great.
And apart from that, we had tons and tons and tons of content updates.
And I'm going to show you right now a short video about our content updates.
So enjoy.
Let the game begin.
and I'll see you in the next video.
Bye.
Okay, so as you can see, after 180 days after the release, we're still packing the game with updates and people just love that.
And we're still working on more on big content update.
And that's pretty much it. Thanks for being here. And if you have any questions, I'm here.
I'm also at the business area and we have also our recruitment area, so you can find me or my colleagues.
And if you have questions, I'm here for you.
Thanks.