My talk today is called Empathizing with Steam,
How Buyers See Your Game.
So about a year ago, I released my first game on Steam.
And when you're going through the process
and you're filling out all the forms,
you get this store page form.
And it's just this giant blank box
that you have to fill out that describes,
it just prompts you to say about this game.
And I had no idea what to put in this box.
So I made up something.
I just threw words at it, basically.
And my game released, and it didn't sell very well.
It was very positive, I got a lot of good reviews,
but it just didn't sell.
And I just wondered, what the hell
are Steam shoppers actually looking for?
And so I took this really, really extreme.
basically step to do, which is I just started watching people buy games on Steam. I found
people online who are willing to let me do a one-on-one screen share through Discord,
and I just gave them the simple prompt, go shop for stuff on Steam. I just want to see what you do.
And what I did was I did this for 15 hours. Not straight, I did this across several different
Steam shoppers, and I really got a good sense of what they're looking for.
And so what I'm going to show you in this talk
is what I learned in those 15 hours.
I'm going to show you how to get good screenshots, good videos.
I'm going to show you that I found some really strange
behavior that players are incredibly genre-focused.
And they really know what they like and what they don't like.
And then I'm going to show you some tricks that I learned
during Steam sales and how to make your game more attractive.
And then the other thing that I did was I found out
that their friends really play a big.
big, big role in what games they pick and which ones they don't.
And so I'm going to show you how to kind of maximize that and really get good word of mouth
based on your Steam page and just in general marketing.
Okay, so there's going to be five parts to this talk.
I'm going to talk about the methodology that I use and why I did it.
I'm going to show you how to make your Steam page that sells.
And I'm going to show you the steps that a typical user is going to go through when
they're looking at Steam.
I'm going to show you how to know your genre and why that's so important,
how incredibly important it is.
And then fourth, I'm going to show you
how to manage a Steam sale.
It can be a little crazy.
And then fifth, I'm going to show you
how to turn those wish listers into actual buyers,
because you can get stuck in the cart and not get out.
So I'm going to show you all of this today.
So let's start with the methodology.
I'm an indie game designer, but I'm also a marketing consultant.
So in addition to making games, I also
help other companies sell their own games
and make their marketing just as tight as can be.
So I have a real interest in this and a lot of history
with helping.
people make better games and marketing them better.
My first game was One Screen Platformer on Steam.
And before I got into games
and before I started becoming a marketing consultant,
I was a UX designer.
And this is actually a picture that I took.
It's at an airport.
I used to work for an airline.
And what I would do is I would go and watch
how people actually use the products that I worked on.
Because as a designer, we were trained over and over again,
do not start designing
until you understand what the user does.
And so here I am watching some folks get boarded on a flight to Chicago,
and this same approach is what I applied to Steam and understanding how the Steam users shop on Steam.
And the reason that's so important and why UX designers learn that is because the users of your software or Steam are not like us as designers.
Being a designer or game developer is a very specific field, and we have different notions of what is good and what's bad than the average consumer.
And so it's really important that you actually step in and empathize with your users by watching how they actually use things.
And so instead of the airline being my client, Steam is my client.
So I treated it the same way I would when I was working in industry.
And so what I did was I recruited users and I set up a one-on-one screen share for about
a half an hour per user and I just gave them a very simple prompt.
I said, what do you do when you start Steam? And then I just let them go.
And the way that we do it in UX is you try and shut up.
You do not want to influence the user too much.
So we do something called talk aloud.
And basically I give them a simple prompt that says,
just say everything that you're thinking.
And that really makes sure that people,
when they click on something, I know why they clicked on it.
Or when they stop, the hover.
I know why they're hovering.
And one of the participants said,
you mean like a let's play of Steam?
And I was like, that's exactly it.
It was so hard in UX to get people to talk aloud,
but gamers understand this concept
of narrating everything that they do.
So it really wasn't very hard to get people talking.
And over the course of the study, I used 15 participants.
The color coding just shows the different phases
of the tests that I used.
So I'm gonna keep them anonymous
because that's part of our agreement.
I didn't wanna.
bring everybody public about who they were.
So I just color code them and name them with a letter.
I actually did three phases to this test.
So there's a phase during a normal steam day, just no sales or anything, then during a Halloween
sale, which was a seasonal sale, and then phase three was something called a diary study,
and it lasted for three whole months. So I'll show you all of these. Again, the colors just
kind of indicate the people that I used in every study. So for example, participant A was used in
all three of them, and that's why color-coded as orange, because I originally met that participant
in phase one, and then they just carried through to the other ones. So it just,
the colors indicate which phase they're in.
I also recruited worldwide.
I really tried to get a good broad swath of the population.
I got every continent except for Africa and Australia.
Unfortunately, Africa doesn't use Steam very much.
I really tried to find some folks,
but it's really hard to find them.
And then this kind of matches a demographic
how Steam is made up anyways, just by the percentages.
I also over-represented female gamers.
This was to really get a broad swath of use cases.
There's some estimates that it's about 18 to 5%
of Steam's audience is female, but I got it up to almost 50%.
I had six identified females in my participant.
list. Also did 18 and over. That's because I made everybody sign a disclosure form so that just to
have an agreement that it's okay for me to share this data with all of you and for me to record
them. So I wanted to make sure there was 18 plus, so there's no reason I didn't want to have to
recruit parents to get their kid to sign this form or anything. So and most of my audience
anyway for indie games is over 18 anyway.
I also made sure that all the participants had over 50 games.
And that's because I'm an indie game developer,
and the people who buy indie games buy a lot of games.
That's just because most players who only play
maybe a Skyrim or a CSGO just don't have that many games.
So I really wanted to target an indie buying crowd.
And you're probably wondering like, 15 people, that's it? What
about sample size? And so I know that's that's a very critical
thing for quantitative research, which is the opposite of
qualitative research, which is what I did. With quantitative
research, you're really trying to identify the giant data sets
and prove...
perfect correlation using Spearman's Row and all these giant numbers.
Qualitative research is the other side.
And what you're trying to do is a breadth of experiences.
So, for example, here's a very famous industrial designer named Pat Moore.
And what she did was she was trying to study how the elderly use the world.
And so what she did, she dressed herself as an older person,
she bound her hands, wore glasses that made it hard for her to see.
And she just explored the world and figured out where things were difficult
for somebody who was
elderly or who would be elderly like that.
And her research, and she was a test case of one,
led to things like the OXO Good Grips.
She helped design the OXO Good Grips,
those kitchen tools that have nice,
giant grips that are easier to
use for people who might have mobility problems.
And again, those just were insanely popular.
And it was all because she took
a qualitative approach to design.
Similarly, another industrial designer named Doug Dietz, he designed the CRT, the imaging
machines at hospitals.
And he designed this whole thing, all the engineering was sound, and they put it in
the hospital, it worked perfectly.
And then one day he went off to the hospital just to see how it was used, and it turns
out it was in the pediatric ward.
And when he sat outside the pediatric ward
and he saw folks coming in, he noticed
that the parents and the people who
were going to be using it and the children
were just not very excited about using this machine.
And it wasn't until he actually went and observed
real users using his device that he realized
that it was just impractical.
And so what he did was he redesigned his CRT machine,
his imaging machine, so that it was a lot easier and just more
appealing.
And so even if you can't get a huge, huge sample set,
when you're doing qualitative research,
you're really trying to get a breadth of research.
And Nielsen Norman, who is part of this research group,
they do a lot of UX design and UX research,
and what they say is discovering the unexpected
is part of the reasons you do this type of research.
Basically, you don't know what you do know,
you don't know what you don't know
until you do qualitative research.
And the idea is that you should always pair qualitative with quantitative, because quantitative
can prove definitively a couple single points, but you could be proving the wrong one. And the
qualitative research is a great way to kind of look back and see a broad range of ways that you
can do research. And when you're doing qualitative research, the most important thing is something
called saturation.
And saturation is basically I'm looking not to confirm the same thing multiple times.
What I'm trying to do is find all the edge cases and all the possible paths that people take.
So for example, there's kind of a good rule of thumb.
After about six or seven interviews,
you start to notice the same things being said over and over again.
And that's the saturation taking place.
And I definitely saw that.
And so what I'm trying to do is,
and that's why I overrepresented women in the study,
is I was trying to find all the different aspects that could implement,
that could be the use cases that people have on STEAM.
So qualitative, again, is a good way to do a springboard for quantitative research.
And I really hope that people who watch this video or read my talk later will actually
take this as an inspiration to go do more quantitative studies based on what I've initially
found here.
So the important thing about qualitative research
is you're not going to hear me make judgments
about how many things happen.
So for instance, if I saw something happen with seven
of my participants out of 15, I can't say,
oh, this is going to happen 46% of all steam
is going to do this.
I'm not going to make those value judgments of how often it
occurs.
But I can say, I've seen this happen
or this is a common workflow.
So that's just a way to understand the way
to interpret qualitative data.
OK, I could go into how I recruited.
I'm not going to do that today.
You can read more about that on my website.
I did a whole article just on how I did
the methodology for this study.
But let's just get into the good stuff here, all right?
So I'm going to show you how to make a Steam page it sells.
There's basically three steps here.
You've got to attract them, tell them what your genre is,
and then build trust with them.
That's what your Steam page is going to do.
And I'll show you how to do that.
Now, I'm going to go rapid fire through this.
This is way too fast to take notes.
On my website, I actually put together a special document.
It's just a checklist of things you should do on your Steam page
before you hit the Publish button.
So it's a nice form that you can use.
It's just kind of like a guide.
Okay, so there's eight steps that people go through when they're looking to see whether
they should wishlist your game. They browse, hover, click to inspect the page, go to your
Steam page, then they view the game's media, they check tags, they skim the short description, not
do a full read, they totally skip over the long description, and then they check for the negative
reviews. And I'm going to show you step by step how that works.
Okay, so the brows, you know, they look at the Steam page,
look around for any icons or any of these capsule images.
And if they find one that's interesting,
they do what I call the hover.
And here's a video that I took,
this is just an animated GIF,
of somebody who's doing this hover.
And what she's looking for when she does this,
is she's just watching these images cycle.
There's a four image cycle that goes on,
and she's looking to see what the genre of the game,
and if it looks like something that she's gonna want.
I want to actually interact with them, maybe possibly buy.
And she's looking at the user tags,
and she's also looking at the number of reviews.
And if she likes what she sees in those four images,
she's going to do a click.
Now, that is super important to get that tool tip.
And this was one of the greatest revolutions
that I had when I was doing this research, was that tool tip.
And the thing that's so important is that tooltip only appears when they hover over the image.
And so you want your capsule image to be super attractive. I call it a mouse magnet.
For some reason, this capsule is an excellent mouse magnet.
Anytime I was watching participants browse theme and the remnant came up.
that mouse went straight to this image.
I don't know what it is about this image.
There's something weird about it.
I don't know if it's something like Cthulhu magic going on,
but everybody hovered on this image.
And it's just, it doesn't matter the genre,
even people who didn't like shooters
hovered over this image.
I think it's just the mysteriousness of it,
that just the interesting face that guy's got.
There's just a bunch of things that are interesting.
So really test your capsule image
to make sure it turns into a mouse magnet.
The other thing is the hover has four images that cycle,
so you really have to be cognizant of those four images.
And this is totally, just totally unclear unless you've studied this stuff.
This is a picture of the Steamworks UI. This is my game.
The Steam UI does not tell you that the first four images
are the most important that are going to show up in this hover.
So you just have to know that.
There's no indicator here.
Just make sure you prioritize the top four images
on Steamworks to be the four that you want
to see in that hover cycle.
And what kind of images should you put in that cycle?
It's got to be really descriptive of your game
and the actions they're going to be taking.
For instance, here's a game that's never going to be on Steam.
It's Breath of the Wild.
Now, I picked these four images because I think they're cool.
But I don't think these would be good for your first four
images.
Look at them.
They're all showing combat.
They're showing you boss battles.
A user who doesn't know what Breath of the Wild is,
and it's just browsing, might interpret this
as some sort of action RPG.
It could be a souls-like.
It could be a action rogue-like.
It's just unclear what you do in this game.
It just looks like you're just doing battling.
A better four-image selection would
be to show the four key elements of the game.
So for instance, for Breath of the Wild,
you do a lot of open-world exploration.
Then in the top right.
There's some crafting and inventory management.
On the bottom right, you do some puzzle solving,
and then you do some battles and some boss fights,
but that's just one element.
And so when these four images cycle,
you get a better grasp of what the game is.
So really be cognizant of the four images you pick.
You don't want to repeat yourself,
and you want to show a good set of the verbs of the game.
The other thing that people check are the user tags.
Now, the user tags, you only get five on the hover.
So you got to make sure those first five are just describing your genre perfectly.
I see a lot of things where it's like indie, that indie tag is worthless. That does not tell people
what the genre is. So you want to make sure that your top five are. The other ones are like,
a female protagonist, that's a noble tag to have, but it doesn't tell the genre. And they can
probably distinguish that, identify that's a female main character from the capsule and
screenshots. So it's worthless as a tag.
The other thing that tags do for folks is they identify things that they might not like about the genre.
For instance, people who don't like difficult games, if they see Metroidvania as a tag,
that's an identifier for them that this is a difficult game. Even if they don't play
Metroidvania, they know from history's sake that Metroidvanias are hard. So they will actually
move away from the game if it's a Metroidvania. Now that's to say, if you do have a Metroidvania,
please put that tag in. That's important.
You just have to be aware that there's reasons people do not want that game.
So if they like what they see on the hover, they're going to click on the capsule image.
And here at this point, they want your game to be awesome.
If they've clicked, they think your game is neat.
They're on your side. They're looking for things to rule them out of this game.
Okay, and so once they're on your Steam page, they're looking at four big things.
They're looking to the art.
then they look at the tags,
then they look at the short description,
and then they skip all the way down
and they look just at the reviews,
specifically the negative reviews.
Now, when they're looking,
this is an actual animated GIF
of somebody looking at the media.
Now you'll watch, they click real fast
and for the screenshots.
They're not watching the trailer first,
they're looking at the screenshots.
What they're looking for is gameplay.
They want to see what you are doing,
what the verbs of the game are.
And so they click through them really, really fast.
This guy's actually going slow
because he's trying to explain what he's doing.
Then they might go to the trailer.
And when they're looking at the video,
they're skipping ahead really fast.
Watch, he's skipping ahead right there.
Now, I have some friends who make trailers
and they were a little afraid of this.
And the main thing is, I'm not saying to ditch trailers that have any form of
cinematics. I think those should be still made. You just don't want to include them on your Steam
page. They're great for YouTube to have rich story elements, but for Steam, they just want to see the
action. They want to see the verbs of the game. So cut out anything that isn't you actually playing
the game. No big intro wind-ups, no slow panning environment shots. They just want to see the action.
Okay.
So this is how not to do a trailer. This is an actual video.
Only cinematics. I want to see some goddamn gameplay.
You can hear the frustration in this guy's voice.
Jesus. Let me see gameplay. Oh, that's the gameplay. All right. Where's the UI?
Why do you want to see the UI?
To get no more of the
House God I
Mean whenever you see the UI you'll be able to like at least assume some of the portions of the game, right?
Like how how would you be playing it and things like that? This one doesn't tell me anything it's just
He was so frustrated he did a little bit of swearing there I had to beep that out. Sorry folks
And what he's frustrated about is he just wants to see gameplay.
And one of the surprising things is he also wants to see UI.
When I was originally designing pages for Steam, I thought
they just want to see a majestic, beautiful screen.
Nobody comes to see menus.
They actually do want to see menus.
And the reason is it helps them identify the genre.
If you can see a UI, you can identify the genre.
Look at this one right here.
Two bars, some characters and a number of timer in the middle.
Obviously, that's a Street Fighter game, a 2D Street Fighter.
A nice reticle, a gun in the bottom, some health,
some bullets.
That's a first-person shooter.
Easy.
Just two anime characters and a dialogue box.
Obviously, a visual novel.
The UI really tells you the genre.
Better than any description or anything else.
So show UI in your screenshots.
I would have never guessed, but it
is so important for players to be able to identify the genre.
After they look at the media, they go over to the tags.
I already talked about that.
A lot of them won't expand the tags to really look for them.
You have the control as a developer to really pick your tags by eliminating them.
Again, remove indie, remove anything that doesn't tell genre.
The most important thing that they're looking for is identifying the genre.
Now the short description.
Here's another animated GIF of a
person who's shopping here, they're just skimming it. And
what they're looking for are verbs. They're trying to
identify what do you do in the game, not the setting. They
don't care about characters, story. They don't care any
about the fluffy stories. Even people who love games that are
story-based, in fact, this participant does, they don't
care about story at this point. They're just trying to
identify what do you do in the game.
In fact, I heard a lot of people when it was a big story-based short description,
they'd go, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. What do I actually do? They actually said,
blah, blah, blah. They don't want to see a big story or lore dump. Stick to the verbs,
stick to the actions of what you're doing in the game.
Okay, the long description, everybody skipped this thing. So I'm going to skip it too. You
could put a recipe in there for whatever I know. It doesn't matter. Okay, the negative reviews,
they'd always skip down. And it's not that they hate you.
I was really afraid when I started reading negative reviews when they started coming
in for my game.
But it doesn't matter.
Have heart.
If it stresses you out to read negative reviews, don't worry.
Because the only thing that players who watch your game are looking for are, are the reasons
this person had a negative response the same reason I don't like games?
So if they're a story-based player, and if they...
care about the story, they're going to look for reviews that maybe say,
hey, the story is bad, the characters are two-dimensional, the ending sucks.
That's what they care about. But if it's an action-based player, somebody who cares about
FPSs or good action, they are looking more for things like maybe frame rate or how the
character or how the maybe enemies behave, how the AI is. They're really looking forward to
see what they match up with. And we all hate these type of negative reviews that just are like one
line, nope. We tweet about them, we complain about them.
Don't worry. Don't waste any emotional energy on them.
The reason is shoppers hate these type of reviews too,
because they don't give them the information that they're looking for.
They're really looking to see why don't you like this game.
So if you care about this, don't. Put it outside of your mind.
I came back with a nice warm feeling for negative reviews after studying users.
It doesn't matter that much.
Okay, so after all that, if they like you, they put you on your wish list.
Everything that I just described took 90 seconds.
Let me go through and let's actually watch somebody
do this in 90 seconds.
Oh, that looks really cute.
Side note, she is in a speed lapse section.
And that's why there's no hover.
So that's why you're seeing a little bit of a video.
It's $5.
Lost Robots is a new prequel chapter, blah, blah, blah.
Let's click it. Let's look at it. Did you get a blah blah blah? She said blah blah blah.
So now she's looking at the page. And we'll go through the picture. Oh look how cute that is.
Super fast through the images. Super fast, right? What's the tag? Skip the trailer.
Any adventure noir, point and click single player, story rich cash. What's it?
Oh, it's from the Bear With Me people. Oh yeah, Bear With Me, The Lost Rebels. I have
one of the Bear With Me's.
This is so cute. When did this come out? July 31st. Let's take a look at the reviews.
Skip the long description. Did you see that?
Curators. Anybody on my curator list? No.
Why don't you like it? I'll always look for the negative ones.
Looking forward to playing this. Lone chapter. So it's very short.
Too short wanted more. Okay. Well, I mean big deal. It's five bucks guys. What do you want?
See she hates negative reviews just as much as we do. It's adorable. It's point and click
It's a known
Uh bear with me series. I know that series
Yeah, that's adorable
Again that took 90 seconds
It's really a fast process that happens.
You've got to make sure your page is dead on,
really easy to navigate.
So let's look at part three.
And I call this know your genre,
because the most important thing
is understanding what genre your game is
and putting it straight up front
so that users know your game's genre.
Okay, a big misconception that new people new to marketing is
that they think that it's like a used car salesman. Like when
you're doing marketing, you're trying to like convert somebody
you actually are not what you're trying to do is find your tribe
find the people who would be predisposed to like your game
and proving to them that you are exactly their type of game.
And then what you're basically doing is this sort of process.
Now, I put these shapes in to represent games that people like,
that maybe a person like, I only like triangle-shaped games,
or pentagon-shaped games. I hate octagon-shaped games.
And then when they look at your Steam page, what they're doing is they're comparing
your game to see if it matches their predisposed interests.
And if it does, great, they're going to buy it.
But if your Steam page is kind of this amorphous dog's breakfast of a conglomeration that's
impossible to identify, it's not like every party is going to do it.
They're actually going to compare.
They can't determine if it is something they like or if it's not.
And if they can't determine what it is, they're just going to toss it out.
You have to be very absolutely clear what your genre is.
So I'm going to show you.
This is some...
What I did was, anytime they came to a page, I just shut up and just let them speak.
what you're going to see is a video of people looking at a steam page for the first time.
There's no video because I want to just to hear and to read what they say.
It's like Super Meat Boy but with a little bit of 3D or something.
This game is looks very similar to Civilization so I think this is very interesting to me.
Ah looks like FDL.
I actually like these ones.
It looks like Mario Party.
No, thank you.
Reminds me of Alien.
Alien Isolation?
A little bit, not quite.
Yeah, it seems to be some sort of
like city building game, but on a
skyscraper.
Doesn't
interest me specifically.
It feels kind of
night in the woodsy.
And I like that. Oh my god, the art style is so pretty.
A real-time RTS city builder. That's really the kind of combo I love to go for.
Um, I've loved games like The Settlers, Age of Empires.
One of the things that we as indies were always told is,
know your hooks, be as unique as possible, stand out, shatter genres, and guess what?
they didn't mention the hooks as the reason they liked the game.
They mentioned the things that were the same. I call them anchors. That's just a term I came up
with. But people are very genre-focused, and they're not excited about what your hook is
all the time. The first thing they want to know is, what genre is this? Cut it to me straight.
What genre are you?
And so what I'm trying to say is your store page should be stripping out everything that your game is not and being absolutely clear
Focus on appealing to the type of people who like your genre know the genre the top game in your genre
Did you notice that they kept referencing other games?
Like this guy who said it's like an f2l ftl
Flat faster than light. I actually like those type of games
He didn't say, like an FTL, clone, get out of here.
No, he was excited that this game was the same as an FTL.
So don't think like that.
We really need to start kind of going back
and being sure of our genres.
Okay, I'm going to go quick tangent, and this is to show how important making the genre is.
Now, I'm not making fun of this. I think this is really cool. So indie romance authors are some of
the smartest markers you've ever seen, and I really take a lot of inspiration from them.
So we complain a lot because Steam has 35,000 games, right? It's an apocalypse. Games everywhere,
right? Guess what? Indie romance authors are on Amazon, which has eight
million books. I'm not making that number up. That is literally, it's 8 million books on Amazon.
They look at our 35,000, they say, oh, you sweet child. So how the hell did they get their books
sold when there's 8 million books? And some of these indie romance authors make a million dollars
a year. So let me show you. OK, these are indie romance book covers. They all look the same to
you, right? There's a very special language going on here. OK.
I'm just gonna walk you through this real fast
and it's gonna be life-changing.
Okay, again, I'm not making fun of this.
I think this is awesome.
Okay, so there's a very sub-genre of romance
called Highland Romance, romancing a Scotsman, I guess.
If you see tartan, a sword, and a castle in the background,
you know you got Highland Romance.
Shifter Romance, which is like werewolves,
but why stop at wolves?
We got bears, dragons, tigers.
If you see an animal behind a hunk,
that is a shifter romance.
There's another subgenre called reverse harem romance.
Instead of multiple girls, it's multiple guys.
You know that it's a reverse harem
if there's a bunch of guys in the back.
Love that name, nail and studs.
Okay, so, sub, sub, sub romance genres.
They have even more specific tastes.
And now, I'm not gonna tell you what this one is.
You can just identify it
because you've learned the language.
What do we have?
We have a wolf in the front, multiple studs in the back.
What is that?
Shifter, reverse harem.
You know the genre.
Okay, this one here, wolf in the back. The guy's wearing a kilt with a nice tartan and
there's a castle in the background. Guess what this is? Shifter Highlander. You know this romance.
You figured it out. You know the language now. Now, I wrote a whole blog post on this and how
to look at genres for romance novels. And this guy on Twitter was like, why even be in the anymore?
And I kind of, I get him. I get it. And those covers are cheesy. I'm not saying we literally
need to do that. Although those would be more fun, wouldn't it?
Here's what to learn from romance indie authors.
And this is the key point here.
You gotta know your audience's kinks.
Learn what they are.
Romance authors have studied the sub, sub, sub genre kinks
of their audience.
You should learn those too.
And then they put those kinks straight up.
They know the language that people are looking for
so that it's crystal clear.
Be absolutely clear with your genre
so your shoppers will not have any questions.
It's so that in an instant, you can identify the genre.
And like when you're coming off of a romance novel
like Bridges of Madison Counter,
you don't come to the book and say, maybe I'm into this.
I think this might be my genre.
You're like, you're either in for the bear or you're not.
Get out of here.
Okay, and so I think we should have similar confidence
on our pages.
Be very, very clear what you are
and just put it straight up there.
And we've got this actually in games right now.
Look at these simulator games.
You know what kind of simulators they are.
You've got a farming simulator, a truck simulator,
just in an instant.
And look at the font.
They're all very similar.
You can tell the genre based on these signifiers
that you've got to learn.
Same thing.
We used to make fun of these FPS covers
that all look the same.
But guess what?
You know a first person shooter cover
the second you see it.
We got to learn the tropes of your genre.
Same thing with UI.
When you see the UI, it is like those signifiers
that are in the romance notes.
You gotta learn the tropes and the UI tropes of your genre.
Okay, again, this goes back to coercion.
You're not converting somebody
to try and love that bear book.
You are speaking to the audience
who loves bear shifter romance.
You want people to say when they see your game,
this is the game that I've always wanted.
Thank you for giving this wonderful gift to me.
All right, sorry for that diversion.
Let's get back to steam.
Okay. After all this, did that person buy that game that they bought on the wish that they
added to the wish list? No. No, it was just a wish list. Then they closed the browser and they
standard their day. When do they actually buy? Steam sales. If you have a game on Steam, you
know most sales come in during the big seasonal sales. So I did part two of this, of the study,
and I'm going to dip into how to manage a Steam sale.
So I'm going to get you from how to get wish lists,
how to go from their wish list to get you into the cart,
how to manage your sales pricing so that it's appropriate
for people who are shopping during a sale,
and how to get from the cart to their library,
how to actually get out of the cart and get purchased.
So let's do part one of this.
Okay, so for this next part, I had six participants
and I did a separate study
that was only part of the Halloween sale.
So what I did was I got everybody who was,
game to do another part three of them were from the previous study that's why
they're orange and then I found three new people who would do this screen
share with me and I told them don't we got a Halloween sale coming up don't
look at the store if the steam sale starts don't talk to your friends about
it please don't open steam don't open those wish list emails that you get I
want to see your first impression so they were really good and within the
first two days of the steam sale I got the first impressions of people
shopping on steam during this Halloween sale
So here's how they navigate during a Steam sale.
So they're usually a takeover page on Steam.
They browse it just like they do with the hover,
the mouse catchers where they hold over
and look at the hover, same deal, same rules apply.
The next part is they go and they manage their wishlist.
So they switch over to the wishlist page.
I'm gonna show you an actual video
of somebody browsing their wishlist during a Steam sale.
Here it goes.
So now I'm going to.
By discount.
Did you see? It wasn't price. It was discount.
So these are the usual games.
They are pretty much always on sale.
I can buy this one.
How do you know they've always been on sale?
Because I have the notification on.
And whenever there's a game on sale, I get an email.
And there are some games I already know by memory
that they have been on sale a lot.
For example, this one is on sale every time.
There's a sale every time.
This one has been on sale a few times too.
I added this one recently.
That wasn't a bad thing for him, by the way.
He kind of liked it.
I'm not really sure what's this and what's in my wish list,
but I'll look at it later.
Did you hear that last one?
Not sure why this is on my wishlist.
I'll look at it later.
I noticed over and over again,
people don't remember why they have games on their wishlist.
It was like there were new games to them.
We love as indies, we think,
oh, as soon as somebody wishlists our game,
they just think and pray every night
that the sale gods are gonna come down
and put that favorite game that I just wishlist on sale.
That is not happening.
People have a lot of games on their wishlist.
They don't even remember how they got on there.
So, you have to treat your page during a sale assuming that people who are coming for the
first time, even if they wish-listed your game.
So you want to make it look fresh because I noticed a lot of people when they were going
through their wishlist and they'd look at the page, they wanted to make sure that it wasn't
a dead game. So do stuff to kind of freshen up your page before a Steam sale. That includes
posting a little update alert, theme your capsule to the holiday, put a Santa hat on somebody,
post an announcement. That also will show up in the little banners.
of things that have recently been updated.
Upload a small patch so that you can see that the game was recently updated
and comment in the forums. Make sure the forums are still active. So you really
want to make your page kind of freshen it up for the big sales.
Now, he joked about it. You heard him. He said
this game is always on sale. Well guess what? He knew those games that were always on sale.
He didn't know the game that was not on sale. I don't know the strategy.
You might prefer to do fewer sales or more sales.
I'll get to that later.
It's up to you, your business model.
But I got to tell you, when you do frequent sales,
when every time there's a sale and your game's on sale,
people become familiar with it.
They're not going to have that aspect where they're going to say,
what game is this again?
How did this end up on my Steam page?
Why am I wishlisting this?
You want to be familiar for your users.
Okay, so how to do pricing.
let's look at this. A lot of the power users actually use second-party sites like GGDeals
or SteamDB, and what they're looking for is something called historic low. Those sites
will actually track if your gains dollar amount, it's not based on percentage, whether the dollar
amount has never been reached before, because it kind of adds a fear of missing out element.
So if you time your big Steam sales with the historic lows, you get a double punch. It's
kind of like a multiplier effect, and people are more encouraged to do it.
Also be careful because historical lows are a limited resource.
Once you go to one price point, you can't be a historic low again for that.
So kind of stair-step your price changes downwards.
Don't go too deep too fast because you miss out on a whole bunch of historic lows.
They'll also check your history.
Those third-party sites will actually show these little histograms.
So they will see, how often does this go on sale and are we in a real deep discount?
Because if you're in a deep discount, they're going to buy your game.
So be strategic about this.
All-time lows are a very non-renewable resource.
Okay, what they do now, when they're on Steam page,
they get buyer's fever.
And so their finger's kind of hovering on the buy button.
They're not sure if they're going to buy it,
so they're looking again at your Steam page
to see if they trust your game.
And here's what they do.
They look at a couple key things.
They look at the developer and publisher
to see if they remember them,
if they've noticed them or...
kind of identify the publisher. Of course, people are going to know Xbox Game Studios,
but they want to see if they remember who you are. The other thing they look at is this kind of
more from section. And again, they want to see, did they play another one of your games? So,
if your game's in a series, multiple sequels, they want to see, wait, did I play this game?
Was this part of something else? Remember on the video, she said, oh, it's from the Bear With Me
people. She knew some of those folks. You're just building trust that you're going to stick around.
You are a trustworthy developer.
Now what does this mean?
Stay alive, live to make more than one game.
I know you're focused all on this game,
but if you can't survive to your next one,
or if your first one doesn't sell very well, it's okay.
Your second one will have that boost
of having more reputable coverage
because your other game is gonna show up
in that more like this.
So it's kind of you're building that reputation.
So please don't quit after your first game,
even if it doesn't sell well.
I know it's hard, but please do.
Okay, so then they do this genre relevance evaluation.
Back to the identification, what they'll do, you know how I said you got to match up just
like a romance novel, they're looking for the genre to make sure.
So what they do is they check this bar on the bottom right.
That's a very important bar before they buy.
They'll check this, and what they're doing is this top part where it says,
similar to games you've played.
That helps them identify the genre.
It's just like that guy that said, hey, this is like an FTL.
If that game had an FTL icon in that section, he'd be like, that is perfect.
The other thing that they check,
and this is super duper important,
they look to see their friends recommend it or not.
Because not only do they know the genres that they like,
they know the genres of their friends
and the friends that like certain genres.
So if they see somebody that they trust
who also likes the games they like recommending it,
that is such a bonus.
And if a friend recommends against it,
but they know that that person
has different tastes than them,
they're like, oh, it's okay.
He likes FPSs, I don't like FPSs,
it's okay that he hates this game.
Okay.
Boom.
They found it.
You're a trustworthy dev.
What do they do?
They add it to their cart.
Do they buy it?
Hell no.
They still, after all of that, you are still not clear.
This is the final part.
How do you get out of the cart and into their library?
because it turns out that your Steam cart
is actually a secondary wishlist.
And so what they do is they'll actually stop and say,
okay, I've loaded up my cart for the Steam sale.
I'm gonna take a little break.
I'm gonna go check with my friends.
I wanna see what's gonna happen here.
And so what they do is they step away
and they call all their friends and they say,
I'm thinking of getting this game.
I actually saw this happen.
So one of the participants I was watching, she was considering Sundered.
And what she did was she messaged her friend, who also had a good review for Sundered, and
she in Discord, this is in Discord, she sent him a screenshot of Sundered.
And she said, Hey, I'm thinking of buying this.
And he said this, go for it.
And then she bought it.
Imagine that.
All the marketing that had to be done for this to happen.
Those three magic words, go for it.
I don't know how we sell any games at all.
This is how much it takes to get a game sold.
And that comes to the next part, which is word of mouth.
You need to turn your current customers,
people who've already bought your game,
into advocates for you.
You need to be offering good support, be friendly.
Don't just run once you have their money.
It's ongoing because they're going to be recommending your game the next time there's
a sale and somebody comes to them and says, hey, do you recommend this person's game?
You better hope that they say yes.
They better hope that they say go for it.
Okay, second part, cart problems.
This is kind of out of our hands, but it really matters here.
Okay, we know when a Steam style starts, they get this email that says you got a wish list on an item on sale.
What are you going to do?
This is a very powerful way of doing it, but guess what?
They put the game, they may have put it in there.
I got this comment from one of the participants that I was studying.
I put Grim Dawn franchise in my cart, but forgot to actually purchase it. Major oof.
My god, they didn't actually go back to their Steam page after that cart, after they checked with all their friends.
This is something in the online retail industry called abandoned cart recovery.
When people abandon the cart, they need to be called back to say,
hey, don't forget the sales ending.
Steam does not have abandoned cart recovery.
Let me show you this.
The worldwide, everything like Amazon.
All online retailers estimate that it's like 75% of all people will have stuff left over their cart
and never buy it. This article that I linked below actually said gaming's pretty safe with this.
They only have a 64% abandon rate. Only 64% abandon. Oh my God. But the good news is they
found that if you engage in email marketing and re-engage and say, hey, by the way, sales ending,
you got some items left in the cart. Do you want it? They were able to recover.
10, almost 11% of people were to come back
and actually finish the purchase, 11%.
Now that doesn't sound like much,
but if you go back to your Steam sale,
go back to the last sale,
take whatever you earned in that last Steam sale,
multiply that by 10%, add that on,
that's what you missed out
because Steam does not have abandoned cart recovery.
It is a big thing.
It wouldn't be that much that you would need to do.
If we just had an email that Steam would send out,
let's say, a day before the Steam sale ends, and just says,
hey, you've got something left in your cart.
Do you want to pick up this game?
It's almost there.
There would be a total major oof avoided,
according to that user.
They want this.
They didn't want to miss out on that sale.
Now, next time you have a meeting with Valve,
if you've got one of those behind closed doors,
and they ask for suggestions, say,
please implement an abandoned cart recovery email sequence.
They're going to look at you sideways and say, what?
Explain it to them.
Show them.
Show them what an abandoned card recovery email sequence is.
Hopefully they implement it.
We can't hope.
There's probably some technical reason they can't do it.
I don't know.
But the next best thing that we can do
is plan a big marketing push at the end of a sale.
Make sure that you re-up on your social media,
your email list, say, hey, sale ends tomorrow.
Don't forget to pick up.
If you've got something left in your cart,
don't forget to buy it.
It's a.
It's all we got.
We can only do so much.
Bug valve about it.
Hopefully it fixes this.
Okay, so part five.
How to turn those wishlisters into actual buyers.
Okay, so.
I published a lot of my findings that I just talked to you about on Gamasutra,
and I got a lot of comments, very good comments that said,
well, the way you were doing the screen share and everything,
you're probably influencing them.
That's probably why people didn't buy as much as what you saw.
And this is something called the Hawthorne effect,
which is when somebody watches, a person being watched changes their behavior.
And it dates back to the old factory days.
They wanted to see if they lowered the lights, if it would increase or decrease productivity.
But it was managers who were doing the observation.
So...
Of course you're going to work faster when your manager is watching you.
That's besides the point, but this is how we're going to test this. And what I did was
not another screen share for part three of this study. I did a diary study.
And what a diary study is, is I took seven of the participants,
two of them, those are those orange people,
from the previous studies, and then I found five new people.
And what I did was every week I sent a survey
that had two questions.
What did you buy last week and why?
And what did you wish list last week?
And how did you hear about it?
That's all I asked them.
I sent them in a Google form like this.
And I sent it for three months, starting December 15
and ended just today, March 19.
So I would get these little stories back
because they were like little diary entries.
And they're almost like Hemingway-esque
in their simplicity and their just earnestness.
Seven Days to Die.
This early access game has become a favorite of mine.
This was the 11th copy that I purchased.
This time as a Christmas gift for a friend.
God, you better hope that you get this customer.
She bought 11 copies of this game.
Here's another one.
Monopoly Plus.
I sought after looking up board games
to play with my daughter in another state.
It is a game that I have seen on sale for Humble Bundle.
Man, that one gets me every time I read that one.
So these are the type of comments that I got.
Here's one for this one.
Listen to this.
Demon Crawl.
Saw about it on Discord,
and it looks like something I'd love to play.
Will likely buy it before the end of the sale.
Now, buy it before the end of the sale.
Guess what I did?
I waited till the end of the sale,
way out well after it was over,
and I emailed the guy and I said,
hey, did you get Demon Crawl?
Did you ever buy it?
Nope.
I ended up forgetting about it and realized too late, like a few hours after the sale
ended.
Abandoned cart.
This is what I'm talking about.
We got to get abandoned cart.
Talk to Steve.
Abandoned cart.
Okay.
So again, I did three months of surveys.
That turned out to be 13 surveys.
I observed or got little messages about 229 wishlisted decisions, 278 buying decisions.
That's 507 of those micro stories.
So what I did is I went through and I tagged them based on what they said,
whether they got it from Discord or Steam or a bundle, who told them about the game,
all that stuff. Here's what I found. Here's the research.
Okay, so the top list is all the participants, the seven participants.
Just underneath, I'm listing them in columns. So participant A bought 24 games between
December 15th and March 9th.
Participant D bought 86 games in that three months,
all the way over to participant O, who bought 62 games
during that period.
This is purchase.
This is how many they wish-listed.
So A bought 27, O bought 32, reads like that.
I'm going to break it down based on all the things they did.
Again, these are only purchases and wishlists
during that time period.
Okay, how many, what percentage based on Steam? Because some people played Switch games or they
bought Xbox games. I included those in the survey and I tracked them. So how many of them included
Steam games?
It's a pretty high number, 42%, 53%, 76% of the games that were bought during this time period
were for Steam. I counted anything that was Humble Bundle, even if they get a Steam key from Humble,
as a separate thing, and I'll show that in a minute. You might notice participant L had zero
Steam games. He was boycotting Steam at the beginning, and I was like, I wonder if he's
going to stick to his boycott. He did. He did not buy any Steam games during that three-month period,
so very good on him.
Okay, so how many of these purchases were from Humble Bundle?
Turns out a very high percentage of people get their games from Humble Bundle.
So if you notice, D and K, they have very large inventories of games that they purchased.
That's because they're big buyers of Humble Bundle games.
Fanatical Bundle was another bundle that a lot of people bought off of.
Some people were not bundle buyers, like M&M. They just didn't get any bundles.
Now, let's check social media. So, one of the questions, like, did you buy this game and why?
If they said, oh, I bought it on Twitter, I saw somebody on Twitter tweet about the game,
so I bought it. How many? Nobody. Nobody mentioned that they found a game based on Twitter.
Let's talk about Discord. How many? One person heard about a game on Discord and then bought it.
And then Reddit? One person. One person bought a game because they saw it on Reddit.
Now,
That's kind of strange, but if you remember,
top of the funnel, bottom of the funnel,
I always talk about that stuff.
Nobody, I always say, nobody sees the game
for the first time and then buys it.
That's true, and that's what this study did.
So I looked at the wishlist, I looked at top of the funnel.
How many people wishlisted a game
and claimed that they wishlisted because of Twitter?
So same thing, let's see, three people.
Three people said they saw a game on Twitter,
and so they wishlisted it.
Discord, a little bit higher, six people.
And then Reddit, 12.
Now, participant D loves Reddit.
So he's a very heavy Reddit user, but he was the only one.
And side note, I've found a lot of these people on Reddit.
They just don't shop for games on Reddit.
Okay, what about streamers?
How many people buy games because of streamers?
So let's look at wishlists.
So because of what they saw on like a streamer do it,
bought that, that's not great, but it's something.
How many purchases based on what they saw on a streamer?
Not many, three people see it on purchase.
Really, it's a wish list to purchase conversion. Now, I think part of it might be that they wish
listed it long time ago. So if they may, in my data, they didn't actually say that they bought
it because of watching somebody on YouTube. But I really think wish lists don't straight convert
to purchases based on streamers. Okay, now I've mentioned friends all the time. These are kind of
what
if anybody tagged a friend, if they said,
hey, I have friends who play this,
so I bought it because of that, I did that.
I also counted if they bought a game for a friend,
this will be it.
If they were gifted a game, I tagged that as a friend buy.
So how many games did they buy
because of a friend recommendation?
Let's see.
A pretty high amount.
Some of these participants like L and N,
50% of their games came from friend recommendations.
Friends are very, very important in buying games.
What about wishlists?
Just as high, a third in some cases.
Now, you might notice participant D
does not actually have any friends.
No, he has friends.
I actually asked him, I was like,
yeah, you okay?
Maybe you have friends?
He does, he just doesn't have gamer friends.
All his friends do other activities.
Who knows what they do,
but they don't play games together.
Okay, how many gamers,
how many of these participants bought games at full price?
Zero.
Zero people bought games at full price.
Isn't that astounding?
These people wait for sales.
I know it's not a surprise, but my God,
looking at all those zeros, there's a surprise.
Okay, so what gets people from wishlist to purchase?
How do they actually do it?
I got one of these comments,
because I'm always wondering,
like how do I convert somebody
from being wishlisting it to actually buying it?
And here's this guy.
He said, Stardew Valley, was tempted,
but I have some unfinished business
with one of my Harvest Mootin' games on Wii.
We'll finish that first before buying Stardew Valley.
What? Like, we have to now compete with Wii.
Like, who knows why people buy games?
There's no reason. We just have to basically keep pushing on it, keep pushing on it.
You just have to market all the time because who knows when somebody is going to finish that Wii game?
I don't know what to do. I don't know what to do.
So games have a long life cycle.
Stay alive. Stay alive.
Just whatever may occur.
Okay, so what actually moved the needle after doing all this research?
Okay.
Bundles were the highest percentage of the converted to
actually purchasing something.
Next down was friends.
Now bundles, we get like fractions of a cent in some of those bundles,
so it doesn't quite count.
So the number one thing is friends.
Now.
full price purchases were zero, which means sales actually drive a lot. But I can't quite identify
how many sales came from not being mentioned on friends and bundles. It's kind of like asking
somebody, asking a fish about water. They don't even notice it. A lot of these participants
wishlisted things and bought things just because they were on the Steam front page and all that
kind of stuff. So I think those are the major drivers. But the things we can kind of control
are purchases because of friends and getting your game in bundles.
So here's kind of the top recommendations based on the second round of research.
Make a really good game that people recommend.
Stars around that, that's the most important thing.
People aren't going to recommend your game if it isn't good.
That's why we say start with a good game to market.
Okay.
Develop a plan for word of mouth marketing.
We got to invest in how we get our games shareable, not through social media,
because apparently they don't do it through social media.
Just make sure that friends know, maybe bundle two keys so that somebody
will give a key to a friend, who knows?
But think of ways to do word of mouth marketing.
Put your game on sale a lot.
We know that people only buy it on sale.
I told you that when frequent sales happen,
your game is more front of mind.
And eventually put it in a bundle,
maybe a windowing system.
Eventually you'll end up in a bundle
because that really does drive people to buy your game.
And I guess just wait for people
to finish all their games on Wii.
Who knows? I don't know.
Okay, wrap it up. Let's do this. I keep all this research while I was doing I
kept thinking I'm like, I'm gonna have to present this to a bunch of indies. I'm
gonna have to tell them to like, put their game on sale a lot. I'm gonna have
to tell them to stick to genres. Don't be too crazy. Don't have too many hooks.
Don't be too out there. Just stick to genre conventions. Like, I keep
thinking of that guy, like, why even be indie anymore? It's true. Like, I
wonder about this, but
Here's the thing, this is kind of what I came around to.
Your Steam page, we saw with that woman
who went through the Steam page, it lasts 90 seconds.
They shop for 90 seconds on your store page.
They are gonna forget your store page by the end of it,
but your game will live on.
So this Steam, you can be cheesy and trite
on your Steam page, that's not your art.
Your Steam page is not your art.
And a key thing, I kind of realized this when I heard about this.
So this is Marcel Proust, famous 20th century author,
you know, one of the greatest thinkers we've got in the 20th century.
It turns out, here he is, his first book was something called
Remembrance of Things Past, right? Smart guy.
OK, for Marcel Proust, Le Figaro was the front page.
It was his Steam page, equivalently.
Like, if you wanted to sell 20th century literature to Frenchmen,
this is where you put it.
And he got a bunch of front page reviews for his Remembrance of Things past, right?
Well, they recently had an auction for some of Proust's old letters, and they were going through his letters, and they found out
that Proust actually paid people the equivalent of
$900 in today's dollars to write favorable reviews for him on the front page of the Sleif Agar.
Now, I'm not, Steam, I'm not telling them to buy reviews.
I'm not, if you're Steam, don't kick my games off Steam.
What I'm actually saying is, he hustled.
He hustled.
And he knew that sometimes you have to
really change your policies in order to get your art seen.
And really what Marcel Proust kind of did was,
we don't remember it.
It wasn't until we dug deep into his letters
that we found out that his page was trite
and that his items were bought.
We remember his art, not what he did on Le Figaro.
Nobody remembers what he did on Le Figaro.
So what I'm saying is, just get that hustle, do it.
So he actually actually got his friend
who painted this portrait, name listed off to the left
so I don't butcher the French,
he got him to write one of the reviews.
So use your resources, don't cheat the system,
don't buy reviews, but your store page is not your art.
Separate those two.
Please, your page is not your art.
Be a little bit cliche.
Okay.
I called this talk Empathize with Steam because, I don't know, we look at all these sales charts,
we look at these number of reviews, and we just hate these people that just say nope.
And we kind of hate Steam.
But after watching this and reading stuff like this, a person who wanted to play games
with her daughter in another state, I don't know, I kind of got this feeling.
There's this feeling called sonder, which is basically that says, everybody, every random
passerby actually has a full life.
I thought about that when I did this research,
is every negative review,
they're probably having a bad day or something.
And all those upvotes are probably from somebody else
who's also having a bad day.
And so what I'm telling you is,
if you kind of feel down about doing this stuff,
go do what I did.
Talk to Steam people, not the crazy ones, not the mean ones,
but find people and talk to them.
And don't just treat them like a number,
like, oh, this many upvotes, this many downvotes.
Really, learn your audience.
And I think it's gonna be a real positive feeling for you.
So please do it.
Again, if you want that Steam checklist, go to my website, howtomarketagame.com slash
Steam checklist.
I'll send you a free version of that if you sign up for my newsletter.
If you have questions, this is a weird GDC this year, so I'll answer them on Twitter.
Please do it.
Thank you very much.
I appreciate your time.
Thanks for coming out.
I love you all.
Have a good day.