Hello, my name is Tatiana Villela-Dos Santos.
I'm a game designer and digital artist based in Paris, France.
And I'll give a talk at the GDC this year about my works called Game Design Beyond Screens and Joysticks.
I make games with alternative controllers or as interactive installations.
Sometimes even immersive rooms with performers.
Basically, any game that works with an uncommon interface.
I make most of my games in artist residencies, and then I exhibit them in different places around the world, from galleries to clubs.
Designing with the freedom of a contemporary artist allowed me to develop my own tools and methods to create this specific kind of game,
including in my researches not only the digital part of the experience, but also the ones staged in the physical space.
And especially how to use interfaces to shape players' behavior.
If you are curious about my works, you can have a look at my website, makeburn.fr.
Looking forward to see you all at the GDC.
Bye!