Hello, everyone. My name is Ifrat Shaik and I want to talk a little bit about what can
game designers learn from competitive reality show.
Before I start, I want to acknowledge the land in which I'm speaking to you
is from the traditional territory of many nations,
including the Mississauga of the Credit, the Anishinaabe,
the Chippewa, the Aztec, and the Wendat people,
and is now home to many diverse First Nations, Inuit, and Métis people.
I would also like to acknowledge that Toronto, also known as Toronto,
is covered by Treaty 13 with the Mississauga of the Credit.
So who am I?
My name is Ifat Cheikh.
As I mentioned, I'm an assistant professor
at York University in Canada.
I'm also an experimental game designer.
I'm currently working on games that
are made in non-traditional game engine.
The current one uses Miro, and I made games in Excel as well,
and bots that examine issues around AI ethic.
I am not going to talk about any of those here,
but rather I'm going to draw of my love of the trashier side
of TV, which frankly I do not consider to be trash at all,
and examine the game design of specific reality show,
as I believe that there is a lot we can learn from them.
This to say, not this talk came to be
because I really like Survivor, and I'm
trying to convince more people to watch it.
I should note, I tried to make this talk intro
into a more practical look at this show with the idea that by the end of this talk you will come
up with some idea of how you can use those games to implement in your own design.
But I only have about half an hour so I will probably only whet your appetite and interest
on the topic or just make you think that it's not worth your time. I'm also an academic so
sometimes I can have myself an overcomplicated thing.
So, on August 23rd, 2000, more than 50 million Americans watched the final of the first season
of Survivor, making it a cultural milestone and birthing the age of reality shows. It seems silly
nowadays, but looking back at the popularity of the first few seasons of Survivor,
and later Big Brother, made the participant of this show a youth celebrity,
if only for a very short while, and managed for at least a few years
to dominate the TV landscape until eventually being replaced by Prestige TV.
It is important to note, Survivor was certainly not the first very popular reality show out there.
I want to give credit to the real world, but, and can also be argued that game show also can fit
into the term reality show, and I think some of them, I can think of something like the Crystal
Maze is well worth exploring. So, this to say, reality shows are still being produced.
For one thing, they're cheaper to produce.
While Survivor, at this point, has a huge amount of people working for it,
it's still cheaper than working on a more prestige TV drama.
And a lot of them also share production with other countries, so
the cost of running a reality show is still enormously less than other type of show.
They're still very popular.
While they do not reach the height of popularity and buzz
that they had in the early 2000s,
they're still very successful and a huge part
of the media landscape.
And they're still getting a really high rating.
I think Survivor is still one of the highest rated shows
on Wednesdays.
They proved that they're here to stay.
Survivor has 40 seasons.
Big Brother, the American version, has 22.
The Circle is a huge hit for Netflix.
And then shows like RuPaul's Drag Race, The Great British Air Cuff, etc.
We did not talk about the cultural impact.
For both good and very bad, reality shows have affected our culture.
By all accounts, the image of the former president of the United States,
which helped him get elected, was heavily influenced
by the image constructed by a reality show.
Lastly, there's a lot they can teach us.
Their design can teach us how to improve our own design.
There's a lot of things we can analyze and critique about the shows,
from issues of race, colonialism and gender, to the evolution of strategic gameplay.
For the sake of this talk, I'm going to focus on how competitive reality shows,
which I will describe in the next section, create emerging gameplay,
and how player agency affects the overall thematic game.
I'm going to look at the way the players interact with the system of rules set by the designer of the game,
now they use those to create their own rule and game dynamic.
While those rules of the show do not change that much, the way the player use them and
interact with each other is ever-changing, creating surprising new interaction in narratives.
So let's talk about our competitive...
reality shows first. What do I mean? So there's many genres of reality shows, and their popularity
tends to change over time. From documentaries like shows where there's very little production
interference like The Real World, skill-based competition like Who Paul Drag Race, The Great
British Bake Off, American Idol, etc., which are probably the most popular nowadays,
soap opera style like Docusoft and celebrity reality.
like the Kardashian and the Real Housewife,
which mimic sort of the liberty tries to mimic
the appearance and structure of a soap opera.
Home Improvement Show, which there's
a full channel just for those kinds of show.
Dating show like The Bachelor,
Too Hot to Handle, Marriage on First Sight, etc.
And there's many other genre in it.
I would like to focus on one specific type of reality show,
which I call competitive reality show, which might be a sub-genre.
It's a bit hard to quantify, but those are competitive shows
in which ordinary people compete to win a prize, usually a cash one.
And they have a strong game like elements to them with specific game mechanic, the idea of
entering the magic circle, strategy, procedurally generated contact and etc.
So what are the specific elements of the show? How do we differentiate them from other types of reality genre?
So the first one is the prize. The show will generally involve a large cash prize.
This will not include job offer, collection, etc. but strictly money.
Survivor probably has the largest prize which was a million dollars and I think since 40 was 2 million.
because the amount of hardship they have to deal with and they're offered affect the amount they
get. And I think like the circle is much less. I think it's like 100k. The second element is
ordinary people. The contestants do not have specific skill and are often chosen for personality
and archetype they embody.
And the last thing, which is probably the biggest thing, is immunity,
in which contestants can win the right to be exempt the next time
a contestant might be eliminated from the show.
This allows for strategic gameplay as the players
are not only trying to not lose but also to get immunity.
In my opinion, as I said, this is the element which allows the game to become a complex strategic game
as players are not only trying to win or to lose, but also trying to be safe
and or trying to prevent other players from being safe.
I'm gonna there's a few shows that fit the bill survivor obviously as I mentioned the amazing race big brother the American version
Canadian version not the more international version
the circle
But for the sake of time and keeping the top focus,
I will only focus on two shows, Survivor and The Circle.
For one thing, I'm the most familiar with them.
And while there's a lot to say about Big Brother specifically,
but the two different versions of the show
and my lack of familiarity with it.
American Canadian version, I felt I'm not an expert enough on those shows to talk about them.
I also think there's something fitting in talking about the oldest and the newest show of the genre.
So, level of engagement. You can look at those shows and games with four distinct
level of engagement. The producer, the player, the editor, and the viewer, with each level
separately contributing and helping with the success of the show.
The producer, who act as both the game dungeon master and the game designer,
they are there to design the rule of the game and make sure they are followed,
as well as making sure the production of the show is running smoothly.
I call this category producer, but it includes almost everyone involved
in the overall production of the show, the behind the scene.
That includes survivor, vast medical staff, and the poor person whose job
is to describe what the players in the circle say.
While they are mostly silent, the host acts as their face and reinforcers,
sort of we can look at them as the main dungeon masters,
and their job is to guide the player and make sure that the game is run smoothly
and maintain the illusion of reality in a make-believe situation.
In some cases, like Jeff Probst from Survivor, the host is also the executive
producer and his control is much bigger than other hosts,
and it can even change or modify rules on the fly.
The amount of control the producers have is different from show to show
and reports of producer interference is always part of the conversation
around those shows.
Survivor especially was accused many times of having the production interference
change the outcome of the vote.
This has never been proven.
Big Brother has also been accused and frankly,
the producer interference is a lot more visible there.
There are actually quite a lot of fan theories around producer interference.
which I won't get into.
The second level of engagement is the players.
The players are the people chosen to play the game.
They are the ones who produce the majority of the emerging gameplay content
of the show as they are the folks who are interacting
with the rules set by the producers.
Some of those interactions are amazing and wonderful.
There is wonderful humane moments, there are wonderful strategic elements.
And some of them are extremely unpleasant,
like the contents of being outed as a trans man.
I don't have time to specifically talk about the casting process,
but with a lot of them, players are chosen to fulfill a specific archetype
and are often presented that way.
In a recent TikTok, Kelly Wentworth, a Survivor contestant,
mentioned how her archetype was the farmer's daughter,
and so she was only allowed...
to bring in clothes that fit that archetype.
The next one are the editors.
The players are often filmed 24-7.
And the editor's job is to distill this narrative
into a chunk of about 45 minutes,
depending on the show, which tells the viewer everything
that happened in the span of a few days
and craft a coherent narrative from the footage they have.
The editor have full control to pick and choose how to tell the narrative,
but the narrative is also completely dependent on the player action themselves.
If the players have nothing to show,
even the most interesting editing won't help with crafting an interesting story.
And the last ones are the viewers.
The last level of engagement is the audience itself,
which engage with the show as linear entertainment,
sort of as a spectator in a sport event,
and have no power to control the narrative of the show,
but can engage in participatory action when the need arise.
Example, anything like voicing their opinion on social media,
as well as creating games based on their show.
which I will talk about in a later session.
So how does this mechanic of the game encourage player agency
and create emerging narrative?
How does the intention of the designer and the player
interaction with the game affect the gameplay?
And
So before I give specific example,
I'll talk a little bit about what it means
when I talk about emergent.
This is sort of my definition mixed
with a lot of other definitions.
And some of you might say, oh, this is wrong.
That's OK.
But this is just sort of to put us in the same place.
In the simplest term, emergent is
when the game allows the player to craft their own experience
in the game.
It is the unexpected outcome of player interaction
with the system of rules set by the designer.
Emergent is sort of a buzzword nowadays as game companies are looking more and more into procedural techniques
which will allow them to prolong
player engagement with their product.
The problem with that is that unlike crafted story, emergent stories and systems are not something we necessarily know how to design
and even how to approach it in a way that creates an engaging play experience.
So the single most important act of emergence in Survivor
happened in the first season.
And it defined not just the show, but the genre itself.
Initially, Survivor was billed as the greatest social
experiment on the planet, a show in which
a group of ordinary American are left stranded on an island
that has to build a new society.
Most players took it to heart and while they voted a player every week, those players were
generally the people who could not handle the physical and social aspect of the game.
It was Richard Hatch, the eventual winner, who understood something that not even the producer
did. Survivor is not a social experiment about who can survive in the wilderness, rather it is a
complex strategic game and in order to win you need to deploy game theory strategy like the
prisoner's dilemma and the Nash equilibrium.
On day 10, he formed a plan which led to his victory.
He formed a voting bloc or an alliance with three other members of his tribe.
For the rest of the season, the four-person alliance dominated the game,
voting out everyone else until there were only four left.
At this point, the alliance was shattered and the game became an individual game.
And while this character constantly evolves since then,
the concept of alliance become a pivotal part of Survivor
and other competitive show like Big Brother
and The Amazing Race.
So there are other reasons that season was a resounding success.
It was Richard's hatch strategy that
cemented Survivor's success in its culture influence.
It's also.
from its core gameplay loop, creating an alliance
and understanding which path you need to follow in order
to win the game.
And it was probably the main factor in survival longevity
as it made the game interesting.
Another sort of emergent thing that actually caused
a new mechanic to be introduced was in, I believe,
season 9, which was Palau.
And in this case, one of the tribes, the Ulaan tribe, just couldn't win.
They basically lost every immunity challenge in the game and one by one they were just decimated
until there was only one tribe member left, Stephanie La Grossa.
And because there was no merge, because there was just nothing left of that tribe,
Stephanie had to stay one full day at the island by herself, surviving by herself, and
sort of shining a new light on the hardship of the setting.
And it was such a poignant TV moment that the producers saw that and actually sort of introduced,
they never said it to us, but they did, introduced a new mechanic which is the Exile Island in which
players have to stay by themselves alone on an island for a day.
And that mechanic already was introduced in the next episode and sort of became kind of a
main mechanic of the game for at least a few more seasons until it became kind of redundant.
But yeah, that's a really good example of how that mechanic
how the player and what happens in the game can lead to new mechanics.
There's also, there's countless other examples, this is just a few of them.
In the circle, again, fairly new shows, so we don't really have that many examples.
But we knew that the idea of the catfish mechanic, where a player can play as different people and not as themselves,
was a huge success, at least in my opinion, when two players who play as catfish go on a date, a virtual date.
So Alex was playing...
as Adam. Alex was married, a married man, a straight married man. He was married, he played
as Adam, like a very handsome single dude, and he had the ability to go on a dinner date with one of
the players, and he chose Rebecca because they sort of had a connection. Rebecca was also a
catfish, it was actually Seabird who was Rebecca's boyfriend.
So basically there was a bunch of awkward flirtation
and some really inappropriate questions
and they sort of started this fake relationship.
Again, if you have seen the circle,
they can't see each other.
And it turns to show Rebecca pretended
to be completely crazy over Adam,
while Adam accurately tries to keep the relationship going.
Adam was, um, was Alex was cut from the game.
Sibran actually was a finalist.
But, um, these two guys going on a date,
these two, uh, not single guys going on a date,
both playing totally different characters,
was just, there was TV gold, frankly.
So, a little development of the gameplay.
So I want to talk a little bit about the development of gameplay strategy
from setting up the alliance in season one of Survivor
to the far more complex strategy deployed today in most of those games
like Shift and Alliance, etc.
The simple mechanic and the player interaction means that the strategy of the games evolved over the years.
And I wanted to give a quick overview of those.
I should note that most of this is based on Survivor and a bit of Big Brother, as the circle is still fairly new,
but I won't be surprised if it follows the same trajectory.
This to say, I might be completely wrong.
So one thing to note is the way the game is played in season one really affects the way in which the
game will be perceived in later season. In season one nobody knows what to do and the overall theme
of the game will be determined. So in season one of Survivor Richard Hatch forming an alliance
submitted the game as a strategic game that is based around alliances and making alliances and
breaking them.
With The Circle, for example, Joey's niceness and his friendship with Siobhan
sort of made The Circle a far more wholesome game, and far more, I would say, soft games.
And while the game is actually fairly different in international version,
even today when you watch season two of The Circle, that particular strategy of being
genuine and nice continues, even if there's more complex strategies.
By season two, strategies are more refined, players make less mistakes, but there's still
a few cases that will show future players what not to do.
So in Survivor, for example, Colby chose Tina and not a goat, which was Keith.
I won't talk exactly what the goat dynamic is.
And in the circle, for example, the use of Jack kind of...
who was playing Emily, a very sweet sorority girl,
failed the makeup challenge and sort of outed himself
as a catfish.
And more fish are introduced, and it's usually
a much better season.
Season three, the mechanical strategy are more refined and dominant strategy is emerging.
And this is where the game kind of gets a bit stale.
And so at this point, new twists are introduced in order to counter it.
So in season three of Survivor, the dominant strategy at this point was begonning, which is
that one strong tribe will vote out, one bigger tribe will vote out the smaller tribe.
And so they had to
introduce a new mechanic, which is the tribe swap, which is
nowadays a main mechanic in the game, which will make players
basically have more shifting alliance and not just be only
with the alliance with the original tribe.
By season four, new strategies are introduced, probably as a twist on the dominant strategy.
This was very apparent in season four of Survivor, where the smaller tribe managed to basically
vote out the bigger tribe by having two members of the bigger tribe join them as an alliance.
In season one, twists are more common,
strategies getting more complex,
but new dominant strategies start to emerge.
So in season five of Survivor,
there was the strategy of begonning still exists,
but also a new strategy emerged, which was the goat,
which is basically chosen the weaker player
to sit with you at the end,
so you will definitely vote, get the vote.
So it's important to note a little bit
of a dominant strategy.
Dominant strategy is the optimal move for an individual regarding how the other player acts.
And they will quickly make your game stale and so they need to be neutralized as fast as you can.
In reality show it's often done by adding a twist. In Survivor it was the tribe swap and then
idols and many others. There's Circus Season 2 introduced the Joker
and Big Brother is filled with them.
The dominant side can also create uncomfortable and often ugly situations
when players are too observed in the reality created in the game
to understand the repercussions of their behavior.
The most planted example was season 39 of Survivor,
where the strategy was for the big player to be kept over the strong player
so the player in the middle will have greater chance to win.
which is a fairly regular strategy in both Survivor and Big Brother,
but it doesn't make the most interesting of games.
In this case, it means keeping the player that was accused of sexual harassment
over a strong player who happened to be the person who was harassed.
So a weak player was kept in the game despite actions that went beyond strategic
just because everyone knows they can win against him.
The person who accused him was voted out because she was a strong strategic player.
Reality show and game.
So can those show work as more interactive game?
The answer is both yes and no.
The answer is yes, but we have to look what fans have done.
Sorry.
Rather, basically, Survivor does have an official release,
a video game or interactive game.
I think there's two of them.
that follows the original mechanic of the game.
It's very, very bad.
It's available to play on, I believe, archive.org.
I post a link at the end.
And so this was an example, but it didn't work.
But it doesn't mean that the mechanics of Survivor
cannot work in those order circles, stuff like that.
But we want to look at what the fans have done.
So some examples are, for example,
Survivor Alexa, which was a fan, Alaska, sorry,
a fanfic that used dice to determine
the result of each vote.
Survivor Edging, which slightly unfortunate name,
but it's an editing metagame in which player
analyzed the editing of the show to determine the result.
the winner. There's a few survivor LARPs or tabletop RPGs like Survivor College Edition
and Survivor Quarantine which allow players to play online, usually in Zoom version of Survivor,
and there's videos of those online, you can watch them. And there's the Circle Discord which is a
LARP tabletop RPG that is played on Discord. So what can we learn from all of this?
So first of all, pay attention to your player,
and is there the one who's going to make and break your game?
And it's especially important in reality show,
as the casting really changes how the game is every season.
Because the rules don't change that much.
We can trace the way in which strategy is evolved in these games,
which can be very useful when looking at games with strong strategic elements
of tempo competition of sort.
Dominant strategy will be introduced.
Some ways in which the show tried to come to them,
for example, in the circle,
because players, especially catfish players,
can just coast and just like...
be nice. The producer actually used the weekly mini-games, which are usually fairly non-sickle,
to out one of the catfish players who did not prepare well for being a catfish.
with their own makeup.
This will mean that next time players who are catfishing
will have to make sure they're really prepared.
In Survivor, the dominant strategy of begonning,
I mentioned this before, was sort of twisted
by having the tribe swap, and so making
alliances that are more dynamic.
Four, if the mechanic can only be countered by one dominant strategy, then remove it from the game.
Edge of extinction in Survivor, a. when losing players are sent to another island and have the chance to come back to the game,
really has one way for the player to win, by giving up immunity in the last try or cancel.
And so by the second time this strategy appeared, the players themselves really disliked it and
basically the mechanic was cancelled.
Five, just because a mechanic was successful or unsuccessful in one season
doesn't mean the dynamic in the next season will be the same.
One world in Survivor was a great idea, but the players in the season were so awful that the plan didn't work.
XR Island was a great concept, but it ran its course fairly quickly.
Six, a very good mechanic will allow strategy to become complex and the game to not be stangled.
Seven, simplicity is key for emergent but messy game can work if the overall gameplay
compensates for the messiness.
Big Brother and Survivor are very messy with a lot of useless twists, but if the contenders
are interesting and there's enough interesting strategy, you'll be forgiven.
Survivor Fiji has the worst twist in the game, but since the player were interested in it
and the gameplay was good, it's not a bad season despite being so messy.
Eight, it doesn't matter if the gameplay is good, if the player are bad, the game is no longer enjoyable.
Survivor World Apart had pretty good strategy and gameplay, but everyone involved was so helpful
that it became an unpleasant viewing experience.
The games are often unfair, but if the narrative is well constructed,
it's worth it.
the player will forgive you.
For example, no player in the circle
often does not have a chance to win,
and luck plays a big role in Survivor.
Give the player 10.
Give the player freedom, but make sure
that you still have control without being obvious about it.
Adding twists to the game or new mechanic
is a way to make sure you're still in control
of the overall gameplay.
The idol in Survivor is a good example.
giving a player enough freedom how to use it,
but you're the one who decides where it is
and how many there will be in the game.
A little bit harder in the circle
because there's only two seasons.
And 11, moderation is important.
Something really bad thing will happen,
and you need to anticipate them and stop them.
The method of season 13 of Survivor
would have been maybe not so awful
if the producer would have kicked out
them the first time.
in a properly touch female players.
Okay, before I finish, just a bunch of links.
This is some of the stuff I use
or some of the connection,
some of the videos and stuff I looked at.
Once you have the slides, you can check the link.
And thank you very much.
If you have any questions, I will be in the Q&A after and this is all my information where
you can find me on social media or the internet.