There's Markus. So my history, I've been working on software projects for about 25 years.
Initially, like multimedia, CD-ROMs and websites.
And then a couple of friends of mine started a company called Sulake, where I joined to make Hubble Hotel for about 10 years.
I was also the lead designer for Virtual Magic Kingdom for Disney in that company.
Then started my own startup in London called Neki Lab where I made 3D printed toys and games.
After that moved back to Helsinki to work on next games where I've been
working as an executive producer and a game designer.
My name is Markus Montola.
I've been working on location-based games for 15
years.
In 2009, we wrote a book and published a book called
Pervasive Games, Theory and Design, because we already
knew how to design this kind of stuff.
Then iPhone happened, and the playbook was rewritten.
I was working on the first mobile location-based MMO
Shadows at least, and after that, I've been working on
different mobile gaming startups in
Helsinki since then.
Well, so today's topics.
So we're basically going to talk about how we made the
original source of gameplay for the game.
And to get you started, we're going to first basically
explain what the game is.
So how many of you have actually played it?
Okay, quite a few. Awesome.
But for the rest of you, to give some context,
then we're going to be talking about the prototyping and pre-production research
and things that we did to really figure out what the game was that we wanted to build
and then about some of the designs that we actually landed on.
So Walking Dead Our World, it's a location-based game.
It's a single shard MMO, world scale,
where every single one of the players is in the same...
reality.
Same to same missions, you can persist things on the map so you can actually put that stuff
down, other people will see it.
And you basically play the game by going to these missions that you see around you, kill
the walkers, get some collectibles, and become more powerful to go into even harder missions.
And this being based on the TV series, it features a lot of the characters from the TV series as collectibles.
So you can actually find and play with the actual show cast and get them to be more powerful and help you in the missions as well as collecting weapons that you can use yourself.
And when you go to the missions, it kind of looks like this.
So here I'm with Carl shooting some zombies.
You can use AR if your phone is compatible.
So they actually like do real world human scale AR things, which is really cool.
Last but not least, we do a guild system where each one of the players is pushed into a guild very early on during the game where you can chat.
But they also have these task boards where you start to complete these tasks together collaboratively with the rest of the guild and unlock some of the best rewards and then get progressively harder challenges as a group to complete.
And this actually turned out to be a lot more successful than we thought it would.
Where for me as a game designer, basically I've been reading some of the feedback we've been getting on this particular feature.
And people are telling us crazy stuff like somebody is biking 30 kilometers every freaking day
to complete more missions to actually be able to help the guild advance in the tasks.
And a lot of people actually telling that they never quite felt this deeply about collaborative social gameplay in any of the games that they've played before.
Which I think is a really cool achievement for me as a game designer to actually be able to pull it off in a small mobile game.
So how did we end up on this and creating a Walking Dead game in the first place?
So the previous game we made was called The Walking Dead Domain's Land, which is a tactical
kind of like turn-based shooter. Looks a bit like maybe XCOM but super simplified for mobile.
And we featured similar elements where you were collecting the show cast, you made teams of three,
went into missions and like of different types like solve little puzzles with these guys.
And we were really happy about how this game turned out.
And AMC seemed to really enjoy us as well and like the game.
And simultaneously, the Walking Dead as TV series
is still doing incredibly well.
So back when we were starting the project,
we were looking at the show and figured that like,
the brand has some true longevity.
And AMC was quite happy with us,
so we figured it's kind of like a no-brainer
to make another game with those guys.
And at Next, when we start working on new projects, one of the things we really want to do is figure out gameplay mechanics in the games that make sense from the brand perspective.
So we primarily do games based on IPs, and now that we were creating a new game for The Walking Dead, we wanted to figure out what would be a logical combination for that brand.
And many of the viewers of the show actually like were telling us that they have this core fantasy of like really thinking what they would do if the zombie infestation actually happened.
So we figured that like, let's maybe try to prototype location based gaming and see if that works, because it's a really good brand fit actually, like being able to really put you in the situation where like now you're alone, you need to get better weapons, better teams to be able to survive the zombies.
Now, this being the beginning of the project, we kind of figured,
OK, let's actually look at location-based gaming, what's
been done in the genre before, to understand it better.
But also come up with a really live in the present and plan
for the launch, where you need to come up
with a feature set that's actually
doable in high quality during the production,
which has to be also really competitive when
the game goes out.
So I think one of the big problems is when you have a production schedule of a couple of years,
you need to figure out a set of features and gameplay that's going to be competitive and
compelling to the players when you actually ship the game when the market's already changed to
something different. So what can we learn from the past? Shadow Cities is like where you will
actually look into multiple games.
Including Shadow Cities, one of the really early ones that Marcos had made back in the day.
And the gameplay basically was that you could build resource production buildings on the map,
become more powerful, build teleports that allowed people to cooperate and travel the world.
Super interesting. But also featured really brutal PvP, where when you logged in,
you could see your surroundings, but all the other players immediately as well.
And if they weren't powerful, you just got ganked immediately.
And that was kind of really cool if you were the most powerful kid on the block.
But many weren't.
So the location where you logged in and what time of the day really mattered.
Because you started to learn these patterns of where the other powerful players were.
That's the areas to actually avoid due to some of the other players being there.
Pokémon Go had just come out, so it was in the early stages of a lot of people trying to play the game.
And this used a fundamentally different design from what Shadow Cities had done back in the day.
In Pokémon, one of the things compared to Shadow Cities is that Shadow Cities gives you perfect information as a player immediately.
So everything on the map was immediately interactable and you could see it.
In Pokemon, they actually hide the vast majority of the content,
and they want to incentivize you to move to be able to play the game,
so you find the things on the world,
and you could really not play without moving at all.
Some of the content was obviously visible,
so if you wanted to get more Pokeballs,
you'd need to go to the PokeStops you did see somewhere around in your neighborhood.
And in order to access a gym,
it's very likely that you again needed to move,
because they've been so sparsely...
placed in the world that it was quite unlikely there was anything next to you.
And with Pokémon, one of the other things I got asked a lot in the early stages of the project,
like how do we replicate this level of success? Or I think the primary reason why Pokémon is so
successful is, again, simply the fact that the activities the players do in the game is an
excellent, like, real brand fit that people were expecting to make in the game.
So if you see the animated series ever, you're going to expect it.
Yeah, I'm going to walk around the world and throw balls at the Pokemon and collect them.
And this is exactly what you do in the game.
So the mental model that people had in their heads before they started playing
perfectly matched the gameplay that they actually got when they started playing the game.
So the hard thing when you start making a location-based
game is that there are not really that many
location-based games.
And especially, there are not that many successful
So when we started, we knew that we would be, again, into
a very exciting and challenging endeavor where we
would need to figure out a lot of basic
stuff from the get-go.
The thing is that usually when you see people playing mobile
games, the play pattern is something like this.
You're somewhere, and then you play there for two seconds,
and then you go somewhere else.
Most mobile games are not really mobile.
Location-based games are actually mobile.
So we had to face all these kind of different play
patterns that players might have.
We had to figure out from the design angle, again, based on
Shadow Cities, based on Pokemon Go, based on other
games, how would players maybe possibly use this game?
This would be me.
Most of the time, I'm a commuter player.
So if I'm at work, if I'm at home, if I'm at a games
conference, if I'm in the bus, that's when I play.
This is one of our key use cases.
But we have to also figure, how is this game going to work
for people who walk their dogs for one hour every day?
And how are we going to keep it balanced for them?
Some people like to jog a lot.
They like to play real-world games while they're jogging.
We don't necessarily approve, but this is something they
will anyway do, so we have to figure out how
to deal with it.
Something we learned once we actually had launched the game,
we had a lot of tram riders.
Trams move a little bit slower than buses, so they are
perfect for playing The Walking Dead Our World.
You're sitting in the tram, you're grinding a mission, and
the reason why you're sitting in the tram is that you're
trying to grind as efficiently as you can.
We had half of our team sitting in the tram one week
when we were in the soft launch trying to
optimize on a mission.
The key point you have to decide is.
Do you want the players to move in order to play, or do you want them to play while they're already on the move?
This is how Helsinki looks like.
Next Games is based on Helsinki.
And you can see the little dots on the map.
They are the Google POIs where we spawn all our content.
And when you're looking at this kind of map and when
you're working in this kind of a city, you get all these
exciting ideas about how this kind of a game could work.
Maybe you go to a gas station to get some gas, and then you
go to, I don't know, to the riverfront to get some fish,
and then you craft something.
And that's, of course, a very good way of doing a game if
you make a full collector game, like, for
instance, Pokemon.
But we knew that the brand of The Walking Dead is not about
assembling collections.
It's about something else.
It's about survival and fighting and that kind of
stuff. So we couldn't really do that.
And the reality is that much of the map looks like this.
This is Kansas in our world.
You can, again, see the POIs on the few roads
that you have there.
We couldn't really afford to have the fantasy of going to the gas station to get some gas,
because let's face it, we are in the mobile free-to-play market, and mobile free-to-play
market is about...
about allowing players to generate value
through going through core loop,
iterating over the core loop again and again.
And if you're in this business,
you have to be able to get the player
into the core loop and out of the core loop
and again into the core loop
multiple times during their first session,
no matter where they start.
And since we were not doing a full collector,
we had to make sure that our game
was always playable everywhere
and it would be nice and exciting experience
no matter where you were.
Of course, you can add that kind of frills later, but fundamentally we had to be a core loop game.
So, we went back to the basic.
Let's forget about the location for a moment and let's focus on how to make a really great mobile game.
Like many other designers, we got highly inspired by the self-determination theory of motivation.
If you provide players with competence, if you provide players with autonomy, and if
you provide players with relatedness, then they will be highly motivated to play your
game.
This is one very good recipe for a very good game.
Especially we identified the relatedness as a key USP that we could reach in the game.
Other location-based games are also social, but we wanted to focus on guild play.
We wanted to focus on the inclined social, because that is very much what the series
is also about.
It's about pulling together, not apart, as Rick Grimes would say.
So based on this round work, we started shaping up these core design pillars.
Play everywhere.
Wherever you log in for the first time, wherever you log
in for the first time on every day, you will get a full and
interesting complete session in there.
It's always worth opening the game in the new location.
There needs to be enough discovery that I want to see
what's surrounding me.
We wanted to support couch play.
We wanted to make a little bit more traditional game.
So we wanted to make sure that people who would be mostly
playing at home and at work would have a nice experience
nevertheless.
In our philosophy, getting a better location, moving
around, it gives you a nice opportunity.
It gives you better optimal situations, but
it's never mandatory.
We wanted to focus on the strong collaborative social
mechanics.
And finally, we wanted to be true to the Walking Dead TV
series.
So now we have some core pillars,
and we should start to get thinking about,
like, how do we approach these?
How do we validate these ideas?
And how do we prototype them?
And Sulka is going to tell you a lot more about that.
All right, so we kind of figured out that there's five big questions that we needed to answer before we knew exactly what we wanted to build.
With the core loop, what were the constraints of how you actually can create missions that are meaningful on the map that people will be interacting with?
And does the locational context bring something to the gameplay?
Like, what are the things that you can do?
And are there some must not do's that we needed to take into account?
We figured that this is a map and with geography there might be really interesting opportunities to create area-based gameplay.
And with being able to place things on the map, we knew from Shadow Cities that this is a good opportunity,
but we needed to figure out what is the gameplay that we would be doing within the context of this game.
For the social gameplay, we wanted to try two different ways of adding social into the game.
One would be on-location social, so that you'd actually need to be interacting with the other players
or the content that people have been placed on the map.
But also, could we do a meta game on the social level that would be played through the on-location missions,
but you still progress things on the meta level.
Dan Cook has this really fantastic iteration, like illustration file actually iterated on the games.
So the way we think about this is early on in the creative process, you're going through these
cycles where you want to add value and not try new things, but you need to be able to identify
what's valuable and cull away all the all the things you are trying that don't actually
ultimately add value to the players of your game.
For the prototyping, the core cycle that we looked into that we wanted to do with each one of the prototypes is
gather ideas and research, design the gameplay mechanics that we wanted to implement into the test,
then build and really do the testing, and evaluate the results to see if this was something that we wanted to put into the game itself.
And I think we ended up doing something like dozens and dozens of iterations ultimately on different features.
I started basically just using paper. Paper is really fast.
I recommend actually using like wooden tokens, whatever it takes, to figure out the initial ideas, because this is really cheap.
But we pretty quickly got into the actual questions.
First being with the core loop, is there something like constraints that the on-location gameplay puts into how you do gameplay in the game?
So the first prototype basically looks really simple.
We took assets from the previous Walking Dead game that we had done.
So the workers actually looked really weird because the perspective was different.
You could just tap on them to kill them, like mega simple first-person mechanics.
We figured that this might be a good fit.
Put some missions on the map where you just could collect more weapons and get some bullets.
And we already got like from this really simple set of super interesting findings.
Where firstly the first person shooter looked promising so we decided okay let's keep on iterating on this.
But what really fascinated me was that there we again proved that there's no magic circle the location-based game.
So when I was playing the missions and like while I was brewing coffee for myself,
waiting for the kids to break off from bed for me to take them to school,
the gameplay experience was fundamentally different from when I was playing the same missions,
walking toward lunch with my friends, where if anything like on the road took longer than
something like 10 to 15 seconds, everybody else needed to actually stop and wait for me.
And that was socially really awkward.
So we kind of figured that like anything that we put onto the map itself,
the interaction speed needs to be really, really fast.
You need to be able to complete those missions and interactions like in seconds.
So the very good kind of like, OK, like this looks promising,
but we can continue on this.
But let's aim to keep things simple.
With the missions, we did actually a couple of different iterations.
Again, we thought that maybe we can add depth to the individual missions
if the gameplay here is really...
It's simple by like allowing people to see perfect information about what's inside the
mission versus imperfect information and make different type of decisions over like what's
the gear that you're going to be taking into the mission like do you need to come up with
a plan.
And turns out actually the mission version where you got the perfect information made people optimize their gear so much to the point where they actually kind of like this analysis paralysis of like overthinking what they need to do, which turned out to be a really bad idea.
So we kind of figured that like, okay, less thinking is actually better.
Like, let's make sure that the interaction again is really fast and people don't need to think about things when they go into the missions.
The other, like one of the actually really big ones is the players immediately started asking for a shared reality.
So the first prototypes just randomly put stuff onto the map and you couldn't actually play with your friends
because when you went walking with your buddies onto the world, both of you saw random points on the map.
So I saw something really desirable and like told, okay, let's go to that direction to pick up that mission because I really want to play it.
My friend would say, actually, that, like, no, like, I'm seeing the same, like, whole mission the other direction, and that was really awkward.
So we need to realize that we actually have to create the system to make sure that all the players share the same content, shared reality on the map itself.
And which brought us to starting to iterate on a deterministic procedural content generator
that produces the same results across the board for each one of the players.
And we're taking the Google POI data with prominence information that's really important
that we're using to spawn the map to the players in a way that actually where the players see the
exact same things. It took many, many iterations to actually get this right and produce the
desired gameplay patterns.
The way we're using the prominence is Google actually tells us what are the most important points in the world
and we can place some of the more important content that players are most likely to want to play
in points that they're the most likely to visit during their commute during the day.
Continuing on to the next question, so with the core loop we wanted to know about the area-placed gameplay mechanics.
So I figured that Travelling Salesman is a really nice NP-hard problem that you can probably gamify in this context.
And so we added this, like, with the missions, we figured out, okay, like, the heroes, you can take them, they have movement points,
so you go through multiple missions to come up with these chains that became progressively harder,
but you got better loot, and, like, this was a disaster.
So players immediately lost immersion when they saw the 2D map versus actually the, like, the map they projected you.
And mixing on location play and the 2D map turned out to be incredibly confusing.
So vast majority of people kind of like not only lost immersion,
they couldn't quite figure out where they were, where the heroes were,
and like they just like lost, like they just couldn't cope with them
with the information they were seeing.
So we figured, okay, like this is going to be way too complicated for a loop
and we just decided to kill this.
The other prototype we did with this is we split the world into a Voronoi graph, a very fancy way of actually taking any area and splitting it into places or smaller areas.
You could capture the areas by playing a couple of missions and you got better loot if you progressively played more in the same areas.
And again, like completely disastrous results were way too complicated to be the core loop activity.
And also secondly, like this felt psychologically wrong where we have this mental model of the
world where we kind of think where the natural boundaries of areas lie. And the people are like
really objected to us splitting the world into areas that didn't really correlate with anything
that they had used to actually see in the world.
Or we chose to kill this partially because this was kind of an unsolvable problem.
Or if your players have a certain way of thinking about the world,
it's very unlikely that you can actually solve something like that in a games project.
So I'm sure a mapping company might be able to do something with areas and natural boundaries
that conflicts with how people see the world.
But in the scope of the project, we just could not have been able to solve this.
With the player-generated content of the map, the first prototype we did here is a lot just very simply put treasure generators on the map, get resources, do appointments, super super simple.
And building stuff on the map felt really good. Being able to see stuff like next to my home was very powerful, but not being able to access the buildings where I weren't there felt really really bad, like super bad.
So the overall player sentiment was that needing to figure out where to place stuff in the world,
especially when you were potentially like, should it be next to your home or next to your office?
And maybe you were commuting through a daycare to drop off your kid,
and figuring out what the optimal pattern for place in the buildings would be,
took some of the bad aspects of people needing to think about their daily routines in the context of the game
in a way that made the decision process way too complicated.
The verdict was that we wanted to retry the building,
but in some completely different form that didn't have the boundary,
like the limitations of how you access this.
So for the social gameplay, we actually decided to take the idea of the buildings
and build a collaborative gameplay on location mechanic out of it.
The concept was safe havens, so I did mission types for like admissions
where you can rescue survivors from the walkers.
And build buildings like safe havens for these people to take into to get loot.
And they actually like this, firstly the rescuing felt really good,
very much aligning with the brand. So you can be the hero of rescue people from the walkers.
But also the fact that you can now get the sea buildings from other players
really like made the world feel alive.
And the fact that we turned it into a collaborative play
where you were leveling buildings together
and it didn't really matter where you dropped the survivors
into suddenly turned the entire feature around
and made it feel really good.
So we actually figured that we need to turn this into,
it continued to writing and turn it into a real feature.
We also thought that we would do cooperative missions on the map,
where players would be able to drop stuff on the map and play things together.
So we made a simple prototype on this lure thing,
where you could jump in and play missions.
And this turned out to be pretty disastrous as well,
where the density of players at any given point in the world
is actually something that's incredibly difficult to predict.
And these missions that we built were fantastically fun when you had five of your friends participating in when you play in them.
But immediately when you got more, we actually turned this into accidental arrival good where players started to feel that the other people, like too many people playing the missions, took the nice easy missions away from them.
And it became a race on who gets to complete the missions first so that you could play.
And we kind of understood that if we want to do anything that you do cooperatively with the other players,
we would have needed to go to the drawing table and figure out a completely new way of approaching this problem.
So we decided to kill this for now.
We might do something with this later, but not now.
So social. So lastly, the collaborative metagame gameplay with the location-based.
So we got this idea that let's add show locations from the show into the game,
where like say Terminus and so you'd get some couch play missions if you unlock these by completing missions on the map.
Say kill 100 walkers in one of the missions and the place opens,
so you can play some missions like no matter where you are.
And do this collaboratively with your guild.
And the result here was actually like we...
This was unexpectedly fun.
So suddenly the progress bars that you got at the end of each one of the missions
turned to be the most fun thing in the entire game.
Much more fun than like any of the collecting mechanics,
like any of the other like finding new things.
So we kind of felt that like this has to be something that we expand very significantly
in the like and make something much much better out of it.
And at this point we kind of felt that we had our five answers.
For the on-location gameplay we were happy with the first person shooter and figured that we need
to keep this incredibly simple for the core loop on the map to actually be something that people
want to engage with. The area-based gameplay was deemed to be not the fit for the product
and the player generated content was turned into a social feature rather than something that
people would be doing as part of the core loop by themselves.
The on-location social gameplay was deemed to be something that we should work on eventually,
but it was too complicated for us to figure given the scheduled project.
And the social metagame driven by location was deemed to be so beautifully nice,
and people loved it, that we decided that this has to become a really good, large feature in the game.
And Markus is going to now talk about a bit more of what we actually did.
So as Sulke described, we figured all these things that
don't work.
And that's when our pre-production ended and we
shifted into the production, trying to figure out like,
OK, we're going to do a game now.
And the game has to stay together and be engaging and
nice and fun and fulfill all the goals.
So let's see what we did.
We did what we like to call a bite-sized FPS.
So every session is pretty simple.
First, you log in and you have a look around.
You maybe collect some stuff around you.
You look around at the fights around you, and you pick a
fight.
You shoot walkers for 15 seconds.
In this video, the player is rescuing a
survivor from walkers.
And when I say you shoot zombies for 15 seconds, I
really mean like 15 seconds.
And that often includes the loading times.
We really wanted this to be short and
snappy and bite-sized.
You get some stuff, and then you use that stuff to upgrade.
You log in, you have a look around, you collect stuff, you
pick a fight, you shoot for 15 seconds, you upgrade.
That's really simple.
We wanted to make sure that you could do this everywhere.
We wanted to make sure that you would see nice things
around you while you do this.
We wanted to make sure that every time you did this, there
would be stuff to play, stuff to collect.
We didn't want to ever have any failure sessions when there
would be nothing to collect.
And our collaboration with the Google Maps has guaranteed
that we can actually do this.
They give us really nice points of interest everywhere,
except for some designated no-play areas, like air
strips, where we don't want players running around.
Upgrading is quite simple.
We were doing so many novel things in this process
that we wanted to make sure that at least something
would be tried and true,
and we wouldn't need to figure it all out.
So basically, you collect weapons, you collect heroes,
and you collect some other items from the series,
and then you level them up,
just as if you were playing Clash Royale.
We want the players to unite with other players.
So in the end of the tutorial,
you will be offered one guild to join.
And the choice is basically, join this guild or search more.
In The Walking Dead No Man's Land, we have learned already at Next Games
that this is the best way we can sort of encourage you to join a guild.
Give you one recommendation, zero decision making anxiety, and join or don't.
We actually intend to be even more aggressive about it in future.
We're actually thinking about forcing players into guild.
Consequently...
90% of our daily active users are in guilds.
And we've learned that the business value in retention
monetization in all respects, that the guilded players are so
much more valuable for us than the other players, that we
don't really lose anything if players who don't want to join
a guild leave our game.
Scavenging is also a big part of The Walking Dead.
And we wanted it to be a big part of our core loop as well.
So.
Every time you log in, you can see some resource crates around you where you can collect things
like energy, you can collect grenades, and first aid kits.
Some free-to-play games decided to make these kind of resources extremely scarce.
They want you to have that one, I don't know, lollipop hammer that you will treasure looking
for the impossible mission.
We wanted to do this in a completely opposite fashion.
In our game, you get consumables all the time.
However, the caps are very low, so you need to also spend them or you end up wasting them.
This creates a loop where you're actually constantly spending consumables, constantly getting consumables,
and sometimes you actually do run out, and that's the monetization point.
But if you want to just, like, if you just walk 100 meters, you will get some more.
So even though it's a pinch, it's not that kind of pinch as we usually think of it in free-to-play games.
So let's look at our core loop.
You log in somewhere. You look around. You will scavenge.
The consumables.
You will take the consumables and spend them
in different kinds of fights.
You will gain cards and coins and survivors.
You take the survivors into safe houses
to get even more cards.
And then you use the cards and coins to upgrade your things.
Rinse and repeat as many times as you like.
So we were not entirely satisfied with this core loop at this point.
It felt a little bit dull.
The players kept requesting all kinds of discovery.
They wanted to really go to that gas station and get some gas.
And we were like, we're a little bit short of resources
and we don't want to do that big an investment in that kind of gameplay.
So we introduced rare and epic missions,
where you would get guaranteed rare and epic cards.
And suddenly players were seeing
a purple glow in the horizon and they would be walking there to see what's in there.
They would be talking in the guild channels like
there's a thing in the market street, if you're near market street you should go there and get it.
We were also introducing both dynamic and static difficulty missions.
We wanted to make sure that there would be always nice content for you to play,
so we had to resort to dynamic difficulty most of the time.
However, if you design a game that only has dynamic difficulty,
you end up in a situation where progress doesn't feel like progress
because the difficulty always increases.
So many of the rare and epic missions we spawn are on the static difficulty, so they communicate to the player like,
if you were a tougher guy, you could also be playing this mission.
So, the core loop is now a little bit more complicated.
There's different rarities of missions, there are different rarities of raids,
and there are a lot more options what you can do while you...
move around. Of course, these are very contextual opportunities, so if you happen to be in a nice location,
then you will have nice opportunities, and if you're not in a nice location, then you have to figure out
whether you conserve your energy and your grenades, or whether you will use them on the bad opportunities
right here, right now.
Sulca mentioned the safe havens. Nowadays, they're called safe houses.
Players can build buildings in our world.
After you've built a building, you can leave survivors there.
You get rewards, and you also improve your rating
in the safe house leaderboard.
If you leave enough rescuees there,
then the safe house will be upgraded.
If you don't upgrade your safe house in a while,
then it will be destroyed by raiders.
We also have different kinds of safe houses
that give you different kinds of cards as rewards.
So suddenly we are facing a surprisingly complex decision space.
You have to figure out whether I want guns or heroes this time, whether it's important
for me to upgrade this safe house, whether it's important for me to beat the other guys
on the leaderboard to become the leader of the safe house and get improved rewards, or
whether it's important for me to save a safe house from destruction.
The leaderboards also have a really nice quality of showing
that other people are also playing around you.
And they create this kind of neighborhood-friendly co-op
competitions where someone is a leader in this house and
someone else is a leader in that house.
And if you try to be too greedy about too many safe
houses, then you actually can't be a leader in any of them.
This is kind of like.
We wanted to make the location a social opportunity for you.
And this kind of simple, kind of complex game
allows for that.
Sulka mentioned that we are a single shard game.
So we are.
Everything in the world is mostly similar to all the players.
So when I can see something cool, I will tell you that it's on the market street and go there.
However, we wanted to also introduce a feature to facilitate that, and that's why we created a feature called Flare.
Flare is a consumable that I can deploy here, and if I deploy a Flare here, all my friends in my guild can teleport here for free.
This helps us a lot in creating kind of a social dynamic where it's somewhat patronage.
It is couch play because I can invite you here while you're, I don't know, ill at home or whatever.
It allows virtual tourism. I have been sharing Moscone Center several times this week because I want to tell everyone that I'm here.
And when we get to the deeper social tasks, the flair allows for added coordination.
So the core loop, let's add some exploration.
So you have different kinds of safe houses.
Now it's starting to become a little bit of a resource
management game.
You have this one survivor, and you have five safe houses
around you, and then you're trying to figure what to do
with this guy.
And the way we built this thing is that it's mostly
cooperative, so everyone is benefiting from this friendly
competition.
But the guys who are playing most actively and making
smartest choices are benefiting even more.
It's also not a very serious game.
The benefits that you get from leaving your survivors
into better safe houses are actually quite small,
but they are nice.
So we wanted to make sure that you can't make mistakes,
but if you're smart, you can be a little bit better
in the game.
Also, we wanted to give an alternative to the walking and
discovering, which is the teleportation.
So now you can ask your guildmates to flare you
somewhere, or you can share something that you find and
flare others to there.
You can share the location opportunities to other players.
It looks nicer now, the core loop, but not nice
enough just yet.
Remember this, Sulke showed this and said that nothing felt
as good as seeing the bars progress after a battle, and
this is very much true.
This was a very good prototype for us, and based on this
simple progress bar system, we wanted to develop something a
little bit more sophisticated and, let's be honest, a little
bit more complicated.
So this is a guild board.
It consists of about 25 missions that you complete.
There are also three chests on the board.
And if you complete a row and a column, then you can collect
the chest in the intersection of that row and column.
But the thing is this.
Everyone in your guild is collaboratively completing these quests, and all the rewards are social.
There is no way for you as an individual to benefit any more than everyone in your guild benefits.
When you unlock the chest, everyone unlocks the chest.
The only thing that you can gain in the guild board for yourself is that if you're a top contributor to a task, you get your face on the wall, like the four yellow portraits in the top row.
This has turned out to be a surprisingly strong motivator for players.
Some people want to, I want my face on the wall so that I can prove that I play a lot.
I want my face on the wall so that I won't be kicked away from the guild.
I want my face on the wall because I already have seven and I want more faces on the wall than Sulko has.
This is how the tasks look like.
Win 40 battles.
This is an easy task.
This is actually so easy task that when you start playing
the game and you're in the guild, you start kind of
accidentally completing the quests.
And this is what hooks you into this somewhat complicated
guild board system.
Actually there's a funny story about this screen on the right hand side.
A programmer was implementing this feature and they came to me and they complained like
I just played this mission and I completed seven tasks or incremented seven tasks.
So isn't it a little bit weird to complete seven tasks at one
go?
And I was like, if you choose the optimal hero
and the optimal gun and the optimal mission,
and then you go there with optimal, I don't know,
grenades or something, and you manage
to progress seven missions at the same time,
isn't that cool?
So actually, we ended up designing the easier guild
boards in a way where this is very likely and constantly
happens.
On the later guild boards, on the harder tasks,
you will get these kind of missions.
Lone Wolf, one group member must win 80 level 20 battles
with a reclaimer shotgun.
So suddenly you need to parse together
quite a bit of information
and you need to start sharing tasks.
Who's gonna do the reclaimer task
because someone else is doing something else?
This 25 square board is, in a sense,
it's a simple representation.
In a sense, it's complicated.
But the interesting thing is that it has surprising depth
when you're trying to track the progress of everyone
in your guild and trying to figure out what they are
actually doing and what is your best way of contributing
to the common task.
It's also a great collectible motivator, because if no one
has the reclaimer shotgun, no one's able to
complete that quest.
So this is a way we can shuffle players' collections
around and make sure that even the
weakest weapons are used.
We organized these guild boards into 20 different tiers.
On every tier you have three identical boards.
So the boards are identical except for the target counts of the missions.
So on the first board of the first tier you might need to complete 10 battles, then 20
and then 40.
And we designed this in this way in part because we want the
first board to be a practice board.
Usually the first board takes a good guild about one day.
And that is the one day during which you learn to allocate
your resources and coordinate your efforts so that when you
are tackling the real challenge of the third board,
you will be educated and understanding the
task you have to do.
You have one week to complete every tier.
So this is a time pressured challenge.
And this works really nicely for us in a weekly cycle.
Every Thursday when the boards open,
we can see a peak in the player activity
when everyone is enjoying the fact
that they can progress seven missions at one time
and when they are charging through the easy board.
However, if you don't complete the tier in the week,
then you will be starting that tier over the next week.
So it's also a challenge that becomes harder and harder
every week.
And finally, we have eight weeks in every season.
And we have a leaderboard where we track
the best guilds in the world.
And after the eight-week season, you
will get a massive reward and start over.
We spent a lot of time iterating these guild boards, trying to figure out how we can make
them work.
One important thing we did was that we specifically decided that none of the tasks require you
to be co-located.
So basically, you can play with friends from anywhere in the world and succeed in the guild
boards.
It was far too complicated for us to even plan about the missions that would require
everyone to go to, I don't know, Moscone West to do something.
That would have been...
Super complicated.
One of the important features in the boards is that it's 25
squares, so the learning, it is super hard.
So one thing we did was that we decided that one of the
chests is easy chest, another chest is a medium chest, and
the third one is the hard chest.
And every mission that leads to the easy chest is actually
super easy.
So that when you're semi-randomly doing
things on the map, you actually see that these quests are
starting to complete.
And then you're actually figuring out that there's an
opportunity of grabbing the easy chest if you just
coordinate the efforts a little bit.
And then, of course, when you have done that, you've done
quite a bit of work towards the medium chest as well.
So that will be half complete when you're
done with the easy chest.
And the same goes on with the hard chest.
One thing we also did here is that some of the missions are, as the previous example,
they are lone wolf quests so that one player needs to focus their efforts on one task.
This has been a really interesting, dramatic tool for us.
One thing we can do, for instance, is that we take the best player away from some difficult
mission so that the others need to shine because the best player is focusing on the lone wolf
mission.
The lone wolf missions also become competitions between players when both want their face on the
wall and then they are effectively wasting their efforts in this glory hunt, which is really nice.
We worked even further with trying to make sure that these guild wars would always be...
So that the players would also have hope in completing the guild wars.
So here you can see the difficulty curve of the guild wars.
Basically on the left side you can see the tier 1 and on the right hand side you can see tier 20.
And you can see the small numbers, but I can tell you
that the highest, most difficult guild board has
difficulty multiplier of about 300, compared to the
difficulty multiplier of about one of the easiest board.
So on the first board, you have to win 10 battles.
On the last board, you will have to win 3,000 battles.
So they get extremely difficult towards
the end of the stack.
It was hard for us because players were getting stuck on
the boards, and then your social dynamics start to go
awry, because when you lose hope, then there's nothing fun
in the game anymore.
And then some people stop playing, and then it gets even
harder to progress.
So one of the important things we did was that, as you can
see here, the difficulty curve of the first board of every
tier is actually quite lenient.
So no matter where you are, you can always complete the
first board.
The second board, which is the medium board, is a little bit of a challenging,
and then the real push is the third one.
But then there's another aesthetic that is really nice here, besides the aesthetic of hope,
which is that the first board is always a really nice reward for you.
Like in Clash of Clans, the reward for upgrading your Town Hall level is not really the better Town Hall,
the reward in Clash of Clans is that you get to upgrade all your stuff really fast,
and so the game becomes very fun to play.
And here the same thing happens with the first board
being fun to play and super quick and super fast.
We found this math of hope really important part of the
dramatics of the Guild Board system.
So let's look at the core loop.
It was a little bit complicated already, but then there are different kinds of missions
that you have to do.
And you have to start optimizing not only between the rare missions and the safe house
that you want to save, you have to also start to coordinate with your friends and you have
to start to figure out which are the best ways for me to contribute in these guild
quests.
And it gets pretty complicated because there are now multiple social systems that are interacting in unpredictable ways.
You have both the local social system of safe houses, and then you have the guild-based social system of the guild boards.
And both of them are dynamic, both of them are unpredictable, both of them are gamed by not only you but also your guild.
And that makes the game quite deep, actually.
Of course, every game gets stale over time, so we also
added some token events.
So sometimes you want to go somewhere even to get this
week's special mission tokens.
I think I heard of the term smart depth first time about
10 years ago in a WUGA presentation.
And their point was that you want to enrich your core loop
while you want to keep your core loop just as it is.
So you want to add smart depth.
while keeping it simple.
And I think we succeed in our world in this task, because
this is still a really simple decision space.
You can't do anything wrong.
You can just fail.
You can just introduce waste in your process.
There is no failure.
Every time you log in.
You pick a fight, you shoot something for 15 seconds, you progress in the game.
But if you're really smart, you can progress a little bit more.
And even for advanced players such as myself, sometimes I'm, I don't know,
walking on the street and I don't want to think that much, while at other times I want to be
super careful of my resource management. Like I have one energy, what is the best
way for me to use this one energy here right now?
Of course, from design perspective, this is kind of difficult to handle because there
are so many options.
So we were thinking, like, how can we simplify this?
And then we figured out, like, let's just assume that players are scavenging quite optimally
at all times.
Let's just do all our Excel math, assuming that they get really good grades at all times.
And that helped us a lot.
And then we figured out, let's just assume that they put
their stuff in really good safe houses at all times.
And if they don't put their stuff in the really good safe
houses at all times, then they're introducing waste, and
that is their problem.
And then we figured, let's assume they win all the
battles, so we don't need to.
Think about the difficulty in terms of economy design.
Of course, we think about difficulty a lot.
But in terms of economy design, you always win.
And since location is just an opportunity,
even the teleport flare feature is just like,
we just assume that you have really good opportunities
at all times.
So from economy design perspective,
this is how our game looks like.
Time equals progress.
And it's modulated by skill and effort
so the player can introduce some waste if they are not ideal.
And of course, no one is ideal.
But at the same time, it's still the social fantasy
of the walking dead surviving by pulling together and not apart.
So time to start getting into actual takeaways.
So looking at the core pillars that we set early on in the project,
we wanted to achieve, we feel that we pretty much nailed all of these.
You can play the game pretty much everywhere.
It's always worth opening the game when you've moved.
The game is quite couch play friendly,
given the location-based aspect of it.
Social mechanics, we wanted to make something that was really strong.
We actually did it.
And the game really does feel like The Walking Dead,
where you absolutely have to coordinate your efforts
with the other players in order to actually succeed.
So even though the shape of the game that we ended up making was quite different
from what we imagined at first, we're very happy with.
A key takeaway is that when you do novel design,
you have to do a lot of prototyping and validation.
And the important thing in the prototyping and validation
is that you have to accept that it takes time
and it requires many failures.
And of course, paper prototypes are the cheapest
and quickest way to fail, which is very good.
But ultimately, you will have to,
especially with the social systems,
you have to actually build good, proper prototypes.
And we spent a lot of time doing that.
So having said that, yes, you need to be able to and prepared to kill all the darlings, even if they're really cool.
I personally like the, we as humans, very easily fall with the sunk cost fallacy,
where we think that we put so much time and effort and love into a prototype,
and it must succeed simply because we like it so much, or we invested so much energy into it.
But let's all, as game designers and game developers,
try to fight that and make sure that if something doesn't
actually fit your game, just kill the feature away
and your game's going to be so much better for it.
Even though there are no references for novel design,
you can always have references.
And you should look outside the box for references
if you don't have them.
Our guild board system is basically a marriage of Disney Tsum Tsum's bingo boards combined
with Everwing's guild quests and our shooting mechanics combine Operation Wolf with Whack-A-Mole.
So the language of games is still very important when you don't have anything direct to look
at.
With the core loop, once you actually figure out something that really works,
continue iterating and adding more features, but really do try to keep it simple and have the same
way of people approaching how they play the game throughout the process. So you'll end up with a
loop that is still easy to play, but has so much depth if the players actually really want to look
for it.
And finally, you need to iterate your own game until you're hooked to it.
On the right hand side you can see a guild board on tier 3, which I completed alone because all my guildmates were slacking that week because I wanted to progress and they didn't.
So, thank you, hope you enjoyed and really good to see so many people here despite the, I assume the party starting at 6 o'clock. So, I'm Sulka.
My name is Markus.
And please remember to fill up the feedback forms if you like the presentation.
I assume we might have time for like maybe one question.
I'm just curious about how long did you guys spend just in pre-production?
So the core prototyping, I think we spent maybe 10 months on it.
Actually doing things that ultimately mostly got chucked away.
And the team was at some point...
I remember the programmers asking,
do we really want to spend all this time
doing things that we're going to throw away?
So we did, but we did.
We did a huge refactoring pass of actually rewriting a lot of
the code from the prototypes to be
something that we could actually put
into the final shipping product.
Cool. Thank you.
Cool. I guess that's it. Thank you.
Thanks again. I never work on a location-based game, so maybe my question will be dumb, but
did you see some changes in players' behavior based on climate, or like warm countries,
or during the season? And did you make some adjustments with events or stuff like that,
or rules based on level design to accommodate that?
We are internally debating on how much those effects influence our game.
Personally, I know that when my hands freeze, I stop playing.
So in order to accommodate players like me, we have done some increase in the couch play
lately to accommodate for the winter, but we don't really know conclusively.
The other thing to keep in mind is the geography of the world is fundamentally different depending where you go.
So one of the features of Helsinki is that the city blocks are huge.
So the number of buildings that you actually see at any given point is actually not that big, because the buildings aren't so big.
But if you open the game in India, like in typical Indian cities, the game has to load about 5,000 buildings, because they're all very small.
So the way we've built, as humans have built,
the systems in which we're living
is so fundamentally different that if you
want to design a game that actually works across the globe,
it's not only how warm it is somewhere,
but there's so many aspects that you actually need to look into
and you need to play and teleport around the world,
look at how the game works across the globe.
So it's very complicated to actually isolate any one thing
that would, um...
make a difference to the players depending on where they are.
Thank you.