so
Hi, everyone.
Thank you for coming.
I've been told to tell you all to turn your cell phones off.
So you should probably turn your cell phones off, but it's OK if you don't want to as well.
My name is Graham Parks.
I'm the main writer and one of three creative directors behind this indie game, Before Your Eyes.
It came out two years ago on Mac and PC, released on mobile via Netflix last year, and just about a week ago launched on PlayStation VR 2.
But if you're not familiar with the game, you definitely will be by the end of this, so don't worry.
Um, yeah, in 2014, it was my last year of college, um, and one of my oldest friends from high school, Will Hellworth, who you see right there, uh, called me up and pitched me this crazy idea for a video game he wanted to make for his college thesis project.
And, uh, basically what he had discovered is that with this readily available plugin, even the most basic computer webcam could do eye tracking.
And he wanted to design a game around that, specifically around the process of blinking.
He was intrigued by the physical inevitability of that process, that no matter how hard you try to keep your eyes open, you'll ultimately fail.
And he saw this as a metaphor for death, which is something that he'd been wrestling with in his personal life for a variety of reasons.
on
I think his question was, what if we make a game about losing, where you lose, no matter how hard you try, you can't win a staring contest with a web camera.
You're going to have to blink.
And so what if we made a game where you lose over and over and over again, and then you die, and that's the end of the game.
And the game will take place on a character's deathbed, and life is going to flash before your eyes.
And every time you blink, you'll jump forward in time to a different memory of your life.
And Will knew I was a writer.
grew up, but we went to the same high school.
We took the bus together and spent all our time talking about video games, basically.
And he knew I wanted to write games, and so he wanted me to come on and write this game for him.
And I can tell you right now, it was the single greatest call I'd ever received in my life, because this game, this pitch, felt like the culmination of everything I wanted to be a part of creatively.
While Will was at USC studying games, I was at NYU studying playwriting, but really spending most of my time watching old movies at the Film Forum, this repertory movie theater where I used to work.
smoking a lot of weed, playing a lot of video games and in my very pretentious NYU film kid way I'd become obsessed with this idea that these filmmakers that I was learning about from the silent era or Alfred Hitchcock or the French New Wave that if they were alive today they'd probably be making video games and not films because you know you watch all these groundbreaking old films that were sort of playing with the form and I wasn't seeing that kind of formal innovation in the current cinema
But where I did find it was in games.
And I don't think it's really discussed enough, but those were some really incredible years for narrative indie games, I think.
It felt like every few months something was coming out that was totally left field and groundbreaking.
And being the perfect age in college, it just felt like my mind was constantly being blown.
Here's a few of the classics.
that left a big mark on me.
Yeah, and it felt to me like playing these games must have been what, like, seeing Breathless or watching Psycho or something must have felt like in the 60s, this sort of feeling of, I didn't know this medium could do this.
And that was so core to what, you know, this concept that Will had pitched me.
I had started signing up for classes at the NYU Game Center, which was sort of a new thing at the time.
had a great time in all the theory classes and all that but as soon as I signed up for a intro to unity course I had to drop out because three weeks in I was just too dumb to follow along so this is a GDC talk from somebody who couldn't make it through an intro to unity course
Yeah, I hope it gives some hope to people who maybe are as dumb as I am.
And because of that, I kind of felt like, well, I'll probably never get to work in games.
It was this medium I was obsessed with, but it just felt like there wouldn't be a place for me.
So then when I get this call from Will, I just decided I was going to grab onto this thing and never let go.
And at first it went really well.
Will brought in more of our old high school crew, like some of our, all our sort of best friends from high school, Ollie Lewin, who was the composer and became a co-director, Griffin Libby Blesser, who was our art director.
These were like people that I'd known since I was like three and six and twelve.
um, and he brought us all on to kind of bolster out his USC team that were building the actual game and together we created this 15 minute version that we submitted to IndieCade in 2014 and it got in.
Um, and it barely worked.
I mean the BlinkTech really was rough at that time.
Um, but
When it did work, we were kind of shocked by people's reactions.
And I'll be honest, the game really wasn't good enough to elicit the reactions it was getting.
I mean, people were leaving the booth crying.
And speaking just for myself, the writing certainly wasn't.
There's a comment that we received on the YouTube upload of it that stays in my memory.
on
in the concept that was just sort of inherently emotional.
By creating this physical connection between you and the game and forcing you to lose this staring contest again and again and again, the game sort of breaks down your defenses.
And you have no choice to get kind of invested.
In 2014, it won the developer's choice at IndieCade, which we were shocked.
And we decided we'd put more work into it.
I wrote a totally new script.
We basically rebuilt it from the ground up into something much better and more polished.
It still was
very rough by where it ultimately landed but something that was better uh... and then in twenty fifteen it won the student award here at GDC uh... at the IGF uh... and uh... off of that we started getting kind of cocky we really thought oh maybe we really have the magic fairy dust here so we decided we were going to make a full version of the game a two hour movie length experience that could fully explore this concept and really break us as this studio to be reckoned with and uh... what did that lead to was
five years of constant failure.
Um, so that's what this talk, talk is going to be about.
It's going to be about the failure, this sort of cyclone of failure we found ourselves in, why it happened, how we eventually, eventually pulled ourselves out.
And so it might seem a little grim at points, but I do promise a happy ending.
Um, structure of the talk is going to be quickly
take you through why I think we were failing so hard at these three key areas, and then just doubling back and explaining how I think I pulled us out of that rut.
Not how I pulled us out, but how we pulled ourselves out.
So we'll start with the first, which is the one I'm most responsible for, which was the story.
Back in college, I actually had the pleasure of working as a part-time assistant for this amazing screenwriter, Michael Arndt, who has this great talk on the writing beginnings for Pixar that you can find on YouTube.
But in it, he says this, that writing a script is like climbing a mountain with a blindfold.
What seems like the hard part is climbing the mountain, and it certainly is, but the really hard part, and the part that can really take years, is even finding the mountain at all.
And that really resonates with me for this game because it took me five years to even find the mountain of this story.
and so to prepare for this speech I went back through all these different versions and it really was shocking to see how many versions there were of this game uh... the first one was you know a shameless death of the salesman ripoff which at twenty two years old I was audacious enough to literally steal dialogue from verbatim actually found the quote that I stole from I guess that's homage not plagiarism I'm not sure uh... you know then there was uh... this one which was kind of
had this extending framing device, I think this was the GDC, I think, I don't, I literally don't remember which, which story went with which build at this point, but this, your estranged father is reminiscing with you and the twist, you know, takes you out on this fishing trip and the twist is that you've both been dead the whole time, which I most certainly stole from some Twilight Zone episode.
Um, love that show, but that is basically always the twist, that they've been dead the whole time.
And then we, you know, started experimenting with Twine for a while, so there was another version where, you know, we had all these different endings where you could end, like, as a rich CEO or you could die as an alcoholic on the street, and Twine is an incredible tool.
But as I said, I'm very dumb, so it made me very confused very fast.
And all these versions, I think, were clever enough.
If there's one thing I've always been OK at, it's consuming and internalizing other media.
And I had no shortage of amazing work to pull from, which dealt with the themes that I felt this game needed to deal with, with death and regret and the passage of time.
But the stories always just felt like excuses for a tech demo, really.
They showed the potential of the concept, but taken on their own, they were inauthentic.
But there was another big issue, which was, how the fuck are you supposed to tell a story when the player might blink out of any scene at any moment?
And that leads us into how we were failing at design.
So for those short early versions of the game, literally every single time you blinked, you would jump forward.
So if the player is good at staring contests, they might see the whole story, but if say they had allergies or hay fever that day, they'd just rapidly blink through all the most important scenes.
It was sort of, you know, interesting in a punk way.
But yeah, it was, as you can see here, it was not the most comfortable experience for our players.
And it kind of left me screwed over as a writer because, as we know, good writing is often built on structure and callbacks and how are you supposed to call back to something if I don't even know if the player has seen it or not.
But it also felt like it was impossible to abandon this design principle because
It was sort of core to the pitch of the game, which was every time you blink, you jump forward in time.
We found a couple short-term solutions.
We took out 3D movement.
We switched from text to VO, which was something I had always wanted to do anyway.
And those just allowed you to focus more on the staring contest and not worry about other elements of the game.
And we introduced that narrative's framing device, the dad on the boat, and that allowed us to at least have these little siloed sections where you would blink a bunch and then you would go back to the framing device and you could kind of rest your eyes.
But no matter what we did, the player feedback was the same, that the game was fascinating and interesting and the concept was great, but it was really annoying to play.
And it worked in a 15-minute festival setting, but it certainly wasn't going to work for two hours, and it certainly
you know, wasn't something we could charge for unless we wanted to, you know, only have a bunch of refunds.
Uh, and this led to big arguments, um, about how the Blink should work and, you know, should we abandon the Blink or find some new use for it?
And, and that became this, you know, kind of philosophical argument about what the game is supposed to stand for.
And, you know, as this team full of
old best friends, that was happening a lot.
You know, a conversation about, you know, some section of the game would spiral out into, you know, these giant, you know, arguments about who we are as people.
And so that kind of leads into how we were failing so badly at our process.
you know after uh the big win at IndieCade and IGF we got cocky and we did what all indie teams do when they get cocky we uh made a kickstarter and uh it uh it funded uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh
We raised $35,000.
And I still laugh when I look at that number, considering the scope of what we were trying to do.
We were all like, you know, cheersing each other after that.
But we were young and basically consisted of five high school friends, none of whom had ever shipped a game before.
And we were heading into our actual 20s.
You know, college was behind us and our side gigs were turning into real jobs.
and time was getting tighter and tighter, which was stressful enough on its own, but then, you know, we had these Kickstarter backers and they were getting angry, which was totally fair, because we had over-promised and under-delivered, as a lot of Kickstarters do, and our comment section quickly devolved from these words of encouragement to tirades against us.
Here's a favorite.
I just like when he says blowing smoke up my ass while you spend backer money on whatever yuppity fuck sushi lunch or new age toys you choose.
I just think, I mean, we weren't doing that, but I just think it's kind of good dialogue, you know?
It kind of feels like David Mamet or something.
But this guy's good.
This guy's got a future.
Yeah, so we began to feel that there was this angry public outside with pitchforks, which only compounded our stress, so we did what any
team of immature man children would do in that situation, we turned on each other.
And we started pointing fingers and we started blaming.
And of all our failures as a team, and this is a talk about failures, this is really the only one that I'm actually ashamed of.
You know, because you really can't create anything without an emotionally safe environment.
And you can't call yourself a team
unless you trust each other.
And a couple years into our failed Kickstarter, we found we had neither of those things.
And that was really hard for us to admit to ourselves because we were all such old friends and we loved each other so much, but maybe that was sort of part of the problem, that we loved each other too much, kind of like family, and there wasn't, you know, the kind of clear boundaries that you maybe want in a work situation.
In the months passed into years, the game became a kind of real source of stress for me and I think for the whole team.
I mean, I'll only speak for myself.
You know, I'd be out at dinner and a family member or friend would say, hey, what happened to that game I gave 40 bucks to, you know, two years ago?
I'd have to try and explain it away.
And it felt like a really impossible situation because on one hand, we all knew what we were doing wasn't working and our lives and mental health would definitely be better if we just abandoned it.
But we also had too much pride.
And I think, you know, we still somewhere really did believe in this game.
We just had no idea how to make it.
And, you know, I'd like to say, now we're going to get to the solving problems part of the talk, I'd like to say that, you know,
just
make that clear, but they're a company that was recently bought by Verizon.
They were looking to fund sort of experimental VR and AR.
We were their first, like, you know, game.
We kind of got in under the wire, you know, because we were going to do a VR slice of the game.
But we ended up meeting this producer, Jake Sally, there, who'd been aware of our game from back in the day, and he felt like it was a great fit, and he convinced us to come in and pitch it to his bosses.
You know, I said this to Jake recently on text, but there's really no way that I'd be here or anything would have happened if it weren't for meeting him at that point, because for some reason he chose to believe in the game and the team at a point when truly no one on the team believed in it.
Later we also signed to Skybound Games and they were equally, I mean probably more important for the game's success, but I focus on Jake for this talk because he's really the guy that kind of was the light in the darkness.
And you'll find those people throughout the life of making games.
Um, yeah.
But so to our surprise, Riot decided they wanted to fund us and it wasn't a ton of money, but it was enough that some of us could go full time for a little bit.
And, uh, more important than that, we could bring on new team members.
And, uh, you know, the team really started to grow and it grew outside of just a bunch of childhood friends.
And this is, you know, how you fix a process because, you know, first of all, you just sort of have to button up when you actually enter a real professional situation.
You get other voices, other perspectives.
And you also get, you know, when you're this long into working on something, you've completely forgotten what makes it cool or what makes it exciting.
I mean, I think that
out
to uh uh rejuvenate a process and uh the other thing we started to do is we had the infrastructure to playtest and so Jake would help us organize playtests with the Riot employees and obviously playtesting is helpful but I found one of the things that you know consistent playtesting and obviously this is anyone in games this should be obvious but as I said
We were dumb, so it took us a while to learn this, but it helps you table arguments.
If you're disagreeing, you can just say, well, we'll find out at the play test.
And it just makes everything feel a little less personal.
And that kind of led us into how we solved the design of the game.
We had hired a new designer, Bella Messicks, who had just launched his own game, Little Bug, which is very cool.
You guys can check it out.
He was a solo dev, and we brought him on.
He was one of the people that really helped us start looking at the concept with fresh eyes.
And he was like, why are you guys not just using Blink?
Why are you just using Blink for this one thing?
Can't Blink be used for other things that can be more fun and joyous?
And he just kicked off a conversation that became months long with tons of iterations.
But we kind of landed on
Embracing that idea, you know, that we could use blinks for other things than just passing time forward.
So we started using blinks to do things like you blink and you reveal the environment around you or, uh, what just happened there?
And you take photos, or play music, or paint.
But because we still need to retain that essential idea from the game, that genius idea of Will's, at a certain point in the scene, you're going to see this little metronome come up.
Well, not yet here, but about midway through the scene, you're going to see this little metronome show up.
And now the game is going to play like the game always played before.
And so this is telling you that the next time you blink, it's going to be your last.
And what's really cool about that is like, we were able to, you know, put the scenes into these two halves, so you didn't have to be constantly frustrating and freaking the player out.
You could let them have fun, let them actually in and enjoy the moment of the scene, and then introduce that tension of, okay, you're about to leave.
And we could also kind of mix those two designs because we could introduce, like you see here, interactables, blinks, after the metronome, and those are like these little islands.
So it's like if you blinked before you got to that, then you would jump forward, but you can kind of jump over to that and blink, and that can help you to stay in the scene.
So we actually found by sort of being a little more flexible with our concept, we were really able to actually bring out what was great about that initial concept, and we didn't have to lose it.
And it allowed me to retain that sense of frustration of, shit, I missed it, I keep missing out on things, but also not letting that frustration totally dominate the experience.
And you can see here, like this is a little scene from the final script.
And every scene I was able to kind of write at the bottom, at that time we called it the blink counter.
I don't know why.
So I could kind of know, okay, I'm going to put the necessary stuff, the stuff that you need to know that I might call back to before that, but then once that comes up, I'm still going to leave, we had an amazing voice cast, I'm still going to leave all this really charming dialogue and funny stuff.
and interesting moments that fill out the experience that you can still miss and still get that feeling of, oh god, I missed out.
But you're not going to just jump through stuff that you need to even understand the story at all.
So we were able to have our cake and eat it too, which leads to how I ultimately solved the writing part of the game.
I think the real key to it was that I had time.
As I said before, most of the other team were taking other jobs.
And when we started with Ride, I was able to have about four months where I was the sole person working on the game full time.
And I recognize this is a really rare opportunity for game writers.
We're often asked to fit our work around crazy production schedules.
But I think as writers, we sometimes have to advocate for that importance of that time and just
uninterrupted time, because I really do believe the most important work happens in your subconscious.
And if you don't have that time to think and to gestate, and you're always on that next deadline, you're not going to access the deep work.
And that's what those four months gave me.
And so I'd have these long meetings with Will, and sometimes our art director Griffin, and Ollie, who would become a co-director on the game.
And we'd all just sit around and
and you know pitch ideas and then I get to go off and write and at the end of the week I'd send them stuff and they'd send me reactions and you know it was it was sort of a dream for a writer.
And, uh, I realized that what was holding me back for so long was this imposter syndrome because, you know, all those years ago, Will had brought me this incredible idea, maybe my favorite idea of all time.
And I felt like it could be the most meaningful and heartbreaking work ever.
I think there was just something about a blanket, you know, you're going to literally blink through someone's life.
Um, and it kind of felt like, why isn't, you know, Terrence Malick doing this?
Why am I doing this?
and to kind of give up on that feeling of we're going to do the best version and just try to figure out what's the version that I know how to do and what's the version that this team knows how to do.
because that was something we had that other teams didn't.
We were all childhood friends.
We grew up within biking distance of each other, and we were all intimately aware of each other's upbringings and life story.
That's me and Will at prom.
That's Ollie and I when we were literally four years old.
There's Griffin and Ollie.
I don't know what they're doing there with their boxers.
So we started kind of taking a walk down memory lane, and we digitized old home movies of our real childhood memories, and we're sharing things with each other.
And a lot of the props and environments you'll see in the final game are taken directly from those home movies.
Like the house in the game is actually based directly on Ollie's childhood home, which I grew up two doors down from.
You can see there at the wrap party for the game, we actually projected a streamer playing the game against the house.
that the house in the game was based on, so it was a very meta, crazy moment.
But through the process of unearthing these memories, I started to think about a time in my life that I didn't think about that often.
In middle school, I dealt with a pretty severe chronic illness, had to have a big surgery and was homeschooled for a year and a half.
There's a picture of me in the hospital.
And yeah, that was a tough time.
And a lot of memories and emotions I realized, you know, going back, I realized, you know, I had repressed, I had not thought about these things in a long time.
and bringing those memories back led me down the path to finally breaking this story and finally finding the mountain that I felt I was meant to be climbing.
uh... which was figuring out the central twist that the plot hinges on which if you play the game you'll know but i won't spoil uh... actually found this photo on face book yesterday they've been posted by ollie and i like this one one comment why the fuck did you put this on the internet but you know i'm actually this is i i i guess fifteen-year-old met me was angry that he put that on face book but i'm not now you know thirty-year-old me is thirty one-year-old me is very uh... happy that he did so i had it for this speech uh...
But all at once, sort of in a meeting with Holly, I figured this thing out and I rushed home and I wrote out a little two-page fable version of it and I sent it to Holly and Will and for the first time there was unanimous praise.
There was no fighting.
They both told me they cried after reading it and we all felt sure this was going to be the game.
You know, only four years late, but we got there.
And of all the positive press we received, this little article on fanbite is one of the ones I'm most proud of, because this writer had no way of knowing that some of this stuff came from personal experience, but she could somehow feel that, because she had gone through that same experience.
So she didn't need to fact check it, she just knew.
And, you know, I've always hated that advice to write what you know, because I always felt like I'd never experienced anything worth writing about, but I also think genuinely you should write about whatever you want.
But I do think what I learned is that on some level you should be, or for certain projects, I think you want to be able to be able to write from a place of personal vulnerability.
to approach subjects that make you uncomfortable, things that you maybe want to run away from, you know, you have to be maybe a little bit willing to put your hand on the stove and hold it there.
And I think if you kind of force yourself in that direction, you know, into those vulnerable, uncomfortable places, I think that's where, you know, a lot of the magic really starts to happen.
Um, and don't just regurgitate the structures from other media that you've consumed.
Cause that's what I did for, for all those years.
And again, it didn't work.
And you know, uh, we all know there's something coming that is probably going to be better at doing that than all of us.
Um, and one thing chat GPT can't do is be vulnerable.
So I think, uh, now more than ever, it's a good time to, to lean on that.
Uh, yeah, so.
Looking back, if there was one thing our team needed earlier, it was to get comfortable with that discomfort.
And I would have hated to hear that seven years ago, but I just think it takes a certain amount of life experience to get to that place.
In 2014, we had set off to make this game about loss, but we didn't really know anything about loss.
But in the seven years of failure, we got to know it very well.
First was the loss of the dream that we'd be the successful rockstar indie studio out of the gate, but we also endured personal losses, family members, ended long-term relationships and partnerships, and even friendships, some of which were strained to the point of breaking by the very pressures of making this game.
And I just wanted to take a moment, in case anyone ever finds this who worked on this game, just take a moment to share some gratitude for anyone who worked on this.
There was so many people that worked on this game.
There were so many errors and so many people that put so much of themselves into it.
And I worry sometimes that the ones that didn't get to see it through at the end feel like they can't share in its success, but they absolutely should because the game really does belong to everyone.
I mean, yeah, a game that takes that long has a lot of authors.
And yeah.
So the story ends with us winning a BAFTA.
Winning a BAFTA is a crazy process.
After you get it, you're taken off stage and you have to sign all this paperwork, which
stipulates that you don't own the BAFTA, but you're actually renting the BAFTA from them, and you gotta take care of it, and you can't sell it, and you can't let it get stolen or lose it.
But at the after party, I lost both of the BAFTAs.
So it actually ends with me losing a BAFTA.
I was drunk.
I was supposed to be watching them.
I tried to blame Ollie for a while, but I'll admit it here, it was me.
And then I came back and he said, you were supposed to be watching.
And we ran back and they were gone.
This was an email we had to send to BAFTA.
and we had to send the last photo that we had of it.
As if we didn't already seem like two dumb Americans who didn't deserve our BAFTAs.
There's Ollie looking like an idiot with the two BAFTAs.
Yeah, but don't worry, you know, it worked out.
It turned out just the Forza team had won so many BAFTAs they thought they were theirs, so then they sent them back in.
But in the span of those two hours, I went from feeling like this artistic genius to once again the biggest idiot on earth.
And my phone had died in the process, so by the time my phone came back to life, we had lost the BAFTAs, so my first call to my parents was an
I won a BAFTA it was I lost my BAFTA which is a bummer but you know I tell that story to just illustrate that the years of failure aren't going to be all made worthwhile by reaching some big glorious ending and if you think about it like that you're definitely going to be disappointed because you know the universe has a way of reminding you who you are that just a dumb guy who couldn't make it through an Intro to Unity course
uh... and over the last year we started work on a new title we're still part of the goodbye world family but we've actually created a brand new studio called nice dream which literally just went public today so we don't have like any followers so if you guys wanna get in on the ground floor there it is
Um, and we're still idiots and we fail constantly but I think that what this one success has given us it's the ability to not be so afraid of failure.
Um, the team certainly still argues over what the right path is but we just sort of assume that everyone's a little bit wrong and that we'll find out later in play testing.
Um,
The last couple years I've gotten really into two things, jackass and, you know, from software games.
These have been my comfort viewing.
For some reason, going back to jackass, I don't know why.
But I was thinking about it and I realized what links the two and why maybe I like them so much is that they're really about celebrating human failure and our incredible ability to know that we're going to lose and that we're going to get very, very hurt, but still go out and try to do impossible things.
And if you choose to make games for a living, or any highly collaborative art form, that's what it's going to be like.
Sort of like trying to win a staring contest with a web camera.
You're inevitably going to lose over and over and over again.
And then you're going to die.
So there's your happy ending.
Hope you guys all enjoyed it.
Thank you so much for attending.