Good morning GDC, hi. I am supposed to remind you to turn off your noise makers, so please do
that now. And let's get started. So, I'm going to start with a little bit of background.
My name is Clemens Scott. I'm the co-founder of a small studio based in Vienna, in Austria,
called Broken Rules, which was founded by these five guys. Actually, the studio itself
was founded by...
These three, Felix, Jan and Peter, who made a prototype of a game that was nominated for the Student Award Showcase at IGF in 2007.
And after that they made a full game out of it and it was called And Yet It Moves.
And it was done in 2009, which was also the time when our studio was founded.
And a short while later...
Martin and I joined the team and together as a team of five people we created two games.
The first one was a Wii U launch title called Chasing Aurora and the second one was the PC
follow-up called Secrets of Raticon that was released in 2014 I think. And now a few years later
Felix and me are working on a game called Old Man's Journey,
which is a game about an old man living by himself in a house on a cliff by the sea.
And he one day receives a letter, and upon reading the letter, he just packs his stuff and starts walking.
And as he walks, he kind of thinks back on his life,
and players find out what happened to him
that he ended up in this house.
And the gameplay, or the game itself, looks like this.
So this is the core gameplay mechanic.
What you do is you can touch the hills and shape them.
to create intersections between two hills
and wherever there's a visible intersection
between two hills, the old man can jump
from one hill to the other.
But when we started out with the game,
it did not look like this.
It looked like this.
and we had no idea of what the visuals were going to be for that game.
We had total creative freedom on how to develop this thing,
which is great, but choosing a direction of a project
that will dictate most of your wake time for the next two years
and your financial future demands
to be a really well-considered decision, right?
And creative freedom is the reason that I decided to run my own studio.
But, the more creative freedom you have, or the more freedom in general,
the harder it is to make a choice which way to go.
But luckily, there are tools.
Introducing...
The Box.
The box really is just a metaphor for setting yourself goals based on your own constraints.
And you can kind of use that to question or to test your own decisions or try to find answers to questions that you have about like where you're going to go and how you're...
going to do it. So this in and on itself is not a very particularly new concept and many people use it in project
management, but it's also one of the the cornerstones of why Oldman's journey looks like the way it does.
And to us this has like sort of like three main ingredients
and that is the constraints that you have
as a game developer and the goals that you have
for the project and sort of the strategies
that you will sort of how you will achieve those goals.
So when looking at the constraints of broken rules for us as a team, there are kind of like three things.
The one is then games that we want to make, games that we are able to make, and games that currently have a market.
And so the games that we want to make...
are things like they push the boundaries of the medium and they offer unique experiences
and usually are not free-to-play.
Games that we are able to make
often have sort of a strong aesthetic and builds believable worlds that players want to spend time in.
And the interesting one is kind of like the third one, and especially where the overlap is.
So, games that currently have a market do not push the boundaries of our medium, at least not too hard,
and are also often free to play, but with exceptions.
But the overlaps here are kind of like the unique experiences and the unique aesthetics or the high production value.
So with these constraints in mind, Felix and I...
set up the goals for what Old Man's Journey was going to be
like way before we were actually like producing the game.
When we were thinking about what are we going to do next?
What do we want to make?
And we decided we wanted to make a premium high quality
one time experience type of game
that connects with players on an emotional level.
that is not as common in games.
In our case, our starting emotion
was sort of the sense of wanderlust
and wanting to travel and be somewhere else.
And also we wanted to make a game that has mass appeal
without compromising our own artistic integrity.
Also,
We wanted to make a game that is so beautiful,
it will stick out of the mass and make editors
want to decorate their storefronts with it,
which means features for us, and that is good.
We also wanted to make a game that is so accessible,
it can be enjoyed by a widely arranged demographic
using the simplest form of input, which is a single touch.
So, you can move the old man
by just pointing and clicking somewhere,
and he will walk over there, and you can ...
drag the hills by just touching them.
And finally, we wanted to make a game
for the so-called reading nook,
so the place that you sort of retreat to,
that where you kind of read a book
or have kind of like no time pressure to enjoy something.
So we decided we wanted to make a game
that has about 19 minutes of playtime and about 15 levels.
These were the goals, but what strategies
were we going to use to achieve our goals?
One of the strategies that we thought we wanted to employ
was to tell a simple story
that everyone can relate to only using images.
There is no text in the game, there is no localization,
there is no reading.
All the story parts and the whole narrative is told through the old man's memories.
So at the end of each level, he kind of sits down and rests and then thinks about his life.
And then one of an image, an animated vignette like image like this is shown.
In this case, when he was still young and he went on a road trip vacation with his
then future wife. And the core theme of the narrative is the topic of family. So we think
that family is a topic that everybody has some sort of connection to on an emotional level. So
if you have family or not or whatever relation you have to your family, there's some sort of
emotional connection to that immediately.
So, that was the one thing. The other thing was that we decided that we wanted to align every single element,
every choice that we make in the game, we wanted to align to a so-called emotional progression curve,
which is an idea that we took from that game company who did that with Flower and Journey.
emotional progression curve looks like this in our case.
So at the bottom you see the numbers for the levels
and the line going up and down is kind of like positive
and negative emotions.
And as the player progresses through the game,
this is where sort of like the level of where we are
in terms of positivity and negativity
or happiness and sadness.
either the old man experiences,
but that is also reflected in all of the puzzle,
game mechanics, and the interactive elements
and basically everything else.
So this was really useful for us
to help pick the right environments
and help pick the right landscapes and moods
and colors for wherever we are.
It helped pick prototypes, distribute different puzzles.
and cut content if necessary,
and it also made communicating with the team a lot easier
because we could tell them what emotions to aim for
for whatever they were working on.
Finally, we also decided we wanted to build a world
filled with whimsical details and rich interactivity.
So there would be all these things
that you can sort of like touch and they would react
and something would happen.
And lastly, which is a little bit of a no brainer in a way,
but assemble a team of excellent collaborators.
which I'm pointing out here because
one of those collaborators is Salon Alpin
and they are an animation studio that are partially based in Vienna
at the same office as we are
and partially based in Lisbon in Portugal
and they are specialized on visual narrative
so basically telling story only using imagery
and Lipp, who is the art director of Salon Alpin
played a very important role in
finding the art style for Old Man's Journey.
And that's basically it.
This is where our box is done in a way.
Now we have all these components that we can then use
to inform the decisions that we were going to make
with the art style.
And that is a nice concept, right?
But it still does not really explain
how we got from this to this.
And that is still the same level, right?
So this was one of the is the first level in the game and it introduces the players to
to being able to switch between hills.
So we all we had was this pink figure and this blue kind of like target marker to tell players where to go.
And that was that.
And when we first only had these prototypes,
I started, and also when our box was not yet done,
I started making mock-ups for the game
and testing out various things.
And since our game, our previous game,
have been very much based on vectors,
it was sort of, for me, a logical step
to do something in vectors.
And the game was also based on these flat shaded shapes.
And it seems like that would be a good approach
because I came from a gameplay side of things.
So my ideas were always informed about, you know,
by then already worrying about things like readability and that player would know where
they would be going. So this was another mock-up that I created and it also had the very first
character design of the old man which was an egg-headed potato-nosed old clown with a tiny
backpack and a jumpsuit.
And we pretty much realized immediately that was not going to cut it.
And so I played around with different vector designs
and very stylized variants of this old farmer guy or something
that could be the player.
And we did not really know about the character of the old man by then.
I was just kind of like...
playing around and seeing where we could go.
And so I kind of like did more,
did sort of like this key art mock-up type of thing
that looked like this.
And it was also sort of.
informed by concerns of the core gameplay.
Like you could immediately read,
okay, there are these hills and you have these intersections
and that this is sort of like what's going on,
but there was no real emotional hook to this whatsoever
because intersections are not like a good.
emotional hook for anything, probably.
And so, we decided to hire Lip of Solo Narpin
to come up with some concept art for the game.
And his approach was radically different.
So, him coming from a cinematic background,
he did not give two cents about readability
or gameplay or whatever that stuff was.
He just aimed, or his approach was all about
vibe and emotionality and textures.
and that suited much better for what we had set out for
and what sort of like our box was kind of like developing towards.
And it also had the character of the old man,
which already kind of looks like what it does right now.
But at the same time, when he was doing that,
we also came up, we thought about who the old man was.
And so we came up with all these kind of character traits
about him and the three main characters in the story.
And we could communicate that to Lip.
started sketching around and assembling a couple of ideas
and came up with this design which is pretty much what he looks like in game now.
This was pretty close to the final design.
So, we were really happy with those results that he made but...
We felt we needed to figure out a way how to translate that into the game.
So we asked him to do another mock-up of something that was closer to the in-game thing.
And he did this.
And while we really liked, or I really liked the textures of everything, and also kind of liked the lighting,
It was still very hard to read and there were still technical aspects about it
where we did not know how we would implement that technically.
This was the point where Lipp's non-existing experience in making games
started to become a little bit of a difficulty.
So what I did was to go back into one of our prototypes, which looked like this.
and try to apply some of those ideas
that he had put on the table.
So in this case, this is a level where players learn
that you can drop down waterfalls.
They act like sort of like one-way downward conveyor belts
in terms of gameplay.
And again, I was coming from the gameplay side of things,
but I tried to apply those ideas
and do something more kind of like painterly and textures
and found the results pretty mediocre
and not very interesting.
And I was kind of, I felt like I just couldn't pull it off
what he was doing,
and that my skill set just wasn't high enough.
So...
Since I was going to be the lead artist on the game,
we had to find a style that I could make work.
Instead of doing something painterly,
we thought, okay, what could we do?
Maybe what about 3D, doing something in 3D?
I went into Blender and did this low poly type of mock-up thing
of what that same scene could look like.
We got the waterfall, we got the three hills.
It's the same scene built in 3D.
And we surprisingly really liked the results.
It had, for the first time,
it had very vibrant, nice color choices.
It was still kind of readable.
And one of the things that we liked
is that you get this instant lighting situation
where you just place one light
and all of a sudden you got shadows and you get mood
and this just kind of came along with that.
And so we decided we wanted to experiment with that a little bit more
and do another one of those
and try to solve some other problems as we did that.
So in this shot, the camera is pretty close to the player,
and so we decided we wanted to experiment with some more extreme distances.
like this one. So that this dark grey hill could be pretty far in the distance and maybe we could
we could do something about that. And one more thing that we were kind of like asking ourselves
about was what would we would be doing with that blue flag.
But because we felt it was like a super gamey element
that we wanted to get rid of in the final game.
So we had to find some solution for better signposting
so players would know where to go.
Because if you remove that flag
and just present that with players,
nobody would know where to go, right?
I tried to tackle both of these issues and came up with this.
Again, we really kind of liked it.
The colors were really nice and vibrant,
and it also introduced something that is still in the game today,
which are color hue shifts from top to bottom.
When you look at that yellow hill, for example,
it is brightly yellow on top and fades into this orange
becoming green eventually.
And this is a concept that is still throughout the game today.
And also it kind of supported that emotion of Wanderlust
and seeing the distance and wanting to go there,
which we kind of set up in our box.
So that was good.
And I put this little hillside village there
to try to solve the issue of signposting.
But it still lacked a lot of the details that we wanted to have and sort of that would make it feel rich, right?
And I did not really know how to approach that because I'm not really a good modeler at all.
So I would be super slow with that and I'm not really a good painter at all either, so I did not know how to go on from there.
And at this point I stumbled across a music video called Latin Voice, which was produced by the animation studio Encyclopedia Pictura.
And I really liked that video, so I started researching about who made it and about the animation studio behind that,
and I found the concept artwork by...
a guy called Isaiah Saxon.
And this image just really inspired me
to go back to my own roots,
which is actually line drawing.
So that is kind of what I feel like very comfortable with,
which is something that I've always been doing.
So I decided to do same scene just with line drawing,
which then ended up looking like this.
And then I kind of just put it on top of that.
3D mock-up using like the same colors and
and came to this and
So it was it was still like this similar to the mock-up
But it contained the richness that I wanted to achieve actually I went a little bit overboard with it
I aren't all these tiny details and
And I really like that idea though
you had these little workers and they're picking up their grapes putting them in their bags putting
on their truck driving off.
And it could immediately imagine all these stories
of what was going on in this world.
The sheep kind of like bumping around there
and stuff like that.
So I liked that.
It had a good depth and it gave a good idea.
But the outlines also made everything
a little bit too cartoonish for my taste.
Also,
having characters in there for the first time sort of like introduced the idea of
scales really
because
On that first hill, the old man could be pretty large and very well readable,
but as soon as he jumped on that second hill,
he had to be about the size of those characters.
And jumping on the third hill, he had to be the size of that wall at the house or something.
And then the next one back there, he would be like this tiny little dot
that you could not even see anymore.
So, we already then saw that distances like this
are just not going to work in terms of gameplay.
so we had to find some sort of middle ground and
also like the next logical step was that if we are going to use this village as the signposting type of thing then
Logically the next level would have to play inside the village I guess so what would that look like?
Once again, I came back to our puzzle prototypes.
This is one screen puzzle where players learn
that they cannot shape the hills that they are standing on.
They have to move on those dark gray blocks.
They cannot be shaped, they are static.
They are moving off that curve,
and then they can pull up that shape below,
and move up, and finish the Level.
And we had to find something that could be represented,
that could represent these dark, dark grey blocks.
And with the idea of like making a village,
you know, I thought, you know, what about like houses or something?
We could place houses on there and then he would be like
chomping on the roofs of the houses.
Maybe that could work.
And so I roughly sketched a village with houses over the same scene.
And I also decided in terms of better signposting, I wanted to give a better idea of where players came from,
where the old man came from and where he was going.
So I extended... wrong direction...
I extended that sketch on the top and the bottom
because I wanted to give a feeling of the old man
actually entering that village
and then kind of like walking up
and as he reaches like the top.
there's nowhere else really to go and there's this hotel so this is obviously kind of like okay this
I guess I'm here now for a place that was how I was thinking but it introduced one more
completely new thing that we all have had camera movement or we needed to add camera movement to
make that work and before we had only like one screen single puzzles and all of a sudden we were
like oh okay we can have like multiple scenes and the camera can pan around and zoom and
kind of parallaxing layers and mind blown basically.
And but it also introduced like a whole lot of new questions
and problems that we had to solve.
But that's sort of a different topic.
But also the ideas for all of these houses,
they didn't come out of nowhere when Felix and I.
we're talking about the idea of sort of like making a level inside a village.
Felix came with the idea of, he proposed an Italian town called Cinque Terre.
When I saw that image, it was kind of like,
oh wow, yeah, I want to be there.
I want to be there right now.
You know, this is so beautiful.
It's so vibrant.
It's great.
I'm going to take that as an inspiration
for our little mountain village.
And I started sort of like gathering images
and assembling a mood board
and of little kind of these mountain villages
and little street scenes and houses and things like that.
And...
When you look at those images, especially the top two ones,
especially maybe the first one, the top right one
with this yellow house, and then you look at this.
This is kind of similar, I guess.
And the top left one, the green one,
and then you look at this.
Ah, okay, yeah, okay, that's pretty familiar there.
So these things obviously didn't come out of nowhere,
but they were interpreted in the style of the game.
So I did the sketch and I extended it even more to add.
like a bit of sky or a lot of sky actually because I thought it was good for the composition and it had that nice vertical bookmark like feel
and started putting down some colors and at this point I showed it to Felix and we only had like this super rough thumbnail and he was like yeah this this is it I want to do that that is something he already kind of like started dreaming about yeah this
makes me feel like I want to spend time there.
And in terms of colors, it also already shows
like the first sort of like compromise
of what we did in terms of realism
and being natural in a natural, believable environment.
And that was that we kind of like used very, very natural colors,
but for the hills used pretty magical colors
because there are no blue hills or red hills like that.
But they are within the rest of the color scheme,
the rest of the color palette.
So they don't stick out too much, but they're clearly readable.
And since...
the one really magical thing in the games are the hills,
that you can shape them and just jump around.
It's also okay if they have sort of like magical colors
that signalize them.
And so it is easy for players to accept that fact.
So, yeah, I just started detailing that a little bit and added some sky, and at this
point I basically call it done.
This was it.
It was like the benchmark of what we wanted to achieve, and also the image that we used
to communicate of where we wanted to go.
But it still lacked sort of like the...
the amount of detail and we still also didn't know if we,
you know, what was with that idea of doing stuff in 3D,
you know, maybe that, you know, especially now that we have a moving camera,
you know, and 3D objects have actual perspective,
that could be really cool. Let's keep on experimenting with that.
So, I blocked the same three houses in Blender
and slapped some textures on top of that
and did a couple of hill textures
and we put it in Unity in a level and we had this.
and while we kind of really liked the results,
but I felt I disliked the geometrical look
and the very clean edges,
so we invested some more time into figuring out
if we could come up with a shader
that would imitate textured edges,
but I never really found the results
to be particularly convincing.
The rest of the team did lean sort of towards the option
of doing stuff in 3D,
But I felt I had to give the 2D version a better case
because I actually added a lot of detail to the 3D model
that the painting before did not have.
So the concept thing looked like this.
So it was still a lot more simpler.
And so I went back.
and added more details to that and came up with this.
And this is sort of pretty much what it is in game right now.
So yeah, now I felt like they were sort of on par in terms of quality
and we could not decide which way to go, which way to go, what we liked better.
And so we came up with all these pros and cons and lists of what it would mean to choose
like one way or the other in terms of production and what the pipeline would look like and
what the possible problems could be doing it this way or that way and tried to gather
as much information as possible to make an informed decision and came up with a tie.
And we still did not know how to do it.
So, we consulted our box.
And what did our box say?
It said we have experience making 2D games,
we have no experience making 3D games.
So that was kind of an obvious hint that we maybe should stick with 2D.
But I also thought that the natural stroke of a painted line
better supports the tone of the game and what we wanted to achieve.
But in the end, it really ended up with being a gut decision.
That was still like by the end, we just said, OK, you know what?
Let's just do it 2D because we feel better about it.
And that's what it is.
But we still kept on sort of like experimenting
from here and there with 3D elements.
So at the end of this hotel scene,
or at the end of this level,
there's the scene where this bus drives in
and we initially like modeled it in 3D
to see if it would be a cool effect
that you could see the front and the back
depending on where.
where the bus was in the scene.
But we never quite found, figured out a good way
to make it really integrate in the scene.
And so we just decided against using 3D models
for most of the game.
And yeah, technically, it still is sort of like a mixed technique,
because behind the scenes, our Levels look like this.
They are all just flat layers stacked on top of each other
going into the distance.
And here is another Level
that shows what it looks like behind the scenes, basically.
So ...
This is also one of the core ideas that informs the art style.
Everything is flat and everything is stacked on top of each other.
And there's almost no real lighting in terms of volume.
Everything is sort of like top to bottom.
So this is easily viewed when looking at like a single asset,
like a generic asset, like a bush.
So the way it works is we have this basic, clear, sort of reduced shape.
add some darker bits, some sort of shadow on the bottom,
a little bit of lighter bits on the top, and some details,
and add another layer with a little bit of a color shift,
and basically the same details, and then a third one,
and this sort of gives you an idea of a bush, right?
But there's no real volume, it's just like,
boop, boop, boop, three layers, that's it.
We thought that would work well,
but then realized that when we put that in the game,
we would need many different color variations of these bushes,
and saving all those sprites,
the same sprites in different colors,
is not a very effective way of doing things.
What we did was to make monochrome versions of that
and create a shader in Unity
that would color map two or three colors onto that sprite,
and we could get pretty similar results with that.
But we could also make something like this,
or something like this if we wanted to.
That was good, and I still had to figure out ...
like the overall vocabulary.
It is easy for me to break these things down right now,
but in reality to get to this point,
there was like a lot of experimentation involved,
and also kind of a consulting lip from time to time.
One time when I wanted to come up with an olive tree,
and I really struggled with that,
I asked Lip how he would do it.
And he always had the idea of very strong lighting
situations and sharp shadows and lots of volume,
but we could not really make that work in game
because if you have these strong lighting situations
and you would shape a hill,
the hill would sort of have to dynamically adapt
to the lights.
and that was for us just technically very hard to pull off
and we did not even have an idea of how we would do it.
So anyway, Lib proposed this as a tree
and what I liked, a lot of the ideas
and again sort of like the textures
and especially the trunk, it had too much volume.
So I did my own version of that
and I sort of like broke it down again into.
into those separate layers using these gradient-like color changes.
And, yeah, we were really happy with how that looked.
So we split it up into different parts,
imported it to Unity, reassembled it there,
added some physics, and we had bouncy trees.
And we were happy, that was good.
So, what about characters?
There's the same scene at the top of the level at the hotel.
And this is my initial sketch of a camper guy sitting there playing his guitar,
waiting for his girlfriend to pick him up with the bus.
And it was OK, but I didn't feel like it was according
to the rest of the style rules that we were currently
sort of like building and making.
So again, I asked Lip if he could give me
some feedback on that and maybe make another version.
And this is what he came up with.
And this was instantly like 500 times better.
It had clear shapes, it had the color variants in it,
everything was a lot more flat and easy to kind of like split into different parts and animate it,
and it fit into the rest of the style, so it was great.
So, let's look at environmental design.
When we started our level designs, it usually is on paper and it's with sketches like this.
And this is one of the later puzzles where you use sort of like these rolling wheels to break through walls to be able to continue.
And that was the mechanical side of things.
So then I sort of like, oh, wrong direction again,
started sketching on top of that
and adding like more different scenes in that whole level,
different camera views and sort of like trying to figure out
what the landscape would be and adding stuff here,
adding stuff there, and then I would take
one particular piece of that sketch
and do a new sketch and sketch it on top of that
and like,
If you leave that like laying around for two days
and you come back to it,
you have no idea of what is going on anymore.
So it is really important for,
or was really important to pretty soon take those ideas
that we thought out on paper
and sort of make a little bit of better readable versions
of that.
And this is not the same level right now.
Unfortunately, I don't have those sketches anymore,
but it kind of like shows the principle of,
like already on paper trying to figure out what the landscape aspects of that specific level would be and what all these hills and things could look like and
this is the point where you start thinking about landscape itself. So of course that also means that the level design
starts to modify a little bit because for things to work visually you have to push around some things move some things over there
Try to keep with the stick with the same idea in the core
level mechanic
But make it work visually so this was always kind of like a push and pull between me and Felix who?
Felix was the game the level designer and I am the decorator so to say who's trying to make things work visually
And especially in the beginning where we did not really know
which elements are going to work
and what we're gonna put where
and there was still like all these questions and open ends.
This approach was a little bit more chaotic.
So we already had puzzle prototype levels
that already kind of like looked like this.
And then I kind of like sketched over on that
and then we flipped those around and put them somewhere else
and it was a very, very iterative process in that way.
And...
Often what I did then was to, when trying to figure out what the environment would look like,
was to assemble a mood board and set up a basic color scheme of where we wanted to go,
which was informed by our emotional curve, and then kind of came up with this...
mood mock-up sort of where we are right now,
and then kind of like do this overview,
simple overview and start working on textures
and trying to bring that into the level.
As we worked on the project,
all those processes became more and more streamlined.
So, later on, we already exactly knew
which puzzles were going to where,
we were doing a lot of play testing,
and we already knew better what worked
and kind of like what the difficulty curve would look like.
So we basically kind of stitched together various puzzle prototypes to make one level.
And this is how I'm usually doing mock-ups for a single level now.
It's by going into the level, taking screenshots of each camera view in the level,
and then I stitch them together in Photoshop.
and I roughly sketch the landscape on top of that, already digitally.
And also again in this case, we are in the middle of the level,
so our emotional progression curve is kind of...
dipping downwards at that moment and this is exactly what the theme of this level is.
There are like a lot of waterfalls, you start at the top and you go downwards and the theme
of the level is basically everything's going down. And so in terms of coloring that was also
the idea of what we wanted to do, that we wanted to have something like a brighter
warmer top and as you sort of like move downwards it gets more blue and cold.
So now that I have the basic outlines I go in and put down the main sort of like diffuse colors
and make sure that no two hills that connect anywhere have the same color so it stays readable
once everything is rendered and then I add some more details to those diffuse colors.
and kind of extend the color range a little bit.
And then at this point,
or at this previous point, by the way,
I'm usually also adding gradients
and those color changes from top to bottom,
which I did not do here for some reason.
I think it was mainly because I was going to use
the shadow layer as sort of a ...
consistent way to change the colors and nails.
You can best see that sort of on the bottom two cliffs,
left and right, the red and the sort of greenish turquoise one
that it changes sort of from red to something more purple,
blue, and sort of like similar on the other side.
And so I added some sort of adjustment layer with a gradient,
so I would get the effect from the top being more vibrant
and warm to going something more blue and cool,
and added a couple of trees to that,
and basically the mock-up is done.
From here on, we try to get this into the game.
The way we do that is by first setting up the hill Textures
to get most of the big color blocks,
the big chunks into the Level
so we see what it will look like really quickly.
The way I do that is that I set up Textures
that look something like this.
So, I set up the colors, I set up the shapes,
and what goes where, I put that as it is into the level
to see if things work out with the curves
and if nothing really glitches out.
And so, I have these sort of like temp textures.
And then I pass it on to our support artist
who's actually mainly a character animator,
but also doing a lot of the art and the rendering.
And he adds.
he does the rendering and adds all of the details
to make it look good.
And before that, when all those textures are,
or most of those textures are in the level,
it looks something like this.
And
Once those are in, I again go through all the camera views and take new screenshots
and take those screenshots in 4K because our game is based on 4K resolution so it can be
played on like a super beefy PC.
but also it's actually a tablet game,
so you can play it on small resolutions as well.
But this is 4K is our base resolution.
So I go in there and I start drawing,
sketching the props in there
that I would then sort of like export
and put back into the game.
So.
I got this 4K screenshot and I put a single prop in there.
And that is now also sort of obvious, but when we started out working, like trying to
figure out how we would make our 4K pipeline work.
We thought we had to like each texture actually had to be like 4,000 by 4,000 pixels, which is not true obviously
so they are
in in the appropriate size according to this specific camera view and
Since we know what our camera views are like we can set those up in the according resolution
If there is ever a single prop in two different camera views,
where one is closer and one is further away,
we usually choose the one that is closer,
depending on how much of you actually see.
After that, once that is set up, I again pass it on to Brian,
who is doing the rendering, and then we put it into the game,
and we do that with all of the stuff around that,
and at some point, it looks like this,
which is pretty close to what it is going to be finally.
I also go into the level and start adding all these objects manually, like bushes and trees that
can behave dynamically and react to what you're doing, or they sway in the wind,
so they're separate elements. And I also add a couple of smaller rocks and details like that.
So this is the basic process of how we build and decorate our levels.
But obviously doing a game for mobile,
there are technical bottlenecks.
And these are the major three bottlenecks
are fill rate, loading times, and file size.
So fill rate basically is that you have
a lot of transparent pixels on the screen.
And the more transparent pixels you have on the screen
overlapping each other, the more performance it will cost.
we tried to tackle that by splitting the meshes
into transparent and opaque parts.
So we are using a plugin for Unity called SpriteSharp,
which does that for us.
It splits all the sprites in an opaque core
and sort of a...
an outline around that.
And that is important because both of them
are then added in the level as two separate game objects.
And one is rendered with an opaque shader,
and one is rendered with a transparent shader.
So this basically looks like, for example,
if you have something like a circle like this.
In Unity, it will actually create a mesh
that puts that texture on top that looks like this.
And the opaque core in this case is this.
So even if you have opaque pixels,
but you render them with a shader
that supports transparency, it will cost performance.
So if you can render those with a different shader
that is an opaque shader,
it will...
be a significant change in performance.
So we have this opaque core,
and then we have the outline around it,
and this part is the one that is rendered
with transparency, with alpha.
And this was, like, if you do it for all the sprites
in a level, that was that.
huge, huge, huge, huge performance increase.
That was the main thing that pushed our FPS upwards.
Also, one of the advantages that we have
is we have a very slow game,
so we can get away having 30 FPS in parts.
You do not really need 60 FPS for a game
about us old men walking slowly through the landscape.
One of the things that I learned when doing that,
when I was painting my Textures,
that I often did things like this.
It is not really good to see, so I did another shot of that,
cranking up the levels. This actually looks like this.
There are all these semi-transparent pixels somewhere.
When you put that in Unity, you get this,
and that is obviously not good. When doing that,
you have to make sure that the core actually is,
like you can pull up with a circular marquee tool
and make that part actually opaque.
Another problem is of course loading times.
We have tons of textures, it's super asset heavy
and we use sprite sheets like many other people as well.
It's quite a common approach
and we use level specific packing tags.
So only those.
Oh, there is nothing here. There you go.
Only those Textures are loaded in the Level
that we actually need.
And that generally works best with, like,
small to medium-sized sprites,
because the Atlas itself cannot be larger than 2048 by 2048.
So we have sort of like Level-specific sprite Atlases,
and sort of like the Atlas is used over multiple Levels.
And finally, for the file size,
what we do is to generate asset bundles for various devices.
This works mainly on iOS,
and it doesn't matter really for PC
because if you have to download 1.5 gigs, that's all right,
but if you have like a tiny iPhone, it's better
if you have like a smaller app size, right?
And so, the App Store has this feature called App Thinning.
And so, we basically generate four different packages
with different base resolutions where all the other sprites
are kind of scaled down toward a specific resolution,
create these four packages, upload them to the store,
and when you download the app,
sort of Apple knows which device you use
and gives you the appropriate package.
So this is basically it.
I hope this gave you a bit of an insight into our process
and how it work and how also like building a box
can sort of like help you find an art style
and make decisions.
But so a box is a great tool to help you do that.
But it can't give you all the answers.
So there's still a lot of manual labor
and experimentation involved to find the right.
solutions. So, also a box should kind of like always be a little bit flexible.
A box art is like if your rules are too rigid, you kind of get unreceptive for natural growth
and opportunities. So, for example, one of the rules is we have no text in the game, but we
actually broke that rule a little bit because we have these bits and pieces of French flavor text
that we're never going to translate. It's just on signs and things like that.
So, and goals and constraints usually work best
when they complement each other.
So, constraints that contradict each other
will stay contradictory up until the release of your game.
For example, if you want to make a game about permadeath,
but your sort of like constraint is maybe
that you are going to do something about encouraging.
playful curiosity, those two things might not mesh up together too well because every time
players playfully and curiously do try something
and they get a hammer over their head and die and have to restart again,
they're not going to do that anymore.
So, yeah, I think this is it. Thank you very much.
You can follow us on Twitter.
I'm also available for questions later on in one of the wrap-up rooms.
And, yeah, thanks for coming.
So, any questions?
No, good.
Oh, I have one question.
Oh, where?
I'm over here.
Oh, there you are, hi.
The way you're using art and the kind of simplicity
of the game mechanic reminds me a lot
of other games that do that,
that keep me into the game.
The game mechanic seems to be there
to keep me involved in the game.
primarily to enjoy the beauty of the art style.
It really becomes a work of art that can exist over time,
and that time is expanded because of the game mechanic,
and the art seems to be,
and in this case, the emotional narrative,
seems to be the primary goal.
Which are things, actually, I personally love games like that.
Is that something that you guys,
is that something also that you see as primary goals,
or is it?
So the question is that if our primary goal was to create gameplay that would make one
to spend people time in the game.
That's right, your primary goal is to make a beautiful work of art that people spend
time with, or your primary goal is to make a game?
We wanted to make something in between.
It definitely does have this experience first character to the game,
and we wanted to make or have a game mechanic that would support that.
But we always knew that the game mechanic around shaping hills
would never give really enough depth as a game mechanic
to create really brain-twisting, difficult puzzles.
But we were confident, or we felt that it was...
just good enough to keep players interested, but never frustrated.
So that is sort of the idea of how we wanted to design the game mechanically, in a way.
And yes, it is about experiencing the story and experiencing the world.
The other thing I love about it is it seems like, in this case, the game mechanic itself
also becomes a metaphor that really relates to the narrative itself.
This idea of reshaping hills, reshaping, and the idea of how that relates to memory.
That memory is a flexible thing that never is specific.
We tried to do that.
as much as possible without like enforcing it
and that it feels starts to get like rigid or cramped
or feel like forced in a way.
But there is, for example, this one level
where you have to move away hills
and you dig deeper, deeper, deeper
and he walks downward, downward, deeper, deeper, deeper
until he finds that one memory.
and that is sort of a metaphor
that goes from the gameplay to the narrative.
So these ideas definitely were something
that we consciously chose.
You remind me of stuff I love about Monument Valley
and other games.
Yes, yes, they're wonderful.
Thanks for making time.
They were a big inspiration, thanks.
Yeah.
All right, anybody else?
Yeah, yes, please.
I'm wondering if you have a deadline for settling down the R file,
because I saw you jumping back and forth on who should be saving on their personal accounts,
and who should be saving on their financial accounts.
Yes, so the question is if we had a deadline in various stages of the production.
Yes, we did, but we initially planned to only work 12 months on it.
Now it is...
14 months and we're still going to take a little bit longer to finish it
But we are sort of within our time frame
But our pre-production phase took a lot longer than we initially expected all this experimentation and and iteration
it took about five months and
But that is all working full time on the game.
So for example, building our box,
I think that took like way longer,
but that is something that needs calendar time.
That is something that you think about on and off
and sort of like have it in the back of your head
and then sit down sometime again,
talk about certain things or try to decide certain things.
But that took like six months
before we even started actually like working on the game.
We were working on grant applications.
budgeting and things like that.
And so we do have deadlines and we do have an idea
of how long things should take.
And we also make plans about how long
we want to spend on things.
But there is a certain amount of flexibility,
especially like in a smaller studio.
We feel you need to be agile and things need to
kind of like take their time to be able to sort of like,
grow and
kind of just sit there and develop themselves a little bit too.
Does that somehow answer your question?
Okay.
How long it took us until we had that final thing where we decided this is how we were going to do it.
So that for us was the pre-production phase that took about five months.
But then there was a lot of the vocabulary and how we would translate it to all the other levels.
that definitely was still took a while longer and is something that was also like sort of a little
bit of an ongoing process as we went along. Like by now everything is sort of like all the questions
are pretty much answered and we really can just kind of like produce that thing and and draw the
textures without having many questions anymore. So but yeah the initial phase was five months and
then the rest was kind of like along went along as we worked on it.
You're welcome.
All right. I think we're good to go.
Yeah, you can just ask me afterwards somewhere down the hall
if you have any questions. Come say hello.
Oh, yeah, and you can also, of course, play the game at the IGF booth
as well as at the Unity booth if you want to try it.
So, yeah, thanks again for coming.