Thanks everybody. My name is Chris
I'm Tyler. We're we're pretty much co everything on
Red Hook studios on darkest dungeon and just thanks very much for being here
There's a panel on writing sex scenes at the same time as this talk
So really appreciate you guys making them very poor choice to be here
So we're probably going to use the full 30 minutes,
unless miraculously we run short because of some reason
that hasn't happened yet.
But we're happy to talk to people in the wrap-up room
afterwards.
Just corner us, and they'll shoo us out of here
somewhere where we can talk.
And we'd love to talk about the challenges and things
you're facing in your studios.
So quick preface, this isn't like an instructional or prescriptive talk.
I find those really abrasive because I don't think there's any like
true flight path through, you know, something as personal as a partnership.
So we thought we would just try to expose our working relationship,
given that our company structure is 50-50, which is somewhat uncommon,
and we've had some troubles with that, and also some really good successes.
So this is really a subjective recounting of how we structure things and how we do it.
And hopefully there will be something in there for you guys
to apply to your own situations.
Yeah, and the other thing is we don't talk a lot about the
team in this talk.
So apologies to the team members who are sitting here.
This is really a focus on-
It's our time, not their time.
So a little bit of background, Red Hook,
we were already, I guess, veterans in the industry
of various places, but Red Hook started
with just Chris and I and an idea,
and the only money we had was savings
from working at other studio jobs.
And so this partnership has seen it go from that
to something that ended up being quite a bit more successful
than we ever thought it would be, to be honest,
making a game not for everyone about.
the grim dark.
And so we've seen different challenges.
We've seen the no money challenge
and we've seen the money challenge.
And along the way there's been a lot of things
that we've had to tackle.
As Chris mentioned, we are co-presidents,
we're co-everything.
We don't do the same things all the time,
but sometimes we do.
Our skills are very different,
our personalities are very different,
but we share all the decision making.
And as you might expect, that's sometimes cool
and sometimes really messy and complicated
as probably some of the team members.
They'll be in the wrap-up room too, if you want to ask.
Yeah, venting.
Having two bosses is not always, it's not streamlined, really.
So we'll get into that a bit.
But the bottom line, I guess, of this whole thing,
and if there's any real context to put on it,
is that we truly believe that the game would not
have been as successful without that messy, imperfect
structure.
So.
all the reasons why you partner are pretty self-explanatory so we're gonna
gloss over the good stuff just like a steam review we're gonna ignore most of
the good stuff and take it for granted and then really focus on that just the
trash it's not the first hundred hours that matters is that last ten minutes
yeah it's a slap in the face wow
So, obviously, you can accomplish more together than apart sometimes, having two people.
The key takeaway of this talk is two people can do more work than one person.
I know.
Let it, like, sink in.
There's moral support.
You can really leverage different but compatible perspectives.
That's all great and pretty self-explanatory.
What sometimes gets overlooked, especially early on when you're talking about
partnering up with someone is you can lose the realism with all the enthusiasm.
All of these benefits of partnership have a very real price.
You can have competing egos, you can be fighting each other for the authorship of the thing.
There's a huge potential for conflict, arguments, and many, many partnerships flame out.
I mean, we're not the police, but like the police.
Simon and Garfunkel, obviously.
He worked up the Simon and Garfunkel thing,
and I was like, I don't know if it's gonna land.
It's there, it's so old now.
The hit band Simon and Garfunkel.
So really the thesis here is
partnership is a double-edged sword.
We're not gonna hit this analogy the whole time,
but if you don't know how to use it,
you're gonna hurt yourself.
So I think this is pretty common usually when you decide you're going to partner
with someone hopefully you know them and you've done some things but sometimes
it's just you're sharing ambitions you like I want to make a game you want to
make him let's do it in our case we had known each other for years we worked at
we first met another studio.
and had a chance to kind of work nearby each other
on different projects and then work together
on some projects.
So we started growing an appreciation
for the other person's skill.
And that planted definitely a seed.
That took many years to germinate.
And over those years, we ended up going other places,
working, doing a million other things.
We became friends.
And probably the most common thing that we did
is we'd get together once a month and play poker
with a few other friends in Vancouver.
And that alternated between like really heavy poker
at the beginning of that, maybe like six years,
and then went into therapy sessions and then back to poker
because it was taking like an hour to play a hand.
But during that time, we got to know each other
and not only what their skills and values are,
but ambitions, that was really important.
But just like relationships and other things,
timing is everything.
So once, you know, we had talked about working together.
We actually tried a web comic at one point.
It didn't make it very far.
It never got out there, so don't go hunting.
You know, we thought about making a really elaborate
choose your own adventure,
because we were figuring out ways to blend our skills.
So when the timing finally came up,
let's say we both had disasters at our previous companies,
which ended up being really fortuitous.
But we're like, okay, we're doing this.
But we discussed a lot of the hard stuff up front.
And as you might expect, the first thing is like,
okay, well, who's the boss?
As shortcut, spoiler alert, nobody's the boss.
But the biggest thing was the 50-50 talk.
There was...
a proposal for 5149 for really good symbolic reasons.
And then that really, we had to confront those no-go lines.
And we ended up at 50-50,
and I guess the main message from this is like,
and that was just as symbolic as the 5149.
You wanna have these discussions up front.
I guess we're not trying to be prescriptive, but.
It's a bad idea to have that discussion after you've
created something of value.
Like even if it's just, OK, now we have a full design.
And it forced us to work through something hard
at the beginning just to test, test ourselves.
Quite a scene in that Starbucks.
Great reason to partner up.
You can leverage your compatible interests, your skills.
You can carve out areas of expertise.
Really feels like you've got someone who's got your back.
You're able to make progress in multiple SKUs at once.
Again, glossing over the positives.
Yeah, the positives are kind of boring.
However.
As you might expect, apologies to all the Tony Danza fans,
but who is the boss?
The reality is, you know, some areas require a lead.
You can't just, hey, we're gonna just link arms
and make every decision.
Our skills are different, our minds are different,
and that's really difficult.
I think that's an area of can-be-heavy team confusion.
It still happens.
Chris will give a piece of direction.
I'll come in and contravene that accidentally,
or vice versa.
One thing that is, I guess, been really helpful,
but is also challenging, is the right now versus the future.
Sometimes you take on a role to get it done,
or this needs done, or I'll do this,
or maybe you're just better positioned
to make that decision right then.
But then the other person's thinking, oh wait, did I, you know, you, you give feedback to
the composer and then I'm thinking, did I just, you know, am I no longer the music guy?
Was I ever the music guy?
I don't know.
But these are easy to think about in the short term, but they become really scary when you
think about totality of like, am I handing over the keys to this part of the business?
Yeah, some partnerships I think are really effective,
because you might have two completely different skill
sets, so the business guy, the creative guy.
And we have a lot of overlapping interests and skills.
And so for me, I spent years and years and years of my career
going up through the art track, concept artist, art lead,
art director, studio art director,
back to concept artist.
And the whole time just fighting tooth and nail
to get into that secret room with the designers and the story
guys.
I felt like I had a lot of ideas.
I felt like they were.
like really good.
But no one was listening to me.
So, but in those larger, you know, triple A structures,
they're compartmentalized for good reason, I guess.
But it was very, very hard for me to actually get to the place
where I felt like I was being able to express all of my creative potential.
So that's why we've started the game.
I want authorship on the design.
I want to be a part of it.
It's important to me.
But funnily enough, that's a huge overlap with Tyler.
Yeah, I mean my background, my business card has said game designer for a long time.
And, you know, originally, and it's really simple, you know, we look at each other and it's like,
okay, you're an artist, I'm a game designer, let's...
Despite what you're seeing here.
Make a...
Ha ha.
So...
You look like the artist.
Ha ha ha.
And so, you know, I, that's a big,
that's what I'm bringing to the partnership
is that background.
And, but it's not that simple, you know,
like, so there's a lot of,
the reality is like Darkest Dungeon was created by
all of us, and a lot of the design decisions
were made by Chris and I working together.
And it's definitely challenges the ego a little bit,
right, to figure out like what's your role
and what's my identity,
because sometimes you enter that
with your own self identity.
And that tension is really hard,
but it's also definitely really key to making things better
because basically an outcome of that tension
is that you make better decisions together.
despite our extremely similar address code,
we're different people, we think differently.
And that means two sets of eyes,
but sometimes two sets of eyes just represents,
like, you know, okay, someone might,
you're thinking the same,
you might catch a mistake that they missed.
But when you fundamentally look at problems differently,
it's better than that.
It's a way to solve things from different angles
and stress test all your decisions.
And it really does apply to...
to everything, you know, not just design,
but business decisions, strategy, staffing, all that,
and I think marketing.
And I think that's been really helpful.
And to like illustrate a little bit of our differences,
I guess, using the poker analogy again,
you know, Chris can read people really well.
He can play the situation.
He can play the person.
Manipulate? No.
He can...
That's not a nice word.
He can take the temperature of the situation really well.
And that's a real advantage to have that sort of like bird's-eye view
and that intuitive gut feel.
Conversely, playing poker against Tyler, you can be very confident
that whatever move he made calculates the pot odds,
is fundamentally correct, maybe not right in the moment,
but absolutely mathematically the most common sense,
sound choice to make.
a lot more methodical, a lot more numbers-oriented,
and communication-wise, I'm French-Canadian,
so give me a glass of wine and we'll just hash this shit out.
Like, it's fine, we'll just get right into it,
we'll make a decision, we'll move forward.
Tyler's a little bit more asynchronous,
so we've had to adapt our communication styles
where I can be bigger and bombastic
and then know that he needs to go away,
take it, think about it, parse it a little bit,
and just adjusting our workflow back and forth like that
has been really, really helpful.
Devil's Advocate is great fun, especially for me. I'm a huge fan of the devil and all of his advocacy
It's it's more than that though. It's necessary
And I think you know human nature is when you hear someone argue passionately for a point of view a perspective
You assume that this is something that they believe in
And we really tried to break that down and argue passionately for things that we didn't believe in.
So that we could really stress test the correct answer.
And so we spent a lot of time trading positions on things.
Even when, you know, let's say my gut was against it, I would argue as hard as I could
for the reasons why we should do something.
So, anecdotally, before we launched the early access of the game,
we were broke, like we were running out of money.
Everybody on the team was running out of money.
It was very, very stressful.
And we had shopped around looking for publishers here at GDC,
and we met a lot of nice people, and they all wanted 30%.
And then they wanted to recoup their ad buy,
and it was going to be just really hard to create a scenario in our minds
where that made a lot of sense.
But finally, at the 11th hour, this group came forward,
and they said, well, we'll give you $500,000.
as an advance.
And my gut was like,
no, we should live and die by the decisions that we made.
We spent a long time worrying, stressing, and bleeding for this.
It's three months out from release.
Let's just go for it.
We earned the right to at least, you know, watch it unfold.
And I felt like the die had already been cast.
But I remember arguing very passionately for why we should take the money.
You know, I got a mortgage, I've got a family, everybody was stressed, we could pay people.
There was a million reasons why it made sense to take that cash.
Yeah, and that situation I think we looked at it from both angles.
I mean, our message here is not, don't go with publishers.
It's just more of a reflection that we were pretty late in the game.
We had already kick-started, we had already created value.
And so we also looked at the numbers side and said,
like, wait, it's two months before we go early access.
you know, does that risk profile,
does that amount of points make sense?
And we both arrived at the same conclusion,
and it was really hard to turn it down, to be honest.
But it felt good.
Later.
So it's great to have all this amazing decision-making power
at your fingertips, really.
Well, at arm's length.
It's not that close.
But really, you can only leverage
that when you're aligned emotionally,
when you're in the same head space
and you've got the same mental landscape.
And a development cycle, as I'm sure everybody here knows,
three, five years, a lot can change.
A lot can change.
I had a baby girl partway through Darkest Dungeon.
Do not recommend having a child.
when you're trying to make an indie game.
A second child, even worse.
I should have run the numbers on that decision.
And more seriously, Tyler experienced some death
in his family.
And these things have real consequences,
especially on small teams and especially
where there's very few decision makers.
And you can find yourself trying to make good decisions
by putting your heads together, but if you're out of sync,
it doesn't work.
Yeah, and I think it's very common that you're aligned on the game, or you got into it for
a reason, you have the same goal of, I don't know, walking up on the IGF stage and grabbing
a trophy or selling, or whatever it is.
But those externalities are not always aligned, and that's the thing.
When you first get in it, you're like, okay, you're not really worried about the long term,
but if you have a good partnership, you're going to want to keep working.
So in my case...
Yeah, like Chris mentioned, like six weeks after early access, my father passed away,
and then just a year ago, one of my brothers passed away.
So two deaths within one game development cycle, not recommended also.
It was hard, and we had to lean on each other, had to lean on the team.
It was tough.
And basically last year, I realized, OK, we got Crimson Court out.
And it was like, I need a break.
We are not aligned right now on just the life,
but not so much the game.
And so those were hard discussions.
They weren't easy discussions, but we ultimately, I did.
I went away, and I took the better part
of a couple months off.
And Chris, that meant more responsibility on Chris
during that time.
So those are.
Handled it beautifully. So yeah, so those were hard discussions
But also those are real things that you might have to face over the course of several years
And I have a problem with this slide.
So Chris has dismissed the Highwaymen.
I'm renowned in this.
Why am I looking at it?
I'm not even aware of what's happening.
Because I've got your back.
Yeah, I know.
But he's just, I'll handle this.
I try to be sincere like one time.
I know.
It doesn't work.
It just looks like I'm completely
oblivious to what's happening.
Anyway, this is an obvious benefit.
You don't have to do everything yourself.
But paradoxically, having a partner who's very competent
and focused on another area of the business off,
especially working as a distributed team,
you can create a real nice narrative
around how you're doing more work
than anyone else who's ever lived.
It's very, very easy to fall into that trap.
And you can get backed into a corner if you're forced to do a couple of jobs maybe you didn't
want to do, like, oh, I got to do the UI, and now I'm like, I'm doing all the UI.
It just doesn't, it's very easy to fall into that pitfall and feel like the grass is always
greener, you know, the other guy's got it easy, and start to feel like the partnership
is becoming unbalanced.
Which, again, when you have overlapping disciplines and you're 50-50, it can really spell trouble.
over time I think what I struggled with in this area was
the the
art in the game sat on, I thank god I have Trudy working with us now, but for
the core game was all on me and I felt a really
uh... a lot of pressure to deliver high quality stuff the best I could
uh... but in early access specifically
Tyler would be like, OK, we're getting ready for the patch.
How's the art coming together?
I'm like, yeah, it looks really good.
But it's coming along.
And I'm like, how's the design?
He's like, oh, you know what?
I looked at Excel, and it fired out there.
We'll see what the community says.
We'll just see what they say.
And you know what?
Paraphrasing.
It's colorful.
I said I was French-Canadian.
So I felt a disproportionate amount of pressure
to do finished work, where I felt like over
on the other side, it's like, oh, it's
just work in progress.
Yeah, so that frames your view of things.
And so the pressure I was feeling simultaneously
with a lot of that going on is some weird reason
several years ago I went back and got an MBA
because I was interested in entrepreneurship.
So I started doing more of these business operations thing,
liaison with accountants and lawyers.
I mean, these things just happen.
They suck up time.
Someone proposes a potential partnership,
you're excited and you're looking into all this.
And I felt like I was doing more and more things just
to keep the wheels turning.
Like when it was just a couple of us in a room,
there was not much of that.
But once there's a community, store for instance to manage,
all these things, it just grows and grows.
We all know this, right?
It's so much work.
And so I was feeling like, oh, I'm
having to do these things that are not, they're very thankless.
And they're kind of hidden.
It's like maintaining the car just so someone else
can drive it all the time.
And so I think it's easy to get buried in your own perspective.
Another benefit is, I guess it's related to the not having to do it all yourself, but
passion is infectious.
I'd like to think of the darkest dungeon parties, you know, someone fails their affliction check,
other characters get stress because cowardice and fear is infectious.
So is heroism, you know, and we even have that mechanic.
If someone goes virtuous, then they can start stress healing other people in the party.
I mean, that's exactly how it works on the team, too.
This one is, I think, like the two bosses one,
is really probably one of the hardest challenges.
We got into this because we want to make games
that we come up with, not that people tell us to do.
And that does result in sharing.
and sharing authorship, sharing credit,
seeing things referred to in articles or other things that,
hey, wait, I actually did that,
but they attributed that to the other person.
And again, we're not talking about the team here,
and I understand there's a lot of angles in it,
but just each other, trying to maintain that tension of,
we made this together, it's not always easy.
Yeah, and it's a creeping death.
It's a slow thing.
It's not like one thing happens and you're like,
suddenly you feel boxed out of your own game.
But you know, anecdotally, Valve emails Tyler,
hi Tyler, we want to put the game on sale.
I'm like, okay, why not?
Or I email them and say, please let us put it on sale.
That's more.
And I'm CC'd, which is cool.
And then, you know, I see him on Slack and he's like,
okay, Dana, I need you to check out these numbers.
Hey, this looks good.
I'm gonna talk to PowerUp about this other thing.
And then there's an article that comes out,
you know, deep dive, game director, Tyler Sigmund.
And it's like, over the course of a couple of weeks,
a few things happen and you can, again,
build that sort of sense of like,
wow, am I getting lost in, you know, the swimming pool?
I don't know why you get lost in a swimming pool.
I should have...
it's a it's not a good one that's a really good to be where a lagoon
perhaps yet
uh... but we develop this way of kind of coping with this is we again we really
try to talk candidly it's not easy to do but
we sat down a look we both
want credit for this game that we both made
and that's natural and normal and this isn't like we don't spend all the time
talking about how great is have credit
But we made sure that when we do a solo interview or something, we credit the other person and
shout them out, and that helps take the edge off.
And we try to share or alternate interviews or things that are really important to us
like being right here.
We're sharing it.
It would have been maybe, who's to say if it would have been better if it was just me?
I don't know.
Who is to say?
We'll never know.
You know, it's not practical for that always to be equal.
And I mean, we'd like to think we're above worrying
about things like credit, but it does matter, right?
That's like your reputation and also, you know,
it's a discussion point, so it's not always easy.
So yeah, basically from that conversation,
we evolved this, this one of our big like kind of takeaways
is don't let anything fester,
especially when you have this sort of odd arrangement
of overlapping skills and 50-50 ownership on something.
And we have a zero tolerance policy for anything that gums up the gears.
And what that looks like practically is somebody says something that the other person doesn't
sit well with them.
And if that feeling, however ephemeral or vague it is, lasts for longer than a day,
the victim in this case has an obligation to raise it and discuss it with the other
person.
And that's very tricky because a feeling bad is not something that's...
easy to solve and and the causes the root causes might not be something that
are immediately apparent and it requires the other person to be extremely patient
and to put down whatever they were doing
at the time that the you know the wounded party so this is a man we gotta
talk
and sometimes you know it's inopportune
but making that time means that our machinery is at least free
from this sort of sticky goop that can kind of accumulate over time.
You know, death by a thousand cuts, or like just feeling wounded every day for
for three months kind of builds up, and we just refuse to allow that stuff to
accumulate. But there's a time cost to it. There's a maintenance cost.
Yeah, I think one of the huge benefits of talking sooner rather than later, if any of
you have been to relationship counseling, you probably know this too.
Not that I have ever.
All my relationships are perfect.
There's no point.
But you diffuse assumptions fast, right?
It's easy to sort of construct, especially if you're a little more introverted, it's
easy to construct sort of a Tolkien-esque, like Cimmerillion backstory of...
of why this person did this thing that hurt your feelings
and create motivations and start constructing a scenario.
Is this the beginning of a change in dynamic?
But when you just go right to the heart of it and talk,
then often you find out that, oh no,
maybe they just did it obliviously.
They weren't trying, it was not even a thought.
And those diffusing assumptions is really powerful.
So another thing that we found really useful,
and it's taken quite a while to totally formalize this,
even just how we refer to it, is veto power.
We don't have to agree on everything that happens,
but nothing happens unless we each approve it,
generally speaking.
Especially, I'm talking big decisions here and things.
And so the concept of veto power,
that if something is truly something
we don't want to live with,
or we think it's bad for the company or the game,
we can veto.
And that pays the way for differing levels of enthusiasm,
or even being able to give power to the other person
based on their expertise.
Like, hey, I trust you with this call.
I don't hate it so much that I feel like we should stop it.
I don't necessarily love it, but I trust you.
And so pardon the reference to current geopolitical climate,
but it's a little bit like the nuclear keys.
You each need one.
You each need to turn it to.
to uh... start the business. Maybe I should do just a secure lock. Yeah. We each need to turn the key to open the secure lock.
You know I have an employer thing too. You know I hate that stuff. I'm sorry.
The other benefit of structuring this sort of like veto power
and maybe some of you are thinking, yeah but how do you even get everything done?
But it really helps relax the pace where I can see
things that maybe I'm worried about or that I think in advance I might not like.
I don't need to jump on them right at that moment because I can rest assured that
you know when when it comes time to make a call
I've got to green light it and the same thing with Tyler.
So it really helps take some of the pressure and tension down and you don't
feel like someone else is sort of like
you know driving the car off the road or in a direction that you're
unsure of.
So another aspect of working on a multi-year project
is just nothing static.
And recognizing this is really helpful,
you know, as we've gone into just how situations can change.
But the truth is, like, your partnership
is going to change too.
for all those reasons and other ones that we haven't mentioned.
And a real good concept that we use is like,
or think about is solvable versus manageable.
It's really wrong to think that
every issue in your partnership is solvable.
There's a lot that you just have to keep it from
becoming a conflagration out of control.
You have to manage it, you have to address it,
it will grow again,
you prune it, you weed it,
and that's something we do constantly actually.
So really, it's not a sword, it's a marriage.
I had this epiphany like a year and a half ago,
I was lying in bed with my wife and I was like,
you know, whoa, whoa, team I.
Like, it's funny, you know, it's like I'm married to Tyler
and she's like, yeah, no shit.
So maybe she should be giving this talk.
When I got married to my actual wife,
my dad took me aside and he's kind of old school
and he's like, here's the deal, son.
It's only a good marriage if you feel like you're doing 65%
of the work and getting 20% of the recognition.
And I'm like, OK, that's kind of old school.
And he also says the only voice a man has is the in voice,
so you've got to take it with a grain of salt.
But I think that's important to feel like you're always
in a state of overperforming.
But you have to take time out to praise and recognize
the efforts and the work that your partner is doing
and restore some intimacy.
You know, we go on dates.
We'll go and get a steak and have a couple glasses of red wine
and really just try to get out of our heads and, you know, away from the game a little bit.
And it's kind of funny to dress it up this way,
but really it's a powerful tool to sort of really ease things out
and help us both like just relax a little bit.
And just, again, maintaining is really important.
We have shared a kiss during early access.
He threatened to do it.
If early access did well enough that we could survive,
it happened.
It was a good moment.
But no, the bottom line here is that.
is that it does challenge our egos.
It does challenge a lot of pieces of us.
But the bottom line is we need each other.
And we look at each other, and we know that we could not
have made something like this without each other.
And so that forms a basis for working through the kinks.
And that's us.
Wait for it.
Yeah.
We have time for one or two questions.
If you've got a question for Tyler or Chris,
please come to one of the mics in the aisles.
We'll probably leave this slide up.
This, it just has a bell in particular.
No, no, go one more.
I think there's some more content.
I think it's done.
I think that's the end of the slides.
I have a question for you while we're waiting
for other people to possibly come up.
So you talked about doing the,
figuring out the 50-50 thing early on.
Did you also discuss what would happen
if one of you decided to leave the company later on?
Because that actually happened to me
with a partnership that I was in before,
and it was tricky.
Um...
No?
No.
We had an interim agreement when we started that, um...
we would, the ownership would shift back
because I had a sketchbook that I had written
Darkest Dungeon in and had like a bunch of drawings
and some notes and that was the 51-49 argument.
So we had an agreement that if we couldn't get
to make anything, if things imploded too quickly,
then I'd be able to walk away with my sketchbook.
But then once we started to build something of value
and really create a game together,
we just broadened that to be sort of a standard
like shareholder incorporation shotgun clause thing
and just went from there.
But there was a bit of time where it was kind of,
I guess, in hindsight,
maybe we shouldn't be giving any advice.
You got one?
All right.
Hello.
Hey.
So you talk about having a lot of overlapping interests
as well as skills, and both also having veto power.
So I guess my question is, what would you
do when, say, Tyler, you have a lot of opinions about art,
but they conflict with something that?
like a pre-existing idea or another direction,
how would you resolve that kind of conflict?
Sure.
Especially if you were really, really opposed
to a certain direction.
Yeah.
I'm going to slightly shift here,
because art is the one area that actually isn't that hard,
because he's a fucking amazing artist,
and I cannot draw shit.
So that one's pretty easy.
But UI, oh my god, UI.
We battle so hard.
We have in-jokes.
We tease each other.
It gets, we get angry.
But like not really fun teasing?
Yeah.
There are moments of momentum where, you know,
it's just somebody's gotta,
we, remember one of the slides said like,
is this a dying on the hill thing?
So there's a lot of momentum sometimes where somebody,
you know, has already taken it a certain far.
And so a lot of times it's a practical decision,
because we're like, look, this is almost finished,
or we have it figured out, and I know you don't love it,
but now we gotta go back to the wall and figure out,
and we have a deadline.
So sometimes, you know, then that's when you can do that,
say, well, okay, I don't love it, but if it doesn't work,
Like, I'm, we're gonna have a chat.
And we've done some of those, like,
do your thing, I'm gonna be back to visit
if it doesn't work out.
And so there's no one answer to that,
but there's a lot of clash,
just not so much on the actual art.
I generally say, ooh, that looks cool.
Okay, so there's a bit of trust that like,
something about it will work,
but if it's really a failure, then you can revisit it.
Yeah, we showed off the Crimson Court promo art and I was like super amped about it because I'm like mosquito vampires
it's gonna change the world and
We put it out and then Tyler go hey, man
I'm not really wild about these bugs people
He's like they're all drawn so I was like, okay
But it took a little bit of trust because I'm like,
it's going to be great.
Here's why it all works.
I think the thematics are super strong.
So it's just something you have to talk about.
And we trade victories.
That's the last thing I'll say.
All right, that's going to be the last question.
If you have more questions for Tyler or Chris,
please come on up and ask them.
And make sure you fill out your email surveys
to give them feedback on what you thought about their talk.
And before you go, let's give them
one final round of applause.
Thank you.
Thanks, guys.