Hi everyone, welcome to Lessons from Labor Organizers.
We're gonna be doing kind of a moderated Q&A panel
at the beginning and then halfway through
we're gonna switch into kind of an open mic audience Q&A.
So be thinking about your questions leading up to that.
Yeah, so my name is Emma Canema.
I'm a labor organizer with Game Workers Unite.
I'm joined today by Justin Melito, the Director of Organizing of the Writers Guild of America
East, Liz Schuler, the Secretary-Treasurer of the AFL-CIO, Linda Dow, a labor organizer
with SAG-AFTRA, and Kevin Agawadse, the Treasurer and Organizer with Game Workers Unite UK Union.
Yeah, it's a great group of people.
So before we jump into any questions,
I think we might just go down the row
and do a brief self-introduction,
maybe expand on what your title actually means
in terms of the work you do.
Justin, do you wanna start?
Sure.
Hello, and thank you so much to Game Workers Unite
and to all of you who are so interested
in the idea of collective action
and perhaps building unions in your industry.
My name is Justin Melito.
I'm the Director of Organizing
for the Writers Guild of America East.
What that means is as an organizer, I work towards helping people who want to build unions in the industries
that they work in
into the House of Labor. And so specifically
at the Writers Guild,
we're the union for film and television workers. There's an East Coast and a West Coast union.
We also have a large number of news members,
about 3,500 members.
in New York City and the East Coast.
Recently, that number is over 5,000
because we've organized about 20 digital publishers.
So places like Vice, Vox, Future,
Talking Points Memo, Salon, Slate, and a bunch of others
have organized with us fairly recently.
So that's the work that I've been involved
in with a team of organizers most recently
to expand the power of the union to new groups.
Thank you.
Liz?
Hi everyone, Liz Schuller, I'm the Secretary-Treasurer of the National AFL-CIO, which is an umbrella
organization of 55 unions.
Riders Guild East and SAG-AFTRA are two of those.
We represent 12.5 million working men and women in the United States and Canada.
We are working across all industries and sectors which are, you know, anywhere from professional football players to professional technical engineers to teachers and construction workers.
And my role is basically as an organizer as well. I came from my local union out of the electrical workers.
And we are...
excited to talk about the future of work and what that means for working people,
what this country is starting to look like in terms of employment, and
getting your fair share of the wealth that you create on the job.
Linda.
Hi, I'm Linda.
I'm an organizer with SAG-AFTRA.
Right now I work closely with voice actors.
Those who work in video games, foreign language dubbing,
and TV animation.
So I deal with new organizing and internal organizing.
So new organizing is similar to what Justin said,
where we're trying to organize new shops.
But with internal organizing, we also
deal with collective actions and building collective power
to have leverage while we negotiate.
existing contracts.
Awesome, thank you.
And yeah, thank you again for being on the panel.
So I kind of want to start off with,
I think probably a question for Kevin.
What lessons have you and the other kind of fellow workers
and organizers from Game Workers Unite,
what lessons have you kind of learned
and what obstacles have you been having to overcome
as you kind of spin up your new national union
and starting to organize game workers?
Right, so as opposed to unionizing shop by shop,
like performing a national union,
we sort of have a lot of members,
so like the most union friendly in a lot of companies,
but we don't necessarily yet have big membership
in any particular shop.
So it's nice that everybody in the union right now
is very active and wants to get involved,
but we still need to build campaigns
in all the shops in the UK.
The other sort of thing is we spoke to a lot of the
big and established unions and like the games industry space where there's a lot of like
highly trained professionals that do that like very different things from art to programming
community management and it is very like globalized international it's like a space that traditional
unions
aren't super sure how to approach yet.
That's a space that has been traditionally not unionized,
and it is a challenge to figure out how to do it.
Yeah, and I mean, you're talking about, you know,
spaces that are traditionally not unionized just,
and you, of course, have quite a bit of experience
organizing kind of new territories
where workers aren't unionized.
Can you maybe expand on some of the challenges
involved in that?
Yeah, in 2015, some writers from Gawker Media, just show of hands, do people know about Gawker
and maybe the campaign to organize at Gawker?
Great.
Came to our office because they were interested in organizing a union.
And we immediately began to work with them in an approach that in some ways was different
than traditional labor organizing approach and in some ways quite similar.
The thing that was different is that the sort of premium on transparency from people that
worked at Gawker made for a process that was much more horizontal in terms of how the organizing
happened.
meaning that all of the decisions and all of the activities were public,
and so public, in fact, that they were all on a blog as people were deliberating
on whether or not to organize, which is pretty unique.
I share that anecdote because the most important thing,
the most important lesson really there is to make sure that we listen
as organizers and as the labor movement.
You know, when we're trained as organizers, we're told we have two ears and one mouth,
and therefore we should be doing twice as much listening.
So as an institution and as organizers, we listened very closely to what it was that
people in the digital media sector were saying.
They were talking about overwork, underpay, the precariousness of the industry, some traditional
bread and butter.
labor issues, but they also spoke a lot about diversity and equity and the need for transparency
and decision making.
And so we emphasized in our communications the importance of that.
And in fact, as organizers, really just facilitated the communication that happened as opposed
to being the institution and communicating on behalf of.
of the workers. They also had the added benefit of being professional communicators, so it would be
pretty foolish for us to redo their communications about why unions were important.
And then lastly, one lesson that was extremely important and has maintained...
throughout is having a movement approach, meaning that we're not talking about just
organizing one shop and one place that happens to be either the bad place or the harder place
to work. We're talking about organizing the entire industry so that standards are set
across the board no matter which company you happen to be working on any given day, which
of course, as you know, is very important when in this economy as people jump from job
to job, we no longer live in an economy that
people go to work at one factory for 30 or 40 years, they jump from place to place.
And so therefore the union effort and movement has to be
across all companies, across the entire sector,
and really based on the labor as opposed to any given particular company.
And then lastly, very much using the technological tools that people use at work,
having those tools be used in the organizing campaigns.
So use of Slack, use of Twitter campaign were all very effective for developing solidarity and building strong unions.
Yeah, I feel like Game Workers Unite has also kind of taken up a lot of those approaches,
right, using communication methods that workers are already using, being more flexible, thinking
about building movement as opposed to just focusing on individual shops.
Yeah, that's really interesting and I think that applies a lot to our industry as well.
Linda, I think you do a lot of work in terms of organizing with voice actors,
and I've always been really impressed how voice actors are often directly involved in the organizing campaigns,
just in the way that the writers Justin works with have been directly involved.
Can you speak to a little bit of that process, and maybe touch on how you feel like voice actors
and organizing with SAG-AFTRA relates into the larger labor movement within the games industry as a whole?
Sure. So maybe I should start off by giving a little overview of the last
interactive negotiations and the strike. So when we're in negotiations 2016 we
had been negotiating trying to reach a new agreement for almost two years. So
finally the proposals were too far apart for us to feel that it was a good
agreement. So eventually there was you know a strike authorization vote and we
did go on strike.
And three of the main issues were, one was transparency.
They wanted to know either the name of the game
or the genre or if there's sexually explicit
or racially explicit or violence in the game
so that they can make a decision
on whether they want to audition or even work on the game.
And secondary payments was a big deal
because with actors, usually they,
get residuals on other contract areas.
And this is the model that works for them
because it's not guaranteed that they work every day,
not even guaranteed that they work once a month.
So having a secondary payment on the back end
really helps while they're in between gigs.
And the other issue was vocal stress
because a lot of these games,
they're exerting themselves, they're screaming,
they're dying like a million different ways.
So like vocal stress was a big issue because.
if they strain their vocal cords too much,
they might get bleeding, swelling,
might have to get surgery,
so that means they can't work
if any of those things happen.
So that's kind of like the overview,
the big issues that they were fighting for.
So even while they were negotiating.
and bargaining for two years, they started off doing one-on-ones.
So it's basically doing your initial conversations, figuring out who's the leaders in the community,
who's really influential, and then building like a leadership structure, kind of like
a core group to strategize and reach the larger community to assess support.
And they did things where they would do house meetings,
they would do caucuses at the offices,
smaller group meetings, mixers,
and then obviously they had a Facebook group
that they would chat with and do education,
and they did a newsletter using MailChimp and...
just always keeping the community in the loop and educated about everything.
And they still do that now where even though there's no contract,
there's no negotiations happening,
that they still actively use that Facebook and that newsletter
to keep everybody updated.
And they're continually doing issue-based organizing.
because we couldn't get exact language for what is vocal stress on the contract,
that they're continually partnering up with industry professionals
to do all-day workshops and evening panels
so that we can look into this even more and figure out,
oh, how do we protect voice actors from losing their voice?
And I mean, Kevin, so I mean, I feel like a lot of what Linda just said is stuff that
you all do in the UK, right?
A lot of it really, it seems to boil down to community building, right?
At the end of it, right?
Yeah.
Can you speak to like, how community building works into your organizing model in the UK?
I mean there's a lot of those things that we do, right?
We have a newsletter that is bi-weekly, we have a Discord where people can speak to us.
We are going to have a weekly meeting just with our membership where everybody can just join
and ask questions about what they're doing or ask how they can get involved.
We have regional groups and local meetings once a month in different regions.
So just people can meet up in real life and actually get to know each other.
We just constantly communicate what we're doing.
And it's very important because a lot of people in the game industry have essentially no idea
what a union is, how it works and what it does.
And it's really important to show how we're helping people.
which we actively do, but it can be hard if you're just working somewhere, you're crunching,
you're trying to focus on yourself or maybe on your mental health or your kid,
then it's really hard to like actively stay engaged in what the union is doing.
So we need to show people the good we're doing.
Yeah, I feel like education has to be a very core component,
especially when it comes to these new territories
where people aren't familiar with unionization,
they aren't familiar with a lot of the labor rights
and things that come with that.
Liz, so in a lot of your work,
you do a lot of involvement with young folks
in the industries.
who are wanting to get into labor and organizing new territory.
What component does education play in that, and how does the AFL-CIO play into some of those things?
Absolutely, and it's been so interesting to listen to the panelists so far
because I think you're seeing a lot of examples of creative and innovative organizing across different sectors,
and I want to compliment Emma because...
what you all have done to come together collectively already just since last year.
I think it was birthed, right, at this conference.
Yes, it's just been tremendous because it does take some guts, right, to step out there
and talk about these issues, and there's a lot at stake.
And what I've been hearing from the panelists so far, the theme is, is workers taking risks
and workers who want to get a return on the value that they are creating for these companies.
and in the economy.
And I don't think it's a lot to ask
when you're in an industry
that is three times the size of Hollywood
for you to be getting a fair return on the work
and the risk that you are putting into
the product that you're creating.
So, that is what it means to come together in union, whether it's in a union or collectively
in some other form, right?
And that's the beauty of this is the law protects workers who want to come together collectively
no matter what your workplace looks like or what kind of work you do.
So, that's what the AFL-CIO tries to do as an umbrella organization is lift up the organizing
of the various affiliated unions that...
belong to the AFL-CIO, but really speaking out for working people
across the economy, no matter if you're in a union or not.
Because we all deserve basic rights on the job, we all deserve fair pay
and protections, and equality,
and transparency, and accountability, which was spoken to earlier on the panel
as well.
And so it really is about this power dynamic.
And what we're seeing not just in your industry, but everywhere is that there seems to be this
concentration where the profits are going to a handful of people and the working people
are the ones getting the short end of the stick, not getting the value on the risk and
the return that you should be seeing in your work.
And so just a couple of quick examples, we're seeing activism unlike we've seen anywhere
in a long time.
Obviously in your industry, but most recently in the hospitality industry.
Unite Here is the union that represents hotel and restaurant employees, housekeepers, room attendants,
who just went on strike against the most profitable hotel company in the world, Marriott.
And they wanted fair wages, of course, and better working conditions.
You can imagine the stress and taxation that is happening to a room attendant who is lifting
up heavy mattresses and dealing with cleaning materials.
making sure they have those safety protections on the job,
but they also were fighting for protection
against sexual harassment because of guests in the hotels
and what they encounter when they are cleaning rooms.
Also technology.
and the introduction of automation in industrial kitchens and robots for when you check into
a hotel.
They wanted a voice in how that technology was going to be implemented in their industry.
So they used their collective bargaining process with their union.
to have enough power at the table to say,
here are our ideas and this is what we would like to see.
So that was an example of workers coming together
most recently, along with teachers who have been,
you know, out on the picket line saying,
you know, enough's enough, we want better,
smaller class sizes in our classrooms and,
you know, more school supplies so we don't have
to buy them out of our pockets.
So I think this is a moment, we're calling it
a movement moment that you're a part of.
Yeah, and you touched on hospitality workers, service.
There's burgeoning labor movements,
not just in games, but in technology.
And you recently published an open letter to game workers
calling on them to unionize
and start organizing with one another,
and that the time was kind of right for that.
Why do you think it is that, not just in the games industry, but kind of really the whole
national picture, why do you feel like labor is kind of resurging in this moment?
What do you think creates these kind of conditions?
And that kind of ties to your first question about education.
I think people are starting to discover that, hey, we don't
have to just sit back and take it.
We do have a way to fight back.
And I think people have a lack of awareness
that you can form a union, for the most part.
Or they have old stereotypes about what unions are.
I cannot tell you the number of times I get on an airplane
and people ask me what I do.
And I say, I work for the labor movement.
And they either look right back down at their book.
Or they say, oh, that still exists.
I thought that was back in the 30s or whatever,
you know, for people who work in steel mills.
And yes, that's true, but I think in this moment
where our economy is becoming so fluid
and work is looking different,
and as you were saying about nobody works
in one place for 30 years anymore, right?
We are experiencing a modernization and a surge
in people wanting to come together collectively
like we haven't seen before
because of what the economy has been doing, right?
It's been repressive and the fairness and equality
is absolutely non-existent and people are feeling very alone
and this is a way to fight back.
Yeah.
So in your letter, you're talking about
now's the time to organize.
How do you feel, as the Secretary-Treasurer of the AFL-CIO,
a national kind of umbrella org
of all these different labor movements and unions,
how do you imagine game workers and tech workers in general
fitting into that national picture?
How do you imagine us incorporating into the larger whole?
Well, this is so incredibly exciting because
The world is your oyster, right?
There is no one particular way to do this.
And I think we could benefit from your creativity
and your innovation in thinking about
what a model could look like.
Now, there are models that exist,
and I think that could work for this industry as well.
I came out of the electrical workers union, right?
Where electricians who work in construction
are moving from job to job, it's very dynamic,
it's very fluid, they get all of their training.
through the union because they're constantly coming back to the union as a center of gravity.
They get their benefits through the union.
People think portable benefits is a new conversation.
It's not.
Because for over 100 years, unions have been doing this, right?
So that is a model that exists.
Now, there could be a model like a guild, for example, that Uber drivers have formed
in New York, where they come together and they fight against
Not only company policies and to be recognized, that's how the tipping policy was changed, actually, with Uber.
As the Independent Drivers Guild went to the company and said, this is absolutely locking us out.
And then also, certainly with the Taxi Cab Commission and the regulatory framework, they're able to use their guild to leverage that.
There could be a model where you might be a member of the AFL-CIO, for example, directly,
independently, and we could provide support and infrastructure.
But I think the one thing to think about is there's the movement piece of this, but there's
also the organization piece of this that's so important.
And a lot of people think, yeah, we got a movement, but you also have to have an organization
to be able to deliver on the goals of that movement.
So I kind of want to make sure we have a nice decent chunk of time for audience Q&A, but
before we get on to that, I think it would be really nice to take a moment and step back
maybe from that larger picture of everything, but to people who are maybe new to the labor
movement, people who are new to organizing and talking to their fellow co-workers about
these kinds of things.
Each of you, I'd like to hear just briefly kind of like,
what maybe a general tip you might be,
you would just give to someone who's just starting out
and maybe like, what first steps would you
recommend them kind of following?
Justin, do you wanna start off?
Yeah, I think that,
boy, it's hard not to jump in on the economic situation
for people in the industry and the big picture.
But can I just say one little thing about that is that,
What's happening is the massive disparity of wealth inequality in this country is, I feel like I'm preaching to the choir here, but I feel like it's worth saying that there are a few people that are taking everybody's money and making people work like 60 or 70 hours a week and giving them
just enough for them to survive to continue producing wealth for them.
And that's the moment that we're in.
That's the moment that this country has been in in the past, and this world has been in the past,
and the solution to that situation is mass organizing.
into militant, strong labor unions.
And that's, I feel like, it is a moment, it is happening.
People are doing it, and it's up for institutions
to figure out how to interact with that
and provide the necessary resources
for people that are on the front lines fighting that.
And I think that that's also what's really exciting,
is that's happening everywhere across our industry,
and people are looking to fight back,
and we have to figure out how to help support that.
And that's not necessarily helpful day-to-day advice.
So I will circle back to that and say
that beginning to have conversations with people
that you know and trust about what's
happening at your workspace, what's
happening in your working lives, is the best way to start.
You'll find that there's obviously tremendous fear
about collective action because.
the corporations that you work for are in a structure where they have most of the power.
But you'll also find that when you have open conversations with people who are experiencing
the same or very similar situation as you are, that there's going to be tremendous solidarity
and tremendous receptiveness to at least talking about those things.
So just to elevate the notion of community building.
We do a lot of happy hours, we do a lot of coffees, a lot of teas, where people just start breaking
down the isolation that they're facing and realizing that it's not just them who are facing these
problems and that it's actually a systemic approach for companies to maximize profit off of your
labor. That happens through one-on-ones and that happens through people coming together
collectively. And then the next step is trying to build that organization.
And that will come after.
But really just developing the solidarity by talking
to each other about what you're experiencing.
Thank you.
Liz?
I think the education piece is really big in knowing your rights.
And Emma can be also a support source for that.
But also the broader labor movement is here.
You've got a whole table full of people who want to help.
And so us being there to answer questions and encourage you along the way and support you.
So knowing your rights and then, as Justin said, talking to each other.
You're used to living in an open source environment and solving problems collectively.
Have those conversations with each other and think outside the box.
I hate that saying, but I'm going to say it anyway.
But, you know, it's why not be brainstorming new ways of doing things.
And we can be there as a labor movement infrastructure to support you along the way.
Awesome. Thanks.
Linda, what advice would you have for someone just starting out?
Yeah, I'd really stress the importance of one-on-one and the building trust amongst one another.
And because when you're going through these organizing efforts,
these are going to be the building blocks and the relationships you carry throughout every step of the way.
You want to make sure that people are educated, you're talking to people,
that people are involved and are excited to be involved.
So one-on-ones are super important.
Yeah. And Kevin?
I feel like I'm preaching to a choir here, but yeah, it is talking to your co-workers,
talking to the people you work with and figuring out their problems, building connections.
Because a lot of people in this industry are marginalized or feel isolated and believe
that they are facing these problems alone, by themselves, when we're all facing those
problems and we want to stand up together to fight for better conditions.
It's not just like figuring out what our problems are, right?
It's building actual human connection to form like a culture of care where we care about each other,
we care about our problems, we care about solving the issues we're facing together.
Yeah, and I'll add my two cents.
I think everyone kind of touched on it, really,
but Kevin, you really articulated it.
A fellow organizer once told me that to her,
organizing is about building a culture of care
in your workplace, right, and in your industry.
And I think that's really kind of a profound
and very sweet way to approach organizing, right?
It's about building a culture of care.
And that means actually listening to people,
hearing their problems, genuinely caring,
and it doesn't matter what their position are
on unions and things, what role they play in the industry,
genuinely approaching them with genuine empathy
and care about their situation,
and learning to listen first,
and not just lecture and share stats and things,
but focus on emotion and story.
I think that's at least something
I would definitely share with new organizers.
Awesome.
So, we're going to move into the audience section.
So if you have any questions or advice that you want to seek from our panelists, there's
a lot of really wonderful perspective and knowledge to share up here.
So we could go all night, but we've got about 30 minutes.
Yeah, we'll start over here.
Hello.
What are the unique challenges presented by, say,
an indie developer where you might be alone
or working part-time in a different industry
and in your free time making games?
Sure.
Justin, you want to take that?
One thing that, as I've looked at and just starting to learn a little bit more about this industry,
is that the independent development scene looks a little bit to me like the independent film scene in our union.
And so, oftentimes, people will wear the hat.
many different hats and do many different things within a production.
And so the things that have worked for our union in that space
is the community building. And so we'll have an independent film caucus where
people who are working in isolated situations can come together and talk
about their craft,
talk about funders, talk about the various issues that are impacting them
as individually,
and look for common, potential common solutions related to that. Or just get
together and
talk to other human beings.
seems to be actually of value for folks in that.
And then also, the union has a contract
that can be negotiated whereby you would be,
if you're the indie game developer
and you're working sort of as a self-owned
or self-produced entity,
that you can actually become signatory
to the union contract and become eligible
for health insurance.
And that contract was developed
as independent film makers got together and talked about ways in which that contract should
be structured.
And so Indy, if by Indy you also mean some smaller companies, then I think it's important
to take an industry-wide approach so that not just one or two of them are unionized,
but all of them are.
Well, I'm talking about people who are not in a shop, specifically.
Can I add an additional part to that question?
Briefly.
Yeah.
What about groups that already exist, say like the IGDA branch of your local thing,
how will that, how will Game Workers Unite distinguish itself from that or be joined
into that?
Maybe they don't want to be joined into it, but the community already exists.
I'm kind of like thinking of these like case scenarios, edge case scenarios.
I'd actually like to tackle that.
For clarity, when it comes to labor organizing,
it always happens on a shop by shop basis.
It's a very local, grassroots approach.
Even if it's a part of a larger national
or international movement,
it's always about the individual workers in the shop
coming together to find whatever path forward
and whatever issues they want to work around
and what solutions they want to find.
And so in that way, it really is up to the individual groups of workers in their studios
to find out their own path.
And so, yeah, if they want to find community and solidarity in the IGDA or Game Workers
Unite or any community really, that's wonderful.
And Game Workers Unite is here to help with education and providing organizer training
and kind of building up the general skills of the populace, but really it's again about
that local shop.
And they might choose to go with any one existing union.
They might choose to keep their own independent just themselves union, right?
They might also want to form as a collective of other shops that are unionizing a larger like National Union
Say it's very flexible and it's up to what the workers themselves decide. Does that provide a little clarity on that? Yeah. Thank you for sure
If I could add a couple of thoughts here. That has been a debate around, you know, traditionally
we've seen people organized around craft. So, for example, I used my union electrical
workers, we're all electricians in the country.
based on their craft organized a union.
Then you have also this sort of more horizontal industry example of, you know, steel workers,
you know, and their companies would go across a company, no matter where that company's
footprint was, they organized by the company in that particular industry.
And sometimes you could have an industry-wide...
you know, all the companies coming together too at one table where we've had models like
that.
But for folks who are independent who aren't employees...
there's a distinction there because under the National Labor Relations Act, you're not
eligible, I guess, to form a traditional union as an independent contractor.
So that's where we're seeing these new models emerge, where I mentioned the Uber Drivers
Guild, where they still can come together collectively to leverage their strength, right,
because you're more powerful together than you are on your own.
And so they're organizing in different ways.
Car wash workers, taxi drivers, folks
who have been on their own, feeling alone,
have a way to come together and bargain or negotiate.
So the AFL-CIO is exploring this right now
because we're doing a future of work initiative
where we're thinking, how can the labor movement actually
think more creatively, more fluidly about how
work is going to be organized in the future?
Because there is, as we know, this push.
to try to, employers to try to, you know, skirt responsibility, to be honest, right?
They don't want to be an employer anymore.
Of course, we're going to fight that, but we also need to figure out a path forward
for workers who want to come together in a different way.
So it is about scale, and I would guess as someone who works on your own independently,
you still want to have access to affordable health care.
You still want to have access to, you know,
perhaps maybe one day buying a home and getting a mortgage.
Who knows, right?
And also discounts on things that, you know,
when you are part of a large organization,
you can get cheaper access to staying at a hotel
or whatever it is.
So I think we're looking at a model
of how we can open up the labor movement scale
to leverage that for workers
who aren't necessarily employees, if that makes sense.
Thanks for the question.
Yeah, over here.
So.
Very similar to my question.
So I'm a freelancer, and I've debated
putting up on my website discounts for studios
with union labor, that employs union labor.
Is there any other way that freelancers
can support our fellow workers in bigger studios
than just discounts or showing up to meetings?
I feel like either Linda or Justin could probably tackle that.
Linda, do you want to take a stab?
One of the things that, since we've started organizing in digital media,
the folks that have been able to join the union
and be part of the collective bargaining agreement
are the staff and staff workers at places.
But just like in your industry, in the writing industry,
there's many, many freelancers who are either doing an article here
and there and.
are not eligible to join the union.
And so we have a sort of an adjacent effort of freelance solidarity that happens where
people who are in the freelance space come together at our union office and look for
collective solutions to try to either increase the rates that they're part of or to support
contract campaigns that places that they write for.
are part of.
And so that requires, just like Liz was saying,
thinking about things a little bit differently
and adapting to the actual economy that's in front of us,
which includes multiple freelance pools of labor
and multiple ways that companies, frankly,
are working to get around.
having traditional employee-employer relationships.
So I think as long as a lot of the same things apply
if you're freelance, and that's about building community,
building collective power.
If you look at some things the National Writers Union
has done in terms of
They've done lawsuits around non-payment for magazine publications and have been really
innovating doing new collective actions for freelancers.
So I would argue that it's going to be extremely important to make sure that freelancers are
part of any future unions within your industry.
Linda, do you want to touch on that as well?
Yeah, I think it's a matter of, you know, what Justin touched upon, it's like where
you have a space where you can also stay organized even if you're not particularly in that bargaining
unit of the union.
Because one example of SAG-AFTRA is that choreographers are not considered part of our union, but
they...
A lot of them actually are members because we do cover dancers, but then they created
kind of like their own space, but also work closely with the union where they call themselves
the Choreographer Alliance and use this alliance model where they still have a lot of autonomy
where they can create their own meetings, they teach classes, do fundraising, and they
still talk to one another.
are able to actually create minimums for each other.
So I think there's still ways like using kind of like the alliance model of like
this is kind of like the on rap to activism and organizing and they're able to do that.
But also be in solidarity with the dancers and the union and work together.
I just want to add because it works slightly differently in the UK. In the UK, even if
you're a freelancer or a contractor, you have no job. You're allowed to join the union.
There's just a fundamental right of every person in the UK to have the right to join
the union. And one of the things that we at our solidarity workers and the AWGB achieved
is that for the Liverpool and Uber drivers.
They formed a union for them, they successfully unionised and in high court they thought that
these careers are recognised as employees with full employee rights, sick days, vacation,
paternity, maternity leave.
Because, I know it's scientific, yes, but there's one thing that a lot of people work
on like rolling contracts from years to like just a couple of weeks, that actually like
they should be full-time employees, they should be bought in-house and just get a regular
salary and regular benefits.
And that is also something we are trying to fight for.
I'm sorry, another thing that we're experimenting with that might be relevant is bargaining
for all.
So that, for example, the UFCW commercial workers are in negotiations with big grocery
stores and they've invited non-union workers to their bargaining table because they're
going to bargain for lifting standards for everyone.
So that might be also an outlet in the future.
Thank you.
So there's been a lot of talk about organizing by trade, specifically.
Like, Linda, you were saying, for example, that choreographers aren't included in SAG-AFTRA.
Can you talk a little bit about a solidarity union model
where you're organizing not necessarily just the game
workers, but everyone in the shop, including janitorial
staff, and using the leverage that game workers have?
as folks who have a little bit more of specific skills
and therefore leverage in order to raise the standards
for workers in their shop who their bosses might see
as more disposable, heavy air quotes.
I think that's really crucial.
Do you wanna tackle that?
Yeah, so even to continue talking about choreographers,
like we know that.
they have a super specialized skill set,
and usually they will be in solidarity with the dancers
because a lot of them grew up and trained as dancers
and are part of our union because of dancing.
So they would even show solidarity with the dancers
where they can say that we want this project
to be covered by union contract.
they've been building, and then the choreographers will go to other shows,
like say they go on tour with a musical artist,
where they're like, okay, and then they still float that idea,
because the choreographer, there's only like,
there's a smaller set of choreographers doing this kind of work,
and then they're constantly getting work.
So if they go to, like say on tour,
then they can also float that idea of like,
we want this to be, you know, covered by union contract,
we want union dancers and, you know,
help organize in that way, so that.
there is that solidarity and that education going on and they
were able to, that's still like an ongoing effort to
organize music tours, but they were able to do it with a Justin Timberlake tour in 2012
and then recently he went on tour last year and then that they were able to make that a union tour as well.
Awesome, and yeah, I would just further expand by
emphasizing that at least for me,
and I think a lot of people in Game Workers Unite,
we really do buy into the industrial model of organizing,
which kind of, as you were describing, means, you know.
Yeah, that's exactly what I was describing.
Yeah, to reiterate is kind of yes about like organizing all workers across all disciplines
because it's a little harder to separate people when we're all banded together in one big group.
And I think a part of that absolutely, it absolutely is organizing all workers.
If you have any role to play in the work of our companies and our studios making games,
and I mean genuinely like engineers, artists, writers, QA testers, right, community managers.
I mean, the folks who work down in the cafeteria
or who maintain the building,
everyone's playing a hand here, right?
Like everyone's enabling this medium that we work in, right?
And I think it's super essential to,
yeah, as we've been saying,
include everyone when we're trying
to improve our workplaces, yeah.
In a campus...
Great, thank you.
Sorry.
The example might also be with campuses.
We've been seeing, you know, that solidarity come around on college campuses where you
have, you know, obviously the faculty, you've got the grad students organizing, you've got
cafeteria workers, and they're leveraging, you know, each other's strengths.
In some cases the whole campus is organized and they help the cafeteria workers lift up their voice.
And also in Silicon Valley we have an example of what we call Silicon Valley Rising,
where you saw at Facebook and Google and other places where shuttle bus drivers,
cafeteria workers and security guards organized a union.
Because of the support in the Silicon Valley area of all the other labor unions coming together,
lifting them up and using every tool at our disposal,
whether it's capital strategies with our pension funds and
leveraging, you know, at shareholders meetings,
it's, you know, legislative and regulatory pressure strategy to
get the company to pay attention, media, you know.
So we bring all those tools to bear together in a particular
geographical area to help workers who may not necessarily
have as much of a voice.
And to button that, I would also say,
I think we genuinely have a lot to learn
from those people who have organized, right?
Those cafeteria workers, those shuttle workers,
those maintenance folks.
We have much to learn from them,
and they are already doing that work in our studios,
right, in our companies, right,
at Facebook and other places.
So we have a lot to learn from them,
and I think that's a healthy relationship
we should be continuing to develop.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for coming.
So.
There are entire parts of the video game industry
that rely on free labor that generates money for companies,
for example, like streaming or like kids making skins
for Minecraft.
Like another more well-known example of this
from another industry are like BuzzFeed quizzes.
And I'm just wondering, how has this
happened in other sites of organizing,
and how has it been addressed?
And are these people considered to be workers?
Are we bringing them into these efforts?
So you're kind of talking about community made labor and products of labor. How does that fit into this? Awesome question
Does anyone want to tackle that?
In one thing I tell you if you came from union is deciding on who who's eligible eligible to join
I go to draw the line. Is it a
Professional eSports players they get a salary from the company that makes the game. Are they considered game workers?
freelance game journalists like
where do we people who work on middleware for games who are gonna have a day
consider game workers
one of the things you have to do is that
anybody who is involved in the process of making games at some level is in the union
when it comes to user-generated content, when it comes to modders or YouTubers which are
seen as professional esports players. There we draw the line because
Like, the Games Industry is a very big, big space where it is hard to get the solidarity
you need from all the workers.
So until we can really get a foothold in this industry, we don't want to stretch ourselves
too soon and try to cover too many bases.
Maybe Linda or Justin, I think this is kind of slightly also related to things like spec work.
In the industry we definitely have an issue with people requesting spec work, which for those who aren't familiar are
requesting essentially free labor, free examples of your creativity or ability before actually hiring you or paying you.
We even had a very notable example at last E3 where Ubisoft had a program that was essentially
asking for community spec work.
Is that common in maybe your industry I would assume as well maybe?
Yeah, that's an even, you know, in the film and television industry and for script writing,
it's quite common.
And the way that folks have addressed that is through a collective bargaining agreement
that sets out the standards for what people are paid for doing labor.
And in order to get there, there just needs to be a common understanding of the people
who are doing that work and a shared responsibility to hold each other accountable to not working
for free.
But that problem definitely doesn't go away with a union because people are doing work
that they are passionate about and they care about and are trying to break into an industry.
So that's definitely a challenge with or without a union, frankly.
Thank you.
Hi, any advice for students who, especially undergrad, who want to raise awareness and stuff in
schools that sometimes the teachers are a bit more
old-fashioned about this, especially because I don't want to rest on my laurels and say, oh, it'll be solved by the time I graduate.
We'll have a union by then.
Yeah, does anyone want to tackle the kind of subject of students?
How they fit in? As far as activism? Yeah, and getting them involved.
Yeah, there's an organization called the United Students Against Sweatshops that is very active
on campuses speaking out.
Of course, the motivator for them or the reason why they formed was because of the college
athletic wear that was being sold on campus was being made in sweatshops in other countries
and they wanted to change the standards.
for what they could sell on campus, right?
We want clothing that's made using, you know,
folks who are being paid a fair wage
and aren't being taken advantage of.
So that activism kind of branched out
and now is, I think, a very fluid organization
that turns over in leadership quite often
because the nature of students coming and going.
But it's been evergreen.
And I don't know, you could look them up online probably.
But also, you know, you're able to start a chapter of your own if you want at your campus
in terms of connecting with the players in your community and being a voice on campus
for the organizing that's going on in the community.
I would also say there's kind of an inverse relationship too to be mindful of.
At least with Game Workers Unite we do a lot of work around preparing education materials
for students about not just the reality of the industry but also basics of how to advocate
for yourself in the workplace and things.
And I think it's super important that we include student voices in our organizing work because
even though they might not be workers now, they certainly will be.
in a few years and this industry is really hard for new people.
Jumping in can feel like going right into the deep end and
I think as much as we can prepare people for it is
really essential so your voice and any student's voices are super welcome and
appreciated
in the movement and I would encourage everyone to get involved for sure.
We probably have time for about one more.
Yeah, so yesterday we spoke a bit about how in a union you can't have anyone who's got
a hiring and firing power.
And looking at the business cards you've been giving out, there's lots of executives on
there, but there's no supervisors, there's no lead developers.
a lot of these people would be exploited as well
by the executive class, they would be at risk of layoffs,
like frontline workers.
Is there a labor organization model
where frontline workers can unite with them
to form a united front against
the highest levels in the companies?
Nothing that I'm familiar with, does anyone have any?
Oh yeah.
That's really hard for me to hear.
I think the question was about people being part of the labor unions who are technically
under labor law statutory supervisors or otherwise ineligible, right?
Is that what you're asking?
Yeah, yeah.
So basically like low to mid-level managers who would also be at risk from abuse from
executives and how they can help us form a united front against this kind of executive
overpaying.
We've been, the organizing that we've been doing since 2015 has been all outside of the National Labor Relations Board.
The National Labor Relations Board is the entity that enforces the National Labor Relations Act.
And that is to us essentially a law that is designed in many ways to prevent workers from organizing.
And so we've been operating outside of that law, which gives us tremendous flexibility in terms of bargaining unit composition,
meaning
that people that that law may consider to be supervisors or managers or otherwise unable to join a union,
can in fact join the unions that are being formed at the companies where people are working.
And that requires tremendous solidarity of the people that are organizing,
and it's much more difficult to have folks like that included.
and you have to leverage the company to agree to that
through using direct action tactics and public shaming
and whatever else you can find in your arsenal
up to and including the threat of withholding your labor
in a strike.
But we have found it to be useful to have unions
that have more people in them,
who sometimes have more power in them,
to get better things from the company.
But it's definitely a, it's a challenge.
I would also tack onto this that I know you're from Ireland.
And so something to note also is that we're
talking about the National Labor Relations Board,
and that's very US-centric.
And I think the thing to really say
is that the legal framework and context around labor and unions
and things really does vary a lot by country to country.
And that's something that would just
have to be researched for your actual communities and studios.
But yeah, to build off of what Justin was saying.
It isn't terribly uncommon that managers and supervisors, creative leads, things like that...
can be sometimes included in an organizing campaign.
And I think, just to extra emphasize something
I think Justin was hinting at is,
I think it's really crucial that when you're organizing
with those types of folks, one, I would say,
you bring them on a little bit after,
when you've already organized many of the
kind of base level workers.
And secondly, when you're organizing,
ensure that the actual structures of the organization
and how you run things and how voices are represented
in the democratic structure of the union is,
is taking into account the kind of natural power dynamics
that some of these leads and directors and supervisors
tend to have in the company.
So that way they're not overrunning anyone's voice.
Yeah.
One small point is the scenario we see most often is very confrontational.
But there are scenarios where employers and managers actually will work with you to form a union.
And they are rare, but they do happen.
And I guess we should maybe approach it always first with the rationale that, hey, we're in this together.
We're creating value at this company.
When we do better, you do better.
We all want to see this company succeed.
So we want to form a union just so that we have a seat at the table.
And we want to be a shareholder, so to speak, and have a voice.
And so I come from a tradition where that is the case.
Labor and management are together in lockstep
because we are the skilled, trained talent
that make the money, and they know it.
So the union benefits them in this way.
So I guess that's one thought I had
when you were talking about management
is that we can't always assume that they're our enemy.
And because in some cases, middle management benefit when there's a union in the company, right?
Because we're raising that lifting tide or that raising tide lifts all boats
that the managers actually end up benefiting when there's a union in the workplace.
Yeah, and I think, of course, it's always, throughout that process, even if we go in
with good intentions and assuming the best of folks, always having that kind of caveat
there.
Absolutely.
The relationship is inherently one where the workers and the bosses have different needs
and interests.
That's more common, yes.
And yeah, I think that's a wonderful question.
Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Yeah.
So, we are now out of time. Thank you for, you know, the panelists for being here today.
It's really awesome to hear all your perspectives and voices. Thank you for your questions.
Some of them I actually hadn't heard before, and so I think having these conversations
and these trickier questions are really, really helpful. I also want to say thank you to our
wonderful techs who are running the conference. They are our siblings in labor at the IATSE
Local 16.
Thank you.
Every single session that you've been at this week has been run by union labor.
Yeah.
And it is them who make this conference as smooth and wonderful as it is.
So we are deeply grateful.
Thank you for doing the work that you do.
I also want to super thank all of our CAs who are just doing an amazing job.
They have so much on their plates, but they do it with such passion and kindness and just
endless support.
And your labor is also very much valued.
Even though you're only here one week out of the year, you're still doing very excellent
labor and we recognize that and we wish you the best as well.
And finally, I would also say, please thank all of the service workers who are working
on the conference.
The people working at Moscone and Yerba Buena work very hard to make sure that this place
is a safe and comfortable environment that's clean and friendly and very approachable.
So please do thank them when you're kind of spending your final day here at GDC.
And then, yeah, lastly, I would just say I'm supposed to remind you that you'll have an
email in your inbox for evaluations.
Please do fill them out.
They are very helpful for both the conference and those of us up here who, you know, really
would appreciate the feedback on how the panel was run and what kind of content you'd like
to see in the future, right?
And then finally...
We have a roundtable, a community roundtable just in 15, 20 minutes.
It's in the South Hall in room 216.
And we would really encourage everyone to come out.
We're going to have a really great discussion about next steps and talking
about granular problems we're all facing and how people can get involved.
And we would love all your voices to be there as well.
But yeah, thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks to Emma.
and developers against each other.
So this is what's...
We really don't want to fall down that hole again
where they're pitting workers against other workers
because the more people that are organized,
the better industry standards we can create.
So SAG-AFTRA totally supports this.
The voice actors totally support this.
So any way we can support, we're all for it.
And this is super exciting for us.
Thank you.