Whoa, that's loud. Hi, everyone. Welcome to the GDC Twitch channel. My name is Brian Francis.
I am a contributing editor at godmonstranger.com. I'm the community manager for GDC. I am, uh,
unfortunately invisible, as always, uh, hanging out, whispering into your ears, uh, whispering
into this, uh, fine gentleman's ears. Um, uh, we're here today playing a game called Creature
in the Well. Um, I'm gonna try and tweak something while we're playing here.
Um, Creature in the Whale is a hack and slash, pinball meets Zelda kind of game.
Uh, yeah, you guys are gonna see that, aren't you?
Alright, let's try and move that over there. There we go.
Okay, um, it is, uh, as you can see here, as my little, my little robot is trying to navigate this desert,
um, it's sort of a top-down game.
Uh, what's gonna get really interesting and unique about it is, A, the look, which you can sort of see about right now,
and B, um, this very, it's got, even though it's got a dungeon-crawling kind of top-down design,
the mechanics, you aren't fighting monsters, instead you're, uh, not using one of two tools to knock...
to power up this factory.
And also, here's the thing that made me want to check out this game.
Here is the 20-foot-tall skeleton
that is creeping around in the background.
For folks at home who are new to the GDC channel,
this is a channel where we talk to developers
about interesting games they're working on
to share knowledge with you about making them.
So if you have questions for our guest,
you can ask them in Twitch chat,
and I will grab them for our guest.
Speaking of which, I should finally introduce him.
Our guest is Adam Volker.
Adam, how are you doing?
I'm doing well, thank you.
And you work for Flight School Studio, right?
I do, I sure do.
I was this close to saying Night School, and I remember that's the studio here in LA, and I was like, wait, no.
And I was like, Flight School...
Those guys suck.
No, no, they're great.
No, I know, they're friends, and their game is really cool looking, and they're lovely people.
Yeah, oh my god, and then Oxenfree was really good.
Yeah, great.
Love Doxanfree.
Anyway, but we're not here to talk about Doxanfree, we're here to talk about Creature in the Well.
Adam, I just told them what Creature in the Well is.
What do you think Creature in the Well is?
And what do you do on Creature in the Well?
That's a good question too.
Yeah, I mean, man, Creature in the Well is a pet project for my colleague Bowden and I.
We've been dying to make a kind of video game that we thought was a little different, a little wacky.
and as beautiful as we can make it.
But I think, you know, calling it a pinball hack and slash is the quickest, most succinct
way to describe what it is.
for those watching at home, the basic mechanic is on display here where I'm using one of
my tools to hit the balls around, soon I will get the other tool, and that will let me charge
up the balls.
But yeah, as you can see, those are pinball bumpers, these are balls that you launch,
you navigate from room to room, and again, the 20 foot tall skeleton is kind of your
nemesis here, although I'll have some thoughts about him later.
Adam, you talked with some other outlets about where this game came from.
For our audience, what was kind of the foundation of Creature in the Well?
What was kind of the first thing that made you go, oh, this is a game we can ship?
As opposed to, this is a great mechanic that's going to take us 20 years to make.
Yeah, that's a good two-part question.
We started the project as a sort of competitive multiplayer local co-op multiplayer game.
It was going to be like air hockey with a character.
And we built that prototype and it was a lot of fun to play, but we started to add like little pylons to it
And we're like well these pylons are cool. Wouldn't it be cool if they were like pinball?
They had you know bells and bouncers and all that sort of stuff
And then we started adding more of those and like well, maybe we just make a game about that instead
Multiplayer was something we were toying with but was a little too much to chew on
And then you know like as we built these rooms we found that that was like really fun
mechanically to mess with
When we found out we could ship it was actually much later in development.
You know, like you can see the project where you want it to go much earlier than it actually gets there.
And it was some third party feedback actually we got.
That was like, I don't know that you guys have anything yet.
And it was a big moment in development for Beau and I to be like, wow, we really need to kind of
dig deeper into what we've built and expand the mechanics.
And that's kind of where the dungeons, the eight dungeons that each have like a different mechanical theme all came from.
Before that it was just a little less challenging. There wasn't quite as much progression in it.
So I would I would call those two
realizations very different parts of development.
Your role in the project, you're a creative director and also the art director, right?
Yeah, and like I said, it's a it's a team mostly of two people and so there's a lot of overlap
but my principal job is to
manage the style, the story, and then a lot of the level design.
Right on, yeah. Let's talk about level design for a minute.
Sure.
What's kind of the underlying logic of, like we're right now seeing some introductory puzzles,
but we'll see some more complicated stuff later. What was kind of the,
what's the core logic for building a pinball puzzle like this? I love this part where you just get fried.
Yeah, so you go room by room. We tried to make sure that everything was kind of like
The puzzles would be built so players would walk into them and have to activate them,
have sort of a twist or a conceit in them, and then solve them within a room.
So the progression was something we could also sort of plan dungeon by dungeon.
So we knew like, let's put something that's just difficult, like this room, for instance,
doesn't have a lot of challenge, but it's fun to like let the players.
just mess around and bounce a ball around every once in a while.
Yeah.
Um, but the...
But it's always kind of like, activating the puzzle was a big part of like,
what we built the design around.
Yeah.
And then each dungeon has a mechanical theme, so it was like,
what you activated would change.
Um, and then, there's uh...
Man, it's hard to describe.
Like, the last room had what we would call like an AoE bumper.
Yeah.
We have just like boring dev names for these things.
Area of effect bumper.
Yeah, it shoots a...
It shoots like a beam out in a line.
So when we were building one of the dungeons around, like these ones here,
when we were building dungeons around that, it was like, can we put them in a cross
and then alternate with ones that, you know, go horizontally?
Bo made tools for me to set timers on them so I could make them fire in rapid succession
to try to move the player around the room.
We wanted to make sure that we weren't letting players just kind of
hit the ball and stand in a corner and let the puzzle win itself.
So it was really important to put the ball where you would get the dispenser,
like had to be in a dangerous area, or had to come from something that would shoot the ball at you.
Providing a ball to the player was another huge challenge.
Making sure there was always one available, making sure they were respawning at the right speed,
making sure that there weren't so many that you could get them anywhere.
Right on. I'm going to loop over to chat real quick, give folks a chance to get some questions answered.
I'm told that the answer to when this game can be played, the answer is soon, although you might have seen it if you dropped by PAX or GDC or E3 recently.
Ed Rockt would like to know, what is the playthrough time on this game and are there plans for DLC?
Which I guess is like, if you can answer Ed's question that would be great.
And then my follow up question would be, when you're planning a game like this, how do you gauge out what the right playthrough time would be for a game like this?
Yeah, so we did a bunch of testing in our Discord server.
We had some players come in at about 10 hours.
That's not necessarily like 100% complete content, but that's like through the story.
Bowden and I take about half of that to play through now when we play through,
so I think it's safe to assume somewhere between 5 and 10 is what like an average
play through the game will take.
As far as extra content, there are some mechanics that we haven't used in this game that maybe
would be cool to put into stuff later, but there's nothing official about that.
But yeah, I think we wanted to make something that offered players a main through line where
they could complete it in a shorter amount of time, but then a bunch of secrets they could
also discover if they wanted to extend how long their playthrough of the game was.
Right on, I also want to highlight what I'm sure you must be shouting at me to just walk over and hit the glowing thing.
I like how the game is clearly telling me, go hit the glowing thing, and I just walked away from it and walked into town for a minute.
Moving on from that question, thank you Ed Rockt.
What I would like to know...
is there's kind of an element in this game of the fact that puzzles can be skipped you're going to
see later on that like there's just moments where i just i've had i've had it i've got enough power
moving on from the puzzle what was kind of your design decision for making like kind of creating
this broader um players don't need to make every clear every puzzle to advance what was kind of
your thought process around that yeah i think this is this is sort of a two-part answer
The first part is kind of a difficulty question.
So like, if there's a puzzle that is either like not communicated well, how it's supposed to be solved,
or it's just too difficult or maybe you're underleveled,
we wanted players to be able to opt out of that and still progress through the game.
And then I think like...
The second part is about resource management.
So every time you hit a bumper, you'll see numbers pop up, even these bubbles here, and
that's your currency of the game.
And managing that currency isn't super important, maybe in the first dungeon, but definitely
in the later dungeons, you'll have the ability to spend that on teleporters to make the dungeon
run back to the boss fight easier.
You'll have the ability to spend that currency to level up in town.
And then so managing that when the temples start to branch and the exploring becomes a bigger thing
Is a lot of why we allowed players to like skip forward
Some of the rooms they didn't want to spend time in yeah
There are there are places where you know we'll let a player sort of we'll reset the bumpers
They're all on a timer so each of the rooms reset
And we'll let players if they want to you grind out
To get more power to like level up everything unlock everything you know unlock all the teleporters
But we wanted to give them the option to do it or not do it.
Right on, um, uh, let's talk about the, uh, camera perspective for this game.
How did you and Beau kind of come together on like, uh, there's sort of a lot of ways
this camera could've gone.
You could've literally just made a set fixed perspective of pinball, like, make it look
like a pinball table.
Sorry for any frame hitching you see in the video by the way.
That's my recording setup, not the game itself.
Um, what was kind of your thoughts on designing a camera for this game?
One that could keep everything clearly visual and visualized for the player.
Yeah, good question.
So the way the camera works is that room by room, I set it.
Bo writes some incredible tools.
There's a camera volume.
So in Unreal, there's a box.
And every time the player enters the box,
I blend it from the camera.
I don't blend it.
The game blends it from the camera it was in to one
that I set.
I can set things like FOV, distance, rotation,
all that other stuff.
And so what I tried to do was find a nice hybrid between a shot that I wanted to compose
and then what was good for gameplay.
We found really, really quickly that the game is super crappy to play when the camera's
low because aiming is really difficult.
So as close to directly above the player as possible is better for gameplay.
But I've always kind of wanted to make it more cinematic, both Bo and I.
come from a film background. And so there's a few hallways and a few rooms where I can
really take the camera low and have it track the player as you're running to try to get
interesting shots and make it feel dynamic. But what's cool is like we can fix it room
by room. So if there's a particular puzzle that the camera I've chosen makes it too difficult,
it's easy to just go in there and fix. And there's also a setting on it to decide how
much the player is tracked.
I can lock it so it doesn't move, and you'll notice in this room it drifts a little when you move.
And that's just another cool value to tweak as we make the puzzles.
So when I would make a puzzle, it would be like, load up an empty room,
and then fill it with a design, set a camera, play it a bunch of times, have Bo play it,
and just kind of tweak as we go.
Right on. Is there any kind of effective, broad guideline you observed about the game's camera?
Anything interesting you learned about that you think another developer could benefit from?
I mean, if they're making a pinball hack and slash game, I've got a lot of specific advice.
I think aiming something really makes... Wow, I'm so glad you got this on the first try.
Nobody gets this puzzle on the first try.
Pro gamer, Bryan Francis right here.
Pro gamer.
Like I said, the top-down thing was really important.
I had to figure that out as we went.
Blending it from more than a 90 degree angle, from room to room really caused us a lot of bugs.
That would be something I would avoid.
We'd end up with cameras that would literally whip around 180 degrees if I'd set something incorrectly.
I don't know, like the entrance to the room was on the right side and the camera needed
to be on the left and it was coming from a room that had the opposite setup.
The camera would really struggle to spin around.
So it's just kind of like stuff you can't really find out until you run the game as
is intended.
Um, uh, there's a good question in chat about engineering I do want to get to but, uh, before I do, you talked to Boa before about using camera to control the mood for this game?
Yeah.
I don't know why I came back here. Uh, why did I- why aren't you going through the door past me?
Um, oh yeah, I guess I was trying to see if I could control that ball through the door. Um...
Anyway, so the question I have about mood, you mentioned in some other interviews that you're super inspired by Mike Mignola.
This does kind of have a Hellboy, BPRD look about it.
Awesome.
From... man, I got that on the first try too.
Yeah, those are difficult shots to make.
What I wanted to know is, this game has kind of like, you can see between the numbers bouncing up and the kind of high score-y elements, but there's kind of an arcade-y component to the game.
But there's also, as we've seen, like this very moody, deliberate aesthetic going on.
Like the kind of, I think in another interview described it as Oscar the Grouch as a bad guy.
That's kind of one of your inspirations.
There's kind of a deliberate mood about this weird apocalyptic setting you're in.
Can you talk about the decision to not make it stylized and not just a high score, charging single player experience?
Yeah, so, that's an interesting question.
I think like, I think a lot of this...
Wow, how do I answer that?
Beau and I build the game piecemeal, and it had a lot of inspirations when we started,
but it's kind of like one step at a time, like that's working, that's not working.
And so what you end up with as a final product is just an amalgamation of all of those little
decisions along the way.
I think we wanted something really dark and moody.
The character who is speaking to the...
player out of a trash can turned into the creature. We needed darkness to put him in, but we didn't.
But we wanted him to feel large and scary. And like every time we would make a decision,
the whole game would sort of have to adapt and grow to that decision.
And all along the way, we're just trying to retain, you know, the mood, the feeling,
the camera and the arcadiness that we wanted, hoping that all of those elements would speak
well together and not be, you know, not compete, or that they that they would harmonize.
Um, so it's interesting that you're pointing out like it's arcadey, but also really moody.
Um, hopefully those things work well together.
Uh, but it wasn't really ever a decision to try to mash something disparate with something that wouldn't blend with it, you know.
Right on. That was another hard shot I pulled together.
I can now grab Nath Rackus' question.
Obviously, Bo sounds like he was kind of your tools guy.
He was doing a little more of the programming side.
What kind of engineering challenges did you face with a game like this?
This is an Unreal, right?
Yes, it is. It's in UE4.
So yeah, you're correct. Bo is the tech side of the development.
So I'll do my best to answer on his behalf.
And I'm sure if he's watching, he's rolling his eyes already.
But I guess one of the things that we did was, he really wanted to get right, was player movement.
That's something that he iterated on a lot.
How the animation, like how quickly the animation responded.
You know, how aiming worked.
Whether we rooted the player, which we do.
When you're charging the ball, how fast the dash operates, all that sort of stuff.
It was a huge challenge, it was an ongoing thing. Character control was really important to him.
The other thing that's kind of anecdotal, which is cool, is we originally made the game to handle the dungeons procedurally.
So Bo built a bunch of tools for that to work and then later in development we decided that wasn't the game we wanted to make.
And we got rid of a lot of that work.
But we're still able to keep the way the rooms connected.
So my job was to build...
Basically these art boxes, like I built this room without any bumpers in it, and then I
would set doors and where they connected and what type of door they were, and Bo had written
all these tools to create the dungeon so that anywhere I could connect any two doors together.
And then any room could hypothetically be connected to any other room.
And some of that stuff carried over from when we had originally made the game as procedural.
before we changed it to be, you know, handcrafted.
Right on.
This is, I'm actually really glad you finished answering right there,
because this is a great moment to talk about.
That was the first time I died in this game,
and I got grabbed by the titular creature in the well.
There's the creature, there's the well, there's the...
Anyway,
This death loop is really interesting to me because you can, you know, you die, uh, you get a moment with the villain of the game where you just sort of like get to stare down each other a little bit, and then you walk back through the dungeon.
You're gonna see it happen a couple more times, but it's kinda, um, it's a death loop. It's interesting death loop to me because it's not as, um, it's not, you know, as rogue-like, like, oh, you died, like, some stuff gets retained, but you lose other stuff.
It's not, it doesn't have that same, like, loop function to it, but that's still, like, that looping failure back into...
In the end, the game feels pretty good here, and it's an interesting decision, especially when later, as you see, I actually fail and then I have to walk a pretty significant ways back, and I have to take a long walk back through where I've been.
How did you sort of come to the decision to implement it that way?
Yeah, so that was about storytelling for us. It was kind of making sure that the player interacted with the creature, and that we made them feel like...
He was always watching.
I think it makes you feel really vulnerable for him, the villain, to pick you up and physically move you.
It reiterates that he doesn't want you doing what you're doing and fixing the machine and going back into the mountain.
And then we encourage you gently to read the dialogue we wrote for the story parts of the game.
And so all of that, we just felt like... I'm glad you feel that way.
Because all of that we felt like was reinforcing the relationship with the creature, the story, and all of that stuff.
The run, it's interesting that you mentioned the run because that is another point that we really, really wanted to...
We really paid close attention to.
Right after you died you actually walked up to a door in town that had a red blinking light.
Later in the game, once you complete more of the dungeons, that door opens and makes your run back much quicker.
And then this room actually turns into a teleporter.
If you spend money later in the dungeon to unlock it,
you can teleport right to the boss room.
So both of those devices were ways
that we made that easier for players
that they wanted it to be, the run to be a little shorter.
But we felt like the story win we were getting out
of having the creature pull you back to town was cool.
Nice.
Moving through my question pile here.
There's kind of an interesting thing you talked about in another interview I was watching.
We were talking about making sure that rooms don't beat themselves.
I thought that was kind of funny.
What's the danger of setting up a room like that and why was it something you wanted to avoid?
Well, I think it just makes for a boring game.
You know, if a player can just bounce the ball and then nothing...
you know, they don't have to do anything.
If the game is in design, if a game is solvable, that's really bad.
Meaning that if there's only one solution to beat it,
and that solution is really clear to the player at the beginning,
and there's not a lot of thinking, then it's not as interesting to play, etc.
So a couple of ways we tried to handle that was to make the puzzles activatable,
like I was mentioning before.
There's also a lot of engineering under the hood about how long a ball will bounce
without you interacting with it.
So you'll notice the balls change in color. That's based on the player level.
Makes them more powerful. They'll complete a bumper. They'll fill a bumper with power in less hits.
But if you don't hit them, they'll slowly lose power and then they will only bounce three times.
And then they'll disappear.
So turning the balls into these sort of abstract energy things was a big part of fixing that solvability.
Apologies to the folks at home, we did not get to see that entire puzzle because unfortunately
this is a great game with some particles moving very quickly across the screen, which means
that's what causes load on the CPU when you're trying to record footage.
Um, uh, moving... oh man, like, chat said too, we missed that beautiful, just, moment of chaos.
Yeah, those are kind of our, like, breakout Plinko rooms where, like, if you get, if you sneak a ball
into the back of it, the whole, it's like that really satisfying where you're playing breakout
and you can get a ball to bounce up under the corner. Yeah. Yeah, that's a good, yeah man,
that's a good breakout, like, that's a good game to reference here, I think. Yes, of course,
through development that was one of our major references.
I really love this room because it feels like a batting cage.
Yeah.
Um, uh, um, uh, you, uh, talked somewhere about, uh, um, speed games done quick, SD,
SDQ, um, and how you were working with speed runners for some testing on this game.
Um, what was kind of, we, we've, we've done, I've done an article about this in the past.
We've been interested in how, uh, game developers kind of learn from high speed players.
Um, what was kind of the thing you learned, like working with speed runners to test your game?
Yeah, and again, this is a Bo question because this is near and dear to his heart, but I will try to remember all the things he was saying while he was making the game as good as it is.
It's kind of about like, if you were, it's really difficult to look at a game that you're making objectively.
Obviously, you spend all this time laboring over, you know, trying to design a puzzle that, like, you think is really cool.
And it might be bad, you know, it might just be boring.
or not interesting or whatever.
And so I think when we would always talk about speedrunning,
Beau would say, is there a way a player will skip this
because they can do it faster a different way?
And that was a really good question
to review what we'd made with.
So it would be like, yeah, he would be like,
I know you spent all day on this, but.
I can just beat it by cheating and standing over this and doing it this way, and we would have to change it for that reason.
I think when we think about doing it quickly and trying to optimize, it's a bit like optimizing the gameplay, right?
That's when speedrunning and that stuff comes into play.
You've also, like I said, you've taken this tour around to a bunch of shows.
Is there anything you've learned about just playing at shows like PAX and stuff and getting
feedback from players that helped you guys out on this game?
Oh, for sure.
I think the first time we showed it was at GDC and we had a demo version then, but we
definitely went back to the tutorial.
It's always the beginning of the game that gets iterated on the most, I think.
We went back to that part a lot after we saw...
You know, we'll put the game in the hands of a bunch of new players.
We try to do as much testing as we can with friends and family, you know, in the middle of development.
But showing it like officially, announcing the game and all of that, you really learn a lot of new stuff about what assumptions you've made.
And the mechanic is so different and new that like teaching it is really, really important.
And so that those first three or four rooms in the game, you know, are probably like the newest rooms in the game.
Right on. Yeah, actually speaking of like how new and different this mechanic is, there's a lot of, you know, common language in game development.
Like a sword, when you swing a sword like this, it should do kind of this.
Right.
Your game does things differently in specific ways, but it's also, you know, there's like some conventional aspects, there's some unconventional aspects.
What have you learned about like designing game elements to help players understand what they are?
Like, kind of these orange things are an interesting example because they're not...
Enemies that you hack and slash to kill, they're energy things that can be dispelled with the ball, like they swarm you and add pressure.
What have you learned about designing in-game elements that are abstract, but, you know, they might be pinball-y and conventional, but they might not make sense in a hack and slash.
Yeah, that's a good question. Those particular enemies are still kind of a sticking point for me and Bo.
We decided to make them killable by the ball and not the sword because we want to make sure that the player is thinking about the ball always.
Yeah.
Um, but it is, it, it, I have noticed like of player after player find that not, um, super intuitive.
Um, so it's, it's, it's a difficult thing to answer.
I, um, we sort of operate on the design philosophy that we've stolen from a filmmaker.
Uh...
His name is Steven Spielberg.
It's just some random filmmaker.
He, uh, his company Amblin Entertainment put out this idea
that like, um, audiences like newness in a, in sort of like a
70-30 relationship to things they already know.
So 70% being, um, things that people understand with a twist.
So it's our world, but there's an island of dinosaurs or it's
suburban California, except there's an extraterrestrial that
lives with a small boy.
or befriends a small boy.
And so we were like,
there are swords, but they don't behave the way you expect.
Or it's a dungeon crawler, but it's full of rooms with pinballs mechanics.
I think if it was all super abstract and new,
we would have a lot more work to do to tell people about it.
But I think it's important for players to look at the game and go,
oh, I can see how that would be fun.
And I understand the format of how I'm going to play that, and that's really important to us.
So that, you know, it's not just...
It's just fun, you know, you should be able to speak the language fairly quickly, even if there's a lot of newness.
So, like, that's why we went with swords, and that's why we went with dungeons and rooms and boss fights and connecting them all that way.
Right on, right on. Do you think that's helped you? I don't know how hands-on you've been with any of the marketing for the game, because you have some support from Pop Agenda and stuff, but uh...
Um, uh, what, um... uh...
Do you think that's helped you, like, explain the game to people, as you've tried to, like, get it out in the world and convince people to buy it when it comes out?
Looks at spreadsheets soon.
Uh, yeah. Well, I mean, I basically just say whatever they tell me. That's how I know it's good.
and appropriate. But really, a lot of the messaging comes from players.
The first time we played it at GDC, somebody called it a pinball hack and slash,
and then the next PAX East show we brought it to, somebody said pinbrawler.
And it's players being able to tell you,
like, oh, this is how I would describe it to a friend has been the best way to...
Continue to talk about it
Because Bo and I have all this baggage about what it used to be what it used to look like it used to be a
Multiplayer game it used to be have a lot more RNG in it and stuff like that so
It's it's kind of just like about listening. I think
Okay
Twenty-five, thirty minutes left in our show here.
If you've got questions, keep them rolling.
We'd love to ask them for you.
So Flight School Studio also does a lot of work in VR development.
You all have a cool World War I experience with Hardcore History's Dan Carlin out there.
I know you didn't work on that one specific, or I don't know if you did, you mentioned that.
Okay, yeah. You have said you've done some work in VR. I know this is sort of a tricky question, but I'm curious, how have you as a developer, like joining a company that's doing work for hire on VR projects and doing interesting...
Like, what's that been like working at this company compared to other game design jobs you've done before?
So, I think what's cool about what Flight School does is that our media... we work in all sorts of like...
real-time mediums, whether it's augmented reality or virtual reality, or just gaming.
It makes our team look at design abstractly.
And so, some of the VR stuff that I have done at Flight School has been both narrative and
gaming oriented, but we try to ask really fundamental questions about the way people
use those devices and what sort of thing we want to make.
and how it would be best on that device.
So wouldn't, you know, like one of my pet peeves is like joysticks on a phone, you know,
those digital joysticks.
I feel like we try to avoid things like that, and I'm trying to say this in a positive way,
we try to design for the platform, right?
And so...
What's been really cool about coming from that VR background is we're always asking those big questions throughout as much of the development process as we can.
So that's really let, like when we started making Creature, it was like, well, if we're going to make a game, it needs to feel like it belongs on the platforms that we would want to play it on.
And that affects the way it looks and the way it plays and the mechanic.
I think that's part of where the arcadiness came from, and it's definitely where the visuals came from.
And since there's stuff like that.
Right on. Does that mindset... I know you didn't necessarily design this for the Nintendo Switch first in mind,
but does the Nintendo Switch as a device make you think about making games differently than it does, say, Steam?
Yeah, for sure. I think you need... because...
I play my Switch a bunch on dock at home, but I also find some of the most fun I have with it is when I'm on the go.
Making something that was graphic, that could read at a small size, was huge.
You know, like I think, we weren't, you know, developing and putting it on the Switch like
every month or whatever, but we did have it in the back of our minds as we were developing.
We started the game on PC, obviously.
And then when we put it on the Switch, it was like, a lot of review of the UI, a lot
of...
Like tweaking of the colors, like it was very easy to get back into these dungeons
and say like let's make this a little brighter, let's make the contrast a little higher so you
can see the player, that sort of stuff, the stuff we tweaked you know with all that in mind.
But yeah it definitely affects it. You want it to look good where people are going to play it so
it would be foolish not to review it that way.
Right on.
Comments from chat.
Madame Laboe would like to know if you used the touch screen on the Switch.
Which is a really interesting weird feature the Switch has, that touch screen.
It is cool we don't use it.
I don't use it a lot when I'm playing games on my own because I don't want to dirty my
screen.
It's weird, it's not like the DS which gave you permission to tap away on the bottom screen.
The Switch feels more delicate than my iPhone in some ways, so I don't want to rub my dirty
fingers all over it.
But it's so wild that Nintendo was like, oh yeah, we're going to keep mobile touch screen
functionality.
I guess that's helped some companies port mobile games to the platform.
It's just me pontificating.
John Nova would like to know, what was the most complicated part of development for you?
Getting the design right. I mentioned earlier that third party who came in the middle of development and was like,
I'm not sure you guys, that was really hard feedback to get, but was really really really helpful.
At that point, we had sort of maybe rooms like this, but they weren't...
This was probably the best that the design had at that point.
We sort of had this big moment where we're like, okay, let's gut everything that we've built.
And Bo made, as he saved me again, as he usually does, he made eight example rooms.
What he did was just kind of like, okay, I'm going to stop what I'm doing for the week and
make and try to take the game and create eight really, really unique puzzles that all have
different, super different mechanics. And he actually ended up having to create a bunch of
new stuff for that.
But it was really good to really try to take the pinball hack and slash mechanic
and spread it out as wide as it could be so that players got something different
as they played through the whole game and it wasn't just hundreds of rooms of the same sort of stuff.
And then once he built those example rooms, we reviewed those for their uniqueness
and then I tried to build the dungeons based on his example.
So all of those, that's kind of how our design process works.
His bow would be like, I think this has something unique and this is what I was going for, and then I would expand it into the dungeon.
And then, you know, we would obviously be bouncing. He'd have an idea to make a room and then we would fine-tune each other's designs.
But that was really one of the toughest parts of getting something that felt like a whole game.
You know, it was kind of always a prototype until that moment, I think.
That's a really good answer, I think.
I want to talk about this mysterious stranger, this mysterious third party who came in and said there wasn't a lot there.
I guess they're going to remain unnamed.
I don't know. Jim, can I mention who it was?
Yeah, so it's a guy named Nigel from Devolver.
Oh, yeah.
And we were talking to him about the game, and he was like, it's cool, but I'm not sure.
And I really, really appreciate the feedback, so shout out to Nigel.
Right on, shout out to Nigel.
Really quick, where I was getting to with that is,
as a designer, I think a lot of game designers
and game developers are very used to critical feedback,
are used to, you know, ideas aren't precious.
They are meant to be worked on and then moved on from.
Yeah.
But when you get feedback like that,
you've been working on something,
you're trying to find a vision for it,
you're trying to find a future for it.
You described a very good...
Reaction to that, to that feedback, which is what you and Bo did, which was trying to realign like how
progression and dungeons work.
But what's kind of your
your mentality for getting that feedback and saying this is proactive feedback that I can use to make this better
and not oh, no, this means we should stop working.
It's not good enough. Like what's kind of the difference to get you across that threshold? I think it's a little more abstract.
Yeah, yeah, that's a tough one. It's about mood, but you know game developers deal with that all the time. That's my opinion.
Yeah, no, definitely. You know, sometimes you don't want to hear it, and sometimes it doesn't matter.
Yeah.
Sometimes you're like, I know what's bad, and people tell you what's bad, and you're like...
I think that...
Ooh, wow.
Like, how stubborn do you want to be is kind of the question you have to ask yourself.
You believe in something, and you have to decide whether you're lying to yourself about its quality,
whether it's something you like.
And maybe a lot of people generally don't.
I think that we really, really take, we really watch new players play something that is new for us,
and we say, like, is there genuine excitement and interest in what we've built?
Or are we lying to ourselves about something we love that maybe isn't resonating with people?
I think, in the case of Nigel's feedback, it wasn't that.
This isn't a game. It was that I don't know that this is going to scale to a full experience was his was specifically what he told us. And so it wasn't.
And, you know, we're reading between the lines, because I think for him, it was kind of, you know, it was a first blush at the game like he hadn't played a lot of it. We were in the middle of development. It wasn't, you know, so I don't even know that he knows how important it was. But it was it was kind of like
We had to decide, yeah, we had to sort of...
The first part of the conversation was like,
do we think that there is a game here?
And the answer was yes.
And then it was like, okay, well,
how do we address this feedback?
And I think we decided that because
we'd been taking it to
a local indie meetup in Montreal
and having people play it.
You know, super development builds, sort of as we went.
And I think the response was genuinely positive, and we had to trust in that response and have, you know,
players were like, yeah, this is cool, cool, this is cool.
And so, we knew there was something there. We just had to sort of expand it and find it.
I think that if, like, you have a core mechanic, like in the basic version of it,
players are either confused by, or they don't find it fun, or whatever,
then you've got a much bigger mountain to climb up.
I also think there was enough of what we built that was just mashups of things we already knew worked.
I think we trusted that Breakout was still a game people had fun playing on some level.
Sneaking a ball behind a bunch of bricks and watching it bounce around was still satisfying.
Planko is still satisfying and Pinball is still satisfying that we could trust that
if we could capture what worked there and add a little bit of Zelda to it then, you know,
we trusted that that would still make a game, you know.
And I actually think that those references gave us the...
were kind of part of the decision to be like, well, do we even keep going?
Yeah, because you're... because, you know, the question's good because it implies that like...
what Nigel was saying is kind of like, you should re-evaluate what you're making.
And once we did, we were like, well, we still know that these other basic games are fun, so...
we could... there's something here, we just have to work to find it.
Right on.
We would still love to take questions and chat from folks.
Bring them on.
We invite them.
We want to know if you're a game developer, if you're a game designer, and you have questions
for Adam, please toss them in.
Adam, let's have some fun.
Okay.
I don't know, it's tough to ask about narrative and mood things in interviews sometimes because
You're better off just playing the game, letting the game tell you what it's about.
But, uh, I think Creature in the Will, the reason I specifically responded to your PR team's email and said,
yeah, we want to stream this game, is I looked at it and I saw that ten-foot skeleton,
and I saw the vibe of the little robot hero, and I was like, oh, yeah, that's my jam.
Like, it instantly clicked with me as a player.
What other kind of ideas did you want to get across?
You talked about Mike McNeil as a source of inspiration, but going deeper into that, what was your vision for what this adventure needed to be about?
Zelda, for instance, is very save the princess, go on a hero's quest, and this is a little bit more Dark Souls-y, reminds me a little bit of Below.
I think you get what I'm going for there.
Yes, so the story of the game is kind of, like for the protagonist, it's about figuring
out what your role in the world is.
And for the theme, I think it's about being insulated.
The town of Mirage is stuck in a sandstorm.
It's been stuck in a sandstorm for so long that the people don't know that oceans exist.
They don't know what a trees, they don't know what trees or forests are.
And they think their entire world is...
just the town and the mountain. And the creature likes it that way because
he lives in the well, and they wish to the well. And they, you know, he gets to control their lives.
I think he sees you as a threat because
this machine might change all of that. And so
thematically everything that we wrote, the way the townsfolk react to you,
the way the creature, what the creatures goals are and what your goals are. What Danielle and Roger, the sort of main
NPCs of the game are all about. It's about sort of like perspective
it's about like realizing the world's bigger than yourself and
and
The dangers of being too insular with all of that. Mm-hmm
I mean, I'm trying to talk about it without telling you how it ends. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I know
I think that's valuable
But like I don't know if you walk up if you walked up to any of these houses in the game
But like you'll see that the people of town like, you know, they're afraid of you
And they're that way because the creatures told them, you know, like don't talk to this engineer. Don't talk to this robot
He's you know, he's threatening to change your way of life and people, you know can be afraid of change. Yeah, and
And so that's kind of what the story is about Roger
It is helping you out because he's really excited about knowledge.
And the thing that he really geeks out about is the machine.
He knows that his family was part of making it, but he's not totally sure how.
And then Danielle is cool with you because she's old.
And she knows better.
And so those two are the only two people in town that are really willing to help you on your journey against the creature.
But that's like.
You know, we tried to build the theme around that idea and build the characters that would
help you, you know, making sure we were really clear about how they felt about that theme
and you know, all that.
Is there anything from your personal life that sort of drew that theme into the story?
Probably.
Like the sense of a town that was intelerate and not wanting to respond to people?
Yeah, well, I mean, I can't think of like an exact example, but I think, you know, the best writing and the best storytelling you do has to come from something that you've lived.
But I can't think of like an exact moment where I was arguing with my grandfather or something about his...
point of view or anything like that. No. That's fair. Let's see. We are 45 minutes into this
chat. We've got a few minutes left here. Adam, I guess you're coming close to finishing this
thing. What's been one of the most exciting parts for you, this latent development? What's
been exciting about getting here, I guess? Showing it to people is really the best part.
It's funny.
You know, the end of the process is very technical and very tedious, and it's mostly on Bo's shoulders,
and I'm trying to not annoy him too much, because it's just, you know, getting it on all the platforms
and, like, making sure it runs, different things break on different parts of it. But, like, really,
you know, getting to talk about it is a big, is sort of a huge milestone at the, towards the end
of a project. Announcing it and seeing how people react is such a huge thing. You know, development
now is...
isn't quite as announced release as it used to be.
People know about games a lot earlier than they are released and that's been a weird
thing to adapt to.
We're used to much shorter productions and so this is the first time when I've been working
on something for this long it's been announced and it still has a long time before it comes
out, back in March when we announced it.
And so it's just been really cool to see people actually be excited and actually anticipate
the release, which is soon I promise.
And so that's always super satisfying.
You work on something for so long and you love it, but you're not sure anybody else is going to love it.
And then if people do, it's really nice.
Right on.
Um, kind of a... I had kind of a follow-up.
Oh, no, I had a question and I think it slipped out of my head.
It was something about... Oh, no, did I die again?
It'll come to you.
Yeah, this was weird. Something weird happened here and that's why I'm going to skip the puzzle when we get back.
It's like the room, the puzzle, like, completed and the bouncer was there when I got back but it was still like wanting me to...
Oh, that's interesting. Okay.
You'll see it when we go through. I skip it at the end.
Um... Oh, there was something... Yeah, oh yeah, I guess, um, uh, when it comes to...
I guess, like, on some level you're concerned a little bit with about selling your game and getting...
I'm not sure if I have any interest for it.
Have you thought anything about how discoverability and how this game...
Obviously you want your game to look...
I didn't heal up when I...
Okay, thank god I healed up.
Have you thought at all about what it takes to make a game that other people...
We'll care about, which sounds kind of vague, but at the same time it's the question that everyone's asking, like,
you can make a wild, unique game that doesn't get anything, or then you can make Slay the Spire,
and suddenly you're one of the most popular games on Steam. Have you been thinking about it at all, about how your design process is affecting that?
Yeah, that's a slippery slope, I think.
We talked about it earlier with the 70-30 thing.
Yeah, it's a bit of that, a lot of that comes in, but I think, you know, you do have to...
You could just make a BR game.
and you know, try to like compete on that scale, like what are people playing the most of right now.
But that's what I say, it's kind of a slippery slope where...
Here it is, yeah. See the bouncers there?
Yeah, that's interesting. You activated the final part of the room but it wasn't completed.
I think, you know, we have to trust ourselves a bit.
And say, because Bo and I play a lot of games, so it's like,
what do we wish we could see that we're not seeing, is kind of where we start.
The 70-30 thing definitely comes into play.
I think, you know, unless you give some players something to latch onto, the newness might
be too new.
It might be too difficult to get people to check it out at all.
And I think we also decide to play to our strengths.
We haven't worked a lot of time, but we've been working for about a decade, and so we
know what we're good at.
And so we try to play.
To pick projects that highlight the things we know how to do well or work with people
who are much much better at the other things than we are.
And so I think we try, you know the best thing to do, the solution we've come up with is
just try to attack that, attack that problem like as logically as we can.
But you know it's a gamble, it's a gamble.
You have to trust your instincts, like, if I like this, maybe other people will like this.
Let's use enough of the genre stuff that we know people do respond to that, like, will fit within those games.
Let's lean into our strengths, and then let's try to make a big enough twist where we actually get some attention,
because people are like, that looks different.
Right on. That is a great note, I think, to end the stream on, unless anyone has any more questions.
So I am going to start the wrap-up process here.
Thank you all for joining us on the GDC Twitch channel.
If you have enjoyed this conversation, we'd love it if you hit the follow button,
because we're going to have more interviews with cool developers.
So, you know, long as long as the lights are on, we're going to keep doing them.
Uh, um, that was grimmer than I anticipated, but don't worry.
Uh, I was, I was trying to lead into hyping up.
We've got some really interesting interviews coming your way.
We're going to be talking to the devs behind, um, Age of Wonders, Planetfall,
which is out this week.
We're going to be talking to them later this month.
We're trying to talk to Richard Rouse III, a game designer who spends a lot of time at GDC,
about his new game, Church in the Darkness, trying to make that happen.
There's some other great games coming out this fall that we want to be talking to the developers for,
and hopefully we will do it with you right here on the GDC Twitch channel.
If you are a game developer yourself and you want to know more about game making,
we encourage you to check out GDC.
If you've got a great talk idea, you can actually submit a talk for GDC.
Right now, the core concepts talks are still taking submissions.
Adam, if you want to submit something, that would be really cool.
Maybe I should.
Yeah, but then also look out for the summit submissions will be opening up soon later this month.
If you are a VR or AR developer, please join us at XRDC this fall in October.
You can check out xrdcconf.com.
I'll put that in...
I just put that in chat for you guys so that you can check that out if you want.
Actually, funny enough, Adam's coworkers will be there with their World War I game that
I'm blanking on the name of.
War Remains.
It's called War Remains.
War Remains, yeah.
War Remains with Hardcore History's Dan Carlin.
They'll be showing off how they made it at XRDC, so check that out too.
And that's all I've got for now.
Adam, if they've got any questions about Creature in the Well, where should they ask them?
You can follow Creature in the Well on Twitter at CreatureWell.
CreatureInTheWell.com has all the links to all the stores and all that coolness.
And that's it.
Right on.
Okay, with that everyone, I hope you have a happy Wednesday.
I hope you're enjoying your summer.
Stay cool, stay hydrated, and with that, have a good day.
Bye.