So my name is Cole Worley and I'm the staff designer and sort of the de facto head of
development at Leader Games, which is a small game studio.
based in St. Paul, Minnesota.
We have about seven people on staff,
which is sort of like large for a small studio,
but nowhere near what like an actual publisher
would look like.
We all still only work in one room.
And over the past couple years,
I have been working for them,
and we have together have made the game Root,
which I'll be talking a little bit today.
And then in addition to that,
I have a small micro publisher with my brother
where we do sort of weird history games.
I've been thinking about and designing games
about conflict, about king-making,
and about how uncomfortable it makes us feel for a while,
and so I'm gonna kind of put those thoughts together.
When I originally sat out to give this talk,
I thought I'd start with something like a Root post-mortem.
You know, this is a GDC talk,
and people seem to like picking apart dead bodies,
but Root, it still feels way too early for it.
We have a big Kickstarter going on right now,
there's lots of content coming down the pipe.
And I just don't think I have a vantage point which I could think systematically about what
Root is and what it's done well and not done well.
Although if you do have questions about the creation, we can certainly talk about that
in the Q&A.
However, when I was thinking about this talk, as I dug into Root, I was reminded of the
strangeness of the design.
Now, for any of you who've sort of gone through
all the paces with the big project,
you know that by the end of the project,
it seems like the most natural thing in the world.
But with a little bit of distance,
you can be reminded of how weird it is.
Root is a strange game, and it's done well.
Every year we'll kind of produce like a breakout hit.
I just had never thought that anything
I'd ever work on would do it.
It just wasn't something that we were designing for.
Now, I don't mean to sound ungrateful about any of this.
Root was blessed with a wonderful creative team.
and a great artist.
These are some drawings from Kyle Fair
and I just want to show off his talent
because I get to bother him
and fill out the art request list
and I want to show it off.
The game is cute, it's adorable,
it pulls people in and it has a really nice pitch.
So Root is an asymmetric strategy game.
Now usually when we say an asymmetric strategy game,
people tend to think about it on the order of different powers in a D&D party.
One person's the tank, another person might be healing, someone's a magic user or a thief.
Root's really asymmetric, so dramatically asymmetric that the different player positions
are almost operating in different games.
So as an example, the way the pitch goes, if I were encountering you guys at PAX East
or something.
It's basically one player is managing a kingdom.
She starts the game with full control of the board,
a warrior in nearly every clearing.
There are buildings all over the place.
She's freshly conquered the woodland.
And all she needs to do is keep the peace.
And she's keeping the peace so that she can move
her resources around and build her kingdom up.
And during that process, a rebellion might break out,
and she might have to deal with sympathy for the insurgents.
In order to put down the rebellion,
she might find help from a wandering mercenary.
But if the mercenary in putting down the rebellion
becomes more popular than she is,
then maybe she'll have to exile that mercenary.
There's no script to this.
All of these interactions happen organically.
And rather than these different events
sort of being dictated by a draw of an event card,
Each one of these different positions is essentially a different player.
One player plays, you know, essentially an adventure game working within the larger game.
The player who's playing the rebellion is having to be really, is essentially playing
a political game underneath the economic game that the Marquis de Cat is playing.
Now usually around this time, if I'm at a convention,
I'll turn around the box and they'll see
these really cute meeples.
And the thing is more or less sold on the spot
because look at that meeple.
But before I ring them up on the register,
I have to be as straight as possible with them.
Root is not a game for everybody.
Usually the test I give to prospective buyers
looks something like this.
Are you okay with the fact that one of your friends
is going to put pieces on the board,
and then another one of your friends
is going to remove those pieces,
and they might laugh at you when they do it.
And if you can pass that test,
you're probably a good candidate to buying it.
There's just no getting around it.
The game is very, very mean.
And it's mean in a way that is a little out of step
with not only the kinds of games
that sell to a broad audience in the hobby market,
but also a more general design ethos.
Now, it's mean, I think when we talk about the meanness,
I should be specific what I'm talking about.
There are no catch-up mechanisms.
There's a lot of direct player interaction.
Some of it is zero-sum.
I'm gonna take something and you can't have it.
It's also got a really, really high variance.
Depending on the faction mixes, the play styles,
all of the things around the actual playing of the game,
a round of Root can look very, very, very different.
and I don't want to hide that from the players.
Now, usually these sorts of elements
are kind of regarded as a little bit old-fashioned,
and they get polished out in the development process.
I've been fortunate to be on the development teams
for many games, and I know that when a game
goes from design to development, the questions shift, right?
When you're designing a game,
you're trying to make an impression.
You're trying to capture the imagination
of your prospective publisher.
But when you're developing a game,
you're trying to make sure that you're not
gonna make your players mad.
Right?
I mean, it's a wholly different set of skills.
You don't wanna make your players mad.
You want them to come back, to like it.
You don't want hate mail on BGG
or really angry Reddit threads.
So when Root started moving from design to development,
I was a little worried because of the things
that I really liked about the game
were the things that I knew
were going to be totally destroyed in development.
Thankfully, Patrick Leder, our owner and creative director,
had the temerity to also let me be on the development team,
and which is an awful decision.
You should never allow a designer to work on development.
I really love development,
and I love the process of cutting something apart
that I've spent a year building.
But I worked really hard to make sure that even as we made
the game more elegant and as we sort of cut it up nicely,
that the weird parts were the parts that stayed.
So, today I want to talk a little bit about
the sharp edges of root, the meanness of the game.
And I want to do this not by talking about root,
but instead by talking about why we think of those things
as sharp edges in the first place,
and what we might be losing when we don't explore them.
And so in order to sort of launch this exploration, I think we have to think about a sort of central term,
and that term for me is kingmaking.
Because ultimately, Root is a game about kingmaking.
I always have a good laugh when I see a thread and someone's like,
oh man, Root, I heard that it has a kingmaking problem.
And I'm like, it doesn't have a kingmaking problem, it is the kingmaking problem.
And it's a political game.
I mean, if you're making a political game,
it makes sense that you're dealing with concepts
like power brokers, right?
But the fact that we oftentimes get friction there
from people wanting to buy the game or from critics,
I think suggests that we are currently in a tabletop era
that is really locked into a certain kind of design ethos.
So we're going to start by talking a little bit about kingmaking and I'm going to try to trace
why I think it's fallen out of fashion and then I want to marshal a sort of like simple defense
for kingmaking and then talk about some practical lessons for those would-be practitioners out there.
So, king making.
The act of making someone king, it's pretty simple.
The term is actually a little bit more interesting than that.
It starts with this guy, there he is,
Richard Neville, Earl Warwick.
By the way, you're gonna get a lot of stupid,
no animation PowerPoints from me with old pictures
because I come from an academic background
and that's how we do our PowerPoints.
So this guy Richard Neville, the Earl of Warwick, Warwick the Kingmaker he was called during the War of the Roses,
that title was used almost entirely derisively because he was, you know,
back, you know, we're back in the era of the divine right of kings. If you have someone, a human, deciding who to become king,
that's an awful heretical idea.
And so it falls out of fashion pretty quickly, although, and just a little note,
so the game on the right is Avalon Hill's famous game Kingmaker,
which I always thought was named after, like, the kingmaking problem,
but it's actually, no, it's about Mr. Earl of Warwick over there.
Now, an interesting thing happens in the 18th century, so a few hundred years after that,
the historian David Hume...
You didn't think I was going to go there, but here we are in the 18th century.
He starts using the word kingmaker in a very positive way.
He loves Richard Neville because for him, to be master of your age was to be in a position
where you got to determine the course of history.
And so the kingmakers are the real heroes, not the kings.
So
Here a slight bit of disclosure is needed.
I love games when I get to make the king,
even if I don't get to be the king.
And oftentimes I even enjoy the experience
when it fires against me.
When I was sort of looking for pictures
deep, deep, deep inside of Board Game Geek,
I stumbled into this one.
Circa 2006 in the Twilight Imperium.
It's in the Twilight Imperium image gallery, guys.
And this is a rare shot of me playing a game of Twilight
Imperium at the moment someone has stolen the victory for me
by passing an idiotic law.
And I just.
There's hatred in those eyes.
But also, that's a game that stuck in my mind.
When I stumbled on this picture,
which I had completely forgotten about,
I remembered so many things about that game,
including the fact that we were playing
in a weird, like, attic-y space,
and we only had three hours to play.
So we played a game of Twilight Imperium in three hours,
if you can possibly believe it.
So.
Even talking about kingmaking and thinking about the idea that it might be desirable
for you to steal a victory from your friend and to be mean to each other, it provokes
even me, a fan of the genre, it provokes a really physical response.
My stomach turns a little and I cringe.
This is strange because we all have opinions about games.
You might like party games or you might like games about Panzer tanks in World War II.
But your distaste for panzer takes doesn't lead you
to have your stomach turn.
King-making, on the other hand,
is attacking something really basic.
And as someone who plays games and designs them
and also tries to really earnestly study them,
that physical response is interesting
because it seems different from other ways of,
other preferences that we express about our games.
So.
Why do we dislike kingmaking so much?
Where does this dislike come from?
Was it always with us?
Is this sort of a new invention?
I sort of want to start here with this really, really broad
historical frame.
Because I think one thing that happens when we talk about
games is we think about them as very new.
And we like to think about, oh, you remember back
when Catan came out?
That was like the ancient age of board games, which is, of course,
not true.
But because the modern iteration of this art form
is only 30 years old, we like to extend our timeline.
And we think in gold ages and silver ages.
And we're really talking about just a couple decades.
So.
I think this is a very, very unremarkable thesis, but it's needed here.
We don't like kingmaking because we like fairness.
Fairness is really, really critically important to how we think about games, what we want
them to do, and all the rest.
We generally view our games as a contest
of skills and experience.
And we have this idea in the back of our minds
that it's gonna be fairly decided, that's important.
And this leads us to sort of weird mental leaps of logic
that aren't always necessary.
So for instance, when you sit down and play Catan,
you might roll very well in the first half of the game
and everybody else thinks, well, I've built my cities
on all of those sixes and eights
and it'll be my day soon.
And even the person who's experiencing the good luck knows that maybe their luck is going to fall off.
Now that's nonsense.
You know, it's possible an eight is never rolled in an entire game of Catan.
But even if you play something as capricious as Yahtzee,
there's a general sense that we are all experiencing the same kind of luck,
and we all need to make the most out of what is gold to us.
Now this is a totally new and crazy way of thinking.
I think that we live in an age that is really preoccupied by fairness, or at least the appearance
of fairness.
As anyone knows, the world is not a very fair place at all.
And this was a little more obvious when you go backwards. Consider for instance
Trojan War. See, I told you guys, I warned you.
Fairness is pretty new. I mean think about the Trojan War, right? Won by a tricky person doing a tricky trick and how dirty of
him to sneak a bunch of people in within a fake horse.
And in fact, Odysseus as a hero is prized for his guile. He's a trickster hero, and we love him for it.
There's nothing fair about the whole thing.
This can be broadly extended to a lot of the ways
that people have written and thought about games
since the inception of games themselves.
Some of the first records of games of chess being played
were games where cheating took place,
and then people were often killed afterwards,
which is why they bothered to write it in the first place.
If you, I mean, you can stumble upon that.
If you just search like history of chess and cheating,
like, it is incredible the number of people who have died
because they slid their.
They just happened to find a way to put their queen on the board in the late game.
There's a famous anecdote about Napoleon being awful at chess, but the other anecdote about
Napoleon in chess is that usually at the end of his game, the person who's playing this
would notice that both of the bishops were on the same color.
But by that point, Napoleon had whisked away and was doing some real conquering.
And it was actually, I won't get into all this stuff
because I could go on all day.
There was a sense that even cheating was part of the game
and what you could get away with at the table,
I mean it was all part of it.
I mean really Bridge, for those of you who have
taken any look at Bridge, so much of that game is
what is the cool informal communication system
that we can arrive at without anybody realizing
that we're sort of breaking the rules of Bridge
without really breaking the rules of Bridge.
Teaching at the University of Texas, we often used this story called
The Queen of Spades by a guy named Alexander Pushkin.
And it's an interesting story in the context of this talk,
because basically it's about a game, a game of pharaoh, a gambling game.
And the main character, his name's Herman, he's an engineer, and
he hates games.
He hates how capricious, how seemingly unfair they are.
And then he discovers that there might be a trick to pharaoh,
a secret strategy which will lead him to always win.
And like so many addled users of BGG, he hunts the forums and he figures out exactly what
the critical trick is to win at Pharaoh.
And he figures it out.
And he cheats a bunch of people out of their money.
How unfair for the people he played against.
And then in typical Russian narrative logic, he loses all his money and goes insane.
So unfair for the people he cheated, unfair for himself, unfair for everybody.
That's games.
Now, it may seem a little trite to just be talking
about literature in this way.
Like, obviously, I'm drifting a little bit
from the stakes of games.
But I want to just make sure that we all realize
that this ethos of unfairness, this
extended to many different spheres of life.
One quick example I'll give everyone
is the trial by ordeal and by combat.
So this is a sort of.
judicial test, a bit of jurisprudence,
where basically if you don't know whether or not someone is telling the truth,
you just start lighting them on fire, or you dump them in the water,
and if they're telling the truth, God will save them.
And if they're not, then
obviously they were wrong.
Now, that seems insane to us.
The critical thing is that fairness wasn't important.
It was this capital T truth that was looming behind things.
And the capital T truth could be paradoxical
and could be rotten and all of those things.
Now in Germany, the fabled land of board games,
in ancient Germany, they sort of spun this
into a tradition known as trial by combat.
And what's interesting about even trial by combat is you don't practice it or you're not supposed to.
It's not about like the bigger guy is always going to win in a trial of combat. It's the person who's right.
They get to win. So this is always, you know, the thing about might versus right that sometimes gets forgotten is
in
so many sort of dogmatic logics,
might is given to the people who are right. It's not like I'm strong so I'm
going to pin you down to the ground and make you do whatever you'd like,
whatever I'd like you to do, which is a very like modern way of reviewing it. It's
like no,
God has appointed certain people to be strong and then they also carry a kind
of rightness with them.
And the more modern like spinning of dueling and honor all that, it kind of
flies out from this. Now...
I'm going to stop here sort of with the historical stuff to just step back and say that, okay,
so right now, if you think about the modern design ethos, how we think about games and
what makes a good game and a bad game, fairness is very important.
And here we have one man shooting another man probably over something really stupid,
although not in this case because it's Hamilton and Burke.
So how do we get to fairness?
Where does it come from?
Now I'm not going to give you guys a full chronology
of fairness because we've got more interesting things
to talk about, but there is a very easy short history of it,
which is to say we can talk about Victorian morality.
Now board games, this is the origin of board games
in the modern sense.
So board games come about in the 19th century
and they're the result of basically three things.
One, printing got really cheap.
You get steam presses, it's easy to manufacture,
you've got a factory system that can glue things
onto pasteboards, so they get very cheap.
More people know how to read, which you need
for a lot of these early board games.
And the last thing is you have a sense of,
a utilitarian sense that maybe we should be
teaching people things.
So this is a very early board game from 1843
called The Mansion of Happiness by a guy named George Fox.
And like most Victorian board games, it's a roll and move.
How fun.
You basically make no decisions and you land on spaces
and then you either get to go further
if you landed on a space where you did something good
or you go backwards if you did something naughty.
And the reward of the game is you get into heaven, which is also nice.
Now what is really wild here is like life is still in circulation, guys.
We have not moved past this point really at all.
We just have a more colorful spinner.
And in 1886, this is one of many, I love this, the game of the district messenger boy or
merit rewarded.
Now, what is interesting about this second game is that it's not couched in spiritual
terms.
Basically, in spiritual terms, basically if you do things that are good and nice, then
you get money in the game and you get more and more money and then eventually you're
Andrew Carnegie.
Now some of you might be noticing a weird disconnect here.
So here's a game that is maybe teaching you about the dangers of gambling, but you're
rolling a die.
So like I roll the die and I landed on, oh dang, bet all my money in cards, go back.
And then someone else rolls the die and they say, you gave up gambling, advance.
But we both rolled a die.
So there's a weird mechanical and thematic friction
happening here.
And I think a lot of our current design ethos
comes out of a desire to fix this problem.
So we arrive then at the fun and fair design ethos.
Games should delight, and they should instruct.
So we want, like those happy, happy Victorian children,
we want to learn in our games,
we want to be enriched by them,
and we want to be delighted by them.
But.
In order to make the games coherent,
you need to make it so that skill and experience
are rewarded by victory.
And I think basically everything about how we practice
design sort of comes out of this tension, right?
We want our games to be fair,
because if they're not fair,
then we're not teaching the lesson that we want to teach.
But if you have a game be charged with something like,
morality, right? If you win the game, you are the most economical, you are the most
virtuous. Then what the game is also doing is, sort of like in Calvinist fashion, separating
out the damned from the saved, the winners from the losers, and anybody who's ever lost
a friend or a family member over a game of Monopoly realizes that there's like a real
charge to this, right?
So remember how at the beginning, when I was talking about kingmaking, I was feeling a
little queasy?
Looking at these Victorian children also makes me feel queasy, because I feel like fairness
itself is a little storied, and when you start thinking about it, when you start thinking
about the cool games that we're making as part of an ideological program, it makes the
games a lot less cool.
So it actually gets a lot worse.
When I was a graduate student, I stumbled into this book,
James Magnin's, or J.A. Magnin's,
The Game Ethic and Imperialism.
I apologize for that just awful type of a title.
I literally stumbled into this book.
It was in a free stack in a box,
and I just tripped over it
as I was walking down the hallway.
And at the time, I was working on a game about Afghanistan
and thinking a lot about
sort of turn of the century game design.
And so I just put the book in my bag and thought, cool,
I'm going to learn about H.G. Wells' war games.
and maybe something about empire and something like that.
And it was, you know, like any book that you acquire,
it takes like a year to actually open it up.
And when I did open it up, I found that it was actually
about something quite different, which is the games ethic.
And I think this is a really useful and powerful idea.
So the basic argument that Magnin makes is this.
Sports, games in general, as a competitive
and serious hobby, they emerge
in the 19th century public school system in Britain.
Now the public school system means something in the British context that's different from
the United States context.
So in the U.S. when we talk about public schools, we just mean state-controlled schools.
In the British context, a public school is about the management of empire and the management
of the broader sort of governmental and bureaucratic apparatus of the state.
So Addis Combe and a whole lot of other schools were basically founded to staff the British
imperial venture abroad.
because they needed clerks, right, in India.
So.
What Mangan talks about is like games, early games,
were not about being fit or having fun.
Like the delight part was just the lure.
It was just the loot box to get you to play again.
Actually, there was an ideological program at work.
And here's how he describes it.
Basically, the school administrators
were convinced in the desirability of games,
especially team games in training the young.
This is a quote from him.
They believed in the value of those games
for the development of ethical behavior.
They had a view of education that was not only national, but also imperial.
They saw it as their duty to give a lead to the imperial world.
So all these schools start spreading throughout India, and they're having Indian cricket teams,
and all the best teams in cricket these days are Indian teams.
But it was part of the civilizing mission to sort of teach fairness, and to teach rules
and law.
because all of those things reflected the sort of ideological program of the British state.
Now, this can seem a little distant from us, right?
Here we are in San Francisco, GDC, and we are so, so very far from the imperial program.
But what you should know is that this tradition is still very much with us,
and many of you guys are somewhat indoctrinated into it, including myself.
I'm sorry to break your bubble.
So rugby, we know, the game of rugby, it comes in name from the rugby school.
It spawned a whole genre of novels called the British boarding school genre, including
a novel called Tom Brown's School Days, which was the blue point for Harry Potter, of course.
Harry Potter is an English boarding school drama.
He's learning right now how to be a good little imperial servant, even though he doesn't think
of himself that way.
But if you get good at Quidditch, you'll get good at Empire.
Now, the point of all this is not to suggest that fairness is wrong and that sports don't
teach you good things about being a person and existing in society.
It's just that I think that we have a lot to gain from giving ourselves a little bit
of distance from the concept and for starting to imagine.
Or maybe not imagine, but starting to treat the history of fairness as storied, right?
If you are shooting for fairness in a design you're working on, you're making a kind of value judgment.
And you should just keep that in mind as you're peddling your design.
So what happens then?
if we look for a different framework to design from?
Maybe not an overall rejection of fairness,
but just downgrading its value.
Suddenly things like spite and being mean for no reason,
like what if those are able to do something?
Well, I think when you boil everything away,
This shift in design priorities leads fundamentally
to games where the winner is decided by a cabal
rather than some sense of individual merit.
In other words, we're talking about kingmaking.
This, of course, being an old cover
of the excellent, excellent game Diplomacy.
So I want to tell you now and just offer a short defense of kingmaking as a concept and
how we can go about that defense and then I'll talk about some design takeaways and
sort of like practical tips for it.
So I want to build this defense first on narrative grounds.
Because I think that games are fundamentally a storytelling medium.
Even when we're talking about games like The Estates or Chicago Express
or some nerdy train game that has a spreadsheet in it,
the biggest math fest game is still a storytelling game.
It's communicating a kind of narrative.
And so the critical language that we use to talk about stories
is just well appointed to talk about games.
In this sense...
I think that we can talk about games in terms of cliché.
So we know, for instance, that in romantic comedies, or comedies more general in the
classic sense, that they're going to end in a marriage.
That's a narrative cliché.
Likewise, you know that when you're done playing an empire builder that everything that you
did is going to cash out in really neat sets of three to one, like gold to victory point.
Because we've got to tighten those scores somehow and make everybody feel like they
were close to the end of the game, even though it was no contest at all.
And these clichés can be frustrating because I'm sure you've had the thought watching a
romantic comedy that it would have been much better if she would have left him at the end
of the first act and the movie would have been much more interesting if she had just
gone on a road trip.
But the song and dance of going through the building of an engine and its scoring.
is it's circumscribing the possible expression.
And again, and I'll say this several more times,
this isn't to suggest that those games are wrong.
I love both of these games, especially Race.
And I think that they are worth designing, playing,
and there's still a lot of room to explore there.
But we shouldn't allow that kind of genre
to dominate our larger thinking about games.
Kingmaking, in this sense, offers an alternative type
of storytelling.
It allows designers and players to tap
into a really long tradition of betrayal and manipulation
that's as old as narrative itself.
And it forms the foundation for a lot of media
that we enjoy today, from The Bachelor to Game of Thrones.
And there's no reason why we shouldn't
play with those concepts.
When we talk about the engine builder, the primary sort of motif is construction.
It's progressive.
I won't go into Whig history because I'll bore you guys all to death, but what Kingmaking
offers us is perhaps the most powerful narrative tool that any writer has ever used, which
is to say it allows you to use irony.
It allows you to tell a story of revenge and redemption without worrying that everyone's
going to feel that they were fairly treated.
It just opens up the kind of stories that you can tell.
Now a quick sidebar to note that
One space in games that has been really exploring this area
is the single session RPG.
There's a lot of interesting work
happening with independent RPG makers
that it's well worth viewing.
And even if playing D&D makes you
self-conscious or uncomfortable, you
should buy some of the books I'm going
to mention here in a second, because they
are very, very interesting.
just from their formal perspective.
And here I'm thinking about Avery Adler's The Quiet Year
and all of the rest of the games she's produced.
And a game by a company called Thorny Games called Dialect.
These are games that really upset
what you might think is even possible
in the space of a game.
And even if you don't play them,
the rules are powerful enough.
Okay, so if we are going to build games about
kingmaking, we need a different framework.
We can't use fairness as the bedrock
to build our design practice on.
We have to find something else.
So what do we find?
Well, some people would jump to this gentleman over here,
Renier Kinizia, who has made a few games.
And he has this quote that you will see
like tacked onto profiles.
And I'll just, I'll read it here.
When playing a game, the goal is to win.
But it is the goal that is important, not the winning.
This is a little bit like the old canard
about the journey being more important than the destination.
And it's fine.
The main problem with it is it's relentlessly individualistic.
It's about your personal experience of encountering the game,
which I think, while that's a nice thought,
it doesn't get into what makes something like Kingmaking so difficult,
which is to say that my personal journey is going to intersect with yours,
and one of us is going to rob the other and continue the journey.
So, in sort of searching for a new framework, I found myself reaching for Bernie DeKoven's
amazing 1978 book, The Well-Played Game, which I think is just an unbelievable text and one
that anybody interested in design should check out.
And in Bernie DeKoven's book, he has this really wonderful distinction he makes between
playing to win and having to win.
And there's a way that...
This could be described simply as like another version of what Kinesia is talking about,
but for De Koven, it has nothing to do with individual experience.
Basically, when you play to win, you must win.
Okay, cool. Everyone's always playing to win.
But when you have to win, you must win because
you are unsure of your own position in the community of players.
And only by winning can you kind of prove yourself in that position.
So basically, you know, if you think about
all of the theory around the magic circle and the exceptional space of the game...
What DeKoven is talking about is if you don't close that circle entirely and you bring in
some of the outside world into your game, you're going to get people who are going to
try to use the game as a way to manipulate the world outside of the game and that's where
all the bad feelings come from.
So he has a short note on this.
I'm just going to, I didn't put this up,
but I think for those of you who are interested in DeKoven's
work, it can all be pretty much summed up
in this kind of short little snippet.
He describes games in this way.
This is a quote.
We were willing to play.
We were each willing to play the particular game.
We were willing to play with each other.
And we arrived at the well-played game
because of the way we combined with the game.
Now, that's a little like woo-woo by today's standards,
and know that if you do buy a copy of The Well-Played Game,
an excellent book, it's entirely like that.
It's like a giant stream of consciousness,
exploration of play.
But I think what is so powerful about DeKoven's idea is
to
back out from the individual instance of the game
and to really reassert the power of play
as the thing that the game is allowing you to do.
The game is the medium that allows players
to interact with each other.
And if you are having the perfect experience of play,
the victory is putting everybody on the same page,
but it doesn't necessarily have to be the thing
that is keeping them there.
So, thinking about.
as a foundation for kingmaking,
I want to talk a little bit about some takeaways.
What are some things that we can do
with this alternate framework?
A framework that doesn't overly emphasize fairness.
Well, I think that I have a kind of set of rules
that I think about when I'm working on a design,
especially a design that I know
is going to feature a lot of kingmaking.
The first rule is that, as in all things,
consent is absolutely critical.
You do not want to misdirect your players.
It's really important that everybody realizes
what kind of game they're going to play.
Dukovin has an interesting chapter in the well-played game where he talks about something
called the dangerous game.
And he notes in this chapter that dangerous games cannot involve people who haven't accepted
the threat or haven't chosen to play the dangerous game.
Now, this is a really interesting kind of two-tiered view of this.
It's a little bit like watching a horror movie.
You obviously would never want to watch a horror movie with somebody who hates horror
movies.
And so that's obviously bad.
But what is less obviously bad, but what is still bad,
is watching a horror movie where half the people
like watching it because they think it's funny,
and the other half the people like watching it
because they think it's scary.
Each of those, that heterogeneity and that viewing base
really can hurt an experience.
And so for DeKoven, it's important,
if you want to play a dangerous game,
to agree to play it, but then also to accept the danger.
So, you should be honest about it.
Now,
It's also important to realize that if you are designing a game about king making,
that the relationships between the players, that's everything.
Mechanisms do not matter so much as the relationships to the player,
and this is a very easy thing to forget when you're working in design.
What will happen sometimes is when the relationships between the players are not highlighted,
the interactions, the king-making interaction
in the last stage of the game can feel like a cruel joke.
If I've been hoarding stone the entire game
so I can upgrade my clay house,
and you take it from me in the last turn
despite never touching me the entire game,
it's not going to feel like
an ironic coup or something worth thinking about.
It's just going to feel like a bad joke.
And this, I think, brings me to Risk,
which I think is still just a brilliant and wonderful game.
Maybe more fun to think about than to play.
But one of the real tricks of Risk
is that there's no negative space on the board.
So what kind of game are you playing when you play Risk?
Well, it's a game where you're going to hurt each other,
and there's no way to get around it.
I often wonder, a lot of space 4X games have this problem where the first third of the
game is very quiet and it's about synergies and building up, and then in the second half
you tear down all the work you did in the first half, and it usually makes people feel
rotten.
And I think if the board started full, you would get around this problem.
This is one reason, by the way, in Root...
the board starts completely full.
And the primary aggressor in the game,
the faction called the Eerie Dynasties,
they're playing a program game
where they are literally having to program in attacks
so that they have sort of deniability.
They're like, I didn't mean to attack you.
It's just that's what I promised I would do
for the rest of the game.
So another note about this is,
another interesting line about that kind of thematic
and mechanical cohesion is a comparison
between something like Inish and Blood Rage.
So these are both like, if you look at just the boxes
and the pieces, you're like, oh yeah,
there's some war happening in these boxes.
In Inish, you fight all the time.
Oh, it's a fighting game.
It's a very fighting game.
But Blood Rage is really more of like a drafting game.
It's like much closer to Sushi Go than it is to Risk.
And that isn't to denigrate Blood Rage.
I think Eric Ling's brilliant and he did a good job with it.
But it can create weird moments
because there are times when like.
you thought you were playing a drafting game,
but then it slides into being a little bit of a war game,
and it feels like not at ease with itself.
Whereas in Inish, you're playing a drafting game,
but the drafting game is entirely about action denial
and about fighting.
So the third thing I think that's very important
is to give players diplomatic flexibility.
There aren't villains in real life.
We have partners and we have adversaries.
And sometimes our partners become our adversaries.
And sometimes we need to find partners
in those who oppose us.
No diplomacy system you design is going to be
as clever as your players.
So you want to try to give them
the most creative framework.
that they could possibly exist in.
I think this is one reason why turn-based strategy games,
especially on the digital side,
really struggle with their diplomacy systems.
It's just hard to create the sort of freewheeling
deal-making that you see in a game like diplomacy
in a digital space.
The last takeaway is I think the most complicated one,
and it's the one that I'm the most unsure of personally.
And this has to do with the management of hope
and of victory.
So victory conditions I think are the most critical element
of any game design.
In my own practice, they are the very first thing
that I put to page, and they are the last thing
that I ever want to tamper with.
The victory conditions put everybody together.
They're like the script.
Even more than the rest of the rules,
the victory conditions bind the players together.
But you run into a problem once another player can't win.
And here I often think of Martin Wallace's 2001 game,
Liberté.
One of the things that's great about Wallace titles
is I feel like he must design very quickly because he
doesn't cover his tracks.
You can sort of see all of the development in the game just by looking at the final game.
And so Liberté is a game about the French Revolution.
It's an election game.
But the way the math of the elections works out, certain factions, certain players are
always going to be like way ahead.
Like after the first election, a couple of players are going to win like eight points
and then every, you can even see it in the screenshot actually.
Like those two people did very well and everyone else is just dead last.
And this will always happen.
This isn't like bad play.
And in fact, in the next election,
those people who are ahead, they're
going to get more ahead.
And the way Wallace dealt with this,
instead of fixing the kind of core math problem that
was producing this result, is he created two alternate victory
conditions, misery conditions, or what they're actually
called, whereby the players who are losing
can kind of flip the table over.
And they have totally different ways of winning
that are so dangerous you would never do it
unless there was no chance you were going to win by points.
And what this does is even until the very, very last moment,
all players remain kind of in the game.
Now, this to me is a very good idea,
and I like it, and I build alternate victory conditions
in almost every game that I've worked on.
But I wonder too, if there's another way
of thinking about victory that isn't so straightjacketed.
have to think about the games of Phil Eklund.
Because the thing about Phil Eklund's games,
they're immensely complicated and goofy
and they're extremely random and mean.
So this is a shot from High Frontier.
If you can believe it, this is like 1 20th
of what the board looks like.
And it is that complicated all the way through.
And in High Frontier, I once spent an hour planning a mission to one of Jupiter's moons,
and then the mission was about halfway through and I hit a radiation belt wrong, and one
of my spaceship components blew up, and I spent the next hour, like hour of game time,
attempting to rescue my poor astronauts who were drifting to one Lagrange point or another.
And it was great.
And there's this amazing thing about Eklund's games
where the story that the game is telling is so bracing,
is so powerful, that even when you're out of condition,
out of contention for victory, you don't want to unplug.
You don't wanna un-immerse yourself.
And this is what usually happens.
If the victory condition is the only thing
that is immersing your players,
then you need to create a system
where the players always have a chance to win.
But if the other storytelling techniques
are giving them something, then the victory condition
starts to be a little less important.
So I want to close with a short quota,
and then we'll have about 15 minutes for questions,
which is to talk a little bit about video games,
since this is primarily a video game design conference.
So one of the funny things is that the space
that I work in in design, these multilateral conflict games,
video games are really bad at them.
Like, horrible.
Like, if you've ever played a game of StarCraft in the free-for-all mode, I'm just sorry.
Because the games just aren't designed for it.
I mean, even multiplayer competitive games, if you think about something like Dota or
any of the other MOBAs, I mean, or Counter-Strike, these are 5v5s, these are team sports.
In terms of the actual game theory, we're talking about formally two-player games, even
if they have multiple humans involved.
Or cooperative experiences, something like Overcooked.
Games just really aren't, digital games, they have a hard time with the free-for-all game,
with the exception of something that's happened in the past couple years, which is to say the rise of the Battle Royale.
I think that these are the most important games that have been developed since Minecraft, and probably even maybe more important because they are truly
multilateral conflict games, and even if you hate them, if you've played them, you probably have memories from the games you have played.
You've played games where you've randomly died,
and then the rest of your squad has attempted to avenge you
as they hunted your killer over the battlefield.
And you watched them with rapt attention
because even though your character was dead,
you were still in the game.
They have amazing storytelling capacity.
When we talk about open world games, we usually...
are not talking about open world so much as a very full world,
where every nook and cranny of a setting
has all these little side plots and branching narratives in it.
For my money, the Battle Royale games
are the only true open world games out there,
because it's really emergent what can happen.
You have no idea the kind of story
that each match is going to tell, outside of the fact
that you need to spend your first 10 minutes feverishly
looting before you get shot.
And, you know, I've been talking mostly about storytelling and not so much like mechanisms
and strategy, although we can go into that in the Q&A if you'd like, but one thing I
will say is these games also produce really interesting strategic concerns.
If you are on, you know, a hill watching the last two squads, or maybe the last two squads,
fight and exhaust themselves...
you might want to intervene and get that loot.
But if you fire your weapons, you
might telegraph your position to those squads
or to another squad that might be watching you.
There are all these concerns about position, exposure,
and supply.
These are really interesting strategic concerns
that are only made possible because we're dealing
with a multilateral conflict.
So in short, I think that by looking at games which are about kingmaking and which really,
frankly, address problems of multiplayer and rather address problems of the multilateral
Let me start that over.
So in short, what I'm trying to say is, basically, designs that feature high player interaction,
that feature multilateral conflict, I think they've got big storytelling payoffs that
are worth investigating, and I also think that they also have big strategic payoffs.
And there's a whole world of different sorts of designs that we just sort of need to explore,
but part of that is realizing our own assumptions about the kind of games that we value.
deciding whether or not we might wanna challenge
some of those assumptions.
All right, thank you guys.
So there's a mic in the center of the room.
I'm happy to take any and all questions
relating to this talk or anything else.
And go ahead and tell me your name and where you're from.
Hi, John Peeble from Tucson, Arizona.
Great talk, thank you.
Just a quick comment, just played Liberté two weeks ago and pulled off a Royalist win
in turn three.
Very satisfying.
Excellent.
And two questions for you.
First, you mentioned about the disconnect between luring players into an experience
they might not be prepared for.
Can you talk about any concerns your team had about the Q-art and the actual gameplay
of Root?
So that is a great, great question, thank you.
John, right?
Correct.
So we work a little strangely
compared to other game studios,
so in terms of other publishers.
So we're a little game studio.
We all pretty much work in one room
and then our artist is remote
and we take every product we work on
from the cradle to the grave altogether.
Which means when Patrick said, hey, I want to do an asymmetric strategy game, and I said,
cool, I want to make it be about counterinsurgency, the question of where we set it and how it
appears, that was a day two question for us.
And we spent a lot of time talking with our artist Kyle Farrin about how we were going
to go about presenting it.
And early on, we kind of arrived at a strategy, which was...
So there are sort of two problems with introductory war games.
Problem one is introductory war games play nothing like actual war games.
And I think Blood Rage is quite instructive here, right?
Like Blood Rage is a drafting game.
It's not a war game, I think, in any kind of meaningful sense, and I don't think anybody
– that's a bit of a straw man.
I don't think anybody would necessarily defend that.
So that's problem one, right?
So we wanted to make sure that if this was an introductory game,
that it was actually going to show people
what the other games looked like.
The other problem that introductory games have
is that they try to bring people into the hobby,
but they do it in a way that isn't actually that accessible.
So Blood Rage has really intense art.
It's just a lot of like blood and brawny guys.
And even like memoir, which is a little more cartoony,
is a game for like your uncle or dad, right?
It's like, oh cool, World War II, yes.
So we wanted a theme that really tried to broaden things out.
And so Kyle, we were working on this adventure game,
and Kyle was setting it in this sort of Robin Hood-esque.
animal world and it occurred to us that that actually might be the perfect way to theme
the game because it gives you a kind of step of distance from the violence a little bit.
So the meanness in Root isn't often nasty, it's more like comical and that distance we
could use to put a lot of actual like really harsh interaction in the design.
So we sort of calibrated it to give people enough space
to address it.
We also, so this came up in the Keyforge talk,
which I thought was really interesting.
We really consciously avoided any direct theming
when it came to the design.
Because I don't care if your woodland alliance are Marxists
or if they're like militia radicals.
I want the players to be able to kind of like
fill in the ideologies.
So all the different player positions are presented
with some ambiguity so that the players can kind of project
and inhabit the world.
And one of the best ways we could do that was kind of
putting it in the storybook setting.
Thank you for that question.
And then one more for you.
Go ahead.
A lot of talk has been made about the coin series and that
being somewhat of an influence.
I was just curious if they were an influence on this
design.
So they were totally an influence.
I've been playing the coin game since Andy and Abyss
first came out.
I try to wear all my influences on my sleeve as best as I can, so I talked about the coin
games and I think a lot of people were expecting it to be a little bit more closely modeled
after the actual mechanics of a coin game.
But by the time the design comes out
at the other end of my process,
it's hard to track where the influences were.
So the thing I wanted from the coin games
was the tension between the different player positions.
I didn't really care about the actual mechanical framework
that maintains those tensions.
So I think if you wanna see the comparison
between the influences.
You find it less by reading game reviews of a coin game
compared to a root game, and you find it more
in the way people talk about the games
and like the after action reports.
Thank you.
All right, we've got like 10 minutes,
so I'm gonna be a little bit quicker in my answers.
Yeah, this is probably gonna be a quick one.
I'm Hans from Stockholm, Sweden.
All right.
A big fan of your work.
Thank you.
For the most part.
But that's on me probably.
So I've been enjoying,
you know, but I'm also a bit puzzled about people are like consuming games,
digital games and board games through Twitch nowadays, right? Like rather than
playing it yourself and enjoying it, you're watching other people enjoy it.
How do you think like Kingmaking games or games to feature a lot of Kingmaking,
is that more fun to watch people play?
Yes. I mean, there is, there is, it is not an accident that Fortnite and Apex
are like all you see on Twitch. There is something...
about the storytelling potential of these multilateral conflict games that lends itself
really well to viewing.
And we found, I mean, so I've done a little bit of streaming, we actually just built a
streaming set up in our office for Games of Rue, and we found it was really active, people
were really into it, just coming by and watching.
One place sort of in meat space that I can talk about this,
is at a convention we have a weird way of demoing Root.
At least if I'm working the floor,
this is what I try to do.
So we set up the game, we give you a little demo,
and then you play it for 15 minutes,
and then we kick you out, and we put in the next group,
but we don't reset the game.
And so you inherit the player position of the idiot who is sitting there before you.
And what's interesting is people will come back to the booth and they'll be like, oh,
how did my little vagabond do?
Is he okay?
I'm like, no, he's not.
Everything is messed up.
But it speaks to that storytelling power and the fun of watching and of sort of moving
those stories to other forms.
We get a lot of like root fan fiction and fan art.
And I think it's in part because like the storytelling is so open.
Cool. Yeah, thank you, Gaul. Yeah, thank you.
Hey, I'm Mark from Creative Assembly in the UK.
A lot of what you said about kingmaking really rung true
with my enjoyment of games,
but what would you say are the main ways
you've looked at to discourage kingbreaking?
Can you define kingbreaking?
Kingbreaking is where you get players who take pleasure
in not helping someone else to win, but stopping someone.
Yeah, this is a really essential question, right?
Because I think that a lot of this has to do
with the frame of the question.
So the way I tend to view it is you want to create
an environment where you are going to be the person
who is made king.
And so if you're thinking about a strategy guide,
for instance, if you're worried about players
bashing the leader, there are ways of playing
a little bit more.
defensively they're going to give you coverage, and also then cultivating the kinds of alliances
that are going to spring to life.
So one thing, I didn't talk about diplomacy much in this talk, but one of the really interesting
things that you see sometimes happen in high level diplomacy games is people will make
agreements that are contingent upon the actions of other players.
So I'll say like, look, hey Turkey, I know you don't want to fight Austria, but if they
fight me, can you commit?
And so creating those kinds of informal coalitions
that will then have inertia to them in the late game
can get around some of those problems.
You are still gonna get situations
where everyone is gonna gang up on the leader.
That's, for me, that's just a phase of the game.
So in En Route, the classic time this happens
is there are these dominance cards you can play
where you basically kick off your victory point marker
and you say, look, I'm gonna win the game
if I control this part of the map.
As soon as someone plays that, everyone is going to pile on you harder than at any time
other than the game.
It's going to be ridiculously unfair, which is why you have to plan and create a situation
where you know you're going to be able to withstand it.
The other thing, the more practical answer to your question is that I think strategic
inertia is really important.
If players are going to lunge into you, it's going to do things to their late game.
if you are going, so like basically,
if you give people too much tactical flexibility,
then it's always going,
it's never gonna be able to tell a story
because it's always gonna feel
like there is no inertia to your own choices.
But if you give inertia to those choices,
then you can get around some of that problem.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah.
Thanks a little bit of a scattered answer.
Sorry, go ahead.
Hi, I'm Chris Camisso.
I go to school at the Rochester Institute of Technology
for Game Design Development.
I have a question about a board game I'm developing.
OK, hit me.
It's similar to Blood Bowl, and we
have a neutral piece, which is just a disc.
And it's basically Ultimate Frisbee with Death Gladiators.
And we have, and I really don't know if it's a super issue, that's kind of what I was here to talk, ask about.
So we have several very legitimate kind of surrender board states, where if you've lost all of say X kind of piece,
it's a very good idea to just surrender, because the game will take another 10 minutes to end, and you're not going to win.
It's just not going to happen.
And so in that way, when the king is made, the game is kind of over.
And my question is, do you think that king-making has a space in a 1v1 strategy game kind of way?
And if so, how could I, in very gentle terms, if you can't really go into specifics, that's fine, because you don't have that much time.
Sure.
Keep it so that the king doesn't just kind of cause the game to end.
Yeah, I mean, my general rule about this in my own practice is that games should be over
the moment they're over, which is to say as soon as the thing is decided, the game should
organically come to a close pretty close.
So for instance, in the redesign of Pax Premier, the game I worked on about Afghanistan, as
soon as one player is ahead by four points, it's a pretty huge lead and the game is just
over.
So there's this sudden death condition that even on the very first scoring round.
which is maybe 20 or 30 minutes into the game,
the game can be over.
And so I think, in the case of a two-player game,
you want to be as explicit and as formal
with those game end rules as possible
so that things don't drag out.
And here, really good texts for you are
Twilight Struggle, obviously,
but then also Fort Sumter and 13 Days,
which are just balanced on a knife's edge.
And as soon as one player gets
gets ahead, the game shuts off,
so that you never have that tail end
where it's just kind of a formality.
Now, in a game that is modeling sports,
that can be a little tricky, right?
It depends on the sort of theming and what you're after.
But I would say in general,
don't be afraid of sudden death conditions.
Just make sure, absolute sure,
that they are communicated to their players very clearly.
Okay, thank you. Thank you.
All right, cool, I'll repeat that here.
If other people have questions
or if you want to talk more about the Blood Bowl game,
I'll be in the wrap-up room on the other side of the hall.
All right, go ahead.
We've got time for a couple more questions.
Rick from the MIT Game Lab.
So I love DeKoven, and I actually wish more players
would read them.
I'm sorry, can you repeat that?
I love DeKoven's work, and I wish actually more players
could read them, to really understand how can we play
well together.
I'm wondering what do you think publishers could do to
encourage these kinds of game mechanics, or
even play communities?
Well, I feel like I'm able to get away with it, because I have never worked on a title
that's been meant for a general audience.
I've been lucky to have a small core audience that I sort of got through Phil, the guy who
designed High Frontier, which I've been able to kind of borrow.
And then even with my work at Leader Games,
like we have a core audience that sort of knows
the kind of work that we do.
Growing that audience takes titles like Root.
It essentially, you know, an existing audience
where you can get enough of that audience
to be playing that game and then encouraging people
who say, oh, well, I've never played a conflict game,
but I guess Root's doing well, I wanna try it out.
And like that's the moment when those audiences grow.
So for a publisher it's difficult,
because I feel like the.
At least from my perspective, the main issue
when I have my publisher hat on is,
who's our audience and how can we serve them
really, really well?
And questions of audience expansion
are kind of secondary to that,
but ultimately I think the kind of thing
that you're talking about is finding ways
to grow those audiences.
And my short answer to that is,
we just have to make the stories that the games
are telling so compelling that they can't be ignored.
Thank you.
All right, last question.
I'm Julian from the game Monster Prom from Barcelona.
The question I had, I found interesting what you said about the Battle Royale games
keeping losing players within the game thanks to emerging storytelling
and how this is encouraged by, in this case, by being very multilateral.
But if you have thought into this, what could you say?
as they come to mind another potential building blocks
to create emerging storytelling on a video game
to keep the players even if they are losing.
So you're asking specifically how do we take
some of these lessons into the video game space?
It could be also for tabletop games.
It's like how you encourage this emerging storytelling
as a way of keeping engagement.
Yeah, so I think that in general, and we're just out of time,
but I have a short but I think good answer to this question,
which is to say what you're doing when you are doing game design
is you're giving players a language to exist in the world.
And you have to pay a lot of attention to how that language is built,
because some languages are going to be quite restrictive
in the stories that you're allowing them to tell,
and other languages can be quite capacious.
And I think a good example of this is something like Fantasy Flight's Netrunner.
When Netrunner first came out,
It was easy to make fun of the fact
that they were calling actions clicks
and they had invented this funny little dialect
to talk about their game.
But what it did is it immersed players in the world
so that even when you were talking about Netrunner,
you were still playing Netrunner.
And so I think from the design perspective,
give your players a language that is as expressive
as the game itself and really well-appointed
to talk about the world that you want them to exist in.
Okay, thank you very much.
Thank you for that question.
All right, and thank you guys
for all the questions and for coming.