Hey guys. Hey y'all. Thank you so much for coming out to hear us talk. I'm Emily, this is Lil, and we're here to talk today about Smash Sisters. It's a series of events that we do for the game that we love, Super Smash Brothers. So Lil, I guess tell us, what is Smash Sisters?
Yes, that's a dying question.
So Smash Fisters is a series of side events that we run at different tournaments featuring
the Smash Brothers franchise games.
And these events are designed to bring both new and veteran women together and also important
to feed back into the overall competitive community.
So our organization is progressive and we are constantly down to change our format and
adapt to the changing needs of the women within our community.
We have now been up and running for just over a year.
Not up here saying we're the pinnacle of success,
but we've learned a lot in that year,
and here we're going to kind of delve into our knowledge.
So first a little bit more about how we started.
About a year and a half ago, you know, some people were talking on Twitter.
Surprisingly, they were shit talking on Twitter.
And a prominent smasher, Reno, was like, hmm, what about East Coast girls versus West Coast
girls?
And he was like, whoa, hmm.
First of all, I'm from New York, so obviously East Coast had it.
And we started talking a little bit about, you know, let's do a crew battle.
And we did this at a Genesis 3, which is one of the biggest grass roots smash tournaments
of all time about a year ago.
And in this Facebook event page for Genesis, I posted, hey, any girls interested in an
East Coast versus West Coast crew battle?
And it didn't seem to take off quite at first.
There wasn't a ton of interest.
And at that time, I talked to Lilz.
I reached out.
And she seemed a little trepidatious about it.
Yeah, when Emily first pitched the idea to me, I
immediately just shot it down.
And was pretty apprehensive about joining, surprisingly.
And it was very ironic of me, and I'll explain why.
Actually, just a few weeks before Emily had pitched this
idea to everybody else, I had written a blog post that was
titled, Stop Asking About All Female Tournaments.
And I'll give you the TLDR which is pretty much can we please stop bickering and hypothesizing
about the success or failure of these and just do it and see what the outcome is and
go from there.
And so in that moment when Emily reached out to me I was like, oh, man, I'd be such a hypocrite
if I were to say no.
So yeah, let's just do this.
And so Emily came in with the strengths of her event organization background.
I came in as social media.
And branding and together the ventures blew up like tons of women started reaching out to our surprise to engage and participate and we've still been running since.
So for today's talk, we're going to talk you all through a little bit about our adventure
from the past year, which includes branding, laying preparation, laying the groundwork,
and then part of our community and how complex the women's community is.
And then finally, walk you through some of the iterations and feedback that we've had
to go through.
You know, it's a lot to cover.
But...
Yeah, just worth noting, we're going to speed through all these topics, but we will be around
after to answer any questions you may have.
So hang tight.
Cool.
So the first part of it is branding.
Blank prep and ground work.
And our first piece of advice, I suppose, is that you should be a part of your community
first.
This means that, well, first of all, you know, I started competing back in 2007.
Both Lil and I have been in the Smash community for over a decade.
You know, I started running events in Dallas like five or six years ago, and now I run
tournaments in New York, and I'm one of the heads of Nebulas Esports there.
And one of my focuses has always been to, you know, lower the barrier of entry for newcomers.
This is all about community growth.
So one thing is pioneering the amateur bracket that allows players to have additional competitive
matches or giving free venue fee or free entry fee for first time newcomers.
And this allows, you know, these little things go a long way in terms of retaining members
and bringing them in in the first place.
So Smash Sisters was kind of like a natural extension of bringing people into our group.
Oh.
Wow.
Rip.
Oh, no.
All right. Don't know what's going on here but I have a slightly different history from Emily. I
started competing back in 2006. Back then I took competing a lot more seriously than I do now. I
also traveled nationally several times throughout the course of the year. And unlike Emily, I
actually distanced myself from the Smash Brothers community for a while because I felt ‑‑
There are a lot of obscure behaviors that I noticed were directed towards me.
May or may not have been due to my gender.
Who knows?
And so I actually came back like a year later after the resent had faded to kind of move
towards activism and raising awareness around these topics, which really lent itself to
you Smash Sisters, believe it or not.
And that segues perfectly into the next section, which is...
Learn the history of your target demographic specific to your scene.
All the things that we understand and all the decisions we made were based around our
knowledge having been in the community in the first place.
So I will lead with the most annoying question a female smasher could ever be asked, which
is who is the best female smasher?
And to give you some history there, the Super Smash Bros.
Brawl community actually dealt with a lot of this.
I believe they actually tried to run singles bracket format.
And what this did was it pitted a lot of the women against each other.
So that being friends was a little odd.
They were constantly being compared to each other and there was a lot of weird underlying
tensions.
And so we, having been there to hear about this, knew that we needed to avoid this at
all costs when we were running Smash Sisters.
So we're going to go through a lot of our core philosophies and formats and why we chose
what we did.
Yeah, so here are the core philosophies that we're about to go through.
We'll go through them one by one.
The first part of it is the crew battle.
This is our event format.
Now in a normal tournament, you have one versus one singles bracket.
In the Smash Sisters event, you have the crew battle series.
This allows you to create a team where you pull your stocks or your lives together.
And you work together.
You have four or five people coming together, strategizing, you know, talking about, like,
who should go in and really working together and building that camaraderie and teamwork
in order to beat your opponent.
And then our next pillar here is...
Oh, geez.
Okay.
Continue.
Sure.
Imagine there's like a really pretty picture there.
So the next piece of it is that we're also always a side event inside a main tournament.
So these aren't standalone events by any means.
You can go to your main Smash Brothers tournament and often find Smash Sisters there, which
means that the majority of our women enter the singles bracket anyway and then, you know,
have fun in the Smash Sisters side event.
And it also provides a fully integrated structure.
Meaning that you have men and women coming out and participating in so far as like cheering on people, you know
Providing commentary or helping with the stream
So it is our you know, it's one of our goals that this side event feeds back into the competitive co-ed scene
You guys can get our slides in the presenter pack, I believe.
Cool. So another core pillar that we abide by is we do not have prizes.
Because we're not interested in having a separate prize pool where people win based on rank 1, rank 2, rank 3.
Our whole point is to promote collaboration and teamwork.
So if the image were there, it would have been a social media graphic that showed you a Temple Storm Maffle that we recently did to give away to participants.
Super cute leggings.
Super cute.
It's in there.
Shadows of a Tempest Storm.
But we provided incentive that way without the pressure of ranking women arbitrarily
in these events.
And we deliberately do things in a raffle format for this very purpose.
A next pillar that we go by is participant safety first.
So...
Okay.
This is an interesting topic because you're probably wondering what is she talking about?
It's about video games.
What do you mean safety?
So an interesting point and an example to illustrate this is when Smash Sisters was
first up and running, people reached out asking, hey, do you want this to be streamed?
Let's get the word out.
And if you're a regular tournament, that would make sense.
Let's get ad revenue, let's get viewers, let's spread the word.
For us, it's about do we want to introduce the toxic online chat rooms to our participants?
It's about their comfort first.
And so we polled them and see what they thought.
Another example is that when we run these events, we actually have private Facebook
event groups where people can improve to join and then talk there so that there's no trolling
or anything whatsoever involved, which we also have seen before.
The next tenet that we want to go over is about inclusivity.
For one of the Smashers events I asked one of my friends, hey, why don't you come out
and play?
You're really good.
You'd really add to the East Coast team.
She was like, hey, I wasn't really sure about this.
I'm a trans woman.
Can I participate?
I was flabbergasted by this question.
Yes, you absolutely can participate.
Anyone who identifies as a sister can totally come out to our crew battles.
It's a very inclusive event.
And then finally, cool, hey, our focus is on gameplay.
Which means as a side event, our goal is not to solve harassment issues.
We're not a social justice group either.
And just because we talk a lot about women doesn't mean we're there to, I guess, like,
protect them in a way.
I don't know if that's a weird way to say it.
But, you know, Smash is a competitive community,
and we're always here to remember that.
You know, we're not here to baby our players.
We throw them right into a competitive environment
where they have to really work for their team,
and we're all out here to win.
It's also worth clarifying that it's not that we don't want to help harassment
or, like, help these issues.
It's just that they happen to be a byproduct of Smash Sisters as a whole,
and it's not our initial prerogative to do this.
So this brings us to our next point.
Prepare your community mentally.
So what do we mean by this?
Back then, before it started, I think I mentioned earlier that I had written a blog post about,
hey, stop asking about women's tournaments, just do it and see how it goes.
And additionally, that year itself, there had been a lot of circulation around the topic of women
within gaming, specific to Super Smash Bros. community.
Now, another girl reached out to me once asking, hey, I'm really interested in Smash Sisters,
and I want to do this for my scene. I believe she was from the Street Fighter community,
and she asked, how can I do it? And I mean, I told her right off the bat, like,
It really depends on the landscape of your community.
You can't kind of take what we found to be successful and apply it there.
Really understand your community first and understand how they'll probably react to something
like this.
And then thankfully for us, it was okay because we kind of laid down the mental groundwork,
if that makes sense.
And part of laying down the mental groundwork is understanding your community and understanding
that the event or the people that you see IRL are super different than, like, the entirety
of the Internet.
So, you know, when we host events, our participants are people around, hey, that was so great,
it's super fun, that was ultra positive.
And then we see what people write online.
And it was...
Not the same.
People hear these little tidbits or pieces or they get misinformed about what Smash Sisters
is and they might start talking a little bit critically.
So when this happens, we try to...
Kind of convey our message a little bit more positively.
So when we host a recap ‑‑ post a recap of events, which we often do on Reddit, we'll
say oh, we had this many players come out, here are a couple pictures, it was super fun.
We also include an FAQ.
In the FAQ, it will often say, well, what is Smash Sisters?
Why do we even do it?
What can you get out of it?
In this way, we can control the message a lot better.
And so we're always trying to respond constructively by saying, this is exactly what we're trying
to say.
Cool. The next aspect that we're going to jump into is branding yourself carefully.
So if you look at this photo below, this grid of women are various avatars of people who
have participated or supported the first Smash Sisters event a year ago at Genesis 3.
If you look, they all have the same color wash, they all have the same Super Smash Brothers
logo in the bottom corner.
And this was completely a deliberate decision on our end as a social media campaign.
Again, there's a lot of controversy when there's a lot of all-women's events going on, and
we knew this going into it.
So we wanted again to promote teamwork.
And this time we did it with something as simple as giving
everyone a very similar looking aesthetic in their
avatars, which kind of took over Twitter and Facebook at
the time and kind of helped us in a way generate even more
hype.
Something else that we again try to remind people and this large block of text is our
lengthy mission statement but the key point to focus on is the bolded part that says this
is a progressive organization and format that is excited to adapt.
This comes and stems from the blog post I mentioned.
We constantly remind people that, hey, while we are both the founders, we don't have our
shit completely figured out.
Like, we're not saying we're completely successful.
It's an experiment and we're working iteratively.
And this has bought us a lot of leeway to make mistakes,
try new things, so people aren't immediately like,
oh, well, that was a failure.
The next point is be careful about media outlets you work with and curate.
Recently I believe a really reputable female gamer was interviewed by a really reputable
larger platform and they effectively took her story and painted her as purely the victim
which she was extremely not happy with.
And we see this happen from time to time.
And so for Smash Sisters, we've taken the time to actually ask people who reach out,
hey, what are you trying to accomplish here?
What's your goal?
And what story are you trying to tell?
We've actually turned down people who have reached out asking if we can purely talk about
harassment and being victims because that's not something we're interested in anymore.
And then furthermore, we always ask if we can review what they've written before they
publish it online.
Cool, so that pretty much wraps up the branding and the foundation piece.
And now we're going to talk about the landscape of the female demographic.
One of our mission statements kind of talks about addressing the needs of women.
What exactly are those needs and who exactly are these women?
I mean, I think we all know this.
Not all women are the same.
Not all women are us.
Not all women want the same thing.
So it's crazy when we talk about a women's organization
where you have to deal with the preconceived notions
that come with that.
You have to deal with all the baggage that comes with
dealing with modern day feminist issues,
which there are a lot of, unfortunately.
And of course, we're not saying that feminism is bad
or anything by that means,
but there's a lot of baggage that comes with it.
We have to deal with the other groups that deal with women.
You know, there are women's leagues out there or brackets, and we have to answer to them.
We have to be, we're responsible for both the positive and negative parts of that.
When, you know, it's not necessarily fair, but it's something that we are a part of.
Sometimes people see Smash Sisters as the de facto women's organization or women's leadership
within the Smash community.
And we don't necessarily like that because we're a series of side events.
But when you talk about women, that's kind of what you automatically become.
So, here are a couple of examples of some, I think they're YouTube and Reddit comments
about a recent video that was posted by Yahoo Esports with an interview.
And at the very top it says, as long as they don't do stuff with the toxic aspects of feminism,
I'm mostly for this.
It's like, alright, thanks dude.
Or like, hey, I was somewhat skeptical
when I first heard about Smash Sisters.
With a C.
Yeah, I was somewhat skeptical about Smash Sisters,
but you know what, they're doing is great
for the community, full support.
Or I think this was my favorite,
I didn't like the idea of Smash Sisters
because I guess I got all my information
from someone who didn't like it.
I'm glad I came to read this.
A lot of these comments are like, what the heck?
Lil and I wondered at first, why are all these people so crazy about these ideas?
It's because of what it represents.
There's a larger picture here.
At the same time, we do understand this is what comes with the territory and we're fully
ready to address it.
So this brings us to the next topic. Learn to embrace true diversity as you scale.
And so usually when you hear the word diversity, especially in like context of affirmative action,
you're kind of thinking marginalized groups, helping them out, et cetera. When I say this
statement, I actually mean the next level deeper. So different types of women is what I'm referring
to when I say diversity. If you take a look at the coed Smash Brothers community at large,
oh, man, some of them hate each other.
And they like rip each other apart online and they don't agree and that's diversity in a nutshell, correct?
So an issue we face with Smash Sisters is because we were small initially and we're still pretty small
We banded together kind of as a unit and with a lot of like-minded women
And so as we started to scale up we started to see new women participate who didn't necessarily see eye-to-eye with our original
Participants and this is something we want to
Fix, we want to make room for them.
We don't want to feel like they need to align
to every single other girl who is already in Smash Sisters.
And I'm not saying we have solved the issue yet,
but it is something worth noting
because it is something we're gonna inevitably
continue to face.
And then like, one of the part of why diversity is great
is the more diverse your community is,
the more innovative you can be.
This is what allows us to continually evolve
and make things better when we get new ideas
from different people.
The next point is we promote camaraderie but we are not a cult.
So because I know it sounds funny but because of all the traction Smash Sisters has gotten
a lot of people have mistook us as the governing body for women in Smash.
We've become almost a noun or a group rather than a series of side events.
This is yet again another branding issue that needs to be addressed and needs to be fixed
and needs to be reiterated amongst everyone else.
Cool.
So our final pillar here is to listen to and filter feedback.
We are always getting feedback from, you know, our demographic.
We want to make sure that they know that they're being heard, too.
And we've changed our events based on a lot of their feedback.
And I also conduct a post-mortem after every single event to say...
Hey, what did we do right?
What did we do wrong?
What do we need to change?
And how is the next event going to be better?
One example of the feedback that we've heard is in how we determine these crew battle rosters,
these teams.
And we can have a draft pick.
So we'll figure out who exactly you want to be on your team, or you can do it by region.
And, you know, at first we did it by draft pick.
We said to ‑‑ in order to balance what the teams would be like.
We heard there's a little bit of sensitivity there.
A lot of girls felt like they didn't make the cut or something like that.
Whereas if you have a region‑based crew you have a lot of pride, you have something
that you can fight for, you know, there's a couple of pictures of people waving flags
for Arizona or the East Coast saying like, ah!
This is our region and we're super proud of it and they can really fight for their team.
At least AnyKey loaded.
So the next part is part of listening to feedback and addressing it is accepting help.
And I think this is the perfect time to shout out one of our sponsors, AnyKey, which is
an initiative that's partnered with both Intel and ESL that focuses on inclusivity within
eSports.
How perfect.
And also you'll see in the photo, no you won't, but there was a photo there.
That was a bunch of girls and us with Smash Sisters shirts on.
And it's because, like, we've learned that through running Smash Sisters,
this is an opportunity to actually empower and help others
and let others kind of get involved.
And you'll see in these photos,
we have people come and do the local recording.
We also have, we invite people to come do commentary,
and some of them have never done it before.
Also, a ton of Smash women have emailed us,
being like, hey, I'm really interested in running my own event.
And they've never even organized an event before,
and we've seen some of them now consistently doing this.
And they're better.
On the international level too.
I think there's like a Smash Sisters France group.
It's been in Sweden and Norway, even across like the US.
And it's really great too,
because when you empower and enable others,
they also feel emotionally invested in your product,
I guess you can call it.
And then they're there with you as teamwork,
working together.
Yeah, so finally in conclusion, one of the biggest parts of this is to get to know your
community.
Once you know your community, you as an individual can understand how you can impact them.
We do this through the power of events.
When you have a single event, it creates a single rallying point that people can get
excited about.
you know, we'll talk to our friends and say,
hey, are you going to the next Smash Brothers tournament?
Are you going to like CEO this year?
And people get hype when they're like,
oh, there's a Smash Sisters event there.
We're gonna be there.
And that also helps us to like send our,
have a single point where we can center
our message around too.
And again, we're not here to say, hey, we are the pinnacle of success, but more so we've
been up and running for a year, and we're still going to run into many more obstacles
and hurdles.
But what we are going to do is stick by these three pillars that we've delineated for you
guys today to make future decisions.
And thank you for coming.
Sorry for the slide issues.
Give us a follow on our Facebook, Twitter.
So it seems like we have seven minutes left.
First note to point out is please fill in your evaluations if you get a chance because
we would love to hear constructive criticism as to how we can do such a complex topic more
justice.
And then secondly, I think we have some time for Q&A.
Correct me if I'm wrong.
Yes?
Thumbs up.
Okay, cool.
Great.
And if we don't get to your question, I think there's a wrap-up room around the corner where
we will be there ready to answer questions.
Hey guys, I know you're not super focused on women's issues and all that stuff in gaming,
but I guess I'm just kind of curious as a semi-outsider how some of the previous efforts
at these types of communities, organizations, or teams you feel like has impacted you or
just other future efforts.
And for example, I saw the comment about Siren.
You want to take this one?
Like is that baggage or?
It's kind of.
Learnings and baggage.
I guess baggage is the worst way you could call it.
But it's something we knew we would have to deal with,
and that's what informed us with why we had to be
extra careful with our branding.
Because we knew if we tripped any wire,
it would just be like, and then come crashing down.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, and then part of that is like,
how do you answer certain people online too?
Like you make one wrong tweet, and you're fucked.
Like that's just gonna blow up,
and it's just like, oh wow, okay, this sucks.
So I guess it caused us to be a little bit more cautious.
All right. So Nintendo is typically hands off when it comes to events. But over the past ten
years we've seen the actual game companies kind of take a hold of events. Do you think that the
game companies should actually be supporting things like Smash Six directly or should they
just kind of leave it open and allow the community to kind of spring up with things to
support female players?
I don't think I have a strong opinion on this because grassroots seems to have been doing
pretty well.
I mean, at least the Smash community has been fine.
I think it would be great if companies did do that, if that aligned with what their interests
are.
So it's really hard to speak for a corporation and to say something like, oh, Nintendo should
do this.
I think the more important question often is, you know, what can you do to impact your
community too?
Do you think that the response would be different coming from someone who is like your peer
compared to someone who actually does work at the company is kind of what I was going
for.
Like do you think the community would reject something if they felt like it was being forced
upon them and not like an organic group?
I guess we'll have to find out.
Has it happened that you've tweeted something incendiary or put up some message that people
have blown up on and then you've had to do damage control on it?
And if so, how do you go about doing that?
Have we?
Yeah.
Ha ha ha.
I must have pushed it out of my memory because I can't remember it.
It wasn't too bad.
I was actually having a private conversation with a Smasher and she was asking me some
clarifying questions about what Smash Sisters is.
Oh, that one.
You know, it's like Facebook Messenger, so we were just talking to each other, I thought,
was pretty candidly.
I think a month or two later...
I saw screenshots of our conversation tweeted out to all of her followers and she wrote,
I think she was like...
We don't have to go into it, right?
Yeah, I mean, it was just like,
oh, the Smash Sisters girls wants this.
And it was like a very small snippet of what I had written.
And I was like, what the shit?
Like, but we were having a conversation.
But every time like this kind of stuff happens,
we'd learn something from it.
So like in our presentation,
we mentioned that our like two things we focus on
is bringing one together,
but also feeding back in the commentative community.
Like that moment definitely helped highlight that.
Yeah.
Okay, thanks.
Hi, you guys talked a lot about branding and how specifically your branding has sort of been shaped by you know the
Environment that we are in right now
How do you balance like staying true to?
Your values and integrity as like standing up for women, but also not like you know
Making sure that your branding is still on point and getting the message that you want to cross
I think what we want and then also our branding are just aligned with each other directly.
I don't think there's ever a neat point where they disconnect from one another.
I think we're just as transparent as we can be and as up front as we can be.
And I think as like the founders being like, hey, we're still making mistakes and messing
up.
I don't know how much more direct we can be.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Do you have anything to add?
No, that's good.
Cool.
Anything else?
I think that's it.
Cool.
Anything else?
One person.
Oh, one more.
Okay.
Do you have any just like numbers or maybe anecdotal, like anecdotal evidence of like
increase of participation or anything like that?
Yeah, we were asked this before.
I guess if we say a number here that's technically going on the record.
Crap.
So, off the record.
It's actually quite a low number.
I mean, in my opinion, it could be anywhere between like...
70 to 150 women.
That's a pretty big range.
A reminder that the Smash Brothers community is fairly small in the first place.
I think the largest tournament that ever happened for Smash was maybe like 1,800 people?
I think it might have been around 2,000 people, let's say.
But if you have 100 women out of, let's say, 2,000 people in a group, for us, that's amazing.
But anecdotally, we've heard a lot of feedback,
people reaching out saying like,
this is amazing, thank you so much,
I probably wouldn't be in the community anymore,
or I got involved because I saw this.
But next year we do wanna actually get more data,
so we have more stats.
And then one of my favorite stories
is about this young girl, she's...
I think she was eight.
Oh, Bowser girl.
Yeah, she mains Bowser, one of the, you know, grime-iest, like, turtle asshole guys, like,
in the Smash Brothers game.
Like, he's pretty gross, but she just, like, she just rocked him.
And, you know, she came out to play and her parents would come to tournaments and she
doesn't have a Facebook, so I was there, like, texting with her dad, like, okay, you know,
you know, let Jaiden in, you know, she can come in and stuff, and it's, like, her time
to play.
And they were really excited for her.
Yeah.
Fun story.
That's why we consider participant safety.
We didn't want her parents to have to read through the chat.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you, everyone.
I think we'll be at the wrap-up room somewhere on this floor if you guys have any more questions.
Back there.
Thanks.
Thanks, guys.