Yeah, thankfully they understand that a lot of us are game developers and we don't expect
to do anything before 10am, so a nice late morning start.
So we're going to be talking about building VR communities, asymmetry, asynchrony and
abuse.
I'm sure it was the alliteration that drew you all to this talk.
Or maybe just the confusion about what the heck are you going to be talking about.
My name is Rob.
I am currently the manager for Google Earth VR.
It's with a company called Google.
You might have heard of it.
We do some search stuff and some crazy stuff on a team called Daydream.
Previously, I worked with Daydream Labs.
So if you've seen me speak at VRDC before, or GDC, it was probably my work on Daydream
Labs that I was up here talking about.
So during my time there, I think we did about 120 different crazy little VR prototypes one
week at a time.
I think that team is now up to about 160, 170 prototypes.
And before Google, about two and a half years ago, I spent eight years running a small game
studio called Lazy 8 Studios. We did a really cool game called Cogs that you might have
heard of, a really cool game called Extrasolar that you probably haven't heard of, but you
should play anyway because it's really cool and I'm going to have to discontinue it soon
because it's way too expensive to run. We're going to be talking today about basically
design considerations for VR and AR applications. So let's dig into this. What am I talking
about when I'm talking about design considerations?
Let's take a trip into the future 10 years from now
and look back at this era in VR development
from that perspective and see what we see.
We have this huge number of dimensions
that we can develop in.
So you can think about solo versus multiplayer experiences,
entertainment experiences, educational experiences,
functional experiences like tools,
cooperative versus adversarial,
consumer versus enterprise applications.
In my mind, when I look at these categories, what I see is this huge multidimensional space
of various experiences that can exist in VR and AR, and we have explored almost none of that area.
Like, if you take the cross product of all of these different categories,
our explorations are so small right now.
So what do we do about this?
We're gonna look back in 10 years
and we're gonna be like,
oh my god, how did no one even see genre X coming?
There are entire genres of games
that we have not imagined yet.
But specifically for this talk,
I wanna talk about three of these attributes
that I think are not getting enough discussion right now.
Asymmetric experiences, asynchronous experiences,
and dealing with abuse,
and abuse especially for embodied avatars
in VR to VR experiences.
So we're going to dig into all of these in detail, but let me first of all roll back
a little bit more to the familiar experiences that we all know and love, VR to VR experiences.
You've got two players with compatible hardware, you know, six-off headsets, you've got head
and hands.
This is like, this is an amazing space in VR.
This absolutely represents the future unquestionably.
And it's just a ton of fun.
So I'm going to show just a few examples here.
This one is from a Tilt Brush prototype we put together.
Not officially launched yet, but we've shared this a little
bit, representing here the explosion, the volcanic
explosion of possibilities in virtual reality.
This is one of those little experiments that we did with
Daydream Labs.
So we've got a couple players in a space together working on a
shared interface, which was specifically what we were
looking at here, how that would work, doing some educational
stuff together.
So they're solving some physics problems together.
We've talked at Google I O about YouTube.
So we have a Co-Presence YouTube
application on the way.
It's a little bit different form of Co-Presence.
So your friends appear on kind of a doc space in front of you
and you can interact with them.
We've got Rec Room. I think everybody here has probably spent a little bit of time in Rec Room.
This is a great multiplayer experience. The other day I went into the Wave VR. This is kind of one of the newer co-presence applications.
It's like this virtual rave, really beautiful experience, different every time you go into it.
But in this particular case, when I went into the Wave VR,
I was the only person there.
And that's kind of expected.
The way that the Wave deals with
this kind of the slow emergence,
the slow growth of VR and VR communities
is that they schedule times
that people come in together and rave together,
which depending on what time zone you're on
may work well or may not work very well.
So it's a beautiful event.
This is definitely the future of VR to VR.
But at the same time,
this need to schedule events indicates a limitation.
How can we get around these limitations? So specifically let's think about like with VR to
VR experiences, what's the probability that your close friend also has a VR headset that's
compatible with yours? They've purchased the same application. They're online right now in
the same application that you're in. It's basically zero.
So when we talk about VR to VR experiences, we're going to fill out this chart over time.
When we talk about VR to VR experiences, we know that's the future. It's really cool. It's
really engaging. You feel like you're there with your friends. But the audience right now is
basically zero friends and a few strangers. How are we going to fix this?
So let me put out a kind of a bold statement out there that I want to toss around for the
duration of this talk. The most inviting VR applications are going to be the ones that
understand how to engage those who aren't in VR. So one more time, the most inviting
VR apps are going to be the ones who understand how to engage those who aren't in VR. So why
is this important? There just aren't that many people in VR. So let's get back to those
criteria that I brought up previously, asymmetry,
asynchrony, and abuse, and sort of express this
as a series of lenses.
So the first lens is, how can I engage a larger audience
by making this experience asymmetric?
And Daniel's gonna get up here later
and talk about this in a lot more detail.
The second lens is, how can I build an audience
by considering different modalities of engagement?
And this is, like, this one didn't fit into our,
This is closely coupled with that first design lens. So when we talk about asymmetry, we're
going to talk a lot about modalities of engagement. The third one is what's the benefit of allowing
my users to engage with an experience asynchronously over time. And finally, how is your application
going to handle abuse? Sai is going to get up here and talk extensively about abuse.
So let's dig into a little bit more of the definitions of these words. So when I talk about asymmetric
experiences, what I'm talking about is letting users on different devices interact with a
shared experience. And this is very tightly coupled with this idea of modalities of engagement.
So we've talked about VR to VR. But what about VR to desktop, the mirror window that we take
for granted that Daniel is going to talk about? What about VR to TV via your Chromecast? VR
to phone? VR to AR? And we're going to ‑‑
Also toss out a fun experimental piece that Daniel is going to show on AR to AR experiences.
Next we have asynchronous. In this case we're talking about allowing users to participate
in a shared experience even though they're not participating at the same time. Maybe
the classic example of this is Farmville. You can go in and see your other friend's
farms and see how they're changing. You can see they recently adopted a purple cow even
if they're not on their farm right now. And finally abuse. This is just going to be a
big one.
I think we're going to be talking about this a lot more as we go through VRDCs and GDCs
and figure out how to deal with this issue.
This fourth design lens, we just need to consider potential for abuse in the very earliest stages
of design.
Once again, Sai is going to get up and talk about that later.
So next I'm going to hand it off to Daniel and he's going to talk about asymmetry, asynchrony
and modalities of engagement.
Thanks, Rob.
Hi there.
I'm Daniel.
I'm a VR and AR designer and prototyper at Google.
Today I'm going to be talking to you about two of the lenses
Rob brought up earlier, specifically
asymmetry and asynchrony.
I'm going to be showing a bunch of different experiments
and examples that we've done in these areas
and focus on a variety of different modalities
engagements, including VR to 2D, VR to AR, and AR to AR.
First, I'd like to talk to you about a type of asymmetry that we often take for granted,
the mirror window mode.
The mirror window mode is a fantastic way of getting people who are in the room with
someone in VR, but not in VR, engaged within the experience.
Great tools like Unity and Unreal have made it super easy to implement.
It's often a no-brainer.
However, it's surprising how much you miss it when it's not implemented.
A great example of this is when we launched Google Earth initially. We didn't have a mirror
window mode in Oculus.
When Google Earth came out, I was super excited.
I invited my parents over to try it.
My dad jumped into VR, and my mom sat on the couch.
My dad loved it.
He was exploring all these different cities.
But my mom kind of sat there frustrated.
She kept asking what's going on, and I couldn't really help her out.
It was overall kind of a frustrating experience.
A couple weeks later, the team updated to have a mirror window mode, and it was a completely
different experience.
My dad again jumped into VR, but now I was offering different places he could explore.
My mom was pointing out things that he missed.
Ultimately, we were kind of like backseat driving in VR.
It was great.
It was a lot of fun.
On Daydream, we saw how valuable the second screen experience was.
So over the summer, we announced that we're going to be adding casting support to the
Daydream headset.
This means that you can share the view of any of your Daydream experiences to any cast-enabled
device in the house.
This transforms a single-person VR experience to something that's fun for anyone on the
couch or anyone in the room.
So like I said, we love the mirror window mode.
But we think we can take it a step further.
Interactive asymmetry lets the users not in VR engage in the experience in a much more
meaningful way.
A couple of examples of this could be super simple things.
Giving the user the ability to move the camera around, look at the scene from different perspectives.
Or coming up with interesting interaction models between those in VR and those not in
VR that lean on the advantages of both mediums.
An example of this could be someone's in...
A cave in VR and the other person has a map and they have to work together and talk together
so it becomes a fun experience for everyone around.
Alchemy Labs in their app Job Simulator launched a spectator cam feature.
As you can see here, it's the normal mirror window mode initially, first person, but simply
by clicking click to cycle cameras, you're able to switch views.
Now, why is this important?
Mirror window is great.
However, when it's a first person view in VR, it's often a little confusing for people
outside VR to understand what's happening.
The camera moves around a lot. You kind of just get a sense of what people are looking at in
that moment in their hands. However, once you start allowing people to move the cameras
around, get different perspectives, you get a sense of the avatars, you get a better sense of
the environment and what's happening throughout the experience. More fun for the people
outside, more able to understand.
You can also do this through a Chromecast.
So this is a custom Chromecast view.
This was an app that the Daydream Labs team put
together, where you could see a lot of what makes this app fun
is the expressions on the people's faces, the character
design, and the interactions between them.
Had this just been simply a mirror mode, then all you would see would be lots of great shots
of the environment. And while the environment is beautiful, that's not kind of what makes
this app special. So simply by writing a custom Chromecast protocol and putting in a third
camera, you're able to achieve a much more exciting experience for those outside of VR.
Now, this expands beyond just TVs and your monitors. It also expands to devices that
are in your pocket.
This was an experiment that our Daydream Labs team did where they were analyzing how to
translate the great act of reading your kid a storybook to VR.
So in this case, the child goes into VR and gets to witness all the exciting, amazing
things of immersive storytelling.
The parent using the device that's just in their pocket can not only see where that child is
looking but what they're focusing on, what they're excited about, what they're interacting
and can walk them through the story. It becomes a much more interactive experience and becomes
more of a conversation than a single person isolating experience.
Another great way of doing asymmetry is through live streaming. While the other examples were
specifically for the people who were in that room, live streaming gives you the opportunity
to share out through YouTube or Twitch to anyone who happens to be watching in real
time and then save it for later for anyone who is not.
Now, this is also another method that you can enhance by making more interactive.
You can see here that the team at Fantastic Contraption did this awesome thing where not
only are they streaming out live, but they're also bringing in the live Twitch comments.
So again, it becomes this more interactive conversation between the people in VR and
those outside of VR.
So asymmetry lets us share experiences across devices.
This is awesome.
Asymmetry lets us share experiences across time.
So why is this important? VR to VR, asymmetry, these are awesome experiences. However, the
amount of simultaneous users is inherently limited at the moment, either by the people
who are in the room or those who are there in realtime online.
By sharing out, you dramatically increase your potential audience, not only through
the amount of users through time, but also through the amount of form factors that can
access it.
A great example of this is through YouTube.
You can see here, this is a video from Tilbrush.
Someone painted this incredibly beautiful painting of Wonder Woman.
It's 3D.
It's awesome.
But not only is this just a video capture, it's actually a stereo 360 capture.
of the scene.
So that means as a viewer online, I'm able to interact with the scene, look and focus
on what I think is interesting and important, if I think the background is awesome, I can
focus on that, if I like these characters or explosions, whatever I want.
And what's great about this is not only is it available on your web, but it's also available
on a variety of different form factors.
So if I just take my phone, open this video, I can navigate the scene by just moving my
phone around, or if I pop in a cardboard or a Daydream device, I can view it in beautiful
stereo.
Another avenue for sharing out is through mixed reality captures.
This is super cool.
So what this basically is, if you haven't seen it before, is it's superimposing a real
video of the person who's using the VR experience within the VR experience itself.
So why is this important?
Well, there are a lot of people out there who have yet to try the awesomeness of VR.
And when thinking about sharing out, this is a great way that we can make VR much more
accessible for people who have an experience, who don't understand what motion controllers
are or what a headset are.
And ultimately make it a much more human experience.
Now what about asynchrony within VR and AR experiences?
How can we make more awesome asynchronous experiences?
Well, we love the idea that when you interact with the virtual world, just like in the real
world, it leaves a lasting effect. Your presence matters in this world. In this demo above,
you can see someone tending to their garden, making changes, choosing what veggies to plant.
They're making an effect on the world. The next time someone goes into the app, they
can see all the decisions the previous person made. It allows for a sense of community even
when people aren't in the app at the same time. So that's sharing apps.
Now we got another one in here, VR to AR.
With the launch of AR-enabled smartphones,
soon to be on hundreds of millions of phones,
soon many people will have a six-off
enabled device in their pockets.
This enables new types of interactivity
that build off of some of the things
I talked about with sharing out,
but allow you to also utilize spatial information
and touch interaction.
This was an example we built. It's kind of dark. You can't see it. But it's of a social
movie making app. Basically you can grab a bunch of objects and props from the scene,
throw it onto the stage and animate them with another person simply by picking them up,
clicking record and moving them around and animating them throughout the scene.
We wanted an awesome way to share out. So we came up with this idea of putting a little
camera in the scene. You can see a view finder on that camera. And one person can shrink
down to the size of the stage and film the scene, creating an awesome video for YouTube,
viewable in many different formats. We think it's super fun. People came up with really,
really fun stories that we shared out internally.
We thought this was fun but we wanted to push ourselves to think about new ways to engage
other form factors, particularly AR. We came up with this concept. How can we use the 6-off
AR phones that we have to interact with this kind of scene? In this case, you can see that
we replaced that camera I showed in the last scene with the actual AR view. So what that
means is it's no longer just a viewing experience.
The person in AR is actually the person who creates the output, the thing that goes on
YouTube.
It engages them.
It becomes less of I get the lesser experience because I'm not in VR and more of a working
together companion experience.
There's a lot of possibilities when building AR to VR interactions.
We're really excited to see what you guys come up with.
So finally, AR to AR.
We're incredibly excited with how multiplayer can make AR experiences more awesome.
We wanted to show a fun experiment that we did in this area. We call this AR boat race. Both
people have their own boats.
in their hand from their phone. They're placed spatially within the scene and all they have
to do is blow on the phone and push the sails down the scene. You can see it's super simple,
it's really fun and people who do it get really competitive. You can see right now Kevin's
in the lead but Samantha's catching up quickly and Samantha gets across the finish line.
So like I said, it's super simple but just ‑‑
The easy way of making this multiplayer using the space and using novel input methods makes
it a really, really fun interactive experience.
So there's a lot of awesome right now in VR and AR.
Incredible platforms, new tech, and new experiences.
More and more every day.
We think it's super important to be creative
in thinking about how you can combine
all these awesome emerging technologies
to better create, interact, and make the content
more consumable for those in VR and non-VR.
We've talked a lot about creating awesome social experiences
but creating these experiences
also comes with a large responsibility,
thinking about and mitigating abuse.
To talk more about this, sorry.
Oh, people are tall. Hi, new friends. I'm Cy Wise. I work at Alchemy Labs. I am their
studio director, owlmancer, and also science. You may have noticed that Job Simulator and
Rick and Morty Virtual Reality, neither one are multipresence VR experiences. So why the
heck am I here? So, oh, what is going on? I want that one.
Hello. So my background in academia and things, so my background is in sociology. I focus
specifically on video game communities, digital tribes, internet fandoms, in addition to that
also computer mediated communication, basically looking at
I'm also an 11-year industry vet, and the majority of that was actually massively multiplayer
online role-playing games.
I worked for NCSoft for a long time, worked on Ion, Lineage, City of Heroes, Guild Wars,
all these games.
And a lot of what I did there was I actually managed the harassment department, sort of
dealing with people who had been harassed, looking at different types of harassment and
helping people out.
I also happen to be both privately and publicly a woman on the internet.
I have occasionally engaged in business or entertainment activities on the internet,
given opinions, all of which add up to knowing about harassment.
So before I get too far along, I want to preemptively apologize.
It sucks that we have to talk about this.
VR is such a cool medium and it's so optimistic and we think about all the things like VR alone makes you think about what's
possible that was never possible before and then we have to spend time talking about abuse and people are gonna be rude.
So, I want to thank you all for being here and being willing to think about this and
talk about this.
And also, now that I've said it, now you can't leave early.
Ah, did you see what I did there?
So I want to start with some definitions, sort of a taxonomy of harassment.
So this can sort of break down into several modes that people are going to be gross to
each other.
One is auditory, saying gross things.
This is basically using voice chat or text, sending e‑mails, just being rude, saying
rude things to other people in a rude way is auditory.
Gestural is using rudimentary gestures to convey gross concepts.
In massively multiplayer games, this has been sort of like using emotes or whatever, using
rough gestures that are available and stringing them together in a sort of way that conveys
gross concepts.
In VR, especially with six-off hands, you have a whole new range of gross gestural experiences
because we are very creative as human beings.
We also have environmental. This is basically using the elements of the environment in gross ways.
In traditional games, this could be the sort of thing of dragging higher level monsters into a low level area.
In VR, especially with six to off head and hands and interactable environment, this can
be the sort of things like, you know, throwing things at people constantly, you know, putting
objects on people's heads, obscuring their ability to sort of interact with the world.
with VR, there's bodily. Bodily is using one's own body to be gross to another person's body.
And this is sort of new to VR. Basically because we have embodied avatars, you're able to sort
of interact with each other.
It's a game that's designed to touch and interact and move around other people's bodies in heck and gross ways.
And between the sense of presence and the freedom of sixth-dof movement,
even if these existed in other sorts of environments,
it becomes incredibly heightened and magnified in VR.
So what's currently being talked about?
Because I am not the first to talk about it.
VR has actually identified this as a problem and a lot of people engaging or who are creating
social VR experiences are talking about VR.
And they are trying to implement things.
So most of what's being talked about right now really revolves around tools, specifically
tools for the harassed.
The block and ignore feature is one that is in most VR games now.
This is alt space. It has the ability to basically block any character.
This is useful for VR with limited or a broad range of interaction abilities.
So alt space is you can use it in the Oculus Rift or you can use it in the Vive,
but you can also access it with a cardboard or Gear VR,
and you can even get through it with a web browser.
So having the same way to block somebody no matter what.
technology you're using is really useful for them so that people don't have to figure
out the new way to block somebody in a new situation.
Rec room is another one.
They have a gestural movement which is actually being talked about a lot.
This is basically the ability to, oh, hello.
Yeah.
So this is basically when you actually use an actual gesture.
This works incredibly well with 6DoF hand tracking.
And it's commonly agreed upon that this gesture-based or other physical resource is really instant
and gratifying.
Not only does it act sort of as like it's just constantly in your back pocket.
You don't have to go through menu systems to try and figure out where the block is.
It's just always there and available to you.
And the other thing is that in a resource and in a...
In a VR experience that is very physical, having a physical response matches that sort of
the desire to respond is to respond physically and having that physical response feels a lot more
useful. In addition to the fact that a lot of times when people are all getting up in your face
they can actually like clip through any UI that you might be using. So having a gesture that again
you have access to instantly is really useful in this situation.
I want to take a quick note here about ghosting versus invisibility.
So once you block somebody, what does it do?
So in the past, Rec Room has done a lot of experiences and a lot of experiments.
Rec Room used to use this ghosting ability, which is once you blocked, basically everyone
turned into a ghost.
I turned, if someone was harassing me,
they turned into a ghost, I turned into a ghost,
we're all ghosts to each other.
And basically what that was supposed to do
was sort of tone down the harassment.
It was supposed to put like a mute on the experience.
You couldn't hear them anymore,
you couldn't see their face, you know,
or what their face was doing, they didn't have hands.
And it worked really well in terms of like
dimming the emotional response, right?
And again, you had an effect on the world.
I blocked someone, something happened.
Unfortunately, everybody else could see both of these characters as non-ghosts.
This is really important because harassment often isn't just to harass the individual.
It isn't just to hurt the target.
It is often very performative.
Harassment is often done for the audience of everyone else to see how edgy they are
in harassing these people.
So even though they're both ghosts, the harasser could still see where the originally harassed
person was and could still act on them in a way that everybody else could see.
This is no longer what Rec Room does.
Rec Room now does the invisibility method, where both parties become invisible to each
other.
But this was a really interesting experiment and allowed us to find these things out.
Another thing that people are talking about is the personal space bubble.
High Fidelity has one of these, which I love.
It basically allows sort of a ring around people that if they try and cross that ring,
they just sort of zoop out.
They don't exist.
They're like...
are not allowed to come into your personal space.
This is really great in terms of being able to protect people
and set their own boundaries based on what sort of interaction they want.
And it goes a long way in terms of stopping the harassment before it begins,
at least in terms of bodily harassment.
They can't even get to you to hurt you.
The last thing that's being talked about a lot is surveillance and specifically audio
and video surveillance.
It's talked about a lot, but it isn't solved.
This is an incredibly hard problem to solve right now.
Everybody sort of wants the ideal world where like all audio and all video is always recorded
and there's just a buffer running at all times.
So if somebody gets harassed, they can be like, ah, I can prove it to you.
It happened and it was recorded and I have now given you the thing.
And that would be an ideal situation in order to take action on these individuals who are
harassing others.
Unfortunately, that's incredibly resource intensive.
For every single interaction of every human being in every lobby, in every private lobby,
it's a huge task and is unsolved.
So, what isn't being talked about?
Messaging and sharing isn't actually being talked about a whole lot.
This is getting the word out.
There are ways that people are talking about their harassment tools and sharing code of
conducts and expectations.
Rec Room has a video series called How to Rec Room that shows a bunch of different...
There are tools that they have available.
There are blogs that people can go and read.
These all happen outside of the VR experience.
Inside the VR experience, people are still working on ways that they can best communicate
expected behavior and tools that people have access to, whether this is tutorials or notices.
Reading in VR is kind of rough.
I don't know if I would recommend that, but this is the problem.
The reason why this is so much a problem is that there are no best practices yet.
Which there's a larger discussion of can there be best practices in VR yet when we're still
only been out for about a year and should we have stopped experimenting yet.
We do need to experiment and continue to do so.
But the problem without having best practices on this yet is that players don't know where
to look for these things.
If there are best practices and everyone sort of agrees that this is how you find and access
this information, then players know where to look for this.
Until we have that, it's going to be a little bit rough.
Persistent identity, permanence of consequences.
There's still a lot of ability for people to log out and switch avatars and switch names
and come back in and harass people again.
So even if somebody's been blocked by every single person in that game, they can just
go out and create a new identity and come back in.
It makes consequences really impermanent.
There are ideas that you can actually pull on from other online experiences, say
reputation systems, where you have the sort of persistent like
judgment from the community that basically says, I am a giant jerk.
This won't keep people from harassing people entirely, but it will help some people decide not to harass people.
If there is that consequence that they have to carry their actions with them.
It also allows the community to sort of identify somebody and be like, ah, that guy's a heckin'
troll.
I want nothing to do with that human being and sort of avoid that person to begin with.
So that's something that needs to be talked about a little bit more.
Another thing that's not being talked about much is lack of agency.
VR is a medium of agency, and when an individual is harassed, especially bodily, when someone's
all up in their face, like you want to have a physical response, right?
This is why the gesture works really well.
But again, a lot of times you get the sense that you've lost agency over your own body.
Someone has affected you bodily, and you weren't able to stop them, and you can't really affect
them in the way that you want to affect them, because they're intangible.
A lot of these tools that we're designing need to have the concept of how do we also
give agency back to these players and make them feel comfortable and safe and one with
their avatar again. The last thing I want to talk about that isn't being talked about
is tools for the not immediately harassed. This is a really nuanced sort of thing that's
come up recently. This is a quote from Cameron from Against Gravity. It's a really difficult
problem. Full disclosure, this was me.
I was harassed in VR, in rec room.
And I went through the whole gamut,
like the whole, I went through the taxonomy,
I had the whole survey.
And so as I'm sitting there trying to navigate
through my menu system,
because I didn't know about the gesture yet,
as I was trying to go through the menu system
to figure out I was having a rough time,
the guy was clipping through my arm,
so I couldn't get to my menu system.
And what I did is something that a lot of people do.
I looked up at my friends who had been spending
the past couple of hours with me.
And they're all looking at their watch.
Now, I know, because they are my friends, that they were also looking for the block
button to block somebody.
But the optics of it actually read very much like someone trying to disengage from the
experience.
This is awkward.
I don't want to be a part of this.
So I'm just going to flip through my phone.
So the idea of the optics of the people who want to help out
is really important there in terms of giving support to the people who are being harassed.
Additionally, there are some people who want to, like maybe off to the side,
watching this behavior, may find it gross and want nothing to do with it,
but they don't want to necessarily announce to the world.
that they're blocking somebody. They may be afraid of being attacked themselves if they announce that they're blocking this person.
So maybe they want to do something a little bit privately. Maybe they want to make a show of like,
yes, I support this person. And there's some nuances there that hasn't really been discussed.
So we can experiment right now. There's a lot to experiment with in terms of what we can make for VR that works in VR.
There's some, there's, you can basically break these down into preemptive and reactive sort of tool sets.
So preemptive, these are like making design decisions that encourage positive behavior or sort of stop the harassment before it begins.
This can be like allowing players to customize their own levels of interaction before they even get into the space.
Rec Room has a little private lobby where people log in and the first thing they end up is in their dorm room and they
can choose their avatar like shirts and hair and customize what they want to look like and this is fantastic.
But could you also choose perhaps the level of interaction you want to have that day?
Maybe you want to meet a whole bunch of cool new people and you want to go out and
If it's me, I'm going to talk about my cats.
But you want to go out and meet new people and have conversations about VR and you're
feeling really positive.
You could just go out and set yourself to public and meet all sorts of new people.
But if you're having a rough day and you just kind of want to hang out with your friends
and just talk about your cats or play disc golf or Cards Against Humanity or whatever
it is you want to do.
Could you actually set yourself to basically kind of being invisible,
so that you can like go out and only be visible to other people on your friends list?
Could you make it so you don't see anyone besides people on your friends list?
There are ways with VR that people can customize their own experience in VR,
which I'd really like to see us play with.
The other thing that you could do is basically remind people sort of what the expected behavior is.
And there are things like code of conduct, you could do like cool posters on the wall or whatever
to sort of remind people of expected behavior.
But there are also design considerations that you can make.
This is something that Daydream was working on.
It's the dog demo.
The dog's playing poker demo.
If I were playing poker, I'd want to be a dog.
So basically the idea is that you have a multi-present VR experience where people are playing poker
and one person loses, and it's always me that loses, and they get heckin' mad, and so they
stand up and they go over to like, I don't give peace of my mind, and the entire world
goes black and white and it dims a little bit, and the person looks around and the only
thing that's highlighted is the chair that they were previously sitting in.
Maybe they should go back and sit in that chair. That would be fun.
And that's the sort of like design sort of consideration you can do to encourage people to like
engage in good positive behaviors. Just sort of remind people what's expected.
And for this sort of situation, which is fairly limited in terms of like, you know, you're seated and you're playing, that works really well.
Reactive.
Designing tools that allow victimized players to protect each other.
This is after the harassment has occurred.
This is already sad times.
But we want the tools to report and remove the threat instantly.
We're already working on that with the block and report buttons.
We want consistent and clear punishment for offending players.
I talked about reputation systems earlier.
These sorts of aspects can sort of make...
So, I'm going to be talking about how to make sure that punishments can't be viewed as rewards,
or they can't be viewed as fun.
I've heard everything like, oh, what if we give them a dunce cap?
Like if somebody's bad, we'll put a dunce cap.
Well, apparently, if video games have taught me anything, it's that we are a hat-based
economy.
And we want...
So, that's something that somebody might actually seek to go get.
Another one that I love, I love this one, I hate it, but I love it, is the idea of like,
oh, someone's attacking you, right?
So, you just push them, and if you push them, they go flying back, and it's great because
you feel super powerful, and you feel like you have your agency back.
It has the added effect of, you know that that person's headset is going to go flying
and they might get a little sick and that could be cool.
It just feels really good.
But that's the sort of thing that harassing players would also use to harass people.
So like, these are the sorts of things you have to think about.
Even when you're thinking of tools that, you know, could be used to help people
you have to think about how they're going to be used to...
Also, humor.
Gosh, I love things that give me a chuckle, especially if it's like, oh, yeah, that's
like perfect, that feels justified.
So this is an example that also was tested, people were prototyping this, and it was the
idea that if somebody started coming at the person, their hands would just fall off.
Like if they tried to put their hands in the other person's face, their avatar's hands
would just drop.
And it was awesome and hilarious and it felt right like yeah, we took your hands away.
Unfortunately, everyone else thought it was funny too. And so people who might be harassing wanted their hands to fall off,
they thought it was hilarious. And so it inadvertently could encourage people
to harass to see this funny effect.
So we didn't go with that one.
So, a note here, this is all a ton of work.
These are really hard problems and it's a ton of work.
It's hard, it's going to take a lot of time, a lot of human power, but the industry as
a whole is harmed by putting out a half-supported social experience.
Just like all VR, a lot of people are going into their first social experiences in VR
And a lot of times their first social experience is their first VR experience.
And so there's a responsibility we have to make sure that the experiences that we're putting forth
are as responsible as we possibly can and make sure everyone's enjoying it.
Somebody can be turned off from all of VR by going into a bad social experience, a bad any experience.
So it's really important that we sort of keep these things in mind
and try and develop good practices as soon as we can.
The other thing is that tools have to be considered during development.
Build your features and support structures into your design as you're building as early
as you possibly can.
If you're starting to put in tools after launch, like, it's way too late.
Needs to be considered as part of your design.
Because if you are designing a social experience, mitigating abuse is part of your experience.
I also want to touch on the culture thing.
We have the ability to reinforce culture and also social stigma, which is kind of cool.
Culture isn't only enforced from the outside, it's encouraging the community to create and
normalize behaviors amongst themselves.
So a lot of what you can do in your game as your making social experiences isn't just,
A lot of times people think, like, oh, the devs are mean, and this is the nanny state,
and they just don't want us to, they're no fun, and they don't want us to have fun, and
they're overbanning everybody, and whatever.
You can actually encourage your community through culture, like, through the culture
of your game, the culture of your community outreach.
and sort of transpose that onto your community as well.
And your community will pick that up and run with it.
If players have a sense of ownership of their own space
and feel like they have the responsibility
of protecting their space, they will also do this work.
They are happy to sort of make the space
the safe space that they want
if you develop a community that sort of promotes that.
So what am I taking home from all of this?
One, don't let abuse considerations be an afterthought.
You want to design tools and empower your community
from the very beginning.
So the minute your game launches,
there should also be a set of tools and abilities
for players to be able to protect themselves
and sort of promote a good, healthy, happy community culture.
And second of all, you want to experiment.
We're still really in the early days of VR,
and there's so much that we can sort of play with.
VR is best done when we're making things for VR that work in VR.
So we can experiment a lot, and while...
We're still sort of in our early days.
We have this opportunity to do so and really figure out what works best.
We have some things that work, but we could find a lot...
There could be a lot of other things out there that work better or interesting
or have these additional side effects that are fantastic,
but we only find that out through experimenting.
So try various things, try unexpected things, silly things, stupid things.
And I would actually encourage you to share with the developer community as well.
We're actually constantly talking about it.
There are a ton of resources.
If you want to talk more about abuse and social VR, there's like Twitter, I highly recommend.
There's constantly game devs talking about this on Twitter.
But there are a bunch of Slack channels and groups where people are constantly sharing
ideas.
And resources and research to sort of figure out this whole wacky wild world that we're in right now.
And that's it for me.
Thanks!
Thank you, Sai.
So I'm just going to summarize really quickly.
Some of you might be thinking, like, this talk is kind of all over the place, other
than three major words that start with the letter A. Like, what ties this all together?
What ties it all together is that we really feel like we looked around the design space
that people are looking at right now.
And from the perspective of, like, once again, I'm going to bring it up, we're looking back
From 10 years in the future, what are we going to look at?
Where did we not spend enough time?
And we think that these areas that we're talking about
today are sort of these design elements where we're not
spending enough time, not leveraging it enough to build
social communities in different ways that are typical.
So just to sort of give you the take home,
I'm gonna once again list those four lenses
that we really want you to think about
and consider applying to your own projects
and thinking about how these sort of design ideas
fit into your personal space.
So once again, how can I engage a larger audience
by making my experiences asymmetric,
using different devices?
How can somebody on their smartphone
that they have in their pocket interface
with an experience that somebody else is seeing
on a high-end VR headset?
or a Daydream headset or a Gear VR.
Closely coupled to that, how can I build an audience by considering different modalities of engagement?
So again, VR to phone, VR to AR, you know, think about where that audience is and how we can pull those people in.
Which also includes...
Well, let's go to this one, asynchronous. What's the benefit of allowing my users to engage
with an experience asynchronously? If we want to build viral channels for our VR experiences,
being able to export those experiences to YouTube, a place where we have an audience of
billions, that's going to be an important channel.
And finally, how is your application going to handle abuse? We just can't let this be an
afterthought. So many people are having their first experience in VR today. And if their
experience is a negative one because of a culture of abuse or because it wasn't handled
properly, they're not going to come back for a long time. We need to think about abuse from
the very beginning and make sure that we're prototyping and thinking more broadly and
working hard to answer these questions. And with that, we have about 15 minutes left for Q&A.
Thank you.
It's early and nobody ever jumps up so I'll get this started.
So great talk, thanks everybody.
I'm Aaron from Google and my question or comment I guess is directed more toward SIA's area.
I've been fascinated and terrified by abuse, like all of us, a little bit for a long time.
I think the problem underlying all of it is the moment we take a conflict-driven approach
where we build complex systems to keep people on one side of a wall, doing things that we
approve of, not doing other things, we're actually building a very beautiful complex video game
for trolls.
So the more energy, the more lines in GDDs, and the more lines of code we write to try and block a behavior proactively, you know, beforehand, I kind of feel like that's the struggle we're in.
So it almost feels like we need a completely new way to think about it, other than...
I don't know that there's a question so much as has there
been any thinking in terms of completely new ways of thinking
about it. For example, when you're welcoming someone into
their very first VR experience, when we go out on the street we
know there are certain risks we take, we know there are police
about, we kind of know the rules of that world. I almost feel
like there's an element, like you said, of getting the message
out, hey, this might happen. I feel like we need sort of
completely new modes of thought around it. Do you have any comments or pointers or anything
we can use? Yeah, it's heck and rough. That's no joke. And it is, again, you don't want
to have to build for the harassers. You don't want to build for the lowest common denominator
of people who are going to be rude to each other.
I have seen some other experiments in things that people are doing.
I know AltSpace, I believe High Fidelity does as well, has greeters.
People who will meet you for, like, they have a great team of volunteers
and they sort of leverage the community to sort of, like,
and they give them that responsibility.
So, like, in terms of giving your community...
agency and responsibility to make that community and reinforce those norms themselves. They do
this in the form of greeters who show up and say hello, welcome, are you having problems? Let me
try to help you figure out. Here are some cool things you can do. And leveraging that has been
really useful. Again, I'm really into actually preemptive.
sort of experiments in terms of allowing players to sort of customize the social experience that they would like to have before they even
reach into it.
Yes, people are talking about it, but we're still in a super experimental phase.
And I want to remind you also of the video that we had, the video that we showed previously of the YouTube experience.
In that experience, the other people who are in that room with you are on the dock in front of you.
And it leaves very limited room for...
A lot of the categories of abuse that Cy brought up are simply impossible. Bodily and
environmental abuse, they're impossible. This was a design decision that came from
considering abuse from day one. This is exactly what we're talking about when we say you
need to consider abuse from the beginning, design it into it. No one is going to arrive at
that solution by first starting with full six off, head and hands, traditional VR to VR
experiences.
You have to, like that experience was born out of,
like, criteria one, make a,
create a situation where abuse is basically impossible.
And there needs to be a lot more creativity
around that space.
Thank you very much for your enlightening talk. I really appreciate it and I feel there's a lot to learn.
So just following up on that train of thought of having consequences or not letting abuse occur.
Doesn't that restrict freedom as well? For example, right now I could go up to anyone and do weird
gestures. Like I'm not restricted to do that. But right now in VR so far it seems like you're
trying to restrict that. So instead why not create identity like...
I don't know if you've used Steam a lot, but there's a VAC ban.
A VAC ban is usually if you've used cheats or have been hacking in games,
and everybody kind of knows, oh, this guy's a cheater.
So is there like a global identity that's being worked on for VR games,
shared across experiences, or because there's Facebook, Google, and Steam,
and it creates a weird issue of how to keep track of all of that.
Yeah, no, that does not currently exist.
It would be incredibly interesting.
So I spent a lot of time in Rec Room.
If I went to High Fidelity and I was being a big old jerk, because that's not where I
usually hang out, so there are minimal consequences, but then I went back to Rec Room and that
reputation followed me.
Maybe I wouldn't go to other social experiences and be a big old jerk.
But that hasn't been talked about right now. That's really hard.
And you're talking about a lot of teams across and various companies working together on this one project.
It'd be interesting. I would really like to see something like that experimented with.
Yeah, I mean, my experience was in the VR's alt room, I think, and it was funny but ridiculous
when a guy came up to me and just started yelling in my face, just at the top of his
mic.
It was the most jarring experience.
So it's way worse than, let's say, playing a video game online and then having people
yell and chat. 100%.
Yep.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
This is also for Sai.
Sorry, guys.
You guys have opinions about abuse, though.
Feel free to just have opinions.
So thanks for that talk. I hadn't thought about the way that I kind of synthesized it in my mind is that you mentioned you as a woman online are harassed in a variety of media.
And now the closer virtual reality gets to real reality, the more we can have this terrible perfect storm of the frequency of online harassment with the impact of in-person harassment, which is a real bad problem.
And so that got me thinking about like,
why is like, maybe I'm wrong about this,
but I would think that real world harassment
might be less frequent or like,
it's obviously they're both huge problems,
but like there might be less frequency
because of like a social contract
or the permanence of consequences of someone like knowing,
you know.
I mean, like, you can, there's cops, there's authorities, there's like, your identity is tied to your like physical presence, right?
I'm wondering if anyone's kind of broken down
sociologically like what that
physical real-world social contract is based on and whether we can have like a super version of it in VR.
Does that make any sense?
Yeah.
Yeah, I spend a lot of time late at night thinking about this stuff because, of course,
I'm going to think about stuff like that.
It is different.
It's sort of in the real world, we have the thought of actual consequences happening to
an actual person.
In any online environment, there's sort of like a divide between the actual person and
how they're represented online.
So consequences don't feel quite like they apply to people.
Yeah, ultimately the idea would be how do we sort of reinforce that and bring sort of
those structures that exist in the real world into VR.
A lot of it's actually social.
A lot of it actually is, you know, fear of getting caught, it's fear of peers not accepting
this.
Totally.
So.
One of the things that we've seen in a lot of our VR to VR experiments with Daydream Labs
is that because the avatars that we tend to use are very sparse, literally just a floating
head and hands, we have a different physical relationship with that other avatar, the other
person's avatar, and I have seen it over and over again, people completely innocuously
go into their first VR to VR experience and they'll say, oh, what does it feel like when
I stand inside your body?
And I mean, you might laugh, but this is super common for first time VR users if you don't
do something to create a negative experience around that.
And it's completely innocent.
It's just like, wow, I've never been able to have this experience before.
What does it look like?
Do you see my head clipping through?
Where does it start to disappear?
Right, it doesn't hurt.
These are just like engineers who are just like, ah, what are the physical limitations?
Is it going to push me backwards?
They're just querying the physics of that space.
But if the person on the other side isn't ready for that,
it's an incredibly invasive experience.
And so it is going to be more common
unless we do something about it.
People do have a different connection to their body
than they do to their avatar.
Cool.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Andrew from Apple, and this is kind of a question, kind of a comment.
I have children who I like to spend time with, my children obviously, who I like to spend
time with in VR, and I like to introduce them into new VR experiences.
But introducing someone into a VR experience is kind of like debugging a software problem
over the phone.
Like you really have to kind of...
There's no direct agency there to really help them through the experience.
And I would love to introduce my kids to Rec Room, but I'm too worried about just being
able to say, all right, back off.
There's someone along with me that can help me through the experience.
And what I'm getting at is...
Should there be a mechanism to be able to, both considering abuse and asynchronous experiences,
to be able to guide someone, to be able to ride along with someone in VR, and in some
ways to reach out directly and affect or improve their experiences?
Is this something that you've considered?
Yeah, I mean, 100%.
Like, this is something that I would love to see experiments with.
Especially, this kind of falls into a lot of my, and I didn't get to expand on it more,
but about the idea of, for people who aren't immediately harassed, for example, you know,
one of these might be, you know, if you're in with your kids and somebody starts harassing
your kids and you're with them, like, how do you as a parent sort of take charge of
that situation and protect your kids?
These are some of the things that we need a whole lot of experimentation with.
Asynchrony?
You have thoughts?
Yeah.
I mean, Daniel hinted at this.
When we added the mirror window to Google Earth,
everyone was sort of able to follow along.
But there has been a lot of discussion about, well,
what if I can point to a place and draw your attention there?
And for a rec room, you can imagine,
if you want to be that chaperone for your child, what
if you have the block controls available for every avatar
right from that mirror window?
And those are exactly the types of asynchronous experiences.
I'm sorry, the asymmetric experiences that we would love to see more of.
You know, what if you can, your child can be in a daydream phone,
but you can be following right alongside on your phone
and have a mirror view of what they're seeing here,
but then some controls to control their experience on the other side of your screen.
Yeah.
I think a similar example is the storybook example that we showed, where again it's directly
bringing your kid into a VR experience, which the book we chose is a slightly frightening
book for children.
And the idea being that you can see where the kid is looking, you can see what they're
focused on, so if they do get scared, it's pretty easy to talk with them, to pull them
out, to take them back, to navigate them through the space.
Cool, all right, thank you.
Thank you.
That's great ideas, and that's the sort of stuff
I'd love to see people experiment with
and try and see what works.
Reminding everyone, of course,
that VR is currently for 13 years old and up.
Yes, 13 years of age and up.
So when you're reading stories to your 13-year-old.
Right.
As one does.
Hi.
So firstly, Rob, I played X for Solo, and it's great.
In fact, I first saw it here at Casual Connect four years ago, I think it was.
There you go.
On to the questions.
So I've done a lot of thinking about the asynchronous sort of player in VR as well.
More from the side of like cooperative or competitive gaming.
So you could have a VR player and then a desktop player with a keyboard and mouse if it's a shooter.
Maybe there's people that are on the ground and then people that are flying around.
So, or maybe someone's like on a phone and they're like doing the tower defense and they're placing things.
And the guy at the end of the hour, which is more.
Agile and movement can sort of do different things.
So is there any sort of things you've thought of
at like cooperative or competitive multiplayer?
In asynchronously, that is?
What's the question?
Should you be doing more of that stuff?
Hang on, I have a slide for that.
Yes.
Yeah, experiment, awesome, thank you.
I'd love to see your work.
Have you guys done anything with that or any prototyping or looking into anything specific?
Do you have a slide for that too?
We have some pretty goofy, I mean we actually took one of the slides out with some of our really really goofy sort of asymmetric games because they were terrible.
Sometimes you have to go down a lot of dead ends to find good stuff.
The lessons that we learned in some of that process is that asymmetric experience is great,
but how do you make the players on both sides feel equally engaged in the experience?
How do you balance that? Balance becomes really hard across devices and interfaces.
I mean, already in many cases, they don't let the console players play against the desktop players
because it doesn't seem balanced.
So when you're talking about completely different interfaces and viewpoints, that gets to be an even harder
question.
Right.
Just a slightly different question as well.
So Google Earth VR seems like it would be a perfect platform for more social experiences
as well.
Is there anything you're doing taking it in that direction?
I mean, I know we have a ton of G Plus users out there, right?
So honestly, it's tough.
Figuring out who's going to win the social space, and
whether we should log into Facebook, and whether you have
persistent identities.
Honestly, Google hasn't delved a whole lot into that space
that much.
OK, one final question.
It's a little bit off topic, but have you thought about
opening up Google Earth VR as a platform for other
developers to build experiences on?
Come talk to me afterwards.
Okay, we have one more minute.
Oh my God, we're already almost out of time.
We're almost out of time.
But give me a question.
I want to hear a question.
I'll be very quick.
So I had an experience recently regarding abuse where a female co-worker and I were
in a game for a few seconds and we were...
People were grabbing at us like crazy and yeah, but just as I was about to start telling them off
They started talking about what they were doing and the short version is they didn't feel that anybody has a right to any kind
Of bodily integrity in a virtual space and that it shouldn't matter unless they're abusing people in real life after
Practicing it in VR basically. Well, that's certainly an opinion. Yeah
So I was just wondering if you had any experience encountering that particular perspective and
how best to speak to it in dissuading people from behaving that way.
Yeah, I totally absolutely have had that experience.
It is an opinion.
I think that's probably why people, I think that's the root of it, right?
I think that's why people are abusing to begin with.
The people who are engaging in those sorts of behaviors.
Generally would not do so in real life.
And again, it comes from this idea that the avatar's body is not your own body.
It's not a real body. It doesn't count.
It's not real.
If you don't like it, why not you just get out of VR?
Which I refuse to believe that VR is for the people who are harassing people.
Just as a standard baseline.
It's really hard to combat.
A lot of this has to do, honestly,
I believe a lot of it has to do with the fact that VR is still so new.
And that the experiences with VR are still so new.
And a lot of people are equating VR as more similar to video games.
And not making sort of that divide of like, no, the avatar's body is my own body.
It represents where I am.
And when you enact in that behavior, to my perspective, it is happening to me and my body.
I have a sense of proprioception of where my body is.
And it is exactly where you're grabbing.
And that's heckin' gross.
So, I'm hoping in some ways, I'm an optimist generally, so I'm hoping that as VR becomes
more prevalent and prolific that people start understanding and have more empathy in terms
of what that experience is like for others.
Does that help?
It does, thank you very much.
Last one, can we do one more?
Hello, so I'm Ken.
So speaking of having your own body in VR, what do you think of motion capturing of your
body in VR instead of just moving a controller and moving stuff around in VR?
Do you think there's a potential market in that?
Mocap.
The line between mocap, it's funny we have like working with academic systems in the
past we have these $150,000 Vicon motion capture systems and now all of a sudden you can buy
your $600 Vive and it does almost as much.
Sure all you have is head and hands but you can guess the rest of your body and do a pretty
good job.
What I'll definitely say about MoCap is that animation system that we showed in one of the videos,
the really dark video that Daniel was showing,
the life that you breathe into everything that you touch through your motion feels incredible.
It really feels like you're giving life to those spaces.
I don't know quite how to answer the question but there's definitely, I feel like we've
just made mocap really easy and it's going to be a wonderful thing and we need more people
to understand and explore the implications of where that's going to go.
As Rob touched on, I think anything you can do to make the experience feel more human,
you know, hands and head are great, but anything you can do to sort of put me in.
Yeah, it helps not only with the experience, but it helps with what the previous questioner asked about,
which is how can we make people feel more like people, not just avatars?
How can we help mitigate abuse through that?
Right. Thank you.
I want everyone to run an experiment. If you're experiencing a lot of abuse, deliberately recalibrate
your floor so you're six inches taller than everybody else and see what changes. I don't
know what it will do but I want people to do this and report back to me.
You can tweet at us. See, those are our names. Tweet at us your results. I'm really curious.
And I think that's it. Thanks, everybody, for coming.