My name is Greg Lebonov, and I'll be giving a talk today about gamifying creativity and
chicory, a colorful tale.
So just introduce myself really quickly.
My name is Greg Lebonov.
I'm a game designer, indie game designer living in Vancouver from Philadelphia.
I've done a bunch of indie games before.
The last couple I've done are like particularly relevant to the subject.
So one I did in 2018 was called Wandersong.
It was like a musical adventure game
where you play as like a bard.
It's a platformer where you can make music at any time.
You're sort of a walking musical instrument
and things interact with your music in different ways.
And there's sort of like a story
and puzzle solving element with that as well.
And then the most recent game I released was called Chicory,
a Colorful Tale, which came out in 2021.
This one is a top-down sort of Zelda-like
painting adventure game where
the player explores this world, like a kind of Zelda-like world,
and then they have this magic brush they can use to color things in.
So the world is black and white, but the player can draw anywhere, anytime,
and there's sort of like puzzle-solving and adventure aspects with that brush.
So both those games kind of mix.
creativity mechanics with like adventure game mechanics.
And after working on both of those,
I have quite a lot of experience in working with
mixing creative mechanics with adventure game stuff.
And that's why I wanted to talk about
sort of the classic problem of,
well, what's sometimes called quantified creativity,
which is known as a like curse problem.
I got really interested in the subject of curse problems
from this talk by Alex Jaffe in a previous UDC
called Curse Problems in Game Design.
It's really, really good.
I highly recommend it.
But yeah, specifically he talked about examples in this sort of like creativity thing.
I'm going to now like kind of summarize what he summarized with it.
So basically the idea is that you want to make a game that encourages people to be creative,
right?
But games also like sort of presuppose to introduce some kind of structure, right?
They promise some sort of structure to a player, like that's like what a game sort of is.
And those things come into conflict almost right away.
Because
Like things like advancing through levels or earning points or like leveling up,
progressing a character, whatever. These are all examples of extrinsic rewards,
right? Like rewards you get for doing stuff from the game. But following your heart and
expressing yourself and being creative, that is an intrinsically motivated activity,
right? Something that people do when they are intrinsically motivated, right? Something you
do to satisfy an internal need and it's supposed to be fun for its own sake.
In fact, it's been found through study that if people are doing creative tasks and they're
expecting a reward for it, they will tend to enjoy it less and they'll be less motivated to do it,
and they'll just be less creative in general. And I've found, a lot of game designers have found,
maybe you've probably found, that when players are offered both extrinsic and intrinsically
rewarding activities, they will tend to pursue the extrinsic rewards. Those will tend to subsume the
intrinsic ones.
So like one example I can think of that is common to a lot of games are like clothes that have stats on them like in RPGs.
So often players will, you know, come into conflict where they have clothes that they like the look of better
and there's clothes that give them better stats and have to pick between them.
And almost always they're going to pick the ones that give them better stats,
especially if the game is like challenging or like the stats are kind of the point of the game, right?
It's like the aesthetic ends up just totally not being important,
even though there are some players that really would enjoy wearing clothes that they like.
So yeah, so this is like the paradox that I've dealt with a lot in my games.
And the way that I've kind of learned to frame it for myself is basically that I think that
creativity can't coexist with logical problem solving, or they just can't be mixed.
So one example that showcases this specifically that I think is really interesting was in
a game called Crayon Physics.
This is not meant as a rag on that game, because this is a really, really sweet game from a few years ago.
But the idea of this game is that it's like a physics puzzle game.
The player can draw whatever they want, and the things they draw become like kind of physics shapes that they can use to solve these puzzles where they're trying to get this ball to the star.
It's really, really fun.
But the thing is that players, even though they can draw whatever they want,
what they will tend to do is draw, like find one thing that they can draw that kind of
solves the problem.
In this case, like they're just like, they'll just draw boxes at every level.
And they'll just do the same thing over and over again, because they figured out like that's,
you know, how to get to the, how to beat the game basically.
Right?
And so the game like doesn't, even though they can do whatever they want, they're not
motivated to do whatever they want.
So even though they can draw anything, they're just going to draw stuff that solves the problems
in front of them.
Whereas what I was interested in was trying to find games that like motivate players to actually be creative and come up with stuff and self-express.
So, but anyway, yeah, I mean, this is all a problem, but don't worry, because I fixed it.
And you can too. So the rest of this talk is going to be me talking about some of the ways that I found basically to work around or solve some of these conflicts that come up with this stuff.
And the first one is to just have both things there and you don't let them touch.
Or in other words, you separate all creative tasks from things that give you progress.
So using my own games as examples, in Wandersong and Chicory,
they are adventure games with stories. There's a beginning, middle, and an end.
There are places you explore and visit. There are puzzles you solve along the way.
There are characters you help. All this stuff are like, you get clear objectives step by step
that get you closer from the beginning of the story to the end of the story. And at no point
in there do you have to do anything creative at all. It's actually all really standard adventure
game structure stuff. Like if you played any Zelda game or Mario or something, you know what this is
like.
But there are tons of optional side activities.
There are characters that will ask you to make art for them.
In Chicory, there's like art classes you can go and do.
There's just like lots of other stuff that is not actually part of the critical path.
All of those are fully creative tasks.
And
Yeah, so they just don't touch.
They just don't touch.
You have stuff you do to progress the game and you've stuff you do to be creative.
And I actually think it's really good that both exist, because I found that players
generally need agency in how and when they engage with creative tasks, because doing
creative stuff is really exhausting.
And, you know, like I point out,
like when people are forced to do creative stuff,
they will not enjoy it.
Like if anyone who has played Tickery,
if you can imagine, right?
If there had been a requirement,
like, oh, to get to this next area,
you have to color in 10 screens or something, right?
I mean, people just wouldn't enjoy it.
They would hate it.
They resent it.
They wouldn't enjoy doing it.
They wouldn't enjoy creating that stuff, right?
They would just be like checking the boxes.
Whereas if you present them creative tasks
that they, that are like,
fully framed to them as being an optional thing.
They know that they are choosing to do this optional thing.
They feel their agency,
like they know they have the choice to do that or not.
They'll enjoy the task way more.
They'll be more creative and expressive too,
because they know that like their progress in the game
doesn't hinge on their ability to do this or not.
And that actually makes it way more enjoyable for them.
The option, like, so like, I mean,
so problem solving, typical game structure tasks,
basically, I think, inhabit a really different part
of the brain than creative things do.
So like in a standard game structure, right,
you're offering the player clear goals,
you're giving them progress,
and these are things that like stimulate them mentally
and then exhaust them mentally,
like solving puzzles and, or figuring out the simulation
or whatever, you know, navigating like a space.
Whereas creative tasks, they're best when they're freeform and expressive.
You give them as few guidelines as possible and let them make stuff up.
It's really fun and it's engaging emotionally, but also exhausting emotionally.
And when you give them the option to have both and switch between doing both
types of tasks, basically whenever they want, that is like ultimate power.
It actually, I think, makes players enjoy both of those individual tasks way more because
they are always engaging with problem solving when they have the energy to do it. And then
when they get tired of it, they have a different type of activity to do instead.
And so sort of the flow back and forth between both gives.
games this like really exciting energy to them. And they're like, you know, when you generalize
it this much, there are a lot of games that do stuff like this. So these are just some
examples of games that, you know, they incorporate some type of freeform creative mode where you can
sort of make stuff. And then they have sort of an adventure, progress, simulation, puzzle solving
mode or something. Both modes exist in these games and they are both part of the standard
experience. So like a player will engage with both along the way.
And I think it works really great.
Like, but so my like little like Greg's secret sauce is that for
Wandersong and Chicory, the starting point was designing the creativity
mechanic, and then the puzzle solving adventure stuff was sort of like made
using those as like the puzzle solving mechanic.
So basically you're always doing creativity stuff.
And even when you're not, so that even when you are not actually doing a creative thing,
like solving a puzzle in a dungeon, it actually still sort of feels like it is creative.
And the line between these two things gets blurred a lot because you're using the same
thing.
Um.
So yeah, I think it actually tricks players into feeling creative and it changes their impression
of the game overall, right? Because they feel more like it is a creative game.
Something that happens all the time when I have watched people play Chicory
is they'll be exploring around, they're solving a puzzle, they're on their way to something,
and then for some reason their attention gets caught. And maybe they notice that there's some
colors in an area or they just like to look at a particular scene or something, they'll
just hang out and they'll start drawing.
And they'll spend a lot of time drawing and like, you know, almost like completely by
accident, suddenly they're just doing creative stuff when they were supposed to be solving
puzzles in a dungeon.
I think the fact that like you can just, these switches can just kind of happen anytime.
It really does make the game really fun.
It works really, really well.
And I think people should steal this idea straight up.
I think if you own a AAA game studio or if you can pitch to one
and someone made like a big budget version of like this kind of game structure,
I think you would do really, really well.
But even if you don't have a big AAA game studio
and you're just like a small indie person looking for some cool ideas.
I gave you permission, you should just take this. I think there could be a whole genre of games
that just do this. But anyway, okay, moving on. So you might be wondering, if doing creative stuff
doesn't give players progress in the game, then how do you motivate them to be creative?
And my favorite answer to this question is with storytelling and role-playing. So
Basically what we do in Chickory and Wandersong is we create setups where players get to deliver
or give the punchline.
So we give them an open-ended prompt, we ask them to draw something, they draw something
or make something, make a song, whatever, and then we give them a really fun reaction
to the thing they did, or we reuse the thing they did in a different context.
We give them some kind of fun interaction between those things.
And so, yeah, basically the players feel like they're in this really fun conversation with
the game, right? And it gives them this opportunity to sort of role play, to insert themselves into
the world, right? To see themselves reflected in the game space. And that is just really fun.
All of the... Like Chikorita and Wandersong, both, they're basically built out of these
little... Tons of little opportunities where players get to express themselves, like that
example. And...
I think it's never mandatory, but when you give people the opportunity over and over
again to express themselves, even the most curmudgeonly person will end up doing it.
And I think that's great because my goal is to give people that fun satisfaction of being
creative and getting to do that in a game context.
So yeah, I just think this sort of conversational back and forth between players and the game
using their creativity is just a really fun part of it.
So in Chicory's 10 hour runtime, there are actually two places I broke my own rule where
there are there is a creative task that is part of like the mandatory goals to get to
the end of the game.
But both of them are like, like very deeply contexted with a story and roleplaying
situation. So like one of my favorite parts of the game is a bit where Pizza, the main
character on the left.
And Chicory, the mentor character on the right, they sort of have this like,
like, so your, your character asks Chicory, her mentor, to like draw a picture of her.
And so Chicory is drawing a picture of you and the two characters are having this sort of like
heartfelt conversation with one another. And then when the conversation is over,
when Chicory's finished drawing you, she doesn't show you the drawing she did of you.
Instead, she asks you to draw a picture of her first.
and then you show the pictures to each other.
And I think this is like, it's for me, one of the coolest parts of the game,
because it really puts the player in the character's shoes
where they are drawing a picture of someone else
and then having to sort of share and compare their art with someone else,
which is a really like, I don't know, like fun activity.
It makes the players feel like a lot closer to Chikorita the character
because they sort of done this like mutual study with each other.
And then, of course, the drawing that we they do of Ticker Ace,
and we get to bring back later in the story.
So we get lots of value out of doing things this way.
And, you know, like it's yeah, I only I only think it's basically only works
like as a creative mandatory task because it is something that has
all the storytelling context to it.
And of course, also, we give players total flexibility to put as much effort into it
as they want. There's no objective, like, you have to fill in this much of the picture,
whatever. Players can literally submit it on Canvas if they want, right? So there is no
actual mandatory amount of work to it. It's just about being in the moment and being in
the character's shoes.
Actually, all of the drawings that we ask players to do, or almost, yeah, most of them are,
they're basically presented as a request from a character. And this sort of format actually
works really well, I find, because when you are making a drawing for another character,
you have a comfortable amount of distance from the piece where you have this opportunity to
express yourself. But you also have sort of a goal in mind of trying to make something that
will make that character happy, which is an ambiguous sort of goal or structure, but just
players basically get to decide how much they want to insert themselves into it
versus like just follow exactly the guidelines they feel like the game wants from them.
So they get agency there.
But in doing all these tasks, they also just engage more with the story
and the characters, like they always feel more connected to a character
drawing something for them.
Like, I think that's just cool.
Another side note, so I think this is a good example of something where narrative design
works really, really well to solve a problem that occurs in game design. And I think there's
actually a lot of really cool potential things for this and lots of different genres of games where
things that are generally accepted as like really tough game design problems could actually be
solved by like a really cool storytelling idea. And there are a lot of great examples recently
of games that do this. So like I think of the way that Celeste
is a platformer that riffs on classic platformer design with its story,
or the way Inscription riffs on Slay the Spire or Rougelike Card Games with its storytelling as well.
These are both just really exciting examples that elevate a classic known game design with a storytelling context.
And yeah, I think if narrative designers are given an opportunity to direct design stuff, it would be really cool ideas.
Anyway, moving on.
So if you are making a game that requires the player to make creative stuff, like one
very obvious way to gamify that is to evaluate their art, right?
So you give them prompt X and then deliver their piece Y, and then you give them score
Z.
makes sense, right? But I think that this is actually like really not fun at all, or definitely
not as fun as people think it is. I think it's actually really degrading because it subconsciously
encourages a player to basically change, like adjust their piece to improve their score, right?
Generally by changing a superficial element. Because the way they're going to be thinking
about this is like, oh, I got this score. Could I get a better score? Right? And then they're
thinking about, okay, well, how do I adjust this to better meet whatever algorithm is deciding
how my art gets rated. And then they're not thinking about expression anymore, right?
They're thinking about logical problem solving. But actually, even more importantly than that,
yeah, I think it's just not fun. It's not interesting or challenging or subversive.
If a player makes something they care about and the game just tells them that it's bad,
it's just not enjoyable. I think it actually just makes people not want to try.
And the thing is that you never know how a player feels about something that they've made for you.
Right? You don't know whether they maybe they thought it was a total joke, but maybe they took
it really seriously. Like maybe they really put their heart into this piece. You don't know that
you have no way to evaluate that. And so there's just never a good reason to tell them they did a
bad job. I think you should just always be nice.
But there is something interesting here, right?
Because they're like the thing that I think that is appealing about this
experience that actually interests players is this idea that the game is like
seeing what they did and then making like an observation about it.
So we push into that a lot.
I think you actually can get a lot of,
like a lot of like good interaction by giving players
like kind of interesting observations about stuff they did.
So to use Chicory as an example,
like Chicory has art classes in it.
And the basic format, right?
Is that, you know, we give them a prompt,
players draw sort of whatever.
And then we give them like an evaluation,
like an art critique afterward.
And the way that it works is, right,
the players submit this drawing and the game sort of like
does this critical analysis internally of it.
Like it divides it up into sections and just looks for,
like it makes a prioritized sort of list
of just observations about it.
So it might say like,
ooh, this green color is the color you use the most.
And like, this area is darker than other areas
on this drawing.
And this area,
is lighter than other areas on the piece or whatever, right? These are all just like objective
things the game can like measure about the artwork. And then it turns those, like it adds
like a little bit of judgment or evaluation to it and then like turns it into these kind of like
statements about the piece that are like framed as an art critique. And things like this are really
like gratifying and fun to hear as a player because, right, it makes, really makes you feel
like the game is noticing what you did and is reflecting that back to you. And that is what
is really, really fun about it.
I'll also mix, so like, I'll mix comments like this
that are like algorithmically generated
with completely handcrafted comments
that are like, like based basically
on the prompt the player was given.
So a character might say like,
oh, like my joy looks different from this.
Or like, I don't understand what's going on in this piece,
but I like that, you know, whatever, right?
So you kind of mix and mix those things together.
And the illusion all together is something that,
yeah, it really feels like the game is reacting
to what the player is doing.
It's really satisfying.
So last thing that I want to talk about in this subject is about creating constraints for players.
So like it's giving a player a constraint or like a goal with their piece can be really fun,
but if you're scoring the player based on how well they meet your, the constraint you give them,
then it basically leads to all the same issues I was talking about with like evaluating their art,
where, you know, then they're thinking about how to maximize their score for this evaluation,
and they're not thinking about like how to actually express.
So just like the twist that I make this always is that rather than giving them like a constraint
with like a goal to meet, we basically change their toolkit. We change what's actually possible
for them. We make that the challenge, right? Because then it turns instead of a, like the
constraint is like part, it's baked into the prompt. There's no way for them to fail at that,
right? They're just given a box to work in. They get to creatively problem solve how to do
something creative in that space. And I am generalizing a lot, but like an example that
might be in chicory is...
you know, like, you know, you have to draw me a picture, but there's something on the
canvas already. Or, or yeah, you only have these certain colors, we're drawing on a weirdly
shaped surface that like doesn't, you know, isn't a canvas or whatever, right? Like there
are tons of these. And also what I really enjoy about this too, is that like, when you
give players really weird constraints, that's always a really fun storytelling opportunity
where like, you can be like.
okay, so there's a guy in the game. You might, as a designer, say, oh, there's a guy in the game who
wants you to draw a picture that's blue. And then you get to wonder, why does this guy want a thing
that's only blue? And then you get to tell a story about who this weird guy is that wants
things that's only blue. Maybe there's something nefarious going on. I don't know. The interaction
between just weird game prompts and the storytelling opportunities, and also just
creating lots of different constraints for different sorts of art projects, there is just
so much depth in that type of gameplay.
Whoop, I just went too far ahead. Sorry. There's so much depth in that type of gameplay.
It's a really fun way to make games and a really great way to basically give players lots of things
to do that feel more meaningful. So, I don't know. Yeah, free game design tip.
And in Chicory, so we had a really good, we had a lot of good outcomes, basically giving players
very open-ended prompts, right? There are actually no constraints. We would just give them an open
ended prompt, like express joy or draw like a cute creature or something. And this is really
fun because again, players get to decide like how much to engage with the prompt and what they think
fits that prompt. And they can't be evaluated on these. They're like not objectively evaluatable,
but that sort of makes it fun. And yet it is fun, right? Like you would think.
oh, like, there's no, like, you're just giving players space, like, why would they be motivated?
But it is motivating because it's actually just fun to make stuff and to express yourself.
So yeah, I, that's, that's, that's the gist. And then, so I'm just going to summarize.
Separate creativity from logical problem solving
and game progression.
Use story and characters and role-playing opportunities
to motivate player self-expression.
Never score or evaluate art, but do
provide specific observations of choices that players have made.
And create constraints by varying the player's toolkit.
That's the summary.
So thank you, everybody.
I was Greg.
Yeah, I'm, I'm, I mean, I, I know I finished a little bit fast, but I'm going to, I have,
yeah, so there's time now for questions and stuff if there are any.
Sweet. I don't know if I can, I don't know if I can see the room or anything,
so I'm just going to like listen for.
Um, hi, great talk.
I was wondering, uh, uh, I assume that you had some very interesting player
feedback from this game, given like the completely open-ended portions of some
of it, and I was just selfishly wondering if you had any like really favorite
quotes that you've had from playtests.
Huh, really favorite quotes? I don't know about quotes. I definitely have a lot of really fun...
I mean, people who... If I look at our Steam reviews, which is a pastime of me
murdering down about myself, I'll look at our Steam reviews. There's always tons of
really good comments. People will be like, oh, I didn't think... I'm not an artist. I thought I
would hate this game because I don't like to draw. But it turns out I have a lot of fun drawing,
and I actually got in touch with that part again. And now sometimes I'm drawing for fun,
on the side. That kind of stuff is really gratifying for me to hear.
That comes in lots of different flavors. I can't think of a really specific quote about it,
but that kind of flavor comes up a lot. And I do really appreciate hearing stuff like that because
yeah, I'm excited to get people in touch with that part of themselves
through games. I think that part is really cool.
But yeah, I mean, everyone, like, the thing with it being open-end is that everyone who
plays these games, they have like a really different experience.
Some people really just don't engage the creativity stuff, like at all, or like a very minimum
amount, a very minimum amount.
And I think that that's okay, because they still are exposed to it.
I mean, they get a game they really enjoy, right?
They play like a cool adventure game, they get to the end of.
and they just do some creativity along the way.
And for some people, that is the most they want out of it.
And I think it's great that they can get that.
Some people just forget to even finish the game,
and they just hang out drawing all day.
And that's really cool too.
So I think both are great.
And I think appealing to both is also great and helps lots of people.
And hi, I just wanted to ask, I love Wondersong and with a game like you said, like some people
don't finish the game, there's so much to do in each area and how you play around with the
main mechanic. How do you pace the content of the game? Because I remember in Wondersong there
were like worlds and how do you decide like this is enough and the player can move on?
I usually use story as kind of my grounding framework for deciding stuff like pacing,
how to move people through stuff. So we think about what's going on in the story.
How long has it been since the last major story beat? How long do you want to be until the next
one? And that's basically how we think about pacing things out.
So yeah, we want players to spend like a comfortable amount of time in each space,
or as much time as they want. But then there's always like the drive, the thing that actually
makes them move towards the ending is always like wanting to know what happens next. So you sort of
like dole out like the story information at a good pace. And that's like a whole other subject.
That's not really game design exactly. But yeah, like I think the story helps guide basically
players to this like emotional journey through the game. And that guides how we pace the
size of like different areas and stuff like that.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Hi, so if you could do away with every reason you had to keep the
story at its current length and level of detail, what do you think
you would add to it?
I just like love the story so much.
Wait, okay.
So if I could if I could do whatever I want, like if I could just
do whatever I want with story and I'm not thinking about game
design at all.
Is that what you mean?
Huh. It's actually a hard question for me because, well, so I think like, I don't know if you are
familiar, but the game I made, Wandersong, I think is like maybe one of the closest examples of this
that I can think of where I think I, that kind of was the aim where Wandersong is like not the most
fun game at every part of it. I sort of was, I allowed myself to make concessions where I really
want the story to matter.
So I'm going to use the game to sort of elevate the story.
And sometimes the game will be sort of frustrating
where I want the story to feel frustrating
or like, yeah, like whatever, right?
I let that sort of be the guiding light.
So that's kind of my closest version of it.
It's hard for me to like totally extract them
from each other because
like what I enjoy about the process of these things is how they are in conversation with
each other. So like, I, it's hard for me to just think of story in a vacuum without having
fun, like game aspects to it. And the conversation between them, I think is kind of partly what
makes the stories like really, really fun. If I wanted to do it without having game design,
I would just like try writing books, but I don't think I would be good at or enjoy writing books,
you know, it's a different sort of thing. So.
Yeah, I don't know. I guess, yeah. Sometimes making concessions for making the game less
fun or the game design less interesting to present the story in a better light, I think,
is the most concession I sometimes will make in this kind of issue. I don't know if that
answers your question. I hope it does. Yeah, that's cool. Thank you.
Yeah.
Hi, so I'm just wondering in the kind of dichotomy you set up between like
separating the problem solving from creative tasks, I'm wondering if you
have any thoughts for how do you like encourage creative problem solving where
you want people to solve problems, but like in creative ways, or if maybe that's
kind of doesn't quite fit in this framework.
It's a really interesting question. And it is like, yeah, I think it's really, really hard.
I mean, it's like, the closer you get to making these things meet, the more you just get into
so many weird... It always never quite goes the way you want. If I try to think of games that
are good examples of this... Okay, so when I think of games that have really creative problem
solving in it, usually the things that seem to be motivated the most...
are games that are extremely hard. And therefore, to solve the problems,
players will start working out of the box and doing unconventional things.
In a recent example, I'm sure we all are familiar with Elden Ring. The way that people play that
game... Everyone plays that game in a very different way because they're faced with a
very, very difficult challenge.
and that forces people to sort of like try different things, right? Or like, like act in weird ways, like, you know, try to clip through walls or go around corners or skip sections, like, they will do things more creatively when they're sort of like compressed to a closer point. A lot of roguelikes, you know, will also sort of encourage this type of thinking. But I do think like, you know,
the creative problem solving in that light, it's very different from the type of creativity that
I'm talking about. So like I'm talking about, you know, self-expression and problem solving
through self-expression is like really, really hard to force, I think, right? Because you can't,
like, if you, if the game is so hard that like players are thinking about how to solve it
logically, then that, that is a different headspace, I guess, to be in. Yeah. It's a
really, it's a hard problem. I hope that kind of answers your question. Yeah. Thanks. Thanks.
I'm kind of curious at what point in development, and this might be more development sausage-making question,
like at what point in development did you start showing Chicory to people and getting feedback
and, you know, evaluating whether your hypothesis of a game was worth pursuing further?
That's a good question. Well, so in the case of Chicory, I was showing it to like, I had close friends who are showing it to like very, very like, right, I would, okay, the very, very first big question I had was just like, can I make a satisfying like painting mechanic using a game controller? Because that already sounded like that was just wasn't going to work.
So, I made like prototypes where, you know, the player had like an MS Paint screen with
the paintbrush and I was just trying different stuff like the physics on the brush and colors
and stuff to see if I could find like kind of a fun version of that.
And I was trying that with people right away because I wanted to make sure that like the
core interaction was fun.
So, just from that, I was showing it to people.
But, you know, the thing is like that drawing is really fun.
Like everybody, every single human being at some point in their life has drawn and had
a good time doing it, you know?
Which you can't really say for a lot of activities.
So once I had a little drawing app that you could use to draw with the controller,
people did enjoy playing that. I knew that was going to be fun.
The question was how to get people...
They tricked people into doing that as often as possible.
And as long as I was succeeding at doing that, then the game was fun.
So I didn't have...
Yeah, once I had the basic format for...
The idea, the structure in mind for the game that was going to do that...
I didn't actually have a lot of questions that it was going to be fun.
I think if you can find ways to mix this stuff, it is a fun thing.
And it's not used very often.
People aren't exploring the space that much.
So I encourage it.
I had a question about sharing the creativity outside of the game, like having tools to
go on social media and how it might change the motivation or the balances of the motivation
and what your thoughts were on the right balance there.
Yeah, well, so in Chicory, we included a button that lets people save a GIF of the stuff they
do and post that to social media. That's our accent of it. We never prompt people to share
stuff in the game. It's never like, I tweet this button. I do think that that changes stuff,
because then you're creative performatively. And I actually think that one of the strengths,
at least for Chicory, is that...
for players, it can be a really private thing.
In fact, like there were some streamers who I was
really looking forward to watching play Chicory.
And then many of them were like,
actually, I don't think I'm going to play this game on stream
because I'm having a really good time.
And I just want to like do something on pace.
And the game sort of like encourages that.
And I think that's actually like good.
I mean, it's good for those people, right, individually.
I think it makes the game a better experience.
So those are two different types of motivations
basically for making things.
making stuff to share with other people is also fun.
There are lots of games that do that really well.
Like Jackbox is a game I can think of
that is all about making stuff and showing it to people,
right, or like Telephone or something.
So those are really great examples of games that do that.
I think they are motivating
in a really different way though,
because you're not really thinking about expressing yourself,
you're thinking about how do I make the people
in this room laugh or something, which is different.
but interesting as well, and a totally cool space to explore.
I haven't thought of like mixing that
with an adventure game kind of format, the way I have here,
but yeah, yeah, I think all that stuff
is really, really interesting
and different ways of expressing this.
Thanks.
Hey, Greg.
Great talk and amazing game.
Thanks.
I found when I was playing it, how much I'd
bother to color in a scene would kind of fluctuate
throughout playing, depending on my creative energy.
Sometimes I'd really intricately color something,
and sometimes I would just be like,
oh, I guess I got colors in.
I guess it kind of went in line maybe like almost like role-playing like with the game.
Yeah I was interested in what were your observations of people playing and whether
that fluctuated and also kind of how do you account for people that might be like completionists
and I definitely found a couple times I was like obsessively painting something when I was like
tired like creatively tired but because I wanted to.
to, you know, be a bit of a completionist.
Right. Well, so we don't reward players for coloring things.
And this is like really important to me.
And I mean, I was hoping that it would mitigate some of that a little bit.
Right. Because when you were testing this, there were a lot of people
that were saying, hey, it'll be really cool if like when you color in the whole
screen, something happens, you know, like there's just like the character
does a little dance or you get like a little star on the map or something.
Right. And I like made really sure not to ever do that,
because as soon as you have that, people will do all of them just like by necessity.
So I really tried to make sure that people knew that they did not have to do that.
Like there was no...
You have characters appear though, don't you?
Yeah, we reward them, but it was kind of meant to be like a surprise thing.
And they don't show up for coloring the whole screen.
They show up like you might not even color the screen like very much
and they might show up sometimes.
So it was meant to like disconnect that a little bit.
But yeah, I guess it does sort of like it does it right.
And it's tough.
But it was something I was concerned about,
like something that we did separate to that,
where we have things in the game that are sort of intended
as like, when you get to certain points in the story,
the game sort of prompts you to take a break.
And that was another way that we were trying to say,
like, hey, like if you've been playing for a while,
like you should maybe stop for a bit.
Like you're trying to find ways to insert,
like ways to encourage people to do that.
But yeah, I mean, if...
It's really tough to completely stop people from doing it. I mean, you give people the agency to
draw as much as they want. Some people will draw more than they want to because they just kind of
get into it. I have that problem playing lots of games. I would be super interested to figure out
ways to do it, but to mitigate that as much as possible. Because when people are playing past
the point of exhaustion, it's not fun for them, and they kind of lose some of the experience.
The checkpoints worked well, I found. I did stop playing at those checkpoints a lot of the time.
Awesome, I really appreciate hearing that then at least.
But yeah, it was something we were concerned about
and something we thought about.
I hope that your experience was more good than bad.
Oh no, it's like my game of the year.
Okay, sweet.
All right, great, we're out of time.
Thank you very much for joining us today.
Yeah, thank you for all the great questions, everybody.