Hi, I'm Guha Bala, president of Valance Studios.
I'm Kartek Bala, Guha's brother, CEO of Valance Studios.
You know, previously we were founders of Vicarious Visions,
which we started when we were both in high school back in 1991 in our parents' basement.
Now, Vivi became part of Activision Blizzard in 2005.
We led the studio for 25 years and worked on some good games.
And then we set out on a new adventure to become entrepreneurs again.
We founded Vellum Studios in 2016
to build a studio focused on discovery.
Our desire is to build a sustainable studio
with creative and financial independence
where industry veteran teams
could take the sort of creative risks
and create new kinds of game experiences.
We're a studio of around 90 employees right now
based in Troy, New York.
And simply put, our mission is to create breakthrough games
that are magical.
Our first couple of games, you know, first one we launched last fall, super proud of it,
Mario Kart Live Home Circuit, released October 2020 in partnership with Nintendo.
Now that's a mixed reality video game that brings the Mario Kart experience into the real world
by merging an AR camera-enabled RC kart and a video game world into one. It was a prototype
that was invented at Valon and then developed into a fully realized game in partnership with Nintendo.
and just announced recently is Knockout City,
a new kind of online multiplayer team-based action game
in partnership with EA Originals.
The core mechanic is based on the simple premise
of throwing and catching a ball
and amplified into a dodge-crawling online game.
There were so many technical and design challenges
with this title, with latency being a key issue,
that the team had to build a new game engine
from the ground up to pull it off.
Just a quick plug, we've got an upcoming cross-play beta,
April 2nd through the 4th.
We'd love for you to join and check it out.
We think you'll like it.
Now, the game will be coming out in May
and in partnership with EA Originals.
Now, the games couldn't be more different,
but their path to discovery and creation have a lot in common.
You know, when we talk about the culture of discovery at Velen,
for us, it's essential.
to think about convergent and divergent thinking.
They're starkly different approaches to creativity.
It's not that one is better than the other,
but they serve very different goals.
Now we hear everyone talking about innovation,
but what does that really mean?
Is it making something that exists better
or doing something totally new?
A lot of great developers focus on being the best
in their craft.
Now, this often overlaps with the goal of being best at what exists.
There are existing game genres. There are established game behaviors for consumers.
It's easy to understand when described, or you pitch, or you show a trailer.
And craftsmanship is key.
And these are examples of convergent thinking where you're best in class.
You know, most franchise extensions are based on this.
easier to plan for, communicate, fund, and publish.
Then there are developers who focus on something new.
At first, every pitch starts with, hey, this is really new.
But we found that really new ideas
have a few things in common.
Uniqueness is key.
You feel different when you play.
It has a unique emotional response.
The moment-to-moment interaction is different,
whether it's narrative.
or it's a new kind of Twitch-based mechanic.
It feels different at its core.
It's hard to describe it with just video and text.
Playing is believing.
You've got to get it in a player's hands.
So it's really important overall to make an explicit choice
in which way you want to go, because it
becomes the basis of your culture as a studio
and the business model.
When we decided to be game developers,
as creative people often do,
we often think about the new things
we're setting out to invent, to think differently.
But we quickly discovered
that most of the commercial opportunities
that are out there were built on convergent thinking
rather than divergent.
There's a lot of reasons why.
Convergence is iteration and craftsmanship.
It's the only way to become and stay the best in class
in a very competitive marketplace.
Companies iterate for a variety of reasons.
First, they're committed to their value chains
and their business models.
The value chain is a set of organizational choices
that they've made, people, infrastructure,
management bias, like how you think
about business in the industry.
These things are woven together in a system of activities,
how they're gonna deliver for their customers.
Their business models in particular.
are sort of areas of focus.
They really specialize and differentiate
in their business models.
Some companies are committed to free to play games.
Some are very category specific,
MMOs or MOBAs as the case may be.
And some are premium price publishers.
And no matter what they do to do things differently,
they come from that place.
Each of these companies strategies
are as much a factor of their current resources
and expertise as they are about
where they'd like to be in the future.
Second big reason that companies iterate, all companies need to focus, usually around how
they're currently delivering their cash flows from their customers to their shareholders.
And it sounds really smart to have a complex strategy. The problem is complex ones don't
usually work. Simple strategies with focused execution is what really works. And that's a
lot of the reasons why companies iterate as well.
There's also more reasons.
There's lower market acceptance risk.
When you put all the capital into building a game,
all the costs, the money, the effort, the time,
it's much easier to know, is there anyone out there
that's an audience for your title?
It's easier to focus test and research it,
however formally or informally.
Iteration is much easier to do this.
It's a lot easier to forecast financials.
You can look at similar titles out there.
and say, hey, I can make this a little bit better, a little bit plus 10%.
So the bottom line is, is that it's a lot easier to invest in a bigger bet.
That's even better for customers by giving them more of what they already love.
You know, finally, and this is one thing that's always been a little uncomfortable
for people to admit, it's something that we've gone through as well.
There's a lower chance of failure.
At least until the idea gets old.
There's a lower chance of failure in iterative ideas
because when was the last time someone got promoted
at a company for failing in the marketplace?
Well, typically if you fail in the marketplace,
you blow up and it's a sort of a career limiting move.
So you tend to iterate rather
than do something completely different.
Everyone seems to have the story of the brand
that they helped create as executives in a company.
I was part of X team or Y team.
Usually people don't talk about,
I was part of a team that took a risk and it didn't work out.
And then finally, and this is a big one,
it's a lot easier if you're in a $100 million business
to get the extra 10%, the over $10 million of revenue,
or in a billion dollar business
and get an extra 100 million.
Wow, that sounds really like a big number, right?
Then it is to get to the first 10 million of revenue
on a new idea,
or the first $100 million of a new idea.
And so for someone looking to build a career,
jumping off the deep end with a brand new idea,
it's the reason why creative people sometimes
get in the business.
But it's not the best path for the most predictable career.
Frankly, if all creative companies was divergent
thinking, and so everybody in the world
was doing things differently, then eventually, luck
might run out.
Even the most divergent of innovators
need some convergence and iteration.
But of course, the same old, same old, as we say, gets old.
There's always room for something new, especially now.
Now, that's a lot of the reasons why we got into balance studios
and started our studio in the first place.
But especially now, it's a good time to recognize
that the industry is very cyclical.
It's always in a process of consolidation and fragmentation.
And they're always breakthrough new products coming supposedly out of nowhere.
Usually it's a team that worked for ten years to get the right idea going,
been incubating forever.
And supposedly all the new ideas come out of nowhere.
Established game categories are getting bigger, that's a truism.
That's where the consolidation is happening.
Only the top few MOBAs are getting the consumers today,
the top few Battle Royales, the top few match three games.
And they have staying power because they can invest at scale.
And before that, before today, or now,
big publishers controlled access to capital, distribution, marketing, and PR.
But at the same time,
we've never experienced a time where each of these areas are more disaggregated.
When it comes to new types of experiences, there's always new capital or
always capital chasing new creatives.
The different distribution options,
virtually for any business model.
And there's world-class marketing PR
that's looking to support the best new creative.
So we frankly don't see many advantages
of being within a single large organization,
especially if you wanna get something done that's new.
There are multiple routes for unique experiences
if you're deliberate in your choices.
It's not.
It's not actually the field of dreams where build it and they will come.
It does take a few very deliberate steps.
We'll talk about our perspective on doing divergence.
The key is for us to build ideas that are simple.
By simple, we mean sort of really easy to get, easy to understand, accessible.
It's easy to get into and start playing.
It's something that is emotional or captivating.
within the first few minutes of play.
It doesn't take a long exposition,
a long sort of experience to really understand what it is
and say, ah, this feels different.
But simple doesn't mean it's complex under,
it's not complex under the hood.
A lot of times simple ideas haven't been done before
because they're super hard to do.
Second principle, defensible.
Is there a secret sauce that makes this hard to copy?
You know, I remember when the first couple
Battle Royals came out and we went to that.
E3 with our working prototype for Knockout City.
This was 18 months in incubation, we got it to feel really good and
we want to show it to others.
And so many people thanked us for not showing them another Battle Royale.
It was about 50 to 100 other Battle Royales in development.
Because the ones that had been established had quickly gotten to scale.
And the new ones that were coming out were just competing for
diminishing audiences.
Not great barriers to entry once competitors were already at scale.
So think about secret sauce, why is it hard to copy?
But also what the set of capabilities on your team
that makes your team unique
and probably the best to do it as well.
Third principle, is it scalable?
Scalable in a sense of player engagement,
can it engage a player for hours, days, weeks, and months?
And second, can you engage numbers of players?
Can you do hundreds of thousands of users?
Can it go to millions of players?
These tend to be very important
because when you're taking very risky bets.
Hopefully, there are many, many people willing to enjoy it
over long periods of time.
Sometimes takes a while to figure those things out.
So, when we started Valorant Studios,
our initial focus was not about any specific game idea.
It was all about defining what kind of culture
we wanted to cultivate,
the type of team we wanted to assemble.
We really wanted to bring together veteran talent,
as well as new talent,
who are all about going after bold new ideas.
And so that kind of divergent thinking, it starts with the team.
So it's really around building a core team and giving them the room to explore.
Now, it's amazing how we hear all the time that a lot of brilliant, creative,
and technical folks, they weren't given the room to explore.
And these are folks who are deeply curious, deeply curious about new play patterns.
They're not just dreamers, but they're makers.
And at Vellum, there's no separation between inventors and developers.
It's not like we hand it off to some other team to go build.
You know, we build it.
You know, come up with the ideas and start building and prototyping and
proving or disproving the fun.
And it's all about trying to have the smallest possible team
to find that atomic core unit of fun, you know, that makes the game work.
above all, the team needs to have permission to fail. Failing needs to be seen as equally
as good outcome as success. It's when you don't know which one it is that makes it really difficult.
But the team needs to have that permission to fail so they can actually take some bold steps.
So, the core limits to this test is, can the team build it? And then hand the controller over to
someone else to feel that magic.
people just stop playing and they walk away or they can't let go. That's a really important metric.
The second thing is once you've kind of defined that culture and you've kind of assembled a team,
then it's really about a sort of structured R&D process that comes second. And I'm not
talking about pre-production. Pre-production comes after this sort of period of R&D.
You know, quite frankly, we place sort of minimal value on pitch decks or, you know,
videos and all that kind of stuff.
You know, it's really about let's go prototype something and build something and prove whether
something is fun or not.
And it's really sort of investing against the magic that the team finds.
You know, it's the team being really passionate about going after.
you know, specific problems that they're trying to solve. It's finding the magic in these core
interactions that are really novel and unique and different. And you got to build it and iterate on
it until we can put it in the outsider's hands, you know, and subject to a peer review and see
what other people think. And this is, you try and be as rapid as you can. You try and not put a lot
of frills around it. This isn't about.
And unless the game is about an aesthetic
that you're trying to define,
and that's what's unique about it.
You know, if it's about moment to moment mechanics
as an example, you don't need a lot of art.
You kind of focus down on what is really necessary
to prove or disprove a concept.
And you iterate as rapidly as you can.
Now the trick is, and this is challenging,
is that it requires independent funding
from the actual project fund.
you need to have a lot of patience because the prototype might not work out. You may just have
to throw it away and do something else completely different. If you're prescriptive about the
project from the get-go, when you haven't proven like the core magic in something,
that becomes really hard and you kind of box yourself in. So really, if you can decouple
a different funding source in that R&D period when you're looking for that magic, then
you can, you have something that you can then take into pre-production with more of a project
financing approach. So I mean just a couple of quick examples like with Mario Kart Live,
for example, when the prototyping began, it was not about making a Mario Kart game.
You know, it was actually inspired from drone racing and it was about bringing this visceral
feel of driving an RC car in the real world, but making it drive as easily as a video game car.
Then it was bringing video game rules around it.
to make it a fun game experiment. And this was a self-funded prototype, which was risky,
especially since we didn't know if there was a dare there with this sort of experience.
And we were lucky. We actually found that magic kind of early. It was about in that
seven to nine month type of window that we were able to unlock what was special about it.
With Knockout City, we had this core idea of throwing and catching a ball.
And every three months or so, we thought we had this core figured out. We put it in the hands
of trusted peers and it failed. It wasn't fun. There were problems with it. But the team kept
at it. And it actually took 18 months to really nail that core experience that felt great in
people's hands. Sometimes it's really hard to know when you should cut bait on an idea and move on
or keep going. And at the end of the day, you got to trust the team.
and decide as a team whether you want to keep going or do something else.
At the end of the day, when you're green lighting a project and you're going into full
pre-production and production with the intention of building it, we believe that the creative
should drive the go-to-market strategy.
This is often like the opposite of what actually happens in companies and large scale companies.
It's usually identifying a market opportunity and saying, hey, we need to go after these kinds of consumers or Battle Royales are awesome.
They're really hot. Let's go make a Battle Royale. By the way, we play Battle Royales.
Nothing wrong with Battle Royales, but like it's more of a methodology, you know, where.
companies often focus on the market and then say,
hmm, what products should we build?
As opposed to you figure out something special and new.
And again, this is the path of divergent new ideas
that creative drives the go-to-market strategy.
And so when you do have that magic,
when you do have that prototype
that's really special and unique,
you then figure out what the right go-to-market strategy is.
Sometimes you can go at it on your own.
Other times you need the right kind of partner
to be able to.
take it out to market. And if you've, again, proven the fun and you can put in their hands,
it's a lot easier to go find the right partner where it really just kind of clicks, the vision
clicks, they really understand the game experience and the audience. But you can do it independently.
And if you do it that way, you can start small, but you want to get it really community-focused
and into players' hands as quickly as possible.
Now, like Mario Kart Live, it was a very different set of go-to-market challenges than Knockout City.
With Mario Kart Live, we had a hardware and software experience that we needed to build at scale,
and Nintendo was a great partner for us for that project.
And with Knockout City, it's a digital-only, live-service game with a lot of infrastructure requirements to pull that off.
And we talked to a number of different potential partners when we had our prototype.
And EA, and particularly with the EA Originals label,
became the right partner for us.
Ultimate goal is getting it into gamers' hands.
That's what we're really trying to do.
Now, we've talked a lot about divergent thinking.
There's a point at which you've got to make the sucker.
So this is where the dreamer has to become the horse.
transition from divergent to convergent in order to build it and ship it and evolve it.
So sustainability is all about saying, hey, look, we found the magic.
We know what really is something special and new.
We figured out here's a risky but viable pathway to market.
Here are the partners that we need to do it.
You got to put it on a timeline.
You have to make it.
Building and shipping it and then evolving it.
is really how we think about this as a complete package. Building is iterative.
It extends beyond launch. And part of that is because player feedback is key. This is something
totally new. So you think you know how players will respond to it. You can even focus test it
along the way and that kind of thing. But you don't really know until your experience is out in a while.
You know, we didn't really, we put track creation into Mario Kart Live,
but there isn't a native sharing feature in Mario Kart Live.
We were astounded that there's so many makers out there
that are building amazing courses and posting them
and making the experience really their own.
Gives us a real insight into UGC in the real world.
Something that we found out,
we knew that building was a fun part of what we're doing.
We didn't think that the community would embrace it
quite the way that they.
wind up doing it. So shipping it is just a step along the way of delivering an amazing experience.
But, and then budgeting and planning is harder in this context, because when you're looking at,
okay, well, how much do I have to build into this before it needs to get out?
What kind of break-even do I need to have? They don't have easy comparables.
So keeping it as tight as possible in that initial feature spec is super important.
because you are taking a risk, because eventually the market
needs to accept it.
And then you need to go from there.
Now, the fundamental truth, and I
think every developer has encountered this, especially
on new stuff, everything takes a lot longer and costs
more than you think.
To build some safety margin in there in your system
as well as you're doing this.
Importantly, though, and we've heard a lot
of talk about this in software and startup culture.
Minimal viable product is a really hard concept for us to get our heads around.
Minimal viable product often means, hey, look, you just have this little bit
and people are going to pay you for it.
And then you can take it to whatever future it needs to have.
What we think we need to do is determine the scope of the experience
that feels complete at launch, but has the potential to grow.
It represents a value for your pricing model,
but then you can evolve it from there.
Fundamentally, it's about finding your audience,
listening, and evolving it with the player community.
And all of this is a combination of iteration,
about being as rigorous as you can be, patient as you can be,
and getting the thing out.
So all of these are sort of a four-part concept.
We summarize it in our business plan
that we've actually posted here.
This is a bit complicated, as you can see.
Now, just a little bit of background, you know, Carthick and I both have MBAs.
There's a proverb in Silicon Valley, you take the number of engineers, multiply it by 10,
divided by the number of MBAs that you have, and that's your IQ as a company.
So fortunately, there's just the two of us, and there's lots of great people here at Valiant.
We've experienced being indie before it was cool, when we first started.
We've been in large studio environments as well.
and with mega franchises.
Now being back at NDA, it's fine for a different,
it was important for a different kind of plan.
You know, beyond the 50 to 100 page decks,
beyond all the market studies and things like that,
we really laid it out to the simplest possible method
that we can have.
So build an awesome team.
Find the magic in something new
that the team is truly passionate about
because passion drives the patience.
and the insight for innovation.
Figure out how to get the market,
because if it's really great,
there's probably a way to do that.
Probably partners that can help you do it as well.
And then build and ship it, evolve it with a community.
So that's what we set out in October, 2016.
And look, some of this is a work in progress.
We've had some success with Mario Kart Live.
We have great expectations for Knockout City.
We think you're gonna love that too.
But what we found overall is that simple is hard.
So it's always easier said than done.
So every bit of the plan, you know,
simple plans have a shot at working
because there's a million details to execution
and execution has to be great,
both for consumers as well as the competing marketplace.
Complex strategies tend to fail
because you're stacking complex strategies
on top of complex execution.
So the most important thing for you to do in all of this
is to be able to say,
how simple can I make my effort and my proposition?
Well, we're on a journey.
Good luck on your journey.
You know, when we look for ideas,
we look for the best ideas that are simple and powerful
with hidden depth and nuance.
We try to find them in creative people everywhere
and bring them together in an awesome team.
Our effort at Balanced Studios
is to build a sustainable model to do this.
We just wish that as many people that can do this are doing this, because I think that'd be great for the industry, great for consumers, great for players everywhere. Thank you.
Thanks for spending 30 minutes with us and listening to this talk. Appreciate it. Take care.