I've got a couple of announcements before I go.
You've heard these all week.
Please silence your cell phones.
Also, I'm going to throw one in there.
If you've got an iPad, don't just hold it up taking
pictures of the slides.
Really distracting.
For evaluations, you guys will receive an email
after the session.
Please fill those out.
I'll read them, GDC will read them.
They really help us out.
On top of that, after this, and I'll say this at the end,
I'll be in the wrap-up room to answer any questions.
I'm probably gonna be really tight on time,
so I won't be up here answering questions.
Other than that, I hope you guys enjoy.
Thanks for showing out on a Friday morning.
I'm Richard Carillo, I'm a game director at Ubisoft Toronto, and welcome to Interviewing
for Game Design.
My goal in doing this talk wasn't to stand here and say, hey, I'm an amazing interviewer,
you guys should do what I do, although if you feel that way at the end, that's totally
fine.
My goal was to solve a problem that I noticed at my studio and I expect may exist at many
others.
So I've been at Ubisoft Toronto for over five years interviewing candidates as we grew from 150 to over 500 people.
And in that time I've interviewed candidates that are in no way game designers, all the way to people who are industry experts.
And five years later I still go into interviews and end up talking to candidates that are not game designers.
But the problem was that other interviewers in our studio, other game directors, other senior designers, had given them a thumbs up.
And instantly I thought, okay, how do we solve this?
What questions are you asking that lead you
to such a positive assessment?
What questions am I asking that lead me
to such a negative assessment, and how can we resolve that?
So this is more of an interview post-mortem
as I deep dive into the processes we've gone through
at our studio, and I hope that other studios can use this
to better their own hiring practices,
and even candidates can use this to understand
what's gonna happen in the interview process,
and also what to expect from the job.
So when I noticed this problem, my first instinct, of course,
was to talk to the other interviewers,
figure out what questions they're asking,
figure out what answers they're expecting,
and then also to kind of watch them interview
and see what's going on.
And I noticed a lot of the standard go-tos
that you'd expect.
First off, deep dive into experience.
So obviously the interviewer pulls out the resume,
asks them to do a quick rundown,
and then starts probing at interesting points along the way.
And this can lead to what I call the resume trap.
That candidate has put everything they can talk about
on that resume.
And you're probably gonna spend a majority of your time
trying to see if they actually did what they said they did.
But even after that,
if you determine that they have experience,
it still doesn't say whether or not
they're a good game designer,
just that they have experience.
Also, I noticed a lot of questions about process and documentation.
I never really understood process questions.
The answers generally are these, in a perfect world, this is what I believe my process is,
and most answers to process questions start to sound the same from candidate to candidate,
so it doesn't really do a good job at separating candidates.
game ideas. A lot of interviewers will ask questions about, hey, can you pitch an idea
for a game you really like? Can you pitch an idea for our game that you're interviewing
for? And everyone has ideas. And I'll say this throughout the presentation. Game designers
do not come up with game ideas. That's not our job. Our job is to pick all the different
ideas we reference from other games, we reference from the team, put those ideas in the systems,
and make sure we're building something that actually works.
uh... so when you ask about game ideas and ask them to pitch him as an
interview
uh... you know really determine if they're games under a game enthusiast
of course again everyone has ideas
And finally, this is a major one.
You end up spending a lot of time testing interviewing skills
instead of testing job skills.
A lot of interview questions are those open, broad questions
where even if you ask, as the candidate,
what are you looking for?
They'll respond with,
oh no, I just wanna see where you're gonna take it.
These are horrible questions
that end up really just testing
if the candidate understands what you're looking for
and can control the conversation.
But there's a lot of great game designers
that aren't good at interviewing.
There's a lot of bad game designers
that are great at interviewing
and can BS their way through that process.
So I noticed a lot of these things going on in the interview, and the majority of the interview were these questions.
And they all dance around one main question, but they never really ask it.
And that main question is, are you a game designer?
This is probably the most important question, and this is what you want to get out of that interview.
Because again, they can have experience, they can have a process, and they can have ideas.
None of that makes them a good game designer.
So how do you ask this question?
And this became kind of the main thing I started focusing on in trying to resolve this problem.
First, you have to understand what game design is
and define it for your studio.
And this is my definition.
It may be different from studio to studio,
as some studios may be more technical
with their game designers.
Some studios may actually have level design
with their game design.
But this is for our studio.
So game designers design systems.
We are not idea generators,
and I kind of said this already.
A system is a series of mechanics,
and mechanics are a series of ideas.
So that's why when you go to your game designer
and you say, hey, I got a cool idea,
wouldn't it be cool if,
and the game designer looks at you like you're crazy,
it's not because it's not a cool idea,
it's because they're stepping through it and going,
okay, how does that idea change the mechanic?
How does that alter the system?
How does that affect the game?
And that's the mental process for game design.
That's what they own.
And that's not something everyone can do.
But again, everyone has game ideas.
There's nothing special about that.
We're also problem solvers.
We aren't design critiquers.
To solve a problem, you have to understand the system,
you have to identify the problem,
and then, of course, you have to propose solutions.
To critique design, you just have to not like something.
I don't like chairs with poor lumbar support.
That doesn't make me good at designing chairs.
And finally, we're big on owning the player experience,
but we're not level designers.
And the difference there is level design
focuses on player experience,
but they focus on building engaging spaces
and good flow through those spaces,
while game designers will focus on
building engaging gameplay loops
that keep the player hooked
and keep the player invested in the experience overall.
So this is my definition of game design.
Again, it may be different from studio to studio,
but the first step for me was to define it,
and then on top of that, now as an interviewer,
I want to ask questions that lead me to answers
that are on the green side,
and then I wanna stay away from questions
that generally turn toward answers on the red side.
Because again, I don't want idea generation,
I don't want people design critiquing.
So let's step through each of these sections, starting out with basic systems.
And I want to give you guys a bad question and a good question that I've seen in this process,
so you can get a better understanding of the issues we had at our studio.
So first bad question, and you may hate me because you may ask these questions.
What's your favorite game and what would you change in that game?
There's a lot of variance to this question, but my main issue with it is
it really is just saying, I want you to talk until I hear something interesting.
And then if you say something interesting, maybe I'll join the conversation and
maybe we'll go deeper into systems.
But what you really want from this answer is for
them to deep dive into a system in a game they like, pick it apart,
figure out some problems that were with it, and
then bring up some solutions that might fix those problems.
but this isn't what this question's asking.
What you're actually gonna get from this question
a lot of the time is, oh, I like this game,
but I wish it had more characters.
That has nothing to do with game design,
but it's a valid answer because you asked
some sort of an opinionated open question.
So breaking this question down a little further,
again, it's not about systems or game loops.
For the candidate to be able to answer that way,
that's just them understanding that that's what you want
and then controlling that conversation,
which is good for them, but you may be missing out
on great game designers that aren't good at that.
And again, it's all about idea generation and design critiquing.
It's just too open.
And the easy way to figure out if your questions are too open is take 10
minutes, sit down, write down all the good and bad answers to that question.
And if you can't do it because there's infinite answers,
it's way too open of a question.
and generally if you can't figure out all the good and bad answers, how can you quantify
their answer?
And at the end, that's what a lot of game designers kind of, it goes off of feelings.
I really felt like that was a good answer.
And this guy, I didn't really feel like his answers were good.
And that's why you get certain designers that like candidates while at the same time other
designers really don't like those candidates because it's all completely subjective.
and what they talk about again you know no i actually had this happen me i've
asked all these questions and for five minutes this person went on about in the
game i've never heard of but they really enjoyed and i just had a thinking ok i
can't fall is at all
this is a horrible never asking this question again
Now I tried to figure out some solutions to this and try to change this question a little
bit to still get the hint of the question that leaves it more open for them, but also
really making it more about them tearing apart systems so I can understand they understand
what game systems are.
But really the only way I found to successfully figure out if the candidate understands systems
is to ask about a specific system and then add or remove a mechanic from that system
and see if they understand the implications of that.
And that leads us to our good question about systems.
You're working on a game of rock, paper, scissors.
Your creative director wants you to remove
one of the three options,
giving the player only two options to choose from.
What goes through your mind?
Now, stepping through this,
I started easily with rock, paper, scissors.
This is something no one's gonna be confused by.
If you don't understand rock, paper, scissors
and never played it and you wanna go into game design,
just you're failing already.
And again, your creative director wants you to remove one option.
That's me removing one mechanic from that system.
I want to see if you understand what that does to it.
And then what goes through your mind?
Generally, I don't care about the answer.
I don't care about them jumping straight to something.
I don't want to say, OK, solve this problem.
I want to hear about their mental process.
That's the main key for game design, is understanding, OK, maybe if I do this.
No, wait, that didn't work out.
I want to hear when they fail.
I want to hear when they succeed.
I want to hear the steps they take.
And generally this is what goes through a game designer's mind when they hear this question.
I sort of just peed on rock, paper, scissors, the holy grail of game design, and they're
just completely in mass hysteria usually and completely confused.
Why would you want to do this?
You're a horrible creative director.
But let's talk about a bad answer.
I actually came up with this question
out of frustration midway through an interview
because the candidate just seemed like someone
who wasn't a game designer.
It seemed like someone that was more of a project manager.
They didn't really design systems.
They brought people together to design systems.
So they couldn't really solve problems themselves
in that way.
And then I really, when I came up with that,
I was like, okay, this is gonna be simple.
There's no way this person's not gonna be able to answer this.
Everyone in the world knows what happens
when you remove an option from rock, paper, scissors.
And this was his answer.
I would ask why he wants to change it.
This is valid to a degree.
This isn't a horrible response,
wanting to understand the goals of the creative director.
Now I have to play the role of the creative director
and say, okay, he wants it to change
because he feels three options is too complex of a system
and it would be easier for the user
if there was only two options.
It's a horrible answer, I know, but whatever.
I don't like removing options.
Okay, so I'm getting a little frustrated here.
I don't really care what you like.
But is that because, you know, it's just based off your feelings and you're just a game player
and you like more options?
Or is that because you understand that removing an option builds a less engaging system?
I'm not sure what you're getting at.
I would try to convince him not to do that.
Again, play the role of the creative director and I just said, okay, he's not convinced.
I'd get the team together and we'd figure it out.
And this was the key point in the interview where I was just like,
alright, this is over.
You didn't understand at all what that would do to the system,
you didn't think about systems at all,
you're just thinking about how to manage that creative director,
how to manage change in the game space,
and then how to manage other people
to bring them together to solve this problem for you.
And this is another answer I haven't gotten before.
But I'd kind of be excited to get it.
I would remove paper, the confidence in that.
Just like paper's stupid, no one likes it.
But so far up to this point,
even though I thought this sort of was a silly question
that most people would be able to talk about,
it's done a great job at separating candidates
into people that understand systems and people that don't.
So let's talk about some good answers.
Impossible! This actually was a game designer at our studio, because I felt so bad and awkward
after coming up with that question, thinking, okay, maybe it's such a crazy, ridiculous
question. Like, it's so simple that it confused him. So I brought it to other game designers
in our studio, which is, I just want to make that point, test out your interview questions
with other game designers. It's the easiest way to playtest them and see if they actually
work.
That would destroy the balance of the game, of course.
This is kind of the basic process that you would think of
when you remove an option from rock, paper, scissors.
If you remove paper, the rock would always win.
I added this in here because I wanted to talk a little bit
about the different perspectives of these answers.
That would destroy the balance of the game
as someone thinking about it
from a systems perspective.
If you remove paper, the rock would always win.
As someone stepping through it as if they were the player,
noticing that, okay, if I do that, then I do this.
So it's just an interesting opportunity
to look at different perspectives and answers.
You can't do rock, paper, scissors with two options.
One always wins or it's always a stalemate.
Of course, that encapsulating answer.
But again, I ask them to kind of walk
through their mental process.
So at this point, usually I say, okay,
now what's your response to the creative director?
Because that gives them a chance to take a step back.
They're not just rambling their mental thoughts.
They're thinking, okay, I have to compile this now
into something for a superior.
And this can actually lead to great answers, which it has.
And that great answer being brought to you by Seinfeld.
uh... so george and jerry were having an argument and they played with a call
missio the choose game
uh... what i call on the needs and this is a two option system so this is a
candidate that not only recognize that okay that destroys rock-paper-scissors
but the creditors to want to option system i can give it to option system
uh... so in this game uh... you have to pick teams one players on one players
evens
you're going to be able to throw either a one or two out at the same time
you add up the fingers, and in this case it's three,
so odds wins.
There's two opportunities for odds to win,
two for evens to win,
but there's actually an extra step,
which is a little bit more complexity.
Now you have to select teams in this game,
whereas Rock, Paper, Scissors, you don't have to select teams
but there's three options,
which the creative director thought was complex.
So at least this is a proposal for the creative director
who wants a two option system.
So again, a great answer for someone
that recognizes the issues, Rock, Paper, Scissors,
and then still tries to give the creative director
what they're asking for.
So when asking questions to try and see if the candidate understands systems or game
loops, some takeaways, don't ask open questions.
Open questions generally lead to opinions, they lead to really weird answers, and I don't
think you can really determine whether or not they're good for the job based on those
type of questions because they may go really off into weird areas that are still valid
but don't really tell you whether or not they're a good game designer.
know the good and bad answers.
Now what's key here is again,
I went through all the good and bad answers
and even a great answer here,
and that allows me to quantify their answer.
I mean, if it's too open,
I can't figure out if it's a good answer or bad answer,
really, I mean, it's just based off feelings.
On top of that, if I know all the good and bad answers,
I can give that to a recruiter
and they can do a lot of the work for me,
kind of screening these people before it gets to me.
And if you've maybe noticed at your studios,
Generally, recruiters will ask for questions
and it's actually very hard to do
because they don't understand game design,
they don't understand how to judge open questions
and these open answers,
so it's not something they can do easily.
So finally, to test systems,
add or remove a mechanic from a known system
and then see if they understand those implications.
So this is kind of my great way of understanding
how to test systems and game loops,
but we still have two other skills,
which is problem solving and player experience up next.
And I generally like to use real world problems.
I wanna see them step through something
they might be stepping through on the job.
First, of course, bad question.
You need to design a new NPC for a game,
where do you start?
I've actually seen this question asked
and I sort of cringed because I don't know
even what they're looking for.
Is this a process question?
Are they asking him to solve a problem somehow?
Where do I start?
I start with understanding the game
and then the NPCs that are currently in the game
and how I can challenge the player outside
of what you're already challenging.
But what this question feels like it's saying
is just design, go.
Design something.
uh... which is very difficult to answer and again it's one of those
open questions that's just
i want to hear you talk
and and see where you go with this
now a great answer for this question isn't going to your process that's kind
of a boring answer no one's really pay attention to a great answer to this
question is going back into your experiences and talking about when you
design an npc why you designed it that way what process you went through that's
actually looking for it's not what they're asking great interviews will
give that to emporium viewers won't just be confused
And a good question, if you're looking to figure out
how they design an NPC, if you're looking to figure out
what their process actually is,
don't ask them what their process is,
ask them, give them a scenario
and try and have them step it through that scenario.
So this is a good question.
You're working on Far Cry and the creative director
asks you to design a tank vehicle as an enemy encounter.
Two points to keep in mind while designing this.
One, Far Cry is an open world game and the creative director wants us to be a roaming NPC that can be encountered anywhere.
Two, Far Cry supports a wide variety of playstyles from the stealth archer to the demolition man.
All playstyles should be able to overcome this tank encounter.
What's the first thing that crosses your mind when given this task?
It's a loaded question, obviously, and something I give more to mid- to senior-level designers.
But stepping through it, starting with Far Cry.
A huge franchise for Ubisoft, and if you haven't played it, you shouldn't be interviewing for game design at Ubisoft.
It's that simple.
And I want to stress that for anyone that's looking to interview in this room.
I've interviewed a lot of people, oh, I haven't played Far Cry, sorry.
You shouldn't be here.
You're asking to take the keys of that franchise and be on the game design team.
How can you do that if you don't know the game?
uh... second point is i'm asking to sign a tank vehicle i'm not asking to sign a
dragon for drug sequence in far cry
that's really complex and again i don't care but their answers i don't care but
their ideas for designing dragons
i want to keep it very simple
uh... because what's really important is these two problems that i laid out
far cry is an open world game we want this to be an open world encounter
which means we don't want to be an arena encounter which we've all seen those
where you walk into an arena
there's rpg scattered everywhere and you're like okay
something's about to go down
That's not the type of encounter we're looking for.
We want something that is just roaming the world freely
with systemic rules.
Far Cry supports a wide variety of play styles.
So what are all the play styles?
How can you solve that?
And what's the first thing that crosses your mind?
Again, I wanna hear their mental process,
but more importantly, I'm trying to turn this interview
into a design session.
Interviews generally test interview skills.
Design sessions are gonna test their job skills.
And the more comfortable they can be
in that design session, the better.
So let's step through some bad answers.
I love doing that.
uh... skipping encounter i've had can i can it that actually once said okay
okay design a tank encounter
okay so that you destroy one tank and you know what to make it difficult
worldwide to tanks
and i was blown away like you just passed everything
uh... you'd be this can it did not understand what really game design was
and what the meat of their job really was gonna be
tangents that dodge the question
uh... so i had a canada's well go through all i would love to steal a tank
and drive the tank and for five minutes when stop talking about driving the tank
which completely wasn't this question about and take a vehicle as an enemy
too much reference
and references good generally but if you never bring it back
to solve the problem there's no purpose to it if you talk about
uh... which one can it did just battlefield tanks for the next five
minutes uh... it didn't really help out in in solving this problem and i kept
trying to bring him back to the problem is trying to solve
and they don't understand the problems. Again, I laid out those two problems
and the whole point of the question is
do you understand what issues will come if you get those problems and try to
design a tank with those in mind?
And that leads us to our good answers.
The first one being the open world problem, which again, it's not an arena.
This is now something that's roaming the world that has systemic rules,
which generally means the player needs to bring the solution.
There's solutions that are scattered everywhere.
Now you could scatter the solution all over the entire world,
but that may cause its own problems.
and in play styles. So this is a chance for the designers to try and think of
okay what are all the different player types that existed in that game that I played
hopefully and then what challenges and opportunities can be used to overcome the
tank in those different player styles. If I have just a bow and arrow, how can I take out this tank?
And this starts to get a little bit dangerously
into idea generation.
So it's your job as the interviewer to say,
okay, what other problems might that idea create
that you just mentioned?
You gotta keep bringing it back to problems to solve.
You wanna see, as I said earlier,
if they have an idea in their head,
can they judge, okay, what does that do to the mechanic,
what does that do to the system,
what does that do to the overall game?
Can they own that process?
And this is an opportunity for you
to bring bad ideas to the table,
ideas you know have holes in them,
to see if they can detect those holes.
And most importantly, combined, problem one and two
actually create a major problem for stealthier players.
People have to bring their own solution,
and then also they have to somehow overcome this tank
as a stealth player.
And that leads us to a great answer.
So this was actually a candidate
that was sort of failing at this question.
I was trying to turn it into a design session.
He was fumbling around, didn't really understand
until finally at one point his nerves went away
and he just sort of felt good
in that design session type mentality
and started riffing really well
and talked about Splinter Cell.
mentioned, we had this thing in Splinter Cell that NPCs are generally walking around with
weapons the entire game and they can get kind of monotonous.
NPCs don't really feel like real characters if that's all they're doing.
So there was a couple things added where sometimes an NPC would have his gun far away from him
on a table, leaning up against a wall, taking a smoke break, or he's talking to another
NPC, and if you startled that NPC they'd freak out and try and rush towards that gun, giving
you more opportunity to try and take that NPC down.
but it also added a lot more narrative into the world
and made these characters feel more real.
He utilized this and turned it into something
the tank could do, that's roaming the world,
the two guys get out of the tank, have a smoke break.
This gives an opportunity for that stealth player
to take those guys out, or an opportunity
for you to steal the tank.
Now, again, this is tough between,
is this a cool mechanic system
that could be used throughout the game?
Is this a cool idea?
But it didn't really matter,
because in that design session,
what this did was provide a revelation,
that it's not a tank, it's two guys in a tank.
And for a stealth mechanic, that's huge.
Because in stealth games, what you're usually doing
is manipulating these NPCs,
and it's hard to manipulate a faceless tank.
But if you know there's two guys in that tank,
now you're thinking, okay,
how can I get those two guys out of that tank?
Can I smoke them out?
What else can I do?
And that really made the design session start to come alive.
And that made me think, okay, day to day,
I could talk with this guy.
I could have a cool design session with him,
and we could solve problems together.
So, again, to solve problems, some take away for problem solving and player experience.
Don't ask how they design, offer scenarios with problems.
Generally, what you're really asking when you ask them how they design is, hey, how
do you solve problems?
And I don't know how to ask that or even answer that, to be honest.
If you ask someone how they solve problems, don't be surprised when they say, oh, I think
about it, and then solutions come up.
It's a very confusing, weird question and a weird answer.
Turn the interview into a design session.
It allows you to test their job skills
instead of testing their interview skills,
which I kind of mentioned before.
And then finally, keep the conversation on track.
You want it to be about solving problems.
So you want to see, again,
you want to see if they can take that idea
and say, okay, how does that affect the mechanic?
How does that affect the system?
Work it up through that process.
That's what game designers own.
So as a kind of recap, I kind of successfully, with those two questions, talked about how
to get those skills, those four skills I'm looking for, out of the interview process.
And those bad questions I talked about, how to stay away from idea generation, design
critiquing, those type of things you're not looking for.
Generally, rock, paper, scissors, a great question for junior designers.
The tank question, again, more mid to senior level designers.
But what about game directors?
And I wanted to throw this in here
to step through this process again
just to get it ingrained in your head.
The first thing we start with
is what skills are we looking for?
So high-level direction and the ability to build brands
and understand brand values.
And if we take that further
and start talking about a bad question,
which many of you may have heard,
where would you take the next far cry?
uh... so this again i hopefully by now you can see this question ago of this is
too open
all's releasing is a technical ideas
don't be surprised if you ask this question when the person says all
parker could be in space and talks about space for the next ten minutes and all
you're doing is that they're thinking why ask this question i don't care about
this idea
A good question, critics are saying that many Ubisoft franchises like Assassin's Creed and
Far Cry are becoming too similar of experiences.
What's the root of this criticism?
How are these brands different?
And how would you help differentiate these brands in future installments?
I'm going to put these questions side by side because it completely represents kind of the
point I'm getting at right now.
Too many people asked the question on the left, not enough people asked the question
on the right.
And it's not about amount of text.
With the question on the left, you're gonna get very open answers that are gonna be all
about idea generation.
Is this person good for the job?
I have no idea.
Do they have bad ideas?
Yeah, so does everyone else.
On the question on the right, you're going to get at the root, which is, here's a problem to solve
that we actually have in the world right now.
And also, do you understand the brand values of Far Cry and Assassin's Creed?
Do you understand the things that makes them different?
Obviously, at Ubisoft, we have a lot of Ubisoft values we try and put in all of our games,
which start to make some of the games overlap in terms of open world great experiences.
But what makes each of these franchises also different?
And how can you build on those differences to separate these brands in the future?
So hopefully you guys will start noticing
as you ask questions, as you listen to questions,
where they're gonna go, where they probably shouldn't go.
So just a final thoughts on where we go from here.
So for interviewers, define game design.
It's sort of the first step of your job
is to figure out, okay, what are the skills I'm looking for?
What does it mean for my studio?
Again, it may be something more technical in your studio
which you wanna add technical questions.
You may merge game design with level design at your studio
which you wanna include those skills as well.
Build direction, or build direct questions, sorry,
for that definition that you laid out.
And then know the good and bad answers for those questions
so that you can maybe even give them to recruiters
so that you can understand and quantify those answers.
turn interviews into design sessions,
because again, you're trying to test job skills,
you're not testing interviewing skills.
And you can actually get people to ease in a little better,
because generally people get nervous around interviewing,
people don't get nervous that are designers,
in design sessions they feel a lot more comfortable.
keep reviewing your hiring process on this is extremely important and this
isn't like something to do annually
every time you ask a question you get a bad answer
wonder if
that was a bad question
uh... really judge yourself and start testing questions on each other
uh... buff if someone says something poor interview if they're going for the
next interview talk to that person is gonna be interviewing them
uh... really figure out okay this was bad see if you can probe their little
further see if i think he was a bad question or maybe
uh... he just understand
Raising it out to me this raises the bar for the entire industry.
If we can raise the bar for a game designers if we can raise the overall
our industry will improve.
And I just want to add a section for candidates as well.
There's a lot of people I know that want to be game designers. A majority of those
people don't understand what game design is.
And so my first step usually is to try and scare them away from being game
designers
and see if they can handle that.
So a couple of things to keep in mind if you want to go into game design or if you're looking for another job.
Game design is a profession. Too many people treat it like a hobby.
And what I mean by that is too many people are turning their nose up at indie games because they like major games,
or at mass market games because, oh that's the 8th iteration, oh it's all the same, I'm an indie game person.
This isn't a hobby.
This is a profession.
So you want to play everything, reference anything.
And I tell my game designers, if it's 90 plus, you've played it.
If it's 80 plus and in your genre, you've played it.
Everything else is your hobby.
You can do whatever you want with that time.
But you've got to really start taking this seriously.
Game design is tedious.
You're designing a world.
You have to really fill all the holes in that world
to make sure they're designed before it goes
into production or you're gonna waste a lot of time.
For more information on this,
Liz Englund actually has an amazing blog post
called The Door Problem.
Really goes at the tediousness of what your job's
actually gonna be and hopefully it will scare people away
from wanting to be game designers.
uh... think out loud your mental process is the main important thing we're after
i don't want you to flounder around on top too much not knowing where to go i
don't want to go straight to the answer i don't care what the answer i'm not
gonna use that answer i want to hear your thought process and where you go
in terms of
all that the system that works here that doesn't work here okay made that fails i
want to see where i can take this
uh... that's the main key
uh... not only is that help you interviews it's gonna help you design
sessions and help you pitch
your design systems to the team
uh... because you can say okay here my goals
here are the problems i was trying to solve
Here's some ideas I had that didn't work, and here's why I went to this one.
And generally that's going to get people on board more often.
Game design isn't about your ideas,
it's about everyone else's, and I can't preach that enough.
The entire dev team is a group of passionate people
that will have ideas, and I usually say ideas
are like Legos in a sea of Legos,
and too many game designers are picking up a Lego
and going, look, this one's mine.
And there's Legos everywhere, who cares?
Nobody cares if that's yours.
Your job is to build something out of all those Legos.
That's the key.
Understand which ideas work, which ideas don't work,
and then build the experience you're trying to build.
That's my talk.
This is my contact information.
I usually throw it up.
People tell me not to, but whatever.
I love to keep the conversation going,
both on the interviewer side, on the candidate side,
if you guys have any other thoughts.
Also, two years ago I did a talk
called Designing Your Design Team.
It's on the GDC Vault.
Please check this out on the GDC Vault after as well.
And if you look at those and have any other thoughts
on either of those, I'd love to hear it.
So please, let's keep this going.
Also after this, probably out of time,
so I'm gonna go to the wrap-up room
if you guys have any other questions.
Thank you.