All right, hello everyone and welcome to our talk about how to make things pop.
This talk is going to be about how audio and visuals can be used to enhance the experience of a video game.
It's a dive into our thinking and methods when working towards the common goal.
She is Inna Hansen.
And this is Martin Kvala.
And together we have worked on these four games together.
We are also currently both ending up working on a new super secret project that we are in talks about and can't share.
But however, today we are here to talk about mixing up the disciplines together with you.
Almost a year ago, we did talks back to back at Nordic Game Jam.
Strangely, the points we were making were the same ones.
My talk was about color psychology and Martin's was on how to choose the right sound style.
So we decided to get started journey where we could talk about the same things from the respective points of our views together here.
It's also kind of funny as a sound designer, because I sometimes quite often get the whole thing of like, could you make this sound more green?
Or could you make this rain sound more yellow?
So I've always been curious about, maybe Ina has these secrets to be explaining to me.
So that's my ulterior motive.
So we are the bread in the sandwich.
We come from two completely different disciplines with tools that don't overlap at all.
We are in many ways a metaphorical bread in the metaphorical sandwich.
You start with art and you finish with sound.
And we all hold it together with carbs.
Delicious carbs.
In this talk,
We will talk about these things.
So why should you care about great audio and art?
Which is a bit about the benefits of prioritizing this for your game.
How to make it stand out.
How to cut through the noise.
How do we work?
And we'll go through our processes and how we address the same concepts and goals.
How to make the pop stick.
making memorable experiences by playing of vibes, associations and making patterns and shared language.
This is a little bit of how and why you should talk to each other.
At the end of this talk, you will be able to identify how to bring out the best in your project.
We'll get into the way we think when creating visuals and audio, and we hope that you sincerely can take something away from this.
Audio person, talk to your artists.
Artists, involve an audio person early on.
And solo dev, go talk to the artists and audio people.
Talk to each other.
We hope you want to.
Making video games is a collaborative project for the most part.
And we think we gain more from connecting all the dots early on.
We also have to say that mostly we come from an indie background.
None of us have really done much work on AAA, which means that we don't know much about them, but judging from their output, their power does seem to lie in impressive craftsmanship and the band's big budgets.
However, as indies, we mostly feel that the cool thing that we can do is affording to try the big, weird, spiky and cranky ideas, which we also want to argue is our strength in this talk.
Okay, indulge us in a little experiment here.
We'd like some participation from you guys.
So, before we start going into our points, let's try to do a yellow clap.
That's a tiny, slow clap, like this.
Yes, careful.
And then, an applause.
That's an orange clap.
It's like this.
But in a...
What comes in between of these two?
Can we try it?
Let's try it.
Yeah.
Tiny clap again.
Yes.
Okay.
Perfect.
That's really good.
Thank you.
So, why should you care about having good audio and art for your game?
Let's get into the problems that we all have to deal with because every day, especially I like, for instance, on Steam, there's about 50 games being released and it's very hard to break through this noise.
And even when it captures someone's attention, how do you leave them with a good impression?
Sad, sad clip.
So, how do you make an impression in the world of so many impressions?
We're consuming so many things every single day.
It's not just games, it's also series, apps, social media, etc.
Yeah, and we're all trying to make our project as best as we can.
We want to make the case for how our graphics and sound can capture and hold people's attention through this all.
So, how to make your game stand out?
We also have many opinions about this part, and there are many ways of thinking about this topic, so listen to our take coming now.
First of all, make a good game.
We don't really have a lot of say in this normally.
And you can definitely make a great game without caring about audio or art.
But if this is you, you're free to leave now.
Shush, shush, shush, shush.
We'll be waiting for two minutes while everyone leaves the room.
Identity.
The essence of the game is communicated and formulated through its identity.
Finding the direction of it all is establishing palettes, and that means both for sound and for color.
A screenshot should look like... Every screenshot in your game should look like your game.
Although this is not a marketing talk, this can be a super handy tool for marketing as well.
You can clearly see that this is The Simpsons.
This is not even a screenshot, but you can still recognize them from a few LEGO blocks.
And this is South Park characters.
The IPs are using character design for the most part to have their identity be associated with them really strongly.
This is a game example.
Limbo is very striking with its filmatic grayscale look and eerie atmosphere.
And the eyes of the protagonist is little creepy, glowy eyes.
Firewatch is not...
very stylized in its graphics but it keeps repeating this gradient throughout the game by utilizing light and color grading to make it look like fire or a sunset.
Then we have Matrix.
Matrix is very green and all of the movies are super green and you can always see it from any screenshots.
And that used to be the color of tech.
It's not anymore, but it used to be.
And they used the green and black in their digital reign, which I would argue is still iconic to this day.
Yeah.
Crafting through this philosophy, it makes you know what decisions benefit this direction and which do not.
To make indecisions, basically, we'll have a framework further down the line.
In the same way, we could say every clip should sound like a game.
If you hear something like half a second from a trailer somewhere, it's really nice if you can go like, that is that game, I do know it.
And of course, since audio takes time to show, we're just going to show three quick clips I hope you all have heard before.
So games are pretty much often fully imagined worlds completely created by a team of quite competent creators.
The sounds should also be every bit as tailor-made and unique as anything else in this.
We're going to talk a little bit about how we make the decisions and what kind of decisions that we make.
For instance, with sound, with recognizable sound, personally I like to work out of two different constraints.
First of all, knowing the intentions behind the thing, what is it supposed to be doing, both in the game in the figurative sense, like what are you actually doing, but also what it's trying to convey.
But I'm also finding it really nice to have a set of rules and limitations.
And this is a good example of a limitation that I like.
So Hidden Folks is a hidden object game with only mouth sounds, which is very practical.
Basically, if you're having a mouth, if you have a microphone, it's quite simple that most teams could even kind of mostly get a decent result by just using this rule without even having a sound design on the team.
It's just a very good kind of limitation for its kind.
Then we have something like this, which is a more conceptual imitation.
And Among the Sleep is a narrative-driven horror-adventure game in which you have to play as a two-year-old child.
Here, the audio needs to get the player to feel really small and scared.
So, like, for instance, the sound needs to enhance this emotion due to the player.
Dragging a chair needs to feel like you're dragging an even bigger chair.
Like you're seeing this chair is three meters tall for you, but it needs to feel like you're dragging something which is like 10 meters long.
It's huge.
Seeing your mother lash out while drunk, it needs to feel incomprehensible and frightening.
As a limitation, this is a more open in a practical sense.
More things are allowed in that sense, but it does need to provide this way more importantly to drive home the narrative elements of it.
So, how do you pick the color and how do you pick the sound?
As we found out that our ways of working shared a lot of similarities, not while we did the Nordic Game Jam talks, we started delving further into our processes.
How do I pick my colors?
How does Martin pick his sounds?
And there we have a little demonstration of an example.
This is Gunner 2, a game we both worked on and we focused on maintaining a little bit and elaborating the existing identity of the first game, pushing further the candy-like quality of the color palettes and the dark backgrounds makes everything glow in a
Yes, and alongside with the candy we want to give players something savory to listen to, so I like to think of the audio as popcorn.
It's kind of like you bring a scoop of a hand down in a bucket and you take a big swig of it, or you know, a bite I guess.
And you just want to continue and have more because it's salty, it's delightful, it's many many small things and maybe it doesn't really have to make sense, but it's all part of the kind of whole of it.
I'm
So, in the game Sunlight, we created the forest as a metaphor for humanity.
The harmony of the trees are speaking in unison, so each tree is a part of the story yet distinct its own.
Together they represent the narrative to you, the player, in a calm, serene pace as you walk around.
The serenity of the forest is underlined through its earthy greens and greens, creating a relaxing harmony in the colors.
The sunlight, of course, being at the center of attention, bringing it some warmth.
Another example.
Exploring the world with the wind in your whiskers.
Discovering new ingredients and flavors to make the best dishes ever.
Customizing your truck to your heart's desire.
So in the game Fruit Bus, it's a bright and whimsical game, and the fruits and the foods are at its core.
We explored how to make everything look delicious, and that bright color palette came out of that.
And from these visual choices, we went for a tasty blend of realism and abstract sounds.
And the reason for this is the game is quite a tangible game.
Everything in there has a purpose.
Like, for instance, if you drive a car, you better remember your handbrake, right?
So to give the player this idea that this world is tangible, we used realistic sounds to ground that.
And we used abstract sound to keep it feeling really good to interact with.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
We're not done, though.
We're not done.
So how do you find the essence?
You just find your themes, and this can be really abstract, and sometimes it can be really concrete, as we just talked about.
And then you just run with it.
Yeah, and keep reinforcing your own rules.
Essentially, if you keep repeating a concept of the rules you set throughout the process, you're doing it right.
Remember the vision, and as everyone who's ever played everything knows, consistency trumps quality.
Consistency is quality, essentially.
Iterate.
This is probably the only slide we haven't changed, which is kind of funny, but it is spot on.
So personal style and essence.
It is very important to know your taste.
Also for when choosing who to work with.
So when you're hiring or partnering up with somebody, it's much easier to work with them if they understand why the thing you're trying to make is really, really cool than not.
Here are some examples from my own style.
I don't really have a personal style per se, but I do have a taste and a color philosophy.
So you can see that you will get some sort of version of the bisexual color palette.
I think similar to Inna, I also have more of a process maybe than a style.
I do like to work quickly, destructively and exploratory, which means I seldom know what I'm doing, but I like doing it.
It also kind of ends up sometimes being something that is a bit...
Sometimes ends up standing a little bit beside the game not necessarily in it But kind of fits with the game in a way in again in a spike away, right?
So even though I might have a disregard of some of somewhat overall direction I might have my own idea of a direction that I keep and maintain and this keeps things feeling quite consistent in the end
So, making the pop stick.
So if you're working within the found essence, well, for using the identity to guide your decisions, how do we take this further, the next few steps?
If you make a memorable experience by applying with vibes, association and patterns, we think you're on a good course of something right.
In audio as well maybe, however I don't really quite know.
However, with audio, which I quite like, I often quite see it as a sort of player whisperer.
It tells the player a lot of things that they don't really necessarily think about.
And even though I think quite a lot of people understand how music treats them and influences them, for instance with audio, I think that if you have something like a gun in a game, you can have a lot of information to the player by making the gun feel more or less powerful than the enemies around you.
If you're basically having a more powerful gun, you'll maybe have a little bit of a gun power fantasy, and maybe that will act... enforce how you behave in the game.
The other way, if you're doing it a more European, realistic, or like darker way, you're probably gonna feel more weak, and the gun is gonna be like, pew pew pew, feel like a peashooter, and that kind of influences you maybe crawling around to creeping a little bit more, maybe you're a bit more aware of the ammunition.
In essence, it's a lot of these kind of things that I really geek out about when it comes to audio, which I hope most people don't notice because that also means I'm doing my job just right.
You can do similar things with colors.
You can use colors to enhance the feelings of your game.
You can easily underline a feeling by desaturating or intensifying a color, like low-key, while the player doesn't need to pay attention to it, they still feel it.
So you're guiding the player into their emotions.
So when designing Fruit Bus, we wanted to push the associations of delicious foods, while the agenda became making the game really comfortable and cozy.
And the game also has a little bit of surreal nature to it.
It's reflected in the colors and stuff, but it's also reflected in the environments.
Yes, and the delicious foods, darlings, it also is served with a hot plate of sounds.
They complement the visuals by juicing up the interaction of cutting, slicing, cooking, goosing and flusing.
I'd like to explain a little bit about what's going on with the psychology of it all.
You've probably heard of bottom-up and top-down processing.
When you're doing bottom-up processing, you're seeing a bunch of things that are laid out in front of you, and you're trying to make...
Everything makes sense.
You're trying to make patterns within your brain.
And if it's top-down processing, you already have an idea about what's going on, and you are projecting that on whatever is in front of you.
And these, of course, play back and forth.
Top-down processing can be playing of perceived expectations, like shorthand communication.
Color coding is a good example of this, color coding of rarity items.
Although there are some slight variations of these systems, it's very obvious for a player who plays within a genre to understand what is going on at the screen, and you get a lot for free.
Another example is how to convey that a door is locked.
It's quite simple with sound.
A good little door knob rattle makes it go and work 100% of the time, conveying a sound without having to do much more.
And you can also set up expectations by making a pattern.
making the player rely on information that is being presented to them, making the stuff in-game pop a little bit, and this is an interplay between sound and vision.
Here comes a little example of a thing from Goner 2 again.
I really like that snake.
The snake is the exit and entrance to each level.
So you can easily spot its vivid body.
It stands out quite a lot.
And the color, it's coded to be like everything that is good and helpful within the game.
And it also serves as a little pause in between levels.
Yeah, and the same thing in the sound is kind of helping out here is being that it goes from chaotic, it goes from like quite a multitude of things into like a very calm thing, everything stops, nothing plays anymore, and the music gets muted.
You can kind of hear... Oh yeah, never mind.
Our next point is that patterns of repetition works quite a lot.
And we know that because repetition works.
Repetition works.
This is Martin's joke, you don't have to... But it leads us into a really fun topic, which is...
Subverting expectations.
So, another little example from Gunner 2 is the blue-toned, turquoise-toned grandma Death.
And I mean, she's Death, so she's a little bit intimidating.
But all in all, she is related to everything that is good in the world, because she's
turquoise and blue, and like, ammo flowers or the tree where you get the skulls from, which is a good thing in the game.
Grandma Death is associated with a safe hub space.
And the enemies are generally coated with warm reds.
So, at the end, and this is a huge spoiler, I'm sorry, she appears as the last boss in the game, and it should feel a little bit like fighting your own granny.
Same thing with the game, usually upgrades are fun.
You get fun heads, you get fun guns.
However, we have a little joke which is the poop heads, which some players like, but essentially it's a game that gives you almost no health.
It makes you shoot bigger bullets and it kind of sounds a bit crummy when you do it, which makes that each sound is a little bit of a punchline.
This is another game that I worked on called Dead Pets Unleashed.
And in the world, both the world and the protagonist are coded in purple and pink colors.
So this becomes a pattern throughout the game.
When you go into this environment, you can feel how out of place the character is without anybody saying anything because, well, this is very devoid of color.
Except for the little uplifting notes, which are pink.
Very subversive.
Mmm, subversive.
Yes, because game direction is audio and art direction.
In theory, there is one person, one team that ensures that audio and visuals support each other and support the overall direction.
But in reality, it's sometimes not the case, at least in small indie teams where we're all wearing a bunch of different hats each day.
But it is up to us to talk together and figure this out, and this is how we suggest approaching this.
We came up with this talk from discovering how often we talk about the same stuff from two different angles.
And this talk itself is a result of communication.
Figure out what people on the team have strong opinions and wishes about for the projects.
How do they differ or concur from yours?
Yes.
In any case, we wish we talked together earlier in all cases, pretty much.
So please, please, please reach out to each other.
And we're all working towards a common goal.
So, in summary on this talk, remember to find your essence.
Yes, the thing that makes your game special.
Practice making rules and limitations.
Remember to stick with it, repeat, stick with it, repeat, stick with it, repeat, and enhance.
Make it pop.
It popped.
Be yourself.
Remember your tastes.
They're what you want.
They're also what other people want from you.
Make patterns happen.
It can be powerful to know when to subvert them.
Get talking early on.
Yes, talk.
It's very nice.
And involve art and audio.
Me and Inna make them communicate, make them write the talk together.
It's pretty funny.
And also, I guess this is also how you make something sound yellow.
It's also how you trick people into giving you an applause.
I hope we made a good impression.
And more than anything, we hope we stood out to you in a memorable way.
All right.
I believe we have four minutes maybe for Q&A.
Yeah.
So if anyone has a question, please come up to the microphone now or be forever quiet unless you see us in the park outside at some point.
What are some tools for the sound creation side that you recommend for people that like don't have the resources or could, it's like a luxury to have like a sound designer on their team.
So like wearing many hats kind of thing, like what tools do you recommend?
Oh yeah, I think this is a question we often get.
In essentially like for small teams you mean that doesn't really have a sound designer how to be able to do it.
I think trying to figure out interesting limitations, sticking to like single piece of gears.
There's for instance cheap synthesizers that are free.
There's online tools that runs on Chrome for instance that you can like spam coin sound and it will create you like 15 variations of that that you can download and use for your game.
I always say that of course if you find something fun that you can do.
It's kind of the best, especially if it's something you do yourself.
For instance, running around like crazy with a mobile phone.
In general, you can end up with a lot of fun sounds.
And you can find some free software to cut it up.
You can put it into your game, and it's going to be fine.
I think the main thing is just mostly about balance.
If you really, really, really take the audio volume down low when you test things, you can hear if it's really sticking out too loud or too low.
And the rest is just gonna be make sure you have fun with it, make sure you spend enough time with it.
It really is about time.
Thank you.
Hello, Tess.
Okay, good.
I have a question about like communicating in general.
I'm a programmer by trade.
So I often like to talk to my, with my like artists and sound designers.
And we often like try to communicate from different ends.
So it's like we often end up these metaphorical question like, I want this
like the scene to feel more like dark and gloomy and atmospheric, but I don't know exactly how to describe it at times.
What do you think is like very helpful in terms like when describing more concretely?
I always recommend using references.
So if you have something very specific in mind, try to find that reference.
Don't be afraid to like riff off something that already exists.
You will make it you, like it doesn't really matter.
Do you have something on the sound side?
Exactly what Ines is saying.
For audio, it helps quite often to just go to YouTube, find a video, find a reference saying like, this is kind of what I want.
If you give them three different things, they will kind of triangulate that.
That's the job, basically.
Also, please let us know when it's the last question.
I think we have time for at least one more.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks so much.
Okay, we'll be in the wrap-up area.
Thank you so much again, and see you in the park.