Okay, I'm going to get started. Thanks for coming down again. This is Keep It Together,
where we're going to be talking about how to get players to cooperate with each other
when they're playing in co-op games. So, I'm Patrick Redding. I'm currently a game director
at the new Ubisoft Toronto studio. We opened a little over a year ago. Prior to that, I
spent about five and a half years, six years at the Ubisoft Montreal studio.
where most recently I was the co-op game director on Splinter Cell Conviction.
And then before that I was the narrative designer on Far Cry 2,
and then played various game design roles on the last generation of consoles, Far Cry
games.
But today, I'm going to talk about player cooperation.
And I mean this in the sort of most obvious, explicit possible way.
I'm not talking about...
cooperation in the sense of when players get together and agree to abide by the same rules.
I'm not talking about stepping into the magic circle or any of that stuff. I mean actually
players working together to try to overcome the challenges that are posed by the computer.
So co-op play. Before I get into that, I just want to step
back a couple weeks ago to an article that I was reading on Greg Castigan's blog, which
is Play This Thing.
And there was an article posted by one of his regular blog contributors.
It goes by JZW.
And JZW was asking, he was sort of thinking about the current situation in the Mideast
and some of the recent popular uprisings that have taken place in places like Egypt and
Algeria and whatnot.
And he was asking, if someone was to make a game that was about a modern, non-violent
revolution, what would that game look like?
And this, you know, this prompted kind of a lively discussion on the comments thread,
in which a variety of people brought up different games that they had seen over the years they
thought kind of fit the bill.
Games that this is a force more powerful from a few years ago.
And pretty quickly the author had to kind of push back and say, well hang on, a lot
of the games that people are talking about are games in which the player is kind of a
revolution tycoon.
He's somebody who's sort of taking all of the resources that make up the populace.
and figuring out how to allocate them in support of a revolutionary movement
in order to take down the man, as it were.
And his point was that in real life, as we've seen
somewhat vividly, somewhat tragically in some cases,
real revolutions are started from within.
They're started by people whose necks are every bit
as much on the line as the people who they're organizing.
And that furthermore,
the nature of this kind of movement is that...
It started by people reaching out to their friends and to their family and to members of their immediate community,
the people with whom they share all of the common interests that lead them to have a grievance in the first place.
That it's not about just simply sticking a YouTube video on the Internet and then having 20,000 people show up in a public square the next day.
And there has been kind of a popular misconception, I think, in the last couple of years
that somehow...
modern non-violent revolutionary movements
come about as a sort of
smart mob
uh... with slightly higher stakes
uh... that the fabric of the twitterverse has somehow just kind of given rise to
these movements
in some kind of magical
emergent way
and in fact this doesn't turn out to be true at all
it turns out that the same kinds of strong social links
that were needed five thousand years ago or five hundred years ago or fifty years
ago
are just as critical and important now as ever.
That it's not going to be your 958 Facebook friends
that are going to help you when you're up against the tanks and the barricades.
And the reason why this is ought to be relatively apparent,
but there's some non-trivial consequences to it.
Basically, if you're dangling at the end of the string,
if it's an existential stake that you're up against,
then those strong social links that you're depending on
are a mechanism for negotiation.
You're depending on the fact that you have license to negotiate action in the service
of some kind of collective goal.
And what's interesting is that the negotiation actually helps to reinforce those strong social
links and then the strong social links in turn help to reinforce and enable the negotiated
action.
When we apply this to other types of collective goals.
say the collective goals associated with an alternate reality game or even an online multiplayer
game, something like World of Warcraft. What we find is that the same effect is true, obviously
slightly smaller stakes, but players become invested primarily in the success of their
collaborative partners because of that ongoing process of negotiation, because of those leveraging
of strong social links. The negotiation process converts.
their individual selfish motives into the motives that are associated with the collective
goal. Now, it's probably too dark, but that's okay. Like a lot of people within about five
square blocks of this auditorium, I've occasionally been playing Minecraft in the last year.
Mostly I've been playing Minecraft on a multiplayer server maintained by a small group of friends
of mine who are scattered all over the world in different time zones. And what's interesting
is...
We hardly ever actually see each other when we go on this multiplayer server.
We show up, we do our mining, we do our crafting, we construct massive monuments to our personal
hubris, but we don't actually see each other's avatar very often, and we don't even really
chat that often.
So interestingly, a couple weeks ago, probably around the same time I was reading that article
on PlayThisThing, I had to sort of take a bit of a hiatus from playing Minecraft.
To be honest, it wasn't a hard hiatus to take.
As much as I enjoyed mining and crafting and building extravagant monuments to my hubris,
the truth was that, you know, I had a point where I had other things that I needed to
take care of, like creating GDC talks.
But one weekend I decided to fire up the server because I was kind of, I needed a break and
I was curious to see what had been happening in the two weeks since I'd been on there.
You see here in this kind of dark image is kind of an elaborate urbanized area with
elevated light rail systems and waterworks and lava pipes and various barricades for
the mutual defense of the inhabitants against marauding mobs. None of that had been there
two weeks before. It had been desert and waterfront and mountains. It was like visiting people
in limbo in Inception. All of a sudden there was like these giant cityscapes that had emerged
from nowhere. And I was almost instantly overwhelmed by the need.
to devote the next 48 hours to working on my territory.
I felt this powerful sense that I was not only missing out on all of the cool collective
things that had been going on in the meantime, but that maybe I was actually not holding
up my end of the bargain.
And I think the point here is that players respond very, very powerfully to a sense of
collective agency that's at work in the game space.
It's more powerful and more potent.
than maybe any one individual game motivation that they might experience as a single player.
And for scientists who study the psychology of people in games, in games that have multiple
players, this is known as shared intentionality.
And it lies at the heart of what we're going to be talking about in terms of cooperation.
So that's fine.
That's Minecraft.
That's eight weirdos playing a game that doesn't actually have victory conditions.
a game that hasn't technically been released yet.
For those of us that are working on kind of these mass-market commercial mainstream games
that have a co-op component, how do we achieve the conditions in which shared intentionality
becomes an important factor in the enjoyment of the players and therefore causes them to
want to work together and to want to cooperate?
Now this isn't trivial because by definition if it's an online game, the players are separated
geographically.
If, to a large extent, our statistics are correct, and we think they probably are,
probably at least half of them don't even know each other.
They're playing by a matchmaking and various other mechanisms.
Also, let's face it, as game developers, as designers,
we really prize and prioritize individual player agency.
Right? We have huge fights about it.
It's probably the one fight that every single designer has had at some point
with the rest of their team.
As we argue that...
regardless of what the production realities are, regardless of how polished the scripted
events might look in a particular section, that if we're eroding somehow the agency of
the individual player, if we're taking away from interactivity, that we're fundamentally
degrading the play experience.
And we're actually correct about that.
However, sometimes I think we develop myopia because we don't stop to consider that also
multiple players need to be able to have a kind of collective agency and that we need
to support that systemically.
So I'll talk about some lessons that I learned with my team while I was working on the co-op
part of Splinter Cell Conviction.
Well, the first big lesson is that players will work together if they determine that
there's a way for them to use that cooperation to optimize the output of the game's systems.
To talk about that, I'm going to just refer very, very loosely and very broadly to the
detection model that we used in Splinter Cell.
This isn't going to be a technical discussion of this, by the way.
So if you're in the AI business, I apologize.
It's not very deep.
So the number one lesson that we obtained from observing our players is that stealth
is a difficult enough thing to achieve in a single player game, but when you have more
than one player running around in the game space, stealth becomes an extremely fragile
condition.
Okay, well what do I mean by stealth?
What am I talking about?
Stealth for us is really a condition that we achieve by allowing the player to either
be detected by the AI or not be detected by the AI, and it's all the various actions the
player can take one way or the other in that direction.
And to understand how that works, we just need to sort of see that our AI has been kind
of built to be tricked, but also been built to incrementally detect the player.
So there's a number of states that permit this.
We have kind of an idle default state, which is everything that the AI does.
between the time that it's instantiated and the time that it's killed or unloaded,
whether it's systemic or scripted, it's going about its business.
But if something happens to disturb the AI while it's in that state,
then it can move into this kind of perturbed condition
where the behaviors are all about searching for whatever the source of the disturbance was.
And if enough disturbances occur, or if the player just simply outright allows themselves to be detected,
then the AI will enter a state where its behaviors...
are those that we would associate with combat,
with trying to close with the player,
or trying to kill the player,
or more specifically and accurately,
trying to entertain the player
while looking like it's trying to kill them.
And an important point here, again, not technical at all,
is that these transitions that I just described
between states, these are thresholds, basically.
This represents an accumulation of events
that cause the AI to move from one state to another.
And if we look at just even a single player that's operating in the game space, what we
see is that it's actually kind of difficult to know exactly how any one little action
or event contributes to those transitions taking place.
I mean, you can do it.
You can build a giant list or a log.
You can build a big matrix that shows exactly how one particular action by the player under
certain conditions will cause this to take place.
It would just be a lot of work.
If we add a second player to the mix, well, we have to do all that as well.
We have to see how the second player can contribute actions that will cause the second player
to be detected.
But then, very quickly, what we realize is that, actually, it's even worse than that,
because then we have to account for how player one can cause actions that will cause player
two to be detected, and then player two can do things that will cause player one to get
detected.
So you can see, I mean, it turns into a non-linear and highly messy combinatoric.
expression that I wouldn't want to have to draw the matrix for. Bottom line, just because
you have two players in the map doesn't mean you only have twice as much chance of being
detected. In fact, it's possibly a whole lot worse than that. But the flip side is that
if the players are behaving intentionally and they are observing the AI and learning
how the AI operates and learning how the detection model works.
they can actually work together to reduce the chances that they're going to be detected substantially.
And the point is here that players are acting with their knowledge and understanding of the game systems,
not because the game has told them that that's what they should be doing,
but because as they study the game and as they play the game,
whether they're playing cooperatively or not to begin with,
they realize that they have a better chance.
of success if they work together under these conditions.
And what's interesting, maybe even paradoxical, is that that power that comes from that knowledge
and understanding of the game systems, that kind of procedural literacy, actually is giving
the individual players more permission to express themselves as individual players.
And this is something that we actually observed when we were doing our play tests and when
we were looking at other games as well.
Is that self-expression...
becomes a much more interesting and deep and rich thing when there's multiple players around.
At the high level, what we saw was that players working together will do so to develop strategies
in the pursuit of the game's objectives. That at a mid-level, those players will work together
to create planning and to delegate individual low-level tasks in order to support those
plans. And that when they carry out those low-level
actions as individual players.
they're more likely to take risks and to try things that they wouldn't have tried
if they were playing as single-player players.
And that over the course of the entire game, as they are developing this kind of
mastery, this kind of literacy in the game systems, their understanding of
how the AI works, how the 3D navigation system works, all of these things,
that they are willing, more willing than they are in single-player to explore
optional paths and try alternate play styles,
because they know that they have a reasonable
chance of regrouping with their team and trying another approach if it doesn't work out.
And what we find is that if both of these conditions are present, if the players have
an understanding that they can use their cooperation to optimize the output of the game systems
and that the game is letting them express themselves as individual players more because
of cooperation, then they actually enjoy the game more. In fact, their enjoyment from that
from this, from what I'll call meaningful cooperation, is so good and so high that they're
willing to forgive an awful lot of flaws and an awful lot of lack of polish in the game
that would maybe bother them if they were to scrutinize it while playing as solo players.
Okay so I use this term meaningful cooperation. I want to examine meaningful because it's
a little bit loaded. But basically what I mean by this is that it's important in terms
of their actual success in the game.
It's not just something we're telling them,
you ought to do this, because it says co-op on the box.
But also, even though we're not telling them
to jump through hoops, it does matter
in the context of the game systems.
The game systems recognize that they're doing something,
in this case cooperating, and it rewards them for it.
Okay, so now we have this idea that we would like to try
to create circumstances for conditions
for meaningful cooperation.
Now we need design tools as designers.
that are going to allow us to support that. We need specific strategies. Now, today I
want to talk about the strategies that are hopefully usable by the largest number of
people. So I want to talk about strategies that don't depend on any one particular aesthetic
wrapper or particular genre. I want to talk about strategies that are hopefully scalable
and are replicable across the whole game that are not dependent on a particular special
case implementation, that are practical in the context of most productions.
So I'm going to talk today about what I'll call cooperative dynamics, which essentially
just means I'm talking about enabling cooperation through the game's dynamics. Okay. Another
loaded term, dynamics. Actually, it's good that I'm talking on a Thursday because those
of you who've been here for the week will likely have now had several opportunities
to run into this usage of the term, notably Clint's talk from yesterday and if you've
attended the game design workshop, you've heard those guys talk about it.
Basically, it's dynamics in the sense that we need it in the MDA model.
And in Mark and Robin and Bob's paper in 2004, they describe it as the runtime behavior of
the mechanics acting on the player's inputs and each other's outputs over time, which
is a way of saying it's what the game does when you're actually playing it.
Dynamics are what is delivering the final player experience.
In this case, it's cooperation.
meaningful hopefully, but cooperation meaningful or otherwise.
And what I'm going to talk about today are seven of the dynamics that we were looking
at on Splinter Cell.
This list I'm not going to pretend is complete, but what I am going to try to do is demonstrate
or claim that all seven of these dynamics, which I'm going to go through, sit on a continuum
of what I would call coerciveness.
They run the gamut from the top to the bottom of...
dynamics that are highly prescriptive, in the sense that the player can avoid them,
down to those that are entirely voluntary. The player retains control over whether to
participate in them or not. And interesting gameplay emerges out of that.
Okay. So let's look at the first of these. What I'll call gating or tethering. This is
probably the one with which the majority of players and the majority of people here are
familiar. It's kind of the most brute force. It essentially is just saying that
no player is allowed to proceed in the game unless all players are allowed to proceed in the game.
And this should be familiar to anybody who's ever run into an invisible wall
because there was a teammate that was straggling behind them,
or has been abruptly teleported forward because a teammate hit a checkpoint in advance of them.
It should be pretty evident that this is a highly prescriptive approach towards keeping players together.
It's either straggler-centric or it's sprinter-centric in the sense of relying on these outliers
to determine whether it works or not.
And most importantly, maybe, is that there are lots of ways to tart this up and make
it look like something more and deeper than it actually is.
But even if it is glossed over with a lot of production value, it is just going to be
an invisible wall or an invisible tether mechanically.
Now, that doesn't mean there aren't good implementations of it. In Uncharted 2, if you're playing Gold
Rush mode in their co-op, you'll encounter situations where the two teammates need to
work together, for example, to move a burning obstacle out of the way so that they're able
to advance forward. It's a good implementation. It fits the fiction of the game, the kind
of action-adventure sort of fiction that's been used there, and it's consistent with
the level of production value that you find elsewhere in the game.
On Splinter Cell, we used, I have to admit, a lot of different gating strategies. Some
of which were, I'd say, heavily realized, and some of which were just straight up gamey
invisible collisions. We had things like exotic doors that needed both players to pry open.
But we also had our holding points between different sections of the map where one player
would just simply be forced into an idle position until the second showed.
Okay, the next I'm going to talk about is what I call exotic challenges.
And the term exotic in this case means specifically that the normal camera and controls that the
player is using during core gameplay have been altered and substituted with something
else.
A unique perspective and a unique set of controls that are for different types of gameplay.
And what's interesting about this is that it creates the condition in which the player
who is required to use these different controls.
is still susceptible to all the same kinds of threats
and all the same kinds of defeats
that he'd be confronted by when he has his core gameplay controls.
So, it's moderately coercive
in the sense that it's not a binary threat.
It's not something that is immediately going to snap and then it's kicked into effect
and now you're unable to proceed.
What it means is that the risks associated with the player playing by
themselves
grow sharply over time.
and that furthermore, you need more than one player to avert trouble in order to survive
because there are other players who've retained the core gameplay controls and are therefore
able to support you. So, classic example of this is the sort of wizard performing astral
projection while the muscly fighter guy, you know, hangs out and keeps track of his lifeless
body. The modern warfare equivalent to that is I equip my laptop in order to control the
predator drone.
while my friends continue to use their tactical movement and shooter mechanics in order to
protect me.
What's interesting is actually in the case of Modern Warfare 2 and the spec ops levels
that they have is the flip side's also true, right?
I could be in an AC-130 gunship and I'm actually the one helping to avert trouble for my friend
on the ground who's using the core gameplay mechanics.
He's outnumbered, he's fleeing a larger force and I'm firing shells in order to help protect
him and cover him and play, run interference.
On Conviction, we had a few different exotic gameplay moments.
Probably the best realized was the wireless hacking sequences where one teammate would
need to go up to a particular computer, interact with it, and then had to remain within a certain
radius of that object in order to be able to maintain the signal strength to download
the secret data, which meant that they were constrained.
They still had access to a lot of their core gameplay, but they couldn't move away from
that point or it would interrupt the download.
who retained free movement would have to run interference, move around, try to protect
the two of them against the inevitable horde of security forces that were responding to
the hack. So the next two systems I'm going to talk
about are kind of two sides of the same coin. In the case of punitive systems, what we're
saying is that really, one player is trapped. One player is trapped and another player needs
to come to their rescue or it's game over for them.
I think the obvious thing about this is just that it requires
rescue by another player in order for the first player to survive.
The less obvious thing is that it actually represents
punishment and negative feedback to everyone involved,
not just the player who's been trapped.
The player who's been trapped is being punished because he was careless
and wasn't paying attention and wandered away from the group,
all the usual things you would expect.
The other players are being punished because they let the player wander away,
but also they're punished if they don't respond in time
and don't take the necessary action to.
to recover the situation. But the less obvious thing is that it's not a particularly coercive
mechanic because it can be avoided. If you're smart and if you've mastered the game, you're
able to recognize that the dangers are there and you're able to get away from them. Probably
the best implementation of this that we've seen in recent years would be in the Left
for Dead series with the smoker. I think the smoker is perfectly balanced in the sense
that the signs and feedback associated with it, the distinct sound that accompanies it.
the smoker appearing on the scene sort of sets the entire party on edge. They quickly
look at each other to make sure they know where each other are. They quickly scan the
rooftops to make sure that they can see where the smoker is. And maybe kind of disgustingly,
the smoker's tongue is like the perfect progress bar, right? It's like the ultimate organic
timer as it drags you to your doom. Everybody can see exactly how much time they have left
in order to try to save you. We had a couple of punitive systems in.
Splinter Cell Conviction co-op. We had the usual one that you associate with these kinds
of games where one teammate has been wounded, is going to bleed to death unless the other
teammate comes and rescues them. But we had an additional one which is at higher levels
we started to encounter enemies that were capable of grabbing an unwary player and holding
them in a choke hold at which point they would start to asphyxiate. And then the second player
would need to run to their aid and the first player could throw the elbow and duck down
and create the window of opportunity.
What's interesting is that these two systems actually ended up working together in a really
surprising and delightful way, which I'm going to talk about a little bit later.
The flip side to those would be buffing systems. Buffing systems are pretty familiar. It's
just the idea that one player is mechanically making another player more powerful. And as
they are doing that, it's creating this kind of back and forth movement between the team
being sort of unbalanced in a way.
the buffer is probably rendered vulnerable by this and the buffy becomes very overpowered.
One thing that's interesting is that it can be implemented in a way that's either passive
or intentional. Passive in the sense that as long as you stay close to me, you'll be
tougher or less visible. Or it can be intentional in that I actually have to target my teammate.
The benefits are almost always conditional and usually temporary in order to avoid a
permanent unbalance. And it's entirely voluntary. Players can opt in or not opt in to this.
An interesting approach to this on a game that's nominally pretty realistic would be
in the Army of Two series, the aggro system, which literally allows one player to buff
the stealthiness and the invisibility of his teammate just by standing up and making a
bigger target of themselves. And this is a system that's actually grafted above and beyond
the normal behavior of the AI, accompanied by a bunch of signs and feedback in the HUD
and in the game. Now, we had a buffing system in Splinter Cell
Conviction Co-op.
And people definitely used it.
However, if we're being honest with ourselves, we probably
have to admit that a lot of them didn't realize that they
were using it.
We had the mark and execute system, which was developed
for single player, which enabled the player to pre-mark
targets and then, under certain conditions, take them
all out in one attack to sort of enforce that idea that
you're the elite spy who's a crack shot and you're able to
do this.
In co-op, what we allowed players to do was jump in on
each other's executes if they shared.
line of sight on any targets, but also if any other marks were available nearby, so
that we could essentially extend and boost the range of the area of effect of the mark
and execute. And it was a great system, and people definitely were using it, but when
quizzed about it afterwards, a lot of them weren't even aware that they were using it.
So, fail. Asymmetric abilities are, I think, a pretty straightforward notion to people
who played, for example, rock band style games, games that are supporting.
different sets of abilities for the characters, and we're talking specifically about the characters
in this case. The idea being that the group is constantly moving back and forth between
conditions of being sort of overwhelmed by the challenges of the game or overpowered
just as they sort of reconfigure themselves to tackle those challenges in the right way.
It could be an entirely built out orthogonal class system like you might see in an RPG
game.
Or it could be the consequence of a customization system, players spending experience points
in order to specialize, in order to give themselves unique abilities.
But the one common assumption here is that no one player is going to be able to max out
everything, right?
They can't just turn themselves into a super generalist.
But what's interesting is that players are still free to progress with their own limited
subset of those character abilities.
They can try it, and in some cases they can succeed at it.
It's just that all of those complementary advantages and disadvantages tend to lend
themselves in a fairly obvious way to the players to working together for mutual support.
Borderlands is a game recently that I think has done a very good job of this because at
the start of the game, while we have different stats, the different characters have different
stats, nevertheless they do share a kind of core set of mechanics that they can kind of
learn to use at the same time.
And after about an hour of leveling up.
they are able to unlock their unique abilities and then become very powerfully motivated
to explore those unique abilities even while they've retained their understanding of the
core systems.
The fact of the matter is that on Splinter Cell Conviction, we didn't explore this particular
dynamic very much.
The both of the players, in spite of the fact that one of them is supposed to be an American
Splinter Cell, the other one is supposed to be a Russian Voron agent, have identical abilities,
identical movesets, they use the same animation, the same fighting ability, they just look
different and sound different when they talk.
So the onus was entirely on the player to use the PEC challenge points in order to customize
their weapons loadouts to give themselves either armor or more weapon ammo capacity
or gadget capacity. And the sad reality is that most players didn't explore that system
very much at all.
So next is combined actions. Now, combined actions on first blush is going to sound a
little bit like asymmetric abilities. It's the notion that there are different...
player skills that are implicated in the gameplay and that players need to understand that no
one player is going to be able to tackle those challenges by themselves, or at least it's
going to be very, very difficult for them to do it.
And the key here is just that players are able to recognize the nature of the challenge,
break it down into its individual component challenges, and then divvy up.
or delegate those roles between them, at which point it becomes almost a formality. Now,
this hinges on an idea. It's pretty simple, but it does merit some explanation. So the
notion that any game challenge that we describe can be defined by the specific player skills,
not the character abilities, but the player skills that are required in order to overcome
it. Now, here's a list of player skills, precision, timing, measurement in the sort of analog
input sense.
resource management, tactical choices, strategic choices, puzzle play.
This might be a complete list, but I'm not going to stand up here and debate whether
it should be like eight more things or five fewer things or whatever.
I mean, the point is that if we accept the notion that there are skills and that the
skills are implicated by discrete gameplay challenges, then it's possible for us as designers
to ensure that the tempo of those challenges is just always beyond the comfort zone of
any one player.
At which point, it's up to the players.
to identify what those compound challenges are,
agree amongst themselves as to who's going to take on what,
and then at that point, it becomes a rather enjoyable
process of overcoming it.
Red Dead Redemption and the Outlast to the End co-op
does a very good job of this, actually.
The specific example I'll use of I'm driving the horse-drawn
stagecoach, so I'm having to engage in precision and timing
in terms of controlling the horses,
a certain amount of analog measurement in terms of my speed.
at the same time that my buddy who's riding shotgun is having to use precision to line
up targets with the crosshairs, is having to make tactical choices about which of the
bandits to shoot in which order. This is almost a classic example of how combined actions
would work in order to help promote cooperation. In Splinter Cell, I mean, we call ourselves
a stealth action game, and in co-op it was a mandate on the level design side to try
to support multiple styles of play.
players being able to use action, being able to use stealth, being able to use gadgets
in order to make their way through it. The reality is that an awful lot of the skills
associated with those different styles of play are the same skills. They differ maybe
by one or two skills in a couple different areas. But we didn't really fully explore
or take advantage of this approach. But it's definitely something that we could.
The last dynamic I'm going to talk about is one that I think is probably familiar to people
who have played a lot of the bullet hell style shooter games.
its notion of survival and attrition. And as a dynamic, it really is a kind of oscillation
in terms of player motive. So it's almost at the level of metagame. It's the notion
that play can continue for as long as there is at least one player alive, which is essentially
saying you can be a hero, but you can also be dead.
many players are possible, or many survivors are possible. In fact, all the players could
survive until the very, very end. But if you die, you're out for the round. You're going
to be waiting for however long the round lasts until your friends are done and you get to
listen to them laughing and screaming and yelling and enjoying themselves. What's interesting
about this dynamic is that it makes survival itself a kind of victory. It just makes it
kind of a slightly lower tier victory.
At the end of the day, there can really only be one most valuable player.
And that pressure to say, well, I've survived the last few levels, I'd really like to be
the hero, I'd like to be the MVP, means that players will, over time, tend to stick their
neck out.
They'll weigh the risks and the rewards and they'll give it a shot.
And some of them will do it, and they'll be the hero, and some of them will die, and then
the next round they'll probably play a bit more conservatively.
This particular dynamic lens itself.
really, really well to sort of the squad military style game, because that whole aesthetic,
the whole conceit of we're a military unit, we have certain mission objectives we need
to achieve, but at the same time, you know, we have to keep the squad alive, we leave
no man behind, this kind of concept works very well with this dynamic. And the recent
Ghost Recon games, Grawl 1 and Grawl 2, did a very good job of leveraging this approach.
Now, I can say with absolute certainty, we did not use this dynamic in Splinter Cell
Conviction co-op at all. Because in Splinter Cell Conviction, when one player dies, it's
game over for both sides. Now in our case, I think it was the right choice, because it
fit the fantasy of the two covert agents placed in harm's way, unable to be able to complete
the mission unless both players are able to do it. So it fit, and it wouldn't necessarily
have made sense for us. Although, something we would explore.
Okay, so those are the seven dynamics. And I'm going to just go through some of the lessons
that we learned on conviction as a result of seeing how these things worked in practice.
The first thing that we found is that more players in co-op were tending to use the mark
and execute system intentionally than they were in single player. Why? Because we let
them share marks. We let the players mark individual targets on their own.
and then we let either of the players execute on those marks.
Now initially, players would mark targets because it was a great way to communicate
with each other. It was a great way to say, oh, hey, there's a guy over there. He just
walked around that, oh, there, okay, there he is. And then that created an opportunity
as players were earning execute tokens for each other by taking enemies out hand to hand
for the players to use, mark, and execute in exactly the way we designed it.
Next, and this gets back to what I started to mention before.
we got real drama, like real, the sort of true archetypal water cooler moment
out of the interaction between our punitive systems.
Because it was possible for a player to be wounded
and to be immobilized on the ground bleeding to death,
to have their teammate come rushing to their rescue,
and to be within steps of reaching them
and then get grabbed by another enemy in a chokehold.
At which point, the player on the ground...
was able to draw a sidearm.
They could scream at each other over their mics,
duck, duck now, duck.
And the guy would duck and say, take the shot,
take the shot, exactly like we've
seen in every movie 100 times over.
Pop them in a headshot with both of their health bars
shrinking as the whole thing's going on.
And then the freed teammate would race to his friend's aid
and rescue him at the last second.
We knew it was possible when we were designing the system,
but we thought, eh, it's probably kind of an edge case.
We'll be lucky if we see it once in a while.
Happened in our first playtest.
It was honestly probably the most ecstatic moment I've ever had as a game designer.
And here we had these players who up until that point had been playing a pretty, to be
blunt, shitty, mediocre build of a game.
Struggling with all the different problems that we were having with the controls at that
moment.
Didn't know each other, because they were just guys we pulled into the playtest.
Suddenly they're like high-fiving each other, and, you know, they're best friends.
It's good stuff.
The fact is, while they were useful and they helped us to, in a very pre-planned way, author
moments that fit the spy fantasy, the fact is, exotic gameplay moments and exotic challenges
did have the effect of exposing limits on the interactivity of the player.
Because up till that point, the players using core gameplay mechanics.
is in the groove, is developing a kind of familiarity, that kind of literacy that we
talked about, the ability to optimize the outputs of the game, the ability to cooperate
with each other and communicate with each other, and then all of a sudden we're imposing
a very specific constraint on their action. It's still a tool, it's still a useful tool,
but we need to be aware of the fact that it's a big sort of screech in the flow of social
interaction in the course of the co-op game.
Something that we realized, and this wasn't really a big surprise, because it's also true
in single-player games to a large extent, is that high-level plot is never going to
be as important as the kind of low-level interactions that we support between characters, and in
our case, between players.
In our case, we were able to exploit that.
We built a lot of the dialogue between our two-player characters around systemic output.
So in other words, when certain kinds of gameplay...
outputs would occur. The two characters would acknowledge it, they would share a bit of
dialogue, and we allowed the nature of that dialogue to evolve over the course of the
whole game. So that these two characters who, in the plot, aren't supposed to like each
other at the beginning of the game, are kind of slowly beginning to respect each other.
And this is reflected in their systemic barks in their gameplay dialogue. Players appreciated
this. In fact, it's the only thing they talked about when it came to story.
when we read the forums. They'd long since forgotten what the plot was, something about
EMPs and Russia and mobsters and things. But they talked a lot about Archer and Kestrel
and the fact that these guys didn't really like each other, but they seemed like they
were buddies and then, well, I'm not going to spoil the ending.
So just to kind of go over some generalized best practices in order to wrap up, I think
the first thing is, if you don't have to...
Try not to pour production values into highly prescriptive systems.
Alright? You're not fooling your players.
If you stick an invisible collision or a glowing wall or whatever it is,
your players will understand what it is.
They'll realize what you've done and they'll understand that you had a reason for doing it.
They might not like it, but they'll move on.
If you attempt to make it look as though everything is normal and okay,
then they are going to bump into that collision in a more painful way because they will be
trying to use their collective agency. They'll be talking to each other. Wait, no, maybe
we need to go around to the left. Okay, you try going to the right. Okay, see if you hit
that. Okay. No, actually, no, you're just not allowed to do that. So better to go the
gamey route and embrace it and have them deal with it than to try to convince them something
else is happening. Whether or not you agree with any of the dynamics that I've described,
just please, my appeal to you is give the players tools for mutual support. You can
find your own language for it. You can find your own way of doing it. But that's really
the key here. This is what matters. Recognize that when you have more than one player in
the environment, that generates noise. It generates all kinds of noise. It generates
the actual noise of multiple players' characters moving around in the game space. So the sensory
noise. It generates a system's noise.
of multiple players perturbing the system, the AI, and all these other things in lots
of different ways that make the environment more chaotic. And you have the social noise
of these two people who might be sitting on a couch or might be talking over their microphones
distracting each other. So when you're designing the ingredients at the level of kind of aesthetic
level of level design, focus on readability, on the legibility of those ingredients first,
then make it pretty. To give you a good example of this.
on conviction in the single-player maps, which were beautiful. Lighting was initially done
as a kind of an art pass. Basically, the lighting fit the logic, the architecture, the intentions,
the mood of those maps, and it was beautiful. And once it was beautiful, then after multiple
iterations, looking at heat map results, all this other stuff, the team was able to go
in and tweak and adjust the lighting to work well with the AI's detection model. In the
case of co-op...
we had to do it 180 degrees in the opposite direction.
We built, our lighting was giant circles of light,
like you'd see in a Bugs Bunny cartoon.
And we would sort of string these circles of light
to create our shadow paths.
And once we knew that we had enough of a shadow path
to accommodate more than one player,
then we'd do a pass to try to substitute
those light sources with something
maybe it felt a little more logical.
And then we would go through and do these iterative passes
to make it more discreet and more subtle,
and have it look a little bit nicer.
And the message there is, players will forgive that.
Even if they were to do a side-by-side comparison
and go, woo, geez, man, co-op lighting
looks a little old school.
It's OK.
They're more interested in having the ability
to do what they want to do than they are
in whether the lighting pass was done exactly the same way
between single player and co-op.
Finally, and this is sort of the high level takeaway, I guess,
is you need to trust that your players will find a way.
they will, if you let them work together and if you give them a good reason to,
they will find interesting solutions to the gameplay challenges that you present them with
that maybe you wouldn't have anticipated.
So, after everything else I've said, at the same time,
don't freak out, don't feel like you need to control the player experience
for these two people or three people or four people.
Their numbers will give them the added collective intelligence to tackle these problems.
Now there's some things that I think would merit further investigation.
They're outside of the scope of this talk.
They were almost within the scope of this talk until I realized that it would be a two-hour-long talk.
I think we've talked about dynamic solutions that are meant to be relatively accessible to lots of different types of games,
but it would be an interesting discussion to see how specific aesthetic directions,
specific level design solutions could also help make a particular game type.
more conducive to mutual cooperation and meaningful cooperation.
There's an entire discussion about how we can use presentation design. In other words,
the HUD system, cues and prompts and visual signs and feedback inside the game environment
in order to give players a stronger sense as to situations where they can cooperate
or where cooperation might be a good idea.
And then I think there's an entire talk or two on the subject of tools for communication
and coordination, which is really communication coordination being something entirely distinct
from just straight collaborative working together to solve problems, but it feeds into this
and there's so many dependencies here that there would be an entire discussion on it.
So these are all topics that I encourage any of you who are involved in the development
of co-op games to think about.
and maybe offer suggestions on, but it's a GDC talk for at least a few people in this
room if you want to give it a shot. And that's where I'll end it. So I'll start taking questions.
We have two mics. There you go.
in the neighborhoods and taking care of the lawns nice.
But at some point, they get competitive about this.
Like, mobile is a big part of the solution.
Is there a role for cooperating or competitiveness
with the agent cooperation in terms of ways of thinking about
these other platforms.
Will you ever have a meeting?
Um, yes, absolutely.
The, the...
It's funny you say that. So, coopetition, which is the horrible portmanteau that we use for this,
is absolutely, has a role in probably the majority of cooperative games.
Because at some point, when you reach that level of mastery,
where there's so much shorthand and these strong social links are allowing players to use shared intentionality,
and na-na-na-na-na-na-na, you start to want more.
And what's fascinating about that is, we can either, again, throw that entirely
to the player's discretion and just try to seed the world and seed the game system space
with lots of opportunities for one player to kind of elbow aside his fellow citizens
in his own pursuit of his own glory. Or we could do it in a really deliberate and intentional
way. My suspicion is the more deliberately and intentionally we try to support co-opetition,
the more we'll screw it up. But the long and short of it is I absolutely think there's
a role for that. I mean, I think there was clearly evidence of it in Splinter Cell.
and I think probably we would love it if we could support that even better than we did.
And how do you avoid the player from becoming a co-op?
kind of punish that is going to fail badly. It's just simply going to degrade the experience
for everybody. So there's a certain amount of this that just needs to be self-policed.
It needs to be people trying to act somewhat like civilized human beings, although that's
always a tall order online. But the other aspect to it is just that we need to bear
in mind that co-op is often the easiest way for a new player to get into a game. So when
we're designing our co-op modes, whoops, co-op modes, we need to be thinking about that.
It's, there is often a temptation to think that, oh, well, because it's multiplayer,
it must be more hardcore, right?
But maybe we don't need to think of it that way.
Maybe what we ought to be trying to do is imagine that it's the perfect opportunity
for an experienced player to kind of help bring up the speed, a less experienced player
help them level up a bit faster, kind of twink them along a little bit, so that then they're
able to get into playing single player and really get to know the system.
I don't know how to change human nature, but I do know that maybe we as developers need
to be careful that we're not deliberately making our co-op modes the more hardcore mode.
That would be my solution.
Yeah.
Right.
It's a super good question.
I mean, we had local co-op on Conviction.
We had split screen, for example.
And we felt like it was super important to support it.
I think the main issue, there's a number of usability issues
that come about when you're sharing
the same kind of screen real estate, which is, again,
outside of the scope of this.
But I think, again, that almost is the perfect example
of where you have two players who are co-located.
They're geographically sitting on the couch with each other.
or at least in two different rooms if they're playing over SysLink or something like that.
But presumably they know each other, right?
They're talking to each other in like meatspace.
They're not on their microphones. They're like throwing beer cans at each other and all this kind of stuff.
So in a sense, that's a classic set of conditions in which
the player in a sense is able to supply most of what's needed in order to facilitate the communication.
The shared intentionality has spilled out of the game and into the real world,
into the living room or wherever.
So that they're able to kind of do that negotiated action
In a way that's very human and you know ancient so to a certain extent
That's an example where we almost don't want to intervene because they're gonna figure it out on their own
I know it probably sounds like that's my answer to everything is just don't intervene, but
But in this case, it's true.
It's like it's much harder for us
to negotiate these things with online play,
because we just don't know what the conditions are.
I mean, you might have a guy in Lithuania
playing with a guy in Buenos Aires.
They literally have no common framework
in which to speak to each other.
And one guy's been up since 3 a.m.
and the other guy's just woken up.
So it's, I mean, those are the hard problems
for us to solve in terms of social interaction.
Thanks.
Right.
So I think, I mean, for me, when I'm using the term exotic challenges and exotic moments,
I'm really talking about situations in which we have fundamentally altered.
the sort of interaction space of one or more of the players.
Like, we've changed their camera, we've changed their controls,
we've changed the way they move, we maybe even have altered their perspective completely.
So, the situation you're describing, where maybe one pl- the players have been forcibly separated,
you know, one guy's fallen into the pit and is now fighting the Sarlacc,
while, you know, so-and-so is trying to, whatever, call in an airstrike,
um, I mean, those, those...
what you're describing are situations where players still have access to their core game mechanics.
and to the normal level of agency that they do in the game world.
They're just, they've just been confronted by a level design constraint
that causes them to be separated.
Now in those situations, I think that, you know, that creates some interesting variety.
I wouldn't want to abuse that.
I wouldn't want to force players to go through that more than, for more than maybe 5 or 10 minutes
before they get back together.
But I think that sort of situation works out rather well.
I'm talking about situations where...
you're the first guy to hit the trigger,
and so now all of a sudden,
you're the one that's flying the biplane around
and you can't do any of the things you normally would do
and you're vulnerable and you're, you know.
Those are the situations that I think
we need to use sparingly,
or at the very least,
understand that players will recognize
that it's imposing some kind of limit on them.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, no, really, really good point and I don't know if you noticed like for combined
action.
Yeah, I had my screenshot from StarCraft 2, that was like my token RTS moment, I didn't even talk about.
But, but you're, no, you're correct. In fact, I mean, I find it actually weirdly, like, sports games and RTS are like, it's like these two sort of subgenres of game that we in everywhere, in everywhere else land often fail to look to in order to find lessons.
But you're right, we absolutely looked at that. And actually, I'd say that, that over the course of the last few games I have worked on, and dot dot dot...
We have spent more time paying attention to real-time strategy for the lessons that we can we can extract from it
And and yeah, it's it's true like I think
You know I think for like combined action in Stargate or Starcraft 2 is a perfect example of this right
It's the that kind of ability to share resources as you know in a kind of intentional way that that I'd say
Is perfectly exemplified by that
Thank you
Yeah. Yes. Yes, absolutely.
Yeah. Oh, I see. I mean, I mean, okay, now you're getting into stuff that's under the
hood that the players maybe either don't perceive or aren't sure about.
It's interesting, we've had people ask us,
oh hey, so if one guy's fallen,
does that mean you're more likely
to get grabbed in a chokehold?
The answer is no.
I mean, the only way in which it's more likely
is that the second player is running to get to his friend,
so he's automatically being not as careful,
not as conservative in his movement,
and he's heading straight for the place
where there was enemy activity.
it really is an emergent outcome of those two systems.
And we didn't have to do anything to monkey wrench it,
and I probably would be very, very cautious,
well, as no big surprise there,
I don't think we should intervene.
I wouldn't probably try to force the issue.
What I think is interesting, though,
it's a more interesting challenge is,
can we come up with like a third system
that fits in perfectly
in a kind of rock, paper, scissors way with those two?
That's a tougher problem.
But you're right, it does seem like it gives us
a more organic moment
that players really feel ownership of.
And I think I'm getting the eyeball from everybody.
Okay, yeah, last question.
Going back to the Capture 12 versus SolarWinds...
Yeah?
...are there systems that you provide
that only do one or the other,
or that are not really...
...succession-ready?
I mean...
anything which depends on incomplete information for one player or the other is probably not
going to be very effective in split-screen or couch co-op. But I mean, I would have to
look at the whole list and probably do a, kind of build a matrix for it, but yeah, yes,
yes, for sure. Cool. I think that's it. Thank you very much, everybody.