Hello, this is Marcin Przybyłowicz, music director at CD Projekt Red.
And I'm Piti Adamczyk, senior composer at CD Projekt Red.
And this is Immersing with Music, Approaches to Musical Storytelling in Cyberpunk 2077.
We have to do this one virtually, but hopefully next year we're going to hang out with you guys.
Now let's jump into our presentation.
So, first of all, spoiler alert. And now, without further ado, let's jump right into it.
So as we speak to a group of audio professionals and game developers,
you are all probably familiar with the term immersion.
For those who are not, immersion, according to the Cambridge Dictionary,
is the fact of being completely lost in something.
Now, you know, why would we even want to have that?
In our book, immersion is engagement, and engagement is fun.
It makes combat more exciting if the player cares
about the character.
It makes story more intriguing if the choices
and consequences that the player makes
resemble some sort of reality.
And it makes exploration more intriguing
if the player's curiosity is fed back
by the design of the world.
And this concept is not a new concept.
It has been known since Aristotle, through Shakespeare and Tolkien,
that in order to truly appreciate a work of art,
you have to either suspense disbelief
or create secondary belief in the presented reality.
Now, how we try to immerse players in Night City.
In Cyberpunk, we were dealing with four different types of music.
We had original score, we had source cues and diegetic music,
we had radio tracks, and media music.
Now we would like to talk about each of those groups,
how they all fit together,
and what challenges and possibilities they presented.
I give the floor to Marcin.
So, first of all, how Cyberpunk sounds.
The most important question we had to ask ourselves.
There are already several examples of what people have been considering as cyberpunk sound for years in movies, video games and music in general.
We knew we wanted to find our own recipe, to have our own take on how cyberpunk music can sound.
Also, the IP itself pushed us to explore new territories.
Our game is an adaptation of pen and paper cyberpunk 2020 after all,
and it draws heavily from the world Mike Pondsmith has created.
Night City is a fast, overstimulated and dangerous place.
Also, the story.
It's not a one-dimensional journey
focusing only on metaphysical elements
or any other for that matter.
It touches on several tropes of the genre,
so it's obvious music needs to answer that call
and fit the world, narrative arc,
character development, and so on.
Okay, so what to do?
Our way out was pretty simple.
Let's ditch the 80s and go with 90s instead.
For us, that 80s sound people are so familiar with
didn't have what it takes to illustrate brutality
and intransigence of Night City.
90s, on the other hand, that's a completely different story
from our own perspective.
We grew up listening to Nine Inch Nails,
Race Against the Machine, The Prodigy, Beastie Boys,
and so on.
Bands representing different musical styles,
but having that attitude in common.
Okay, custom scoring and implementation of quest music.
That was a huge part of our approach
to scoring Cyberpunk 2077.
You know, since Witcher 3, we're aware
that system-driven music or generative music
is not really our forte.
Witcher 3 was notorious for having the music on
all the time, and this time we wanted
to try a different approach
and maybe introduce silence into the mix.
Also, there's a lot of attention given to story and cinematic storytelling at CDPR.
So we wanted our score to feel bespoke, to score the many different possibilities, many
different play-throughs of each quest.
And we wanted to feel that our score supports V throughout her journey.
Also, minimal amount of typical cutscenes.
was a design feature that at first we didn't feel like we have to change our approach that much.
But once you give the control of the camera to the player,
and for example you can't see the protagonist's face,
a lot of things change.
Especially mood-wise and pacing-wise, music had to support scenes even more.
So the conclusion for us was simple.
We have to spot and score every main quest
and every side quest with custom assets.
And that was a huge undertaking
for a game the size of Cyberpunk,
but having two in-house composers capable
of producing assets and implementing them,
and having Paul Leonard Morgan as our outsource composer,
it felt doable.
And in exchange, we got a lot of control
over the playback of the cues.
And our unwritten motto became, if a player
hears a piece of music in the game,
it was hand placed there for a reason.
And whether it's score or cutscene,
or whether it's score or source cues, or diegetic music,
or radio tracks, whatever, we wanted
to make sure that the cue that's audible for the player
is the one that we intended it to be.
We started the gargantuan task by spotting the whole game.
And here you can see a bird's eye view
on our spotting document.
We would get videos from QAs,
and based on those videos,
we would prepare the first set of assets.
Then we would implement them, playtest them,
and if we maybe missed something or the design changed,
we would then reiterate on those assets.
And the list you saw, it could be more detailed,
but each of the line actually represents
like a whole family of cues
rather than just one piece of music.
And to further illustrate how we divided those scenes,
I would like to play you two examples.
This one is the scene where the relationship
between Johnny Silverhand and Vegas established.
This is sort of their first of many quarrels,
and I would like to play you this one
to show you our approach to narrative scenes.
Need a smoke.
Where'd you stash yours?
So this scene starts with a fairly soft, moody, dark drone,
and it's played on a loop.
Where did you even come from?
How are we even talking?
How the fuck should I know?
Now we introduce a one-shot cue.
The fuck kind of droid toy are you supposed to be?
That's playing Johnny Silverhand's theme
in a very transgressive, weird way.
Who you work for?
Start talking.
Fuck.
And because of the design of the scene,
This cue has a very long tail.
And when we cut to black,
we actually play one more cue on top
of the already playing one on a different stance.
The reason behind it is we wanted to time
the end of this cue with the cut to black.
I'll take control.
I'll find a way.
You hear me?
Now we play another cue, which is again a fairly soft drone.
It's to kind of keep the tension up.
But also try to sell the idea that the scene is over, but it's actually not.
Here we start another loop.
See you never, asshole.
And that loop will play till the end of the scene.
Another scene I would like to play you is from one of the Nomad quests,
and here V is becoming one of the Aldecaldos.
And a similar approach was taken.
We divided the scenes into many different segments,
and whenever a player is in control of the action,
we basically loop the piece of music.
And when there is a more scripted segment...
the approach is more free.
So the first cue starts when V gets on the truck.
And the music that is playing is a version of Pan Am's theme.
which means this family will go to hell and back.
Now this kid is actually a one-shot kid.
Do your worst.
And if you take your time answering Sol,
you're an Aldecaldo, Kevin.
It will actually fade to silence.
Great to have you with us, V.
Which may seem weird,
but it actually adds a pretty cool tension to the scene.
Welcome to the family.
But now we reintroduce Panem's theme here.
That's what they say.
Easier to gain a cobra's trust than an Aldecaldo's.
So I know how much this means.
Do you, to me, think...
And now we play a segment that's also looped.
And actually this segment comes off one of the tracks
that a Nomad guitar player was playing in some other quest.
...as Bobby tells it, and I won't even mention Pan Am.
Go to hell.
Saul's right, though.
I mean, let's face it, V, my life was in a million pieces.
You broke it into him, though.
But sometimes it's only then that you can piece it together again.
Now the sound effects here are actually done by our sound department.
And they are sort of underscoring the fact that this disease is developing.
It's, you know, it's almost...
Like, V is dying.
When she gets down from the truck,
we introduce a subtle drone
to also support the fact that, you know,
her disease is developing.
And here once again we reintroduce Panem's theme, this time in a very subtle way, to
help support the dialogue and help this scene and the description of the scene sell the
idea that Panem and V are now very close friends.
Themes were the glue we used to illustrate narrative arc.
Our goal was to take the advantage of the first-person perspective
and find the way it immerses players into the storyline.
Even in the early stages of development, the game, even with no music whatsoever, felt already very cinematic.
After a few months of experiments, we've ended up with a number of themes.
Short, flexible motifs that can be easily adapted to narrative arc and serve their purpose in a number of ways.
Also, their short duration nicely corresponded with the genre choices we've made regarding overall musical direction.
We've ended up with two main themes and a few secondary themes.
V and Johnny's themes, our main motifs.
And several secondary themes, illustrating Arasaka, obviously,
but also transgression theme, which is a big part of the storyline, death,
and a number of smaller themes or riffs or patterns
tied to specific locations, gangs, and so on.
I'd like to present now an example of how we've been using our themes throughout the whole game.
We're gonna listen to V's theme and a few of its variations from various parts of the storyline.
That's a main menu cue.
First thing players hear when they launch the game.
So the music doesn't waste much time
and within two and a half minutes of duration,
the music presents the general vibe, emotional palette
and some punch in B part we are listening to right now.
This cue plays when Johnny manifests his presence
for the first time.
V, it's important you get all this.
You'll fix me up, right? Vic?
If I could, I would, V. Believe me.
But this is... it's way beyond what I know how to do.
You're the best of the best, Vic. Why can't you help me?
This one plays during Tapeworm quest, which is stretched over the length of several other quests.
Not having control.
You can't stand it.
Seeing some things are out of your hands.
Don't be ridiculous, V.
Cyberspace, near end of the game,
where the player has to decide
who's gonna take control over V's body, V or Johnny.
On V's behalf, thanks.
As for V, I'm sorry.
And finally, one of the endings.
Back to you, PT.
Open world music using a wider brush.
So we scored all quests, all side quests,
and we were ready to congratulate each other
and high five because we delivered all quests way
before the deadline.
And then we got feedback from one
of our designers who spent most of their time
in the open world asking us why there's
no music in the game.
Well, it turned out we were so focused on scoring quests and V-Story,
that we kind of underestimated the amount of gameplay we need to cover with our score.
We initially thought that street noise, that, you know, media music and radio tracks
will create enough of audio distraction that exploration music would be superfluous.
Also one more comment that we got was that combat felt underwhelming.
Compared to scripted quest events, not having music and combat encounters in the open world
kind of feel lame.
And we tried a few different things like placing radio emitters with source music next to possible
combat encounters, but it all just didn't feel right.
So...
Our solution to that was produce even more assets.
And we had to be smart about it.
We didn't have the time to basically write everything
from scratch.
And that would be impossible.
That wouldn't be practical.
But we also didn't want open world content
to feel less polished than.
quest events or side quests.
So we once again went back to our spotting document
and we diligently went through all minor quests
and all street stories and we identified their needs.
For more narrative moments or dialogues,
we music edited already existing cues,
especially the ones that didn't have
one of the already established themes.
And here, once again, you can check the bird's-eye view on our spotting document.
This is all the mine requests, and this is all the street stories.
So, for each of the in-game factions, we had to produce a specific combat music group.
We called them combos.
And every single faction got one combo.
Some of them were already produced for quests or side quests,
but ones like Valentino's or Sixth Street had to be written from scratch.
Each set consisted of stealth, alerted, and combat state.
It was mostly driven by AI, but it was also frequently triggered from quests.
For example, when a combat started, when an alarm goes off,
it would be weird to start with stealth, so we would start with alerted then.
And we tried adding more states to combat,
but again, it kind of got in the way of the groove
and just didn't seem right.
And as you can see, we kind of prefer horizontal interactivity over vertical one.
There's various reasons for that, but I think the main one is the type of music we're producing
doesn't really work well with vertical interactivity, because what you would
really want to have is a track that's compressed, that's well produced and put together,
because then you really get the kind of energy we're looking for.
Now I'd like to play you an example of the combo for Valentinos.
So we start with combat.
We go to stealth for a brief moment.
This is what alerted sounded like.
Back to combat.
So we had combat encounters covered,
but there was still a question of what we're going to do
with exploration ambiences.
So again, we had to be smart about it and cover a lot of gameplay.
So the technique we used, we decided to take stems from already existing cues,
record them back to cassette tapes at half speed,
and then play them back through a 4-track cassette recorder
with delay and reverb, tweaking some EQs and playing even more with the varispeed control.
and recorded them as stereo tracks into the DAW,
and did very little post-processing after that.
And that technique felt right for the world.
It also felt right for the fact that we
were trying to evoke the 90s as much as possible,
so that tape hiss added an extra level of 90s into the project.
And also, thanks to that technique,
we were able to produce a lot of assets, over one hour of assets.
Yeah.
in one day. So it was a great technique and also those ambiences weren't that
interactive. They were basically just kind of playing in the background. So it
all seemed to work and I'd like to play you an example of what it sounded like.
And the way all those types of music fitted together is we had a fairly simple yet powerful bussing system created and...
The quest music was the most important music, so it would basically block any other music that was trying to play.
Then, the next level of importance was combat music, which would mute car radio or radio that was pumped through speakers on the level.
And in those two, car radio was more important for us, so it would mute all the radio emitters.
And the ambiences were the very bottom of this chart right here.
And it was basically played only outdoors and only if there was no other music playing around the player.
So all those things combined as exploration ambiences,
the reuse and music editing of existing cues
and combat music design was a compromise
between our handcrafted approach and a more systemic one.
So source music or diegetic music
played an important role in Cyberpunk.
It was not only treated as some kind of audio fluff,
but we tried to use it narratively.
And what it gave us is that it broader our stylistic net
or emotional net.
And also one more thing that it created
an interesting musical fourth wall breaker,
which I'll talk about in a minute.
This scene is a pretty important scene.
This happens right after Jackie dies in the prologue,
and you're trying to honor him during an ofrenda.
And...
We could have scored this scene maybe with V's theme or the cue that we used when Jackie actually died,
but we decided to go with Source Cue and basically score this scene with that score screen.
It's just me playing the guitar.
And you could see that it makes the scene special.
It's not, you know, yet another scene when you have some synthy drone playing around.
It actually creates an interesting lore building, because we don't really say what this track is.
Maybe this track is Jackie's favorite tune.
So there's actually also a bit of exploring to be done on the player's side here.
Okay, on occasion, source music was actually played in 2D
from the same sort of virtual emitter
that the score is played through.
And once again, it added variety,
it prevented us from using the same cues too many times.
And most importantly, in this particular moment,
it's actually cued by one of our made up bands,
Tainted Overlord, so it kind of fits well
with the Nomad vibe and with the overall lore of the world.
And this cue happens right after you rescue Sol in one of the side quests.
So we found that breaking the musical fourth wall added variety and extra level of immersion,
but it worked intriguingly well when those both worlds, the diegetic and non-diegetic,
were actually played together at the same time.
This is an example of how we did that in one of the early quests in the prologue.
If you choose to take the Corpo path, you end up in Liz's bar, and once you get into Liz's bar,
there's a Source team playing, which is actually created by GazelleTwin for us.
And once the Arasaka guys come to V, we introduce the drone that's played as part of the score,
while we keep the GazelleTwin track playing in the background.
Now there's a subtle but audible filter on the Source Cube.
And we're all in score now.
And as the scene ends, we actually go back to a different Source Cube.
And here's an example also from the prologue,
when you're infiltrating a scavenger's base.
And here we have the scavenger combo,
and on top of that we have,
with the same tempo, same cue signature,
playing a variation of the scavenger's theme
in a very hardcore rave sort of vibe.
But the biggest fourfold breaker was this guy right here,
Johnny Silverhand.
We wanted to introduce Johnny's theme,
and first of all, we wanted Johnny to have a theme
because he was such a prominent character.
And we also wanted to introduce that theme
as one of the Samurai songs.
But we didn't want this to be introduced in Chippin' In
or Never Fade Away.
No, we wanted it to be like a cool B-side, you know?
So we had to create a theme or a motif that was simple,
that could work in many different contexts,
and mostly because it had to work both as a samurai song
and also as part of our score.
And the added difficulty was that at the time of writing,
you know, the story was actually still in development.
Although we knew who Johnny Silverhand is,
and we knew...
you know, how this story will go.
The specifics that would be required
to create a bespoke asset, sort of the assets
I showed you during the custom scoring bit,
that was another difficulty.
So here you can see the very simple rendition of the theme.
This is basically how this motif looks like.
I mean, it looks nothing on the page,
but it was actually surprisingly flexible.
It could score a whole bunch of different scenes.
So this is the first time the theme is introduced.
Johnny is basically once again going to kick Arasaka's ass.
We also used it in an emotional context
when Johnny is talking to Alt.
and it was also part of our combat queues.
Now, we had to drop it from A, because A was the key that most of our score was written in.
We had to drop it to D to really make use of that drop D tuning that Refused is playing in.
And so the whole riff and the whole motif is now in D.
And it became a part of one of the Samurai songs, the ballad.
And I'm going to play you a fragment that's actually the very beginning of the track.
And also there's a development section when the riff in the way I just played you is actually
countered with again the same riff but played in a slightly different rhythm.
But I was once a teaser man
Promises I was made
Were made to keep me asleep
Come on now, I'm kept on a wage
I've come the worst of my rage
One day the...
So it wasn't the only theme that we actually used in our score.
Other Johnny Silverhand songs like Chippin' In or Never Fade Away were also
modulated and reimagined as cues in our score.
For instance, this is Chippin' In.
And this is a rave version of Chippin' In. ♪♪
And also Never Fade Away got a similar treatment. ♪♪
It was used in this way as the ending cue in a lot of the Corpo quests or the epilogue quests for Johnny.
Radio playlists are a big part of Source Music too.
They play primarily in cars and other vehicles as well as in a number of clubs, but also
everywhere else where we felt adding some extra musical layer would improve the scene
or the location.
The main idea behind them was to come up with a variety of genres
citizens of Night City would listen to.
It's a tiny but still important role music has to contribute
into the world building process.
Teenagers, after all, would listen to different music than maelstromers,
hence the presence of pop.
Jazz in 2077 is considered as new classical music
and it's listened to the cultural elite.
Snobs, Corpos and other people.
So, how do you populate 11 playlists with enough songs?
We've commissioned over 150 original or unreleased tracks,
plus we've licensed several jazz pieces recorded in 1970s
by Miles Davis, Thelonious Monk, Chet Baker and other jazz icons.
Why not going with licensed song in general though, for the whole thing?
First of all, our game director, Adam Badowski, didn't want to create any unnecessary connections
between the real world, our world, and the reality of Cyberpunk 2077.
To a degree, he once said to me, it wouldn't make sense to listen to The Prodigy in 2077.
They would be so old, after all.
Second reason is the license eventually expires,
which forces the developers to issue an update to the game,
which removes expired tracks.
We really wanted to make sure playing our game,
even a few years after the release,
will deliver the same experience
and the music will remain unchanged.
We've invited dozens of artists to contribute to the soundtrack.
And to make sure we do not break the immersion of having
2020s artists existing in dystopian futuristic world.
Everyone get their own alter ego.
Lots of bands appear in quests, not only Samurai, but also Kerry Eurodyne,
AskRax, pictured here with V and Kerry, Lizzy Weezy and others.
We took great care to make sure every quest a particular band or artist may be a part of
is suited with the fitting tracks by this artist, not only from the
world-building perspective, but also from a musical point of view.
Retrospective parts of Johnny Silverhand's past as a rogue legend slash terrorist,
Kerry's storyline about his beef with us cracks are just a few examples of that approach.
Of course, since it's an RPG game, V can differently interact with all these musicians,
which results in different outcomes.
So, for example, Kerry finds out there's this band that stole his song.
He wants V to take care of the problem.
It's up to the player, though, to decide how this should be played out.
In the result, it may happen V manages to end the beef between Kerry and us tracks,
and have them work together on a new track together.
The track we obviously would produce.
Okay, so what we've learned throughout the process of scoring Cyberpunk.
So first of all, repetition, repetition, repetition.
In order for teams to work and for players to be able to identify
which motif belongs to which character, you have to repeat them a lot.
But you can't do it haphazardly.
You can't put these themes in every single combat queue.
You have to pick your spots and then go with it.
Also, spotting was key, and identifying the needs of the game.
In order to, you know, try to create the illusion of having a very linear story, we basically
had to custom score and implement everything.
So identifying what you need and what the player is going to hear from scene to scene
was absolutely essential.
Also, performance and interpretation.
In order for the music to come off the page
and actually create an emotional response,
you have to either take your time
or give the right instructions to the players.
And it doesn't matter whether you're using instruments
or synthesizers, performance and interpretation
of the material is absolutely key.
Also, context creates emotions.
you know, don't try to put a hat on a hat.
Sometimes you just have to let the already established
relationships between the characters
kind of speak for themselves.
And not every scene needs a terribly emotional music.
Sometimes you just want these things
to be gently pushed along.
On a more production-related side,
in-house music theme is a pretty cool thing to have.
We can make a lot of music, a lot of assets quickly,
implement them, and kind of take ownership of our work.
And it doesn't matter if it's score or custom source music.
It's a good thing to have.
Also, we still stack at systems and generative music,
but you try to make up for it by producing
a lot of bespoke assets.
And we think we're getting better at it.
One more thing to add is that features like the dynamic 2D, 3D switch or other things
that we talked about shouldn't be gimmicks.
I mean they should be used just in the right spot to be as effective as possible.
And on a final note, be bold and don't be afraid of using music.
Don't mix your music too low.
It can be a great asset.
It can enhance immersion and essentially, and hopefully,
make the game better.
So this is our presentation.
Thank you for being with us.
We hope you've enjoyed it.
And hopefully, see you next year.
And if you want to message us, you can reach us out
on our social media.