Awesome. Hi, everyone. My name is Abby Sherlock.
Greetings from sunny Los Angeles to San Francisco.
This is the Dramaturgy of Video Games,
Theater, Story, and Empathy,
which is a part of the Game Narrative Summit.
So let's get this started.
So talking about why this talk, how did this come to be?
I saw the chat earlier,
saw all the theater kids in our audience sprinkling in.
This kind of came to me when I went to my first E3 back in 2018, and I realized when I was talking to folks at different events, so many folks had been cast or crew in, you know, theater plays in high school, or they did a theater undergrad, or they just really
loved musical theater and they listened to musical theater all the time in their car and we just talked about the shared love of theater so I was like there has to be something there about that connection about game dev to theater pipeline and vice versa.
So previous GDC academic topics on the subject did talk a lot about immersive theater and LARPing,
but not really just two comparing and contrasting of the two different mediums and what they mean
to each other and how they relate to each other. And this was true for my own story and for my own
path. My most recent project was inspired by Tennessee Williams plays taking place in the rural
South United States. And then I actually do a lot of work on camera hosting, which is so much like performing and acting. It's basically the same thing. And that was kind of a grew out of right, I was at an event, I had a broadcast producer who said, Hey, Abby, you can talk go on camera. And I said, Cool. All right, here I am, I guess. And kind of that progression I noticed happens for a lot of other people. And actually, my first professional experience was actually at the La Jolla Playhouse.
uh not in gaming but in theater so as an actor uh kind of again a rundown of why i'm so passionate
about this i've been an actor for more than a decade done shakespeare
Greek tragedy, I'm stage combat certified, can do swords, knives, ow, getting hit, hitting
others, trained at UCLA, Boston University, the American Academy of Dramatic Arts.
So this is really in my blood, I would say at this point for the gaming industry, I've
interned kind of all over Wizards of the Coast, some voiceover stuff, hardware, and then
Nerdist and Geek and Sentry.
Yeah, it's just kind of what I've done in the space, but.
talking about, we're going to refer back to my project Heirloom, which is heavy work with performers and VO.
And I was a game developer on it, but also a producer and the director, right, of those performers.
And it all leads us back to how are these two places tied together, right?
So I argue that empathy in games and empathy in theater
are the only two forms of storytelling that require active, and I mean active, participation
from the audience or the player. So I, again, this is my hot take, right, that video games are the
most highly evolved form of theater. So we're using technology, right, as a conduit of empathy
and storytelling instead of live performance. Again, nothing I'm saying really is new,
but hopefully the framing of it.
can be used in accessible and productive ways
for teams to enrich their stories?
What can we creatively steal from the oldest art form around?
So how is this different from books and film?
We love our books, big, you know, we love reading,
we love movies, but these are very different mediums
and they require different kinds of engagement
with their audience.
So for games, right, the player has to actively
move something in real time.
unless a cut scene and it happens on its own.
But even then, you might have to press something analog
to have something else happen.
But you have to actively move something.
If I wanna go left, I'm gonna take my scroller and go left.
And then with theater, right,
the audience has to watch actively in real time.
So that means I have to, I'm engaged, I'm watching,
and then the performers have to perform actively
in real time, exactly kind of like players too.
And you have to be actively watching in these media
that is changing as you're watching, right?
You cannot stay static.
You have to keep momentum for them.
And you say, how is this different Abby from a book
or a film I watched that and it happens.
So if for the book, if I'm reading a book
and it says the character went left and I'm like
what if they went right instead?
They can do that in a game.
And then in theater, theater metaphor time,
if I'm a performer and I'm giving a joke,
and I notice that the audience reacted differently,
I can change my joke, right, in real time
to give the audience more space for laughter,
or I can go quicker if I need to.
That kind of active, I'm like,
this activeness that's happening is special.
And again, we love our books and we love our movies,
but it's not kind of the same, right?
So the actor within player and performer,
and I'm gonna use, you know, these roles, right,
that the actor portrays character on stage.
That's our theater.
And then games.
the player portrays character on screen. So we both have characters, but we have the medium
being different and the role being different. And I again, argue that they are the exact
same functions really.
and control stream, but they are different mediums.
And again, I use this with, you know,
first person player that I am the character.
I am that character moving on stream.
And then acting, I am that performer.
I, we can talk, you can talk about method later
and I am the character versus portray,
but you are that character, right?
And so when we're talking about empathy,
I broke this kind of down into three factors
that I think really kind of sum up all of these kind of.
similarities between these two worlds. Biggest one, I believe, is empathy. You know, empathy,
the definition being the practice of feeling close to emotionally and personally to someone
other than yourself. And I gave this little quote of, I might watch someone cry at a movie theater
or be moved to tears myself, but I myself am not crying as the character within their specific
situation like I would be.
in games or theater.
And so again, that actor within character
and player within character.
And this is a type of relationship
that I have to emphasize that is rarely able
to be recreated in other mediums.
Again, theater and games, unlike movies and books,
are not static and are active.
And I think this identification process
is never so tightly wound as it is within these two mediums
because I think just the, again,
the activeness of their situations.
lend it to us of identification. And again, for all my D&D players out there where you become the
character or you're a live thing and you become your character, very similar, very similar. And
I use this example here, one of our favorites, Mr. Tom Hiddleston as Hamlet by William Shakespeare.
And then Link, one of our, also one of our favorites from The Legend of Zelda, Skyward Sword.
I use this example of a Wii remote.
and this was the first Skyward Sword came out in the Wii
before the re-release on Switch.
I would use the Wii as the master sword
and I as Link was making those cuts on those enemies.
And then the actor with Tom Hiddleston as Hamlet,
there is that fear, right?
That he's making these cuts and strokes
and we don't know, we hope, right?
Player safety, I'm a stage captain, they're gonna be okay.
We hope our ensemble, everyone,
all the actors are gonna be safe.
But there's that.
you don't know what's gonna happen. It's live theater. Maybe what's gonna happen with the sword.
And that similar kind of what if is also in Legend of Zelda because if I don't put my arm right,
I might die, right? And so that level of I don't know-ness is really important and potent.
And so another factor, we have empathy, now we're talking about catharsis.
So it is a release of emotions for the audience or player.
So emotionally purging oneself is beneficial for humans and innate,
even if you don't know it, what we look for in narratives.
So this goes back all the way to funeral dirges and wailing
within Greek theater laments, where you would just, ah,
you would yell because there was nothing else you could do.
to get that deep emotion out of you, right? And again, it doesn't have to be as dramatic as that,
but we are looking for some sort of release from how our day-to-day lives in our stories.
And so it is, again, I said, hopefully brings resolution, right? We're looking for our stories.
Storytelling was used originally to talk with others, share stories, make sense of natural
phenomenon, but it also asks us to make sense of ourselves and how we operate.
right? And the questions we need to ask ourselves through our stories. And I think this is super
important when you're asking for catharsis within your narrative. What am I looking for? What
catharsis am I looking for within my narrative from as a designer standpoint and then also a
player standpoint? And I give these kind of very broad action verbs to escape, to feel less alone,
to laugh, to cry, to journey, to feel.
But they could be broken down much smaller after that.
But what do you want that player to feel?
What catharsis are you aiming for at the end of that experience?
Like you see here, strong emotional catharsis in both of these,
Ellie in The Last of Us 2 and then The Trojan Woman by Euripides.
Then performance, three.
So we have empathy, catharsis, performance.
Someone in the audience maybe is saying,
I'm not performing, Abby, when I'm eating some chips
and I'm laying on my couch in my living room
playing on my game console.
That's not performance, I'm relaxing.
Okay.
We're gonna reframe it.
So the act of performing on stage
is an actor within character.
And then the act of performing within screen
as player within character.
I always say this as friends with a lot of actors myself,
if they're by themselves in a room and they're monologuing,
they're still an actor and they're still performing,
even if they're by themselves.
So even if you're by yourself,
you're still performing, right? And they both do, both of these mediums require the willing
suspension of disbelief to give into these performances. You enter into an agreement,
right? That I know this world is not real, but I fully will pretend that it is. And I have to greet
it with openness, that I will be affected by what I am seeing in this medium. I will allow myself to
feel, right? And that kind of easiness into that is not always, you know, a given, but.
If you again we want to embrace these things as with openness and our hearts for them to change us as much as possible.
And then I had to add as someone with a marketing background has worked with influencers and talent streamers that game platforms and streamers are performers role playing publicly I shocked that we don't talk about this more like you see with Meg mage
here for cyberpunk 2077 playing.
It's so meta, Twitch, because you have a streamer who is, you know, I am performing for my audience,
for my Twitch chat, and a lot of streamers are also performers, right? And then there are also
this LARPing, this role-playing that's happening within the game, right? So it's a really cool
phenomenon. And then also some lovely performances in theater, you see the great James Earl Jones and
Cecily Tyson.
So cool Abby we've talked about you know how are they similar how they beautifully crossover, give me some practicalities help me out I want to, you know, incorporate more of this with my writing team, I'm a small indie studio and I just want my
creatives to be stronger. How can we use these principles of drama for game developers so job a turgey as world building for game designers.
Then we're going to cover structure, plot, and development.
And then my favorite, probably actor objective work
within game scripts for developing stronger characters.
So dramaturgy is not even in the drama world, I would say, is kind of like in the background, people don't talk about it as much, but it's so cool. I just I it's really neat. Not everyone is always super lucky to have a dramaturge on their staff.
In the past productions I've been in our second assistant director was also the dramaturge so some people can double it up but there are.
programs out there where you can get a, you know, a degree in dramaturgy, but it is its definition, the study of dramatic composition and representation of those main elements on the stage so that that mean your dramaturge is a researcher, right, of your script
in your world so it is adjacent to a writer.
They work a lot with words.
They're basically your lore keeper for all my fellow nerds in the audience.
They keep your lore.
They know what the characters want and their needs and how they operate.
And I'm going to give some examples that if you're in, you know, game design, you could
hire a consultant for.
drama work specializes maybe in that genre that you are working in a theme or have individual people on your staff that maybe have an interest in it or background on theater class to do it if they're interested.
Some examples here with shell games they did an awesome job where they are working on a food.
game, food VR game right and you have different cultures, all different cultures have all
different cool foods, so they reached out to academic masters of their crafts on different
food to kind of serve as dramaturges on that subject for the game.
And then I personally knew much of the staff for how to defend yourself by Liliana Padilla,
which is about.
a group of women learning self-defense on a college campus. And so what Liliana did is had a
bunch of women, since it was about Greek American life, sorority women, ask them questions about,
you know, what is the specific lingo you're using? Why do you have these practices? And those women
kind of acted as dramaturgs, right, to give Liliana the kind of lay of the land of how this
world, right, which she didn't know much about how it operated.
And that made her life writing so much easier, right?
So world building research, and I give these kind of little bullet points you can write down, or just things you can ask yourself right internally when you're writing. So, as a dramaturg would ask themselves all of these, I should know all the rules and
specifics of how this place operates politically, ethnically, socially, culturally, religiously, what are the demographics, what's the history, all those who love backstories, this kind of works in right here.
So metaphysical expressions and specific lingo used in the world.
Word choice is so important. I cannot emphasize that enough. Why people say the words that they say says so much about them and their character. I think of the example of y'all.
I'm originally from South Carolina,
and when I hear someone use the word y'all,
I immediately think, oh, are they from the South?
Where did they learn that?
Do they have a family member?
And it sets you off on a path, right?
And so word choice is important.
When I say that, maybe it tells you a bit about me, right?
And if you're doing your character,
their specific word choice would tell you a bit about them.
So again, why this word choice?
How could that word be used in different situations?
Does it change meaning if it's used in different situations?
And also, does it mean something deeper if the word is used multiple times?
You should know the history and cultural importance of other comparables in the genre.
Knowing what else is out there is going to be so helpful.
And knowing what's already been done, don't remake the wheel.
you know, and seeing what people have done really well.
And then how can we learn from the design of this genre
and other developers?
What are the expectations?
Are your players going to be angry
if you don't have a specific, you know, UI element
that's typical of that?
And there's all these, but for character, right?
You say, are there expectations of how relationships operate?
If we don't give them that,
are they going to be frustrated?
And then again, what these other comparables do well,
what did they not do well?
And I say this with no shade or shame of like,
oh, not good.
But just being self-aware about what you like as a designer
and what you're looking for, I think it's a holistic,
right, you want a holistic viewpoint.
And so second thing we've talked about,
so dramaturgy, narrative structure.
So another technical duty the dramaturg could do
to help the actors or director would be breaking down, usually in a chart or some other graphic
form, is your emotional beats, right? And I personally, someone ADHD, if you can't tell,
love kinesthetic graphs. They're so helpful with sharing with other people,
with your ensemble, with your team, kind of...
your emotional beats. You can write about it and you can talk about it, but when you can show a
graphic of it, it's just really impactful. So you should have a physical copy of the emotional beats
or narrative track in a graph or visual form. Again, this is something a director would know
or a writer would know, and I have this really great game project macro, courtesy of Richard
Lamartian, one of my professors for my project, Heirloom, but you can kind of see here how helpful
this is because we went through every single moment in our script, in our game.
and you charted it out. So your sequence, right? So what is it?
Characters encountered. Who are you meeting?
Your brief description of events happening, the location of where that is,
the player mechanics. So what is the player doing?
But this, I think, is our little golden nugget here is player goal.
So what does the player want in that moment?
music like little arrows in my hand.
And then designer goal.
What do I as a designer want to communicate in that moment?
Right, and they could be different things.
They could be the same thing,
but they could definitely be different things
that they need to be.
But I think the most important is the emotional beat.
What is...
what are all of those elements leading you towards?
They should all be in focus of that.
And that's gonna give you such a high level of control
with your narrative, if you're doing a linear narrative,
that you're just gonna be in such better shape.
And then if you do have scoping issues, right?
Or you're talking about, like, I need this to be shorter.
You can look, right, at your emotional beats
and see, is this in service of, right?
As a creative, we're hopefully in service of our projects
and of.
you know, making them the best that they can be. Is this in service of the project? Is this in
service of the emotional bead that this moment's leading to? You might need to cut then if it's not.
So again, this can take many different forms. A lot of y'all know already the Campbellian
hero's journey or a classic rising action, falling action, just being able to track it
in some kind of physical structure, right? So again, structure of the holistic project.
I should know the writer's journey of the whole experience and be able to map it.
on a visual chart. Where is the beginning, the middle, the end? If it's an on rails narrative,
does this make sense to the player? And when I mean on reels, I mean like
No A, B, C, or D choices.
You just got your one choice and that's it.
You're on the rails narrative, Captain Now.
And then do I know the flow and rhythm of the piece, right?
Does it slow down at certain parts?
Is it too speedy?
What's its pacing?
It needs to be intentional.
If it's really slow and everyone's like, oh my gosh,
like it just keeps going and going,
then you're probably gonna need to cut something, right?
Because your flow and rhythm is gonna tell you a lot
about how playtesting is gonna go too.
And then I have to mention this because I have such respect for branching narratives, but
even harder if it's a branching narrative, the acclaimed open world, but does this make sense
to the player through each separate storyline? I know as a player myself, there is nothing
more frustrating than picking another path.
than maybe the most popular one,
and seeing that it's not as enriching, right?
It's not super impactful as maybe that main path would be.
So how can we as designers make that path less traveled by,
more enriching and valid?
I think it goes back to this emotional beat structure,
where you're gonna need to iron out the emotional beat
of every single path, right?
And that's huge scope,
but it is something if you wanna nail it down,
it's gonna be really powerful.
And even if I said there's an ideal path,
I want as the player to feel like my choice, no matter what, is valid.
So again, really good and difficult narrative design is when you can track
each of these through a branching narrative and they all hit equally.
Right.
So our third thing we're going to talk about is character work.
So.
character work. Often an outside actor will do this. Once you give them a script,
you've written your script, I'll get my script, I'll write it up, mark it up, as you can see in
this lovely example of House Husbands by Heath Thompson. If someone on your team can do this,
or a performance director can, usually they will automatically, it can really help.
I want to clarify when recording when I direct my script is I like analog copies I don't, you know, I just want to feel it in my hand I mark it up it is different colors, lots of writing on it and you're using these tools of after study right to use
game narratives that can make.
characters richer and more thought out.
And a dramaturg usually will also do this,
not, you know, again,
you're not doing the actor's job for them
and you're not doing the director's job for them,
but as writers, right, or as designers,
you are nailing down kind of the exacts of this world.
You're making this, I use a sandbox analogy.
You're using a sandbox.
You're giving them the constraints of the sandbox
so then they can go around and play in it.
But you need to establish what the constraints are,
or you're just gonna be,
I don't know, we're not gonna know where you're playing in it.
So psychological theories and objectives, right?
So I should be able to go through the script
and break up a character's changing objectives
through each scene.
Objectives, objectives are super important after work
because it means, I use the example of hunger.
I was really hungry all when I woke up this morning, my objective was, I would like some food, and then I had some food and then I was not hungry anymore, my objective change.
That's the very simple way of TLDR of using an objective right and so our objectives as humans and as characters.
are ever-changing, right?
So usually I would go through and see
kind of what are my objectives throughout the script.
So, and this is super important,
I would say for character work,
is what is their objective overall?
What's their big grand master plan?
What would they love to have?
What do they see at the pearly gates?
What grounds them, right?
So these are like these big life-searching questions
that are fun, right?
As writers to discover about characters.
And then.
What are they motivated by?
It could be money, love, fame, family, et cetera.
What keeps their engine turning?
What makes them go?
And then this, I think, is almost the most important part
that no one talks about as much is how.
All of character depends on the how.
How do they go about getting their objective?
And we really break this down into action verbs
and theater, which is you use these action
verbs within lines.
I'm going to do an example, but you would have a line
and you would have this, you know, with this line,
I want to do this action verb, which
is how I get my objective.
So if the line was, I want the papers, please.
Let's try that with to entice.
I want the papers, please.
So that was enticing, yeah.
And then we're going to try to punch, OK.
I want the papers, please.
My face changed, your voice changed, audio changed,
everything changed, right?
And so action verbs can be really helpful
if you are small in scope on your team
and you need to direct action verbs.
That's a great way to already like,
get you started on directing.
And then what's the subtext of a line?
You don't need to do this with every line.
Again, like I'm saying,
everything here is just a suggestion,
things to help you out, more tools in your tool belt.
But subtext of lines can be really important
if it's a very...
intentional moment that a lot of hinges on that, maybe that that dialogue.
So what I say versus what I actually mean.
Another example, we have a you're doing a great job, honey, is the script.
So I actually mean it.
You're doing a great job, honey.
Oh, she's so happy. She loves honey. Sweet.
OK, then she does not think honey is doing a great job.
You're doing a great job, honey.
Completely different right we're using different resonators, it's all different so subtext is super super important and fun to work out.
I should know the relationships between characters and why they are the way you are all my writers that they are saying, Oh my god my backstories work.
Yes. You typically would not give your backstory to an actor.
Um, because that would be like a lot of information to like process, but if you have a dramaturge,
that would be great. Or if the actor does have questions, right, and you do have that answer
in your backstory, that could be a good time to say, well, actually, now that you ask,
so it could work out. And then why are they this way, this character this way? Where did they come
from right before the scene started and where are they going? This is so helpful when you're acting
Acting is fantasy, right?
And so this grounds you.
It lets you know, what are the logistics of my reality?
And so knowing again, where, when
is super important for performers.
So examples of performance practices
for some of your game teams you have,
can you hold a read through?
for your script, right?
Where you're gonna read through the script,
but I'm tush, wonder why they named it that.
But there you can do table work.
And even if you don't have professional actors,
please, please, please read it out loud.
I cannot emphasize enough how I think writers are like,
wow, I didn't realize it sounded like that
until you said it.
And so having someone else read your words
as they are on the page.
is going to be so helpful because you can listen and take notes of what feels good
and what's like a little awkward or more like oh that needs to go or like oh that could stay
and so having that is just going to make your process so much easier and again does not have
to be professional actors can be your friends can be your parents can be whoever would like to read
for you and then can you record your talent together if you have voiceover actors please
do this this is so cool um it's helpful for performances and it's really
bonding. And you can see the ensemble building relationships, their performances are more
nuanced because they're listening to each other. And it's really hard, right, when we're remote,
Zoom, but I just did this this past fall where I directed two voice actors in their own booths
and they were listening to each other and we got great performances that were super
intertwined because they just, you know, they could listen to each other
IRL instead of, you know, being in a solitary booth by themselves.
So if you can do this, I know it's hard with scheduling.
I really would recommend it.
So there are some comparables within the space professionally
that I had to mention, right?
This, you know, different, like literally same duties,
different medium of, you know, roles within the industry
that I just think are so similar
or similar duties and different name
of folks who are maybe a little different,
but we kind of do the same function, right?
I think when we recruit from different spaces, we're going to get diversity of experiences, backgrounds, and different sorts of folks.
I was super lucky that my program at USC, I didn't really have a lot of game dev background, right?
I did a lot of marketing and social media, but I didn't have a lot of dev experience.
I had a lot of theater experience, and I feel really lucky.
for that opportunity to be in the space. And I think I would love to see more folks, right,
from theater if they're interested, right, and bring them in. And diversity only makes the games
industry better by having more folks of different intersectionality backgrounds and able to, you
know, give us more feedback and different, like, perspectives on what we need. And so a designer,
a designer should always, you know, have many knowledge, their fingers in many knowledge pools,
right, because it's only going to make you stronger.
And so that was a lot of talking.
So we're gonna bring it to our conclusion, right?
Is it solves my question when I was at that E3 hangout
is why are there so many theater people in this industry?
Is this like the natural path for all of this?
And I see all of you in the chat,
like, wow, there really is something here.
And I think it is that we literally have very similar roles
or literally the same positions and practices.
And it is a path, right?
That we should see as reasonable as computer tech.
or computer science or tech.
And like I said, it would be just really cool
to see read throughs at different places
and just more carrying over at these practices
because they're only gonna make us stronger, right?
So in conclusion, thematically,
there is a reason theater kids flock to game dev.
It feels like home. Games are my favorite medium. I think they're the most evolved art form possible.
They're more accessible to more people. Theater is not... We love theater, obviously, if we're in this talk,
but it's not super accessible, and games have the ability, like TV did back in the 1950s,
to go into people's living rooms and be there in their heart, in their home.
and we can make these games that make people empathize with each other more
because that identification process, right, with characters is never stronger
than it is in games or theater. And we can make the world, why I'm in games,
to make the world a better place, right? And so practically, I hope all of you in
the audience can maybe take some of these practices and bring them back to your studios,
your teams, and make your game stories richer, stronger, and more impactful. So I do have some
future resources and citations if you're interested if you were like we need to read more on this.
There you go. There's a lot of these that I think would be really helpful. I have to give a thank you to Professor Melinda Finberg of critical drama studies.
Hannah Nicklin PhD and Professor Richard Lemartian of game design at USC.
for his game design outline that we used earlier. Also a shout out to the mentors
who helped me with this and the summit advisors of the Narrative Game Summit for making my first,
this is my first GDC talk. Thank you for selecting me and allowing me to talk about this
and help others. So that is it. I have my website here, my email, and my social media. We will not
have time, unfortunately.
for questions, but if you do have questions, please feel free to DM me, um, mostly on Twitter
would be good, but if you would like to stay in contact, please, here I am. I am looking for full-time
roles, uh, with production, uh, directing or working with actors after graduation, uh, for in, in May from
USC, but I want to thank you all so much, and I hope you have a great rest of your GDC. Bye!