Welcome everyone to GDC, I guess, if this is your first day.
Congrats on missing a day of GDC.
If you don't know who I am, I am Felix.
I am a scout for Fellow Traveler.
And my talk today is discoverability from day zero.
We're going to talk a little bit about discoverability
in general and what that means to me as a scout specifically.
And then we're going to go into a few more details.
I'll do a lot of rambling, I'm sure.
And then hopefully you'll have a takeaway at the end of it.
Cool, who am I?
This slide is a lot for me to look at.
I am currently a producer on Neo Cab, Tunic, and Sable.
Those are all indie projects, small scale,
eight people or smaller.
And I am producer and marketing and PR
for both Fingy and Polytron.
I'm a scout for Fellow Traveler, which is a small publisher located in Australia.
We focus mainly on narrative games and narrative experiences.
I'm also a publishing consultant with Panic, with Nick Sutner, who's somewhere in the room.
I can't see any of you anymore.
There, waving. Great, there, you did it.
And they're doing Untitled Goose Game,
which is really lovely as well,
and it's an honor to work with Nick and Panic on that.
And previously I was on things such as
Towerfall Ascension and Oxenfree,
and I worked with Iron Galaxy
in a lot of different ways as well.
So, done a lot of stuff, but today we're gonna focus
mainly on my experience as a scout,
and how discoverability plays into that role,
and publishing in general,
and for developers pitching to publishers.
Okay, discoverability.
Let's start with a bit of what discoverability is.
And before I get to my definition even,
I'll say that a lot of discussion and discourse
about discoverability has been focused on post-launch,
at least in my experience.
We tend to put it on platforms to solve discoverability.
And I'll be really clear,
I could talk for much, much longer than 25 minutes.
on discoverability on platforms and saturation of market
and what all that looks like post-launch.
But for right now, I wanna come at this
from the perspective of a scout,
someone who gets to see a lot of pitches
before launch, obviously, and then has to determine
both the viability of a project to ship
and its market potential.
So what do I mean by discoverability in this context?
What is the ability of someone who knows nothing about you or your game to find out both that it even exists and
also, what is it? So discoverability is
this in the whole, but we're gonna break it down quite a bit in the next 20 minutes.
I can't believe I only have 20 minutes to do this.
OK.
So phases of discoverability.
Let's break it down a little bit in how
I approach the potential of discoverability in a project
when I'm looking through a deck.
This one, reach, is where I see the most push right now.
It can take lots of forms, but I think the most common
is the like.
past success or public champions with high social media presence, for example,
like you have lots of followers on Twitter or you have a big community from a previous game.
Reach is extremely useful. You should think of it as a multiplier on discoverability in general.
I think this is a big reason why a lot of developers are looking for publishers again in
2019 compared to earlier, 2011, 2012.
They know their reach isn't exactly what it could be,
and they want to hand that off to someone
who is a better multiplier.
Findability.
So it's a little trickier.
Findability is a little trickier.
It's the step that happens after seeing, say, a tweet.
of a super gorgeous game, a GIF, let's say,
but then where do I go to find out more?
If it's just a GIF, can I click on a profile or a link?
Where is that info, right?
So that's findability is the next step.
Accessibility.
Oof, this one is definitely the scariest
of all the points here, in my opinion.
I define it like this.
How much info do I need to have enough knowledge
to make an informed decision as to whether I like your game
and most importantly, whether I'm gonna buy it
or support it.
And for me, as a scout, it's whether we're gonna sign it,
right, in this context.
How do you know when you've informed someone
to the point of hooking them?
Have you done it within their attention span?
That's really big.
And is the information you've given them clear
and representative of the experience,
or at least the experience you want them to have?
I know that it's a little harder pre-launch
to describe a game, but we'll go into that in a second.
OK, so take these, and let's talk
about some dangerous assumptions that I see a lot.
Developers in general contacting me,
submitting decks, submitting pitches.
The first one is definitely the conflation of reach and discoverability.
It's super important and it applies to a lot of us,
whether you've made a game in the past or not.
Reach is just not discoverability,
and I would say it actually applies even more to us
with social media followings and previous project communities.
It's not to say it can't help.
So, like, if you've made a game in the past and you have a huge community, that is obviously
not a downside.
That's a huge help.
but it's not one and the same.
Reach is useful for pushing marketing materials
and hopefully means that you'll have people
who will champion your game,
both on the consumer and the business side
because you have a reputation.
How to get champions is a whole other talk
that Nick Suttner is gonna give on Thursday at 4 p.m.
I highly suggest everybody go to that one if you can.
It's super, super useful, so please check that out.
I won't go into it so that I leave it for you, Nick, sorry.
But, anyway, reach doesn't necessarily guarantee that the design of your game and your vision
is accessible or discoverable to anyone who matters.
The second step is a step in discoverability, right?
And I think it used to be this.
I think a lot of discoverability was
when there were only a few thousand games on Steam, say,
or you had X many indies,
you could measurable amount of indies on a platform,
putting up a Steam page and a website
and a Twitter was definitely enough.
It's just not enough now.
It's tough to just end it there.
You'd be surprised how many people.
Check the box.
Now they're like, okay, I have a Steam page,
I have a website, I did it, I'm discoverable.
But that goes hand in hand with this next one,
which is that discoverability is passive.
This is an assumption that a lot of us make
when we work on super, super small teams.
I think it's, I have a lot of sympathy for this one because I think that talking about
this kind of stuff takes up an immense amount of mental space.
Even just thinking about when you're making a game by yourself or on a small team, what
it takes to be seen and how you're going to reach.
either an audience or a partner, such as a publisher,
it's so easy to say, well, I did everything that I was told
in 2011, all these things, I checked out these boxes,
I have a Steam page and I have a Twitter and a website,
why aren't I being seen?
And I don't have a clear answer for that beyond,
it's just not enough anymore.
It really is not passive.
It needs to be active constantly,
and you need to be reaching out to people all the time.
So again, another really dangerous assumption.
It's just a piece of the puzzle in general.
The discoverability, findability and discoverability
aren't the same.
Okay.
I could talk about the next one for ages, but I won't.
This one can't be assumed at all,
and I think I see it a lot.
You probably have seen pitches like this before.
It's not the pitch that really worries me anymore.
I used to do a whole talk on why you shouldn't use
an elevator pitch that is like,
I'm making Minecraft meets Papers, Please.
And that was true, I think, at one point.
And now I think that it's a little less dangerous
on certain levels.
Like, I think you can use shorthand quite a bit,
or depending on who you're speaking to.
this is not a problem. The danger is assuming that you can or already do have
their audiences and you might be surprised again and how many pitches I
get where they're saying I'm making Papers, Please Me's Minecraft therefore
all the people that play either of those games automatically know about my game
or will know about it very easily.
And that, again, oh boy, is a whole can of worms
that I could go into and I won't.
So dangerous assumption.
Shorthand.
Okay, shorthand can be super, super useful,
but also really dangerous.
If you're 1000% certain that everybody in the room
knows the shorthand you're using,
like I mean common game dev terms,
or even genres like roguelike or something,
then you're fine, right?
But if you're not sure, you risk losing people right away.
Accessibility is super tricky,
and shorthand is pretty binary in whether it works or not.
Well, that's exciting.
But when you're using it, are you actually communicating
why your game is different from every other game
that uses the term you're using, such as roguelike?
Or are you just alienating an entire audience off the bat?
When you're pitching to, say, a narrative studio,
please use all the narrative shorthand you want, right?
But also arm us with context for that shorthand.
Make sure that we know what you're talking about
in a larger spectrum and make sure that other people
are understanding you.
Not all shorthand is useful.
All I can say there is use shorthand with caution
and with an appropriate audience.
So these are all the don'ts, like really common don'ts I see.
The next slide is sort of safer assumptions.
The reason I wrote it this way is that, and I'm
going to preface this with a bit of a ramble, I'm sorry.
I scrapped this talk from this slide forward
probably four times last year.
It's been really, really tough.
The industry changes all the time, right?
I mean, everything is constantly changing
and major platforms are making huge announcements
and the way we experience shipping a game
changes all the time.
And that's super scary, right?
Like I, in addition to being a scout,
like I said, I'm a developer,
so I get to see sort of both sides of that coin.
And it is really terrifying.
It's been super hard focusing on this talk in general
while so many different announcements are being made,
especially the way games are gonna be sold in the future
and all these sort of new platform ideas, et cetera.
So please understand that these assumptions are safe
or not necessarily a tutorial.
If I had more time, I might have been able to do more,
but here we are.
So I have to say that
Designing with discoverability in mind is more important now than it, I believe, ever has been.
If you can't start testing your vision and its discoverability potential from day zero,
the risk of designing a game that is inaccessible and undiscoverable is much, much higher than it was in 2011.
What I mean by that is there are tons of developers
making games now, indie games specifically,
and in order to know if your design and vision is accessible,
I don't think we can afford to make the game first
and hope that it's accessible later.
We have to start doing it from day zero.
We have to communicate visions from the start,
and testing that communication to make sure it's accessible
is essential to the process.
I know this is super vague, all I can do right now
is try to drive home the takeaway
that this stuff is important.
I'd love to caveat with I'm not you,
I don't hold your vision,
and if you're already working on a project,
I'm certainly not your dedicated game designer
that you've definitely hired.
So I've come to realize that I can't give
much universal advice that applies to every project,
but I can talk about some things in the abstract.
So discoverability is proactive.
It's on us as developers now and to find partners such as publishers.
It's on scouts to make sure that we are seeking out projects that are
close to discoverable, but probably need a little bit of help.
It's all about these partnerships that we can create and and flourish with from.
We have to use our reach and make sure we're pairing with the right pair of people basically, but it's just not enough, right? That's a multiplier.
So, you need to be able to make sure that your design is accessible from the get-go
in order to take advantage of that.
Discoverability is fluid.
I was told recently that there was definitely, I don't remember it, but I was told recently
that there was a point in time where Twitter was an excellent tool for discoverability.
It probably had something to do with hashtags back in the day.
I don't remember ever using those, but I know it happened.
I definitely believe that has changed, and that's just an example of how we have to make
sure the tools we're using...
and the multipliers we have are effective.
So we have to pay attention to how the market's shifting.
Who is looking for what?
What kind of games and what kind of audiences
are platforms seeking and focusing their attention on?
And that might be different now
than it was five or 10 years ago, right?
Like we all have an idea in our head
of what kind of audience comes to a specific platform
and what kind of publisher publishes a certain type of game.
But pay attention to those shifts and do a little bit of research.
I know that sounds really 101, but it's something that takes a lot of mental space, and I think
it's deeply, deeply worth doing early, because if you try to leave it until later, it's much,
much harder.
Okay, I don't think I've discussed accessibility enough
in general in my life, and definitely not in this talk.
So we can talk about it a little bit more here.
Your product is accessible if it takes relatively low effort
from the listener to understand.
and then be equipped to make a decision on continuing to engage or not.
Of course post-launch that gap is
pitch
think buy, but if you're pitching to a publisher, it's pitch, think, learn more, right?
That's all you can hope for.
I'm not going to assert that
I'm going to start, sorry, that the only way
to make sure your game and design are accessible
is by pitching it to people and testing their reactions.
And I definitely don't just mean other game developers.
It's super, super easy for developers in general,
especially at GDC, to get caught in the mindset of,
but I have so many people who love my idea,
it must be really good and accessible.
But if all those people are fellow developers
and you've never tested the game out on anyone else,
you're doing yourself and your game a huge disservice.
So, my advice on this one is,
I don't know if you have this, but I do.
That uncle at Thanksgiving who approaches you
and says, I have a great idea for an app,
it's gonna make us a million dollars,
and it makes me wanna shrivel up
into a raisin of a human before dinner even happens.
That's who you have to pitch to.
And I don't mean he needs to like the game.
And I don't even mean that he has to deeply understand it.
he will give you an excellent sense of what sort of attention span someone who isn't already
in your dedicated circles or even interested in games has.
And that's the goal, is to know what that attention span is.
Because if you can make your game accessible, if you can make your pitch, forget the game,
it's not about playing it, even your pitch from day zero, if you can make it accessible
to him.
during dinner at Thanksgiving, you've done it.
Like that's the measure, right?
And I think accessibility in general
is probably the strongest point that gets you a publisher.
It's what tells me as a scout,
okay, we can talk to an audience about this game,
and that audience, even if it's niche,
is gonna understand and be excited about what you're making.
I will say Becca Saltzman did a talk yesterday, I believe,
oh, I might be wrong on that, that covered pitching
and how to do that to publishers.
It was yesterday, right?
Yeah, thank you, John.
I highly recommend checking that one out.
She sees a lot of pitches like I do,
and I don't want to overlap with her too much,
so I won't go into pitching to publishers
on a detailed level.
that talk probably will arm you with a lot of details on how to make an accessible pitch in general.
I really wish I knew a way to ensure accessibility beyond telling you to talk to annoying Uncle Jerry
and going through, or going through each and every one of your pitches, right,
to make sure you're all making products that have accessible cores.
Or even if I could define for you now,
so that in two or three years we can all agree
the pitch is still accessible and desirable, I can't.
But it does bring me to my favorite slide
that is in all my decks.
Unpopular opinions.
Things I don't say on Twitter anymore.
Okay, I don't think you're pitching your creative vision,
so please stop trying to communicate that vision.
I think that your creative vision is deeply important,
and it is yours, and it's something
that not everyone can understand.
Therefore, I think you are actually pitching a product
inspired by your creative vision.
And so the thing that has to be discoverable
is not your creative vision.
And I think a lot of people get stuck in that initial loop,
where they're like, but you just don't understand.
If only you could see my vision,
you would understand why this is such a good game.
A really big part of that is not pitching a product inspired by that creative vision.
I think that there are lots of people probably in the world that can help you with that.
I mean, there are people, there are PR people, and there are designers, and there are all
sorts of people in the world.
But if you don't have contact with them, this one becomes very, very, very difficult.
If you're isolated in some way, this one's very difficult.
You can really get stuck in your own head over it.
I also believe heavily that publishers and champions are more necessary now than ever.
I think that pairing with a publisher who even sees your creative vision in some way
can lead to you having a product.
You just have to convince them of that, and that's where accessibility comes into play.
I also strongly believe that—well, this is math—but I strongly believe that multipliers
on zero still equal zero.
It doesn't matter if your reach is—
a million Twitter followers, if they don't understand anything and they're not going to champion your game, that multiplier is just multiplying zero.
And it's very frustrating. I see a lot of people doing it a lot of the time and it breaks my heart.
But so these unpopular opinions, I just need to put this in here.
You know...
I'm okay with it, by the way, if you don't want to make money.
That's not what I'm talking about here.
I'm saying that your pitch needs to be something
that an audience can imagine spending currency on,
and that currency can be attention, money, time, all three.
At a high level, it's kind of irrelevant.
You're going to use different language for each of those currencies,
but the mentality has to stay the same.
I'm designing with this accessibility in mind
so as to communicate it easily and effectively.
So pitch a product, please, please, please, please pitch a product.
Whether it'll make money or not, that's fine.
Okay, what does anything that I just said mean?
Turn your creative vision into a plan for a product.
Not necessarily a product.
I get that there are steps in between, right?
Please try to turn it into a plan.
This will ensure discoverability,
at least from a publisher's point of view.
Seeing that you have a plan at all for a vision
into a product is gonna be massive for us.
Take it from day zero, outline a plan.
I can't go over all of this in this talk.
I'm already at 20 minutes, 21 minutes, which is so tragic.
But this is why things like design documents,
even if they're just a stream of consciousness are crucial.
You have to hone your vision down
until Jerry at Thanksgiving dinner can understand it,
or at least can give you 30 seconds of his time
and you can retain that, right?
Something, oh, sorry, yes.
I don't know how to emphasize this enough.
Jerry is a nut.
Jerry is good, a good start.
Uncle Jerry at Thanksgiving is a good start.
I just need you to test it on everyone you know.
Once you get down, once you've got your design,
you're like, okay, I have this vision, I love it.
I'm gonna bring it down to something
I think I can communicate.
You have to test it on literally everybody you know.
And I know that's scary, especially with as many games
that are coming out right now.
Developers are loath to share their ideas
and are really scared about doing that.
But if you're pitching to people who have nothing to do
with games, it's much lower risk of another fellow designer
running off and making your game, right?
I know we all have that worry because we're all trying
to make a living, but I really do believe that
we can't afford anymore to hold it so precious
and then to make the game and then to find out
once we launch it that nobody understands it, right?
Discoverability isn't the end result
of who saw your game at launch.
It's much more than that, and that part feels
pretty important to me, so I'll throw up
on the slide of its own.
Sorry, I forgot to put it here.
But, oh, no, I'm stupid.
I forgot the most important part of the slide.
If you're having a tough time communicating how a player interacts with your game,
you might have a design problem.
It will feel like a communication problem, right?
But I urge everyone to take a step back again.
If you're testing it over and over again
and there's a block, it might actually be
a design problem from day zero,
not necessarily a problem with just your pitch
or someone else understanding your vision.
That one's super, super intense.
Okay, in conclusion.
It's not the end result of who you saw your game at launch.
Discoverability is the quality, process,
and design by which your game holds potential
for people to see it at every phase of development.
And I believe strongly that this starts at day zero
and relies on a plan for a product, not just a vision,
and that gets me in trouble all the time.
But this is how I feel.
There we go, it's there.
really want you to think about this as making us, especially Scouts, believe in not just
you but also your product.
And if you can't do that from the beginning, it's just going to be much, much harder to
do it later on.
Kind of the end.
I wanted to leave room for questions.
We're at 25 minutes, I believe.
That only leaves five minutes for questions
and 25 minute talk isn't much.
At the end of the day, I would love,
if the only thing you take away from this
is don't be afraid of making a product.
It'll empower your vision to reach the most people.
That would be the most discoverability
you can possibly get, for sure.
And I urge you to check out both Becca and Nick's talk.
And I did look at the schedule.
I'm up against some really amazing people in this slot.
I'm so glad for the vault
because I think you should probably check out
everybody else's talks today too.
That's it.
It seemed like it went by really fast.
But there it is.
Cool, I can't see any of you, so if you have questions,
I have no idea how I would know.
No, none?
I don't know, I can't see, so.
Oh, there's a mic, okay, perfect.
No, then, we're good.
I'm gonna drink this boxed water.
It's very weird.
It tastes like cardboard.
All the mics went off.
OK, hi.
No.
There we go.
Never mind.
What would good aspects of an elevator talk be?
Elevator pitch.
OK, so this is a whole other talk.
And I've done some cool elevator pitches.
I think there's actually a really good elevator pitch
talk this year.
I have to look it up again.
From a publisher's perspective, an elevator pitch is much more than the consumer pitch
that you're going to give.
You have a lot more space and time, and you really do need a deck.
I don't think I've ever signed a game that had just an elevator pitch in my life.
I've signed plenty of games, but they're all full decks.
The beauty of talking to a publisher is not that you have to have a one sentence that
describes your genre.
genre and hook and theme and narrative, like whatever it is that you think needs to go in your vision or needs to be
communicated from your vision.
For a publisher a deck is incredibly important.
There's no way you can communicate to me whether you're designing with discoverability in mind in general or whether you're designing with an audience in mind even,
except through an entire deck that outlines your vision.
And that's where I would say, sorry, I'm deferring the question, but that's where I would say
definitely go to, or, okay, you can't go to it, it was yesterday, it's the past.
But look up Becca's talk, because I think that's going to help quite a bit, yeah.
And elevator pitches are, we have, I mean, it feels like now it's a little easier than
it used to be in that we have a little more space to talk to consumers, there's like a
little more, you know.
you can gain a following on Twitter
and you can have a Facebook group and stuff like that
where you can discuss more.
But as of right now, from my perspective,
an elevator pitch just isn't enough.
So yeah, doing a whole deck is what's really important.
Yeah, sorry, that was kind of a non-answer.
You tweeting things?
All right.
Oh.
I got a question.
So one thing I wanna ask is,
When you're going around to publishers trying to get them to see your game and you're sending
lots and lots of emails, a lot of publishers I know get hundreds of emails a day and can't
really sort through them all.
What would you say your tips are for having your best shot at getting a response from
publishers?
Yeah, awesome question.
Badger? No. I mean, do bug, right?
Like the thing is, when I get hundreds of emails a day,
oftentimes things do slip through the cracks, right?
Following up on an email is like not a bad thing to do.
I think a lot of us think of it as a bad thing.
I think many, many people are like,
well, I sent an email in October, I didn't hear back.
I sent a new email in December, I didn't hear back.
Threading is very powerful.
Responding to your email and following up on it
with the same subject line is gonna put it in a thread
in my Gmail inbox and it's really, really powerful.
It also is a great indicator as to, you know,
when I was super busy so I can look back and say like,
oh, I did see this, right?
the chances are I did see it or that a scout did see it,
it's just that at the moment it wasn't the priority, right?
Hearing back is really, really tough.
Like, it is a difficult thing.
But I think that getting involved,
a lot of publishers have communities now
and getting involved in that community
is also really awesome.
So, for example, Fellow Traveler has a Discord
and they have a whole community of people
who are playing their games.
and if you can show any interest in the community that fellow traveler, for example, or any publisher
is cultivating and partake in that, it might be a little bit easier for them to take notice.
That's not me saying DM everybody all the time, but it is saying don't be afraid to do it, right?
And you'd be surprised how many people approach me at a convention and say,
oh, I emailed you last year, but I never heard back, so I just didn't think anything of it.
and I'm mortified, first of all, right?
I mean, I'm a human and I miss things,
but yeah, I really do think that
if that initial email had all the things in it, right,
which is to say, I need some form of hook.
So if your game is beautiful, please send screenshots.
If your game has a strong narrative hook
and you want fellow traveler to publish it
because it was like other games they've published,
mention that, right? Make it really easy for me to just to find out more about your game. So that's where that initial
findability comes into play where it's like put up a Twitter, put up a website,
send me a bio about you. Like selling yourself and selling your game are one in the same at that point.
So you have to be able to package it all so that it takes me
less than five minutes to click through things and find things, right? If it's just a cold email with just text,
I'm always gonna pass it by, right?
It just won't take precedent over other stuff.
So I could go into, I mean, I did a talk recently
on literally like everything that needs to go into an email.
Hi, sorry, yes, I am finishing right now.
And I can't, unfortunately can't do that one here,
but email me and I can go over it with you
and I can send you that slide deck for sure.
Cool, all right, thank you very much.
All right.
Be good.