Hello? Hello? Alright. Alright let's get this talk started. Thank you. Okay please
silence your devices. So hello and welcome to this talk. Thanks for coming. Really
appreciate it. My name is Adam Miller and the talk today is titled the mechanics of
explosive growth.
So I am a VP of Engineering at Roblox.
And for those of you who are not aware of Roblox,
we're the largest entertainment platform for kids under 18.
And I've been at Roblox for five and a half years.
And while I've been there, I've been fortunate enough
to witness really interesting trajectory of growth.
So I'm gonna tell you a little bit of that story today.
Oh, I got to turn the clicker on.
That would be a good step.
All right, anyway.
So this one slide kind of captures
the essence of this whole talk.
So this is the story of many, many years
of moderate and steady growth.
And then all of a sudden in the beginning of 2016,
boom, hockey stick.
We hit the inflection point and things really take off.
So today I'm gonna give you a little bit of background
on how we got to this point,
how we experienced it while it was happening,
how we analyzed it,
and some of the conclusions that we came up with.
So I am not an expert on growth theory,
on company growth in general.
This is one data point that I think is interesting
and hopefully has some takeaways.
So a little bit of background on how we started.
Roblox first launched in 2006.
And we began with a fundamental premise about people,
which is that humans want a place for self-directed,
imaginative play.
And increasingly in this world, it's
harder and harder to find that, especially
for teenagers and kids.
So when Roblox started, we wanted
to try to give a place that allows that online.
And it started out as a physics educational tool or toy.
But quickly we added some basic functionality
that defined our platform.
So giving every character,
every person who plays on Roblox an avatar,
that's the 3D representation of yourself in the game.
We added Lua scripting.
From being just physics, adding scripting,
we enabled more compelling experiences
and games to be created on the platform.
And finally, we added the ability for our community
to create content as well as just creating in-house.
We thought first we could create the content,
but by bringing these tools and releasing them
to an existing passionate user base,
we found that they could create content better than us,
not just in terms of quantity,
but even in terms of the quality.
And in the end, we have this system
where there's all these games, these rich experiences,
they stream from the cloud,
people play them with their friends,
and kids can jump from one to the next and have a good time.
So this video is a little bit of an overview
of what Roblox looks like many years later.
You can see it's 3D, it's avatar-based,
although the avatars can be kind of funky and fresh.
you still see a lot of social activity.
People are talking to each other,
running around doing things like working in a pizza place,
exploring worlds, chatting, driving cool vehicles,
playing in platformer type situations,
or even being a bird, flying through a forest,
scavenging for grubs, things like that.
So there's a phase that I'm calling
the formative years of Roblox.
And this is the long period of time
where we focused on building our core vision.
This is the 10 years from that launch in 2006
until that really big growth thing
we're gonna talk about in 2016.
So in this time, we focused on trying to solve
these really hard problems.
And to do that, you build an amazing team.
You build a team that focuses and thinks
about these really hard, long-term problems.
And some of the things we've built in this time
We're enabling easy play with friends,
really doubling down on that social experience.
So kids can be together, they can be on different devices,
they're in one same virtual world,
they're jumping around, talking to each other,
having another experience in another game,
making that seamless so it goes across PC, Mac,
iOS, Android, Xbox, VR,
and you can all be playing together in one world.
That's not so easy, not a lot of people do that,
but we focused on that as one of our big things.
and enabling these tools that work in a way that creators can create a piece of content
and quickly push it to the cloud, have lots of people playing, and it just works automatically.
We scale to lots of people.
So in this time, we're experiencing a growth that's in the 30 to 50% year-over-year range.
And it's steady, and there's challenges that came along.
challenges for our own toughness. So competitors would launch, potential competitors. Sometimes
these games would launch and they would just explode. They would take off. They're getting
10,000% week over week.
The challenge for us, the big thing we thought about was,
do we try and copy them?
Wow, they're having all this success over here.
Should we do some of the things they're doing,
or do we stay to our true vision?
And I would say this is the period of time
when we really focused on our vision
and kept that same course.
So 2016.
And to step back a little bit.
The beginning of 2015, we set a company goal.
We said, we're gonna grow at 85% this year.
And it was crazy, it was outlandish.
We'd grown at like 35% the year before.
We're like, no, we're gonna grow at 85,
we're gonna set this really high bar.
So everyone's like, okay, I don't know if we can do it,
but we're gonna try.
So the 2015 holiday comes around,
and it's the best holiday season ever.
We're taking off, there's tons of traffic,
but we always do well during the holidays,
so it's not that big a surprise.
It's like, okay, things are good.
But then January comes around, and things are even better.
Instead of dipping down again,
we're just continuing to grow,
so this is crazy, like, what's going on?
People are looking around, maybe it's a stat collection problem,
no, things seem okay, maybe it's a botting problem.
Got all these bots attacking us.
But no, they're paying us money.
Bots don't normally like to pay you money.
It's probably not that.
So all of a sudden we realize that this is real.
We're hitting 300%.
All of a sudden it's just going crazy.
So, very exciting.
And we wanna figure out why.
Because if it's one thing we just started doing,
well, we better make sure we don't undo that.
And we weren't quite sure.
We started to think about it, but at the time,
so much of our effort was just keeping things running, right?
We got this amazing growth,
and we wanna make sure the servers stay up,
and the site doesn't come down,
and the database doesn't collapse under the load,
and we just ride this train.
So, people talked about theories,
but there wasn't even time to figure it out at the time.
So we said, okay, cool, we know something's going well,
let's ride it for now, and see what happens.
So we had a bunch of theories at the time.
When I researched for this talk, I got a bunch more theories.
There's as many theories as there are people
that you can talk to about it.
And a lot of them are very interesting.
So I'd go to the marketing team and I'd be like,
hey guys, why did we grow like this two years ago?
They're like, oh, it's very simple.
Yeah, we did these awesome co-brandings.
We really got our brand out there
and we got our name out there.
It just like took off.
I was like, ah, cool, good story.
And then I'd go to the web engineers and be like, hey.
Why do you think we started, Ryan?
Oh yeah, it's because we fixed the polish on the site.
Like, the site used to be so ugly.
Now it looks professional.
Like, we took Comic Sans out of the website.
Take Comic Sans out, I mean, there's just no limit
to how much you can grow.
It makes sense, right?
So, you think I'm joking, I'm not joking.
So, and I go to like the product team,
and they're like, why do you think we're going?
Oh, it's very, there's a great reason for it.
We finally enabled excellent party play,
like the ability for people to jump in game together.
We fixed all those problems,
we really unlocked that social dynamic.
That sounds interesting.
So there's all these theories going on.
Everyone's got a different one.
Let's dive into a couple of what I think
are some of the most compelling ones
and take a look at how that plays out.
So theory number one, YouTube influencers.
These are the YouTubers who are either new to Roblox
or started streaming Roblox around the beginning of 2016.
Right around the time when we're growing,
all of a sudden there's tons of YouTube videos going up.
And some of them are getting millions of views,
tens of millions of views.
Clearly they're driving traffic to our site.
So this could be it.
Like maybe we hit some kind of big thing on YouTube
and that just took over and drove all the traffic.
So looking back at the charting of it,
I'm plotting two things here.
So I'm plotting the Roblox activity on YouTube
versus the Roblox signups.
And when we see this, the YouTube activity
turns out is a trailing indicator.
So it's actually growing a little bit after.
the Roblox signup indicator.
And so, what that means is,
it's actually the new Roblox users who are saying,
oh, I wanna also go to YouTube
and watch videos about Roblox.
So that makes sense, right.
And it's still a great thing for the company,
we appreciate it, but it can't be the one factor
that explains our growth trajectory.
So, theory number two.
We've always had some international presence.
Back around this time, 2015, 2016,
we made a big effort to put servers
in different countries around the world
where we had a lot of players.
And the theory was our games are all networked
and if you're connecting to a server,
you have a lower latency,
you're gonna have a better experience,
you're gonna wanna play Roblox more.
And this graph shows what happened
when we launched.
our servers in Germany, all of a sudden in Turkey,
which is pretty nearby, you can just see this
jump in activity.
It seems very clearly correlated.
I think the internet isn't so good in Turkey.
So, this seems like a pretty compelling explanation
when you see a jump like this.
But,
Then you start to look at what happened in Germany itself.
So Germany itself, even though they got the actual servers,
there's no change.
And it's not 100% clear why,
but we think it's because their internet
was already pretty good.
So they had some kind of connection to somewhere else
that was already good enough,
whereas the Turks really had that jump in experience.
And when we looked across the world
at all the different places where we added servers
in all these countries, there were some pockets
where there was some change.
But it wasn't enough to really explain
the whole change in our growth.
So another good thing, but not the answer.
Very compelling theory, our Xbox launch.
So we first launched an Xbox at the beginning of 2016.
Right in January.
and it's that little white bump that starts appearing at the top of the graph.
So it's a lot of new users coming in.
And there's a theory that beyond just these new users you're getting,
there's additional benefit for the existing users.
So if you have one house and two siblings want to play,
and all they have is an iPad and an Xbox,
all of a sudden, if the Xbox can play too,
you've got more benefit because they can play together.
So you take these two things together,
it's a very strong theory.
So we have to dive a little bit into
how growth works to analyze this theory.
So for growth, there's really only two things you can move.
You can either get more new users
at the beginning of the funnel,
or you can lose fewer users at the end of the funnel.
And looking at this growth in this particular time,
we realized that it was new users
at the beginning of the funnel that was changing.
The retention metrics didn't particularly move.
So okay, that sounds good.
That seems to match what we see with Xbox.
We see new users with Xbox.
But here's the problem.
So this is a graph of overall traffic.
But we're seeing a change in new user acquisition.
Now new user acquisition,
is a leading indicator for traffic,
meaning the users that were acquired
and the change in rate at which they were acquired
happened earlier than this growth.
So when we look back at when it really changed,
it was actually August and September the year before
where we started to see this uptick
in new user acquisition.
So that unfortunately invalidates Xbox, that's the theory.
So this is where things get a little bit more murky,
but super important.
There was a really fundamental change
we made on our platform in 2014,
and we call it DevEx, or developer exchange.
This is the ability for the creators on our platform
to take money out.
So up until this time, for the previous eight years,
They'd been working in a way where they'd make content
and share it, and they'd get some virtual currency back.
But it would just accumulate in their account.
They could spend it on things on Roblox, but that was it.
In 2014, we said, OK, you guys can take that out
for cold, hard cash.
And this was actually a really hard decision when we made it,
because we already had this huge community there producing
tons of content.
Clearly, people liked the content.
Why would we give them money when they'll do it for free?
But what we've seen is this is probably the best decision we ever made,
because it changed the whole nature of how people make content on the platform.
They started to take it much more professionally.
These people who had built up all these skills
and connections and community began to create
in a much more serious manner.
And that produced a level of game quality
that far outstripped what we had before.
So this is actually very difficult to chart
because it happened over a period of years.
But what we see is a combined network effect.
We have two network effects here
that are feeding off of each other.
There's a community of creators.
And we see the more creators there are,
the better it is for each creator
because they can form these teams and groups of people
and work collaboratively to create awesome content.
And then the better content they make,
we have the player community,
and they have their own network effect
where the more players there are,
the better an experience it is for each player.
And these two things feed off each other.
So I do believe this was a factor in our growth change,
although it's something that happened
over a long period of time,
and probably can't be a sharp uptick in itself.
So,
Back to our theories.
I can disprove all of them.
I can prove that every single one of these theories,
I believe, I could be wrong,
is not the one thing that made Roblox grow.
They're all great, and they all helped.
And the tough thing is, people wanna believe them.
We all wanna believe them
because they're things that made our product better.
And they happened around the time of this growth.
So they make such a convincing narrative.
So what did change the growth?
So my theory is that it's a lot of these things added together.
And this sounds like a little bit of a cop-out,
but I'm going to explain.
So if it's a combination of all these things,
there's a natural question, which is,
why would there be such a sudden uptick?
Why wouldn't it just be slowly,
there's one thing and then another thing,
and then it just layers in over time?
And that's an important question.
So I believe I have an answer to that question.
And it has to do with the nature
of how people want to play together.
And I'm going to illustrate that by showing a video of kids
playing.
This is kids playing Roblox.
These are two of my kids and one of their friends
from down the street.
And I'm going to show the video, and then I'm
going to explain why I think it's relevant.
Yes!
No, Zoe!
Zoe!
Yes!
You got an assist kill for Leo.
We both killed Leo together.
Now I'm just going to take out his turret.
Yes!
Because there's a crate on the map.
Epic crate!
Oh my god, I can't believe it.
I'm hiding from LeGal.
I am so hiding.
Look where I'm hiding.
Do you promise that's home?
I promise I will.
It's not.
My god.
Isn't it a good spot?
Yeah.
I'm surprised we killed Leo.
High five.
Daddy!
We just killed Leo and Polly Pugs.
You can see my daughter at the end.
She realizes I'm recording.
She's like, ugh, dad.
But...
The key thing about this, watching kids play like this,
is it's maybe a little bit different of a model
than how we adults play.
It's very social.
It's completely engaging, and they're constantly talking.
This isn't like an isolated incident.
When they're sitting there and playing,
they're always talking to each other, sharing screens,
like messing around with each other.
It's a very different way they engage with the product.
And I think this ties into how Roblox became viral.
So when you think about virality with our demographic,
it's not on Facebook and Twitter.
They aren't sharing links on social media.
They don't have social media.
This is old school virality.
This is kids in a classroom, on a playground,
talking to each other.
And when they have a great experience
that they wanna share,
they'll tell people about it, and they'll bring them in.
And so my theory is, at a certain point,
we'd unlocked enough of these things.
We'd found we'd had a product that people wanted.
We unlocked the blockers.
We fixed the things that were kind of broken.
We made the experience work for our audience.
And that opened up their desire to bring in more people.
And when you have some kind of critical threshold,
three or four kids in one class,
and they're all playing on one system,
they want to bring in that extra kid
because that adds so much to their experience.
So, this is our ultimate answer.
In our story, we took a long big vision.
We worked really hard on it for a long period of time.
We worked and invested in the people and in the product.
And in the end we created a system where it was viral
and it fed this word of mouth experience.
So I'm gonna conclude that there is no one trick
that just let growth magically happen.
And is that a good thing or a bad thing?
I think there's pros and there's cons.
So the con is, well, it would be great
if there was one magic trick that everyone could use
and then you just grow like crazy.
But I am glad we live in a world that's different than that.
I like living in a world where we try to build really difficult products, really challenging
big things, and when we succeed, that's where the real interest happens.
It's better than a world where it's just armies of growth hackers fighting against each other
with tricks.
So I can't promise this approach will work for everybody
in every situation, but I think I encourage everyone
to consider it as a potential strategy.
Thank you guys.
Are there any questions?
While other people are thinking of questions,
it's not totally on topic, but I'm curious,
in this growth spike, how your creator,
like what percentage of your population is creators,
how that's grown with your player base?
Like is it, have you seen like a linear relationship,
or is it lagging now?
How's that look?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the question is, is there a linear relationship
between the growth in our players and our creators?
And mostly we find it's a little bit sublinear.
So they both grow and they track each other.
But there are a little bit faster growth in players than creators.
And I think this makes sense that there's a little bit fewer people,
especially as you get out of the early adopters,
that are as excited on the platform.
But for us in particular, we find that
Our community, there's a lot of blending
between the two types of people.
And especially with children who want to be creative,
they'll play one day and then they'll create another day.
And so there's always gonna be some crossover.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi.
Did you ask any of your users, I guess,
before the growth spurt and after the growth spurt
to see if there was any delta in reasons
why they might have signed up and started playing?
So that's a good question.
Did we gather good user data on what was changing before
or after?
The answer is not great data.
Unfortunately, we have started doing more
of that user gathering data since then,
but we didn't have it in place at the time,
so we unfortunately can't go back and get that information.
With a bunch of different creators in your ecosystem and a bunch of different people spending money in those games
Do you take any responsibility or how do you manage the longevity of something that somebody else has created or is still creating for users?
While knowing that your spenders in that economy have an expectation that their money is going to be valuable in that user-generated content
Today, but also months from now
Great, yeah, so I'll repeat the question,
which is if users are spending in a game,
how do we ensure that that game, what they've bought,
is still valid down the road?
So the first thing we do is we have a commitment
to make sure we don't break old content.
We go to extraordinary lengths to make sure that old content is still relevant.
And we work with the creators to make sure that we don't cause them problems.
We find that most games still operate, if they're making money and they have a significant
community involvement in their game, they will continue to operate that game and not
break it.
There are times when...
When things like that do happen, somebody bought something
in a game, and the game creator broke it and doesn't care,
it's relatively rare.
It does happen.
I'm not exactly sure on our policy at that point in time.
But we do sometimes offer refunds in certain situations.
Hockey stick growth is kind of a double-edged sword.
With that growth comes management problems,
scaling problems, not of the systems necessarily,
but the humans.
Additionally, it increases speculation on your brand.
And I'm not sure if Roblox is publicly traded or not,
but that can tend to be quite volatile.
How are you addressing the non-engineering risks
of explosive growth?
Good question.
So how do we handle the other parts of exclusive growth,
the downsides?
So first, Roblox is a privately held company.
And so we don't have to worry about external pressures,
which are tough, I'm glad.
At the time when we were going through this phase,
I think a lot of it came down to our culture.
And there were challenges, but what we did was
we grew slowly within our means.
We didn't say, okay, now we're a different company.
Now we're going to be like that company over there,
we're gonna rethink ourselves.
So we stayed within our existing plan
and didn't try and overshoot.
We didn't take, I think where people can get into trouble
is saying, I've gotta capture this thing now.
I better hire a thousand people tomorrow
because we're this other company now.
And we didn't do that.
So that seemed to work for us.
Thank you.
Hi. Since observing the growth in the Turkish market when you opened your German servers for the game,
have you developed any sort of scheme to track potential player bases
and see if there's interest in having servers set up in that region of the world?
Good question.
So are we tracking interest in different parts of the world,
and how do we determine how we're going to approach it?
We do.
So it turns out that currently about half of our usage
is international.
maybe just a little less than half.
So we have a ton of early signal on where users want us to go.
And it's interesting that some countries tend to be much more
popular than others.
So for example, South Korea loves Roblox.
Japan less so today.
And even though we haven't done anything in particular
for either country.
So we get a lot of strong signals off of the existing traffic.
And then we get to target where we want to deploy more services, translations, things like that.
Are there any identifiers that are specifically outside of the game that you've noticed in particular?
So one that I've noticed is YouTube streamers.
So that seems to be a strong indicator that there's a cultural affinity for the product.
So with South Korea, Thailand, some other places,
unexpectedly you get these streamers
who have millions of views of Roblox
that's maybe out of proportion to the traffic
from that country itself.
And so that potentially is one of our indicators
for hey, we should take advantage of this.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, were there any factors you identified as critical
to the very steady 30% year over year growth
prior to the hockey stick
that were not talked about already?
Yeah, so how did we identify the steady 30%?
So what's funny about that, I've thought about this.
I guess this is natural to humans.
You have some kind of status quo,
and then you just accept that, oh, this is the thing, right?
But we don't actually have any way
to prove that that was the thing we should have
expected versus the change.
So the answer is not really.
The nature of the growth at the time, I think,
was word of mouth, viral growth.
We didn't do a lot of advertising.
We never did.
But.
So I think there was a coefficient
of how fast people come onto the platform.
And that 30 to 50% represented that.
But I can't prove it.
There's no mathematical basis for either phase, I guess.
Hi, I have two young girls that absolutely love Roblox.
Yes.
I spent hundreds of dollars on great games and Nintendo Switch,
and they prefer to play Roblox, which sometimes infuriates me.
My question is.
My question is, as a parent, since the players are so young, and anybody can create, and anybody can create whatever they want,
do you have, are you thinking, or do you already have something in place that monitors the content and curates it in some way?
Yeah, good question.
So how do we monitor, moderate, and curate the content?
So because we are targeting young children,
this is built into our DNA from every phase of our product.
So every chat message, every piece of text
goes through scrupulous text filtering.
We have teams of moderators that stand by and react
in very quick time to anything that's behaving badly,
any kind of.
anti-social behavior, any content that is not appropriate.
Every image, sound, mesh, and so forth
goes through a moderation queue
before it can view it on our site, and so forth.
We can't be perfect.
We can't absolutely catch everything and guarantee it,
but it's very good.
And we're always working to make it better.
Thank you for your presentation.
So you mentioned you have quite a few players
in South Korea and Japan.
So I'm wondering, are you thinking about
creating some content that caters to the Asian audience?
And also just how do you think about
the timing of international expansion in general?
Yeah, yeah.
So the question is,
what do we think about the timing of international expansion
and do we want to create content for the Asian audience?
So...
What we want to do, we don't create any of the content ourselves.
Our goal is to make the best tools, the best platform that enables content creation from
the community.
And we do believe there are cultural differences in different parts of the world, and people
do want to experience different content.
There's gonna be a lot of overlap,
but we wanna support all of the variety.
That's one of the great powers
of having a really long tail and a huge catalog.
So the way we achieve that is we build
really robust communities of creators around the world
in all these different cultures and countries.
And we make sure that we provide the tools that let them create.
And then we make sure that the discovery part works as well.
So in fact, today on Roblox, you can go to our games page
and see games that are popular near you.
And that list will be different in Korea
than it will be in America.
And as we really expand internationally
over the next couple of years, hopefully we're
going to see a lot more really cool differentiation
in that area.
Thank you.
Hi, you mentioned that there's basically a double network effect.
Did you realize that in order to unlock one, you needed another one?
Was there like a chicken egg problem?
How did you solve it?
Yeah, so how did we solve the double network effect
in unlocking creators versus players?
I think we started with a single network effect.
And we really started very small.
We started with just the simple vision
and built up from having two players online
to wow, we've got 10 players online at once,
that's amazing.
Now it's 1.5 million, but it was a very slow growth
to get to that phase.
Yeah.
Did that mean you were creating content initially?
So only at the very beginning, like literally only
in the first few weeks of creation.
Because in the beginning, we had to create a tool
to create the content anyway.
And as soon as we had that tool, we
could give it to the people who wanted to play.
Got it.
Cool.
Thanks.
Did you find that the distribution of play
within the games changed as the growth grew?
So did the distribution of play change within the games as the growth grew?
so
We didn't see any major change. I would say we always have a pretty long tail of content
There's a few games that are super popular
There's maybe a top thousand that have
like dozens to hundreds of people in them at a time
And then there's a super long tale of pretty obscure stuff.
That fundamental distribution did not change
when we had our growth story.
That's time?
OK, thank you everyone so much.
Really appreciate it.