And also, if you could fill out the little flyer or the, what is it?
The survey, yeah.
If you can get that done, that would be great.
I would really appreciate feedback on this.
So everyone's all settled, I'll get started.
My name is Sarah Bonser, and I'll be talking with you today about world building with architecture.
and more specifically, designing for an authentic experience.
I know that sounds a lot like some words
you're familiar with, but authentic specifically relates
to how feelings are generated.
There's a way to get to engaging, immersive, unique,
et cetera, without encompassing this trait specifically.
For something to be perceived and remembered as authentic,
it can't feel manufactured.
Authenticity is
best achieved below the level of consciousness.
Architecture is actually fantastic at this
because it requires no acknowledgement
for it to have an impact.
Bernard Schumi famously notes,
architecture cannot satisfy your wildest fantasies,
but it may exceed the limits set by them.
I'd imagine the opportunity to capture an audience
on it's got great architecture is exceptionally rare,
but the capacity to make a game unforgettable
with the help of architecture
appears to be unbounded by genre.
Architecture has the capacity to affect occupants,
whether it's behaviorally portraying a sense of space
or providing a lens through which to perceive information.
Levels work in a similar way,
organically teaching strategy,
providing a backdrop for lore, and divulging plot.
And admittedly, this is a lot to cover in an hour,
so here's a quick rundown.
I'm gonna catch everyone up
on relevant architectural theory,
then we'll look at how it's applied to video games
as well as some built structures.
After getting the hang of it, we'll go in depth into three well-known games as case studies.
I'll close out with some sources to learn more.
A little bit about me. I'm an artist and a licensed architect in the state of Washington.
I got some degrees from The Ohio State University and work as a project architect now.
And actually, there's a very rigorous process
to getting a license.
It's about 5,600 hours of apprenticeship, seven tests,
six years of school, and a state-mandated 1,000 hours
of the Sims?
No, that's not right.
Notably, theory is actually baked
into our profession through education,
whether we use it day to day or not.
We need it.
so that we can explain to any client or consultant
that we're working with,
whether they know architectural theory or not,
because it's good design
is not actually a viable defense for an idea.
This knowledge is the way to keep our concept intact
as constraints get layered on.
So that makes buildings like this look really impressive.
And as I mentioned before,
architecture works without the occupant's acknowledgement.
And I wanted to find how that works precisely.
There are a ton of little indicators,
scale of material, types of openings,
striation of level, and lighting.
Each of those little indicators informs a viewer
why, when, where, what, and who built this thing.
Even the context provides a lot of information.
So we see in this one, it's actually
manufactured materials that clad it.
That was built in a factory and had to get shipped to site
and had to get told to the people that are installing it
exactly where those go.
That's not a brick.
That's not something that you just lay on in a certain order.
That's not something that one person
is trained to do over many buildings that's
specific to that single building.
So that tells you a lot about the intent
of what it's trying to convey,
and a lot of things about what kind of strategies
were employed to create the building.
These indicators allow a layperson
to pick up on characteristics of a building.
For instance, some buildings just look evil.
Shout out to our evil buildings for some of these ones.
Spikes, evil.
Going into space forever, evil.
Some angles, probably evil.
Without knowing anything else about it,
a first impression actually goes a long way
to evoke feelings.
Cirilio figured this out and codified it
with these two illustrations of comedic and tragic scenes.
These sets demonstrate a series of indicators
which set the context for how characters are feeling.
Take a moment to compare the two.
We'll start by looking at the tragic scene.
The tragic scene has a ton of gravity
as the space keeps going back into that set.
The buildings fall in line and stand at attention,
enforcing center framing.
Cornices loom over the street
and decorations are carved in stone.
Then we compare this to the comedic scene,
where the buildings are individually expressive.
The massing does not appear
to have been coordinated overall.
Individuality is expressed through decoration
and articulation of colonnades.
We see a wider variety of architectural styles,
and these propose a more casual feel to the setting,
as they're far less subjected to rules
and overarching organization.
So let's look at these again.
and note the ways they're leaning on the set
to use that opportunity to show and not tell.
Unlike relying solely on dialogue for storytelling,
where you must select a reading level
that you're catering to,
environments have the unique opportunity
of displaying layered information to players,
freeing designers from catering solely
to the largest demographic.
So let's just take a moment to look at
how levels have been used in the past.
We'll start with the extrusion of the ground floor
and how that's clad in indicative textures.
So these are strictly informative.
They tell you where the bounds of your playable area are.
From there, we got these graphically excellent
illustrations of architecture,
but not necessarily functioning beyond something like a set.
Shortly after, we see architecture being used
to fill in narrative gaps for players.
It can be also used to indicate advantageous strategies
for upcoming obstacles.
Since then, we've seen many sophisticated combat games
leverage level design for strategic purposes.
But what's even more interesting to me
is something that's on the cusp of my own reach
as an architect, empathy.
This is a fascinating direction for games to move
because it can make the problems of others
seem familiar and relatable.
Specifically, creating an emotional impact
on an adult audience requires authenticity.
I see an unparalleled potential for this medium
as it has evolved to this in just two short decades.
Architectural theory has some ability
to help clarify opportunities to impact spaces
and
how that can affect occupants.
Writing topics can also serve as a guide
toward a more critical dialogue for game designers.
We'll start by looking design
in the most utilitarian application,
introducing a player to a game.
Tutorials can be the most immersion-breaking moment in a game.
The character and the player
are at opposite ends of the spectrum.
Presumably, the character has been running
and jumping for years,
but the player is being asked to do this
for the very first time.
Having control over the environment means supplying
information to the player intentionally.
Put simply, overt design requires the player
to gather information.
Subversive design gives the player information.
Overt design calls for the audience to draw information
about complex subjects.
You can use it to convey history, social norms,
and political climate from surrounding atmosphere,
similar to the way you learn about a city's culture
by traveling there.
The urban fabric is heavily influenced
by the culture of an area.
Most people can recognize the plan of Paris
because this bizarro thing happened.
This guy Hausman came in with this plan
to get some avenues in there,
and it took about 75 years to carry out.
So that threw it into this way different trajectory
than any other city, giving it a sense of place.
Subversive design conveys information passively,
like designing a push and pull side for a door handle,
which looks visually different,
or tactile transition surfaces for pedestrians
going into a vehicular area.
In louder ways, it can direct you to take the stairs
instead of an elevator.
Without being tied to a single language,
we can universally convey a lot of information.
One concept which architects grapple with
is this idea of consciousness.
Phenomenology is a word that I'll try not to bank on,
but it breaks down to something that adds to ambiance.
It registers as a coincidence or a phenomenon
and creates an experience
below the level of acknowledgement by the occupant.
Plot should register above consciousness
as the player needs to have an understanding
of why they're providing actions towards a role
and foreshadowing as a tool becomes available
once that context is understood.
Doom 2 actually uses both very skillfully
as information is baked into the game environment,
providing lore and strategic information to the player.
It trains the player over a series of levels
to navigate the halls of hell more adeptly.
Your character is a paranoid space marine
armed with a pistol methodically working his way
through a demon stronghold.
This environment uses lines and lights
to direct you through the level.
Soon you'll find yourself pressing up against walls, frantically searching for more supplies.
Doom leverages overt cues to teach the player where to look for supplies using gargoyles
and grotesqueries.
Later levels appear to have a ritualistic or religious aesthetic to them.
Items decorating scenes have a strong hierarchical and symmetrical design sensibility.
These indicators prime the player to imagine answers to questions they have about the environment.
When monsters spawn or you get dropped into a pit, it can be attributed to any of the
various reasons your brain came up with.
This leverages the player's imagination
to come up with more convincing reasons
than you as a designer could possibly predict for them.
Portal and its sequel also rely on gameplay
with gradually increasing complexity.
According to Chris Chin at Valve,
the first few puzzles scale from one solution to multiple
as the player gains more agency over the character.
Using colored light and iconography,
the players will gravitate towards certain areas predictably.
The grid also provides this burdensome backdrop
for the test chambers.
And those gridlines you see really tap into this idea
of modular furniture
being primarily consumed as oppressive.
Modular materials are classically used in large spaces
with no particular interest in hospitality,
and notably do not tap into fond memories.
DMVs are riddled with these materials, for instance.
These inherent thought processes allow Portal to snap the player
into the character's mindset of escape.
As a result, Gladys and Wheatley dialogue
doesn't have to tell you how to feel or what to do.
This results in an organic and authentic experience
for the player, given the opportunity
to graft their own thoughts onto the canvas as well.
Destiny 2 is interesting because the multiplayer maps,
of course, don't tell you how to navigate
and where advantageous locations are.
But sight lines and organic movement still happen.
And it brings the fights around the mountain.
So focused scrimmage areas migrate as sniping locations
perform as a catalyst.
While the game is technically and graphically excellent,
the campaign doesn't leverage the layout
of the environment in the same way.
It doesn't provide any inherent wayfinding.
This is only evident as a bar because
The Crucible maps are so good at this.
In the opening mission, Homecoming,
it relies heavily on voiceovers and HUD.
As a result of this, your Ghost and Vanguards
forego some opportunities to directly characterize themselves.
They actively direct your player through the map.
This undermines the immersive feel of Agency.
As a result, the storyline must keep raising the stakes
in order to continue to have an impact on the player.
To some extent, as a designer, you must reward your player
for pouring their own thoughts into their experience.
If you set a standard that ceilings are rewarding
and worthwhile to look at, you'll train your player
to use that information actively.
If you mail it in, you're likely to lose
a little bit of trust with the player.
It's kind of like sig figs.
How do architects build these expectations?
We'll go through a quick study noting specific elements
of their impacts.
And for the sake of this talk,
architecture can be described through its materiality,
adjacency, figure, light, and scale.
More complex ideas such as proportion and ratio
can be extrapolated from scale, for instance.
Zaha Hadid uses the Contemporary Arts Center in Cincinnati
to make art accessible.
She uses a variety of tactics to achieve that accessibility,
tackling it from different directions.
So we'll take a moment to get acquainted
with Hadid's masterpiece.
Hadid ushers in the public by continuing this concrete
from the sidewalk up the building in the wall.
The gesture allows the concrete
to characterize itself through texture.
It's scored and rough at the sidewalk
and honed in the lobby.
And it has this formwork texture as it turns up into the wall as a structural material.
The massing of the building relies on sliding boxes indicating function.
She shows how exhibition spaces are laid out via the facade.
Direct sunlight isn't good for art, therefore the space will be devoid of functional windows.
This indicates individual collections and creates a hierarchy for their understanding
and relationships.
Natural light indicates public space.
It's completely glazed and not just punched openings.
The vertical scale of the public space
also allows for natural light
to reach deep into the structure.
And I'll have you note that the entire wall is that window.
It's a curtain wall.
And it goes up that chasm that is the stairwell
that you'll see here.
The exaggerated lighting contrasts the public space
from the exhibit areas, which cannot be naturally lit.
This provides a subversive cue for the occupant
to speak quietly or move slowly in gallery spaces,
while still providing a visual relationship
to that vertical circulation.
So there's a lot of moving pieces in this one,
and they all work to make art seem more accessible.
Hadid pursues motive from a variety of angles
and uses multiple design tools.
This adds to the impact and legibility,
but also takes on an opportunity for improvement
for future architects to use it as inspiration.
We'll analyze three games, two AAA titles,
and one of them is indie, but pretty well known.
I chose popular games for the case studies
such that most of the audience will be familiar
with the story and the lore.
These games hold architecture accountable
for different aspects of world building,
and I'll break down the opportunities they chose to take
as well as a few they might have missed.
Breath of the Wild uses architecture
to communicate cultural values and history.
Fallout 3 uses it to cohesively tell a nonlinear story.
Inside uses it in lieu of dialogue and text to tell a story.
FYI, there will be spoilers.
I'll start with Breath of the Wild.
My favorite part of this game was seeing the villages.
They established Link as a visitor,
which adds to the authenticity.
The lore has been built up by preceding
Legend of Zelda games,
but designers don't rely on that alone.
Each village requires Link to earn an augment to reach
or move through the area, creating a destination
as opposed to something you just stumble upon,
which overall is a very successful strategy
for an open world game.
In fact, the open nature of this world
has created an emphasis on profile
as a defining navigational feature.
For instance, the stables look like horses.
If you see them from a distance,
you can tell you need to put your horse there.
You're drawn to its profile,
which actually exists in real life architecture,
but it's not nearly as effective.
Architecture parlant, or speaking architecture,
visually describes its own function.
Modern parlant has become synonymous
with these literal recreations of profile.
It's an attention-hungry move.
And the worst part about it
is that they're just boxes on the inside.
That's just like a concrete sculpture
that's been put over a box.
It's gross.
But Breath of the Wild commits to it,
which allows the player to get a little bit more information
out of the skyline.
It's composed of shapes that are already recognizable
that can provide a meaning to things
before you have to learn about them.
This gives the player agency,
allowing inherent recognition skills to pay off.
It's also used as a primary design feature
for the Divine Beasts.
They have a cohesive model with the interior
adhering to the exterior envelope
and that makes it way better.
Actually, it creates this great exquisite corpse
because you can even rotate the parts around.
So we'll focus on the Rito Village,
which is elevated by a nearby landscape.
The divine beast is perched at the top of the spire,
just like a bird, and the air drafts in the area
pick up, similar to turbulence around real mountains.
The village is lightweight wood frame construction.
Fabric is a cladding material,
which is uniquely advantaged in virtual architecture,
and ritos, like birds, can fly,
so wind direction is important to them.
So feathers and fabric could feasibly serve a purpose.
This allows visual correlation also to fuselages and gliders.
And it's great considering how that contrasts the Goron's
heavy timber construction.
And actually, this is something we use in real life.
A heavy timber is actually fire resistant.
It creates a char around the outside,
which prevents it from burning down as easily as lightweight
wood frame construction.
So it works twofold as the Gorons actually have very large hands
and would most likely not care to articulate their handrails
with fine details.
So there's a lot of ways the level characterizes itself.
But it also manages to foreshadow events as well.
Just like movies, the level designers and environment
artists decorated these scenes with props.
It's exceptionally impressive that these
work after giving the camera controls to a player.
The profile of the hut is bell-shaped and framed out of wood,
which ends up looking like a birdcage,
but it also matches the profile of that shrine
more closely than any of the other buildings.
This introduces the concept as what we call a dialectic,
providing two ends of the spectrum,
embedded stone versus elevated wood frame.
And the concept of primitive hut is taught this way
by two warring concepts.
Perrault and Logier, on opposite ends of the spectrum,
Perrault proposes that architecture started
with a hut embedded in the earth.
We consider this vernacular architecture
or architecture without architects.
Logier proposes that it happened the first time
columns and entablature were used.
But if this was the case,
I don't know if that's happened yet.
I haven't seen trees do that.
Introducing both allows that profile to work in two ways
and allows the player to fill in gaps,
allowing some indication of the origin of that design.
And as with every great accomplishment,
there's always some way to evolve or improve the concept.
So I'd say the next step would be to create slightly more
varied typologies from the exterior.
Providing exterior variety to the huts
could allow more characterization
and create a spectrum of viable Rideau style huts.
They're not distinctive from the exterior,
which is odd as they're not intended to be manufactured.
Precise, perhaps, but the organic nature of the layout
would also indicate that it's not the intended takeaway.
Shops and interactive huts require you
to pass through the threshold to distinguish function.
This problem is, of course, alleviated
by showing certain items for sale
or these little chick hammocks, which are kinda cute.
They use colored textiles as well
to customize the interior.
So as I mentioned before, Breath of the Wild
does an excellent job introducing
a variety of cultures.
It provides comparable design moments
to demonstrate nuanced information
that can be distinguished between different villages
as well.
Moving on to Fallout 3, it was an ambitious reboot
to an isometric series.
It introduces concrete visualizations
to an already established world, which is hard.
The series is laden with lore and subplots
which allow an experience to become
more or less catered to each player.
The landmark buildings are where the level designers
chose to convey more abstract goals,
so that's what I'm gonna be using as a specific critique.
And not meant to negativity, but there are a lot of reasonable decisions that I believe
led to a less than impactful location, 10 penny tower.
I think there's a lot we can learn from this, though.
So I'll start with the datum of expectation.
Megaton had a lot of roles in this game.
Primarily, it establishes that datum.
It uses materials and layout to convey a concept of makeshift space planning.
They also established the distinction between friendly
and hostile settlements by walling the city off.
Circular walled cities historically have indicated
a culturally important epicenter, which is true in Megaton.
Everything has a view of that bomb,
centrally located in the city.
It showcases constraints of new cities,
lacking means to fabricate and time to design and construct.
This contributes to the characterization
of the industrious wastelanders.
They're settling and developing not only single structures,
but managed to create a somewhat cohesive city from scraps.
So we see a fuselage from a plane underperforming
as its previous life was flying through the air,
and now it's just simply a settlement.
So there are a lot of things that indicate to us
that this is a fallen from what it previously
manufactured civilization, which is very interesting
and very quick to get that information to the player.
Rivet City creates a uniquely restrictive environment.
The city is hosted on a retired aircraft carrier,
which is a highly engineered vessel with precise openings.
Unlike Megaton, these parts were not scrapped and customized.
As a result, the citizens keep the structured lifestyle,
and it feels restrictive, even to the extent
that you must get permission to access it via the drawbridge.
The mall leveraged inspiration from existing architecture
fits very well here.
Even if you haven't been to the United States Capitol,
you know what it looks like, it's iconic.
And even if you haven't seen it,
the style of architecture is so formulaic,
it's enough to demonstrate what's missing
based on what remains.
The practicality of imposing asymmetrical damage
to a one symmetrical building
has an inherent impact on the player.
So given all that information,
let's take a look at Tenpenny Tower.
It's approached somewhat early in the game.
You get the marker for it after exploring only one city
prior to this.
It holds the quest, which presents
the first massive moral decision you
must make with your character.
And spoiler alert, you're positioned
to arm that bomb in Megaton City and destroy it.
Breadcrumbs prepare you for this, though,
learning how to arm the bomb, confirming the quest,
bartering for the reward.
And it will land you some seriously bad karma
if you go through with it.
Tenpenny Tower is where you push that button.
This tower is also one of the best preserved buildings
in the Fallout world, for a while at least,
which creates an opportunity to represent
what life was like in higher fidelity
than any other exterior environment.
It also has the opportunity to justify its longevity
with building materials.
And it may seem nitpicky, but all the rooms
have kind of look like tunnels.
They lack windows.
And for the tallest building in the Wasteland,
I would think that this would be kind of a selling point.
But again, that's probably just because of engine limitations.
And without a lot of sleuthing, we
can look at the New Willard Hotel and see the similarities.
It's a historically tall building in Washington, DC.
And it's not a tower, though.
And that's why I think Tenpenny looks a little bit squat.
Early skyscrapers typically used primarily
vertical articulation.
Architects were actually over the moon
about how high they could build,
and as a result, couldn't even.
About 100 years later, architects finally got over themselves and started exploring
horizontal articulation.
You can see the spandrel panels and floor plates articulating the iconic Lieberhaus,
and the aqua tower provides modulation in the X axis at the cost of practicality because
now it is actually just a radiator.
The New Willard Hotel is actually a block building, which is why it's got that horizontal
banding.
Also, the hotel is massive compared to its neighbors.
The city probably had restrictions
on how tall a building could be on that plot of land.
It's a very courteous building, though,
because it gives back a little bit of space
on that intersection, as you can see that chamfered corner.
But then it does this thing that I have actually done myself.
I feel really bad about this.
That cornice, that balcony, actually just
shields the view for the pedestrian.
So it looks like the building's about 40 feet shorter.
I've had to do this.
I don't feel great about it.
The vaulted roof structure also foregoes that upper edge.
So it's hiding its penthouse floor
as it's timidly approaching its footprint.
So when we see Tenpenny Tower mimic these things,
it appears ashamed of its size, fighting to appear shorter.
We also don't see anything that could pick
to another side of Tenpenny, outside of his dialogue.
Something like strong 90 degree corners
could imply a rigid, unchanging nature,
as he's greeted with the wasteland, but refuses to adapt.
Also, I'm still bummed about that Windows thing.
Choosing reference material requires some insight
on why it's working in its current context.
In fact, you end up inheriting a lot of solutions
to other people's problems.
I could imagine a seemingly valid argument for this design
as it relies on maybe existing in the palette of the Potomac.
It's an existing building in the area.
That would make sense.
But it's easier to defend discrete moves and motives
by referencing symbolic justification.
This allows for more correct answers to your problem.
as opposed to putting collaborators
in a take it or leave it situation as well.
I also saw this alternate concept art.
I don't know why this didn't make it in.
I could probably think of a thousand reasons
why it couldn't make it in,
but it does adhere better architecturally.
So it has those 90 degree corners, which are really strong.
It also has a bunch of different architectural styles,
which is indicative of a single payer.
And it does this wedding cake thing,
where it builds slowly up to that decision point.
And that could have a good correlation
to the way you followed those breadcrumbs.
Fallout ultimately does a fantastic job with storytelling.
I spent 300 hours in this game,
and I didn't feel constrained by an order of levels.
So no matter what path I took,
each did their part to further illustrate the world
and the culture of the Wastelanders.
Now, Inside was a remarkable game,
and I will warn you, spoilers on this one.
I'm saying that because it is a really good reveal.
But the game relies on context and gameplay
to reveal the plot.
There are a lot of clever decisions
which capitalize on the constraints and requirements.
These decisions are leveraged to challenge the player
to solve this meta puzzle.
introducing a desire to know why you're here
and what you're doing.
Playdead uses this to set up and train the player
under a certain set of rules
and has them develop habits and strategies.
This allows for the reversal at the finale
to have much more of an impact.
For architects, experience design and forced perspective
are challenging to maintain for multiple hours.
One building does come to mind,
which provides prolonged empathetic experiences.
Leibskins Jewish Museum in Berlin jars its occupants
with subtly disorienting and harsh conditions
in order to simulate the toll
an environment can take on a human.
The color palette is reduced to mid-gray tones,
forcing occupants to use light to distinguish elements.
Soft shadows strain the viewer
to distinguish similar elements,
and harsh lights produce.
stressful impairment on eyes by providing too much contrast.
Narrow windows consistently cover the exterior,
providing different level of lights
through the same mechanic, that thin rectangular void.
By rotating those, you've actually created
a variety of conditions which can be used
to do that subtle and stark thing
that was messing with people's eyes.
Many museums rely on layout and lighting
to break up displays in an attempt
to help viewers read for more than comprehension,
but empathy.
You're asking the visitor to learn a lot
by giving them breaks between exhibits.
You allow them to rebuild their stamina and learn more.
These sharp corners provide an uneasy feeling
throughout the entire journey,
granting temporary reprieve between spaces,
but not letting the visitor feel rested
or have a clear path forward to the end.
Leaveskin treats the museum
as an extension of the collection,
a machine for creating feeling,
not just something people move through.
Inside forces a reckoning with the players,
seemingly at ease.
The player must use spatial and visual indicators
to discern meaning about their experience,
like lighting, building layout, material characteristics,
and area of effect.
By providing high-fidelity details,
the onus falls on the player to distinguish content.
In Playdead's previous hit, Limbo,
we see a blur as things fall out of focus.
Inside, crisp backdrops indicate their value
as a narrative element.
There's something that's important to you.
They also work to codify planes of action.
Early in the game, the smaller challenges
train the player to focus on opportunities presented
in a single plane while referencing mid-ground
and background for information.
So the scenes can actually be dissected.
So in this one, we see that we have control over the chicks,
and we also have control over the lever.
That's in the foreground.
That's lit by that lamp.
as soon as we pull the lever, we lose control of the chicks
as they go into the background.
Poor things.
The same can be said about this scene
where you have control over your player in the foreground
and start to learn how to control the background.
But they keep the plane separated
as you don't have full control yet.
So we're gonna use that word again, phenomenology.
It's when you're fed information and it stays below the level of consciousness.
The subtlety of clues is actually held as a datum in this game.
The player's consciousness actually fluctuates when they're tasked with challenges.
Platforming challenges come in waves, switching you between survival and understanding the
levels.
The environment is consistently broadcasting clues
to a player on a basis of whether they're in control
or following along.
So two different players would actually have
two vastly different experiences
and maybe get the same story out of it
even though they've been presented with the same material.
So.
this is like a personal problem for me,
but I'm not good at platforming.
And this was a really hard part for me.
I didn't even notice the people in the background
that were watching me do this,
which completely changes the scene.
And then if I was even better at it,
I didn't notice that bus in the background
that brought them,
which indicates an institutional portion of their presence.
And that would have completely changed
the way I perceived that moment in the game.
They also do this great thing where the materiality shifts
from something seemingly less formal and rustic
to something maybe a little bit more industrial
and then gets curved glass at some point
and it has a scientific look.
A life cycle that a lot of technology has
from origin to militarization or monetization
such as airplanes for instance.
I don't have many critiques of this game.
It masters the use of passive and active design cues
by fluctuating the level of attention
the player has the capacity to spend outside of platforming.
This provides an allegory for seeing the forest
beyond the trees, which ends up being tough to simulate.
So going back on that initial thought,
designing for an authentic experience.
And I think it boils down to who the perceived designer is.
The environment has the opportunity
to feel as if it's been designed
by an inhabitant of the world.
Studying architecture and building taste
can improve the ease at which you design
for a varied context.
Another way to build taste is by looking at the way
directors use existing buildings as sets.
Directors frame the camera and change lightings
to recharacterize a space.
These settings sculpt the general perception of spaces
because it feels like they were built just for these moments.
So the way the Bradbury building felt
when you're watching Blade Runner versus 500 Days of Summer
is dramatically different.
And it has a lot to do with the closeness of the characters
to the environment.
It also has a lot to do with the special effects
that are involved.
So there's a lot of things that you can learn
that aren't necessarily even in the structure of a building
that can be conveyed through a variety of means.
Further mastery of this medium also allows movie set designers
to propose new contexts for style learned or adapted
from a real built structure.
So we see Frank Lloyd Wright's Ennis House actually performing
very well in the new environment of Blade Runner
in Deckard's apartment.
If you do like books, I've come up with a pretty good list.
The first book is a good place to start
if you're looking for where this line of study could take you.
The next two are a lot, and it might take some rereading,
but will certainly broaden your horizons.
That last one is like our version of Google.
It can help you find critics or authors sorted by topics.
But it's nothing compared to the recommended reading that
came with the original Sims game.
I cherry-picked the ones that were literally
part of my curriculum.
which is actually crucial to the Max's path to licensure
in all 50 states.
Thank you.
And I actually provided bonus slides
in case anyone asks a question that I
had in another slideshow version of this.
Yeah, yeah.
And feel free to introduce yourself with your first name.
Get to know people.
Hi, I'm Steve.
So in reality, no design is ever truly realized.
There's always some sort of socio-political pressure
that comes in the construction of a building.
And architectural theory rarely acknowledges this.
I have a background in architectural engineering.
In school, I was taught that architects
were the designers of buildings,
when the reality is architects plus politicians
plus whatever.
There's a lot that zoning does.
There's a lot that goes in there.
Similar to this, if you're a level designer, you're an artist, you rarely have pressures
beyond your own ideas, or the ideas of your art team, or the ideas of your design team
for how a space is going to be realized.
In suggesting that we apply architectural theory to the design of a space without also
emphasizing that we should consider what the realities of the construction of a space are.
Do you think that there's a risk that we might give people the wrong impression of how design is realized
and sort of just be teaching them the theory in a vacuum?
Or do you think that this is something that architectural theory can handle?
Like, I don't know if we need, like, fake politicians that come in and...
I would say that the value of virtual architecture
maybe doesn't have to be parallel
with the value of built architecture.
I would say that the paper architects of the 70s,
like, ha ha, you've activated one of my trap cards.
I was gonna mention the metabolists, but.
Leavius Woods has done a lot of writing on architecture
without the bounds of politics.
There are critics that do evaluate how politics do affect architecture,
and that could be an interesting way to kind of look at that.
I think Half-Life actually does a pretty nice job at introducing that,
because they have the Combine and the old existing architecture.
And that kind of war is, I think, visible through the sets
that they choose to create.
So I think that there is kind of an interesting dialogue that
can be kind of approached, but doesn't necessarily have to be.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah.
Okay.
Any other questions?
All right.
Sorry if this question is pretty general,
but how would you go about evoking dread
or unease through architecture?
Hey.
Like, do you have an example for a game or,
in the real world?
Um, yeah, I would say that things like forced perspective,
height, and things that are generally
from a worm's eye view, actually.
You can do a lot to evoke dread.
Not that architects can typically do this.
We are actually like under a Hippocratic oath of a type
to design nice spaces for people.
But yeah, there are a lot of things like Leibskin's work
in the,
Jewish museum in Berlin.
But also, yeah, memorials have a very solemn look to them.
I would say dread is something that's usually evoked
by camera angles, I would say most actively,
but, ah, Gothic architecture has a good amount of it.
Does that help?
Yeah.
Cool.
Hi, I'm John.
Sorry if I said names.
I just want to say thank you.
This talk is like really refreshing and articulate.
Thanks.
I wanted to throw that out there.
A lot of the work that I'm done, I'm interested in is often centered on kind of like the way
that spaces manifest the things that you're talking about.
And I think that, like you mentioned landscapes at one point in the talk.
And this is such a broad topic that it's hard for me to be like, what's...
It's like the way you would do this sort of thing, but I don't know if you had any suggestions for places to look for, like, the way that...
or readings on the way that these buildings,
for example, like Breath of the Wild,
exist in a grander landscape
and kind of take a context from that.
I know, I'm from Chicago and the IIT
is a pretty famous architectural school, I think.
Their student,
like commons areas like used to be a park and then they just
plopped a building on top of it and I was heard that described as post-modernist
architecture but I don't know. Actually they did maintain the sidewalks in that. Yeah yeah.
So they used the tiling of the floor to keep the same like
pathways through, I would say that as far as landscape goes,
there's a lot that actually architects
have designed utopian societies very often.
And so maybe looking in that direction of what
is a utopian society, but also the way
that landscape architects use keyholes, for instance,
which is like kind of using sight lines to direct views
and.
older gardens, like, gosh, Versailles.
Versailles is a really good place to kind of
really delve into the depth that you can put into a garden.
They had these Aesop fables, like automatons
that were powered with water
in just a certain part of the park.
So it's a very interesting thing to read about.
Cool, thank you.
This is kind of a strange question, I guess, but I've interacted with people who are working
in all different sorts of other disciplines, artists, architects, people making films,
people working in the ad industry, authors, and most of them have absolutely no interest
in video games, let alone have put in 300 hours into Fallout.
three. So I'm wondering if you could, I mean you talked a lot about your
background as an architect, but could you talk a little bit about your
background as a gamer? Oh, what made you want to come and present at a video game conference?
Probably Doom 2. No, actually I usually don't play video games with my co-workers
because they don't play video games. No, I think that it provides a great
opportunity for...
virtual spaces to have an impact on people in a way that, like you're mentioning, politics
really does prevent a lot of architects from realizing a design the way they had originally
intended. Or, of course, we are kind of a patron-based profession, so we require someone
else's money in order to realize our visions. So there's a lot of catering to the client.
you've activated another one.
We fall on these crutches a lot as designers,
which is a fair kind of,
this is Philip Johnson's list by the way,
I can't take credit,
but these are a lot of things that designers
of architecture use to support themselves
more than their actual designs.
As far as games that I like to play,
I'm playing Fortnite right now.
Love that.
And gosh, I really put a lot of time into Risk of Rain.
That's been surprisingly a great one.
It's one of those ones that you can, again,
put your own thoughts and your imagination into
because it lacks photorealistic detail,
and I kind of like those ones.
Does that answer everything?
Great.
Hi, my question comes from an art creation point of view.
A lot of the time we are tasked with creating
a certain style of architecture
or a certain kind of building,
but the level design spaces that we're working with
are not the same type of spaces you'd get from that style.
And so when it comes to this kind of,
you know, mashing two incompatible things together,
we often end up with, you know, unconvincing...
you know, yeah, yeah, I see what you're saying.
So if you had any advice on how to, you know,
create a good style, you know, as long as it says that,
you know, this is an Aztec building,
even if it's not, you know, made out of solid,
huge stone monolithic blocks or something like that,
you know, like how to put a style facade or a front
on a building space that doesn't necessarily suit
that style of architecture.
Yeah, I would say the most important thing you could do
is frame the views in the same way.
if that's at all possible, because the Greeks had imagined
the best way to view a building was kind of an angle of it.
And so you have a better idea of the whole thing
instead of just flat on.
And so doing tricks like that could also help.
But then, yeah, like you're saying,
pick up individual parts that you believe
have the essence of.
I would say materials and,
camera angles go a long way for that.
But also the proportions of things.
So if you have the opportunity to read anything
about the proportions that were used,
maybe talking with your gray boxer about those
and seeing if you can kind of meet in the middle.
Yeah.
If that's at all possible.
Yeah, there was a talk sort of relating to that called The Nature of Order in Game Narrative,
but it was very, very architecturally based on Tuesday, I think.
They had something called the 15 Rules, and one of them was scale of detail.
So, you know, from small scale to large scale in terms of details was one of those rules,
which just reminded me.
So, yeah, I think that pretty much answers it.
It's very ideal, you know, like,
talking about the architecture,
it's very sort of theoretical and ideal,
whereas like, the actual implementation
is never quite so, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, it's never so cut and dry.
I would say also picking out something
that sticks out to you in the photographs,
if you see any photographs or documentation of it,
finding a quirk in there,
and really committing to that, maybe embellishing it.
Yeah, that's a good one, thank you.
Christopher, in video games we don't have to necessarily live by the restrictions of physics or geometry or anything like that.
If you've played Anti-Chamber, he does really interesting things with space that is impossible in our mind.
And even in like dream sequences and even AAA games and other indie games,
there's a lot of tricks that can be done with space.
Is there any, I guess, literature or research that's been done by architecture,
even though it's not exactly applicable to architecture,
and how the fundamental principles could apply to those sorts of spaces?
Gosh, I know there's a lot of research done in the 90s
because people were talking about perspective
as it relates to matching camera angles.
And there was a, gosh, I know Kipnis talked about this.
He's a critic as well.
But there's...
I'll email you.
There are people that have talked about
the warping of perspective.
We call it forced perspective.
There is a classical example of it in,
gosh, I forget, it's been a while.
But yeah, there is a classic example of
just the set that goes back into space,
but it truly doesn't.
It's manipulated it in a way.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Grace.
I had two questions, and actually you just covered
One of them for the most part.
In terms of kind of bending that reality versus not reality,
have you ever found ways where it's gone too far before?
Where it's a little unsettling when it's unrealistic?
Oh gosh, I kind of like when it's unsettling though because that means that it's trying harder to hit its character.
I thought Sly Cooper was really on the edge.
That was one that really stuck out to me as cartoony buildings that take a like
entasis, which is the embellishment of the width of a column.
to like the ends of what I believe to be reasonable.
But that was also like a game that really did captivate me.
I thought that the colors that they chose
and the organization of the cities
actually did bring out a lot of value
in the architecture that they designed.
So yeah, I think that that's kind of a fun opportunity
for game developers to take, so.
Since there's no one else here, can I ask the other question?
Yeah.
Can we see the slide again that had the resources at the end
that you were recommending?
Oh, yeah.
Do you want the virtual version or the?
Like the list one, because I was going to read it.
Yeah, yeah.
See if that's it.
Yeah, you can see.
This one.
Yes.
Thank you.
Oh, this one?
Yeah.
Wait, can you do both of them?
Yes.
These will be on the thing, though, the vault.
OK, that works.
OK.
Oh yeah.
Oh.
Excellent.
Thank you.
Sorry, I went a little bit fast too.
No problem.
Any other questions?
I probably can't help you with your foundations
for your decks or houses or anything, but.
If you guys want to know about elevators, I can probably.
I've taken a crack at that.
I have a question.
Yeah.
So just curious, your perspective, mankind going out to space and gravity maybe not being
a factor in the way we build things, how do you think that could possibly evolve into
new forms of architecture?
Oh, I think we're going to go straight back to the geodesic dome.
So Buckminster Fuller was this great guy that came up with the Dumaxian sleep cycle, even.
And so he proposed this way that you can get two-hour segments of sleep.
But he was remarkable at designing these things that may not necessarily need to...
be architectural in the sense that they follow these classical rules. He took a more engineering
approach to architecture and came up with these really great things. So I think we'll
kind of go back to the 70s and kind of look at the way that architecture was designed
back then before we move forward in another way. So yeah, weirdo things.
This guy, this is kind of what the speculative architecture
of the 70s looked like.
They were just like imagining what the world
of the future was gonna be.
And here we are.
Without balloons.
Thanks.
Does that answer?
Sort of.
Okay.
You guys just wanna see some cool architects?
All right.
So this guy's my favorite, Ira Saarinen.
He did the TWA terminal.
This is actually a real life building.
It was like sculpted out of concrete.
I'm surprised that I haven't seen
many things like this in games.
It's like one just cohesive structure
that looks like it was carved out of something, you know?
This is Eric Owen Moss's Angewatt project.
It was speculative, but yeah, he kind of proposes
the juxtaposition between modern and existing architecture.
I think that's kind of neat.
Of course, my man, Libby Woods,
kind of proposing the insanity.
He's actually, he's passed away,
but he wrote a blog before he passed away,
and it's actually really great.
It's really accessible, I would say.
This stuff is weird.
Hayduk is weird, but he's great.
Piranesi is actually referenced often
when people talk about architecture.
It's just the complexity as it goes back into space
is very compelling, I would say.
This guy's currently running SciArc.
It's kind of the way that, we call it parametricism,
but it's the way that...
We're using procedural generation of elements right now.
We're kind of end users to these things,
so like the scales on the buildings
are kind of a weird feature.
Zaha's work, this is some of her newer stuff.
It's a mall in China.
It's pretty great.
She was prolific.
Actually, she was the first female Pritzker Prize winner,
and if you guys are looking to learn more about architects,
Pritzker Prize winners are kind of our best bet.
This is probably the most lore of architecture
you can pack into a single house.
Alvaro Alto's Villa Maria.
Shigeru Ban is a master of just this new architectural style that's coming to China.
He's really defining a new look.
I think it's pretty great.
Gaudi.
Gaudi is the best.
This one's Casa Botlow.
These are designed to look like bones, if you notice.
The columns are bones.
And so it's like this weird version of organic architecture.
Sana has these very clean spaces,
so if you're trying to make something
look futuristic and clean,
you can draw inspiration from them.
They use pilotes or columns without capitals or bases.
Let's see.
Yeah, that's what I got for you.
Second smaller presentation.
Any other questions?
Well, thank you guys for coming.