Thank you for coming. My name is Barry Genova. I'm the platform technical lead at Bungie.
I'm going to talk about multithreading the Destiny engine. To start off, this talk is not about
multithreaded primitives. We're not going to be talking about atomics. We're not going to be
talking about semaphores. It's more about the engine structure and strategies to increase
parallelization in the engine.
and we're also going to describe our system to help program in multi-threaded ways to prove that it's safe.
So sections, a brief overview, and then I'm going to talk a little bit about multi-threading.
I'm going to follow that up with how we did multi-threading in Destiny, what our philosophies are,
and then how we ended up mapping that to the hardware for the different platforms that we shipped.
I'm going to talk a little bit about how we proved that our code base was thread-safe,
and then how we deployed that into our engine.
and the lessons learned from that. Finally, I'll just wrap
that up. So Destiny is a shared world shooter. We want to
provide low latency action. It's a fast-paced game. It's basically
the start of a new generation for us. We're sun setting Halo.
We're starting with two new consoles, the PS4 and Xbox One.
And then of course we're still shipping on 360 and PS3.
A little bit of gameplay footage in case you're one of the people who aren't the 16 million
people who've played our game yet.
So I'm going to talk a bit about multi-threading, why we needed
to do it, how we knew it was going to be hard.
Basically, we determined that we couldn't ship without
multi-threading.
The gameplay needs to be the same across
all of our platforms.
We want everybody to have the same experience, regardless
where they're playing it, if they're playing it on last gen
or current gen.
But we've already shipped on last gen.
This workload is now much more than we've done in the past
because we're doing both AI and networking in the same game
modes instead of just networking for PVP and PVE
being single player.
Our PVE is now shared.
And so we have to basically be able to extract as much CPU as
we can out of the whole system, especially on those
last gen platforms like PS3 with the two PPUs that aren't
very powerful.
But we knew multi-threading was going to be hard.
So we had to figure out a good way to do it.
There's basically three big hard things in it.
Splitting the workloads.
You never really know what the right way is to split things.
Preventing the data dependency misses.
Knowing how your data is going to interact with each other.
And then tracking down those issues
when you've missed all of that and figuring it out.
So as an example for splitting the workload,
I'll take a look at our object move.
Basically, object move calculating the positions
and the skeleton positions by combining physics update,
animation, IK, et cetera.
And so this is usually difficult to parallelize code.
It tends to be very branchy.
You want it to be branchy because you want to be able to improve the responsiveness.
But you have that trade-off. Maybe you don't want to do that.
Maybe you want to make it so it's easier to thread by making everything the same
and getting rid of those branches.
But, you know, at the end of the day, each object is going to want to do something different.
The objects are interacting with the other objects in the system.
How do you deal with that across the threads?
And then, as they're moving through the system,
the things that they're interacting with
are changing all the time.
It's just a difficult problem to actually figure out
the right way to split.
And then you're missing data dependencies.
So let's say you have some workloads that you've got here,
like your AI update, which triggers raycasts and triggers
the physics update.
Physics updates can then trigger the audio update because maybe you've got obstruction or occluders that needs to be aware of what's going on in the physics world.
And so you can see this part here with the physics box that's moving back and forth.
I mean, that job can start late, it can run long.
You don't really know what it's going to actually overlap with, especially if you're just dependency-bound here.
And so there's this missing data dependency on the raycasts reading your physics world versus the physics world actually being updated.
And then the rare bugs. You get a bug from QA. They send you a
video. That's all you got. It's not a crash. You don't have a
core dump. You can't inspect anything. You just get this
video that says, hey, the rocket effect on this player is the
wrong one. It's the same as this other player. What's going on
here?
And that's another bug that's just, how are you ever going to
debug that?
You don't know if it's ever being reproduced in-house.
You don't know how many times it's actually gone on.
And then QA can't really tell you anything.
Maybe they told you, hey, their join in progress happened.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about the multi-threading
that we built for Destiny principles.
First and foremost, we wanted to keep it simple.
We wanted our complexity to be necessary.
And there's definitely complexity that we have,
but anything that we could keep simple
definitely helped us out.
And we wanted to keep everything as cross-platform
as possible.
With the four platforms that we're shipping on,
it's just a nightmare to have to keep separate implementations
and keep maintenance on those.
It just doesn't make sense.
And then the biggest important thing
was having to understand our data access patterns.
If you don't know what your data is doing,
it's just going to be really difficult to multi-thread.
We also didn't want to wait for synchronization.
Synchronization just takes time.
We don't necessarily have the CPU time to actually do that.
Basically, we shied away from using synchronization
primitives wherever we could.
We just wanted to express everything via dependencies.
So work that could start would start.
And if it wasn't ready to start yet,
we would just start some other piece of work.
Like many other engines, it's basically
the flow of the.
of the system is running from simulation to rendering.
You want your game world to be simulated.
You want to put it on screen.
We've pipelined that so our rendering
is overlapping our simulation.
But you'll have the previous frame's rendering finishing off
while your next frame simulation is going, vice versa.
We used a job system.
They're pretty well described by now.
Definitely seen lots of talks on them.
Ron's talk from GDC 2010, definitely a good one.
The job, if you're unfamiliar, it's just a self-contained task.
It's got some parameters, tells you what to do.
For our system, we have them at half a millisecond to two milliseconds.
And that reflects that our jobs do not get preempted
and that we have a significantly high overhead on the jobs.
It's not like making a bunch of SPU jobs where you have that sea of jobs
because you can run two microsecond jobs and not really worry about it.
It's priority-based, first in, first out,
nothing really fancy there.
Our job graph, again, it takes into account
all the different types of cores that we have.
So on PS3, that's going to be both the CPU and the SPU jobs.
And we use dependencies between our jobs.
We don't do fences.
So in this example, we have our AI kickoff and AI finish
bookends that have the dependencies for those actor
update jobs that would be running in parallel there.
What we did find, though, is most systems
tend to do the same work every frame.
You're just going to run that code over and over again.
And it's basically pretty linear,
kind of reflective from olden days
where you're using a single thread to do that work.
And then most of that work is using the same data.
And that data access pattern is going
to be the same across frames.
So we formalized this into a first class citizen.
which we call the fiber system. So we took this industry
standard word fiber and totally corrupted it. I'm sorry. For us
a fiber means a set of jobs that are going to run in sequence.
They will not run in parallel with each other. They can run
with other fibers, but these ones will always run. And we'll
call that sequence of jobs. So in this case network update,
network send, network receive. Those would be three jobs that
form an iteration for our fibers.
And then the other piece that goes with our fiber system is
there's a set of data that's associated with it.
So in this case, the network state that's accessible by all
of the network jobs inside that fiber.
For Destiny, we have three to four fibers, basically.
Our simulation contains all the game logic,
as you would expect.
Similarly, the networking is all of the networking code.
And then we have a couple of fibers for rendering that
covers all of our.
All of the work of extracting that game state from simulation
and pushing it all the way into the GPU, getting it on screen.
Fibers really are acting as a convenience for us here.
It's not like they're really buying us anything apart
from having jobs, because the underlying representation is
just a sequence of jobs.
But what it does allow us to do is communicate with people.
When you look at a big job graph and you want to know and you want to talk to other people about it,
if you're not on the same page, then it's really difficult to talk about,
oh, this specific job over here, we need to work about this.
Getting somebody ramped up to understand that is a lot easier if you basically say,
hey, in the render fiber, when we're kicking off the work to extract things out of the frame,
people can catch that very quickly.
It gives us common ground, basically, to talk about.
It also gives you an expectation of how the data is going to be used,
because you know what data is associated with it.
So there's that general feel of,
this data is owned by this fiber,
versus I'm never going to touch the network data inside the rendering fiber.
And then the other big key thing that it gave us is,
because all of our big systems are fibers,
the cross-system dependencies can be documented in one location in our code.
I don't know if you've ever had to work in a codebase where the dependencies between the systems are spread through the hundreds of CPP files that you've got.
But it's a big pain to try to figure out what's going on, especially after the fact.
So being able to have that in a single function as, you know, 20 to 30 lines is a great way to be able to look and see where that's all going.
Time control is the only real thread that we have in our system.
It's responsible for kicking off all the iterations of the fibers.
It's queued off of Vsync for the different platforms.
We had tried to do this as a job to keep the entire system as a job,
but it basically added a bunch of overhead into our job manager.
It was the only job that was trying to execute with accurate timing.
And so cutting that out just cut out a lot of overhead in our job system.
It's also responsible for serializing all the fibers,
which basically just means draining the current
iterations.
You wait for them all to complete.
You're going to do this if you need to run something in a
single-threaded type context.
So for us, that basically means, hey, we're changing
destinations.
You're going to Mars.
You're going to Venus.
We basically need to do a few things where the rest of the
game can't run at that time.
We'll also use it for system events like suspend, resume,
or some of our debugging events where we're doing patching
and developer mode patching.
We don't really care if it works multi-threaded.
We just want to have it work.
So how do we map this to the hardware?
Well, first off, this is a picture
of one of our job graphs.
This is from Cosmodrome on Xbox One.
It's pretty much an average frame.
It gets a lot more complicated.
I grabbed this frame from Natasha's talk.
And it's basically a lot of rendering and a little bit of
simulation here.
We've got over 100 types of jobs.
Basically, hard to really see what's going on unless you can
zoom in and move around, which again comes back to the fibers
being easier to describe what's going on.
So for us, we wanted to keep all the platforms as similar
as we could.
And that goes in with our hardware utilization as well.
Basically, most of the principles
apply to all of the platforms.
We usually have one job thread per core.
And the simulation fiber, we want
to keep that latency really low.
We're particular about our input latency.
So we need to make sure that we get our simulation work done
as fast as possible with as little interrupts as we
possibly can.
So we're going to try to put this on a high priority job
thread across the platforms.
So we also have async job threads.
A lot of the platforms have tasks
that we don't really have control over.
If they go to sleep, you want to query for your network friends
list.
Hey, that might take 20 seconds.
You're sending an HTTP request to log into a server,
or you're loading data off of disk.
And so these ones run in our async job threads, which
are allowed to run across the serialization events.
They can go to sleep.
They can take blocks.
Basically just calling OS level stuff.
And then, of course, we try to keep that data self-contained
so that if it does need to get serialized,
we don't want to wait for those 20 second jobs.
So I'll start with PS3.
Basically, this is a layout of what we've done for the hardware threads.
There's no affinity on PS3, so it's not like we could say,
hey, this job thread only runs on PPU0.
So we kind of cheated a little bit, and we just cranked up the priority as high as we possibly could.
And that helps minimize a lot of the preemption that we're seeing on it.
And then that job thread is only allowed to run the simulation jobs most of the time.
The other PPU thread is another job thread.
But that job thread has the lowest priority
that we could put in the system.
We basically crammed all the other threads, the middleware
and the async jobs in between there,
so that they can take up time when they need to.
And then across all of the SPUs, we use the six SPUs.
They're just running job threads to consume those jobs.
So here's a capture from Tunr.
This is job thread zero.
You can see here that the preemption,
there's not a lot of preemption events.
There's still some, but it gets a pretty good utilization.
And that allows us to keep that high priority
set of simulation jobs going, which essentially
are these jobs here.
So it's the red jobs that have been marked off here,
all the simulation work that's either simulation fiber work
or.
jobs kicked off from simulation.
And so they're all running during this time frame
up to here.
And then this red line that goes down
marks the end where the simulation is completed
for that frame.
And so we've now opened it up so that other jobs or other work
can run on this hardware thread.
And so you can see a rendering job sneaked in here
on this red job here.
On the other job thread, you can see up top here.
This job thread is preempted a lot.
Totally reflecting what I said earlier, where we put
everything else in between.
The SPUs are fairly well utilized.
We get about 50% to 70% utilization.
which I think is actually pretty good for our first shipped PS3 title.
I know we're a little bit behind,
given that other people are on their, like, 7th or 8th PS3 title.
But this one's our first one, and I think we've done a pretty solid job on moving work to the SPUs.
We've got about 20 different job types that cover most of the code base.
I mean, we've got audio, AI, animation, physics, networking, all running on the...
the SPUs, and of course we have graphics going there too, SPA lighting, other aspects of
the graphics. I think the entire graphics pipeline is running on the SPU for the most
part.
Moving on to 360. So you've got your three cores.
with the two hardware threads each.
The interesting one is the first core, so this one's not being preempted by XAMM.
You don't have that one millisecond time that's getting in, so we're putting all of our simulation jobs there.
And then we've gone one step further and hardware thread one is idle for most of the time and that allows the
contended hardware elements not to be used by hardware thread one enabling a little bit of a speed up on some of the code
for hardware thread zero.
It allows our simulation to finish just a little bit earlier.
Hardware threads 2 and 3 are just regular job threads.
All our middleware is crammed onto hardware thread 4
with the Xam update.
And then hardware thread 5 is also a job thread
and some asynchronous jobs.
These threads don't move around because 360
has affinity that we can lock the threads to the hardware
threads.
So this is a capture from Rad Game Tools Telemetry,
one of their older versions.
This is a frame from the 360.
It's a little bit harder to see what's going on here,
because we're not zooming in and whatnot.
But this red circled section here,
this is all the simulation work.
Everything past that is moving on to different jobs
where we finish the sim frame for 360.
You can see in these circled spots here,
this is the spots where we've left the second CPU idle
so that we can actually get the better performance
on the first CPU.
And then this red line over here, again marking where simulation is complete for that frame
and we've opened it up for the rest of the jobs to be able to execute on that thread.
So on PS4 and Xbox One, there's the two clusters.
Basically use cluster one, so core zero through three,
to run all of our jobs.
Again, core zero, it's our simulation jobs.
That's the only jobs it's going to be running.
Want to keep those as high priority as possible,
just like on all the other platforms.
We're able to set the affinity, so we
don't have to worry about the threads moving around.
And on the second cluster, we basically
run all of our middleware and any of our async jobs.
Here's again a telemetry capture. This is from Xbox One. The PS4 is fairly similar, although it's a little bit more idle than the Xbox One is.
You can see again at the top here, these jobs are a simulation workload. On next gen we are able to complete the frame relatively quickly.
We've got a rendering that starts in after that.
And we actually finish the rendering almost within 33
milliseconds.
We almost don't need to pipeline for next gen.
So we're going to move on a little bit,
and see how we prove that our code base is thread safe.
Because all that job graph is fairly complicated.
We basically want to be able to say, hey,
this is totally safe, right?
So the big requirements here to be able to say that is we need
to be able to get actionable bugs when we're getting it.
We can't have those bugs like I talked about earlier, where
it's like, here's a video that says that the
rocket looks the same.
We need to be able to know when that's actually
happening, how often it's happening, and then why it's
actually happening.
And then we need the tools to actually be able to debug it.
Really, we need to enforce our data patterns.
So I bring up this picture that we had at the beginning.
And you see the physics going where it's conflicting with
the raycasts again.
We want to be able to robustly detect this bug.
How do we do that?
We need to do that because we have 50 client engineers all
banging on the code.
So we came up with our execution environment.
This is our solution to this.
the thing that let us ship across all of our platforms.
And it's really a system to validate resources
and to make sure that the patterns used with those
resources are actually going to be thread safe.
Our goal is really to satisfy those multi-threaded
requirements that I just said.
So it's going to be identifying unsafe patterns,
but it's going to be doing it during development.
You're not going to be waiting to find out later
after you've checked in.
It's not going to be three months later.
It's going to be before you've actually submitted
and unleashed it upon the rest of the people who
are developing in that code.
It's also going to find the potential issues
without you actually having to hit them.
So we want to make sure that if it's
possible to have this race condition,
we found it, not only when the race condition occurs.
And it's going to detect any of the patterns that
lead to the weirdness that you're going to see that's
hard to debug, like those things where, hey,
if this job runs in a different order from this job,
you get a different result. But you can't tell,
and you can't really debug that, because how do you control which
jobs run in the different order without having put dependencies
between them?
And then if you did put dependencies between them,
then you've already fixed the problem.
It'll also catch any of the data race conditions or any
of the other.
crazy bugs that you're trying to find that are all based off
of code running at the same time, banging on the same
data. But I do want to stress that this is verification
only. We don't ship with this. It's totally compiled
out inside of our release builds. We're not doing
any synchronization as a result of what we find.
It's strictly, we're going to assert when we've detected
that you're able to do some sort of access that's
not good.
We'll talk a little bit of terminology. We have a resource.
It's just really a theoretical concept. It's nothing specific.
It's not a data structure. But it's anything that you would
want to have protected. So, you know, anything from our Havoc
world to actor data, maybe your input controller. Anything that
would be used in a multi-threaded fashion.
We have policies, and these policies describe what you can
do with a resource.
We want to be able to say, hey, this job is allowed to
pull the controller.
This job is allowed to read physics.
Those policies are associated with a job, and it's really
just explicit markup that you have to add into the code.
And then we have to provide resource access
checks for everything.
Any resource that you want to have protected
needs to be able to look up into that policy
to see if it has permission to do that work.
And so you need to be able to put in all of the hooks.
And then, of course, you have to actually have a lot of code
coverage to be able to go through all
of those if statements and all the different pathways
through your code to make sure that your policies are actually
properly protecting that data.
And then for our access checks, we're going to assert,
as I mentioned before, when you don't have access.
And that's going to be a clear assert that basically says,
hey, no, you can't read game time from here.
You're the renderer thread.
You have to get it some other way.
The policies can overlap.
This is when you have resource usage that conflicts.
So maybe you're like the example before, ray casting,
but you're also updating the Havoc world at the same time.
That's not a good thing.
These also trigger an assert and it's going to be a clear
assert that says, hey, your Raycast job is trying to read
the physics world, but you're also writing to the physics
world from your Havoc update job.
These are really to detect potential race conditions.
you didn't necessarily hit the race condition.
Maybe it was totally safe to read the Havok world
and do those raycasts when you were updating it
because the parts in the physics world that you were updating
weren't the parts that the raycast was actually looking at.
But it could happen in the future.
And then we're going to check this against all
of the jobs in the job graph.
We basically integrated the execution environment
to be able to know the dependencies between those jobs
so that we can actually tell which jobs are
capable of running at the same time.
And this basically makes us provably safe.
So as long as you have instrumented all of your data
access, exercised all the pathways through your code,
and you're only using jobs, then it's perfectly proven.
I realize that that's a hard, tall order to ask for.
But it's not as bad as you think.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about how we actually
implemented that, got it into our engine.
To start off, writing code.
This is how we basically write all of our code.
And you're going to start off doing your planning.
You're going to plan what data access you're going to have.
You're going to add access checks for all the resources
that you're going to need.
And then you can add policies to all the new code
that you're writing that basically expresses
what you're going to do and how you're
going to access that data.
You're going to run through all the code pathways.
And then you're going to resolve any of the overlaps
that it's found.
So I'm going to talk about these pieces in a little more detail.
The first part, catching every resource.
You know, you can't really just say, hey, everybody
mark up every single pointer dereference
that you're going to do.
So it's kind of crazy talk.
Nobody's going to do it unless you're forced to actually do it.
And if you don't have compiler support to force those people,
you pretty much have to put a wrapper around every piece of data inside your engine.
But thankfully for us, from previous titles,
we actually use handles for all of our data access.
So we had a single point that we were able to put those access checks in
and be able to verify that we had the safe spot.
Handles have been great for us. It's used for every piece of data in our engine.
We just found cache pointers are very often causing bugs.
You can't tell that this thing has been deleted frames ago.
But with handles, we're able to actually see that.
We have salt in the handle that basically says,
this has been deleted.
It's not the same one as when you took the handle
from before it.
So we can have a nice, easy assert that says, hey,
this simulation object that you dereferenced
is no longer up to date.
So the data types that we have, global data.
This is your standard structure that you would normally use.
We've wrapped it with a handle.
The only piece that's actually really global in this case
is the pointer into the data structure
that we've backed in the fiber memory area.
And so that's that area that I said,
the network state at the beginning,
where we had that associated with the fibers.
And that helps group the memory that's
used a little bit more cache coherent as well.
And this accounts for about 10% of all
of the data in our game state.
We also have arrays.
These are typical C-style array.
We call them datum arrays.
The only difference between this is it's got
an element of sparsity to it.
You can have different elements that are not allocated.
So in this example, datums three and four, the gray ones,
are not allocated.
But datum five is.
So there are holes in there.
These are also accessed with handles.
And this accounts for the bulk of our game state, about 80%.
Datum array with heap is our solution for variable size data.
The big usage case of this is all of our content memory.
All of the resources that you're going to see, of course,
are different sizes throughout the game.
And it's really just a datum array
that indirects into a heap.
So with those data resources, these
are the access checks that we've actually chosen to provide.
There's your basic protection, which is just read and write,
which is exactly what you would expect.
We provide array protection for the datum arrays
and the datum array with heap.
It's array modify, array iterate,
which I'll talk about shortly.
And then there's some advanced protection,
producer, consumer, and white listing
that I'll talk about after that.
So array modify is really protecting
the life cycle of data.
It's about whether or not that allocated status
can be changed or written to.
And so in this example, it's hey, datum zero going from unallocated to allocated.
And it covers the destruction side as well, going the other way.
Array iterate is the read side of this allocated status.
It's anything that you can do to discover data.
So it's meant for the typical loop that you're going to have,
where you're walking over all of your data,
doing something for every single element.
But it also covers being able to count or query
whether or not a piece of data inside that datum array
is available for usage.
The producer-consumer is our solution to allow things to create and remove elements while other jobs are capable of reading or writing from that data.
And so this is the case where you typically, you're loading all of your assets into the game.
You need to still be able to read every other asset when you're loading new ones or creating new ones.
In this example, the object update is running, the actor update, rendering objects, they're all going to read into the content.
And so they still need to be able to read that content
when your assets are loading.
Or another example, you've got AI.
Maybe you have a job that's spawning new AI,
while you've got other jobs in parallel that are updating
the existing AI.
You're going to want to be able to do that
without having to serialize those operations.
And the producer-consumer allows us
to represent that in the execution environment.
White listing is our solution for data parallel jobs.
It's about breaking up one datum array
and allowing different access for each element within it.
So you can see here, we have three actor update jobs
that are taking two actors from the datum array above it.
It doesn't need to have the exact same thing.
It's not saying, hey, these ones all have write access.
It could be that the actor two and actor three are only
read access in this case, whereas the actor zero, actor
one is write access.
So you take all of these permissions.
Here's an example of what a policy looks like in our
engine.
I apologize for showing code, but it gets the point across.
Basically, we have a policy builder.
You add access to it with writes or reads for the
different pieces of data, and then you associate it at the
end with one of your jobs.
So you've taken all of that, and we get to the point where
we have to exercise all of our code.
This is a picture of our stress lab.
We're one of the parts inside of our stress lab.
We do a lot of automation in our building.
We have 150 machines that are dedicated just to doing stress
for PC side of things.
We've got 200 machines that are dedicated to doing builds
across the studio.
And then another 200 machines that are doing
content builds for us.
In addition to that, we've got 600 different consoles inside
there that's running test cases on it as well.
And so every time you check in code,
we actually run a stress run for your builds.
And then we have overnight stress runs,
or sometimes longer, that run a more exhaustive test suite
on it.
And this is to cover all of those cases.
And those stress things aren't just, hey, run this same test
over and over again.
Some of them are monkey scripts, where we basically
just provide random input to controllers that you are
capable of exercising code paths that you
wouldn't normally use.
In our last month, I think we've done about 12,000 hours
of stress run, and then 2,000 runs of just check-ins, where
we've done stress against those.
So you found the overlaps. You need to resolve them in some way.
There's really only four ways to resolve these issues.
And they're the standard ones that you're used to.
You can add a dependency between the jobs.
If the two jobs are dependent on each other,
then they're not going to run at the same time.
The data's not going to be overlapping.
You can double buffer or cache your data.
So maybe you want to read.
At the same time, maybe you duplicate that data in a pre-job and pass it into the jobs that read it while you've got the other jobs updating it.
You can do the opposite. You can queue write messages so you know you want to update the actors.
So you build up a big list of operations to proceed and you do that at a point where the actors aren't being used elsewise.
You're basically making it a single threaded part in the future of that framework.
or the worst case scenario, you have to restructure your algorithm. You just fundamentally can't
do it. And that's the hard part. And those are the parts that you want to find early
on where it's just not going to work. I'm going to talk a little bit about the overlap
algorithm. It's a fairly simple algorithm, but it's not really obvious until you've really
thought about it. And so in our case...
We're going to take this example frame where
we've got our AI kickoff and finish with our actor update
jobs in between.
We've got another job that's not part of this dependency chain,
the network send.
And then after the AI is finished updating,
we're going to update the rest of the objects in the frame.
So the question here is, which jobs
can overlap with this actor update job here at the top?
And so step one, we're going to traverse down the dependency
tree.
We're going to mark all of the children of this job.
So all the jobs that can't run until this job is completed,
those ones clearly can't overlap.
So in this case, AI finish is dependent on the actor update
job.
And then afterwards, the object update
is dependent on the AI finish.
Step two, we're going to go the opposite way
in the dependency graph.
can make sure that all of our parents,
so the jobs that need to complete before we can run,
have been marked off as non-overlapping as well.
That case, this is just the AI kickoff.
For the third step, we're going to union all of the jobs
that we haven't marked, and we're
going to take the policy from each of those jobs
and build one big, giant, global policy that
encompasses all of the access that those jobs can have.
In that case, this is the two actor update jobs and the
network send job that we've got here.
For step four, we check that policy to see if that policy
has any conflicts with our current actor update.
And so for this example, we're going to say, hey, maybe the
actor update job just gave full write access to all of
the actors instead of doing a white list.
So in that case, there will be a conflict.
And we take the conflict, and we're
going to walk all of the jobs that we just finished unioning,
the policies for that, to check those individually so that we
can get finer detail information about what's actually
overlapping.
So we walk it.
We see that the actor update, as I mentioned before,
it's conflicting with the first actor update.
So we take note of that.
Likewise, with the other actor update, it's also conflicting.
But the network send job isn't.
It's not using any data that the actor update job is.
So we can mark that as not conflicting.
And so for the final step here, we basically just report
the errors and assert out.
So you're going to get those nice, clear errors that I was
mentioning before that says, hey, the actor update is busy
writing to the actors, while the other actor update is also
busy writing to the actors.
So you know what to go and look for from the get-go.
And you didn't spend time trying to figure out later
what's going on.
why your actors were being clobbered by other jobs.
I'm going to talk about the lessons that we learned from actually implementing this.
Retrofitting the system into an existing codebase takes a long time.
We should not account for how much time it's going to take to mark up our codebase.
It was actually longer to write markup for jobs that already
existed and the multi-threading that was already there than new
jobs.
You just don't know all of the nuances of what's going on in
the code.
You haven't looked at it for who knows when.
You may not have even been the person who wrote the code in the
first place.
So you end up with this tale of bugs that you get where you're
getting those asserts that say you don't have permission to
read this piece of data because you didn't realize that it reads
this piece of data on the off chance that your player is
looking up while jumping.
And then, you know, it was just this unending feel where we kept going at it and kept going at it.
I'm pretty sure it took us multiple months with multiple people to do it.
So we learned we really needed a relief valve.
As soon as we put the stuff in, we were getting asserts all over the place.
We had issues in our code base that we've been skating by for a while now.
And then...
That workload just explodes on all the other people's teams
because you're saying, hey, maybe there's
an issue in rendering.
Maybe there's an issue in the AI update or animation.
And you're basically saying, hey, you now need to stop what
you're doing and fix this multi-threaded bug.
But you can't really do that.
And you can't really do that all at once across your
entire studio.
So you need to have a way to ignore the issues or filter
out the issues so that you can basically add a bug.
forget about it, let the game run, and then at least know
that it's going to get fixed when you triage your bugs
later.
We also had this great experience where we thought we
were smart.
We're going to roll this out in phases.
We're going to start off by adding all of our resource
protection to every piece of data that we've got.
Then we're going to enable resource checks first.
We want to enable overlaps.
We can deal with that later.
It'll be our second phase of rolling it out.
But if you don't educate your team on what's going to happen,
then your team goes ahead and just gives full permission
to every single job.
And then you turn on overlaps later,
thinking it's going to be an easy time,
and every single job in your system
overlaps with every other job, even though the data is not
being used.
And so that comes back to trying to keep your policies tight
with what you're actually doing.
because the issue may not be a real issue it may just be that you've over
subscribed that job to different data that it can use
even if it's not using that data
and there's a balance there
you can't protect all of your resources
I suppose you could if you really wanted to spend all the time
but it's hard to represent all of the safe operations that you can do
There's a lot of things that's really easy.
You can be clever and try to pack data
into different fields.
You can try to do substructure allocations and think that
it's safe for two jobs to be able to write to a different
field inside of a structure, when really it's not because
it's going to clobber it from some weird read from the
compiler because you didn't do it on a atomic
level for the chip.
And so this really helped discourage that cleverness.
But you really do need to figure out what level you're
willing to go to actually protect.
And we did that by restricting what programmers could
actually do in some cases, just to make it simpler.
Validation is not fast.
It gets slower and slower every time you add another job.
Those overlap checks are essentially n squared.
And so we really just do the full validation steps inside
automation.
When you're checking in, you're doing a validation, but
it's not the full exhaustive validation that you're getting
from our automated farms.
But we also found that it improved communication within
our studio.
You think that you've planned out your data well, and
everything seems fine.
But then you go and you implement it, and it just doesn't work.
Somebody's using that data in a way that you didn't know.
The person who originally designed it didn't know that people were using the data that way.
And then of course, the engineer who originally wrote the code
and thought that the data was only going to be used in one way
now finally has a way to assert that that's going to happen.
You don't have to...
wait for some bug that you get six months down the road that
says, hey, Joe Blow decided to use this data,
and I don't want him to use it right now because I'm busy.
I'm busy writing to it.
So really, engineers ended up talking to other engineers.
You ran into an assert from this.
You got an overlap.
And you wanted to find the right solution.
So you ended up working with the people who architected
the original system.
And that was fantastic.
especially for new hires or contractors.
Because those people have just come into your code base
and they don't really know anything.
They're trying to get in and they're trying to do the best that they can.
And sometimes that just turns into,
I'm just going to make it work.
And this system was a good way of saying,
you think it's working, but it's not,
and we're not going to let you keep that code checked in.
It's actually faster than fixing it later.
It seems like the upfront time is huge.
It feels like you're spending more time overall.
But you're really not.
You're actually doing the fixes for this right away,
right when you're doing the code in the first place.
You actually know what's going on.
It's not the three months later, I've come back,
what the hell was I thinking?
I don't know what I did in this function,
and I'm never going to remember it
without reading through the whole thing.
But you haven't even checked the code in at this point,
and it's telling you that it doesn't run because it has data
conflicts over here or data conflicts over there.
But it also has the advantage that when you walk away
from the system, you can actually
walk away from the system.
The bug tail ends.
You get all of the issues up front.
It's not going to last for the next two years of your life
when you try to figure out why the renderer can't work with
the particle system.
The other interesting piece that we had is reorganizing our frame was actually really easy.
We had multiple occasions where people just decided,
hey, I want to be able to get more use of the CPU during this area,
so let's just figure out what runs over here.
And the easiest way to do that now is by trial and error.
You can try 20 different places where this piece of code can run,
and the system will just tell you, no, you can't run there, you can't run here.
or it will let you through for the one place that's there and
you know you can just leave it there without having to think
about it. So you're not in those meetings trying to discuss maybe
it will work here. Let's try this out. And then you've got
those three or four days when you have tests banging on it to
hope that you find some crash. But you can actually do
something crazy like change it just before beta. So to wrap
things up.
In conclusion, we shipped four platforms. We didn't have any
threading issues that we were aware of. We had fewer threading
bugs overall coming out of tests than we had on our previous
titles. And those previous titles were only on one platform.
So four platforms with fewer bugs than one platform was
pretty awesome. We're pretty confident that we wouldn't have
been able to ship without the execution environment. But the
execution environment can't actually protect everything in
the system.
Was it worth it? Absolutely. We had to do it. No questions.
We have some other bungee talks. Natasha's talk on the
rendering architecture is next at 530, room 3005. Butcher has a
talk tomorrow on the core architecture of destiny and the
learnings that we had from it, which was fairly interesting.
And Justin Truman has a talk on how we did our mission
architecture for multiplayer.
we're hiring, come work on the platform team, work in this
environment, it's awesome. Any questions?
Hey, that was really cool. What language features do you use to
declare the dependencies of jobs when you write jobs?
So it was just in C++.
So a dependency from one job.
We had a command, a depends on b.
And you pass in the handle for the a job and the b job.
And do you, I'm assuming you do this
like via some sort of dynamic analysis that tries to just.
Yes, at run time we check the job graph. That was the overlap
algorithm. And then every time they handle the references is
checking whether or not you have the policy permission.
Have you explored doing like static analysis or something
instead? There's a certain element that you can do in
static analysis, but you can't cover everything. So you end up
needing the dynamic analysis as well. So at the end of the day
it's you can cover 80% one way, but you really do need that
final 20%. So...
there's an area that you can explore so you can catch it at
compile time. But you catch it pretty fast at run time.
Did threading your client in this way present any challenges
trying to share game play code between the client and the
server? That's a good question. We certainly had issues for
pretty much everything that we did, right? Any threading had
consequences from one place or another. As for the server side,
I mean, most of that stuff is already serialized via the
networking code. You're sending packets to it. It's a big
buffer. So I don't know of anything that comes to my mind
as this was a real big issue for the server client architecture
doing it this way.
Hello, this side, this side.
And I have two questions.
First, how to define a complete code path?
Sorry, how do you define the?
A complete code path to test.
That's the same problem that you have with any case where you're
trying to get full coverage over your code base.
For us, most of that was done via explicit testing,
where we knew, hey, if you do this, this covers all of this.
Getting rid of branches that seem unnecessary
if you don't need them.
Our stress farm, again, with the monkeys
that I mentioned earlier, where it's just
a big stream of random input that helps get that coverage.
I can't guarantee that we hit 100%, but.
How long machine hours will you test?
How long in hours was the unit test?
It depends on the level of testing that you're doing.
But a check-in job is probably about one to two hours.
The full BVT test suite is easily 20 hours, if not more.
Okay, and another question.
We are putting our engine to the multi-thread architecture
and we face the same problem,
that there are a lot of older systems
that are doing multi-threading in older ways.
And we found that it's better to port the entire system
to the new architecture in one time.
So we open up a branch and when we finish doing this and putting back we find a lot of new bugs
fly out. So I want to know how do you change your old
systems to this new architecture step-by-step or
any other suggestions?
So if I get the question right as you're adding this to an existing architecture
how do you catch all the bugs without
systems. You just mentioned that. So for us it was mark up
all the data and make sure that the access checks are going. As
you find that you're going to see overlaps. We had a system to
filter out those overlaps so we would know about it. We would
create a bug in our database and basically just say don't report
this overlap to any user who is doing it until the person who is
gone responsible for that bug actually fixes it.
So that's allowed us to basically turn it on for the old systems without exploding it everywhere.
Okay, so you have two systems running simultaneously at certain points?
The older system and the new system?
So I mean, you have a toggle in some way to switch between those systems, right?
Like, you're just going to hit that as you toggle between the systems.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi.
So if you had all these really nice systems
for determining when data contention happened,
why did you build this gigantic validation test system?
Well, the validation test system is the thing that's telling us
about data contention.
Well, doesn't it just tell you up front whether or not
you have contention?
It does, but it's the only piece of our system
that is telling us about that contention.
It's not, so the handles would tell you whether or not they've been deleted.
The handles don't tell you whether or not somebody else is accessing it.
This is the piece that takes that information from the handles
and then cross-references what every other piece of data is doing.
So it's doing that, like, after the fact?
It's doing...
Part of it is up front.
So every time that you access the data, it's checking dynamically right there and then
for whether or not you have permission.
And then the overlap checking is after the fact.
We keep about three frames queued up so that you can see
which jobs within there could be running long.
And that piece is just done whenever the jobs are being
added to the graph.
It'll go across all of the other jobs that are
previously there.
Hi. So also related to this question that was just asked. So once you have handles, once you have
policies that specify what data you can access and how, and handles that let you track the data
as you access it, how do you deal with, like normally every engine is going to have a certain
amount of third party software that is not going to have handles in the code. So...
like once you have some components that just use raw
pointers.
Yes.
There's lots of middleware that just use raw pointers.
We've done things where we've embedded,
like our raw pointers for the user data
is just pointing into a handle.
We've had other parts where inside that actual callback
that you might get, you actually are explicitly
calling into the execution environment saying,
hey, check this access.
There's a few spots where, you know,
I've simplified some of the details
where it's not just in the handle access.
There's, there are those places where
that thread that's running in Havoc
that's calling your code is not actually a job.
And so the system does handle that via other mechanisms.
Okay, so it's like on a case by case basis.
Pretty much.
Okay, cool, thanks.
I had a question.
What types of data did you end up double buffering?
What types of data do we end up double buffering?
You know, there's a lot of stuff that we ended up doing.
There is the weirder esoteric ones,
like a bunch of simulation state for timing information
for networking.
Because of the time frame when networking ran,
it ran where simulation was going,
but it could have lagged over the frame.
So it couldn't actually directly access that.
It was most of the time that we were doing the caching.
If you go and you see Natasha's talk, you'll find a big section that we double-buffered from the game state for rendering.
Not the entire game state, but portions that went out and that probably encompasses the bulk of what's there.
Yeah, it seems like if you're updating game entities all in parallel, don't you need to double buffer their states so that...
So in that case, we actually, the way
that we update those entities, we have families,
object families.
So if an object is likely to touch another object,
it's going to be updated in the same job.
And then furthermore, if it has to touch an object that's
outside of that job, it'll just queue a message.
And we have a final message drain
at the end that can process interactions like that
so that we don't have those problems.
Hey, so do you only detect bad accesses on like dynamic tests?
Or do you do it on like commit as well?
So we don't need to do it on commit,
because the scope of a policy is within the entire job.
So in order to actually commit, you
need to dereference the handle.
And in order to read, you have to dereference the handle.
We do differentiate those with different functions
that we can choose whether or not it's a reader or write.
But that's just done at the time that you're dereferencing it.
And it's safe, because later in the scope,
you still have the same EE policy.
So by commit, I meant like a git commit.
Oh, I see. So yes, for our submission process runs through
the automation. That's our gauntlet process. And that's
done where you'll get kicked back. You won't be able to
submit if your code doesn't run.
So this is a pretty inherently complex system. And you
acknowledge that.
has this at A, what do you guys do for code?
How do you code review code about Fabricator, GitHub,
or so on?
And has it added a lot of overhead or time
on your people on your team having
to review a lot of code for people
that aren't as familiar with the system as you guys are?
So I mean, depending on the time frame
where we're in within the production cycle,
the amount of code review that we do is different.
The closer we are to our release point,
we have more code reviews going on.
But.
for the added amount of code review for the extra policy, it's not usually too much. There was
definitely a lot right up front when we were rolling out the system, and it did add a lot of
work for a lot of teams. But in the current state, it's basically, hey, did you run this in the test
build? Did you actually check that it's working? They say yes. You generally look through their
policy to make sure that it looks like it's doing the right thing. It's not a huge amount of time.
And this might be a naive question, but if you, if all of
your jobs declaratively declare what their data dependencies
are, why do you need to dynamically run them?
So you don't need to dynamically run them in order
for that portion, because you've got that piece already
running. That piece is actually statically checked. It just
happens to be that some of the jobs are run in different
orders on different frames. So we do.
check that at the frame level.
But for the pieces, like the question earlier,
where it's like, hey, what do you do when middleware is
calling into this code?
That actually needs a dynamic check going on it,
because you don't know the dependencies
between that piece with the rest of your game frame.
Cool.
Hi.
I was wondering if, in addition to your built-in system
that you tried using third-party thread-checking software,
thread sanitizer with Clang or Intel Inspector?
Sorry, can you repeat the question a little bit louder?
I was wondering if you tried using third party thread
checking software in addition to what you've been doing.
So Clang's thread sanitizer or Intel's Inspector,
which will do runtime checks for.
So we do have some static analysis that we run offline.
We didn't investigate a huge amount of the other pieces.
A lot of those times you get a big bucket of work items that filtering the signal through
the noise is really hard in those systems.
Yep, thank you.
Thanks everybody for coming.
Please fill out your form, survey form.
Thank you.