Good morning everyone. Thank you so very much to be here today at such early hour in the morning
to talk about ethics. It's a subject, a topic that is becoming really dear to my heart and
I really appreciate that you wake up early to come listen to what I have to say.
So my name is Celia Houdin.
I have a PhD in psychology, so cognitive psychology
is my background.
And in the past 10 years, I've been
working in the game industry.
I started at Ubisoft over 10 years ago in France,
because I'm French, hence the accent.
And I was working with the editorial team
there mostly in the strategic innovation lab.
Then I moved to Ubisoft Montreal where I worked at the Playtest Lab and also worked on various franchises and mostly Rainbow Six.
I moved early 2012 in San Francisco at LucasArts to work on Star Wars games and after LucasArts closed in 2013 I moved to Epic Games.
So I became director of user experience at Epic.
I was overseeing several projects
in terms of UX and UX strategy,
such as Unreal Engine and multiple games,
and of course Fortnite.
And I left Epic at the end of 2017 to become a consultant.
So today I'm again UX consultant, I work independently.
And as you can see, I am not an ethicist.
So this is just my humble perspective on the topic
through a cognitive science lens, which is my background.
And this is what I wanted to share with you today.
It's still very much a work in progress.
I do not pretend to offer you the right angle
to treat the topic.
complicated topic, it's delicate.
So it's just, I care about it,
and so I just wanted to offer you my reflection
and where I'm at.
Hopefully it's gonna be interesting for you,
and I'm looking forward to your feedback
so we can start a conversation about this.
Okay, so video games generate the most revenues in the entertainment industry today, while
often having terrible press.
Some of the games we've worked on, or we are working on, are accused of making people violent,
turn them into addicts.
It's quite disheartening, especially since most of this is just fear-mongering with no
solid scientific grounds.
However, as content providers, we have certain ethical responsibilities
that we need to discuss more about.
So today we are going to talk about four main topics.
We're going to talk about addiction, loot boxes and gambling, violence, and dog pardon.
Actually, I'm going to start with Dr. Edmund and I'll talk about violence in the end.
And for these different elements, we're going to go through what the public is concerned
about.
And what science actually says, I'm going to debunk some fear-mongering claims
that actually I believe it's steering us away from addressing what truly is a concern.
And from these concerns, I'm going to see what we could do about it.
Notice I'm saying here could, not should.
This is again just some suggestions of what we can talk about.
This is by no means an exhaustive list.
And this is not about pointing fingers.
I'm going to be very careful to not be pointing fingers in the game industry.
Not because we should not address these concerns,
but I think it's too early in my reflection to start doing that,
and I think it's not the moment right now.
So, it's more going to be like, hey, if you're doing this,
this is maybe what's going on with your players.
It's just, again, an invitation to think about these things.
And again, I'm not an ethicist, and this topic needs much more in-depth expertise
than I have to be tackled properly.
And of course, the diversity of perspective to define, you know,
what are the moral values I want to defend.
But because I have a cognitive science background, I can actually debunk some
of these things and explain some others, and I'll take it from there.
So it's just an invitation.
All right.
Let's start it.
So addiction.
We hear a lot about addiction these days.
And the biggest concern is video games are addictive.
And so you have all these parents
that are very worried for their kids
and people who suffer from addiction.
And in some countries such as South Korea and China,
video gaming has been recognized as a disorder
and treatment programs have been established.
So what does science say?
The Internet Gaming Disorder was added in 2013 in the DSM-5.
So the DSM-5 is the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual
of Mental Disorders, and it's used
by mental health professionals to diagnose mental disorders.
There was not sufficient evidence
to determine whether the condition is a unique mental
disorder or the best criteria to classify it at the time
of the DSM-5 was published in 2013.
However, it's recognized internally gaming disorder
in a section recommending conditions
for further research along with caffeine use disorder
and other conditions.
like alcohol, tobacco, stimulants, marijuana, and opiate,
like substance-related addictive disorders.
Gambling disorder is the only behavioral addiction identified
in the DSM-5, as opposed to substance use.
So the DSM-5 notes that gaming must cause significant impairment or distress
in several aspects of a person's life.
This proposed condition is limited to gaming and does not include problems with general use
of the internet, online gambling, or use of social media or smart phones.
So the proposed symptoms of internet gaming disorder include, I'm sorry it's small, but.
Preoccupation with gaming, withdrawal syndromes when gaming is taking away,
like sadness, anxiety, irritability, tolerance, the need to spend more time gaming
to satisfy the urge, inability to reduce playing, unsexual attempts to quit gaming,
giving up other activities, loss of interest in previously enjoyed activities due to gaming,
continuing to game despite problems.
deceiving family members or others about the amount
of time spent on gaming, the use of gaming to relieve negative
moods such as guilt or hopelessness,
risk having jeopardized or lost a job
or relationship due to gaming.
So under the proposed criteria, a diagnosis
of internet gaming disorder would require experiencing five
or more of these symptoms within a year.
You also might have heard about the World Health Organization
in late 2017 who announced that in the coming edition,
the 11th revision of the International Classification
of Diseases, ICD, gamete disorder will be identified
as a new disorder.
So the problem is that so far, the researchers don't agree.
There's no consensus.
A lot of people are actually saying that there's a lack
of rigorous research to back it up,
to really create a gaming disorder.
And it's creating a moral panic,
and it can also stigmatize billions of gamers.
We have over two billion gamers in the world today.
So if we identify what gaming is a disorder,
like a new disorder,
then we're really creating a specific classification.
And it can stigmatize people,
and again, can create a treatment or a center assistant.
Gamers that actually don't have an addiction,
they can have a problem with games,
but they don't have like a gaming addiction,
the problem may be somewhere else.
So that's right now what the scientists,
the researchers are saying.
It's not, it's really, there's no consensus.
It's way too early to draw these conclusions.
And our research found that 0.3 to 1% of the general population
might qualify for a potential diagnosis of internet gaming
disorder.
So it's very small.
And we need to distinguish between passionate engagement
with video games and a true pathology.
So whether the gamer is distressed with their gaming may be the key factor in distinguishing the two.
So this is what this research is saying.
And this article by Schubeskeel and Orban, they're saying that problematic gaming is best viewed as coping mechanisms associated with the underlying problems such as anxiety or depression.
So, if you have a problem with gaming, if you qualify to say
that you're addicted to gaming, the problem is most likely
outside of that you have anxiety, depression,
you have problems and you escape through gaming.
So, this is where we're at at the moment.
That being said, we do tend to use the term addiction
or addictive.
all the time, and we do that ourselves.
So what we could do, we could try
to avoid using the term addictive
to start, to describe fun and engaging games.
So if you look at games on the Apple Store,
you'll find a few games that are describing themselves are super
addictive, as if this was a good thing.
It's not. It's actually a problem. Some people really suffer of game addiction.
So what you want to say is this is a fun and engaging game, not addictive.
We should not use that term as if it was a good thing.
Words matter.
Using the term addiction instead of engaging
is reinforcing a stigma, and it's
downplaying real addictions.
So game developers do that.
Journalists will use that term instead of saying engagement.
Or gamers also say, oh, it's a fun game, super addictive.
I love it.
Try to think about the words that you're using.
Addiction is a problem.
So an addictive game is not a good thing.
Other thing I wanted to point out is children and teenagers have low self-control and they
have a hard time delaying gratification.
Granted that adults have problems with that too, but children even more so, they are not
completely mature to be able to exert self-control.
So therefore, maybe we should not exploit their weakness and maybe we should try, before
all the names are rated.
teen or everyone should have mechanics that encourage breaks.
Especially if you know that, I mean, if it's specifically targeted to children,
you want to have moments when there's nothing else to do.
Like, think about Animal Crossing.
There's a moment when you have not much to do but wait
until once you've completed your tasks.
So think about how we can have mechanics that can encourage breaks,
especially if you target kids.
There's also a lot of discussion these days about attention economy.
So you might have heard of Tristan Harris, who is an ex-Googler and was an ethicist there.
And now he started his own thing.
He wants to talk about all these mechanics that are made to keep you engaged with a platform.
Of course, all the platforms on the internet, Google, Facebook, Twitter.
Snapchat, they measure their revenues through the time you spend on your website.
This is how they can make money.
And so this is, they're trying to maximize for that.
This is also what we try to do.
We try to maximize, you know, we need to make profits.
So we try to maximize that, make sure that people are engaged.
But while doing that, and it's not necessarily.
We don't necessarily want to do that.
We don't necessarily want to trap people.
But this is what can happen for some people.
If you have a mechanic that you have auto-play on YouTube,
you watch a video, and after the video is over,
you actually have a few seconds before you can say, no, no, no.
I don't want to see the next video.
But they're going to auto-play a next video.
So sometimes it's cool because it's about what you care about.
And sometimes it's a completely unrelated subject.
We do that too, and multiplayer games.
Some games are rematching you in a new game automatically.
You don't have to say, you know, I want to play another match.
It's automatically put you in a new match unless you opt out for it.
Another example that's super under fire right now is Snapchat with the Snapstreaks.
I don't know if you heard of that.
But on Snapchat, if you, so you send a message to.
your friend and your friend has 24 hours to send a message back
and you know if every day you send a message to one another then you
accumulate points and then you have streaks
and apparently it's creating like for some kids they have
a hard time not keep you know stop the streak and if the streak
You know, it's hard for them to handle it.
And they're currently under fire with this specific mechanic
because it's really forcing the kids to keep going and replying.
And apparently some kids are asking their friends
when they're on vacation to sign in on their account
to keep this rate going.
So think about that.
We are also using some of these elements.
Should we not use that?
What's the implication of it?
So it's one of the things that we can try to do is avoid, to start, you know,
punishing disengagement, that would be a good start.
You know, you had the fear of missing out, and if your players are not here, their friends
might be playing and accumulating XP, and you're like, oh, I missed something.
And when they come back, they can see the discrepancy and they can see all the things
they missed.
What we can do instead of guilt-tripping them and saying, oh, look at what you're missing
and your friends are playing and you're not, and here's what they did and you didn't.
we can actually try to not punish disengagement.
World of Warcraft does that, for example,
if you stop playing and you take a break.
When you come back, your XP bar is gonna go down.
It's going to increase twice as fast as if you did not have a break.
So that's allowing you to catch up with your friends if you took a break.
So think about that sort of things so that at the very least,
your players are not punished for not engaging with your platform.
They should not feel trapped into keep playing.
And most of us, I know, struggle to survive given the competition.
So of course, the main question is,
how are we going to be able to survive in this industry
if I do a free-to-play game?
It's extremely difficult.
We see a lot of our studios closing.
Even our studios have had a lot of budget.
It's extremely hard.
So most of us, we're just trying to survive
and make sure that we have good retention
so people monetize, and we can keep making games.
But for those of you, if you have a game that's
super successful, maybe now you can
consider collaborating with psychiatrists
to find ways to identify and help struggling gamers.
And maybe consider working with researchers
to help them define gaming disorders.
So I know it's a hard conversation to have,
but there are some problems and maybe we can start
looking at it before waiting that we are under fire,
just like Snapchat or Facebook or whoever,
to start looking at solutions to these issues.
All right, so now I'm going to talk about loot boxes and gambling.
So the main public concerns that loot boxes are like gambling.
And gambling is not considered like a good thing.
And it's minors are not allowed to gamble in most of the countries.
And the Netherlands and Belgium now consider loot boxes
as gambling and are thus illegal.
The Chinese government considers that the video game industry
needs strict control.
So you've probably heard of that.
But last year, there was a 10-month freeze
before China finally accepted to release video games
on its territory.
As of today, I believe it's a freeze again.
China formed a regulatory committee, the Online Games
Ethics Committee, to oversee the approval of new games
on their territory.
And so the review can take a while.
So now more regulations are coming up,
more and more countries are looking into this.
So what does science say?
So the definition of gambling,
so one of the definition that is the most out there
is playing a game for money or anything of value,
mostly requiring an ability to cash out.
So think about casinos.
But both gambling and casinos and loot box,
and games, and RNG, but we can't talk about all that,
are a form of what we call an intermittent reward
with a variable ratio reinforcement schedule.
Heard of the Skinner box?
This is it.
So I'm going to explain a little bit what it is
because not everybody is super clear
about what the Skinner box is.
So this is behavioral psychology conditioning.
And a skinner put rats and pigeons and whatever in boxes.
And they had to do a certain thing when there was a stimulus
to say, oh, at some point, they're
going to light a green light.
And if the rat presses a lever at that moment
to answer to that stimulus, then the rat
is going to get some food, like a pellet of food.
So you have stimulus, the rat has to have a response, and if it's the correct response,
the rat is rewarded.
If it's not the correct answer, the rat can be punished.
So this is what the Skinner box is.
This is how it looks like.
If you want to shape the behaviors of rats or people,
if you want to see an increase of a certain behavior,
like say the rat is pressing this level at a certain time,
or you want the players to log in to your game a certain time,
you have to reward that behavior.
So you can reward that behavior by giving a carrot.
You did the right thing, so here's your reward.
You have a cookie.
Or you can reward the behavior by removing something
that was considered a stick.
So let's say for the rat, what it was doing
is the rat had electrical shocks up until it
was pressing the lever.
And so if it was the right answer,
then the electrical shocks would stop.
which is rewarding because now no pain anymore.
So you can either give a reward or remove something
that's considered as a punishment.
And if you want to see a decrease of behavior,
you don't want the rat to press the lever.
Then when the rat does it, you punish the rat by, I guess,
a death penalty.
giving a stick, you know, beating with a stick, so a critical shock.
Or if your player, you don't want them to go in an area that's super difficult for them because they're low level,
they try to enter the area, they have instant kill, that's a punishment, and they're like,
okay, I'm not going to try that again. They understand that this is not a good, a good, the optimum solution.
And the same thing, you can also remove a carrot.
So if, for example, the rat is doing something
that we don't want the rat to see,
then the rat is not going to have the food.
Like, we remove the food from the rat's cage.
For players, if we don't want them
to be harassing other players online, and if they do it,
well, we can punish them by banning them
from the community for a certain time.
So when we do that, we shape behavior.
And it's not necessarily a bad thing.
When we design something, it's all about shaping behavior.
Video games, it's a bunch of stimuli.
And the player is going to do some things that's allowed.
And actually, it's good.
You can min-max if you do that.
Or other behaviors are not that efficient.
And so players, through experimentation,
figure this out.
But usually rewards are more effective than punishment
if you want to see a behavior increasing.
So I'm gonna just like focus on rewards.
You have different types of rewards.
Rewards can be continuous or intermittent.
It's continuous every time you do the action,
you're always rewarded.
And it's intermittent when the behavior is sometimes.
rewarded. So if you always open the chest and every time you open the chest you have
something awesome, that's continuous. If you open the chest sometimes you have something
awesome and sometimes you don't, you have crap. This is intermittent. Intermittent rewards
are more engaging. You have different types of intermittent rewards. It can be based on
time, we call that interval. Or it can be based on behavior, it's called a ratio.
Both of them can be either fixed or variable.
It's fixed when you can anticipate it.
It's variable when you don't know when or how it's going to happen.
I'm going to give you a few examples just in games
so I can have a better idea.
A fixed interval is any time the reward
is happening at a very precise moment, like daily rewards.
You know that every morning, if you log in,
you can have your daily reward.
Now, you can log in 10 times.
It doesn't matter.
You only have the reward once.
Maybe it's at 7 a.m., you have the new reward,
and you know when it's gonna happen,
so you don't need to log in several times to have it.
It's once and for all.
So you can anticipate when it's happening.
Variable interval is still based on time,
but you can't anticipate it.
So an example in games would be rare spawns.
You know that at some point they're gonna spawn here,
so you're looking for them, they're here, no.
Oh, it's here now.
So you know that it's gonna happen.
It's not based on your behavior.
You can just dance around,
and I can do a little.
sinks on whatever, it's not going to make the response spawning.
It's just based on time, but you don't know when.
Ratio is based on behaviors, based on what you do.
When it's fixed, you have to do a certain number of actions
before getting the reward.
So typically, it's like if you have to kill 10 zombies
to get an achievement.
that's typically a fixed ratio.
Because you have to do it 10 times
before getting the reward.
And when it's variable,
it's like no matter how many times you do it,
like opening a box,
you're gonna be rewarded at some point,
but you don't know when,
you don't know after how many times
you click on it to open it and get something.
So you can't really,
you don't really know it.
And that's the variable ratio,
that it's at the heart of gamblings,
not machines and loot boxes and card packs and all that.
Back into Skinner box and the rat and all that, this is how these rewards, the impact
that they have on behavior.
So if you look, so you have the fixed ones, so you know when it's predictable.
The variable ones, you don't know how it's going to happen, it's not predictable.
Interval based on time.
Ratio based on behavior.
And you see the ones that are fixed, so after you have it,
because you could predict it, you were like,
oh, I'm gonna do that, it's gonna be at that moment,
or it's gonna be after 10 times.
As soon as you have the reward,
you see there's a decrease in behavior.
So you have it, and then you stop engaging
for a little while until you know you can engage again,
or you want to have more stuff again.
When it's variable, you don't see that drop in behavior.
It stays way more constant.
And when you see an interval, it's constant,
but it's not as intense as ratio.
You can see here that the variable ratio ones,
so loot boxes, is where you have the highest and more steady
response rate.
So we know that this is engaging people more.
So it's not necessarily a bad thing.
There's a lot of games that use that.
Every time you have a game where you have a throw of dice
is using this.
Sometimes you're gonna have a shitty score
and sometimes you have double sixes
and you're like, yoo-hoo!
So it's not, again, it's not bad
and there's a lot of mechanics that use that.
It's more questionable when you use that for monetization.
So for having people...
pay, engage through their money. And again, it's not new. I grew up with card packs.
Yeah, I was super into the middle ones. But you know, like sports card packs.
Of course, magic.
So it's not new.
What is a bit new?
And of course, critical hit.
Sorry, I should have mentioned that.
Critical hit is also sometimes you're going to shoot at enemies
and at some point you're going to kill them.
Because, oh, critical hit, you're awesome, feels good.
And again, it's a type of variable ratio.
So it's not necessarily a problem,
it's actually pretty exciting.
It's more a problem when it touches monetization.
And what's a bit new nowadays is that there are less steps
for us to really exert self-control.
Because in one click now we can buy.
It's not like as a kid you wanted to have a new card back,
you maybe have to ask your parents.
maybe get the money and then go buy it.
So there's a lot of different steps that you have to wait.
And today we don't have all these steps,
so it's harder to actually exert self-control.
And on top of that,
we can have a lot of different hard currencies
that is also adding some distance
between you and actual money.
So it's hard to really remember
if you're actually spending money.
And lastly, there are some games where you can actually get something valuable in real life.
So a lot of people are saying, yeah, but you know, in games, even, you know, you buy loot boxes,
but it doesn't have a value outside of the game, just inside of the game.
So it's not really like gambling, except that you have marketplaces where sometimes you can sell an item that you got through loot boxes.
And then it is like gambling.
So again, maybe it's not a problem for adults,
even though it's hard for us to exert self-control.
We're supposed to be able to do that.
For kids, it's not as easy.
So I don't know if you remember the marshmallow test
where kids, they're shown a marshmallow and they're told,
hey, you need to, if you don't touch the marshmallow,
I'm going to walk away and let you alone in the room.
If you don't touch it, I think it was 15 minutes,
I'll give you two, another marshmallow,
and then you can have them both.
So the kid had to stay in front of the marshmallow
and then.
The experimenter would leave the room, the kid was just all alone in front of the marshmallow,
like, ah, I tried to eat it, but I can't, I won't have the second marshmallow.
And so it's really hard for kids to exert that self-control.
And so loot boxes can be particularly hard to handle
by minors, children, and teenagers.
Don't have yet the brain maturity needed
to be able to resist the temptation to have self-control.
And again, we're not necessarily particularly good at that
as adults, but we're better at that than kids.
So developing the self-control needed to resist loot boxes,
loss aversion, fear of missing out,
all these things takes time.
even adolescent brain is too immature to exert control over impulsive drives.
Minors are not allowed to gamble in casinos and it's easy to control it because we can ID people
if you go to Vegas or you have to show your ID if you want to apply.
And so, can we regulate loot boxes for kids?
I would say we should.
The problem is that practically how we do that,
it's not easy to really ID the people who are playing your games.
It's easy to cheat and say,
sure, I'm over 21 or over 18,
whatever the age we define that as acceptable.
So it's more difficult to control that,
and that's why different countries now
made loot box illegal, like I said,
like the Netherlands and Belgium.
And the Federal Trade Commission announced this year
that they would conduct a public workshop
on loot box later this year.
It's coming, so we need to be ready,
we need to understand why it's a problem
and how we want to address it,
maybe before we get regulations on it, on us.
So what we can do is, at the very least,
we need to protect minors.
And we can avoid loot boxes when we
know that a lot of kids are playing our games,
or even more so if it's targeted to kids,
especially if it's tied to monetization, of course.
And there's another problem.
It seems that child gambling has quadrupled
over the past few years.
So that's from the Gambling Commission in Great Britain.
It was a study on 11 to 16-year-old children.
And apparently, so it's becoming a problem.
It's not just, they're not looking at gambling in games.
They look at gambling overall in like scratching tickets,
stuff like that.
And apparently kids are engaging with this
way more today than before.
And there's another problem then.
There are some gambling ads that appear
in children's games.
So at the very least, make sure that you do not allow
for gambling ads on your games that are really targeted to kids.
So they should not be bombarded by these gambling ads.
And sadly, it happens today.
Another thing we can do is explore more transparent
monetization techniques.
And maybe avoid variable schedules or reinforcement
in ratio in monetization.
Okay.
So...
Again, China is asking to reveal the odds.
When you have loot boxes, you have to reveal the odds.
It's more transparent.
It's not really solving the problem,
because even if you know the odds, first of all,
humans don't really understand odds.
So that's another problem.
But it's not really preventing us from engaging with it.
It's more transparent, but it's not really
solving the problem.
You can also, so Fortnite and then Save the World mode, they had the x-ray on their mind
which you can see what you're going to get.
So that's interesting.
And also what you really have to think about and maybe prohibit marketplaces where loot
box items can be sold.
So sometimes, of course, most of the time it's out of your control, but you have to
be careful because it's usually like you don't control it, it's outside of your system.
But you have to be conscious of that because it's part of the problem.
Okay, so now I'm going to talk about dark patterns.
And the biggest fear is, you can see here and there, is that video games manipulate
us.
Okay, so put a pin on that.
I'm just going to show you a few things
and explain a few things about dark remnants before.
I'm going to ask you to do a little game.
So if you know the answer, that's a bit cheating,
but it's okay, we can participate.
You have a bat and a ball, and it costs $11 total.
The bat costs $10 more than the ball.
How much does the ball cost?
Very quickly, do the math.
If you're well caffeinated or if you sense there was a trap
or you knew that before, you're actually very good at math,
you might not have fallen into the trap.
But most people, when they ask that question,
we don't really think about it because, you know,
we're on a maintenance mode.
We're just like, it's 9 a.m., just like leave me alone.
And we just go straight to a shortcut, which is saying $1.
If you do the math, this is not adding up.
So the ball costs $0.50.
And so that's coming from the cognitive reflection test
that was made by Shane Frederick.
And so there were three of these similar questions like that.
And it turns out 83% of MIT students
answered wrongly to at least one of these three questions.
So it's happened to everyone.
It's not saying that you're always going to fall for traps,
but you're always going to.
fall at some point, you're going to fall for a trap.
And that's OK.
It's not to say that we're not logical beings.
But.
Our brain is very limited.
We have a lot of biases.
And I don't know if you've heard of that book,
Thinking Fast and Slow, from Daniel Kahneman, who
has a Nobel Prize in economics.
He's a psychologist.
And he's studied these biases and is
part of a new discipline called behavioral economics.
So it's behavioral psychology, you'll remember Skinner box,
all that, applying to economics.
What he says is that we have two systems in our brain.
And it's not physical systems, it's not,
you can't pinpoint where it is in the brain,
there's just like functions in our brain.
We have what he calls a system one,
which is fast, automatic, effortless.
If I say three times six, you're going to get the answer right away because you know that by heart.
And if your system one is the only awake this morning, you might have just said one dollar to your previous question
just because most of the time we don't want to do math and we're just going to get to a fast answer.
System two is slow, controlled, and effortful.
It's a system that you need to activate when you have
to do more complex calculation or you have
to really think about something.
So if I tell you it's 12 times 31, then you know
that you can't have a quick answer for that.
You're going to have to calculate.
So it's activating system two.
It's costly.
The brain is consuming a lot of our energy
compared to its size.
And so most of the time, we are running on economy mode.
And we're not going to do the math,
and we're not going to apply control
and effort for computation.
When we, in everyday problems, we're
just going to go straight to the point most of the time.
So we rely mostly on system one, but the problem is that this system is biased,
because it's not careful and is going to go straight to shortcuts.
And most of the time, you know, it's allowed us to survive predators,
because we don't have, you know, to think about, is this really a lion?
I'm not sure.
We have to, you know, run away.
Otherwise...
We wouldn't be here today talking about cognitive biases, but it is with our complex environments.
We still have the same brain as back in the savannah, but our environment is more complex,
and we can fall for biases more and more often.
So it's an issue, and if your system, too, is not awake, is not like,
hey, be careful, there's a trap here, you should actually really think about it.
we're not aware of it.
And so we fall for bias, we fall for these biases
without really being fully aware of that.
And that's okay, I mean the brain is extremely good
at very quickly making sense of the world
with little information.
Again, that helped us survive predators.
But because of that, you know, we're gonna make mistakes.
I know, it's easy words.
But we're gonna make mistakes.
Because sometimes, you know, the easy answer
is not the correct answer.
So, again, all these mistakes the brain makes are insignificant trade-offs in the scale
of evolution.
However, we need to be aware of our limitations, of these biases, to avoid being manipulated
ourselves and also to be a fair society.
So we know the brain has limitations.
I'm not going to cover all that.
This is my usual spiel.
But when we consider UX, user experience, when we build a product,
we have to be mindful of these limitations so we can offer the experience we intended.
So we look at how the brain processes information, how we learn, and it starts with perception.
And then we're going to memorize what we perceived and processed.
This is how we learn.
If we don't memorize, we don't learn.
And this process is influenced by many factors,
including attention, which is really crucial.
If you don't pay attention, it's hard for you to remember.
So I'm not gonna go through that today,
but we know that perception is subjective.
What I perceive is not necessarily
what you're gonna perceive.
It's perception is a construct of the mind.
Therefore, it's heavily biased depending on your background,
your prior knowledge, your expectations, your culture.
Attention is scarce.
We can't multitask.
We're terrible at doing many things.
And memory is fallible.
So we forget a lot of stuff.
And for what we remember, it's not accurate.
And sometimes we even have false memories.
So we have all these limitations.
And we have a bunch of cognitive and social biases.
I'm not going to go through all this.
It's just to make you realize that we have biases.
And we know they exist.
And this is going to sway people.
And this is how we get manipulated.
It's just because.
We don't pay attention to everything because we can't.
And therefore, here's an example of what a dark pattern is,
is to exploit these little, for example,
because we don't pay attention,
we see the big yellow button,
we believe that, yeah, I just, you know, checked out,
I want to check out, I want to keep going,
but we might not necessarily read all the little text
because we're in a hurry and we don't realize
that we're signing up actually for Amazon Prime.
If you want to opt out, you actually need to click on the tiny little link
that you can't really see well unless you really pay attention.
So this is an example of a dark pattern.
This is when what you're trying to do, like engage people more with your platform,
is going against the experience that your user wants.
Just like check out and they don't necessarily want to sign up
and maybe they're going to sign up by mistake.
Another example that I like, it's pretty creative,
it's faking that you have a hair on your phone.
So you're gonna swipe up to get rid of it
and thus you go to the shopping screen.
Yeah, it's pretty creative.
So it's taking, again, it's taking advantage of...
a problem with attention and we don't process things very well.
If you're interested in dark patterns, there's an excellent website called darkpatterns.org
that explains what dark patterns are and gives a lot of examples.
So here's an example of one of these cognitive biases that can lead to dark patterns.
That's from Dan Ariely, another permanent figure in behavioral economics.
And ESOL subscription for the economist.
And there were three options.
You could subscribe for a year only through web, so online only.
Or you could have the print subscription only.
So it was web, $59.
Print, it was $125.
And you could have the print and web for the same price, $125.
So he wondered who would ever pick the middle option,
because it's obviously not as good as the rest.
And so he was at MIT and he did a research
with the students there and asked them,
which one would you pick?
And surely enough, most people would pick
the print and web subscription option,
and no one would pick the print subscription only.
So why do you have that option if no one wants it?
What happens if you remove that option?
So that's what he did, and he asked more students
to answer among these two options, which one you do pick.
In that case, most people choose the cheapest option.
So this is called the decoy effect.
And we use that all the time.
Again, in monetization, this is what
we do when we show the different options to buy hard currencies.
Most of the time we do that.
We have a decoy to make another option look more interesting.
So decoy, if I see in the monetization,
and sometimes I'm like, is it a dark card?
And should we be more attention to that,
should I be paying more attention to that?
But the problem is that whether or not it is a dark pattern
is not obvious, because it's a big gray area.
Look at this.
If you want to delete your character in Wow,
so that's an old screenshot.
Back in the day, if you wanted to delete your character,
it's not just like a confirmation block saying,
are you sure you want to delete that character that you spent
hours and weeks and months developing.
I was actually asking you to type delete.
And today I believe they ask you to type in the name of the character to make sure that you really want to delete that specific character.
So we could say, hey, it's a dark parent, they prevent me,
you know, they guilt trip me.
And granted, the character's not crying.
That would be more guilt tripping.
Like, oh no, you don't want to kill me.
Don't kill.
That would be guilt tripping.
It's not the case here.
I would argue this is actually a case of good UX
because it's what we call error prevention.
Want to make sure because, you know,
you put a lot of effort in that.
You want to make sure you're not deleting it by mistake.
So where's the line?
And it's not obvious, but it's for us to try to think,
talk about these things and try to decide
where's the line and what we should do or not do.
So what can we do?
We can maybe avoid dark partners for kids
and maybe reconsider in other games.
But again, kids, children, and teenagers
are more sensitive to all these tricks.
So there's guilt tripping.
We just talked about it.
There's a
So knowing how human behavior can be influenced
up until now and knowing the acute sensitivity of children,
consider this, a game targeted to kids
in which a character cries if the child dismisses
in that purchases.
It's not hypothetical, it's actually happening in some games.
These are real examples.
So consider what it's doing to the kids.
Is it ethical or not?
Is it doctrinal or not?
I'll leave that to you, but think about that.
So that's called kill tripping.
Loss aversion, so losing a streak, for example.
The snapshot example is an example of loss aversion.
We have all that, we don't want to lose it.
And so it's consecutive days of playing also in games.
Also, if you have a free-to-play game and you start playing,
you don't have to pay.
But also, you're like, hey, if you
want to keep your character, now you need to play.
Otherwise, you're going to lose all that stuff
that you accumulated.
So all that is loss aversion.
The fear of missing out.
Oh, you missed out.
Look at all the things you missed out
and all what your friends did and what you didn't do.
We talked about that a little bit.
Again, for children it can be way more distressing and harder to handle.
Pay to win, so we, usually it's a good practice anyway, like players hate it, but you don't
want to make players pay to be able to actually progress in the game and succeed, or make
them pay to ruin frictions.
Like if you're playing and all of a sudden you're interrupted and there's an ad or whatever,
For us, it's already annoying.
For kids, it's like they have a hard time handling these things.
So think about all that.
Last one, the social obligation.
hey, you really want to progress in the game?
Well, now you need to have friends playing with you
and you need to do things together.
And now they need to send you missions
and now you need to send them things to do as well.
So that can also put players in the social obligation
like, oh, do you still want to play?
Like, oh, if I don't play, my friends
are not going to have the thing that they need.
So think about all that.
And especially again for kids, it's hard to handle.
And it's not, by any means, it's not an exhaustive list,
but this is just a few examples
of what you need to think about.
Last one is violence.
So, of course, you've heard the headline,
video games make us violent.
It's a hard topic to talk about, especially.
with the recent horrible events.
And a lot of people are concerned about that.
And given that we have two plus billion gamers,
I mean, if it was creating, making us aggressive,
we would have a big, big problem.
But so far, we have no conclusive evidence
that violent video games encourage aggressive behavior.
which is good news, but the problem is you still have fear mongering, it's still coming back,
oh it's because of video games. So no, so far we can't say that, there's no evidence that we can
say that, and the problem is that when we focus on these big things like fear mongering, like
addiction and violence, we don't talk about the things that are in the gray areas that could
actually be problematic, because we're talking about the big things that are making people
panic when actually there's no evidence.
need to panic for these big things because they don't really, there's no evidence that this is happening.
However, again, children and teens can be affected by violent content. It can be hard for them to handle it.
That's why we have ratings like ESRB or PEGI in Europe.
The problem is, again, it's hard to control
who is going to play our games.
And even back when we had physical copies,
we did not ID children when they were buying a game that
was not made for them.
And today it's even more difficult because most of it
is just through digital.
So how do we deal with that?
Should it be just the responsibility of parents?
Maybe, but parents don't necessarily
know how to do the parental control on their consoles,
even though all the consoles allow for it.
So they might need help to be educated about that.
But also, we might think about.
What content we put and if again if we knew that our game is very successful for it with our children
You know, how is this content gonna affect them? It's gonna cause us some distress
How can I how they're gonna handle it?
And above that, you know, vitamin B-digens may not be associated with aggression,
but that doesn't mean that their content is not problematic.
We are responsible for the content we put out there.
And again, remember that the notions of free will and rational decisions are
at best quite suspicious.
We are swayed by our environment, and so we are influenced by society and what we see
and experience, mostly unconsciously.
And that's why we still have big problems with racism and sexism and having a hard time
getting out of it, because it's mostly unconscious.
And it's reinforced every day with little things that we don't think, you know.
is important but because it's repeating every day, every day, and every day
that now we unconsciously have certain stereotypes and now we're biased and we don't even realize it.
So this is how stereotypes and discrimination thrive.
They are shaped partly by environment, by our culture,
by our society, by ads, and also by video games,
because they're part of the culture.
They're not a specific thing that's out of it.
They're not, I'm not saying that's all in video games.
It's in everything, therefore also in video games.
One of example of this bias is the availability heuristic.
What comes to mind quickly is going to be a stereotype.
Like, you know, if you think about a very dangerous animal,
you're going to think, oh, sharks, and they kill us.
And you look at the data, it's actually there.
The chance of you to be killed by a shark is very, very small.
Not to say that some people are not killed by sharks.
Happens, but it's very, very small.
Mosquitoes kill way, way more people than sharks.
But it's not the first animal that pops in our mind.
So that's what we call the availability heuristic.
And for example, again, I'm more likely to remember women
like being emotional and crying all the many times
that they did not.
And because the women are supposed
to be the emotional ones.
And we don't necessarily think about all the times
that a man colleague was yelling at their colleagues,
which is also being emotional and not being able
to handle the emotions well.
But for some reason, this is not what pops to mind.
So, this is where we're at.
We're not, again, we have to get out of the guilt.
We just have to face it.
We are biased.
And if we want to get out of it, we
need to think about how the environment is designed
and how it's making us fall for these biases.
This is what we call choice architecture.
The design is going to encourage certain behaviors
and discourage other behaviors,
or even won't allow certain behaviors.
An example, this is again,
let's say a hypothetical example,
because it's not about pointing fingers,
and I'm not even saying that this is a problem.
But if you have a game where you can go see a prostitute
to regen health, and then you can kill the prostitute
to gain your money back.
I mean, it's not necessarily a problem, it's not unethical, it's just you're min-maxing.
This is what you're doing in the game, this is what you're maximizing for what you need to do.
So it's not necessarily what options are in the game that pose problems,
it's the options that are not in the game.
Because in this hypothetical game, can you make a durable relationship with other prostitutes
and maybe have another way to min-max?
I don't think so.
So the other way you can do it is to perpetuate violence on women, which is again perpetuating
biases and discrimination.
So think about what your game is allowing.
We love systems.
We love that a player can take the systems
and do whatever they want to do with it.
This is what makes a game fun.
But you have rules.
And these rules are encouraging players to do certain things
and discouraging them to not do certain things
because they're not helping them to min-max.
or to achieve their goals.
If you want to have more examples of that,
I really recommend you to read the book,
The Ethics of Computer Games by Miguel Sicart.
That's really interesting.
So think about your game as this.
You know, what behavior are you favoring
and what are you punishing?
And what is it normalizing in the name of fun?
Is it okay to have fun raping women?
What is it saying, especially in our society today?
What is it enforcing and what is it normalizing?
And what is it saying that,
oh, it's okay to have fun with that?
So, you know, is it, again, think about casual sexism.
It's not a problem if you have a character,
a few characters in your game that are sexy,
whether it's women or men characters.
It's a problem if only the women characters are sexy
and all the women characters are sexy.
Because then, you know, you're reinforcing that image
that women are just a sexual object.
All right, so what can we do?
Be mindful that despite the ESRB ratings,
minors might get access to violent games
and feel distressed by them.
They might see your trailer, E3, whatever,
even if they're not supposed to see it.
So we have to keep that in mind.
I know it's hard to control.
Again, I'm not saying, oh my God, no violence ever.
This is really not what I'm saying.
Just keep that in mind.
The children are gonna have access to that content.
And we're responsible for the content of our games.
Consider if your game is perpetuating discrimination
or worse, glorifying harmful behaviors.
Do you want that?
If you do, then that's a whole different story.
But if this is not what you want to do,
keep in mind that indirectly, unconsciously,
maybe this is what's happening.
Protect your players from antisocial behaviors, because also your players are going to have bad experiences with other players within your systems.
So antisocial behavior, toxicity, is a very big concern. We need to think about that.
I highly recommend you to...
look into the Fair Play Alliance, they're having a bunch of, they're having a summit today I believe
next door, also look at what they're doing, they exchange it's an org across many different
studios, like big studios, and they share best practices and they think about all these things.
Participate in that and be conscious that people with bad intentions
will use your game and social platforms to harm others.
Do you want to wait until you have a big problem such as Facebook is facing now?
Now our games can be used as a social platform.
It's happening.
And I can tell you that secret services are looking
at what's happening and the games just like they're looking
at what's happening on Twitter and Facebook.
Because some terrorists, of course,
are using these platforms to recruit or to,
and some people are just using it to spread the hate.
So.
It's happening, it's gonna happen,
and it's gonna be increasingly more of a problem.
How are we gonna deal with it?
Because we're gonna have to deal with that at some point.
But again, this is beyond the design.
This is not by design.
We know that it's not necessarily our fault,
but okay, it's happening, so what do we do now?
And I just wanna leave you with that.
There's no such thing as mutual design.
This is from Thaler and Sunstein from the book Nudge.
And if, think about that, if we believe that video games can be educational,
they can help people, be a force for good, and positively change the world, well,
we also need to acknowledge that they can negatively affect our society.
So we need to face it, we need to understand how this happens, and if we care,
try to see how we can do to prevent that to happen.
Thank you so, so much for your attention.
It's a very sensitive and delicate topic.
I hope that you found it interesting.
Please give me your feedback.
Let's start a conversation.
Like I said, I just wanted to share with you
my thoughts on that.
Nowhere near to a completed deep thought about it.
But please, even after this session,
just connect and let me know what you think
and what's missing and what you care about.
And I have one minute for questions.
Yes? Do you want to ask a question?
Have you heard of a person named Raman Shrokasad?
He's the one who posts a lot of articles about the free-to-play
and connecting it with psychology and whole lots of things,
such as consumer-friendly F2P.
Yes.
Raman Shrokasad?
Yeah, I think I've seen a few things.
I don't exactly remember.
So what's your question?
Do you know him?
No, not personally.
I don't.
Have you looked into any of his articles?
Yeah, but I remember maybe seeing one of these articles, but it's not, for what I remember,
maybe I need to look back at it.
It's not very different from what we're talking about, behavioral psychology and all these
elements that I just laid out here.
Because when I looked at the ethics in gaming, it reminds me a lot of those articles.
You should read more into it and maybe contact him too.
Sure, absolutely. There's a lot of people talking about ethics.
And I did read a bunch of it. Yes.
Hi, I just wanted to clarify something from one of your earlier slides.
When you said that about 0.3 to 1% of the general population could potentially be diagnosed
with a gaming disorder, by general population, do you mean people who play games or the population
of the world?
Andrew Shabilsky, are you here?
Yes.
The world.
I figured, just making sure.
Okay, so say that again so I can put it in the mic.
Oh.
The countries that you are referring to.
United Kingdom.
United Kingdom, United States, Canada and Germany.
All right, do we have still time for questions?
Just let me know.
No, okay.
I have signs like, no, stop.
Okay, well, thank you so much again.
I'm gonna stay here to answer your questions.
And again, like I said, I'm not saying
that I have all the answers.
I read a lot of stuff, but I didn't read all the things,
for sure, but this is more an invitation
to start talking about this more.
And I know that people do talk about it,
and this is great, so let's keep moving.
Thank you so much, and have a great GDC.