Welcome back to GDC.
Hope you guys had a warm lunch to thaw yourselves out.
So this is my 11th GDC,
but my first, very first solo talk.
So I'm really excited to be here.
My name is Pete Cooper.
I am a little bit about myself.
I'm a pretty hardcore gamer,
and I have been playing, making,
and designing games my whole life.
This is my at-home work studio space.
I try to make sure I don't have too many distractions.
So I've been making games for quite a while.
Here's some of the games I've helped ship
over the past 15 years.
I'm also the co-founder and creative director at Gamers for Good, which is a non-profit
organization that I run with my wonderful wife Liz, who's in the back there with the
purple hair.
Hey Liz!
And I've been privileged to be part of the art leadership team at Riot Games for the
past five years.
All right, so I'm here to talk about internal game jams.
So when Keith first asked me to give this talk,
I was a little surprised because it doesn't seem
like it's super art specific.
But when I thought about it, it is relevant
because as art leaders, it's our responsibility
to keep our teams creative, highly motivated and energized,
as well as ensuring they continuously have
great opportunities to learn and grow.
So before I get ahead of myself, I want to make sure everyone here knows what a game jam is.
Is there anybody here who doesn't know?
Alright, hey, got one, two.
Alright, so a standard definition of game jam is making games within a super short time frame.
In most cases it's 48 hours-ish.
I've seen them go as long as a week and I've seen them go as short as eight hours, but
it's normally a couple of days.
And they normally have a general theme, something to constrain the team a little bit so that
they have things to collaborate on.
So what I want to talk about is a little bit different.
It's something I like to call a company jam.
And what that is, it's basically giving cross-discipline groups freedom to try things way outside the
box.
So it doesn't necessarily have to be games, but it's basically just finding ways to get
teams doing things.
Now the important thing, it needs to also still have this super short time frame and
hopefully some general theme or constraint, but the cross-discipline part is very important.
It's really easy to say, hey, concept artists,
spend a couple days concepting whatever you want.
You'll get a whole bunch of really cool drawings
and that's great.
But when you make it cross-discipline,
when you combine an engineer, an animator, a VFX artist,
you know, that unlocks everybody's individual skills
and then the sky's the limit on what they can make.
So for a couple brief examples
of how I've seen this work in the past,
is I worked at a studio called N-Space
many years ago in Orlando.
And after we shipped the game,
we were given a few days to try an art prototype.
So we had full freedom to do whatever we wanted
within the constraints of it had to run on the GameCube.
This was also around the time that Doom 3 came out,
so we also wanted to try some cool dynamic lighting.
Anyone who's worked on the GameCube knows
that's almost impossible.
And another example is when I worked at Blizzard on Diablo 3, there was a point where all the
designers were all trying to solve a specific problem and a bunch of the rest of us were
given a few days to figure out and implement any dungeon mechanic ideas we wanted.
We came up with a whole bunch of really cool things and it was really great because when
we presented it to the designers, they were really surprised on what we were able to come
up with on our own.
Now the best example I've ever seen of this is something called
riot thunder dome. And here is a five minute video that will
explain it better than I will.
Thunderdome starts with this jolt of adrenaline.
Three days, over 70 teams.
We've got over 380 people participating in Thunderdome.
It's really about getting teams together to just try
kind of moonshot type things.
If you're doing Thunderdome with the people
that you work with every day,
you're doing Thunderdome wrong.
The team and I are taking League of Legends characters
and we're actually making a fighting game.
We're working on a project to basically
build some robot minions and have them fight.
So we're working on a game called Clash of Fates.
Two players playing head-to-head.
Whoever has the fastest reaction time wins out.
Yeah, let's go and get all the stuff over there.
We're going to try to take six months of work and put it into three days.
So the planning process needs to be really fast and really tight.
We're doing something entirely within our day jobs.
And this is a chance for us to work together on not only something that we can team up and use our skills on,
but something we can develop new skills together with.
So do you want to start mocking up on UI or anything?
Yeah, I mean just anything that we need to get to here.
So first priority is the health bar thing.
We had some hiccups with the Roombas that we ordered.
We're a little bit out of date models because we were trying to be out of budget.
They're actually two months too old to really truly be hackable.
So that's a really big challenge.
We should have a rough something on the screen in two hours.
It's not just about getting everything done, it's about also them playing it and changing it and playing it and changing it.
It's a cool opportunity to try out new technology, play with some stuff that I've been eyeing in the past few months,
and really push myself to see what I'll be able to do in the next 48 hours.
I'll probably take the animation that we showed the first step and we'll see what all the integration steps are.
Got it. Ready? Let's do it.
Day two is just sort of most of the day is just freaking out and wondering if we can
get done on time.
You know it was really great to see the minion molds progressing and like it was starting
to really look like minions.
I sat down and just basically started editing the code that we had done and refactoring
that.
Doing the lights blinking and the eyes and the wand.
For me, I don't ever touch code, and, you know, being able to do that and play around with electronics for a couple days was really cool.
I'm pretty sure what's going to end up happening is everybody will have something awesome on their own machine,
and then we'll mash it all together and they're going to be like,
oh, crap, Frankenstein fighting game.
Okay, I really do have to target those little statues, they look like big ups.
Yeah, they're too bright.
It's like, you know, can we still get everything done if we stay up all night?
It's not loading yet?
Start making the tough choices.
Do we have time for it?
You should try it if we don't.
Yeah, we have an hour and a half left to cut off.
Right now we're just polishing up.
We've been up since, myself, 7th Jane. We were here all night last night.
We're not necessarily the appropriate people to make this type of game by our job title,
but absolutely by what our passion.
Is it working?
Best of three.
As much planning as you do when creating games, you never really know if something's fun until
you have your hands on it, you know, and that always feels so good when it's like, oh my
god, I played it and it was fun.
Oh!
We were changing versions at the very last minute.
I'm down to the wire, I'm pencils down.
We're rushing around trying to finish everything and put the finishing touches on the minions
both visually and...
in the code. So trying to finish all of that in just a couple hours was a little bit hectic.
We're like, you know what? This is what we're going with. This is good enough.
This is our victory dance. It's official now. It's the moment of truth.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
At the end of Thunderdome we have this awesome science fair where everybody presents the
work that they've been doing for the past three days.
We're a very teamwork oriented company.
Engineers, it's programmers, it's artists, you know, audio, everything comes together
to create these things.
And it's sort of how we work at Riot.
You know, there aren't a lot of barriers between different disciplines.
Everybody crushes together and makes something cool.
Three days ago, this was just like an idea in our heads,
and now it's a thing we're actually playing.
People get joy out of it. That's what I want.
Each Thunderdome, we try something more and more difficult,
until one day, maybe we'll be doing something that we didn't even imagine we could do.
To me, this just reinforces how special a place this is.
You guys continue to amaze me every time.
Thanks.
All right, that's Thunderdome.
So, and that's the end of my talk, thanks.
Okay, so I want to talk about six of my personal Thunderdome experiences and what I've learned
from them and what value I think doing these type of jams for any company has.
Okay, so my first Thunderdome was about a month
after I started at Riot.
This was close to six years ago at this point.
And I was initially on the environment team.
So that crew decided that they really wanted
to make a new map.
They wanted to give that a try.
So we had these seven guys,
and this was our team comp.
You can probably see some challenges already here.
So,
This was super exciting for, this is a 48 hour jam,
and this was very exciting for about the first 15 hours.
But then you realize, okay, we're ultimately
this exact same team doing the exact same job.
And by hour 25, you have people who had no energy,
people who were actually fighting amongst themselves,
and the inevitable
ran out of time.
Artists are notorious for being horrible at time management,
at least in my experience.
So that was pretty rough.
So lessons learned.
Team composition matters.
Having all one discipline is a pretty bad idea.
Working with new people is really important.
It teaches you a lot about teamwork, collaboration.
Finishing something is important.
We went in saying, we're just going to have fun.
And whether we get done with something or not, it's all good.
But I could tell everyone on the team
was really disappointed because we
weren't able to get it done.
And producers, while I've always appreciated producers,
I appreciate them a whole lot more
during a very tight game jam session of 48 hours.
And it doesn't really have to be a producer per se,
just someone who's paying attention to the time,
who's allocating resources appropriately,
who's ensuring people are hitting milestones,
and it's, you know,
I gotta have those organized people in place.
Okay, so fast forward to the next Thunderdome.
So this was right before League of Legends All-Star break
where we have pro players,
and we have this thing where some of the pros
do one-on-one matches,
so we decided let's try to make a one-v-one mode
during Thunderdome.
And this time we learned from our mistakes. So we actually had a real team with designers,
engineers, producers and QA and audio. That was good. So a few key things that happened.
At the beginning we were thinking about themes,
what could the themes be?
And someone had an idea to use Magma Chamber.
So for history on Magma Chamber,
this was an old map that we were trying to make
for players a long time ago, a huge map.
And it ended up getting canceled for a lot of reasons
and there was a lot of disappointed players.
So someone had the idea of,
hey, let's just redo Magma Chamber in this
and maybe players will think that's cool.
Next thing, this is my buddy Chris Haga. He's an amazing guy for anyone who knows him. So
Chris Haga is a super soldier Viking. He's like, we don't need sleep, we're just going
all in. Let's do this. By hour 15, Chris Haga was a fucking zombie. Like, he was completely
useless. He was the sole VFX artist on the team. I hope he's here. Is he here? But anyway,
We were trolling him by asking him when you're going to have that lava fall in. He kept saying
I'll get it in ten minutes. We would ask him in an hour and he'd say the same thing. I don't
even think he had any understanding of time for a ten hour gap. That didn't work out too well.
But besides that, we did have a producer.
And other than Chris Haga, we were able to allocate
resources properly, get everything working,
and that was fantastic.
We weren't stressed about anything,
because someone was paying attention
to everything that had to get done.
And another thing was at 6 a.m., my awesome wife
brought us breakfast burritos one day,
and that was pretty amazing.
Thanks, Liz.
So here is the map we ended up with.
We wanted, this was the magma chamber, dark lava theme.
There's Chris Haga's lava falls,
he actually managed to get in.
So this was pretty cool, we were really happy with it.
We had fun making it and overall it was great.
But something we realized is there was another team
that was doing something
that they were having even more fun with.
So this is a character on the left, Hecarim in League of Legends.
He's like a dark, shadow isles, centaur, evil dude.
And one of the crews had the idea of doing an arcade skin line,
which is really over-the-top, silly stuff.
And there was producers at the company who didn't think this was a great idea,
so they used Thunderdome to prove it.
And during the development of this, these guys were having a blast. They were making 8-bit
pixel VFX. We could go by and hear all the silly ass sound effects they were trying to make.
All these beep boop bops and rainbow unicorn horns. They were having such a great time. That
was a pretty eye-opening experience.
So while this was really great, it made me realize,
okay, this is tonally pretty similar
to what we regularly do.
We do a lot of fun, silly stuff,
but I'd say 90% of it is kind of in the serious,
the little more serious space.
So this is where I decided that going forward,
we want to do more lighthearted stuff.
Another thing that happened is
some players thought the magma chamber thing was cool,
other players not so much.
Because we promised this huge thing and then ended up
canceling it, then when we showed them this tiny little
thing that we made, look, we brought Magma Chamber back.
They're like, bullshit, that's not it.
So they were pretty disappointed in that.
And then we weren't actually able to ship this mode to them.
We were trying to, but we had server issues, so we couldn't
get it done.
So they were double upset about that.
So lessons learned this time.
Number one, sleep is good.
That kind of sounds like a no-brainer,
but I've seen a lot of people try to do game jams
and try to do the all-nighter thing,
and sometimes it works out great,
but every time I've seen people just go home,
sleep, come back fresh,
you end up getting a lot more done anyway.
Player expectations.
You know, if you promise something to players,
don't surprise them by saying,
look, we made it something else.
Isn't that cool?
Team size doesn't matter when you have organized people.
This, we thought this team was a little large.
It was 10 people.
So we were a little concerned,
but it ended up working out perfectly fine
because someone was paying attention.
Someone was organized.
And finally, theme and tone can affect work tone.
So because you're in such a tight timeframe,
I feel like doing more lighthearted things
keeps the entire tone of the project
and then tone of the team in a much happier place.
Okay, so next time on Thunderdome.
This time we decided let's make a map skin.
All right, so for a little context, this is ARAM.
This is a mode in League of Legends 5v5 single lane.
And this is Alex Gonzalez,
one of my good buddies and amazing concept artists.
And one Monday he comes to work and says,
hey, check this out.
I did this drawing over the weekend.
I think it would be really cool
if we made a map skin of ARAM.
What do you think of this?
I'm like, wow, this is really cool.
This is awesome.
We've never done a map skin before.
Maybe we should try that.
I'll talk to the production crew
and see if somewhere down the line
we can get this on a schedule somewhere.
And he's like, well, Thunderdome's coming up,
how about we just do it for Thunderdome?
And my initial reaction was like, what?
That's, look at how much content that is.
That's insanity.
And then I was looking at it, I'm like, you know,
there's a lot of stuff that's kind of duplicated,
you know, we may be able to pull it off,
but we're gonna need a pretty big team
if we're gonna do it.
So.
We decided, all right, let's just see how big a team we can make.
So we got a team of 25 people.
I believe 20 of the 25 were artists.
This is a very art-heavy experiment.
So a couple of key things that happened.
So, right before it started, I went to Party City and bought a whole bunch of stupid pirate
props.
I bought foam swords and hats and eye patches, doubloons.
Actually found, I was shocked, they had pirate ship pinata.
I was like, sweet, that's perfect.
So in order to try to keep the fun going, I wanted to do that.
And that actually really helped.
This was really important.
Say yes to everything.
So.
One of our jobs as leaders is actually to not specifically shoot down ideas, but we
have to block a lot of crazy things from going into our products because we have a cohesive
vision that we have to uphold.
So during game jam scenarios, this is an amazing opportunity to let people put in whatever
crazy, absurd, nutty ideas they want to.
Any time anyone walked up to me and said,
hey, what do you think of this?
I'm like, that sounds ridiculous, let's do it.
And this is actually where I fell in love with whiteboards.
There was a point, so there was huge concern.
20 artists were gonna be stepping on each other's toes
left and right, this is gonna be a total disaster.
And I've never been able to get
artists to use Jira or Trello or any of these damn tracking things. Any artists here like
Jira? Are you a tech artist?
So Tim Hill, a producer at the time, he rolled in a whiteboard and was like, guys, just write
down all the shit you want to do. And just write it all down on the board and then just put
your name next to the thing you're putting in and when you check it in, cross it off.
And that was phenomenal.
That was the most amazing eye-opening thing.
Because anytime anyone can get up,
you just look over and say,
oh, hey, Steve's working on the river,
and Bob's working on X and Y.
And it was really great.
We stopped a lot of people
from stepping on each other's toes.
And that made me fall in love with whiteboards.
And I've used them ever since.
So here's a...
video of our production.
So we started by stripping everything out of the map.
And then we did a build every couple hours
that showed all the crap that was going in.
So, man, we put in so much stuff into this.
It was pretty nutty how fast it went in.
And I ripped the audio out of this
because I asked someone for this video
and I think they trolled me
by putting the Pirates of the Caribbean
old ride theme on it.
And it was super obnoxious.
So yeah, we made all new nexuses, turrets, minions, just tons and tons of content. We
actually figured out new tech that we ended up using in the future. Things like rotating
turrets, lots of destruction. Made a new mini map in the bottom corner. People are just
throwing in all sorts of stuff. I don't even know what that is.
There's the rotating turrets. That was really cool. This was a really neat thing. Someone put in the
two boats and they made it so when one of the red side turrets gets destroyed, the blue ship
shoots and vice versa. And then when the last turret gets destroyed, that ship goes down. So
there was just a lot of people trying brand new things that nobody knew how we would make them
work. And...
It was great.
Nobody was saying no to anything.
We were all just trying to get stuff in.
And then here's this great illustration
made by Bo Liu in about 12 hours.
He's awesome.
All right, so my lessons learned from this
is big teams are awesome.
Like we were really concerned about how large this team was
and it worked out super well.
So we're like, sweet, there's no downside.
As long as you have organized people,
you can make it happen.
Prioritizing having fun was a really big win.
Like everyone had a great time the whole time.
Whiteboard tracking for the win.
Holy shit, I love whiteboards,
as you can tell from this talk.
And yes to all ideas.
And not just yes to all ideas.
It's one thing to give someone permission to do a thing.
It's another thing to be really supportive about it.
So if someone comes up and is like,
hey, I got this idea.
Cool. Not only can you get it in, what can I do to support you from getting it in? Can I help
you make a model? Can I help you animate something? And that was a big win. And we also
found out we can make a ton of content really quickly.
After this Thunderdome, we had people from all over the company coming up and saying,
how are you moving so fast?
How can we figure out how to get this type of urgency, this type of speed into our regular daily jobs?
We surprised a lot of people on the team and outside the team, and that was really fantastic.
And this is where I decided that I want to change goals for how I want to go forward with Thunderdome.
So.
One of the things, and I love Riot, but one of the issues that I have is we have a lot of people who
kind of fall into the paralysis by analysis camp. We have philosophical debates about, you know,
the trim of a frame on an icon sometimes. So I wanted to use Thunderdome to
Show people and remind people how quickly we can move,
how fast we can make decisions.
So here are some of the goals that we move forward with.
Make games without over planning.
Do as little pre-production as we possibly can.
Go in pretty blind and see what we can do on the fly.
Get lots of people involved.
I wanted to grab people from all over the company
to make sure we're working with lots of new people
and exposing as many people to this type of jams as possible.
And finally, push people out of their comfort zones.
Try to get people learning,
try to get everyone learning something new
every time we do one of these jams.
Okay, so fast forwarding.
So we've done a bunch of modes, some maps,
a lot of these little things.
We're like, all right, this time
we're just gonna straight up make a game.
Let's see what we can do. So someone came up with a very basic idea of a minion side
scroller. And then I was like, cool, that's a great idea, let's leave it at that. And of
course people wanted, oh, well let's plan some stuff out. No, no, no, stop. That's it.
No planning. Don't do it. Caught a couple people trying. Blocked them. Stop it. Burn
that. Let's not do it.
Okay, so we actually ended up with another 25 person team.
It wasn't the same.
We had about 10 people from the old team
and about 15 new people.
We actually grabbed a couple of people
that this was like their first week at Riot.
Brand new people, so lots of new faces.
We found a room that had a gigantic whiteboard,
which was awesome.
I was like, okay, right when it starts, we have a beginning,
because minions start at a crystal,
then they go to the other side crystal.
So we have a beginning and end of the game.
Now everyone just throw out whatever ideas come to mind.
What do you guys want to see in the game?
And so we did this ridiculous brainstorm of,
hey, let's throw some minions in there,
let's have an epic forest vista,
let's drop Anivia the Icebird in there
and have her drop ice walls
and we'll throw zigs throwing bombs
and have cannon minions
and have Nautilus in mid lane smashing 100 minions
and then you go into the jungle and there's crabs
and people just threw out a million ridiculous absurd ideas.
And then you blow up the crystal at the end
after you fight a super mech minion.
And I was like, all right, sweet.
Now we have 40-something hours.
Where's the producer to organize this?
So 48 hours of development.
Some really cool things happened.
First off, we decided to do flash style 2D style development.
This is primarily because no one on the team
has ever done this.
So we wanted to get people learning new things.
And this was amazing.
Within the first few hours,
there was constantly people going,
hey, I figured out how to do this thing.
Five other people crowd around them and go,
oh sweet, I see, now I get it.
We had concept artists learning new things,
animators, everyone across the board
was learning a brand new way to build things.
This was the first time we purposely kicked everyone out.
We're like, all right.
We probably had one or two people who did a couple,
the super-lates or all-nighters,
but the vast majority of everyone were like,
go home, get a good night's sleep,
nine or 10 p.m., take off,
and then come in the morning fresh.
And it worked out really well.
And the other thing is we spent so much time focusing on learning and putting a million
things in the game that we forgot about the all important thing of iterating.
We had zero time.
So the game was put together, it was Frankenstein together at the very, very last minute.
So we're like, we don't know if this game is any good.
So here's a video.
Of course, you've got to start with that screen.
So we made this really cool intro.
I love motion graphics people.
They're hot.
So we started as a single player game
and then like 5 minutes before
we ended, let's just do multiplayer, why not?
So we just have this
super fun
silly
minion
game.
And no time to animate an enemy, I throw her up in the air and shoot, sweet.
Alright so this video is really long so I'm just gonna take screenshots.
So we fight shit tons of minions, you fight a cannon minion, then you have Nautilus, and
then you go into a jungle.
We made a ton of different environments.
You fight the epic crab boss, then you go to the river.
where you fight piranhas and all sorts of other crap,
and then you go to the other outside and you fight towers,
and then here's the ultra minion mech,
and there's a ton of stuff between this,
and then you go to the Nexus,
and then Garen comes in and takes the last hit
and takes credit for the win.
That's why it's called Last Hit.
So this was a pretty amazing experience,
and there's some really good lessons learned from this.
Number one, we can make a game with almost no planning.
And that was really cool to see.
It surprised a lot of people on the team,
and I think it woke up a lot of people to that reality.
Number two, no crunch needed.
You can totally...
You know, get some sleep.
You know, prioritize.
You can do jams without doing all-nighters.
You know, it's totally doable.
Accelerated learning for the win.
I think this is the biggest amazing lesson.
Like, we all know people on our teams who say, oh, you know,
I really want to learn this new program.
I really want to learn this new thing.
I'm going to put it on my six-month personal development
plan, and hopefully I'll find time to do tutorials.
And then two years later, they still don't know it.
So forcing people to learn things during a game jam is amazing
because you only have two days.
You're going to learn it because all these other people are counting on you to learn it.
So no one wants to let the team down.
So that's a pretty amazing thing.
And finally, this game kind of sucks.
Because we just didn't think of it as a game for some reason.
We just didn't think about iterating on it.
Alright, so fast forward.
This time let's make a good game with no planning.
So one of the things I realized afterwards is
we didn't do a lot of planning, but because we already had a theme
everyone already kind of had in their mind
alright, we know what it's going to look like
we know the characters, you know.
So this time...
No theme, no nothing, zero planning.
Other than we did say we wanna make a twin stick shooter,
but that is it.
This time we brought in a bunch more people.
I was actually inviting people who've never made games before.
At this point I'm inviting people from HR, from facilities, finance.
Like, come on, who wants to help learn something to make a game?
Let's do it.
So when Thunderdome started, we had a vote.
We just had everyone in a room and say, okay, let's vote on.
What themes do you guys want to make?
What's the characters?
What's the environment?
See if we can make a game designed by committee
and still actually have it be good.
So like I said before, we were asking a lot of other people.
And also, this time.
Well, one of the things that stops people from doing Thunderdome at Riot is people are really busy.
So there's like a big commitment to say,
okay, I'm going to go ahead and do the whole end of the week.
I'm just committing to Thunderdome.
So a lot of people have meetings.
A lot of people have end of the week milestones they're still trying to hit.
So this time...
I just said, you know what, if you can dedicate any time, an hour, two hours, if you just
want to stay one evening, it doesn't even matter.
Anything you want to contribute, that's awesome.
You can totally be part of the team.
So another cool thing is...
We had a cool twin stick shooter up and running pretty quickly, but we didn't have any really
interesting unique mechanic. I believe it was one of the guys on the merge team who
actually came up with the idea of having like these Tetris style blocks falling into the
play space and creating blockers. That was really cool. So this is my buddy Warren who is a
phenomenal animator. He doesn't look anything like this. He doesn't wear glasses or ties or
anything. I just love this picture.
And late in the second day, he walks up to me and says,
hey, we're just about done with all of the animation
of the game.
I want to try making an intro cutscene thing.
And I'm like, OK.
So you're saying, I'm like, do you have a plan?
He's like, no.
I'm like, OK, awesome.
So within the next couple hours, you
want to plan, storyboard, animate, find audio support
to get an intro into the game.
All right, let's see if we can make it happen.
And I actually did.
And Liz made us some awesome arcade themed cupcakes.
Thanks again, Liz.
My wife, she's amazing.
So here's a video.
Hell yeah.
Arcade.
This is where we were voting.
Looks like our MVP is going to be Lucian Jinx.
Super arcade gunners to the something.
So are we voting on names?
That's one of the dumbest name ideas.
Oh shit.
Five minutes.
Good morning everybody!
Whoa, that's loud.
Welcome to day two!
Whee!
Day two of making a fucking game.
So here we are.
Wow, Wednesday's dead.
Bow! 9am is dead. We'll call that 10. Just kidding, 10 is dead. Where we at?
1041 to 1 o'clock. Alright, who's the engineers? How much time we got?
Someone who knows math. Tell me how much time we got.
We actually made t-shirts. That was pretty funny.
So we found out one of the people's SOs has a side t-shirt company.
So we're like, can we just get t-shirts made, like, right now?
Who's got a graphic?
Let's do it.
And that was fun.
And here's the actual story trailer and gameplay thing.
Zero Iteration was the name of our team.
Kind of trolling ourselves.
This was like a Smash TV kind of thing.
The Garin Gun.
Fires spinning Garins.
That was my first attempt at pixel art.
Someone's like, hey, we need to cover...
Oh, yeah, pixel art. That'll take about an hour.
Pfft, yeah, I was wrong.
So, lessons learned.
Pixel art is fucking hard.
Bonus props to everyone who makes pixel art.
I was surprised. I've never actually done it before.
Next thing is part-timers welcome. That was a really big win. Letting people join who, it just
basically alleviated anyone from having an excuse to not join in. It's like, hey, if you have two
hours, if you have a lunch break, come on and learn something real quick, have fun. This is an
obvious one. The best ideas can come from anyone. I mean, everyone knows that. But it's really
great when there's super clear examples to point out to people.
And anyone can help make games.
Like, I mean, we really had all sorts of people on the team
who aren't even game developers join in,
learn how to animate something real quick,
learn how to do a VFX, learn how to implement a model.
That was really great to see.
All right, and for the final one,
we decided let's see if we can make
and ship a game with players.
So here's the pitch.
It was...
We're gonna come up with five different game types
and a whole bunch of themes and create a survey,
put it on the League of Legends forums
and let players vote on what it is.
And we'll have the voting end
the minute Thunderdome starts.
So there's zero chance for any pre-production whatsoever.
So we know what it is that we're making
right when it starts.
live. So give players live updates, give them builds, take
their feedback. And then the goal is to build, finish and
ship a game in 48 hours. So we wanted to have it up for anyone
to download and play by the time Thunderdome ended. At this
point I have no idea how big the team is. I think
Someone brought in their mom at one point.
It was massive.
I don't even know how we organized that.
So here's the thing we threw up on the forum.
So yeah, we had the five different game types,
Infinite Runner, Match 3, 2D Platformer,
Gallery Shooter, and a Rhythm Game.
I was really pulling for Rhythm Game.
But the vote ended up being 2D platformer in the arcade theme.
Arcade theme is popular, you know, thanks to that team, Thunderdome, back in the day.
All right, so let's just hop right into one of the dev videos.
It's great having people who are recording shit for you.
I hope this was the little end sequence, what you get when you win the game.
Doran's Ring, that is a shitty item for anyone who doesn't play League.
It's a great starter item, I shouldn't say shitty.
My job is to stand over people, as you can see.
All right. So, despite the fact that we have a
Getting everyone to spend time communicating with players,
getting feedback, all the enemies in the game
were originally concepted by just some random people
on the forums, which was really great.
And then we were translating the game.
Despite that, this went really, really smooth.
It was actually strange.
I remember looking over at our head producer, Blake,
when we were about halfway through going.
Why is this going so well?
Normally, stuff is on fire,
like things are breaking left and right.
We have people putting things in
that have never put anything in before,
so you know what that looks like.
But this went crazy smooth.
And that was amazing.
And here is our actual game trailer.
This is what it ended up being.
This is Arcade Slash!
Alright, so...
Lessons learned.
Number one, planning is overrated.
I mean, obviously this is a gross generalization, but we proved multiple times that teams can
absolutely make things without any kind of pre-production, just making things on the
fly.
And it's absolutely doable, and it actually greatly raises teams' confidence level in
themselves and their abilities.
Engaging with players is amazing.
That was a really, really great thing.
Interacting with your audience is hugely beneficial.
I believe it actually keeps and creates long-term fans.
And just, that was,
it actually made me want to start streaming myself.
It was really great to just be part of the,
be part of the actual player community.
And we proved that we could kind of accomplish anything.
So that was really great.
OK, so before I end, I want to talk quickly
about some Game Jam resources.
Now, not every studio has the resources of a Riot Games
or has the ability to.
to actually make a giant Thunderdome style thing happen.
But there's a lot of great resources out there
that exist that can help figure out
how to make a game jam possible.
One great thing is, I can't talk about game jams
without talking about Global Game Jam.
Global Game Jam is this amazing worldwide game jam
that happens every January.
And it's huge. So as of February 24th, the day I made this slide, there was 42,811 people
registered at 803 jam sites located in 108 countries around the world. So global game jam
is really massive.
So here's some of the posters that are made
for the different locations.
So there's Mexico and Singapore,
and I had to represent Portland, that's my jam site.
And here's some pictures of some of the people
who are at these jam sites.
Some of them are small, there's 15 people,
and other ones have hundreds of people
that show up to do this.
So Global Game Jam is an amazing thing.
And there's ways you can help by simply letting,
if you can just have your,
Global Game Jam happens over the weekend,
so if you can get your office to just sponsor
a Global Game Jam for your teams,
that'll be a really amazing thing for them.
You could also do simple things like sponsoring
with supplies, snacks, and t-shirts.
You could even do a thing where,
allowing your people to go to Global Game Jam over a weekend and then giving them the
next Monday off.
And that would be the only thing you actually have to do yourself, is eat one day.
Now Global Game Jam always happens at the same time in January, but there's game jams
happening all the time.
So this is a site called Game Jams on itch.io.
This is a huge calendar and it's always full of shit tons of game jams that are going on at
any time and anyone can just hop in and join. There's one on the far right that was called
no shit Sherlock jam. That was one I wanted to join. I have no idea what that theme is but
that's cool.
There's another site called IndieGameJams.com.
And when I made this, there was over 50 game jams
happening at the time I was making this presentation.
So game jams are always going on.
So for closing thoughts.
So I've seen firsthand how amazing game jams are
for building teamwork skills with individuals.
So much amazing creative problem solving
happens on the fly during these.
Time management, like huge improvements.
Myself and everyone on my team who's done this
learns how to really focus on getting things done
in a very timely manner.
It also builds, it also gives people fresh perspective.
I mean a lot of us work on these huge games that take sometimes years and years to make.
So allowing your teams a couple days to just kind of make something from scratch, separate
themselves from the product for a couple days, it really gives them, I think it can really
give them a very fresh perspective and help them out.
Sense of accomplishment is huge also.
Like a lot of us work on games that get canceled
or again take a long time to make.
Being able to say our goal is to make something
really quickly in two days.
And having it done, finished,
and everyone's relieved and excited about that.
And finally creative freedom.
You know we can't all let all of our people
throw in all their crazy ideas.
But game jams are an amazing opportunity to let that happen.
Creative freedom is super important for creative people.
So finding these small windows to make sure your teams can do
whatever wild thing they want is really important, and
they'll appreciate it.
All right.
And that's all I got.
So thank you very much.
Thanks.
Oh, one thing I forgot.
Please silence your phones.
Thanks.
And please fill out the survey so we can get some feedback.
And now it's time for Q&A. If anyone has any questions at all,
I'll leave up the resources.
And the last one is gamersforgood.com,
my nonprofit organization.
If anyone has any questions or wants
any ideas for how they can get their teams involved
in game jams, hit me up.
I'd be glad to help you with that.
Hello.
When do you do them?
Like on the week, on the weekends?
What's like?
It's really whatever works for you.
I mean, most game jams are actually happening
on the weekend.
Yeah, but at Riot.
At Riot, we do it during the week.
So we have, we start at noon on Wednesday
and we end noon on Friday.
Thanks.
Yep, and we try to do them about twice a year.
Thanks for the.
The talk was great.
I see you guys, you put together big teams.
How do you guys go, or how do you
go about breaking those teams into smaller pods
or into smaller teams that could work together?
Or do you guys just all work on things individually?
Well, we make sure when we start, we make sure we have some type of very basic leadership
structure where it's like, OK, we know we want to have someone in charge of making sure
the characters are getting in the game.
Someone makes sure, you know, we definitely have a lead producer.
Everyone knows who that is.
And then based on the size of the team, we try to have a few of those.
So for the most part, it's pretty just chaotic.
Everyone figures out where they kind of fit in and where they can slot in.
And then the producer.
team on time. I see the guy that's there's someone that's basically going,
hey, can we get this by 2 p.m. Yes. Yes, absolutely. That's that's what the producers are basically
saying. Hey guys, here's the whole project. Sure. We can keep throwing shit in,
but some of this other stuff is getting cut. So we put it all out there. And then, you know,
it's like, cool. You guys want to add a new submarine? Awesome. This other thing is gone.
Hey, so I have a question.
One of the kind of points throughout with these
different examples was this sort of danger of paralysis
analysis and the danger of over planning these things and
that kind of stuff.
But I wonder, like with the examples you gave, a lot of
these are kind of known genres that people know what a twin
stick shooter is and what a 2D platformer is.
How much do you think that helped?
And can you speak to how that benefited the process?
Well, I mean a 2D platformer is still a pretty broad thing.
But yeah, it definitely helps.
It definitely helps to have some kind of very small
basic constraint so people have something to rally around.
Because if you don't have that, you know,
you'll be spending the very beginning of a game jam
or even a game cycle just fighting over,
are we making an open world thing?
Are we making a fishing simulator?
Like, what are we doing?
So I definitely think having at least the genre.
or just some kind of thing in place at the start
is really going to save time.
Well, hello.
I think that was a very interesting talk,
and also especially to form the creativity inside the team,
and also get to know the people inside the team.
I think that was really informative about that.
My question was more about, even though you
say that in these jams, planning may not be necessary,
but I think there's also a sense of scope, right?
So how do you get the scope so that you can actually
finish the game by the end of the 48 hours?
We normally don't worry about scope at the start.
We just kind of let people go insane.
And then about halfway through, we just start killing things.
Just, sure, go ahead, balloon out of control.
And then it's going to end up getting rained back in at the end.
We actually end up making a ton of content that doesn't get in.
And that's fine.
That's just part of the process.
OK, thank you.
Hey, how's it going, Pete?
Good to talk.
Thank you.
I really appreciated it.
Is it okay to ask a two-parter?
Is that not allowed?
For you, yes.
Oh, okay.
Thank you.
You owe me five bucks for that.
Okay.
Okay, so the first part is, so on that very first Thunderdome, how did you convince or
how was management convinced that it'd be okay to take 10 to 20 people out of production
and to work on something that wasn't product-related?
How did Riot justify that cost?
You're talking about just Thunderdome in general?
Thunderdome in general, yeah.
Like that first one, like obviously over time it proved it had value.
But on the first one, how was it just a leap of faith?
Well, I wasn't there for the very first Thunderdome.
My first Thunderdome was Thunderdome 2.
But I think it...
What I believe is it's really about...
People are working on a game like League of Legends, which is a gigantic game, and it's
very easy, like they're doing the same job over and over.
And so the desire and need for a different creative outlet for the people I think is
just really important, and that was recognized.
Cool.
And the second part is...
The things that you learned over these five or so Thunderdomes, like all these awesome
learnings that you got, do they scale to a larger team or do they only work in small
40-something teams?
I think they scale infinitely.
Yeah, I think there's...
Okay.
Yeah.
Cool. Thanks, Pete.
Sorry, I mean, is there something more specific you're referring to?
Well, yeah, it seems as though a lot of times your findings were planning is overrated, right?
Like, and I know that that was a gross generalization you said that.
But, um, it seems like you just get a bunch of really creative people that are super passionate and just let it rip.
Like, and they're confident in what they're doing and they all have a shared vision.
I mean, is that all really it takes?
Like, is it...
Well, I guess what I'm asking is,
how do you maintain that alignment of vision
across larger groups of people
so that they know exactly what they're making?
Are you talking about for a game jam or for a game product?
I'm talking about a game product.
Like, do these game jam methodologies apply to product?
I think they do to some degree, but a lot of what this is is about doing something absurd.
Most of the stuff is not shippable content.
It's just doing something fun, something super creative, building confidence for your team,
making sure they're aware that, hey, if I needed to make a model with zero planning
in one day, I totally could do that.
So I don't think a lot of this translates directly to like AAA products,
but it's really just about giving teams the opportunity to collaborate with new people,
to build confidence in their abilities, to, you know, just have fun.
And that's what they take back to their desk.
Like when it's all said and done, they take back the experience, the camaraderie,
the, you know, the ability and confidence in themselves
that they can make something really, really super fast, right?
Yeah, and it's also just the kind of reboot.
You work on the same thing every single day.
It's very easy to just kind of get into that mental funk.
So just taking a couple days and doing something totally
different can help reset you creatively.
Cool.
Thanks, Pete.
Creativitively.
Hi there, Pete.
Hello.
This was a great talk.
Thanks.
I was wondering if there were any specific methods of brainstorming that you used.
Yeah, yeah.
We used a lot of whiteboards, which were awesome.
I'm not starting a whiteboard company or anything.
But yeah, we really just, we did a lot of whiteboard brainstorming where we just grabbed
a few people and said, hey, this is going to be the crew that needs to do this one part
of this.
Let's sit down and talk about what we want to do.
And all right, how much time do we have?
And we just.
It's just scribble it all out, and then we put names on everything.
That's the most important thing.
Put names to every task, or that one floating task with no name on it is gonna be floating
and never get done.
So yeah, it's just really writing things down.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Oh, hey, Pete.
Oh, man, it's loud.
It's sick talk.
Also great Aurelia teaser.
I saw that.
That was neat.
So I'm actually a student, and I participated in Global Game Jam
myself, and a few other Itch Jams.
So I'm wondering, what would you say some of the benefits
of doing them when you're still kind of trying
to get your foot in the door, compared
to when you're in a company?
What kind of, like, do you think there's
a huge benefit from maybe starting these projects
and then expanding them possibly into bigger projects
that you can show off for your own work?
I guess what I'm saying is when you're still learning and you kind of get together with
a bunch of people that are still learning compared to when all of you are already professionals,
what's some of the benefits of that compared to when you're already out there compared
to when you're still trying to squeeze your way through the door?
Oh, there's huge benefits for students doing game jams.
One of the biggest problems I see with students regularly
is they don't know how to collaborate.
They don't work within each other.
And they also scope out of control.
I've seen so many student projects that are like,
I'm a student.
I'm making an MMO by myself.
I'm like, what are you doing?
So that constraint of a couple days is absolutely fantastic.
And it'll ensure you're collaborating
and you're getting something done.
So you'll learn, as a student,
learning time management is fantastic.
I don't think I've ever hired someone out of school
who has any understanding of time management.
So please do that.
Yeah, all right, thank you very much.
You know what I'm talking about.
Hey, great talk.
I was wondering how do you motivate people for game jams
or stuff like this?
You know, it's quite common in the video games industry
that people lose motivation to try new things
or get out of their comfort zone.
And they tend to be very hard to motivate.
And that is a great opportunity to get people to do new stuff.
And I was wondering if you had any advice to give
or any opinion on that.
Absolutely. I mean, I think the best motivation is leading by example.
You know, if you're a leader of a crew and you suggest doing a game jam
and they're like, we don't really want to, do it yourself.
Join another crew and then show, bring it back to work.
Say, hey, this is what we made. This was great. This is what I learned.
Do a presentation about it. Talk about it.
Say, look at all the benefits that come from this.
So I just think leading by example is the ultimate motivator.