Hello? Can you hear me? All right. Too loud, too quiet. Everyone who was out last
night is like, too loud, too loud.
So a couple things before we get started.
Please turn off your cell phones.
If it does ring, I will mock you incessantly
throughout this presentation.
And at the end, you're going to get that electronic survey.
We've all gotten them.
Please fill it out.
Let me know what I can do better,
if we need more content, less content,
some sort of synchronized dance-off, whatever.
And it helps me come back next year.
Also, I can talk a little fast when I get nervous.
So if we get to the end of this thing and you guys are like,
what the hell did he just say?
We'll have time for questions,
so don't worry too much about it.
All right, my name is Scott Shepard.
I'm the technical art lead for the 3D department at Bungie.
I've been in the games industry since about 1999,
and I've worked on everything from fantasy MMOs
to survival horror, the sci-fi first person shooters
of Halo.
But for about the past four years,
I've been focused on
building customizable characters for Destiny.
To talk about Bungie's future, we first
have to talk about our past.
The Master Chief is one of the most recognizable characters
of the modern video game era.
His image was developed across 10 years of projects
and thousands of man hours of work.
He has appeared in games, books, animated and live action films,
as action figures, even on soda cans.
His green armor and orange visor ingrained in the minds of
gamers both young and old.
His faceless design allowed the player to really imagine
themselves as the hero of the Halo saga.
I call that out because that point stuck with us in
particular.
So where do we go from here?
How do we, on one hand, build off the successes we learned
from developing the Master Chief, but at the same time
create something entirely unique to Destiny?
Who is Destiny's main hero?
Well, the answer is there isn't one.
Destiny isn't about a singular hero or story.
Our mantra throughout the development of this project
has been to create a world that people want to be in,
to go back to.
This is a place for players to tell their own stories.
In short, our hero is you.
This story is yours.
The idea of telling these player stories
were the driving points for all of our decisions regarding
our player characters.
It was important for us to let the player feel like they were
part of this world, invested in it. That we weren't handing them
a role to play, they were creating their own role. To
accomplish that we needed a system that enabled the player
to discover and shape their avatar in the world of destiny.
That meant allowing each player to stand out from others and
encouraging them to grow and change their character over
time.
To succeed at this, we needed a deep and satisfying
customization experience that went well beyond anything
we've ever attempted before, and something we hadn't really
seen in a shooter to date.
Early on, we talked a lot about power fantasies.
These are the heroes and adventurers that inspire us.
At an early age, this may be as simple as a game of
Cowboys and Indians.
As we were exposed to different types of heroes, it grows to
include the likes of space marines, pirates, wizards,
knights, ninjas, what have you. We took these power fantasies
and tried to wrap them into archetypes that fit well within
our world. What we emerged with were three classes we felt best
represented the types of stories our players would want to tell
on Destiny. These are the hunters, the warlocks, and the
titans.
To begin our explorations, we broke our character bodies
into four slots, the head, chest, arms, and legs.
As players progressed through the world of Destiny,
they would be rewarded with different pieces
of gear for each slot.
This gear would alter their appearance and abilities,
allowing them to make choices that
affected both their visual as well as gameplay experiences.
These four slots offered a balance
between gameplay progression, visual customization,
and aesthetic harmony.
We chose basic silhouette shapes for each of the classes to
help make them more readable. These shapes formed many of the
ideas behind the initial concepts and served as guides
for ensuring each class maintained a unique identity. To
further separate the classes we added a fifth class specific
gear slot. The hunter's cloak, the titan's badge and the
warlock's bond or arm band.
The hunters are our frontier scouts, scavenging and exploring
in the world outside the city to bring back valuable technology
the citizens rely upon. They are hacker cowboys, bounty hunters
and recon snipers. They carry themselves with style and
swagger. Hunters scavenge much of their gear, so we decided on
an almost mix and match haphazard look to their
designs.
Like the wandering adventures of old, they wear heavy cloaks
and combine utilitarian accessories such as packs and
straps with trophies of their adventures, both functional and
fashionable. We drew inspiration from survival gear like gas
masks and hazmat suits. So we chose to design their helmets
with a focus on goggles and breathers. Their armor is
lightweight and fitted to allow for mobility and speed. It is
often comprised of a hard chest plate over a flexible Kevlar
like midsection.
They wear loose fitting pants with pockets and sturdy walking
boots. The warlocks are warrior scholars. Searching for answers
to the mysteries of the traveler and a mastery of its power. They
are mystics, seers and wandering monks. They are mysterious and
secretive with the ability to harness the power of the
traveler to devastating effect.
They wear long overcoats and robes.
And while they generally rely on their abilities
more than heavy armor of other classes,
they still pack a fair amount of hardware on their persons.
They're scholarly, but also practical,
and they are no strangers to the heavy firepower
required to survive in the wild.
The warlocks had many influences and inspirations,
from wizards and shamans
to the trench soldiers of World War I.
We tried to combine all of these elements while always
maintaining an air of mystery about them.
And finally, the Titans, are equivalent to the Knights of
old, heavily armored and bearing the emblems and
heraldry of the city they protect.
They are noble and brave, with a culture steeped in
tradition.
The Titans considered a great honor to protect their city.
They are the most heavily armored of our three classes.
Their designs are most often comprised
of a tight-fitting rubber suit
layered with heavy metal plates,
with large pauldron-like shoulder pads
and sweeping visors inspired
by medieval and renaissance armor.
Large armored thigh pads and boots
are also a common trait of the Titans.
The badge they wear at their side,
the symbol of their achievements, lineage, or allegiance,
much like the tabards worn by knights throughout history.
OK, so we had a distinct look for each of our classes
we were happy with.
But we still had a lot of questions to answer.
What did different versions of these classes look like?
What parts would change?
And what components were key to the class identity?
How do we break up these awesome designs to fit into an
investment and customization system?
We generated countless drawings to help us answer
these questions and more.
And we use these drawings to set targets
for our customization system.
But an old colleague of mine used to say,
designing games is as much about deciding what you can't do
as what you can.
Setting limitations was just as important as setting targets.
For example, many of these designs
called for a great deal of overlapping pieces, which
was technically very challenging.
We did some tests in this area, but in the end,
we felt it was significantly limiting the artists.
So we just simplified it and moved on.
We've done customization before with some success. With every
iteration we've gotten a little more complex and a little more
expansive. Naturally this is where we started. Can we build
off what we had created for the Halo franchise? In Reach we
broke our characters into helmets, chest armor, arm
accessories and thigh packs. This was not unlike our plans
for Destiny. Different pieces of gear for different parts of the
body. The problem however was the scope.
the sheer amount of content we had to produce for Destiny meant
we needed to be thinking outside the box to approach this
problem from a different angle. During the course of building
Helmets for Reach, we created special add-ons intended to add
extra variation to each helmet. This worked pretty much as we
expected. But a funny thing happened. We accidentally put
the add-ons from one helmet onto another and surprisingly it
worked.
We found that a lot of these add-ons could just be Z-buffered
into the base helmets to quickly create new variants.
This got me wondering if we could create an entire
character using that approach.
So I started mocking up a system in Maya,
building pieces and layering them on top of each other,
until I ended up with what you see here.
25 or so pieces used to build 12 different helmets.
Using these pieces in different colors, I was able to create a
variety of helmets very quickly. Adding in textures and decals
in Photoshop, I created this proof of concept image. This is
what we presented to our tools and graphics engineers to kick
off our early discussions. Going into these discussions, we had
several goals in mind for our new system.
We wanted to save as much time as possible in both creation
and maintenance of our content, to have a base of common
assets that we weren't rebuilding every time we had
to make a new piece of gear.
How many artists find themselves modeling basically
the same pair of boots 10 times throughout the course
of a project?
If they're smart about it, they reuse their high poly and
kitbash some of their previous assets together.
But even then, they're generally still ripping new
maps, laying out new UVs, and retexturing
things countless times.
We needed to be more efficient than that.
That meant the ability to build a shoulder pad one time and use
it freely as many times as it was needed in the game without
additional work. We also wanted to remain as flexible as
possible. If near the end of development we realized the same
shoulder pad was over budget or didn't deform properly or people
just didn't like it, we needed to be able to fix that piece
once and not open every piece of gear that shoulder pad was used
in.
We knew that this was a franchise we intended to grow and develop over the next decade.
The system needed to be expandable, something we could build on as we added content in the
forms of DLC, expansions, and sequels.
We knew we couldn't afford to rebuild everything for every release.
We were spanning console generations, which meant we needed the system to be flexible
enough to take advantage of the higher poly and texture budgets that would be afforded
by the new generation of hardware.
And we knew that even within the same generation of consoles,
tech improves, tools improve, artists improve.
It was important to be able to address old content quickly
and easily down the road.
From our design team, the desire was for player characters
to pick up different pieces of gear, what
we call arrangements, for each slot
and swap them throughout the course of the game.
When this happened, we wanted the player
to notice a significant change to their appearance.
Because of this, artists needed to be able to change assets
significantly without having to worry about breaking skinning
or affecting animation.
In short, we needed the ability to create something
that looked completely different with little to no wake
on other teams.
So after some lengthy discussions
with some very smart people, we had a plan.
We needed to stop thinking of our characters like this.
and start thinking of them like this.
The idea was to break our character designs down
into their most base elements.
Things like belt buckles, shoulder pads, visors,
and straps would all be modeled and textured
as self-contained individual assets.
So building this became much more about building this.
These individual pieces, what we call bits,
would be stored as separate files
and assembled by an artist to create a new arrangement
of arms, legs, helmets, et cetera.
If the design for a particular arrangement
called for a buckle, rather than building a new buckle,
the artist would simply load an existing buckle bit
and place it where he or she needed,
with the system handling many of the technical aspects
behind the scenes.
To control the material properties of each bit, we
created dies.
The die assigned to a bit controls its color, specular
qualities, detail maps, et cetera.
We decided each arrangement would have a die for armor,
for cloth, and what we call suit, which is generally
leather or rubber.
Each bit within an arrangement will be flagged as one of
these types and the material properties set accordingly.
So we had a plan.
We knew how we were going to break our characters down.
Now we just needed a way to put them back together.
Enter a mashup.
Mashup is our custom character assembler.
It allows for any bit created by any artist
to be brought in, placed, rotated,
scaled to fit the arrangement as needed,
all without affecting the original bit geometry.
It really is the heart of our player character building
process.
So this is an example of an artist working in mashup.
We start each arrangement by bringing in a core
to build off of.
There's nothing particularly special about the core,
but it is the foundation of the arrangement.
Much like the foundation of a house
dictates the basic layout of the structure built on top of it.
The artist then begins loading in bits
and placing them where needed.
Each arrangement has a set of predetermined points
to aid in placement.
Things like front, back, left upper arm, right upper arm,
et cetera.
Bits can be set to default to a certain point
just to make things a little easier and faster
for the artists.
As you can see, the artist can scale, rotate, or mirror
the bit in a variety of ways to accommodate
the needs of the arrangement.
There's no hard limit to the number of bits an arrangement
can be made of, as the bits are combined at export time
to save performance.
As long as the overall arrangement still
fits in its allotted memory and performance budgets,
we're all good.
After we've established the basic geometry of the helmet,
there are a number of properties that
can be set on each bit to alter its function or appearance.
We can set what type of material the bit takes from our die system.
We can set whether the bit draws in first person or not.
We can set whether the bit...
excuse me...
what platforms the bit is drawn on.
We can also override the bit's default shader,
allowing for texture and shader variation unique to that arrangement.
And we can even add vertex animation to give the bit sway or movement.
After properties are set, we need to skin the bits.
They can be quickly rigid-bound or skinned using our custom one-button skinning tool.
optionally the bit can be custom skinned by one of our riggers
and the skin weight is stored within the bit and applied the
next time an artist brings it in. Now, this video is sped up
to about five times normal speed. And I'm not going to lie
to you, I've built this helmet before. But it comes in in
about three minutes and 30 seconds. So what you're looking
at is a new piece of helmet content in about 20 minutes.
So the other tool you saw in that video is gear manager.
Gear manager allows us to browse through arrangements,
bits, and bobs.
A bob, or a bunch of bits, is essentially a group of bits
stored as a preset.
It allows artists to put together pieces that are more
complex than a single bit, but simpler than a full
arrangement.
A pair of boots, including straps and armor, might be a
good example of this.
Most importantly, gear manager gives us a variety of methods
to find useful bits. The most obvious method being to simply
scroll through pages of thumbnails looking for
something interesting. But there's much more to it than
that. I can filter and search bits by name, by folder, by
class, or by artist assigned keyword. I can also mark bits
as favorites to easily find them later.
For example, I can search for metal bolts,
limit that to a certain class, quickly scrub through
thumbnails, and even rotate and zoom a preview of the model,
all in Gear Manager.
Once I find one I'm interested in,
I simply double click to send it to Mashup.
Going back to our Lego analogy, how many hours
did you spend pawing through that giant container
of Legos looking for that perfect piece?
Gear Manager allows artists to focus
on building their arrangements rather than searching
for the perfect pieces.
Cloth setup is generally the last step of our process.
We use Havok Cloth and a custom wizard-like interface
that allows artists to define cloth regions
without delving too deeply into technical setup.
Artists pick the type of cloth gear they're making,
the type of fabric, and the wizard guides them
through selecting the appropriate verts for skinned,
simulated, and anchored regions.
In the end, once it's been imported into the game,
it looks something like this.
So now that we've built our helmet,
we need to make sure it conforms to the geometry and texture
budgets we've allowed for it.
Because there's the potential for every player
in a given space to be wearing completely unique gear,
we decided to assign each player their own texture and polygon
budgets.
Memory within a mission could then be set aside
based on the number of players it required.
More than that, since each player
can swap out different parts of their character,
we had to further break those budgets down
into an amount per slot.
These were then tailored to best fit each class.
For example, a Titan's arm slot allows for a 1024 by 512
texture on the PlayStation 3 and Xbox 360, and roughly 170K
memory for geometry.
A Warlock's arm slot, which covers less real estate,
allows for a 512 by 512 texture and 110K memory for geometry.
However, the budget for all the combined gear of the Titan and
the Warlock is the same. Okay. Understanding that, let's take
a look at this Hunter's chest arrangement shown in our
texture plate preview. On the left is the empty plate. The
green area is the texture space I have to work with for this
chest arrangement. On the right is the built plate. The engine
takes each bit's textures and UVs and programmatically
arranges them on the plate.
Anything that doesn't fit is displayed in the red area on
the right side of the preview.
So here you can see I have three bits not
fitting on the plate.
At this point, I have a couple of options.
I can remove some bits to make more room on the texture.
I can swap out some of the larger resolution ones for
smaller, or I can change the bits texture size.
Generally, the first two options are my best bet.
If I change the bit's texture size,
it's going to affect every arrangement
that bit is used in.
So increasing or decreasing resolution of a bit
is handled with extreme care.
In this case, though, the orange highlighted bit on the left
was using an inappropriate amount of texture resolution
relative to its physical size.
So I reduced it down.
And that change gets propagated to any arrangement
that bit is used in.
And it allows my three remaining bits
to fit nicely on the plate.
So that gives us a handle on our texture budgets.
Now let's take a look at our geometry.
Here you see the geometry memory profile for our hunter chest.
Unlike the texture memory, each instance of a bit
has to be counted.
So each instance is shown along with a breakdown of cost.
Since many things like UV borders, hard edges,
and shader assignments can affect
the amount of memory associated with the geometry,
we try to give the artist as much information as possible.
If I'm over budget, my options are similar to that
of my texture budget pass.
I can remove some bits, swap them out for cheaper ones,
or I can open one up and make some changes
to the actual geometry.
Many times we'll find that something simple,
like a bit containing a large number of unwelded UVs
or unnecessary edge loops, in which case
it's a simple matter of right clicking the bit,
selecting edit, making my changes, and saving.
With that, I've just made an optimization
to every arrangement that bit is used in.
Now that I've got my helmet built and budget, I'm in done,
right? Wrong. Part of player customization means allowing for
both genders. So now we have to look at building the female
version of our helmet. We initially experimented with
taking a fully built piece of male gear and using a
combination of wrap deformers and blend shapes to create a
semi-automated process for building female gear.
There were several problems with this approach.
First, since it combined all of the bits
into a single piece of geometry to then be
conformed to the female physique,
it lost a lot of the flexibility and benefits of the system.
Second, to meet our high quality bar,
artists were spending longer and longer massaging
the geometry by hand rather than relying on the automated mesh.
So after some careful consideration,
we made a direction change.
We decided that with a few modifications
and additional tools, our current process
was quick enough and strong enough
to use for both male and female arrangements.
We added the ability for a bit to have a female version.
This is particularly useful for things like chest plates
and pants, where we want geometry
that more closely conforms to the feminine proportions.
However, the majority of things, ammo packs and the like,
just needed to be slightly scaled down
and moved into position.
This allowed us to use the vast majority
of the content we built for both males and females.
Now, if you noticed on the texture preview slide,
all of our bits are textured, for the most part,
as gray scale images.
This is to allow for the additional customization layer
brought in by our dye system.
Before I get into that, I want to talk a little bit about the
textures associated with a bit. Like most modern 3D assets, our
primary maps are diffuse and normal maps. But for bits, we
also have what we call a gear stack texture. Here's a sample
gear stack texture from one of our hunter capes. Pretty, isn't
it? What the gear stack is, is three different black and white
masks stacked into a single RGB texture to conserve memory.
We've evolved these masks to be used
in a number of different ways, but the general usage
goes like this.
The blue channel holds a fringe map, or alpha test map.
This is primarily used on cloth bits
to create tatters and holes, hence the name fringe.
The green channel stores our specular roughness map,
which works in conjunction with the assigned spec material
to control specular roughness and intensity of the surface.
And finally, in the red channel, we have our scratch mask.
The scratch mask is used to control what areas are affected
by the dye assigned to the bit.
We call it a dye, but it controls significantly more
than just color.
Areas that are white in the scratch mask get affected by
not only the dye's color using an assigned blend method, but
also the dye's diffuse and normal detail maps, as well as
the specular material response.
Speaking of which, let's talk a bit about how
we handle specular.
Our spec response is comprised of three elements.
The gear's specular roughness mask,
as we saw on the previous slide, and the die's specular lobe
intent.
The specular lobe controls three aspects of the material's spec
response.
The shape of the highlight, the brightness of the highlight,
and the fall off of the diffuse light.
Instead of using a standard Phong model,
we map a content-driven gradient ramp to the surface
to define the appearance and shape of the specular highlight.
The ramp textures shown at the bottom of the image
are applied to the sphere above,
beginning at the point of reflection
and extending 180 degrees around the mesh.
The outlined orange area demonstrates
how the ramp textures correspond
to the highlight they produce.
The specular tint is also a content driven gradient ramp.
And it controls four aspects of how specular will
render on the surface.
The color of the specular highlight,
how the diffuse texture influences the specular
response, the brightness of the highlight based on angle,
and diffuse brightness scaling.
Unlike the lobe ramp, which maps based
on the position of a light source,
the tint ramp maps to the surface based on viewing angle.
The ramp extends from the surface perpendicular
to the view 90 degrees to the glancing edge.
This is what allows us to change specular color based
on angle of view.
Again, the orange outline demonstrate
how these ramps get applied to the spheres above.
The tent also sets how the specular highlight is modified
by the underlying diffuse.
These spheres above are rendered in a debug spec light only
mode.
The one on the left allows the diffuse texture of the sphere
to modify the specular color and brightness.
The middle image modifies the specular response
based on the diffuse luminance, so only adjusting
the brightness.
And the third white overcoat image
ignores the diffuse entirely in regards to specular response.
Put this all together and it looks like this.
Lobe multiplied by tint plus diffuse.
However, this image above assumes a pure white specular
roughness mask.
The spec roughness mask modifies the spec result.
Generally, white pixels in the mask
produce a bright, sharp highlight,
and dark pixels produce a dim, broad highlight.
This combination of elements gives artists
a huge variety of interesting spec responses to work with.
When you combine this with the additional elements in the die,
it looks like this.
As you can see, this allows us to apply a range of materials
from polished chrome to worn leather to Kevlar
to tattered cloth, all on the same base texture and geometry.
All of these are materials we can quickly and easily apply
to any of our player gear.
In addition to the diet areas of gear,
we also have controls for the other side of the scratch mask.
The areas that are painted black can be assigned their own
specular properties as well as detail, diffuse, and normal
maps.
This helps us achieve things like matte paint being stripped
away from shiny metal or a shiny metal buckle on a leather
collar.
Each arrangement gets assigned three different dyes, a dye for
suit, for armor, and for cloth.
Each dye has both a primary and secondary color
associated with it.
These parameters are set on a per bit basis
throughout the arrangement.
The dies assigned to an arrangement helped to control
the color palette, homogenize all of the bits into a cohesive
piece, and allow us to form larger graphic shapes within
the character. The initial design of the customization
system called for each player to have three dies assigned
across their entire character. This was based on the artist's
desire to avoid every color of the rainbows showing up.
The idea was that players would pick up different die items
that would fit into the three slots, armor, cloth, and suit.
These dies were then applied to the arrangement
across the entire character.
Unfortunately, this was a case where the design needs required
us to adapt our artistic plans.
What we discovered was that when a player picked up a new piece
of gear, even though we were changing the silhouette fairly
significantly, the visual impact wasn't enough to produce
the emotional impact we wanted from the player.
In other words, the player just didn't feel as excited about a
new piece of gear as we wanted them to because we were only
changing one of the visual axes of the character.
The human eye reads changes in color better than it reads
changes in shape.
And changes in both color and shape
are necessary for maximum impact.
With this, it was decided that each tier of player gear
would be assigned a different color,
so that it was obvious to the player
when they picked up a piece of gear
that it was of higher level.
The challenge here was to create color palettes that
were distinct enough individually,
but worked well together from one tier to the next.
Here we have our initial passes at creating these color
palettes.
We use simple block representations of our classes
to assess color compatibility and distribution.
These palettes have been continuously adjusted in Engine
to better communicate to the player.
Using this color and shape approach
proved to be pretty successful in creating bold enough changes
to meet design needs while still feeling good to the artists.
So after building all these fantastic assets,
we needed the ability to quickly view and manage
these arrangements and die assignments in game.
So we created Mantini.
With Mantini, we can quickly select the designer-created
investment item the player would pick up in game
and set the arrangement and the default dies assigned to it,
all within the same UI.
I can quickly change and browse arrangements and dies
on the fly, as well as check both male and female versions
of the arrangement.
This proved invaluable for checking various arrangements
for color compatibility, as well as finding issues such as
clipping or missing pieces.
Using Mantini, we put together this video
to show off some of our very early work in progress
content.
Thank you for watching!
So that's a pretty solid overview of the system. But I'd
be lying if I told you it all went perfectly. Let's be honest,
it never does.
We faced a number of challenges throughout this process.
The system is fairly abstract and complex.
Destiny has been heavily concept driven,
and both the art director and the concept team
are far more comfortable with designs of full characters
rather than a modular system.
Though we tried as best we could
to create modular pieces that worked well together,
many of the designs led themselves
to unique, specialized bits.
As a result, I feel like we've still only scratched
the surface of what we can do with the system.
Content creation got too far ahead of tools and engineering
work.
For much of the production cycle,
the tools were very much a work in progress.
Missing features and stability issues
made working with the system early on somewhat
of a nightmare.
This caused a lot of frustration and slowdowns
for the content creators.
And finally, we lost some of the joy of building characters.
To be honest, this is a problem with any customization system
I've worked with.
It's difficult to maintain a sense of creative ownership
and excitement for artists when they're
building small parts of a character
rather than the full thing.
Since geometry and textures needed to stay modular,
it kept the artists from really being
able to handcraft assets to the level they desired.
OK, so what went right?
Overall, the system itself works quite well.
At this stage, a new and unique looking arrangement
can be created in a very short period of time.
For something like a helmet, that may take as little as an hour from start to end game.
We've also seen the system get better and better the more content we add to it.
This bodes extremely well for a franchise we plan to carry on for a number of years.
The flexibility the system provided us has proved invaluable in fixing bugs and reacting to designer and art director feedback.
Don't like the color of something? Change the dye.
That sleeve not deforming properly? Fix it in one place and it's fixed everywhere.
This fits in extremely well with Bungie's approach
of rapid iteration.
Lastly, the system helped to unify content.
With so many different artists working on player characters,
the system proved a fantastic tool
for helping to set the ground rules to bridge
different artists' styles.
Since artists were constantly seeing and working
with each other's content, they quickly
picked up on the design language and style
we were striving for.
The additional layer of the DICE system assured color and
spec responses were also unified.
So an entirely new type of game, an entirely new engine
and tool set, and a largely new team set the challenge for us.
And we learned a ton.
How to best work with the system, what tools and
features were missing.
We also learned a lot about our strengths and weaknesses as a
team, and where we can do things smarter and more
efficiently.
It's been a tough road, but we've set ourselves up
incredibly well for the future, and I'm very pleased with that.
So now that you have an idea of the system and its challenges
and successes, let's take a look at what happens
when you put it all together.
These are just a few of the player characters
you could see when you're playing
through Destiny this fall.
Okay, so where do we go from here? There were key things we
missed out on. Opportunities to make the system stronger that we
didn't have time or resources to take advantage of for this
project.
First and foremost on our list is a more advanced decal system.
Decals are a great way to allow players
to customize their look.
Games like Forza have built entire economies
on player-generated decals.
Our current system requires placement and geometry
to be created by an artist specific to each arrangement.
A system allowing for projected decals based on both artist
as well as user-generated content
would be a huge tool in allowing players to express themselves.
Developing for four platforms simultaneously
is a difficult task for any developer.
To make content more efficiently,
we need better tools to allow artists
to focus on what they do best, making amazing art,
and not having to spend time dealing
with separate budget and performance goals
for the individual platforms.
We would also benefit from an expanded die system.
Additional features in the die to control things like
environment maps, adjust wear levels, and blend in multiple
sets of detail maps would greatly improve the system.
Something we've strongly desired is the ability to add
an accent color that appears in small controlled amounts to
give an arrangement that extra little pop.
In conclusion, Destiny is a hugely ambitious game,
and our player customization system is no different.
Like all ambitious efforts, there
were challenges along the way.
Overall, I believe we've achieved something completely
unique to the shooter genre and developed a system that
will only grow in power and flexibility
as we continue to create content and expand the franchise.
So obviously a system like this takes a bunch of people
pouring their heart and souls into it.
And most of them couldn't be here today.
But I have to say thank you very much to the team back at
Bungie for allowing me to come here and share this with you.
That's it.
So if anybody has any questions, I think they want
you to use the microphones.
but they're not going to turn them on.
And it's on, hopefully you can hear me.
Oh, there we go.
Does this system extend beyond the character to things
like weapons or world doodads, and why or why not?
It does.
We're trying to use the system as much as possible.
We do use it on our hard surface assets
as well, like weapons and player ships and that sort of stuff.
When you end up changing a bit.
How long does it take to propagate that across all the
helmets that might use that bit?
Like, you have to rebuild all those assets, I imagine.
The bits are loaded when you bring the arrangement into Maya.
So from a content creator standpoint,
it happens instantaneously.
As soon as it's checked in and you get latest,
you load up that arrangement, the new bit is in there.
But then when you make the, like,
when you go to use it in the game. So for the individual
artists they will reexport the geometry and it will come in
game. Other than that we do nightly builds. So for people on
the other side of the team we'll see it whenever they get the
next content build. Okay. So my question is will we ever see
tiger man DLC and if not how does your team go about deciding
something doesn't fit the world you're building? Sorry what was
that last part?
How does your team decide something that you've been
prototyping doesn't fit the art style you're taking the game
in?
So I guess I'm supposed to repeat the questions, which I
totally forgot the first one.
The first part was, will we see Tiger Man in DLC?
The answer to that is, you never know.
If we do, you can guarantee I'll be using Tiger Man first before
you guys. Second part, how do we decide if something doesn't fit
the art style? Bungie, as I said, is very much about
iteration. We put things in game and we try to do it in the
smartest way possible, but if an asset doesn't fit within the art
style or within the game play, we cut it.
So you have a lot of, you know, mix-and-match hard armor pieces like an upper chest plate and a lower chest plate.
How do you make sure that, you know, all the different possible combinations don't end up self-intersecting and doing bad things and so on?
Mostly just quick and easy tools for checking animations.
We have in Maya animation previews.
So I can be working on an arrangement
and hit a single button to see that arrangement start
moving through some base poses to test for clipping.
Other than that, we have another program
which I haven't shown called Lightbox, which
goes through all of our content, creates screenshots
through various poses that we can then check for any issues.
I was more concerned about the combinations of them, you know, could people mix and match things that...
Right, so, sorry again, the question is how do we handle
clipping of the various combinations of arrangements.
This was something we decided early on we were going to have to deal with a little more clipping than
we were used to in previous games.
I think any customizable game is going to have to accept a little bit of that.
We don't have a good way of prohibiting certain things from
clipping into other things.
We just use our eyes and try and best guess, is that OK?
Is that shippable?
Is that not?
So in the start of the game you actually choose a character race.
Did that end up actually affecting the way that you're building gear?
Like did you have to actually build gear differently over different races or?
No, the race is sort of a separate part of our character building process.
Although it actually uses the exact same system.
The exos in particular are a perfect example of how we can use the system for that.
Awesome, thank you.
So this is a really powerful tool for your side
of the fence.
How does this level of customization and content
generation trickle down to the player's ability
to customize and leverage the amount of flexibility
that you have?
The question was, this is a really powerful system for us
as content creators.
How does that affect the players,
and how do they make use of it?
right now for the most part it affects them in the fact that we can build a lot more content
than we could otherwise. We can build a lot more armor sets, a lot more pieces of gear
for them to choose from. Pushing forward, exploring the ideas of players being able
to create their own arrangements and stuff is something we've definitely thought about
and I would personally love to explore but it's a long ways out.
How does the bit system affect the concept pipeline?
Does the concept artist then create more of a kind of keynote versions of everything and then the
variations on the individual bits or more on the 3D artist and then create on the fly?
So the question was, how does the bit system affect the
concept development and how the concept artists work?
It's a great question.
And you're exactly right.
The concept artists create what we call a theme.
So they have a set that is like, here is the spirit of
this set.
And then the variations are all built by the individual
3D artists for the most part.
We try, we very much at Bungie don't like to limit our concept
artists, but we also want to educate them on the system. So
they start to know what we can do and what things are easier
and faster for us, but still they have kind of free range to
explore their ideas.
Yeah, I was wondering about upgrades and if there was a way
that you guys had like rules or some way of defining like what
an upgrade would look like, since like color doesn't
necessarily denote hierarchy.
Were there other things that you used?
So the question is about upgrades.
And honestly, I'm not a designer. So the investment
designers choose sort of the upgrade paths and what pieces
they want to use for those. That stuff, since they're constantly,
constantly iterating, a lot of times, um,
we, you know, we try and put in the best pieces we think possible for things,
but they're much more focused on the stats and the abilities and that sort of stuff, so
I don't know if that answers your question, but...
So you didn't have any, like,
ways of defining, like, what those upgrades would look like necessarily?
The way the system sort of played out, we're very flexible
and reactive.
So if they say, hey, we have this thing, and we're going to
do an upgrade to it, then we can quickly go in and say,
all right, let's add a few more pieces, make this thing
a little more burly and a little cooler looking.
So it's more like they establish first, and then we
kind of follow what they're looking for.
OK, cool.
Thanks.
So with the bits, you said that it would go back and change other bits that were already put into other sets.
So was there any instances where a bit being changed in a newer set changed an old set for the worse?
So the question was, since we can change a bit and it affects
other arrangements, were there any instances where this was
bad, where a bit was changed and it broke something?
The answer is definitely yes.
We had some interesting cases where someone would, the most
dangerous aspect is the texture resolution.
Someone would decide, hey, this bit's too low res.
And so they'd double it.
And then suddenly we have 20 pieces of gear
that aren't importing because their texture budget's blown.
So that was something that we, through a certain part
of the production we dealt with, and then artists just
kind of got smarter and better about knowing
what they can and can't do, and also better tools
at checking the content afterwards.
Thank you.
So I think you said that the bits get combined at export time and then so I'm assuming the arrangements get
Stored and loaded by the engines that every arrangement is a separate piece that's rendered by the engine. Is that correct or that's correct
Sorry, go ahead. Oh, yeah, I just wanted to check like isn't that
More expensive than rendering a traditional character perhaps or so there are more draw calls
associated with rendering each arrangement
uh... so the question is is uh... you know does the engine render each
arrangement individually and is that more expensive uh... than sort of a
traditional
uh... full character arrangement or full character setup
uh...
the answer is yes it is more expensive uh... we've done a lot of things to
optimize the
uh... the gear shader process and uh...
you know the skinning and all of that to try and get that as cheap as possible
but definitely the characters the player characters are more expensive than a lot
than say
civilians or combatants or anything like that.
Can I ask another quick question?
Just, I think you said you had a lot of problems with wraps
and blend shapes.
Can you go, but you didn't sort of elaborate what the sort of
problems were with, you know, because I would have thought
that would give you close fitting cloth if you could
deform layers of cloth over a deformable shape.
So the question was about, I think using the wraps and blend shapes, wrap deformers and blend shapes to create female gear.
And whether or not, why that wasn't successful.
And you're right, for things like cloth and soft organics it worked very well.
But as you can see we have a lot of hard surface shapes.
And things like cylinders that would get stretched and shapes would get deformed.
And the main thing for us was...
that in order to really use that system,
we had to combine everything together,
and that just wasn't efficient.
Okay, thank you.
I had a question about the color customization.
If I understand correctly,
that originally a player could choose three colors
for their character, and then you guys changed the system
to colorize the gear,
so it would represent the different scale of upgrades.
So does that mean that in the current design,
there is no color customization for their character?
So the question is, we initially had it so that players could choose three colors and
then we moved to a system where we established the colors to communicate the tier.
Does that mean players can't customize their color?
So, no.
We definitely established what we call default dyes for things, and
the idea is that players will be able to customize their color choices later on.
can take their upgraded gear and then tweak it from its current
value basically? So I can't go into too much detail about this
because it's actually something that's still being worked on.
But as I said, the idea is that players will have some control
for sure.
Hi, I was just wondering about the merging process you talked about.
So when the bits are merged together, is there, at that time, is there a lot of inner penetrating surfaces?
Do you do any kind of ray casting to make a new mesh?
Or if one arrangement overlaps another arrangement, do you make a bake that has a nice AO under the overlapping?
Or do you just try not to make them overlap? I guess that's two questions.
Sorry, the first part of the question again.
like the helmet you showed with all the bits together,
if it generates inner penetrating surfaces,
is there a bake process that makes a new mesh,
or it's just OK to have the inner penetration?
So the question was, do the bits have
inner penetrating surfaces?
Is that OK?
Do we bake things down?
They do inner penetrate, and we rely primarily
on Screen Space AO to kind of seal everything together
and make it feel like it's a nice, cohesive piece.
And then the second part, sorry.
Well, that kind of answers it.
All right, well, there we go.
Like a gun.
All right, thanks.
Justin Quimby.
Hi Scott, great talk. We work together at Turbine. So I'm curious about the production side of
things in terms of dashboarding tools or how does the production side of the house track, you
mentioned, oh, suddenly someone changes texture density and blows the budgets for stuff. What
kind of tools do you have on the production side of the house to keep track of all the craziness
that you can do given this flexible tool set?
So the question is what kind of tools do we have from the production side of things to keep
track of all these changes and all the things that can be done.
Honestly, nothing terribly fancy. We have fantastic producers, really, that are just
very on top of their game.
We don't, as a 3D team, we don't micro track stuff too much, as
our tasks tend to be, this armor set will take four weeks or
three weeks or whatever.
And then we just try and remain as reactive as possible.
The good thing is that because the system is so fast and
flexible, when we do run into those issues, it doesn't take
much time to fix it.
Hi, first I want to say great talk. I was wondering if the
current system for creating like different pieces through bits
and stuff allows for the addition of like normal map
details such as adding like screws or you know different
like vents or valves on like a helmet or something or if that's
part of the decal system you guys are looking towards in the
future. So the question was is if the current system allows for
adding sort of normal map details like screws and things
like that.
actually the, it does in a different sort of way.
So we have, we have a layer of what we call
detailed geometry, which is set within, set as a bit.
So certain bits can be flagged as detailed geometry.
So they're high detail, high frequency type of bits
that then fade out quickly at distance
or don't get exported to sort of the older platforms
kind of thing.
So we do a lot of that with those.
Thank you.
One quick question I had, because this system, it actually reminded me a lot of Borderlands 2's gun system, where they built completely modular guns, and so each player who started up their game was able to have their own unique sniper rifle.
Would this system allow for players to have completely unique, randomized helmets, or is everything built beforehand?
So the question was, does the system allow for players
to have completely unique randomized helmets
or pieces of gear?
The answer is no, actually.
And that was a very conscious decision on our part.
We wanted artists to still maintain control
of the overall design.
We wanted to try and make it as fast as possible
for them to create something cool,
but we didn't want it, we always wanted it to feel
like it was a conscious decision
that we put this piece with this piece.
Thank you.
Alright, any more questions?
You guys are free to go.
Thank you very much.