So thanks for coming, it's the end of the day
so I really appreciate it.
And let's start off by getting vulnerable.
I actually thought this room would be empty,
so I'm very pleased to see so many of you here.
A quick background, I am Cherry, and I'm an accessibility expert.
I've collaborated with teams of many different disciplines on everything from workshops to
accessibility reports, inclusions with art, narrative, and writing teams.
Past work includes giants like Ubisoft, Xbox, and Microsoft Studios, all the way through
mid-sized AAA like Guerrilla, and indies like Gambrinus.
Oh yeah, in the words of Ben Schroeder,
I also practice ultraviolence but for feelings,
so get ready.
My disabilities affect my memory and speech
and are an excellent excuse to break the rules,
so I also read my presentations.
Content warning, I will be discussing difficult things
related to disability, death, stigma, and mental health.
If you need to leave at any time, please do.
I have a lot to cover, so I'm afraid it's unlikely
there will be time for questions,
but please remember if you have any to catch me afterwards.
If there's enough of us, we'll move to a wrap-up room.
Otherwise, I'm happy to answer you on Twitter,
so always feel free to get at me.
So, representation, excuse me, I'm already breaking up.
It's a loaded subject.
I'll set the scene with some words from Emily Grace Buck,
who is a wonderful narrative designer
that you should all follow on Twitter.
You can't do narrative design in a social,
cultural, or political vacuum.
You're providing players tools to live a story.
Their story is informed by the real world.
If you're not considering what your players, all of them,
might want to do and how they might feel at every moment
as they experience the stories in your game,
you're not doing narrative design.
Thinking intersexually isn't a plus, it's a must.
As the pace picks up with accessibility
and more disabled people are playing our games
than ever before,
it's perhaps time to have a frank discussion on inclusion.
I'm pretty sure this is the first ever talk at GDC
on disability representation, so no pressure.
According to Twitter, people really like my title.
I gave version 1.0 of this talk at the Games Accessibility
Conference in Paris last year and got a similar response.
But it's more than just a clever nod to a very famous game.
It embodies what I truly feel needs to change
about how we view disability.
Working in games so often means pouring our heart and lives
into them, and it can be hard to hear criticism.
So I want to reassure you that it's not personal.
I really don't think games that get representation wrong
are bad games.
I truly appreciate every one of you.
I just think that the mistakes we make
are often down to gaps in knowledge and experience.
But, oh, I went ahead.
We do that sometimes.
But I'm not a monolithic voice for all disabled people.
While I've done my best to bring in perspectives
from the larger community,
at the end of the day, I'm just one person.
I always struggle with how to give 30-minute lectures without an hour-long intro on disability
culture and today is no exception because bad representation derives from social stigma.
Well, here's my story in a nutshell.
Until my late 20s, I didn't consider myself disabled.
Then I took an arrow to the knee, which is not true at all.
I wish my story was that cool.
I lived with a lot of undiagnosed physical and cognitive disabilities, which meant difficult
times and unique stigmas.
At 31, I had a sudden stroke when an artery supplying my brain tore.
I wasn't even doing anything cool, like pumping iron or crashing a sports car.
I was slowly walking back from my coffee break at the beach.
It turned out my physical disabilities are degenerative, and at this point I found myself
in and out of hospital, trying to rediscover who I was.
I learned a lot about how negatively I viewed disability.
I found vocabulary and culture and figured out why I'd always struggled so much.
It was a revelation.
By being forced to acknowledge it, I could finally see myself and my disabilities positively.
It's what you make of your situation that defines you.
Lara Croft in Shadow of the Tomb Raider.
A common phrase we hear is that we shouldn't let
our disabilities define us,
but of course my disabilities define me.
And I don't just let them,
I work hard to make them a positive part of me.
They're an inescapable part of who I am.
I experience the world through my disabilities every day,
all with things like chronic pain.
I'm proud to be defined of what I make of my situation.
I want to celebrate it.
If Lara gets that, why can't everyone else?
All right, myths and stereotypes.
Surprise, I use a wheelchair.
I had to ask them to move a table so I could make that joke.
People wrongly assume all wheelchair users
have total paralysis,
but there are so many other reasons for using one.
For me, it's multifaceted due to my muscles,
pain, and frequent injuries.
Lots of us can stand up or even walk a little bit
with the help of crutches, canes, or walkers.
It's not a miracle or someone faking.
Yes, I have had people yell this at me,
including in a hospital of all places.
Here's a list to inspire you when you're thinking of including wheelchair users in your games.
This might not be exhaustive, but they are common reasons to use a wheelchair.
Muscular weakness, amputation, severe fatigue, bone or muscle malformations, chronic pain,
bone and soft tissue fragility, a risk of injury or falls, motor control and movement disorders, and even more.
The type of wheelchair we use depends on our disabilities and the cost.
But somehow, the most common wheelchair we see in games are ugly, heavy things
that have rarely been used outside of hospitals, airports,
and other temporary situations for more than 30 years.
Cloning wheelchair assets looks pretty silly, too.
I've never met anyone with the exact same wheelchair as mine,
and I'd love to see more power chairs.
Here's a hot tip.
If you're Googling for manual wheelchair reference,
use the term everyday wheelchair, not just wheelchair.
As you see, the results are quite different.
More ideally, work directly with people who use them
so you can learn more about how they work.
Another myth, autistic stereotypes, nonverbal kids,
savants, or men who lack empathy
to the point of hurtfulness or violence.
The biggest issue with autistic characters
is we're rarely written as fully developed people.
The most famous and 30-year-old example,
Rain Man's defining traits aren't even autism
like most people think.
It's something called savant syndrome.
We have personalities, we're as human as anyone else,
even if we move or communicate differently.
Most stereotype breaking of all,
my empathy can be so intense it overwhelms me,
but I don't process emotions or sensory information very well.
I do actually like trains,
but I'm also incredibly enthusiastic about birds
and can sort of talk to cats,
when that's only half a joke.
The fictional characters who I think are most autistic
aren't usually written as such.
Futaba from Persona 5 was extremely autistic,
but she was described as a shut-in.
Similarly, Hilda, the Netflix cartoon,
has many qualities as a young autistic girl,
but it's likely accidental,
which doesn't really count
because it doesn't foster the wonderful sense
of acceptance, inclusion, and being seen
that can be so powerful with deliberate inclusion.
One quarter, sorry.
Reflecting worldwide population statistics,
recent studies are showing one quarter to 30% of players
identify as disabled.
And that's a big chunk of the market.
And games are massively important to the lives
of disabled people.
Time is too tight to go into too much detail on how,
but on a personal level, video games saved my life.
I said this during a design sprint
with the studio who make Gears of War.
I meant it half jokingly, but as always,
I didn't realize how deeply I meant this
until I met the eyes of one of the developers
and he quietly and vulnerably said, me too.
Regardless of who we are, this can be our most profound common ground.
It's one of the things that makes us so passionate in our work.
Games have helped me through so many difficult times all through my life,
but maybe nothing greater than through pain and degenerative disability.
So, if a quarter of players are disabled, why are less than 1% of our game characters?
Whether it's hiring practices, community efforts, creator platforms or representation,
disability is often forgotten from larger diversity efforts.
Even if it's not intentional, by not explicitly including us, you're excluding us.
It both matters how often and how we're represented in games,
maybe for no greater reason than how it feels.
The lack of representation, or even worse, bad representation,
can reinforce stigma.
Everything from ideas that disability should be hidden,
it makes us worthless, evil, untrustworthy, a burden,
or even whether we should want to die.
More on that in a moment.
It can cause rifts in friendships when we talk about it,
or it can acutely affect our enjoyment of a game.
It can incite and underpin onslaughts of hatred and toxicity
when gamers use slurs like retard to shut us up.
Negative representation can impact our mental health
and self-esteem on every front.
To put it simply, it alienates us.
Conversely, the feeling of seeing even a glimpse of who you are in a positive light is profound.
It's a nudge that you're not alone, and more importantly, you're welcome.
A little indie called To The Moon was one of these moments for me.
When I started playing, I had no idea that it was relevant to me.
So when it captured so much of what it's like to be autistic, I cried.
And I don't mean I got teary and could hold it together.
I mean I openly sobbed, breathless, wordless,
and completely broken.
Of course, this was live on the internet
for everyone to see.
I was an absolute mess.
I'm not kidding, but this segment goes on for 20 minutes.
It unlocked feelings I had no idea were so intense
that when I finally saw even a shadow of myself,
how powerful that would be.
The way one of the autistic characters experienced the world and the barriers she faced were
so familiar.
Through a deeply affectionate lens, the story told of how hard she fought.
She had autonomy, desires, and opinions.
She wasn't a burden, and she had a profoundly meaningful relationship.
The delicacy and beauty were unparalleled.
Inclusion is so powerful. I deeply adore games because they are great experiences and conduits,
no matter the scope or genre. As storytellers and world builders, you have the capacity to
move hearts and souls like no other industry I know. Hashtag disability representation matters.
I asked people on Twitter how being represented makes them feel, and the responses I got were
overwhelmingly about belonging and visibility.
I particularly liked Jamie Knight's response.
If I exist in the game world, it helps me to persist in the real world.
Helps me see a space, event, or community I can be a part of, rather than feeling like
a permanent outsider.
At the end of the day, that's what it comes down to for disabled people.
We already feel like outsiders.
Games transcend that.
Disabled people are still often segregated,
whether we're stuck at home
or when sitting in less desirable sections on transit,
music venues, sports arenas, or cinemas
away from our friends.
Sometimes we can't even access basic facilities
like toilets.
Too many bars, restaurants, clubs, cafes, shops, parks, and more still aren't accessible.
Even if we can get into buildings, things like table height or limited space exclude us.
Regardless of the poor state of representation, we're less segregated in games.
We feel less alone and undesirable. Take this tweet, for example.
Sorry, this one makes me very emotional.
Daughter is autistic. She doesn't fit in.
She doesn't get praise outside of her close family.
During the first Forsaken mission,
her favorite character told her
to keep us would be proud of her.
She cried.
Thank you, Bungie.
You have no idea how much this means from Andraste Blaze.
So what about escapism?
I know people who don't want to be reminded
of their disabilities.
They just want to feel stronger, more powerful,
and in less pain.
Sometimes it's just about having fun.
I understand this.
I'm in pain constantly, and I'm weaker than a six-year-old.
I've spent hundreds of hours in Horizon Zero Dawn
losing arrows with a ridiculous accuracy and strength,
sneaking around in the grass
like my knees aren't made of glass.
I don't want to replace this facet of gaming.
I believe that enjoying escapism or power fantasy doesn't mean that disability should
be enraged entirely, as it so often is.
This quietly reinforces the idea that disability is wrong, and that the ultimate goal for humanity
is that we don't exist.
Something we have to come to terms with as disabled people is that cures are extremely
unlikely, especially given the vastness of disease and the complexity of some disabilities.
I mean, we can't even cure the common cold or flu.
Some don't want a cure.
For example, I believe that to try and cure me of being autistic
would erase me as a person.
I also love my wheels,
but I'd happily take a cure for my failing digestive system
or never-ending pain.
It's more complicated than you might think.
Mad Max Fury Road was proof that disability and power fantasy can coexist.
Furiosa was wicked powerful, not despite her need for a prosthetic, but because of it.
It was so empowering to see her on the big screen.
Even Mad Max himself has worn a leg brace since the very beginning of the franchise.
That's me, wearing braces, trying to invoke my inner rogue, always.
We have plenty of escapism, so there's really loads of room
for improving representation.
When we do see disability in games, it's mostly extremely negative.
So let's rip off this bandage.
Here's what I call the trilogy of tropes.
We all know the squeaking of a wheel,
the empty wheelchair rolling into a creepy hallway.
Disability is often used to frighten people.
The stigma is so pervasive,
it took me two years of being progressively housebound
to work through it mentally.
Disability can sometimes be scary
to the person going through it,
but it shouldn't be horrifying to other people.
It's similar to the difference between laughing at someone
and with someone.
The empty wheelchair is probably one of the most used pieces of a creepy environmental
storytelling after human skulls.
It's definitely the most common way to encounter a wheelchair in games.
In Fallout 4, I saw the same bulky, unfuturistic wheelchair about 563 times throughout the
entire world.
Now Bloodborne has empty wheelchairs and wheelchair-using enemies.
On one hand, it's cool to think that these enemies are fully capable.
Once I saw one of them miraculously descend a flight of stairs
without tipping over, all while shooting me.
To quote the quote on this slide,
I feel so emotionally ravaged by this game
and not in a good way,
was not about the notorious difficulty.
While I loved playing the game,
the awful way wheelchairs were used crushed me.
To top it all, the story ends with the player's character
being trapped into the wheelchair,
implying that it's a terrible cycle of fate
doomed to be repeated forever.
Apparently, being disabled is the ultimate horror in a world that's nothing but nightmares
that killed you 194 times.
Yes, I counted.
It's left a wound that's prodded every time someone tells me how much they loved the story.
Despite the common narrative that we're trapped in our wheelchairs,
bound to them against our will, for many of us they give us freedom.
I adore my wheelchair. I've never felt as free and bloody cool as I do,
zooming around five times faster than I've been able to move in two decades,
and with a fraction of the pain.
It's a beautiful piece of engineering too, and it's not at all creepy.
This is where I'd pov a wheelie.
But it probably isn't the safest thing to do on stage.
Our body's mind or the devices we use
shouldn't be used as a threat to make players feel scared.
I'm tired of the same old depictions of disability
and mental health that reinforce the negative ways others see me.
And it doesn't come down to one game.
It's like drops in an ocean.
When disability is often seen as worse than death,
maybe it's natural to assume we want to die.
Disabled people face death for many reasons,
from terminal disease to serious accidents.
Or, like me, I live with the risk
that my body can break down without warning.
I've cheated death several times.
Humans are survivors because life is so worthwhile,
even with disability or pain.
Why is it so easy to imagine non-disabled characters doing anything necessary to survive
a horrifying apocalypse?
When it comes to disabled characters in mundane settings, they probably want to die.
In Life is Strange, Chloe becomes profoundly disabled due to a car accident.
The player, as Max, is presented with the dilemma of helping her by killing her, or
forcing her to keep living a life with no friends and nothing to do but stare at blank
walls while in a lot of pain.
Perhaps a more important story to explore
would have been about quality of life.
Why and how is the world failing Chloe
that she's been left with this as her only wish?
And why is it seen as a moral gray area
whether her best friend murders her or not?
The difficulty is there's a dash of truth.
But for me, the ethics behind the way it's presented
are all wrong.
I have friends who have been in accidents like Chloe,
and until they learned to adapt
and achieve the quality of life they deserved,
they did struggle with suicide.
But it's a mental health and social issue.
It's not the fundamental state of being disabled.
It's heartbreaking.
We're passing up truly interesting narratives in favor of overtly negative cliches
that center stigma and fear.
If only these stories would examine why we all have these fears as able-bodied people,
and like the systems that fail us,
and end up with disabled characters being supported and finding new purpose.
Detroit Become Human's disabled character Carl has a super cool wheelchair, which is
actually something I've always wanted to see in games, but at the same time it was totally
inappropriate for him given his apparent inability to self-propel and reliance on being carted
around by an android.
No one I know enjoys or prefers to be pushed around by other people, so it made little sense.
Additionally, since the motion capture was an able-bodied actor in a crappy wheelchair,
I have seen the pictures. He also moved really weirdly. There were so many glaring errors,
I took bets on which bad cliche he was going to be. The bitter, angry rich guy,
or the kind but pitiable one. It was the latter. His character is largely a burden and two-dimensional.
It was rooted in pity, and by focusing on how incapable he is,
it broadcasts how compassionate his android carer must be,
and therefore rouses empathy for the android.
Spoiler, of course he dies,
which is the catalyst for the android's full sentience.
These stories or characters really aren't about our inclusion,
they're plot devices for motivating players into having bad feelings
by exploiting stigma, fear, or imagined ideas of what it's like to be disabled.
It might not be intentional, but it is self-reinforcing.
Ultimately, when this is how you're used to seeing characters like you, it's sad and exhausting.
This is where Hellblade Senua's sacrifice was surprisingly different.
It felt so much less exploitative.
I've spent a long time analyzing why a game that focused on psychosis
felt mature and respectful.
Ninja Theory didn't just work with doctors who diagnose and treat psychosis,
they worked with people who have lived experience of it,
actively working to correct assumptions.
After all, they're the real experts in psychosis.
In other avenues of diversity, we understand the importance of having marginalized people
tell their own stories.
If not as part of the team directly, then via consultation and sensitivity checks.
We should be speaking to disabled people.
Her Web was a piece of art, as evidenced by the awards it won, but it was more than that.
I don't live with psychosis myself, but it spoke to me greatly.
I've lived with anxiety, I have PTSD, and have episodes of dissociation,
and most importantly, I've often felt an outsider as Senua is.
For me, they managed to transcend the tropes I associate with the thriller genre.
Senua was powerful, tender, loving.
The world was hard and cruel to her.
She wasn't terrible.
She wasn't pitiable.
She's a survivor who feels grief, love, and most importantly, hope.
It was empowering.
The game never looked down on her.
Senua also had a sight that meant she could solve puzzles
and see hidden meanings.
As an autistic person, this resonated,
as I'm very good at quickly seeing patterns.
Often, though, this kind of magical ability
frustrates disabled people.
Several deaf and blind people shared with me that this is their least favorite trope,
the savant, such as in Perception and The Quiet Man.
This is written in a variety of ways, and usually poorly.
For example, echolocation for sightless characters
is ironically often shown visually to players.
These cliches only reinforce misconceptions people have about deaf and blind people,
as well as projecting the fact that these characters are broken
and can only be capable with magical abilities.
I think Hellblade dodged this because it wasn't replacing anything,
and it wasn't fundamental to her existence.
It was just like any other skill in an adventure game,
like God of War or Spider-Man.
Again, it was empowering.
I highly recommend watching the talk given at GDC last year by the team.
Spoiler.
They came to the great revelation
that psychosis is just one of many ways to experience reality,
i.e., we're all human,
and disability is just normal human variation.
More than anything, I'd love to see for disabled representation to be more casual.
You really don't have to write about the disabilities.
I see people beside themselves on social media whenever a character happens to be disabled
in games like Overwatch because it's that rare.
This is Angel Giafria, cosplaying as McCree.
She's a one-handed actress that has a real bionic arm.
Hashtag, representation matters.
I really enjoyed Shadow of the Tomb Raider,
and I was shocked and excited when not one,
but three NPCs were blind and disfigured.
For all but one, there was no discussion
of their disabilities, it was just who they were,
and they were good people, and they didn't die.
Back to my visit with the Gears of War team.
There was discussion of representation
and how that might look in a game
with very physically fit characters.
Now, I don't know for sure that it was my input,
so I can't really take credit,
but in the reveal trailer for Gears 5,
we see one of the main characters, JD Phoenix,
stop for a moment, wince in pain,
and activate a futuristic prosthetic.
Major chronic pain representation, just like that.
The best place to start from is to realize that there are more subtle ways to show a
character might have a disability.
Main characters or not, side characters, bit characters, hell we need to be seeing more
disabled people in crowded street scenes since that would just better reflect reality.
So, start small. Braces on a character's wrists, elbows, shoulders, or knees. An indication
that they have chronic pain. Young characters with canes, crutches, or wheelchairs. Just
make sure they're not antiquated or inappropriate. Make deaf or blind characters that aren't
old people or savants.
How about a character that communicates with a smartphone?
Stop giving the disfigurements, limps, or limb differences to the evil characters.
An important note, as with any other character,
disabled people are as diverse as all of humanity.
We're not just white men.
We need to see more disabled people of color, women, LGBTQ+, characters.
Someone could be all of these.
I have multiple disabilities.
I'm bisexual, non-binary, and an adventurer.
At this point, you might be thinking, screw it.
I'm going to make a game about cats because cats are easy.
Well, hold it right there because this
is my one-eyed boy, Odin, and he's here to tell you
that you don't get off that easy.
Ah, the missing eye.
So what's this about villains?
Evil characters are almost always crazy,
disfigured, or disabled.
Even when it's player choice to be evil,
as in Mass Effect or Fable,
you become disfigured and scarred.
Deus Ex was ripe for exploring disability
and what transhumanism might mean for us.
But like most cyberpunk narratives,
no disabled people or accessible streets
are to be seen anywhere.
I live with implants that make me an actual cyborg.
There's a lot of people creating these futuristic worlds
without exploring the kind of devices disabled people live with here and now.
I use wheels.
I get nutrition by IV and have a port that goes directly to my stomach.
They're not a choice.
They keep me alive and autonomous.
They have potentially life-threatening malfunctions.
I love the character design in Deus Ex. Look at that.
That's absolutely what I want my disability representation to look like.
It's one of my absolute favorite IPs.
But Hugh Darrow is the villain in Deus Ex Human Revolution.
He's genetically incompatible with the technology he invented, augmentations,
and unable to cure his own disabilities, he became hellbent on destroying augmented people.
It came so close.
Genetic incompatibility is quite realistic.
I frequently think about the fact
that if I were to need prosthetics,
they wouldn't be an option for me because I'm too fragile.
But why does that lead to Darrow becoming bitter,
hateful, and instrumental in augmenting
people's persecution?
This is bigotry, and disability doesn't make us bigots.
Of course, he also dies.
Spider-Man on the PS4 was another recent example.
Dr. Otto Octavius became evil in part
because of his disabilities, even though he
had altruistic origins.
The only real depictions of disability in the game
were through the lens of devastating disease and cure.
Now, I don't want to make the claim
that disabled people can't ever be bad, but too often,
disability is only a signpost or catalyst for evilness.
If we saw disability applied more positively
in the world building, these games
would have come off much better.
Perhaps we haven't earned the right to make the bad guys and enemies disabled
until we're more deliberate in inclusion.
And here's a shocking idea.
Maybe have even more than one example of disability
in order to mitigate cliches.
When you only have a single representation in a fictional world,
they'll by design be a stereotype.
And since, as I say, a quarter of the world is disabled,
it just also makes more sense.
Now Overcooked is a fun series.
One of the playable characters, a raccoon,
is a wheelchair user.
I love it so much.
We don't know why he uses a wheelchair
and we don't really need to.
Of course, this requires making the levels accessible,
but that should be happening more anyway.
There's nothing weirder than playing a game
and noting the city I'm walking around in
doesn't have a single disabled person,
a dropped curb, or that there's stairs everywhere.
Where did we all go?
Now, Nights in the Woods was a cult favorite.
This is partly because the whimsical story
and characters really had a lot to identify with.
It had excellent LGBTQ plus representation
and surprisingly good mentions of sleep issues,
mental health and movements like flapping.
There was no physical disability,
but many of us appreciate the affectionate nods
to mental health and neurodiversity.
So Hammerlock in Borderlands 2 was probably one of my favourite disabled NPCs.
He had robotic... well, half his body was robotic.
He was so funny and as wholesome as it gets in the Borderlands universe.
Half his quests were ridiculous escapades of revenge on the creatures that took his body parts.
Mass Effect is a difficult one to celebrate,
because it had one of the most horrific depictions
of an autistic character that I may have ever seen.
He was tortured.
But it also had one of the best
physically disabled characters.
Joker was the Normandy star pilot.
It's a shame he wasn't a main party character,
but he was extremely capable and damn hilarious.
His disability was brittle bone disease,
which incidentally is a sister disease to mine.
And so I saw a lot of myself in the Joker.
He made fun of his own disabilities and the crew's awkwardness about it in a very endearing
and realistic way.
The crew highly respected Joker and Shepard even risked her life to save him.
Yes, sorry Shepard will always be a woman to me.
I actually photoshopped that because I could only find one with male Shep in it.
Finally, Moss was the first character that used sign language in a game.
Since I'm not deaf, here's what Susan, who recently passed away, had to say on Twitter.
Seeing Moss use ASL brought me to tears.
Seeing the language I've used my entire life
finally be put in a game as a mechanic
and not a plot device for some victim.
It was just incredible.
So I'm really not saying never explore disability
as a main story arc because if done without assumptions
and the right lens, it can be pretty powerful.
Otherwise, we're still at a point
that even when it's not overwhelmingly negative,
stories about disabled people aren't exactly positive.
Now, the wheelchair in The Surge is a total surprise
as you take hold of the controls.
I was so excited that I actually squealed out loud
and spent an hour wheeling around
where there was no game content
because I knew the inevitable was likely coming.
The wheelchair wouldn't last.
The inevitable cure takes the form of an exosuit,
which is a common plot device along with magical medicine.
Much like Deus Ex and Spider-Man,
the assumption seems to be that all disability
must be cured and that technology will be the answer.
The end of the game is again contempt and fear of the wheelchair, with it being used with horror to taunt the player.
I have really convicting feelings about The Surge because I love the game.
In the end, I'll always fondly remember wheeling around an empty, boring train station, enjoying somewhat accurate wheelchair physics for the first time ever.
Although, they did forget the cushion in the seat.
Let's just move toward telling disabled stories in more positive and respectful ways with less sad stereotypes.
Okay, let's do a quick summary with some takeaways.
Please do include disability in your characters, crowds,
and worlds.
Include disability in diversity efforts.
Portray disability positively.
Make disabled characters diverse.
Include disability and mental health.
And consult disabled people.
But please don't make assumptions.
Exploit disability as a tool for negative emotions.
Erase disability entirely.
And please don't make it the villains disabled.
TV Tropes is an excellent resource to acquaint yourself with common mistakes on representation
across the board.
I meant to put the link in there, I just remembered I did not.
Or did I?
Oh, I did.
TVTropes.org.
Thank God.
A footnote.
Language is hard, and especially since there are cultural differences between countries
and even among individuals.
For example, do we say disabled person or person with disability?
I prefer disabled person, as do most of my friends,
so the short of it is, it's not rude to ask,
so please don't be afraid to.
In fact, questions are so much more appreciated
than using terrible euphemisms like differently abled.
Final footnote, as an accessibility expert,
I have to ask, if you're going to feature stories
about disabled characters, please do your best
to make the games physically and cognitively accessible
to those players themselves.
So it's dangerous to go alone.
Take us.
If you involve disabled people in your process,
as early as possible, you'll be less likely to fall
into the common traps.
Whether actively hiring more disabled people on your team
or bringing in consultants,
ultimately we're the experts of what it's like
to live with disability.
Assumptions are naturally informed by stigma,
and imagined ideas of living with any aspect
of the human condition can never be accurate
because it's really quite different
when you live it every day,
adapting, surviving, and thriving.
Grab my details, but I also encourage you to look for more perspectives.
I could put you in touch with my community or utilize your own.
Please also value people's time and expertise appropriately.
I truly believe that positive disability representation can
begin to heal trauma and stigma, and it doesn't need to be an explicit message.
At the moment, we often just don't exist on a fundamental level in games.
A less direct approach can reach greater audiences than we take a giant hammer with change written
on it and huge letters.
Games are just so powerful because they penetrate people's lives no matter the genre, platform
or how serious they are.
I adore this industry to my very core.
I admire and appreciate all of you that work so hard to make games inclusive.
I fully recognize that in order to get better, we need to make mistakes.
As always, I hope I haven't been too unkind and I'm leaving you with some practical ideas
and a spark of inspiration for moving forward.
The magic of representation happens when all our various disciplines work together and
it's just part of our culture.
Remember, one quarter of the world are disabled,
including people of all genders, races, cultures, sexualities, backgrounds.
And games are profoundly important in so many disabled people's lives.
And finally, please don't forget I took an arrow to the knee
and I'm still an adventurer.
APPLAUSE
Wow, that was pretty traumatic, wasn't it?
But such is the life of an adventurer.