Okay everybody, looks like we're ready to get started.
And thank you, nice to see I got a full house here.
I don't see, I see a few of you standing up
and actually usually there are empty spaces
but I think we've got everything full.
So welcome, this is Game Designer's View
of Neuroscience VR.
And I will...
I'm going to be talking about quite a range here, but I want to start out with a disclaimer right at the beginning that I am a game designer.
I've actually been making games professionally since 1980, so a long time in this field.
been interested in science, as a lot of game designers are all that time.
And I was working for big companies.
I was one of the first employees at places like LucasArts and DreamWorks Interactive.
But then from 96 or so up until
about four years ago, I was a freelance designer and producer.
And as I did that freelance work, I got more and more interested in what was
for a while called serious games.
specifically working with games on the medical side and games that either work as treatment
or therapy for medical conditions or games that are designed to train doctors and caregivers
and that was an area that got really interesting to me.
Then four years ago, I got an offer to come to Google and work as their chief game designer
and couldn't pass that up and spent the last four years doing that, but wasn't able to
really work on the kinds of projects that get out in people's hands.
And meanwhile, I felt that neuroscience in particular
was making wonderful strides and coming together with games and I just wanted to be part of
that again so I've dived back into that end of it.
And I'm hoping to inspire some of you.
Just out of curiosity, how many people here have already worked with medical neuroscience
projects on your side of things?
Not too many.
How many of you are professional game developers?
Okay, so about the ratio I expected mostly on the game side and obviously a lot of hands.
It didn't go up of all the different niches of technology and video and media and everything
that we've got going on here.
So anyway.
I will be speaking about this from a game designer's point of view and I think I'm reasonably
well informed but any of you that are actual neuroscientists can talk rings around me so
my apologies on that level if I don't have everything together for you.
But I'll be talking today about why I think neuroscience matters, why it's such an exciting
field at the time.
I'll be going into three areas specifically, motion in VR and how you move through spaces
with VR and how that relates to neuroscience.
The whole thing about immersion and presence, and I'm not going to dive too deeply into
any one of these just for time issues.
But a lot of people bandy about words like, you know, VR gives you a sense of immersion
and presence without ever really talking about what does that mean and why does it give us
that kind of immersion.
And finally, and the area that I'm most interested in is what does this mean for emotions and
feelings that are able to be evoked by VR and how is that actually affecting our brains
and what can we do?
as developers to learn and take advantage.
Then the final thing will be to sort of wrap that up to talk a little bit about some of
the future, both of some entertainment possibilities and also these health applications that I
think are really interesting crossover.
So in this process I'm going to try to
you know, give you a sense of what I know is really a fact, what is being inferred from
facts and what is pure speculation. I may not always get that right, so when we go to
the Q&A, please feel free to ask, you know, when you said X, did you really mean that
this has been proven and tested or is that just your wild ass speculation? And sadly,
in some cases, it will be the third, but hopefully that will be inspiring too.
My view of all this, in fact, having a long history in the games industry, I think is
relevant for a number of reasons.
I've seen new technologies come and go.
I've seen new evolutions.
The first games that I played on a computer were text-based.
In fact, the very first ones were paper-based before there were even video screens.
And I've seen the evolution first
to video screens where we used them to display more text but you didn't have to actually
worry about whether you were running out of ink, to of course graphics and animation and
then we had revolutions like CD-ROM and suddenly a hundredfold increase in storage, then things
like video and being able to have full, what we called full motion video, the idea that
you could actually do, you know, amazing, you know, about
five frame a second video clips that looked absolutely terrible.
But all the different things we've gone through to get to the latest revolutions in virtual
reality, which are both new and actually very old as I'll get into.
But an analogy that I found useful that I like to look at is that each time you get
one of these new technologies, it's like you're going through a mountain pass and there's
a sense of excitement.
Is this going to open out?
Is it going to be just a little cul-de-sac and you're going to have to backtrack?
There's going to be a whole new continent.
And you really don't know until you get out there and you start experimenting with it.
One of the things that everyone is nervous about...
is that both of those might be right and that you're going out there and you end up getting
stuck on this little precipice with no way to get into this huge area that you see opening
up and all of your competitors are out there and they said, oh yeah, we figured out exactly
how to use VR and monetize it and we're making lots of money.
I don't think anybody's quite at that point yet, but all of us are waiting to see who's
going to find their way down to these open valleys potentially.
entire new continents to explore.
And I really think, personally I'm a strong believer, I think VR, AR, mixed reality, whatever
you want to call it, all of these things are already really exciting and are going to get
much bigger in the near future and I'll hopefully be able to tell you some of the reasons why.
But along that way, it is easy to get stuck.
And part of why I think getting down to science,
I think neuroscience is critical with VR,
I've often used evolution and an understanding
of what we as humans are evolved to perceive
and to appreciate to guide me
into new forms of entertainment.
Because I think if you get down to the fundamentals,
of who we are as human beings and what makes us excited, what makes us engaged.
That's the basis of entertainment, it's the basis of learning,
it's the basis of a lot of what these technologies are intended to do.
So hopefully neuroscience can help us find this right path and get down from these little
precipice and out into the rich farmlands below.
It's in some ways kind of like a compass.
It doesn't always tell us exactly how to get somewhere, but it can point the right direction,
give you some tantalizing hints.
And I'm not going to be giving you a lot of turnkey solutions to things, but in some cases
hopefully I will be intriguing you with areas that you can look into on your own more.
and get into a little bit more depth because there's a very wide range of things to cover
so I don't have the time to get into a lot of depth for any one thing.
Just to give you a sense though, I'm not going to spend too much time on this particular
aspect of it, but I would like to give you a sort of historical sense of where VR fits
in this sort of larger scale of human evolution and technology.
So...
I love this cave painting. This is a cave painting from, I believe, around 20,000 years ago, but
there are cave paintings going back as far as 40,000 years, and of course,
as people explore, they may find even older ones.
I find it amazing that this is a 20,000 year old piece of art, and
try as I might, I couldn't draw anything with the best tools that was even close to as realistic
a bison as that is. It's hard to see in this particular flat picture here, but the artist
who was clearly doing this by torchlight with pigments that had been made Lord knows how,
actually used some of the contours of the rock.
to evoke almost a 3D sense of this bison.
At one point, I knew the actual name of it.
It's an extinct relative of the aurochs,
I think, that were roaming Europe at the time
that this was made.
So it's amazing that for at least 40,000 years,
our ancestors have been struggling with this problem of,
I saw something and I want to describe it to you.
In fact, no, I want you to be able to see what I saw.
And maybe it's not even that I saw something,
but I had a vision, I had something I imagined,
something that came to me while I was sleeping.
I would like to share that with you.
And we've had this quest now for tens of thousands of years of how to improve our technology to do that.
Some of the stuff going back thousands of years, the camera obscura, the Romans were into this, of using a sort of pinhole camera to be able to get this beautiful view of essentially a live action camera of what was going on around you.
In the Middle Ages, they really started to get into shadow plays and projecting a light onto a wall.
and using your hands to make shadows and do animation.
There's been an interest in doing that for a long time.
In fact, the next couple of slides I'm going to show you are the pictures that I took at
a museum in Girona, Spain, near Barcelona, Museum of Cinema.
I'm curious, has anyone been to the Museum of Cinema in Girona?
Just one or two hands.
I would...
Highly recommend it.
There are game conferences in Barcelona,
which is how I got out there, if you have a reason to get out there.
It was great because I thought it was going to be just about movie making,
but they got into all this information about the predecessors,
including things like the magic lantern that you see here.
that was from roughly 200 to 100 years ago where they would start with originally a very
bright flame and then they used electric lights.
It was essentially some of the first slide projectors, but it was a way to show images
and project them against the wall.
And like many other technologies, it was first something that you would, you know, it was expensive and difficult to do, so you would come to a public performance,
and then wealthy people were able to afford these very beautifully made versions of it at home,
and then they started to make less expensive, maybe less fancy, but more accessible versions for the home.
It was a huge thing around the late 1800s.
And moved on, of course, to the...
early film cameras. Same kind of evolution of stuff where you'd have to go to the theater,
and then wealthy people were able to afford their own cameras. Eventually, it became something where
people could afford them. Of course, now we carry around a whole film studio in our pocket.
I love the scene in the Back to the Future movie where he comes in with his 1985 camera,
and Doc Brown is amazed that he's got this whole television studio on his shoulder.
Now, we have something much more sophisticated that we stick in our pocket and give it another
30 years and it will be either on our glasses or possibly embedded in our skulls at that
point.
That kind of process of always wanting to have better ways of showing a higher resolution,
more realistic images, and make it more accessible so that we can have it every day has been
going on for a long time.
Going into the 20th century, same kind of thing.
VR started to get involved earlier than a lot of people have seen.
There have been wonderful talks at other VR conferences about some of the early stuff
from going back to the 1950s and even earlier.
I love this sensorama thing, just really trying to engage all the different senses.
The military with heads-up displays has been working on this for quite a while.
I saw my first virtual reality demo in the mid-80s, I think around 1985, when Jaron Lanier,
who actually was popularizing the term virtual reality, came to give us a demo when I was
working at LucasArts.
It was actually Lucasfilm Games at the time.
He had a company called VPL, which stood for Visual Programming Language.
He was really excited because they had invented this visual language where you could use images
to program.
And almost as an afterthought, he had created something called the data glove that you could
put on and had sensors and you could manipulate the images on the screen by gesturing with
your hand.
And one of the things that kept happening is that he would
be showing us the screen and moving stuff.
And he was so excited about this visual programming language.
And we were all focused on the glove and this idea
that you're reaching into the screen
and you can actually kind of engage
with what was then even at that point being called cyberspace.
And in fact, David Fox, who just walked in here,
was at that very same demo.
But these were early stages, like a lot of things, it was promised to be this wonderful
new thing that was going to be around the corner in just a few years and took a lot
longer than people thought.
The Virtual Boy that Nintendo did was yet another precipice out there that was really
an interesting experiment, but it was just not good enough and way too cumbersome to
be mass-market in the way that it could be successful.
But a lot of what we can do, I think, is a common thread in all of these things is what's
going on with our eyes, with our brains, how do we perceive these things?
What is it about these images?
Going back to those earliest cave paintings, there are still things, we think of that as
a picture of a bison.
Ultimately, what you're seeing are photons from an image that's projected from my computer
of a picture that was taken of a painting that was done of this bison.
There are so many levels between the reality of what that person saw 20,000 years ago and
what you just saw now.
And yet, coming
I'm getting chills just thinking about this.
That wasn't just a thought that they had.
That was a real animal that was alive 20,000 years ago that through this long chain of
technology and humanity has been brought to the present.
You are perceiving it in your brain in many ways through a whole bunch of tricks to trick
your eye into thinking that that image you see, those photons, are like the real photons
you get off of that animal itself.
So if we can understand how our eyes and brains work,
we can also understand all the shortcuts
that our nervous system does,
because it can't afford to take in everything
that's around us and process it all at once.
We're dealing with this now when we've got,
you know, the phones in particular.
are just going flat out trying to do a great 3D display,
much less being able to scan the world around them.
We're just at the edges of them being able to start
to do that a little bit, so we have to get selective.
And understanding what's going on inside people's
visual systems, their brains, their vestibular systems
and balance is really helpful because we don't need
to give all that information.
We can give just the pieces that are necessary.
So the first of these areas that I'm going to get into is motion.
And one of the first things that comes up with VR, of course,
is that idea of potential motion sickness.
This is something that's been around for quite a while as well.
I've got the picture of the boat in a storm out there because, of course,
there's a connection to seasickness, car sickness.
And again, thinking of it from an evolutionary point of view,
If you are moving around in a world and you see things in that world,
there's a one-to-one correspondence with how your head is moving and what your eyes are seeing.
And over history...
If there was a problem, if there was a mismatch, let's sort of get into the vestibular system that's able to sense how your head is moving and therefore keep a sense of your orientation.
If there was a mismatch between what the semicircular canals in your inner ear.
we're sensing that, you know, it's really interesting that I'm sure many of you have
seen this, but there are those three semicircular canals that are oriented like the three mutually
perpendicular areas of pitch, yaw, and roll so that they can sense within your head as
you move your head, rotate it in any direction.
If that was not matching up with what you saw for millennia, for millions of years really,
that usually meant that you had maybe eaten a poison mushroom or maybe that leftover haunch
from the kill from a week ago had kind of turned a little green and you were hungry
and you ate it anyway.
And poison in your system sometimes interfered with what you saw compared to what you were
actually sensing.
And the best response to realizing you were poisoned
was to try and purge your system of those poisons,
which is why we get nauseous when we have things like motion sickness,
from whether it's sea sickness, car sickness, or now VR sickness.
So, it's useful understanding that.
It doesn't do much for the people that actually experience it,
but we have learned quite a bit of how to minimize those things.
And sadly, just as with sea sickness, car sickness,
there are some people that are really sensitive
and can never read a book and be in a car, for example.
I think we're always, and this is just my conjecture here,
but I think we're always going to have some people
at one end of that spectrum who just have trouble with that
and are gonna have trouble with a lot of VR
if they move too swiftly.
But there are things that we can do to help.
I'm gonna talk about how the brain tries to match
the motion of your head with the visual system.
I'll get into some more of the details of that later.
But the bottom line is that if there's a mismatch,
there's a problem.
And unfortunately, there are dozens, if not thousands, of ways that there can be mismatches,
so we're working on that.
And you don't want that sense that you're being poisoned.
Those of you working in developing VR,
something that's happened universally
with every team I've talked to is pretty quickly
everyone finds the one person on their team
that is most sensitive to VR motion sickness
and that poor person becomes the guinea pig
for all of the new demos.
And it's a really simple system.
I frankly don't think we're gonna have a better system
than that for a long time to come.
So those of you that are,
anybody here who is that person on your team?
Oh yeah, I see some,
poor, poor schlubs there that are doing that and happily are committed enough to keep coming
here so more power to you. And hopefully there will be some reason for hope as we can figure
out ways to minimize that. But this will be an issue that we're going to have to deal
with as we move forward. So how can we minimize it?
Turns out obviously one of the biggest mismatches, I say obviously but we only found this out
empirically through trying stuff, is that having a really high frame rate is critically
important.
90 frames a second is being held out.
It turns out that
You can certainly get up to 120 frames a second before it starts to get to the point where I don't think there's a whole lot of necessity to go much faster than that.
The ability of us to perceive stuff happening faster than 120 frames a second is, it is there, but now we're getting down to a pretty tiny percentage of the population.
And yet, this is really an interesting point because frame rate, of course, is governed
heavily by how much you're doing in each frame.
The more processing you do, the harder it is to keep up, you know, the faster a processor
you need to be able to do that.
And so almost everything else that we have in VR...
is fighting against that frame rate problem.
There's this constant temptation to say,
well, we can make the visual field bigger,
we can come into higher resolution,
we could do better quality graphics,
we could just live with a little bit
of a less of a frame rate.
And sometimes that's actually a reasonable trade off.
If you're not moving people through that space,
you can get away with a little bit slower frame rate.
But in general, that's gonna be a critical thing.
and closely coupled with that, is sensing where your head is and what your vision is looking at at any given time.
It's been thrown around many times that 20 milliseconds motion to photon is kind of the minimum that you want,
or rather the maximum that you want.
If it's faster than that, it's even better.
And what that would mean is that you need less than 20 milliseconds between the time you're turning your head
and the time you're actually seeing the visual system respond.
20 milliseconds is actually pushing it.
That's the area where it's comfortable for a lot of people, but not everyone.
It's really hard, again, to get much faster than that, particularly with the kinds of
systems that we have that were not designed for this in the first place.
Meaning that the kind of visuals we have on our phones and TVs and everything were not
originally set up for VR.
They were set up for watching a screen passively and not having a screen that's moving.
So getting all those visual cues right is really difficult.
You don't need to get every single visual cue right, of course,
and I'll talk a little bit about some of the shortcuts.
How am I doing on time?
Yeah, I won't have much time for that.
Minimizing acceleration has been really critical
because of course your inner ear,
tells acceleration if you're moving at a constant speed, it has trouble telling that.
Pilots in planes go through a process where they're shown that if they are very gradually
moved into different planes, they actually don't sense it and they can even be hanging
upside down and not realize it if they don't have the visual cues to help them understand
that.
But there are some creative solutions.
I'll talk about one particular one that I think is a great example of using understanding
of the brain to help use some shortcuts so that we don't have to do quite as much processing
and we can make it more comfortable for a lot of people.
So some of the stuff that we found, having a constant speed certainly helps.
It's interesting, Chris Pruitt, who was just in here earlier in the room, gave a talk a
couple of years ago where he talked about how we've had, as game developers, to unlearn
certain things.
That smooth acceleration into a certain speed and deceleration was the gold standard for
a long time.
And then we hit VR and it turns out that no,
going from a dead stop to a constant speed
and back to a dead stop is much better
because nobody really does that in real life.
So it doesn't set off that sense
that there's something wrong in your brain
that, wait a minute, something's weird.
Because of course it's weird,
just like the other solution of teleportation.
We aren't used to what teleporting is like.
If an alien race that can teleport showed up,
came in and saw our VR, they might be horrified
because we get teleportation all wrong
and it doesn't feel that way.
But luckily, we're not one of those aliens
so we're okay there.
But those are things that work. The other thing that I mentioned is curves. This is from a game that we did at Google
called Zushi. And yes, Google actually does make some games internally.
This was a game, a VR game, where you're on a raft moving down a stream. And we did that on purpose because
it's slow and it lets you see where you're about to turn and curve.
And it did have acceleration as you move around those curves. You're getting, you know,
acceleration around the curve, but we found for most people, as long as the speed was
slow and they could see where they were going and anticipate that they'd have that curve,
it wasn't so bad.
Much like somebody in a car, if you're driving, you're much less likely to get car sick than
if you're a passenger and if you're looking at a book or something and you're not seeing
the world around you.
Or with seasickness, if you're down in the hold and you're not able to see the horizon,
you don't get the right visual cues.
The cues are that nothing is moving and yet your inner ear is telling you you are moving.
So matching those things up really can help.
Now, back in the movie industry, I'm sure most of you are familiar with this little bit,
I have very strong memories of being in a theater in 1977 and seeing that first Star Wars movie.
In this moment where it zooms down and bounces up, you can hear the audience go,
whoa, because there's enough of a sense with this huge screen
that you're actually kind of on a roller coaster ride.
They did it again in the Battle of Hoth in Empire Strikes Back where there's a
a quick moment where the snow speeders do a similar kind of maneuver.
But in general, people don't get movie sick.
There are some people, actually, shaky cams and having that move around can really disturb some people.
But a lot of this doesn't bother people.
And it's a really interesting clue.
When you see, well, why is it that we haven't had so much of a problem with films?
And you look for the cases where it is a problem.
So one of the areas where it does come to be a problem
is in IMAX films, suddenly people get motion sickness again.
The interesting thing there is understanding about the way your visual system works.
You've got what's called the foveal area that is about two degrees left and right, up and
down, the very center.
So when you're looking at something, you're focusing, your eyes are focusing the image
on a particular part of your retina that essentially is for high-resolution viewing.
The rest of your retina has a lot of rods and cones that can pick up visual images,
but that's what we call our peripheral vision.
And even though our brain tricks us into thinking it's a nice continuum, it's not.
Those two areas work quite differently.
And if you can take advantage of that, you can actually shortcut a lot of these things
and can be very helpful.
So what happens is in an IMAX film or other cases where you sit really close to a screen,
your peripheral vision actually sees all of this motion and it's starting, you know, it
turns out that your peripheral vision is connected to a lot of your systems that give you a sense
of orientation.
Partly because if you are focused on, for example, you're stalking an antelope.
You may have your foveal vision aimed right at that antelope, but as you're moving along,
your peripheral vision is telling you the way your body is moving and matching that
up with what your inner ear is saying.
So if you have motion in your peripheral vision, your brain is processing that.
So one of the things that has come up is if you can, you know, there's some really interesting
experiments of processing an image that you see only in the foveal area that you're looking
at and having the peripheral vision, you know, not being as high resolution, not requiring
as much processing power.
It's necessary to have eye tracking and I'll talk about that in a bit.
But one of the shortcuts that people have found is that if you blur or even black out
your peripheral vision and still move the foveal vision, you get an interesting effect.
This is why something like Star Wars was okay, but IMAX can be a problem to people.
What this is called is tunneling locomotion.
Actually, coincidentally, at this very moment, there are some Google Earth people in one
of the other talks, and you're going to get at least a little sense of Google Earth.
This is a brief clip of tunneling in Google Earth.
What they do is, in order to move you, they bring in this grid into your peripheral vision.
and you still see a moving image in the center,
and you're going to have to take my word for it
because you really need to be in VR to get that full sense of this.
But oddly enough, even though this looks really strange,
in VR it actually feels quite comfortable.
If you're looking, for one thing,
as the rest of the peripheral vision goes away,
you naturally are drawn to look directly at the area in your foveal view there that's
directly ahead of you on the screen.
And it turns out that this eliminates a lot of the kind of motion sickness people get
from that acceleration and deceleration, because that is apparently being picked up by your
peripheral vision, and when it's not there to disconcert your peripheral vision, it's
okay, and you can still keep people oriented with the motion that they're going through.
Here's a game that I have to say I haven't played.
I just found this online called Sub Level Zero that does a similar thing.
There are other VR demos and games out there that use this tunneling locomotion.
I bring it up not to say that everybody needs to do this, but just to point out that it's
a really interesting, clever way that not only deals with the problem of
motion sickness and VR sickness here,
but it also means you don't have to process all that stuff.
You're just graying it out and that gives you
a lot more cycles to work on the area
that you're showing in the center of the screen,
which can be very handy.
You can keep up a very high frame rate
in the areas that you do show.
This is likely to be coming to mobile in the future.
And where eye tracking, as I said, is really interesting.
Right now, the foveal view is done by sort of brute forcing,
saying the only thing to look at is this one thing right in front of you.
But wouldn't it be great if we could get to the point where wherever you happen to look,
that's the only area we render in high resolution, and the rest of it we don't have to bother.
And, in fact, with eye tracking rigs that are out there, there will probably be demos.
I haven't had a chance to see what's being demoed here.
today, but I've seen it at a lot of other VR conferences.
There are eye trackers that providentially you need to be really close to somebody's
eye and of course with VR headsets and AR headsets for that matter, we now have a reason
to mount a camera that can look at somebody's eye and see the motions of their pupil.
It's not perfect yet, but it works really well already and as these things become more
commercially available, I'm expecting that it's going to become built into all systems,
certainly on head-mounted VR.
But even on your phone, there's some interesting stuff going on in the announcements about...
the new iPhones and facial recognition.
I've read some interesting stuff about using those forward-facing cameras to actually track
people's eyes there too.
So hopefully even with mobile we'll be seeing this in the near future.
I don't have, that's speculation again on my part, but it's nice not having to work
for Google and worry about having it be front page news if I even hinted something like
that.
I see some of my fellow Googlers are smiling ruefully at that one.
So the trick is, and I only covered this one area here,
but if you learn about the ways that the eye and the brain interact,
you can actually get little cues, little clues really,
that you can use to then ferret out these systems
and find ways that you can take shortcuts that can make the VR quality better.
So that's all I'm going to say about the motion side.
But motion is an important part of the sense of immersion
that we get in VR.
That word, immersion, gives you this sense
of this nice warm bath.
And certainly, VR is pretty amazing
when it gets everything right of how
you feel that you're actually in the moment.
It's just.
It's almost indescribable and the nice thing is this is one of the few areas where everyone
has had that experience and knows what it's like.
But the trick is there's a whole lot that you have to get right.
There are entire talks given to even just single elements of this, certainly this whole
range of things.
I've listed some of the more common.
areas that you need to get right. I've talked about getting the frame rate and the head
tracking right, but that's only the beginning of the puzzle. There are so many other things
that you need to do to try and recreate what we see with our eyes that it frankly at this
point with the processors, with the screens and everything we have, it is impossible to
get really close to what our eyes and brains are capable of seeing. Happily though it feels
that we've gotten just good enough in the last few years that it starts to be a convincing
simulation of that. One of the things that isn't even on this list that I've seen some
interesting first steps on is the fact that your eye works a bit like a camera and that
you focus with muscles in your eye changing the shape of your eye and
of the lens in your eye to focus, as a camera does, close and far away.
So if you hold your finger close to your eye, you focus on it,
and everything else in the background is blurred.
And likewise, if you look in the distance, you can hold your finger up,
and that's kind of blurry.
It's because the lens in your eye is actually stretching and changing shape.
In current systems that are out there now, they can't account for that, but there will be systems coming in the fairly near future that will be able to actually, even with one eye closed, be able to give you a sense of depth.
But right now, one of the miscues that we're getting is that things don't actually change depth of field when you're looking at them through a screen.
You're looking at this screen that's right in front of your eyes.
and you can kind of fake it with some cases,
but it actually doesn't quite do a full job there.
So some part of your brain is saying,
there's something not right here,
and if you're one of those unlucky people who raised your hand,
it's probably making you feel a little bit ill.
So there's a lot to get right.
If anybody here worked on this, don't raise your hand.
I'm sorry I brought this up because I found this online.
I thought it was a great example of what not to do.
And I don't want to hit these people too hard because it's
a language teaching program and they really weren't working so
much on VR visuals.
But some of those things I had on that list before are just
broken here.
For example, in the foreground, you've got a kind of blurred
table and a crystal clear sharp bell that just really irritates me because it feels like that, you know,
if that, why is that so clear when the rest of it is is blurry and the blurriness is consistent. It should actually be
sharper, closer up, and a little blurrier in the distance or vice versa depending on where the depth of field is.
The worst thing about this, in my opinion though, is that the interface that they have is floating there in space in front of you.
And it turns out that this is a bad thing for a lot of reasons.
For one reason, your eyes are focusing on it and they're converging on this image.
And even though that may be shown left and right in slightly different places,
so that your eyes can say, yes, this is about two feet in front of me.
It is almost certainly being done without any perspective change in the two eyes.
And if it were a real thing, you'd have a different view from your right eye and your
left eye, particularly something that's only a few feet away.
You see a little bit more of the edges of something on the right side with your right
eye, left side, left eye.
And in a lot of shortcuts people use like this for interface, they don't do that.
So it's really a mistake to sort of violate that sense of presence by breaking any of
these rules.
And digetic interface is the term that's been brought up to actually put it into the world.
So in a case like this, you could just as easily put that interface.
on what look like some plaques that are part of the 3D world and that are situated in that
3D world that your eye converges on properly and it makes it a lot easier for someone to
perceive.
It's harder, it's a lot more processing to actually put those up correctly, but this
is one of the things that you, I think, should not take too many shortcuts with or it's really
going to be irritating to the people.
And again, study the way the visual system works.
There's a lot more than I can go into in just this hour.
But another thing, another great lesson that turns out to be true of VR as it was
of other things is that less is more.
You don't actually have to get everything right.
You can actually cut a lot of corners as long as you're very minimal about what you do.
And I'll talk about some examples.
But first I want to remind everybody when you do get it right,
It's pretty amazing.
This is one of the first VR images I saw in the modern VR world that really convinced
me.
I saw one of the early Valve tag rooms before they even announced what the Vive was.
It was just a life-changing experience for me.
In particular, I remember
when I was told, okay, pick up the controller.
And I said, well, I can't see the controller.
So sure you can, look over your shoulder.
And there on a virtual table was a virtual controller.
And I remember reaching over thinking,
I thought I saw a table when I came into the room,
not really believing it,
and feeling an actual controller
exactly where this virtual eye told me it would be.
And feeling that in my hand
was one of the most amazing moments I've had.
when VR gets this right, it's amazing.
And it wasn't very high resolution.
It was really just a simple trick
of combining that haptic feedback
of what I could feel in my hand
with what my visual system told me,
and it was exactly where it was supposed to be.
That's really a part of the critical thing,
and part of what I think is the magic of VR,
and what we're really aiming for here.
So go for that feeling.
I've had a lot of people say, yeah, VR isn't ready yet.
You know, we need another 20 years.
No, I think you have that kind of experience.
And how many people here experiencing
VR had at some point that amazing, whoa,
this is way more real than I thought it would be?
Can I see hands?
Yeah.
Look at how many hands.
Virtually everybody in the room is here
because they had that moment.
Believe in it, folks.
You can fool some of the people some of the time, or even all of the time, but there's a lot of us here.
And I've had that experience with every person I've brought in to VR with some very, very few exceptions.
And often it turns out that they have a wandering eye or some other problem that they can't focus and get that full sense of VR.
Okay, next thing I want to cover though, what I think is the most important thing, is sense of emotion.
Anybody want to call out what this movie is?
Creature from the Black Lagoon, a classic.
What was really interesting about this is that it was one of the first movies that was
done in 3D on a large scale with those awful little red and green things back in the 1950s,
I believe.
And what they did is what a whole bunch of people with modern VR are doing, which are
saying, hey, we can scare people with this stuff.
And it turns out that VR is really good at scaring people.
I don't know if you've seen maybe first hand or maybe the videos of people who were put
into some kind of horror game and took their thousand dollar headset and threw it against
the wall before they realized, oh gee, sorry I was just so scared I had to get it off my
head as quickly as possible.
So probably not a great thing to do.
Cinema, as with some of these other things I've mentioned, has been experimenting with these things.
They're great as a place to learn from.
My friend Hal Barwood, who is a film director and writer before he got into the games industry,
had all sorts of interesting stories like this, including one about 3D sound
and how when they started to first do surround sound,
they found that people were about three times as likely to jump from the exact same sound
played behind them as in front of them.
Again, from an evolutionary standpoint, it makes perfect sense why we are hardwired to
be a lot more scared of stuff that's creeping up behind us than stuff that we can see in
front of us.
With the 3D stuff, of course, all the way up even to frustratingly movies that are coming
out this very week, there's stuff being thrown at your face to kind of, oh no.
That may work the very first time you've seen it, but please don't keep doing that.
It gets very thin very quickly.
you end up with something that will look as dated as our little monster here does very
quickly.
So, really what I'm saying is that VR and emotion in VR is a good servant and a bad
master.
You can go from that warm sense of immersion I was showing you.
to really scary horror very quickly.
This is actually, if you have that ability to
defocus your eyes or cross them to make a 3D image,
when this girl sort of pops out in 3D, even just looking at the screen,
it's a little bit disturbing.
But why is it so disturbing? Why is horror in VR so strong?
This is one of those areas where there's some very clear brain science behind it.
At the very bottom center of this, there's the amygdala called out.
And the amygdala is a very old part of the brain.
It's present in fish and reptile brains.
In fact, it's much larger in proportion to the entire brain.
in a lot of our ancestors and our relatives like that.
Our cerebral cortex, all that big gray matter where you do a lot of your critical thinking,
is a relatively recent addition compared to the amygdala.
And what the amygdala can handle are some very basic functions.
Fear is one of the primary things among them.
It also handles anger and aggression.
And those two together give you the famous fight or flight
that you need when you're under a threat
to be able to decide almost instantly,
should I run away from this thing?
Should I fight it?
And that is so much built into our DNA.
that it's the first thing that comes up before we do any kind of extra processing on that.
One of the things that the amygdala also controls that is also just as deep and just as important
for propagation and evolution is arousal and intimacy.
This is also part of our brain that gets activated in romance and when somebody is close to us
physically or emotionally.
A lot of that is mediated by the amygdala.
Now in video games, the fight or flight stuff, aggression, fear, we're really good at that
sort of thing.
The sort of softer emotions like empathy and love, we're not quite so good at that.
We're still working on that piece.
And I'm really excited because for a long time, I've worked for several companies,
LucasArts and DreamWorks in particular, where there were a lot of movie people.
And they were sometimes even a little smug about the fact that movies were so much better
at empathy, at love, at romance, and that sort of thing.
This is something that's gone back a long time, but one of the reasons that they're
good at it is because we feel that sense of intimacy.
In fact, the very word brings forth the idea of being close to somebody, physically actually
close to them.
This goes way back again to film days, about a hundred years ago.
the director, D.W. Griffith, was pitching to some people.
He had Mary Pickford, who was one of the first It girls,
one of the first actresses that was famous
because she was so pretty and had that sense of presence
on screen that came through.
And he was gonna do something called close-ups
where her face could be 50 feet tall on the screen.
And he didn't put it this way, of course, but the idea is to trick your brain into thinking
not that she's 50 feet tall, but that she's normal size and she's really close to you.
And it turns out that movie executives haven't changed at all in the last hundred years,
and that what he was told is, you know, Mr. Griffith, you know, I'm horrified at this.
When we hired Miss Pickford, we paid for the entire actress.
I want to see the entire actress on that screen.
But he was able to convince them that close-ups actually are a good thing.
And of course, they're one of the ways that movies have been able to give us that sense
of intimacy and leapfrog what we don't really get in games.
I mean, having even a full-screen game with a face close-up doesn't quite have
that same sense as when you're in a movie theater.
But with VR, you can be every bit as close, and in fact even closer, and it's even better
than a movie screen or even a 3D projection because it's tricking more of your senses,
and as you turn your head, you can tell that this character
or this person or this hedgehog is right there next to you.
Some of the Oculus people a few years ago gave a great talk about how they actually
ran into trouble with this because I'm sure a lot of people here have seen Henry the Oculus
movie that they did.
He's a sad little hedgehog.
It's his birthday and all of his friends have abandoned him.
He doesn't have many friends because he's so spiny.
And you really feel sorry for the guy.
And part of that, I'm convinced, and now it's conjecture,
but I think it's based on good inference from the way
that your brain works, is because you are physically
right there in the room with him, and he's right next to you.
And you get that sense of empathy and caring about him,
partly because of that.
And also partly because of something else.
He looks you right in the eye.
And he can tell when you look at him,
not so much from where your eyes are,
but just from the way your whole head is pointing.
in the camera and they found that people responded really well
when you look at him directly and he would smile and wave at you and his eyes
would get big.
So they put a lot of that in there. They didn't stop to think that the story they
did is about him being sad and lonely because he has no friends.
Hi, how are you doing? Yeah, it's so awful. Everyone I care about
hates me. Hi, how are you doing? It's like, oh, wow, I guess I'm
a real...
pariah here and he doesn't like me for some reason.
So they actually had a bit of a misconnect between their script and the emotional connection
of both that proximity and gaze.
And gaze is, we haven't experimented with a lot in VR.
As we get into eye tracking, expect we'll do more.
In film, it's been done all over the place.
Actors are famous for their smoldering looks.
And it really affects you emotionally.
And again, you look at this close up,
when Leonardo DiCaprio or Kate Winslet
are right there in front of you,
you can see them close up,
and it affects you emotionally.
Well, this works really well in VR.
And in terms of shortcuts, you don't need an actor.
You don't need full resolution.
Google has something called Spotlight Stories
that I'm still very fond of.
And when I was working for them, I
would try and promote it because a lot of people
weren't that familiar with them.
How many people here have seen Spotlight Stories
and played around with them?
That's not bad.
You see, I'm up to about a third of the room.
I think two years ago I would get one or two hands that would go up.
I strongly recommend, I'm going to mention a few more of them in the next few minutes.
This particular one is called Pearl, and it was the first movie made for VR that was nominated
for an Oscar.
Unfortunately, it didn't win this year, but it did win an Emmy this year.
I'd really recommend you check it out on whatever VR system you have.
It's available on quite a wide range and certainly on Daydream and the less expensive ones, as
well as on Vive.
And it's really effective.
Part of the reason it's effective, it's a very short, it's like a five minute, almost
like the Pixar shorts you see before they're full features.
And as you can see, not very high resolution.
There's no dialogue in it.
So quite simple.
But it's shot almost entirely from the passenger seat of a car.
So you get, this is a full 360 view and of course when it's actually in VR, you're seeing
a much narrower field of view so everyone seems much closer.
And you get that sense of physical intimacy which I believe is triggering your amygdala.
is making you feel like these people are right there in the car with you.
You could reach out and touch them and vice versa.
And that I think is triggering a sense of empathy.
I found myself
watching this in VR, it's extremely emotionally engaging.
And when I've seen it on YouTube on a flat screen,
it doesn't have that same effect.
And then I go back into VR,
and I actually find myself moved to tears again.
So I would recommend that you check that out.
Of course, your mileage may vary about what really hits you.
So for emotion, I would recommend watch out
with fear and aggression.
Yes, you can get really strong with VR very easily,
but you can overdo it very easily.
Let's not.
be the laughingstock of the future and overdo it.
I really think there's a lot of room for emotion and empathy and even romance in games that
we can do in VR films.
I'll get into some speculation on that in a moment.
But realize that VR is building on very old biology.
This is talking about stuff that in some cases is many millions of years old.
The amygdala was formed, as far as scientists can tell,
hundreds of millions of years ago by our very, very distant ancestors.
You can use this to explore some really new approaches that we've never been able to do before.
What are some of those things?
Well, let me speculate on a few of them.
In terms of movies,
Again, I'll hit some of the spotlight stories.
There are two that I would also strongly recommend you look at.
Special Delivery and The Simpsons did a 600th episode in VR.
What's interesting about both of these is that both of these are comedy.
Special Delivery was done by Aardman Studios who do the Wallace and Gromit films.
They both use a 360 view, all the spotlight stories do.
to give you the ability to look anywhere around you.
But they've built a bunch of Easter eggs
and little stories that pop up.
And in special delivery, in fact,
it's about a night watchman who thinks there's a burglar.
And it turns out it's Christmas Eve and it's Santa Claus.
Sorry for the spoiler there.
But the point is that he's tracking Santa
all through this courtyard.
And you're in the center of the courtyard rotating around,
looking into the rear windows.
It was actually kind of Hitchcock-inspired
in a couple of ways.
of all these different apartments.
But if you look away from the night watchman,
they basically go into a pause loop
and there are other little stories that you can uncover
just by looking at them without needing any gaze
but just seeing which way your head is turned.
And some of those play out over several episodes
so that even in the couple of minutes that this story runs
If you go back and look at a woman, she's feeding some pigeons, and that's great.
You go away, you look at her again, there are so many pigeons that she gets scared and runs inside her house.
The third time you look at her, the pigeons have formed a little pyramid,
and the one on top is trying to open the doorknob, and she's inside peeping out in horror at this,
because they want to get all the breadcrumbs right away.
So that kind of thing of building in Easter eggs, I think, is really great.
And the fact that it's up to you, that there's interactivity and that you get to choose where to look.
But another thing that's come up is sort of a negative lesson.
People don't like to stand up and rotate for very long periods of time.
So I really think that we're going to be seeing a lot of 180 degree seated VR, where you sit down
and you can turn your head and see stuff happening all around you it seems,
but you don't need to be constantly looking behind you.
It really is distracting, it's exhausting to try and do it too much.
And that in turn will make it easier.
We won't have to render quite as much.
It will be much easier to shoot it when you don't have to worry about hiding the cameras
completely because of course with regular film you can do that because they're only
pointing one way.
Here's a way of compromising between that wide field of view of VR but not 360.
So I think we're going to see quite a bit of that.
It's easier to shoot it.
It's easier to light it that way.
The interactivity can come through the gaze.
You can tell which way people are looking, at least at first with the way their heads
are pointed, and soon with their actual eyes, with eye tracking.
This could be a shared reality where we're all seeing the same thing, or it could be
essentially single player.
You know, your own particular preferences are either for Kate Winslet or for Leonardo DiCaprio.
You could see it only from the point of view that you want to see and not have to, as we do now in movies, see both points of view of that.
Or you could have something that's meant to be essentially a single-player experience,
that everyone gets a different experience each time that they view it.
But in general, there's going to be strong replay value, so you can shoot these things once.
and have people come back and watch them over and over again to catch all the bits they missed.
With that Simpsons episode, there's one point where I look up and I realize that they've done a little gag on the Sistine Chapel
and painted on the roof above me is a little Easter egg.
It's also the monetization side that if you imagine these kinds of VR movies happening,
you can do ads or product placement in real time so that in the world around you,
there can be actual real time ads that are changed every time somebody sees it.
Okay. Games as Medicine, this is an area that I've been working a lot in. I know not a lot
of people are in it at the moment. I'm going to talk about some stuff that is not VR for
a moment. Just in the last week there have been a couple of announcements. Paratherapeutics
got FDA approval for an app that will help treat substance addiction. It's used in conjunction
with therapy.
There's another company called Akili that I'll mention in a moment, but what's exciting
about them is that they're in the process of trying to get FDA approval for the first
time of actually being able to prescribe the game on the same level as pharmaceuticals,
which opens up a $300 billion annual market where you can actually have a doctor say,
yes, you need to play this game, and here's a prescription for it.
Really exciting area.
They're hoping to get approval.
It's in double-blind testing, so they won't know until later this year.
Play to Prevent was a project I worked on very briefly with some people at Yale.
It's a game, a 2D game, and you see it pictured here.
Jesse Schell's Schell Games Studio did the work on that.
It's this great game to teach kids, teenagers, about risky behavior
and has actually now been found in their own study to actually lower the amount of risky behavior
by teaching them through the gameplay that it's not such a great idea to get drunk
and go out and have sexual encounters, for example.
NeuroRacer was another project I got involved with that was started about 10 years ago here
at UCSF that was to treat aging adults who are less able to pay attention to signs as
they're driving as they get older.
And they found that through game therapy they were able to bring them back to the level
of about a 30-year-old, even if they were 70 when they start this process, in terms
of being able to perceive signs and still control a car.
and process this and that became the basis of this Evo game that is the one that I mentioned
that's currently being reviewed by the FDA.
I really think we're going to be seeing a lot more of this if they get the approval
and it opens up this part of this $300 billion a year market.
There will obviously be a pretty quick gold rush to this.
It's tough though because in order to get approval
You need to make a game, high quality game, as you can see the graphics in this are great.
There's a lot of ex-LucasArts people who were behind this to begin with.
So they drew heavily on the game side, but they also drew just as heavily on neuroscientists and doctors
to make sure that the medicine worked.
And what you're going to see though is that you're going to need to put a team together,
make a game, and then freeze it and test it for sometimes a year or two years, and then
be able to release it.
So all those people you hired have to stick around for those couple of years before you
even know whether you're going to get the approval to release it.
It's not an easy path, but it can be a really lucrative one, and it can be one where games
are actually helping people in a really direct, obvious, scientifically provable way.
So I'm very excited about that.
A lot of possibilities with that in VR.
Some of them have already started to happen.
We've seen phobia treatment in VR since some of the very early headsets.
Woman on top there is an arachnophobe and seeing VR spiders was just as scary to her
as seeing real spiders, but much safer.
Fear of flying, for example, also.
They used to take people into airplanes and then get them off, but after 9-11 it became
much harder to bring people into an airport and get on an airplane and get off.
You can do that with virtual planes, and if somebody gets nervous or has a panic attack
in the midst of a takeoff, bang, they shut the simulation down.
You don't have to worry about the fact that you're actually in a plane and you can't stop.
Post-traumatic stress disorder has been treated successfully with VR.
Acute pain remediation, as you're seeing in the bottom slide there, turns out that VR's
sense of immersion can take people out of their bodies and take them away from that
feeling of pain that they're in the midst of.
It's great for training doctors and caregivers.
There's a company in Chicago.
That's teaching people to care for people with macular degeneration where you get this
sort of black, I talked about the fovea, their foveas are obscured by this essentially gray
cloud as it breaks down.
In the training, you actually have to go through having a dinner.
with some people, and wherever you look, there's this big gray cloud.
So you get to experience very much like what the patients that you're going to be dealing
with have to deal with every day, and you suddenly understand how much harder it is
to be able to just get stuff out of the corner of your eye.
Mirror therapy after a stroke is being done, where if someone's right side is functional
and the left side is not.
If in VR, they see their left side functioning, it turns out that it grows some neural connections
and can regrow some of the connections that are broken by the stroke.
Asperger's, if you look at eye tracking, people who are on the autism spectrum often have
trouble knowing where to look, what cues to get to what emotion somebody may be experiencing.
Now you can tell whether they're looking at somebody's face or not, or even whether they're
looking at the right part of somebody's face, and there's some interesting training going
on there.
There's even room, there's now more speculation, but I've seen some early suggestions that
VR may both diagnose and possibly even treat some aspects of depression, Parkinson's, Alzheimer's.
So really exciting stuff.
But really the future is in your hands.
A lot of that stuff, that last stuff,
is very heavily on the speculative side.
And yet it is inferred because of some very promising
early research that I've seen.
So I'm urging you to get out there, try these things.
Whether you are looking for neuroscience
to inform your games and make your entertainment better,
or use your entertainment to make neuroscience
more effective in treating people and helping people.
Both of those are really exciting areas, and I'm going to leave it at that.
I've got time for just maybe one or two questions, so if people will line up at the microphones,
and also don't forget when you get your responses, your request for responses, to do a rating
of the talk, and I'll leave it at that.
Thank you very much.
Yes, I have a neuroscience question for you, which has always puzzled me.
You know the expression, looks can kill.
So we know that we can give out a certain kind of energy from our eyes.
I mean, without changing any other part of our face, I can look at you in a way that
is devastating, and I can look at you in a place that is loving.
Do we know what's actually happening physically inside the eye when those changes are happening?
I am not a neuroscientist, so this is a very layman's understanding of this.
The one thing about that that I can say is that it is...
easy for us to think that we're getting it just from someone's eyes, but there are a
lot of interesting studies that suggest we may be reading body language and a lot of
other things subconsciously.
So I would question that assumption.
There was a famous, again it comes to the film side, a famous thing where a, I believe
it was a Russian filmmaker, cut between people's close up staring.
Eisenstein, Serge, yeah, Eisenstein.
And that was a case where.
depending on how you were primed,
you read a totally different expression
into that exact same image.
My guess would be that it may actually
be more complex than...
We focus on people's eyes for many reasons,
in particular because it's really
critical to know what that other person
is looking at on you.
I'm guessing, and this is again
a layman's sense,
that it's probably, if I'm looking at you
like this, or I'm looking at you like that,
then my body language may be telling you a lot more than my eyes actually are.
And yet, I don't know, it may be micro muscles around the eyes,
it may be the way that your pupils grow or your pupils get bigger the more attentive you are.
So if I'm looking at you casually, it may actually not be,
my pupils are very small. If my pupils get bigger.
you can pick up on the fact that I'm interested in what's going on.
It's actually a reason why romantic settings are often dim,
because your pupils get bigger when it's darker,
and it makes you feel like you're more,
you actually have more attention of the other person.
So that's about the extent to which I know.
I was just thinking in terms of replicating or evoking an emotion in VR,
that that could be an important thing to know about.
It's an interesting thing to explore,
and that's partly why I think eye tracking is going to be so critical.
But we'll have to experiment.
And one more question, I think I'll go out in the hall if people have more stuff to follow up on.
Yeah, I had a question. So I run an immersive audio company and last year we had a, we worked on a horror VR game and our audio programmer actually had PTSD from having to work inside of, he couldn't, he had to eventually, he said no, no more changes.
It is how it is.
And so we run a, we're out of Tempe, Arizona,
and we run a VR for Good organization now.
And so I'm just wondering, what is the, yeah, it's a.
Trying to make up for what you've done.
Exactly, yes, yes, we're in repentance right now.
But I just wanted to know, what is the discussion
that's happening, like we're talking about this right now,
but what about developers?
I know just reading The Brain by David Eagleman.
He talks about how our brain really functions almost as like a peripheral device
that can take outside information and start to interpret it.
What is, my big question is, what is happening, what is going to happen
once we start taking this incredibly immersive tool,
hooking it up to our brain, and feeding it content that,
that in the beginning it's, it's...
We kind of have this friendly, innocent approach to like,
let's try to scare somebody, but what kind of effect
is that going to have on people?
And are we having this discussion amongst developers?
Yeah, so the good news is I have heard that discussion going
on in a number of areas.
A bit scary part is the fact that it is a little bit of Wild West out there, and there's
nothing to stop people from trying things that may be too scary or too jarring for the
public.
But, of course, that's always been the case with books, movies, a lot of other areas.
I'm not forgiving it, but I also don't think it should be banned or regulated, because
I think we need to let people be able to experience that and make their own decisions.
I often use an example of pastry chefs.
in that if you do nothing but eat exquisite desserts,
it's really terrible for your health,
but the solution is not to ban desserts.
It's to use it in moderation and to use common sense
and to be responsible both as creators and as consumers.
And that's unfortunately the best I can say about it at the moment.
But part of what I've actually been drawn to this partly because I do want to see what
positive things, what undeniably scientifically proven positive results we can get from this.
Because that does help counterbalance the fact that like any tool, I have that, you
know, good servant, bad master thing.
You have to really be careful about how you use it.
And I think we need to be responsible.
I know I'm not the only one bringing this up.
I've heard at a number of other VR conferences people talking about responsible use of that
emotional connection in VR.
But beyond that, I think there's so much we're still experimenting with.
We will have to try our way through that, and I'm encouraged by the fact that there
are a lot of reputable scientists and universities that are exploring a lot of this stuff, and
the faster we can get that information, the better.
So is there a resource that, because I totally agree with you, is there a resource that we
can go to in order to learn more about things that we should be thinking about?
I don't know of any central resource.
I actually have people at another conference, somebody came up in questions and said,
maybe we should start a central repository.
And somebody else said, well, yes, but who do you,
how do you regulate what gets into it
and verify whether it's some crackpot thing that,
you know, it's chemtrails that are, you know,
seeping into our VR systems.
And that's a tough problem.
And it's not really my area of expertise.
So I'm going to dodge that for now,
but I would happily support efforts along those lines.
And I hope that we will have some better ways
of being able to measure that in the near future.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
And I'm going to head outside now so they can clear the room and I think we've got lunch
coming up next.
But thank you very much.
Thank you.