Good morning everybody. Welcome to this panel which has very few of the original members on it.
I was asked to walk in and help out with this and I've been having a terrific time.
So we're going to talk about the care and feeding of wild fan sites here at GDC. I hope you're all prepared for this.
All right, so introductions.
My name is Linda Carlson.
I'll be moderating this panel,
and currently I'm the Director of Community Relations
at Trion Worlds.
Before that, I worked for many years
at Sony Online Entertainment,
and before that, I was a fan site operator.
And you guys can introduce yourselves
and tell us a little bit about
how you have been involved in fan sites.
Hi, I'm Kristen Oberton. I am currently a senior lecturer at DigiPen.
I also work outside the game industry right now, but my history is
I got into games through fan sites far too long ago,
then became a producer in the industry, so now I spent a lot of time
figuring out how to balance the value of building
as well as communicating with community. So it's been a fun journey to be on both sides of that.
And my name is Star Long. I've been making games for about 25 years.
My first game was a game called Ultima Online,
and which spun up some of the very first community fan sites like Stratix and other sites like that.
So, been sort of involved with this from the ground up of working with fan sites, trying to get them what they need,
being very open with them, etc.
And now I'm with a company called Portalarium working on a product called Shroud of the Avatar.
Hi, I'm Jennifer Page. I'm the... what is my title?
What is your title?
Today, I'm the Community Strategist Lead for Microsoft Studios Xbox.
I got started in community and gaming writing for Stratix for Ultima Online.
Aha!
Everything always goes back to UO, I have a theory.
Yeah, hey, me too.
Oh, hey! Reunion.
This happened on more panels than I could tell you.
So not only did I write, and then I also did Sonoma Quest News, which was my own fan site
for a while.
And I kept having opinions and running fan sites.
As you do, yes.
I'm a very subtle woman.
And after a while, a company finally hired me, because I think they wanted me to shut
up.
I don't know that it worked.
So, really grew up from the very basement of the beginning of online gaming and fansites themselves.
Right, so now we're going to talk about fansites and what defines them.
Of course, most of us, when we first started working on this, most fansites were websites, blogs, that sort of thing.
And they still exist, there's lots of them.
But there are so many different types of fansites now.
YouTube, Twitch, Twitter.
Twitter seems like an odd one, but I have a couple of fan sites who operate only in Twitter.
They're very visually oriented, they do a lot of memes and screenshots, that sort of
thing.
Facebook has groups and fan sites.
Wikis are a highly overlooked type of fan site because they're run by players.
Reddit, Discord, Guild Portals, and God only knows what we're going to be doing next year,
it'll be the next cool thing.
So the question for the panel here is, how has the gaming industry's approach to fan sites changed over the years?
I can remember times when it was somewhat adversarial. Who'd like to start with that?
How has it changed? So it's interesting because I think initially, I'm going back to UO again,
initially there were these fan sites that kind of tried to find leaks and tried to get inside scoops,
but also reported on...
Everything that was happening within the game itself, mainly quest and live fiction stuff,
as well as patch notes and all that, but that created community.
And it was a little, let's see what we can leak, let's see what we can get, but it changed
pretty quickly to being things like Stratix, where you could read and find out what was
happening in the game while you were sitting at work, and then it was more of a, let us
be your, you know, microphone for the content that the game is actually creating.
From there it's evolved into everything from QA testers from fan sites because they give
great insight on games themselves to being a core part of the team even in early development
which was not the case when it first started.
So when I was also at Stratix, by the way, and I started the first Neverwinter Nights
site for Stratix, and it was probably one of the first true partnerships with Bioware
when they came out with that game.
And we actually built tools because there were not a lot of data sources for information
about what was going on in the game.
So we were actually, had one of the first tools.
on one of the fan sites.
We didn't really think of ourselves as a fan site those days.
We didn't think of ourselves as a community site.
We were information about the game site.
We didn't really have the nicely framed community site or community fan sites we have now.
And it was really cool because we started off on our own,
and then all of a sudden, Bioware
found out what we were doing.
And they were like, you guys are doing some great stuff.
How can we help?
And it was one of the first partnerships.
And I absolutely loved working with them.
And years later, to actually work alongside them
on some projects and meet them in person.
So it was very cool.
It is when it all comes full circle.
Yeah, it does.
It's interesting.
It really pivoted quickly, I think,
to being a very, very cooperative relationship.
I mean, I.
Yeah, there are certainly sites that are more about the cheats and the exploits, but I mean,
they literally advertise themselves as that's what we do, like we're about hacks and cheats
and exploits.
But for the most part, it really is a cooperative exercise between the two.
But like you said, you know, it has evolved now where for us, I mean, most of our effort
now is directed at wikis and Twitch channels.
Those are the two, I would say, the two biggest areas of focus for us.
And to the point where, you know, another interesting evolution I've seen is that,
you know, a lot of the sites have been scraping data sort of on their own for the long term.
But one of the things that, you know, I see a lot of us doing now is...
intentionally exposing data and giving tools to the sites and the fan, especially the wikis,
and saying, oh, well, I see you're scraping all this data to get, like, all the crafting recipes
or get all the stats for the weapons. And most of that's right, but because of the way you're
doing it, some of it's coming out incorrect and whatever. So, you know, a lot of us are now
actually exposing that data.
directly to them and giving them tools so that they can expose that and present that on a site.
And often, you know, it's, it's, the community is better served in that way because a lot of times,
especially for like, for us, like we're a small project, we have a small team,
we don't have the bandwidth to put a website up that shows literally every single weapon,
and every single stat, and every single...
combination of like when I craft with this material, etc.
But the players, when we give them the tools to expose that data,
and they can assemble a wiki that shows every single crafting combination,
of which there are millions.
So it's really interesting to see that evolution of them manually
scraping that after the fact and us giving them tools to do that.
Absolutely. I think it took a lot of acceptance and
letting go of the fear of what fansites are going to do with this information
and realizing
That they're really doing free work that benefits everybody in the community and the company.
Jen, what is your company's approach to emerging media?
Like, how do you assess the new style of fan site?
Like, have you gone all... did you go all in on Instagram or Snapchat or anything like that when they came out?
We deny it.
No, I'm just kidding, we don't deny it.
We just act like the world doesn't change.
No, experiment, right?
You want to stay real solid in the areas that you know that will produce for you, the audiences will produce for you, whether it's streaming or, you know, wikis and all that.
And then in addition to that, we do put our toe in every water to see how is this.
You're doing a lot of research, engaging with the fans on those sites by showing up and
saying hey I like the work you're doing.
And seeing kind of what they're doing.
Giving them a little information.
Building relationships with those people.
Gone is the day where as community managers people didn't know your real name and they
couldn't find you.
You know?
You used to be like Batman, right?
Now they can find you.
They can email you.
They can ping you on Twitter.
So you might as well have a...
Yeah.
I mean...
Cooperative engagement with your fansites and your fans who are on the leading edge
of all that stuff.
Because I will never be as good as my game's fans.
And I will never be as knowledgeable because they live it.
I work it, which is a totally different perspective.
It is really interesting when they can actually embarrass you by your lack of knowledge in
the product that they know so well, but you're working on a game.
It helps to go out there saying, I know you guys know more than me.
So it's just out the door.
Alright, so we want to talk a little bit about why do we seek them, what are the benefits to it.
Clearly they are community leaders, they can be influencers, they can also be allies in talking to your players,
and they provide free media and content which benefits the players and the company.
So the question for the panel is, how have fansites affected your company and community,
and even more importantly these days of careful budgeting, can ROI be effectively tracked for fansite impact?
Oh, that's a tough one.
I know.
You can start then.
And that's one of the things as a producer,
OK, what's the return on the investment?
Because a lot of times working with community,
there's a lot of demands for what we could do,
but you've got to figure out what you should do.
Every time they make a request for an interview with one of your teams,
especially if it's during the day, that's taking away working on and building that game that they're waiting for,
or that next new update.
Every time you're working on some new art for some fan site,
You know, contest or event, same thing.
You're taking it away from your game.
So you have to pay attention to those tradeoffs.
As much as you want to, sometimes you have to say no.
Because you know the return on the investment is not going to
be the best thing for your game.
And it's one of those mixed blessings, I think, because
you think about.
Oh, at least for me, having been on the other side of that line, right, making those requests.
I was the one who was, you know, writing to BioWare saying, hey, can we get some cool
art for this next site?
Because we're trying to build our community and that was one of the draws we used to use
back then was art signed by the artist because you didn't have as many of the early access
things you do now.
And so on the other side of it, when I'm working on the game, I'm sitting there going, God,
I really want to help you because I remember being in your position.
But now I have a different role.
So balancing that is hard.
Anyone else have any ideas of how ROI can be tracked?
Can you use analytics to see what kind of hits the sites get?
So when deciding who you want to work with,
I think you have to, that's part of the game, right?
I mean, part of it is you don't ignore the smaller,
up and coming, passionate, intelligent fan sites.
You want to feed those, that garden.
But you also have to identify who do you invest in?
Who has messaging that's, you know,
in line with where you're trying to go
and who has a really solid following?
Looking at stuff like impressions, if you're talking about social, how many impressions do these people get?
Does this fan site get?
Looking at the kind of traffic they're getting to their site.
And the kind of engagement, and that's huge for me.
And this is where I've yet to find a tool that does it really well.
It's better just go through and read.
What is the sentiment of the site?
What kind of feedback are they getting?
For us, one of the biggest things we get...
is the conversation in there.
They will tell us, by the way, we're
hearing a lot of this on our site.
There's a lot of concern around this.
And they'll let us know that.
And since we're not in there every day,
it's extremely helpful if it's actionable feedback.
And training your community fan sites how to do that
is a big part of it.
I think the other part is also, do they fill a unique niche?
When you look across your whole bandwidth of fan sites and community sites, are they
doing something nobody else is doing?
Are they covering a part of your game in a way that nobody else is?
So look for those ones that kind of fill in the holes in their puzzle, because that's
where the extra value is and the full coverage of your title and your game will come in.
Star, do you have any feedback on the way that some fan sites, maybe even specific ones,
have affected your company and your gaming community?
Yeah, I mean I would riff on the look at the opportunities, specifically for things that
either you're not able to deliver on your own, you know, like if it's exposing bits
of data that you can't, you know, you don't have the bandwidth to show, if it's highlighting
things that the community is doing, so if you have a product where the community does
lots of things in the game, whether it's
Streaming matches or whether they set up events inside the game, if the players are highlighting that.
If you know, look for the things that you're not, you just don't have the bandwidth to cover. And if they're doing a good job of that, you know, highlighting them recognizing them. That's where you spend your bandwidth to support them.
So, I think it's less about tracking the actual monetary value and more about where they are
fulfilling a need for the community and a gap that you may not be able to fill yourself.
And then also, you know, there are, but there are metrics, like you were saying, you know,
I mean like Twitch, Twitch is a super easy one, you know, like look how many followers
they have, like look, you know, go watch one of their streams and go see how many views
they're getting during the stream.
You know, like if it's somebody that is on Twitter, look how many followers they have.
All those things are easy metrics for you to gauge about how much bandwidth you should spend.
And then to your point about going and looking at the conversations that are happening,
it's really important to look at the tone.
You know, so the tone of a community site is critically important for...
your product.
That's not to say you only want to embrace the fan sites that are
quote, drinking the Kool-Aid.
That are the white knights.
Right. Because then you're going to get the reputation, well, you only
support the guys that are 100 percent on your side.
So it's okay to support sites that are giving you critical feedback.
But you.
You also don't want to go support a site that is all just trolly, negative,
because that contributes nothing to your community, right?
And so that's where you want to be careful about,
or that they're doing even worse,
like they're doing racist or misogynist things, or whatever.
You know, like, so you have to be, that's also where you have to be super careful, you know, about what sites are supporting.
You have to look at what kind of community are they attracting, you know, because especially now in this climate,
that's something to be super careful of because if they are attracting the wrong kind of community,
that can be, that can have sort of wide-reaching damaging effects to your larger community.
Right. We're now going to move on to reaching out. Of course, the gold standard, what we
all started with, is the easiest, the passive fan site kit. And there is no excuse for any
company not to have one of these. Make it easy to find, have it on your website, and
that'll contain things, the simple things, logos, artwork, screenshots, video, audio
clips. A lot of fan sites like to use bits of audio in their...
So, I'm going to ask you to tell us about your own ideal approach to fan site outreach.
How do you contact them?
So for us, they often contact us before we have a chance to even contact them, right?
Because again, we're accessible. You can find us. You can reach out.
And actually right now we're working with a fan site called Phantom Dusted
because we're bringing back Phantom Dust in terms of compatibility and all that.
Look it up. It's an awesome game.
But we knew, this was one of those niche games that had a hardcore following
that was just rabid.
That this game is not new. It's been out for a long time.
And yet this community exists and is just passionate.
And we knew we would never do this game justice like they do.
I mean, they have the wikis.
They have the deck builders.
There's no way we could touch it.
So while they've been in contact with us, just as soon
as they heard the announcement, they started reaching out to
us, we actually now have weekly calls with them about
how can we support you?
How can we get your content in front of our audience?
So we do weekly calls with that particular fan site.
Other fan sites might be.
A forum, newsletters, things like that.
But it's a relationship and it's a trusting relationship on both sides and that's important
to honor if you want it to be effective.
Do you assign, do any of you assign a person to work specifically with fan sites within
your company, to be the liaison for it?
For us it's the community manager, whoever's the community manager on that product.
Okay.
Yeah, we, it's usually the community manager, but sometimes, like for us, again, we're a
small team, and so it's the community manager, but sometimes it's also myself.
Right.
And so, especially if it's a large site, or in our case, like another example would be
for us the syndicate.
So they're the longest running, largest guild ever.
So they started in Ultima Online,
and then they moved to World of Warcraft,
and they've been basically in every MMO since.
And they're like 800 members,
and they've been continuously running.
And so I go to their annual convention.
I have regular emails and phone calls
with their guild leader.
So the same kind of thing.
And build a relationship with them because
And again, building that relationship and maintaining that relationship with a group like that is important because I basically, through their guild leader, got a big chunk of that guild to just migrate from one product over to us.
And through working with them and maintaining that human contact, and for us, that's a really important thing, is like, go to their conventions, or go to conventions where you know they're going to be present and make that human contact.
And we've even, because, so I work with Richard Garriott, and he very much believes in extending
the virtual to physical.
And so we've even formalized community recognition, and so we have rewards we give out.
And so one is that we stole from England.
So we have the, so they're in England.
You get the OBE, which is the Order of the Britannian Empire.
So in our game, the land is called New Britannia, so we have the ONBE,
which is a virtual medal and a title that you get in the game for your character,
but there's literally a physical medal you get as well that we have like a ceremony where we pin it on you.
So like if we see you at a convention or you come to our offices,
we actually give you the medal that you can wear when you go places.
And that's for individuals who do outstanding contributions to the community.
Either through running a website or a fan site or running events in the game.
And then we have...
what's called a royal warrant. Again, we stole it from England.
And in England, the royal warrant is where like the queen will say,
you know, you have a royal warrant to make cars or like, you know,
handbags. And so like, and when you get that royal warrant,
you're recognized as the best person to make handbags in the land.
And so we give royal warrants for groups.
It's basically the equivalent of the ONBE, but for a guild or a group.
And so, like, the first one we gave out to was this group,
the Bards of the Poet's Circle, who crowdsourced all the music for our game.
And the reason we gave it to them was they...
We had crowdsourced...
We had basically downloaded a bunch of free music from the Internet,
and it was terrible.
And they approached us and said, oh, your music's terrible, can we please fix it?
Please make, can we make it better?
Because we're a guild of musicians, and we're all sort of professional musicians,
and we'd like to make music for the game.
And so we worked out this agreement, and we paid them licensing fees for it and everything.
But they run this whole thing where they peer review it, and so we set up this whole thing
of like, if you want to do crowdsourced music for the game, go through this guild.
And so we gave them a royal warrant, and again, it's like this plaque that you can hang on
your house in the game.
Everyone that's in the guild gets that title, but there's also a physical wooden engraved
plaque that the guild leader gets that they can hang on their house in the game.
So again, we formalized this community recognition in a digital and a physical fashion.
So we've sort of taken it to this kind of next level that has proven to be incredibly
powerful and sort of tied them even closer to us than we've ever seen.
I want to talk a little bit about talking to fansites themselves.
We've already established that communication is extremely important, and I'm just going
to list some of the ways that we communicate.
You already talked about going to conventions and meetups.
Email is an obvious one.
It's very easy to track.
IM programs at Trion.
We have Skype channels for...
We have groups of fansites, we have people who we call the dimensioneers, and they're
heavily involved in building stuff in the games.
So Skype, Slack, AIM, I know people who are still using IRC, forums and PMs on forums,
sometimes we'll hand out the office phone to the community manager.
We try not to do it to the producers because they're just too busy.
I hand out my personal cell phone to every fansite that I come in contact with because
it's so much easier for me to answer a text from them than to go through the whole email
process.
Studio visits are also a big one, especially if your studio can afford to bring your best
fansites in.
What types of communications work best for you when working with fansites?
Describe a few of the challenges that you've had in communications.
I'm going to look at a couple depending on the product.
So for a while I was working outside of gaming for a very short while.
It's a weird world.
Then you got sucked right back in.
I just realized you have to be far more appropriate when you don't work in gaming.
That's not acceptable.
Not for me.
But I worked on a community support site that was run by the community and it had 35 million
unique visitors every month and it was run by volunteers.
That kind of...
So, the idea behind this constant change and high-level stuff is we would have a Slack call,
not Slack call, Skype call every week with a PowerPoint deck.
Can you tell I work at Microsoft?
And we would go through, like, here's the updates coming to the site this week, here's
some, whatever, and then we'd have this whole dialogue with the leaders of the volunteers.
And we'd do that every week.
If I tried to do that to my team for some of my other products, they would kill me,
because changes don't happen that quickly.
And I overwork them.
So.
It depends on the product itself, but I have found that day in, day out, quick one-offs,
emails, texts, I need to be available.
Or rather, my team needs to be available.
Yeah, make sure you phrase that carefully.
I don't actually do anything.
But when it comes down to it, all of that is great, but you still have to have, in my
opinion, that person-to-person...
contact and I have some folks that are my canaries that will call me and say,
um, have you checked Twitter? You know, those people who 12 o'clock
in the middle of the night, I get a call and say, no, trust me,
you want to log in that kind of stuff.
I need to have that kind of communication with my trusted community members
because you know, they're all over the world.
So it doesn't matter what time of day I've got people out there watching and
letting me know when to freak out.
That is actually a very good point.
I used to, when I first started working in community professionally,
I was kind of loath to give out my personal contact information
because I didn't want these people bugging me, like bugging me for stuff.
In retrospect, that was really stupid because when I finally started doing it,
they were not bugging me, they were helping me at every single turn
by alerting me to problems that were going on in the community
or letting me know when somebody's running a really awesome contest and that sort of thing.
So I had to let go of the fear of allowing that communication to operate on a very personal
level.
But, could you see it also getting out of control where it's taking over the working
day and the life of your community managers or whoever you've got assigned to it?
Well, you can't always be in reaction mode,
and that's part of the problem.
So having those extra eyes out there
really helps you to focus on when
you do need to get involved.
The volume of negative is you want to drop it.
Drop what you're doing, change your priorities,
focus on the right thing for the community and the game.
But if things are going well, maybe all you do
is monitor it and make sure that it's
heading in the right direction.
So a couple of things that we've done in the past
to help with communication, I come out
of a couple of small projects.
And usually as one of the first producers on the project, I'm the de facto community
manager.
So those first touches are often fall to me until we say, hey, we have enough volume to
hire somebody to do it full-time.
So I have to kind of squeeze it in between all the other things like shipping a game.
And so we have done a couple of things like even setting up very specific aliases within
our company that they know of, they can send to.
So if they see something happening.
There are certain people in the company that are automatically part of that alias, so we
all automatically get it.
So one of us can respond.
And we kind of had a mini on-call for community because we didn't have a dedicated person
whose job was to do that.
So when you're in a smaller studio on a smaller project, you have to be a little more creative
for monitoring that volume.
And you don't want to be that person who wakes up at 7 o'clock to a thousand email messages,
what the hell happened overnight, because you bothered to go to sleep.
So anything you can do to kind of raise your awareness without trying to build out a team that,
to what we said, can keep track of it around the clock worldwide, you just can't do it.
There is no sleep in the game industry.
Star, what are your favorite communication channels beyond going to the conventions and meeting people face-to-face?
Um, you know, so we have our own, we have forums, um, and you know, we make sure that
we set up notifications.
So if someone tags us in the forums or sends us a PM, that we'll get a notification that
that happened.
And, and, uh, we make sure that people know that if they tag us or send us a PM that we'll
respond within a certain amount of time.
Um, you know, like Richard on Twitter.
He literally will respond to every single tweet.
If you tweet a little secret...
I'm totally going to test that right now.
No, he will respond.
So if you tweet Richard Garriott on Twitter...
No, seriously, he will respond.
Like, he responds to every single tweet.
Just like on our forums, I respond to every tag and every PM.
And so we use, we sometimes give out email,
but most of the time we try to channel that communication in the forums.
But we also are always on, you know, so we're also on Steam.
So we're on those Steam forums.
We also do Google Hangouts with our community.
Do you?
And we do a monthly live stream with our community.
And then quarterly, like, 12-hour Hangouts with the community.
And so I think those are...
Wait, wait, wait. 12-hour Hangout?
How does that work?
Are you there for the whole 12 hours?
There's a lot of drinking involved.
Okay, sign me up.
Yeah, we've done some AMAs, you know, they focus on different disciplines.
We'll get all the artists together and do an AMA for anything on the art side.
Just lots of creative things to to kind of engage them in different ways.
Yeah, those hangouts are basically AMAs.
So we collect a bunch of questions ahead of time
and then we answer those questions on air.
But we're also we use Discord.
Right, Discord's terrific.
And we're also collecting questions live while we're hanging out
and answering those, too. So.
So one thing I did on the live stream when we were working on Gigantic was the community
was like they were live streaming from a show and I wasn't at the show, so I was home.
And so what I did was I took all the questions that I knew they didn't have time to answer.
So I would hop in if they were asking some information or if somebody said something
incorrectly.
So I was like, I know what's going on with the game.
So I just said, I will just lurk and make sure that the
data that's being portrayed either by the community, if
they're getting it wrong, I'll fix it.
If it's correct, I'll reinforce it.
So that as you go back and look through the text chat
afterwards, you actually are getting new information about
what's going on with the game.
And it was one of those things that I did kind of
accidentally one time.
And then after that, community team was like,
when you're not at the show, can you make sure you do this worse?
Because there was just so much less that they had to worry about, right?
But they also knew, since I was working on the game all the time,
I probably had the most relative information and
most accurate for where we were in the production cycle for the game.
Let's talk now about setting expectations.
As you know, that's fairly important.
A fansite, they're building, they've contacted you or you found them,
they're very excited that you're paying attention to them.
I do think that it's important to set expectations as early as possible.
Now, especially if you're dealing with some major huge fan sites, regardless of what platform
they're on, and a couple of really small ones that are not really doing that well, sometimes
those ones will expect just as much attention as the huge ones, and how we deal with that
is important.
How do we show support for our fansites in general?
We promote their stuff, we retweet them, we share on Facebook, we comment in response
to their posts and what they're doing.
Very often companies will offer free access to games or items and content that are in
the games so that the fansites have...
Unlimited access to everything that they want to comment and talk about.
Star had already put in here and I should have put it in here too.
Data feeds are extremely important to some fan sites.
Direct access to the community manager for questions.
Access to devs for information, even if it's indirect and must be requested through the community manager.
We often provide support for contests and events that the fansites are running.
When we were developing Atlas Reactor, people kept asking about tournaments,
and we said, well, we're not really sure if it's a tournament-style game.
Here we are in Alpha, and the players are organizing tournaments through fansites,
and that was a great eye-opener. You've got to support that sort of thing.
We offer people giveaways. Maybe the fansites are doing giveaways to their own fans.
And also people are increasingly developing affiliate and profit-sharing programs with
fan sites.
So, panelists, do you have a formal outline for fan support that you give them?
Like, here's what we'll do for you and here's our expectations?
And what do you do if they request things a lot more than you are able to provide them?
What if they start getting really demanding?
So this goes back to what you were saying about...
Can it go negative, having too much contact with your fansites, or having them have contact
with us?
Or how do you motivate your fansites to be a power for good and not evil?
It all goes back to how much value are you giving those fansites?
Are you just expecting them to blow a horn and celebrate you, or are you providing them
with quality?
content or access and all that. If you set that up in the very beginning as part of that conversation of here's what we're going to provide you
based on the fact that you have been identified as a top
fan site. And I'm real clear with people about what we can and cannot do. This will also evolve because just when you're like and this is what we're going to give you
oh wait now there's streaming. Okay now we're going to give you this too. Oh wait now there's
whatever's next. It will constantly evolve and change. But I'm very clear at the beginning to say here's how we're going to make you successful.
They're doing us a favor.
We want to make sure we honor that and provide value.
At the same time, there's real clear expectations out the go of, listen, if, you know, we were
talking about this just the other night.
If you retire and suddenly have a life and don't want to run your site anymore, we totally
get that.
That's not a further slide.
You're skipping ahead.
Cheating.
But, you know, that's totally fine.
They understand that it's a partnership based on mutual.
And that at some point we have to back off a little just because you're not as active.
They know that in the very beginning.
So it's not personal.
And as long as you're honest and just open and transparent, people, they get it, right?
I mean, people aren't, occasionally you got people who want everything for nothing.
But that's going to happen no matter what.
I just, open communication and having it posted very clearly, and I actually like to post
them publicly.
Our fansite kind of policies of this is how you become a fansite, this is some of our
expectations.
Do you do that on your forums or on your website?
I would do it on the site.
On the site.
Don't go look at my sites right now because they're not there right now because we're
still developing it.
But, no, I think it should be very transparent because I don't want people to ever wonder
how come you chose this site and not that site.
It's just, quite honestly, most people get it, right?
We're not new to the internet, but it's just always better to be as transparent as possible.
Remember, most of us get involved in fan sites because we have a passion around that game, that title, that studio.
And passion is personal.
As much as you try and draw that line, as much as you try and keep that...
kind of relationship where it needs to be on the business side, eventually it's going
to cross and you've got to be kind of really careful.
So I mean, I'm blessed to have gotten to be really good friends with a whole bunch of
folks I used to be, you know, on the other side of.
But there are days when I have to remind them, I'm like, I work for this studio.
This has to come first and so I need you to step back a little bit when we're in this
kind of relationship.
So just be careful because you do have to control that line sometimes because there
are just some amazing people out there that you want to get to know.
better, but they also have to respect what you do for the company and that there's some
lines that you're not supposed to cross for both the business and personally to kind of
keep things, you know, in the right place.
Yeah, I mean, it's like we were talking about earlier.
I mean, you just have to, it's kind of back to that ROI thing.
You know, you just have to balance what kind of exposure and what kind of benefit are you
deriving from that site.
So I mean, if they're getting you a lot of exposure, if they're providing a lot of value
to the community.
Then whatever they're getting in response to that, whether it's Steam keys or store
credit or things that they can give away.
For us, an example is Twitch streamers.
Again, because that's a big focus for us and most companies now.
A big focus for most companies is giving Twitch streamers things they can give away during
their stream.
Right?
The amount you give those streamers is directly proportional to the number of viewers they have, right?
So, and again, just be super transparent about that.
It's like, if you have a big audience, I'm going to give you more store credit to give away.
Right? And just say that. And everyone gets that.
I mean, like, that's not a hard thing to communicate or sell, and everyone understands.
And that's perfectly fair.
Like, the nice thing about that is, like, it's a very fair metric, and it's a very objective metric.
There's nothing subjective about it.
You could just, so...
That's... And do you have a formal policy or outline posted as well?
That would be super awesome.
You'll get right on it when you get back to the office.
Just borrow Jen's.
At Tryon we have what we call the creator program.
And we actually formalized it because we had so many Twitch streamers that we just couldn't handle.
And it's a way that they can register so that we don't accidentally miss people.
But then we started finding out that fansites should also be signing up for this because they deserve the same stuff.
So we have wiki operators, reddit operators, fan sites, the Twitter guys, all of these people are now registered through the creator program.
So we try to keep it short and concise, and one of the things we threw in there because of our friends at YouTube is,
yes, you have permission to use our stuff freely and make money off it if you want to and can.
So I think it's very useful to have something formal up.
And you mentioned the affiliate and proprietary stuff, which is a really new ground that's
starting to happen.
Very new.
And we've actually got one example.
We have what we call a trusted trader program because we actively allow a secondary market
in our game.
So we let players trade virtual goods for real dollars on their own.
And so we have one.
person who's a trusted trainer who we let buy materials from our store and then sell
them in a secondary market.
He does it with Eve as well.
Wow.
Neat.
Because Eve also has a similar program.
And, but again, it's profit sharing, so, and he, you know, he can buy things from us
at a discount and then resell them because we have a trusted relationship with him.
He gets his exposure.
You know, he promotes the game on YouTube and Twitch.
But it's a new thing, not a lot of companies are doing it yet.
But it's a really interesting new model that's not starting to...
I don't know how many of you saw the announcement from Twitch on Monday
that they're doing an affiliate program now.
We're actually at Trion Worlds, we're lucky enough to be a partner in that.
Let me tell you, this is so new.
That we're not really sure how we're approaching it yet.
Our platform guys are working with our sales guys, working with the brand guys, working with the devs.
And everybody's trying to get this stuff cohesively together because
affiliate programs can be a real bear to manage.
So if we can get Twitch to do that for us, we're really happy.
We're already partnered with Steam, and of course Steam takes a cut of the profit as well.
But the same sort of thing, you're reaching people that you wouldn't ever reach otherwise.
I think affiliate programs are a really smart way to support fansites because they pour
their life's blood into these endeavors and it's nice if they can get even a little bit
back.
So before we move on real quick, one of the things that we ended up doing when we were
working on Gigantic was we partnered with some of those fan sites and got a fit, they
set up official tags for us so that when we posted they knew that we were officially part
of the game and part of the company.
And they did all this really fun stuff, but it meant that when we had the time to go in and comment on a thread or get involved in that conversation,
which we couldn't commit to doing all the time, they still knew we were there.
That's great.
And it just, you know, they were like, oh, wow, we didn't even know you guys were here.
It's like, we're here, right?
We may not be able to post all the time because we do have day jobs, but, you know, when we do post, they know that we're engaged in the community and we're paying attention.
And that's a form of currency to fansites as well.
That's time investment from the company, and that is a form of payment and a thanks for
a job well done.
Most Reddit mods will also tag your team members if they verify their identity so that they
know that you're not just pretending to be somebody from the company, but that you're
an actual person.
And then you get horribly downvoted to the bottom, you know, page ten, but at least you're
tagged and people know that you're legit.
Let's talk about one of the more challenging things, because this does happen.
Biting the hand that feeds you.
Sometimes a good thing goes bad.
The passive one is, as we mentioned earlier, when people burn out and they move on.
Or maybe they get a job.
For instance, I ran a fan site for several years, thebrass.com,
but when I started working in the game industry,
I no longer had time to do comics and write-ups and that sort of thing.
So, the site might be abandoned or just left up on good terms, that sort of thing.
However, sometimes when people get frustrated with you, it can result in a lot of burning
bridges on their part and sometimes on the company's part, I'm sad to say.
The second danger is that if you give fansites a lot, a sense of entitlement can form, just
because they've got the special access.
Sometimes some people can develop a sense of self-importance.
Sometimes they will have an increased level of demand that they feel entitled to.
And if they're unhappy with you, they're going to vent to a very avid audience.
That schadenfreude runs very strong among the people who read fan sites.
So panel, have you encountered any of these issues and how did you resolve them?
And how do you terminate an unhealthy fan site relationship?
Well, all of the...
Like when you guys, when you partnered with 4chan, you know, how did that turn out?
Well, I'll leave the getting out of it to one of my fellow panelists, but I will tell
an interesting story from when I was actually on the other side and part of the community.
I was running the Neverwinter Stratix site for about three years.
I had an incredible relationship with Bioware.
It felt like a real partnership.
And I had to step away.
I was actually starting up Mythica Stratix because I was super excited about that game.
So I went to step out, but I was also building a bunch of stuff for the back end for Stratix,
and I just didn't have the bandwidth to do both.
And so what I ended up doing was I handed it off to somebody I felt was a really good lieutenant to hand it off to.
Well, little did I know, he felt super entitled.
He had not done any of the work to build a relationship with BioWare and the team,
but he felt like he should just be able to step into my shoes and just have all that trust.
And within three months, BioWare contacted me directly and said,
if you do not take back this site, we're going to sever our relationship with you,
because he was that bad.
And the relationship that we had was too important.
So we made him go away because he was actually damaging our
community and the relationship with the company.
And so I ended up stepping back in, and I stayed for another
year until somebody else actually stepped up.
But from the other side, it could have really destroyed
our site because we had that tool that they were giving us
data for, and it was a relationship that that stuff
came out of the trust.
And as soon as somebody started to damage that trust, we needed to fix it immediately.
So I haven't had that happen on the other side, so I'll leave that one to you guys.
Have fire a fan site?
Yes.
So you can't fire a fan site.
Correct.
They're just gonna be there.
So again, the key is to providing so much value that they want to play nice because you're in.
and you have a trusting relationship with them and you all have the same goals.
And if they start to go sideways, pulling that stuff back should be felt.
In other words, if the fansite, to your point, is getting value from the relationship with the company,
they're going to want to reinforce that, just the same way that we do.
The most you can do is actually pull back those resources and actually say,
acknowledge when people ask, unfortunately we severed our relationship with this fansite.
And part of that is protecting your brand, right?
When somebody goes toxic and negative on the internet,
which is so rare.
Never happens.
Making sure that people understand we don't condone this.
Even if obviously when it's blatant hate stuff,
but even when it's just non-constructive and bitchy, right?
You separate from it.
And saying that publicly I think is important.
You don't have to slander,
but being able to say we no longer support this site.
That's all you can do and not get pulled into the mud.
Unless you have secrets.
That's all you're going to say?
Wow, 25 years in the industry and you don't have a cool story, bro?
I mean, it's really that simple.
You just have to make a public statement and say we're no longer working.
I mean, you can't do anything else.
I mean, you can try and get them back on track.
Like you said, by either pressure or demands or, you know, throttling back on supply.
But at the end of the day, if it becomes, if that doesn't solve it, I mean, all you
can do is make a public statement.
I mean, there's no, there literally is nothing else you can do.
But don't wait too long to do that.
It becomes obvious that it's no longer a healthy relationship.
I am amazed that we're actually on time with this.
You guys are really good speakers. I'm going to have to sign you up again.
The best advice, this is the last formal slide, and there are two parts.
If there was one thing you could tell a community manager seeking to start a fansite program, it would be,
and the second is,
If there's one thing you'd like to tell execs reviewing your budget about the importance
of supporting fan sites, because that can be somewhat challenging as well.
Now, as I put at the bottom, I said, okay, you can offer more than one piece of advice.
If we were super concise and on track previously, chances are low I know you people.
So you surprised me.
So what's your best advice to both somebody who wants to start a fan site program and
something that you'd like to tell executives or offer to the community managers?
that they can take to their executives.
So I'll start with executives, because I work with executives.
Look on your face when you say that.
What's that?
Exactly.
No.
They're out there whether you want them to be or not.
They're out there and they're talking about our products.
And they're giving out information.
And they may be scraping data that's not accurate.
And it may be coming from a good place.
But they're out there one way or the other.
Why would we not take advantage of that reach and that passion and that megaphone for the messaging we're trying to get across?
Oh, and by the way, you don't have to pay them.
So, if you really want to get tricky about it, what you say is,
I can hire two people to go out and make sure we're hitting all these different community sites and getting this messaging out,
or I can hire one person and start a fan program.
It's cheaper, it's more effective, yada yada.
And the feedback loop is huge. For us, that is huge. We want to hear from the fans, and not just the fans from Reddit, not just from Twitch, and not just...
We cannot possibly be everywhere, but the fans are everywhere. So if we open up that communication loop, and we make sure that we're getting that information in,
it's hugely valuable. Especially as, for instance, we announce a game.
We do this big marketing splash with all these really pretty trailers and we think it hit great.
And the audience says, wow, that's awesome.
We love that you're doing giant pink elephants.
I'm like, there's no giant pink elephant.
Like, how did they get that message?
Sometimes what you put out there is not received the way that you think it is.
Having that relationship with all these different places means I can now go to my execs and go, hey, remember how we said that?
Well, now we have to shift our messaging because it's not landing.
Otherwise, you're going to have pissed off players when we sell this game.
That has proven to be extremely valuable for executives.
So they're working as a focus group as well.
That's another benefit.
A rather unfocused group, yes.
But yeah, no, it's a huge benefit.
And for, like I said, it's not expensive.
The returns on it, if you have, so if you are going to set up, I'll go to the first
question, if you are going to set up a program.
Have your ducks in a row.
Understand your reporting.
And reporting has to be consistent and constant.
There is no value if the community manager's
the only one with the information in their brain.
It has to be put in a concise bullet point template
that an exec over lunch or coffee can go, got it.
Because then they're getting value out of it.
And if you're not doing that on a consistent basis,
and taking the passion out of the communication
and making it actionable.
That's huge. But you want to have all that in place so that by the time you go out, within the first week of a program existing, people are seeing value.
Going to be setting up a program, I'm going to echo what you said,
that having a very digestible report for executive
to understand what's happening in the community.
So I'm going to single out Barik, or Matthew Anderson, our community guy out there.
He, you know, so he does a weekly report, it's called our Community Sentiment Report.
It divides the community into different areas, like here's our community on Steam,
here's our community on our forums, here's the community in other locations,
like, ooh, yay, Reddit.
And then sort of rates how they're doing
and then talks about what they're talking about,
but then also gives suggested actions based on that thing.
But it's all one page.
And that comes out right before our weekly managers meeting.
So as an agenda item, we have that list of both sentiment and actionable items from what is going on in the community and the fans.
So having that data in a very digestible and actionable format is critical for that.
for exec and leadership to see value.
And that has to, so if you're setting up that program,
make sure that that's the end result of it, right?
Is this digestible, actionable data coming out of it,
or else there's no point.
It's the actual pitch itself.
Yeah, that's what you're pitching.
So if you're gonna pitch, like, I want to set up this program,
that's your pitch.
It's like, this is the report you're gonna get.
Because if that's your pitch, like you show them that report,
they're going to be like, oh, awesome.
But then the other part of your pitch is, you know,
just a simple data point, which is the cost of user acquisition.
So, you know, the average revenue per user right now is
about a dollar, right?
Okay, so let everyone let that sink in for a second.
You're getting about a dollar per person right now.
The cost of user acquisition right now is about $5.
See that? How that works? So you're losing about four dollars a person.
Okay, so which means you need to scale.
And the only way you can scale, you're not gonna scale
through traditional, no longer can you scale
through traditional marketing techniques, right?
Unless you're like Supercell and you have $26 billion, right?
So if you're anybody else, you need other techniques
and the best way to do that is with community, right?
And so they are your user,
they are an amazing user acquisition tool.
And so that's your other pitch.
Right? Is community is a user acquisition tool and by fostering a community and helping a community,
that's the way we're going to do it.
And one last thing is, you know, if you're setting up a program, you know, always be transparent and honest.
That's key to any program. Like, be open and honest with your community.
And be clear about what works and what doesn't with your community.
Um...
and recognize the outstanding contributors.
So people who are, but don't do that
until they consistently display positive contribution.
Like if someone is doing something really awesome
for like a day, don't immediately jump out there
and go, look at that person who did one day
of really awesome things.
Wait till they like do months of really awesome things.
But once they consistently display something positive over months of time,
publicly recognize them.
Show the community, this is what we like.
This person right here or this group is the kind of community contribution, this is the
fan site we like, and celebrate that to the rest of the community.
Because then the rest of the community has an example to work from and they can say,
oh, those are the guys who are doing really awesome work and they got lots of goodies
because of it.
It is. But it works.
All right. Just a couple minutes left, I guess.
So from the executive point, it's, you know, I had to make this pitch
because I was starting to lose my ability to actually run the project as a producer.
So I was part of helping make that pitch to say we need somebody to do this.
We've got so many people paying attention to us and I can't deliver the quality
that we need to kind of keep that message on task.
But also to echo Star, we're both, the community managers both acquisition and
retention, right?
They're kind of keep the, that's where the care and feeding of that passion comes
in at the community side.
So they're going to help us acquire, but they're also going to retain.
And if they don't play, they don't pay.
So we need to keep them around once we have them.
And the community manager is one of those glue elements to the future of our game and making service data.
And as for the advice piece, is don't forget that as building community outside the studio,
you're also building the community inside the studio.
Because you are basing a lot of the things you're doing on the people who build that game.
And being aware that those kinds of things impact that group,
some of them won't want to do those streams.
But I had the blessing of working
with amazing community managers who were really
stressful time on our project.
And the fact that he supported me
allowed him, gave me the opportunity
to support him even more.
And it was an amazing partnership
between production and community in my studio,
and I felt really blessed.
Great.
And now.
Do we still have time for questions?
Yeah, we have.
OK.
So if anybody has any questions, please line up
at the microphone.
Thank you so much, panel, for taking part in this.
You guys are really brilliant.
Hi, thanks guys. I'm Nick Huggett from KickSci. We've made a big push into mobile gaming. One
of the big things that we've seen is that our players like to communicate through messaging
apps including Line. And one of the kind of roadblocks we've run into is that I was a
part of a bunch of different chats and a couple of them basically decided they didn't want
the company to be able to communicate with the player. So we've made a big push into
overseeing or seeing what they were talking about and basically
kicked me out. So not because of anything I did, they just didn't
like the feeling of big brother looking over top. So my
question is, if you're in a situation like that, you want to
be part of some of these talks that some of your players are
having, but not that they hate you, they just don't want you
looking over their shoulder. Do you respect that and and just
let them do it? Or do you infiltrate and try and, you
know, pretend to be one of the players? Like there's a couple
of different avenues. What's your advice?
You're asking if we want to advocate spying on your community?
You guys, you go ahead and take that.
Absolutely.
No.
Don't?
Don't spy.
I'm asking what you would do.
Yeah, well, I'm asking what you would do.
Yeah, the price you pay is greater than what you're going to pay.
They will find out you're spying, so don't do it.
So instead, just kind of approach them and say, can you guys give us just kind of an
overview report?
We don't need to see the details.
Just give us...
Tell us what you come up with.
Tell them what you're talking about, the things that matter to you guys.
We don't have to be there to get that information.
Well, there's a reason why they're having the conversation.
There's a reason why they're having those conversations.
And it may be that they want to be able to vent without you hearing.
And that's fine.
But that's not what you need anyway.
You need actual feedback that's actionable.
And so the people that are running those chats, to your point,
if they can give you some talking points, that's great.
Otherwise, you may need to start your own.
Or have another group that you can incentivize to start one on your behalf.
And incentivize is again very transparent.
It's a, hey, we would love to, we'll even give you some tokens to give out during your chat.
But the goal is we want feedback.
We want.
Amplification, whatever your goal is, just be really transparent.
But with things like that, it also becomes really gamey, which is, you know,
I mean, it becomes this weird, well, we said, well, we think.
It's like, that's not, no, we're doing everything above board.
If you're not comfortable and you just want to rant, go for it.
That's not something that's useful for me.
And I think the end goal here is you're trying to make sure that once you build the trust
with the community, you keep it, right?
So being transparent about not invading their space if they don't feel comfortable.
Because if they truly feel that they can trust you and you can trust them, you're going to
hear about that stuff faster than the tide of it getting out on the internet.
And that's what you want to build your relationship on, is that trust.
You're going to be transparent, like Jen said.
Be transparent.
Say, hey, we want to join you guys, but we'll respect you if you guys don't want us there.
Also, that's so weird.
It's not. There are a lot of sites out there where people, where honestly devs don't want to go.
But as, no I'm serious. There was EQ2 Flames for instance was a fansite forum that was started as a place for people to go rant and rave.
And we did not have our developers posting there, because remember that a developer's
presence is also a reward.
Do not underestimate the power of your developers.
If you start a weekly chat and invite everybody to it, do not underestimate the power of developers
to pull in people who are really interested in your game.
So just go start your own.
Yeah.
Next question.
Hi, my name is Liz. I work at Pocket Gems on a product called Episode.
We actually have a ton of fan sites, but one of the issues that we're running into is that
the fan site operators actually kind of hate each other.
Oh, yeah. That happens.
So, what advice or insights do you have on dealing with situations like that?
I'm going to repeat the question for the audio.
What do you do when your fansite operators hate each other?
So back in the day when I did have fan sites who hated mine, we actually had to learn to
build, I mean, the companies were not going to fix this for us.
We actually eventually arranged an agreement of respect.
It was like, if you're going to go steal our content, damn it, give us credit, right?
So it was kind of, we had to work out, because it was in the early days of this, right?
And so you know you got these unique screenshots or data from the
But the game company or whatever, the studio, and all of a sudden it appeared on somebody
else's site.
And they didn't credit you.
I was like, I don't care if you cross post, have a good time.
Just tell them where it came from so that we get acknowledged for that effort, right?
So a lot of it was just building respect between us.
And it had nothing to do with the company itself, right?
And it's like, come on, be grownups.
Let me ask in turn, are they coming to you to come solve their squabbles?
So my community is primarily teen girls.
Oh, wow.
So we're talking frenemies here.
Is that where we are?
OK.
So it's like really hard to deal with.
But are they coming to you?
In some cases, yes.
In some cases, it's, did you know that so-and-so is doing this?
You need to ban them.
That's great.
I've heard that a lot.
Yeah, yeah.
Believe me, it's not just teen girls that do that, by the way.
It's not just teen girls.
No, no, no.
I would actually, we take the high road, right?
And we illustrate adult behavior, at least in public.
So when people are coming to us with those kind of complaints, it's like, well, as long
as we're within the guidelines.
You start sounding like a...
Pamphlet or something but to some extent not adding to the drama and not even getting your toe in the water is so important
Yeah, because you just don't want to reinforce that behavior no matter who it is
And then it does get to the point where you just remind people there are in order to be
Acknowledged by us again, make sure you have a carrot make sure you have some kind of value
You have to be behaving within this code of conduct and the code of conduct is important
We haven't touched on that but a code of conduct is important
And outlining in the very beginning, we will not tolerate hate, we will not tolerate toxicity,
we will not, all that stuff is part of that.
And then just pointing to it saying as long as we're okay here, okay, thanks, bye.
And just not getting too involved.
You'll find that they will grow up over time or they'll go someplace else too.
And when I say grow up, a lot of times it's adults who start these fan sites and they
also have to adjust to that social environment.
Definitely not just teenage kids.
I think we have time for one more question.
Okay.
Hello, I'm Rafael from Blizzard Latin America.
Hello!
So, usually we get limited spots to bring people to workshops in the office or to conventions
like BlizzCon.
So, how do you guys value who should come?
Like a bigger fansite or a small one that you want to help grow?
And a follow-up question, how do you guys handle the jealousy between fansites?
Like, why did he get an invite and I didn't?
Star had a really good response to this earlier where you were evaluating fan sites.
You know, so again, being transparent about it, so communicating why you made the decision.
So if you make the decision that you want to bring a smaller fan site for the purpose of growing them and helping them,
just say that is why you did it, right?
And so, um...
Or if you made the decision that you only want to bring web fan sites that are of a
certain scale because they have a certain exposure, but just be clear that that was
the criteria.
Or if you did a mix, also say that.
Say we chose two web, two fan sites that were of this scale because they had this exposure
of this many views per whatever, that metric, and then we intentionally reserved two slots
for smaller up-and-coming sites.
And just be transparent about that.
And yes, you're going to get jealousy.
I mean, that's going to happen.
But if you are very transparent about why you chose those,
and
If you did it by, say, a lottery or something like that,
like the two smaller ones,
we chose the two biggest, and that's an objective metric.
And then for your two smaller ones, say,
we chose ten smaller ones,
and we randomly picked two out of those ten smaller ones.
And then, again, if you're transparent about it...
They're going to get jealous and they're going to have some
foment about it for a little while, but if you were
transparent about it, that won't last that long.
And I do agree, by the way, the combination is the best, right?
Yes.
If we only feed our big, giant fan sites, everybody else gives up.
And suddenly you are dependent on two sites, right?
You always want to have the up-and-comer that is building, has new perspective, fills a
niche maybe that isn't already filled.
But it also helps with the entitlement when it's not just two juggernauts or one juggernaut
fan site.
They become a little less cocky if they realize they're not the only show in town.
And the silver lining is you have several fan sites to be jealous of each other.
And that's a good problem to have.
Well I think that's it for us.
Thank you all so much.