Check? Can you guys hear me?
Alright, before we forget here, Tiny Panther...
...de-clawed.
Any more before we begin?
Is that a sick pet idea?
Hold on, we gotta amp it up a little bit.
Turtle with...
Yeah, double turtle?
Double turtle.
It's like a double Dracula,
like whenever a Dracula bites another Dracula.
Weird shit happens.
Anyway, so, guys,
thank you so much for being here,
and I'm Matt Pearsall,
I'm going to kind of show you guys
my process,
and I don't use it exclusively, but...
I'm working on a game right now for the last few years called Prey,
and 98% of all the sound effects were created more or less in this fashion.
As some more seasoned veterans in here will know that the world of editing-based sound design
can be really fatiguing and uninspiring after, say, I don't know, 5, 10 years of your career.
And what I found is I found my job at one point became a job.
And what I wanted to do, well,
backstory, my Pro Tools rig crashed.
And my computer crashed, and so I had,
and I wanted to travel, and I realized one day,
I'm like, I'm a contractor.
I don't have to go,
don't have to be tied down to my studio.
And so I grabbed this, and this, and this, and this,
And I went to Europe for a few months and just worked remotely.
And it was really a great way to sort of re-evaluate
what I find important about game audio.
And it made me fall in love with it again.
So the process that I'm going to describe today, who am I?
I'm going to talk about myself for probably 22 more minutes.
And then we can get into heavy stuff.
I'm just kidding.
You know what?
Like, I'm whatever.
I'm Matt.
I make video games.
you can ask me my credit list afterwards.
Backstory, computer crashed.
Really, really annoying Pro Tools update.
I'm sure many of you experienced that.
Yeah, many crashes.
Anyway, so let's just get started.
So I have prepared, I was gonna do something today.
I was thinking like something that would demonstrate
this process really well.
And there's really two phases to this.
There's a source creation phase.
and then there's what I would consider the compositional phase.
Today our focus is going to be on creating ice magic,
so that could just sort of riff on that concept.
And a lot of what I do is,
I tend to stay, like I tend to look at the visual once or twice,
try to look at it in game, but I don't actually vidcap it to begin.
I wait to do that and I just sort of...
riff on a general concept and then sort of piece those elements together in the game.
So we have some source here.
I want to start here.
This is a way that I would gather source material.
Right here we have some, this is just a synth, but this is the Aztec death whistle.
And a whale.
Because I was thinking like whales.
kind of, to me, like I just go like stream of consciousness.
So for some reason, the clicky whale thing spoke ice to me.
Plus, I think a few of them live in Antarctica
where there's still ice for the next couple of years.
Anyway.
Ah!
I wanna start there, something nice and gentle.
Say cheese.
Everyone say cheese.
I love to cheese.
Cheese.
A quesadilla?
Feel like a quesadilla?
Spread it on the court?
I'll do it on the court.
You wanna put it on the court too,
Just something that you could, you know,
when you're talking to your mom,
you could just sort of say,
hey mom, this is how I feel about this.
I'm an individual mom, you don't understand me.
That's dope, I don't care.
That's dope.
Okay, so from there, I put these into a drum rack
and you guys can see this here.
I'll lift up the screen a bit.
and we'll focus on this aspect of it.
Ah, fuck, I can't.
Anyway, um...
So, we've got this sample in the bank now,
and let's see what we can do with it.
So my process right now, this is what I would consider to be on the top layer here you can see
what I have is I would say that's my grounding source, that's actual ice. But I don't start
there and the reason I don't start there is I feel like it's best to explore the abstract
before you explore the reality. Reality is easy. When you're fatigued you can always base your
sound in reality. But when your brain is fresh, when your brain is creative, you can handle the
abstract in a much more efficient way.
So I'm going to set a loop point here.
Now I have basically a running loop,
and I'm just going to start fucking around.
So this is some of my source I created about 10 minutes ago.
All right, so.
Okay, so what I like about this process,
so we have this, and this is just a general concept.
Now from here, I'm gonna actually switch to
what I would consider a more traditional editing mode.
And let's just take a look at kind of what we have here.
So I've got this,
and we're gonna furl down to what I have built.
This is my template.
So I always have like a set SFX,
what I call SFX group.
And I like that because I can just open the session
and it's always ready to go with no questions.
So we're just gonna see kind of what we have here.
And like, you know, it's weird.
But you know, maybe we could do something interesting
with a few of these.
Great.
I don't think that's recording properly.
I'm going to take that over here.
and we're going to pull it back to our drum rack.
So now we can begin there.
So in a more clear fashion, I'm going to set one loop.
Okay, so we got this.
Okay, so I kind of like that.
So we start there, now we have this again.
We're gonna pull this back into our more arrangement view.
And we've got that going on, right?
Okay, so something that I really love doing,
and maybe you cats are hip to it.
I'm going to like just, I feel really naked and vulnerable right now
because I'm going to show you guys something that I use
and it's a little hacky.
Anyway, let's jump right in.
So, kick.
This is my favorite kick of all time.
This is a sound morph kick.
Those of you that are familiar.
Yeah, that's it.
Okay, so...
I take this, and so for now, I'm going to just slice this tiny bit and then leave the
rest. Okay? And I think spiritually and emotionally we can agree that's a decent idea. So we're
going to give it another step here. Right? Okay. Now remember the thing we recorded earlier.
So I'm thinking like I'm just riffing here, but I'm thinking about that, that screamy
thing, you know, the whole mom thing, and that was a journey that we went through together
and I fucking feel so close to you guys.
So I want to bring that back, I want to find that again somewhere in all of this madness.
That's it.
Okay, cool.
And what's beautiful about this is like these things can like
fairly seamlessly work together
when you're not mildly nervous.
Let's see. You know what guys?
I thought about it and I thought about, you know, like how far we've come
and I'm just going to re-record it.
It's that easy.
Cool. All right, let's drag this back into our concept here.
And...
Cool, we've got this.
We'll call this the Mom, You Don't Understand Me sound.
We're going to pop this here. Yeah.
Okay, I like that.
So I kinda wanna add a little bit more
sort of high frequency content.
So to do that, I'm going to pull up
an operator.
And what's great about operator is, again,
this is all kind of on the fly here.
We can go into operator and we're gonna select white noise.
That's what white noise sounds like in my heart.
OK.
Filter.
Let's do.
Cool.
All right, so we'll grab that.
Okay, cool. So once I have this, I'm just going to drag it as MIDI into the sound right now.
And that's obviously not working very well for timing, so we're just going to record it and make an audio file.
Cool. Okay.
There's a tool that I like to use a lot. It's called PsyQ.
Are you guys familiar with this? It's a Sound Toys plug-in.
And what it allows you to do is distort or use harmonic distortion only on certain frequencies.
So we're going to add harmonic distortion in the 900 range.
Cool. There's something else that's kind of exciting,
that's sort of off-topic, on-topic that I've been into.
And that is this, I built this, it's like a granulator.
I don't know if you guys know granulator, but you can take any sound source
and essentially loop it, it's a very simple granular tool.
Now, if you notice, see how the EQ is going wild right now?
What I've done is add a Max for Live plug-in on this called Randomize.
And it just takes your whatever plug-in you want
and just literally randomizes it.
like a crazy person.
Now when you first launch it,
the preset is sort of set to dude on speed.
But this is like dude kind of coming down from speed.
So let's see how this sounds.
And it's kind of a cool way to create
some interesting source material.
Let's get off that.
So yeah.
So just one button has a lot of movement.
But now when you add in the file positioning in Granulator, as well as this Diffuse EQ,
which is essentially like a dub style spring reverb.
So let's record a few of those and try those in the mix.
You know, it sounded really easy to do sound design in front of people.
Self-destruct.
Defeat.
Break.
Destroy.
Alright, I like that last one.
That has a nice flow to it.
I thought that
again
seeing as how we've been through so much
together, that one sort of is more representative
of us as a couple.
Oh, by the way,
side note,
pet peeve, people that overprove how happy they are in their relationship on Facebook.
They're like, I had a friend and it was, he's the funniest thing I've ever seen. Never mind,
maybe I should tell this story not here. It's really good though. Trust me, it does involve
nudity. And social media.
Ok, so for now we're going to leave that.
But the cool thing about this is that we can go
riff on this and absolutely make
hundreds of iterations. The reason that I like the drum rack
is because once I have this, so for example I'll title this
Ice Magic, I can save this rack
and instantly pull it up. So for things like
sounds that you make like
consistently
you can have basically like a little drum rack library
of quick, quickly accessible things.
And I think I have a few in here.
My laptop crashed recently,
so I might have lost some of them.
But within my user library,
I've got these patches here.
Can you guys still hear me?
Okay.
Presets.
Instruments.
Transcribe, okay.
Drum rack, click.
Okay, yeah, this is stuff I've made quite a long time ago.
Let's see.
This is called 30 Seconds Left.
I have no idea what this is.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, okay.
This is all stuff I live recorded actually.
Trying to... making some sort of stinger things.
So it's stuff like, you know, like really simple stuff but...
But what's cool is like, you know, I could just pull that up
and just have that instantly to mess with.
So I wanted to show you guys one other thing that I really enjoy doing.
So first we're going to create some source and then we're going to try a quick concepted creature sound.
So this could go like this is I want you guys to know this could go really wrong.
But we're going to give it a go. We're going to be better friends.
OK. All right. So let's begin.
Let's let's say we're doing some kind of I don't know some typical space Satan type shit.
So for now, that's not really space satan-y enough,
but we're going to bring the evil.
Okay, we've got this loop going.
There's a reason for this.
And the reason is, I'm sure you guys already got it,
but this is our core tone.
Now, let's take that core tone, we're going to mute it for right now,
and this is going to be the mic channel.
So, yeah, this is fucking terrifying.
Real.
Yeah.
Let's see.
All right.
This is going to be our mic channel now,
because the other ones are not working, gang.
Right?
I mean, that's pretty space satany.
All right.
So you take this, and we definitely don't do that.
We're gonna pop it here.
Okay, so we're gonna pull up our old friend, the vocoder,
and we're going to use the space Satan's tone
as our carrier tone, or one or the other, I don't know.
I'm not a fucking scientist, dudes.
I'm a.
I'm a barely functioning adult.
Anyway.
So, audio from, and that's SFX 1.
So let's just see, it's not going to sound great just yet, but we'll just see.
Cool.
That's not as bad as I thought it would be.
It's a little on the digital tip tip, but it's, you know, I don't hate it.
That's another thing that can help you as a sound designer,
is just kind of, in general, just like your stuff.
You know?
You know, like, I mean, like it pays to be a little cocky,
quite honestly, like, I'm just gonna say,
pro tip, this goes beyond sound design.
If you don't like what you're doing, go fuck yourself.
Seriously, why are you doing it?
Anyway, but I mean that in like a loving,
it's like a loving go fuck yourself,
not like a go fuck yourself.
It's more like, go fuck yourself.
Okay.
So this is some whale source material that I pulled in.
And we're going to use a trick that I'm sure you guys all know.
But I'm just going to show you kind of, this is again, this is my process.
We're going to gate this on and off side chain from SFX3, which is our Space Satan voice.
Okay.
We're going to take the attack up a bit and pull the release, and again, just see what we can get.
Okay. Right. Now, here's the issue. What is the issue?
The issue is that we're running into that problem where you layer so many things that it sounds like animal choir.
Fuck, that's a great band name.
Animal Choir.
I mean, it's already Animal Collective,
but I don't think it could be like a whole different deal.
You're welcome.
Worth the money, right?
Okay, so I'm gonna pull something in
to try and make this more cohesive.
And this is tough, you know, because honestly,
this is something that I would sort of sit down and do
and like think about and not have to like.
Like I did not have diarrhea while trying to speak anyway, um, yeah, it went great mom
We're all best friends now, okay, so I'm pulling up
Crystallizer and I'm doing this because I find that like when
When you have a group that sort of pitches together it stitches together. It just came up with that that down
money money, baby
OK, we'll do detune, we'll go doublers on this, and we're going to pull our mix.
We'll pitch it.
So I want to make up for some of that high-end EQ that we lost, so I'm going to go back to...
sound toys here and pull up Psy-Q. I'm really, really into distortion right now.
It's something that I used to stay away from, but I've been able to get some really good results from it.
sound effects
Ok, I'm going to say, like, for doing that in 7 minutes...
It's not the worst thing.
I'm going to do something I wasn't sure that I was going to do, but I really love you guys.
Oh, do you like this?
My name in my session is SickGDCPrezi.
Ice magic.
A dude recently got a hold of me named Ice Mage and I was like, we've got to be friends.
So this is a project I've been working on.
And I'm going to look through here and I'm going to find some of the more,
like I'm going to find a sound and kind of run you guys through how I did it.
Cool? Yeah?
Okay.
How much time do you have?
I don't know.
Oh, I don't, I have two minutes.
Never mind, I'm not going to run you through it.
Does anyone have any questions?
Hey, you know what? Fuck it.
I'm going to open a session and just show you guys very briefly.
Oh yeah, okay.
This is the into fear state.
So basically, big monster comes, you're like,
oh man, that monster's really scary.
And then you're like, your camera starts shaking
and you can't move your character very easily.
This is a very simple jam here.
And yeah, it's a very similar process.
This is all based on the drum rack
and let's see what we got.
Yeah.
I must be lost in the dark,
seeking the key to the door that I lost.
Dude, I must be way into space Satan stuff.
Okay, so I'm gonna just run you guys through my bounces
and it'll kind of like, as you see, from top to bottom,
you'll notice that sometimes they're randomized,
but typically it's like idea one, idea two,
idea three, idea four.
I put those in a random container
and see what works best, see what sticks.
So, here's fear in, I think.
This is a concept for the loop, the beginning of right before you get feared.
It's like to bring tension.
That's just my voice being weird.
I don't know what this is.
Nevermind, that's dope.
It's another element that I layered on.
And that's essentially the final with the additional layers.
I think, you know, in retrospect, now that I'm looking at this,
something... time is the biggest teacher.
Something that I didn't do in that final that I wish I would have done
is push the two elements.
There's a high-end element and there's a low-end element.
And I wish I would have been more ballsy with those elements
because I feel like they got buried in the mix.
Anyway, thank you guys so much for having me.
We can talk after. And thanks again.
I really appreciate it.