This is gonna be brilliant for all of us.
My name is Mike, and this is my incredibly long titled,
it's, yeah, it's not very good.
It's a very search engine optimized title.
So I'm here today to talk to you
about something a bit weird.
I know it's a level design track.
I'm gonna be talking about dialog systems.
But I hope that it's kind of an interesting take
on dialog systems using level design lenses.
Maybe there's some stuff in here as well
that might help with communication with writers.
or taking your level design skill set
and applying it in different places in the game.
It's an interesting case study, hopefully.
So, obligatory who am I slide.
I'm Mike Bithell, I think I already said that.
I might do it a couple more times.
I'm an indie developer.
If you've heard of me, it's probably because of
Thomas Was Alone, which is a pretentious
rectangle platforming game.
Overrated in my opinion, but thankfully
I don't write the reviews.
Volume was the follow up, which was a stealth game,
and then Subsurface Circular is the one that just came out.
Out of interest in the room, anyone in there
actually played Subsurface Circular?
Oh cool, a couple of you, awesome, excellent, okay.
If you could just explain to the people around you
what the hell it is throughout the course of the talk,
that'd be great.
But even though I'm known for these games,
I am a level designer.
That's kind of my background.
That's where I'm from.
I worked as a level designer on a bunch of games,
3D platformers, 2D brawlers.
I worked as a graphic designer, a concept designer.
I've done most jobs at some point.
If there was someone who was willing to pay my bills,
I'd make a video game for them.
I did the full level design on Thomas Was Alone.
I oversaw the level design on Volume.
I had a really talented team of guys on that.
And then Subsurface Circular,
which is the game we're going to be talking about today,
I was the sole level designer on,
which was kind of cool, but also practical,
because it's a very small game.
So, the game Subsurface Circular.
This game, it exists because we had a gap.
The polite, politically good version of this is we found ourselves with an exciting six
month gap in our schedule, thanks to our colleagues in the publishing world.
That's one way of putting it.
And we have this gap.
And we had to use it for something.
So R&D made sense as something to do.
I've just realized, by the way,
I didn't tell any of you to turn off your phones,
to fill in your evaluation forms,
or to sit in the middle of the room,
which is a thing, apparently.
I don't know if that's to make it look like
there's more of you in the audience.
Don't know, but it's there.
Let's move along.
So yeah, it was a bit of time we had
and we wanted to do some R&D.
There was a real problem that I saw in our games,
which was that they were very story-led.
They were known for being story-led.
People liked the characters and the worlds we built.
But the story was just kind of something
that happened to you while you played the game.
You know, you did a platformer,
or you did a bit of stealth exploration,
and Andy Serkis told you story over the VO.
And I figured that would work for maybe two games,
maybe three games, and then people were gonna realize,
I'm kind of a hack.
and I kind of wanted to move beyond that
and do something more interactive and more interesting.
The trick, of course, would be to keep it small.
We had, well, we've wasted a month
just thinking of all the stuff I just said,
so we're now down to about five months,
and we need to make something
that can be made in that time with the money we have,
which isn't an infinite resource.
We have quite a small budget we can put into this.
I managed to convince the people I work with
to go for this, so we have to get this game made.
We decided on Subsurface Circular, which we stealth-launched.
It's a narrative game, it's a text adventure game
about a detective who's a robot.
And I'm not going to tell you anything else, I'm going to show you the trailer,
because we literally stealth-launched it, so the audience didn't know anything more
about this game than the trailer, so this is a good way of introducing it.
I might talk a little bit while it's going on, but please pay attention
to how the gameplay works. It's kind of a dialogue system,
that's what we're going to be talking about throughout the whole of this talk,
so keep an eye on that. But let me play this trailer for you quickly.
A bass
And that's the game.
With amazing bass apparently.
That was a great experience.
So you didn't see any level design there.
We're off to a great start.
So first of all, please do bear with me.
We'll get to it, I promise.
The key thing here is that I have used some level design approaches
in the way that we've approached dialogue systems.
So we've got a lot of things that you saw kind of being played with there.
The core gameplay is built around these lists of options that come up,
your standard kind of everything from Mass Effect to Horizon
to any kind of Western RPG you've played.
Dialogue options you can throw into conversation
in order to move things forward.
to make choices.
We designed dialogue around linear paths,
so that standard thing of branching you off,
giving you some options, coming back to a hub
that you've seen in a lot of games
where you'll kind of be able to investigate a subject
or whatever.
We tried not to do that though,
because we had something that was far more interesting
and actually opened up our opportunity to do level design.
which was these focus points.
So in the bottom there you can see
I've actually unlocked one on that screenshot
and I've got a bank of them in an inventory down here.
Focus points are topics or subjects
that you can interject into conversation
either to answer a question, to ask a question.
You can use themes and subjects you've picked up on
to have a conversation.
You can carry them with you, you can lose them,
you can gain them.
And once we added that to the game,
we had something interesting going on.
But we had a problem.
We wanted to make a two-hour dialogue tree game.
And you just saw it.
It's pretty straightforward.
You know, it's mainly just clicking on these options.
And we knew we didn't have an art budget,
we didn't have much time or money,
and we knew that the writing would hopefully be quite good
because that's something that we're known for.
But we also were a little bit worried that it would be boring.
there would be something that didn't really attach with an audience that would be kind of just a long slog.
There was a real concern there.
And how did we fix that using existing skills?
Because it kind of relied on the skills we already had on the team
to actually solve that problem.
Like I said, we couldn't spend much money,
we couldn't bring in too many other people.
And finally...
With interactive fiction, there's a niche audience.
There's a specific audience who plays a lot
of interactive fiction, who have a good time
with those games, but we wanted to reach beyond that.
Our previous games had found kind of,
not mainstream audiences, but broader audiences.
So we knew it was important that we went back
to those players and gave them something
that they would hopefully enjoy
and that they wouldn't be put off by
because they'd not played a game like this before.
What would we do?
Well, we came to a solution.
This isn't my level design.
This is from Half-Life, it's very good.
Just looks cool.
And it's a great level as well.
I realized I was a level designer.
So I realized that actually there were these kind of skills
that I already had in me.
This is a key turning point in the movie adaptation
of this slideshow that we'll be using.
I realized the power was within me all along.
Slightly arrogant thing to say in front of a room full of people.
I realized that actually a lot of the kind of the instincts I had as a level designer
would apply to storytelling.
I realized, first of all, that if I came up with a story that explained why the protagonist
was asking a lot of questions, I'd be onto something.
Detective fiction immediately jumped out.
And there's a reason that so much detective fiction
is about world building.
Your protagonist is looking for answers,
looking for information.
There's very few professions where you can walk into a room
and just start asking people how their day's going
and not get kicked out.
Detectives are a great way of doing that.
Realizing that kind of thing would help,
realizing I could have puzzles and challenges
as a result of that,
immediately I started seeing gameplay
rather than just a chat in a video game.
And I realized that there were so many links
between good writing and good design,
causality, predictability of outcomes, goal setting,
the kind of things that make good levels,
that make us feel as players
that a game is treating us fairly,
are also sort of rules of writing.
They're in all the writing books as well.
There's a lot of storytelling level design overlap.
And this was an, I'm gonna actually hold on this slide
while you take a photo.
You got it?
Awesome.
Let's carry on.
If I have to rush later because of you,
I'm going to hold you responsible.
So that's all very nice.
That's a nice thing to say and to kind of point out.
But how do we actually practically do that?
How do we apply level design to conversation?
Well, first of all is those focus points,
which remain the coolest idea that we came up
with for the game.
Focus points are an inventory.
They're an object you can collect.
And with that single choice.
suddenly you have level design.
You can collect them, you can lose them,
and that can be jarring, that can be kind of a moment
of fear of what, you've had some stuff
and then the game's taken it away.
That's something to use very carefully.
You can combine them in that classic adventure game sense
where you take object A and object B,
put them together and get something else.
That feels like deduction,
that feels like working something out.
That's a cool thing that a detective would do
and can give us some gameplay opportunities.
You can open conversation doors with them.
We do this a lot in subsurface,
arguably a little bit too much.
But the idea of a character who needs direction
to a specific building,
you can go get that information, bring it back,
and give it, that's a door.
That's a key and a door.
The information is the key,
the person who needs it is a door.
Suddenly you've got quest design,
you can do stuff with that.
And of course we can do exploration and world building.
We can have focus points that unlock
interesting doors over here to a bit of exposition.
We can have focus points that are in themselves
a rewarding outcome of exploration
that you can kind of find a weird conversation track
and get some value from that.
Again, all level design stuff,
all stuff that you would use and think about
if you were trying to build compelling levels.
But there's more.
Objectives.
As I said, we've got quest giving.
That's easy.
We can also do aesthetic objectives.
So we can say, hey, you should go over,
or it would be cool if you worked out this.
And then 10 minutes later,
just give you a click on that objective
saying you worked out this.
No game design involved there, but it feels nice.
We can also do cleverer stuff
where we're actually tracking your actions.
and how many interactions you've had,
that kind of thing, locking in your progress
towards a task, which again,
it builds up that sense of progress,
sorry, progression and level.
Multiple characters, you saw there,
two characters just talking in a one-on-one conversation.
That's how subsurface is,
but because every train carriage
has multiple characters in it.
you're constantly moving between different
one-on-one conversations, which become rooms,
and become separate spaces that give the player
a sense of traversal, because you might be talking
to this character, and then you might realize
you need to go over there to talk to that character,
and then you come back with that information
to that character.
Players talk about this in verbs like go over there,
come back, they are a robot sat on a train.
There is no movement or traversal taking place,
but by having just different characters
you can have one-on-one conversations with,
we create the sense of traversal, of movement,
and that's incredibly powerful and useful.
Signposting we didn't really do.
Our dialogue flows in a way that kind of makes it hard
for you to get lost as a player,
but we did, again, find an opportunity there
to use that in storytelling.
We have a literal Chekhov's gun in the game,
a gun that is introduced at the start,
and in a good story, if you introduce a gun
in the first scene, you need to make sure
someone shot it by the end.
We absolutely hold true to that storytelling analogy.
And we also allow for experimental play.
We have characters in the world
who serve no story purpose whatsoever,
but that you can have fun conversations with.
My favorite is the robot who's into Hamilton,
and you can kind of sing songs with.
That's quite fun.
He's right, Hamilton, but you want him to be,
so you sing at him and he ignores you.
And it's a great moment,
which has absolutely no bearing
on the game's story whatsoever.
but it's still something I guess sent screenshots of
almost every day because people find it and enjoy it.
And again, that's the sort of stuff
that regular dialogue systems don't do
because they're not thinking it through as a level design.
And that's exciting to me.
Mu, you're gonna recognize this slide.
Applying level design to conversation.
So technically, what are some interesting parts
of that process?
Well, first of all, making the full cast robotic
was super useful.
Realizing that we could kind of cover up any flaws
in our writing by having characters who are robots
was so useful.
Characters can talk a bit stilted,
they can have sudden emotional shifts.
We don't have too much of that in Subsurface,
except for one big puzzle which I'm gonna talk about
in a minute.
But anywhere where our robots behave in a non-human-like way
we have a canonical reason why that's the case.
It's super useful, and there's no shame in having those kind of narrative and world-based
excuses for the shortcomings of the experience you're creating.
And of course, crucially, we have this, and I didn't know you were going to be in the
audience, Moo.
It's embarrassing.
I do name-drop you here.
Hey, Moo.
Thank you.
very talented coder who came in and built this really nice,
fast, node-based system.
So this is how we build a level for Subsurface Circular,
is with these really cool, very, very zoomed out
dialogue node systems.
Way more visibility than the tools most people use
for this kind of work.
We have a lot less features than they do,
but we basically stripped out,
or just didn't bother to put in in the first place,
features that weren't useful in getting us writing quickly.
So let's talk about that process.
How do you do this?
How do you design dialogue in this way?
Well, first of all, you do what a writer does.
You pull out some Post-it notes or a record board
and you work out your act structure
and all of that kind of story stuff
that you do for any kind of writing,
where you work out the big beats of the narrative,
how that game world is gonna flow.
But ultimately, you're not thinking about interaction,
you're thinking about story progression.
The next step is where you come into the interactive points.
So we would go to a flow chart.
That flow chart then ends up similar to this
on the right here.
It's kind of cropped off, but you can see
blue is focus points, red is objectives.
And you can see there that we're kind of thinking
through the process of different conversations.
Each conversation is numbered.
That's how I'm breaking it up and thinking it through.
But this is the trajectory in just one level,
how we're moving between different characters
and talking to them about different subjects.
It's all very structured.
It needed to be because we have so much writing
on the next step.
So the next step was an initial draft of the script.
So we'd write it like a movie.
So just a very linear, two characters get talking.
super useful. We can work out tone, voice, characterization. We can do all of the good
writer stuff where you really arrive at a character that the audience is going to care about
without having to worry too much about the logic and the game design-y bits.
which we then did next in the node editor
where we would then copy and paste that linear draft in.
You remember from the previous slide, the branching.
I would then add all of that branching
and add all that variety to it.
It's interesting in kind of future experiments
we're taking with this tech.
we actually cut out the linear script stage altogether
because I actually think that forces me or pushes me towards writing very linearly
when I should be thinking in that branching way from day one.
That was a confidence thing and kind of a learning process for me.
So the initial draft step is now not how we do this.
It makes it harder, but it comes out better.
The other thing to point out that's really interesting
from a level design point of view,
there's no blocking stage involved
in anything I just described.
It's, you just write.
And you've got logical gameplay from day one.
There's no white boxing because there's no art pass.
It's just writing.
So you're just trying to,
you're redrafting essentially in the same way
as you would with any kind of piece of writing,
10, maybe 15 times,
but you're just working into the same script,
which means it's fast
and it means there's no dependencies.
our art in the game, you saw in the trailer we got really nice art, but it's kind of devoid
in our production pipeline from the level design. It's something that kind of exists
separately and that's really useful. That means we don't, we're not held up by it, they're not
held up by us, we can just kind of, I can just be writing essentially from day one and I'm producing
work that goes into the final game. I wanted to give a quick example of how this works.
So, Sequence 5, spoilers, but yeah.
Sequence 5 is the most popular level in the game.
I think it's a useful one to use to kind of showcase
how this thinking works, because it's very hard.
when you're just looking at the stream of text
to see what the level design is.
So I did this quick little diagram.
I literally did it yesterday
because I didn't like this slide
and the last diagram was bad.
So the sequence starts with you entering the room
at the top there by that red key.
You have a very simple conversation with a side character.
The red key represents a specific piece of information
about the situation that's going on in the game.
I'm gonna try and keep it spoiler-free.
You then have two other characters get into the train carriage, those two rooms underneath the room with the key in.
Those two characters you have a bit of flavor time with, you can kind of lie to them, you can be honest.
Doesn't really have a massive impact on the story going forward from that point, but it's there and it's a nice bit of framing for what's about to come next.
Then we get into the meat and potatoes of this, which is those two characters are emotionally linked.
So making one of those characters happy or sad or angry also makes the other character happy or sad or angry,
which opens up different conversational paths with that second character.
And as I put it up there,
and because everyone always reads the bullet point
the second it goes up on the screen,
you're ahead of me, which is, that's every 90s FPS,
water level raising and lowering puzzle.
That was a really great opportunity
to use something very specific from these old games I liked
in a dialogue situation and make it feel fresh.
So you're manipulating the emotions, that's opening doors.
You can see on the right kind of a clumsy depiction of that
of different rooms with different keys in.
You're kind of.
finding new focus points and new information
by going down different channels,
and then right at the end,
that long one pointing off to the right there,
you use that little piece of information
you learned from the first side character
right at the start of the scene,
which feels very detective-y
to kind of remember that there was a brick
by the entrance as you came in,
and that breaks the case,
and you realize what's going on.
That unlocks the end of the level,
which you then move into.
So it's...
a progression through a dungeon, but it's also good detective fiction writing, hopefully.
It's all of that logic I'm talking about, all of those shared principles in the worlds
of writing good genre fiction and hopefully designing good levels tied together.
And then you die.
Right.
Spoilers.
You don't die.
You sort of die.
So where did it not fit?
Because this is sounding very clever so far.
It's got to have gone wrong some ways, right?
And it absolutely did.
First of all, conversation flows.
Making a cul-de-sac or a blockage or a wall
or a dead end in a conversation doesn't really work for us.
Or we had trouble with it.
It didn't feel fun.
It didn't feel rewarding.
It felt like the game had broken.
You know, you didn't want to hear the same line
of dialogue repeating over and over again
because the character wouldn't let you past.
that means that the game is a bit more on rails
than you would normally do with a traditional level design.
It feels a little bit more structured.
It's forcing you in the right direction at all times.
That's a limitation of this model.
Similarly, as a result of that,
I relied a little bit too much on arbitrary puzzles.
Anyone who's played the game through,
you're gonna know immediately what I'm talking about.
There's a couple of puzzles in there that are riddles
where you'll be on a really interesting detective case
and then a character will go, well, there are two knights
and one of them can only tell the truth
and one of them can only lie.
It's not that one, but it's that kind of stuff.
and it trips people up and it irritates people
and I'm forever reading forum posts
about how awful that particular puzzle is.
And they're right, they're all absolutely right.
It's a limitation because making something
as linear as we did, the detective metaphor
sometimes didn't work in every situation
and that definitely kind of locked us
into some different paths.
And finally, because, speaking of different paths,
because we were focusing so much on making good gameplay
and good design that felt good to work through,
we did let down the audience on a genre expectation,
which is branching narratives.
A lot of interactive fiction, you can be kind of,
you can choose different paths,
you can choose different actions
which take you in different directions.
Our game's actually pretty linear.
You know, the story doesn't, there are different endings,
but it's all very, very straightforward
because we were focusing on making the design
and the dungeons fun.
because dungeons tend to only have one exit.
So we kind of, that was another limitation
of the design approach that kind of,
it wasn't terrible, but it was definitely something
that kind of disappointed people about the game.
And also it's worth pointing out,
with any talk, how specific this is.
This worked because we're text-based,
so we lean very heavily on the ambiguities
of the written word.
We absolutely don't have to record VO.
That would have been a nightmare.
And to get all the different VO in
that would track different choices you've made
and still sound appropriate would have been terrible.
We lean very heavily on the limitations of our presentation.
There's lots of reasons this wouldn't necessarily
work in everything.
This is the boring slide, reception.
It reviewed really well.
Couple of people thought that there was no game design.
Right.
It's not a very interesting slide.
But yeah, it went down really well.
It was well-received, which is great.
So where can we take this next?
We've said publicly we're playing with this idea
because it did resonate and we think
there's more opportunities there.
So a few of those ideas.
multiple characters in conversation at once.
Our game is about one-on-one conversation,
subsurface circular.
What happens if that's a kind of an Aaron Sorkin style,
five people in a corridor talking over each other?
Is that really annoying to the player?
Or does that feel kinetic and energetic?
And can we play with those, blur those lines
of like where conversation ends with one character
and starts with another?
That could be interesting.
Pairing decision making with more audiovisual output.
As I said, we kept the art and the design
kind of separate throughout the process.
Can we do more?
Can we have music that reacts to what you're doing?
Can we have visuals that react to what you're doing?
Can we get more animation in there?
There's lots of interesting places we can hook stuff
audiovisually onto these outcomes.
Visualization narrative space.
making that diagram, I realized how interesting
it might be to a player to have that kind of awareness
of the conversation they're having.
It's an interesting one to play with
because it might be that that's too much information
and actually makes the game feel kind of arbitrary
or overly mechanical, but there's also a possibility
that tracking that information, giving it to the player
and saying to the player, this is how you're moving
through this dialogue possibility space,
even if we show it to them after they've completed
the level, say, could be interesting.
That one's weird, I don't know.
We'll get to that maybe sometime.
and allowing for more traditional branching around puzzles,
making it that we actually give the IF players
what they want and let them have big story outcomes
of their actions.
That's really just down to focus and time on my part,
writing more stuff, not coming to GDC,
and just staying in my room, writing stuff.
And then finally, of course, because this is a GDC talk,
procedural generation, randomization, spawning.
We had some randomization that was really interesting.
I think the only thing that survived into Subsurface
is that the listener characters have different names
each time you play it.
The original version was much more randomized and varied
and as a result, terrible.
which is why we went much more linear down the road.
But I do think there is stuff.
There is quote unquote filler dialogue.
There are conversations that could happen
that don't need to be the core dialogue of the game.
The equivalent of getting, we were talking about extras
earlier, the equivalent of getting extras
to throw in a line of dialogue to establish a scene.
Why couldn't that be handled by something
that's just throwing in some random options
or built systemically so it's reacting
to what the player's doing or what the world's doing?
There are opportunities there which we can explore.
And the final slide, so if anyone has any questions,
get up, I think I'm gonna have time for one.
Potential for level design in other fields.
I wanna broaden this out,
because I do think there's an opportunity here,
I hope, to take level design principles
like the ones I've talked about,
and apply them in other areas of game development.
Because you're probably not all working
on dialogue-based pretentious robot detective novels.
So we can probably broaden it a bit more.
We already see navigation and exploration
built into progressive system, into progression systems.
I like that in Shadow of War,
there's some interesting branching that's starting to go on.
Feels like a level, feels like moving through a space,
which is interesting.
Of course, quest and mission systems,
we're already seeing great innovation in this area.
Probably there's room for more.
I really don't like, I'm a big AAA fan.
That's most of what I play
because I spend all day making indie games.
I kind of want to relax with a great open world AAA game.
And it's weird to me that the map isn't used more,
that we don't find more opportunities to do level design
and game design at the map screen level
because those games are about these massive worlds.
Surely there's some stuff, I keep hitting the mic, sorry.
Surely there's some stuff that we can kind of do
with that screen as well and kind of.
either tell interesting stories on that screen
or allow progression or movement on that screen
that's interesting.
And I wanted to point out specifically Horizon.
I loved Horizon for a lot of reasons,
but I would put the enemy design in Horizon
up with a lot of the stuff I'm talking about here.
Those bosses all feel like levels.
They're just levels that happen to be trying to kill me.
over and over again.
And that's cool.
As I'm playing those levels, it's not just finding the
sensitive spots. There's a causality
and a progression to those attacks
which feels really good as a player.
It feels like something I can learn and get better at
and that I can master.
And that feels like that's a great opportunity
that that game takes advantage of.
Cool. I've managed to do this
with, I think, two minutes to spare.
Is that right?
Yes, I'm getting a thumbs up.
So probably time for one question.
Thank you very much for your time.
I really appreciate it.
Awesome.
One question.
Yes, hello. Oh, remember to do your evaluation things as well. Hello.
Hey, in the middle of Subcircus Circular there's one conversation with a character that brings up,
it's half joke, half lore, where they start reciting the dialogue from Thomas Was Alone.
Yes.
Where does that, I mean like the quickest level design lens is that it's like putting an old
version of a game into a new version like Wolfenstein does. How do you think something
like that could be built on using the philosophies you just talked about in the last 30 minutes?
That's really interesting. Yeah, it's a joke. I mean, that's the main reason it's there.
It's kind of a... So, yeah, in the world, there's a priest,
and during the writing process, when I was thinking, okay, well, what's this priest?
Do I want to, like, give him a specific human religion?
He's like, oh, well, Thomas was alone. He's about the emergence of gods.
Let's make him a believer in Thomas was alone.
And then he recites Thomas was alone to you. If you ask him to, and he will stop.
If you tell him to, and he'll eventually stop, because I got bored of copying and pasting
all of the Thomas was alone dialogue. He eventually goes, that's enough.
Yeah, I think it's an Easter egg right now.
It literally is the Wolfenstein thing
of just hiding a Wolfenstein level in Wolfenstein.
But yeah, I think the idea of returning to stuff,
of having impact, using players' knowledge
of previous games in that circumstance,
having a situation where you have a more meaningful thing.
So there's one of the things that's in there
for the hardcore Thomas Was Alone fans
is one of the names you can give your character
at the start of the game is Claire,
who's a very important character
to the Thomas Was Alone fan base.
And if you play that character as Claire,
then there's kind of this soft implication
that maybe you're related to that character from Thomas,
and that kind of fits and tracks narratively.
So I think there is that kind of deeper way of doing it.
In terms of like level design.
That's interesting.
There's probably other more exciting ways
of doing that as well.
And also bringing data across
and having that kind of Mass Effect style
game to game continuity would be interesting.
I think I'm probably out of time.
This says I am.
I'm very excited to tell you about,
in 20 minutes from now.
a brilliant talk that I've made a mental note of
called An Architectural Approach to Level Design
Creating an Art Theory for Game Worlds.
And so can you.
I'm pretty sure I read that wrong.
But it genuinely, I was chatting to him last night
about it, it's really cool.
So do stick around and watch that.
That'll be really neat.
I think there's a 20 minute break now.
If anyone wants to chat, I'm going to be around here
and I'd love to talk to you about video games and stuff.
Thanks a lot for your time.