Can everybody hear me in the back?
Ah, there we go.
All right.
Well, thanks to all of you for coming out at 5 o'clock,
the last session of the day, for the classic game post-mortem
on the Oregon Trail.
Enough of all this high-level technology stuff
that in the expo area, it just boggles the mind.
We're gonna have some fun.
I'm Don Rawitsch, co-inventor of the original version
of the Oregon Trail, and I'm happy to be here
to tell my story.
First, a couple of announcements.
Turn off your cell phones.
And don't forget, at the end of the session,
you're going to get to fill out an evaluation form.
You are instructed to check all the boxes
on the highest number level on all the questions.
And one more announcement I was going to make.
You're all familiar with the train jam
that I've seen described.
People get on a train in Chicago and they have 56 hours to make some games.
We're considering that maybe next year that we have a covered wagon jam.
We put a bunch of people in covered wagons to set them out for Missouri.
And the cool part about that is they'll have no excuse about quality because they'll have
six months to get it right.
Okay, what I'm going to do here over the next hour or so is to tell you about the Oregon
Trail game, where it came from, how it got invented, who invented it, how it got into
the schools, how it became so popular, and hopefully at the end a few suggestions that
might be of interest to today's game developers, lessons that we've learned from the Oregon
Trail game.
And I'm hoping there will be a little time for questions
at the end.
We are the last session of the day,
so we have a little flexibility maybe
to extend if there are a lot of questions.
But we'll see how that goes.
So let me just ask, how many of you
have played the Oregon Trail?
OK.
And second question is, how many of you
first encountered the Oregon Trail game
when you were a kid in school?
Okay, so that's typically the pattern, that's good.
And I think because there probably were a few people
who did not raise their hand,
let's just take about two minutes
to review what this game is about.
It is a simulation of an important event
in American history.
As you probably know,
let's try to get that.
Okay, as you probably know,
okay, as we probably know,
the computer always puts up question boxes
when you don't want one.
The country, what became the United States,
was settled on the East Coast.
People,
came and they populated those states, but after a while it became clear for some people
this was not where they wanted to be and explorers had pushed out across this land and determined
that there was all kinds of farming opportunities and other opportunities for the future.
and spread the word that if you want to really have a new start on life, go west, is the advice.
And so they did.
And that people started traveling to the western part of what became the US.
Excuse me.
Perhaps, where is my assistant?
There is a box that keeps coming up that says,
Rescue and Recovery.
And that applies to me, I can see, but shouldn't be coming up on the computer.
I may have gotten it to go away.
Okay, so how did they get to the West?
Well, the explorers had mapped out some trails
over the plains, over the mountains,
all the way to the West Coast, the Pacific Ocean,
and perhaps the best known of those trails
was the Oregon Trail, most heavily traveled
during the middle of the 19th century.
And how did you travel on the Oregon Trail?
You use the vehicle of choice, the covered wagon.
You put your belongings in there.
You got your family crammed in there.
And for the next 2,000 miles, this is how you traveled.
It was about a six-month trip.
And this is what solidified the United States
as being the land as large as it became.
And so this Western migration is seen as very
important in American history.
The Oregon Trail game is a simulation of this trip,
this journey, this hazardous adventure
that these people went on.
And it was popular on personal computers,
starting in about 1979, for about a decade and a half.
It was the highest point of popularity.
It was arguably the best known school software of that era.
And perhaps for many of you, this is the era which found you in school and traveling the
Oregon Trail on a computer.
However, if we're going to get to the story of where the game came from, we have to go
back almost a decade.
So sorry.
So we're going to go back to the 1960s and 70s when computers looked like the thing that you see up on the screen.
They were huge. They required their own rooms to be locked up and kept in.
But this is how computers started coming into our society.
And they were used in business and in research.
It was inevitable that they would come to be used in education.
And so a whole new area of endeavor and of study,
educational computing, was born at this time.
Now, most of the use of computers in education
could be found at universities at that time,
but there were some schools that had a local university
in town and they found a way to connect
to the university's computer and they started offering
to elementary and high school kids.
the opportunity to use a computer.
Some of the larger districts had enough money,
they bought their own computer.
Now this was not the computer that they used
to keep track of their finances,
to keep track of their student attendance,
to keep track of the bus routes.
These were computers that were specifically designated
as to be used for instructional purposes.
Now what did people back at that time
do with a computer in a school?
Typically, in K-12 education, the activity was to learn,
to teach kids something about programming computers.
And the reason that that was the main activity
is because there wasn't much else you could do at the time.
There were no software applications available to schools
that would allow them to do things related to math
and science and social studies and so forth.
Those applications were very scarce.
So, this brings us to the fateful year of 1971 and three young men who were attending
college at the time.
They were attending Carleton College, a liberal arts school in Minnesota.
Two of them, Bill Heineman and Paul Dillenberger, were math majors, and the handsome fellow
on the right had decided that he was going to be a history major.
As a matter of fact, the first few years we were in college together, we didn't really know each other.
But coming into our senior year in the fall of 1971, we were brought together by one thing we had in common.
We were all planning to become teachers.
And because of that, we had to do certain things in our preparation during our college years.
So...
the kind of culminating aspect of your teacher training
when you're in college is to do your practice teaching.
So this is where you're assigned to a school.
You're assigned to a supervising teacher in that school,
and you get to observe how schools work, what teachers do,
and eventually get the opportunity to teach kids yourself,
to take over classes, to...
to do that and this was all to determine whether, essentially, whether you had the guts to stand
up in front of 30 adolescents day in and day out.
So we took advantage of a program that allowed us to do our practice teaching in the city
of Minneapolis and we got an apartment together and the three of us set out to determine what
teaching was all about.
The Minneapolis schools was a fairly progressive district
at that time, and they had set up a computer for the district
that all the schools in the Minneapolis district
could connect to, and kids could have a chance
to use computers.
My two colleagues knew something about computer programming
from their college studies, given that they were in math.
I knew absolutely nothing about computers at that time.
And after we had
After we had been in our schools for a few weeks,
my supervising teacher notified me
that I was going to, in about two or three weeks ahead,
I was going to teach a unit on the westward migration.
and that I needed to prepare myself to do that.
So I thought to myself, well, now,
how am I going to put this across,
this historical information, in a way
that kids are not going to fall asleep at their desks?
And I knew that the one thing I needed to avoid
was to assign them to read all about it in their textbook,
because that's what makes kids not like history so much.
So, I thought to myself that I had read about educators who had created games for the classroom.
Not computer games because there weren't that many schools that had computer access, but
board games, paper pencil games, things that would help you understand a concept better.
So I thought, well, maybe I could do the same
for the westward migration.
I created a very large map of the Western US area.
I drew in the Oregon Trail.
I thought about that the kids maybe
were going to draw cards or roll dice.
So I was ahead of Dungeons and Dragons on this thing.
And so, you know, some way was going to determine what happened to them at each stage along,
traveling along the trail, and they'd have little wagon markers that they could move.
That was my vision.
So I had all this stuff spread out on the apartment living room.
One day I was just getting into figuring out how this might work, and my two colleagues
came home.
They asked what I was doing, and I explained to them what it was I had to teach.
And they thought, well, that was a game was a pretty innovative way to go at this.
But the thing is, that game would be a lot better on a computer.
And that was kind of the spark that got us going on this.
We had at that time two weeks to create something
that could be delivered on the computer
that was available to our schools,
especially my school since I was the one teaching history.
And so we set about on this task.
Well, what did it mean to put something on a computer in 1971?
Well, the first thing is, how do you communicate with a computer?
You use this device, a teletype, which is kind of a typewriter on steroids.
It's a very large and heavy machine, but it's got a keyboard, doesn't have a screen.
You see the roll of paper coming out above the keyboard.
So when you type things on the teletype, they showed up on that paper, just like, kind of
like a typewriter.
And when the computer communicated back to you, its messages also got printed out on
that roll of paper.
It didn't print very quickly and there was no screen, no graphics, no audio-visual, well,
with one exception.
Inside the teletype was essentially a bicycle bell.
And you were told when you bought the teletype that if you put a certain string of code in
your computer program, that when the computer got there, a message would be sent that rang
that bicycle bell, thereby indicating that something significant had just happened in
your program.
That's about all we had back then to wake the kids up.
So that's the teletype, and you know what a computer looks like,
but how did you make the connection between the two?
And to do that, we need a modem.
Now today, I'm guessing modems are about the size
of your fingernail, but back then they
were about the size of a shoebox.
And you see on the right-hand side what
was known as an acoustic coupler.
And this is the way that you could connect the teletype
through a phone line to the computer.
So how did this work?
Well, you were given the phone number
that was attached to the computer in another building
that would pick up your call.
And by the way, that round thing on the phone,
that's called a dial for those not familiar.
So you dialed up the phone and you listened,
and you heard a high-pitched tone,
and that was the computer.
And then you took that handset
and you thrust it into the acoustic coupler
so it ended up like you see on the picture.
Little light came on,
and then the teletype started chattering.
You had made a connection to the computer.
You could now go.
So that was state-of-the-art in 1971.
We started working on the Oregon Trail,
and my friends had told me that we could get something done
in two weeks.
I think later I determined they'd lied to my face.
However, at the end of two weeks, we had a program.
We had version 1.0 of the Oregon Trail on a mainframe computer,
and as near as we could tell, the bugs were worked out.
So it was time, it was time to try it out.
Now, I started thinking about how I was going to do this
in the classroom because even though the school had a
teletype for accessing the computer,
it only had one teletype.
which I reserved for a couple of weeks.
It was put in my classroom next to the phone with the coupler.
And then I thought, but we can't have 30 kids trying
to use this thing all at once.
So I divided them up into small groups.
And I created a rotation of activities.
So you could be playing the game,
or maybe another group would be doing a map exercise,
another group would be reading something about the trails
and traveling west and so on,
until we got through the rotation
and every group had had a chance to play the game.
So we started doing this,
and how did the students react?
They were mesmerized.
With only one teletype in the school,
I don't think many kids in the school
had actually had a chance to use it.
So this was the first thing they'd ever seen,
the first computer activity that they had ever witnessed.
And I think the other thing that probably
caught their imagination was, wow, this wasn't math.
We thought computers only did math.
No, you could do history as well.
You could do any subject.
So we started out, and they took to it like ducks in water.
It was just like today, the first time you hand something over to a young child and,
you know, an hour later they know how it works and you don't.
They really got into it.
They seemed to be absorbing information from the program about this Western trek.
and they couldn't get enough of it.
My friends, who taught math, made up flimsy excuses
why their students should also try the program.
And so they got that going, and they came home
and they told me, once we'd shown this to some students.
We now experience at lunchtime and after school
that a line of kids forms outside our classrooms
because they want the chance to come in
and get on the teletype and play this game.
So we concluded that we had come up
with something significant,
something that was teaching kids and also engaging them,
and that was important.
So we did this for a week or so, but it was now December,
and it's almost the holiday time and the end
of our practice teaching.
And therefore, we printed out the code to the Oregon Trail
program on the teletype.
So it came out on a scroll of paper,
the sacred scroll of the Oregon Trail.
Then, because we were leaving the school district,
and we didn't think we really had the right
to leave our stuff on their computer,
so we deleted the program.
But we had the sacred scroll.
And as we went back to finish up our college senior year,
I guess we all, the three of us kind of wondered,
would we ever have a chance to get this thing going again?
Before we move on to answer that question,
let's take a little bit of a look
inside the Oregon Trail version 1.0.
So the Oregon Trail, as you probably know,
is a resource management type game
and a game that is played in turns.
as is true of many games.
So what would happen is the teletype would print out a date
in 1847, I think, and say you're ready to start your trip.
You got some instructions.
You bought some supplies with some money
that you had at the start.
And the computer then, at the beginning of each turn,
gave you a status, how many supplies you had left,
how much cash, how much food, how much clothing,
how much ammunition, all the stuff
that you need to travel the Oregon Trail.
And then it would offer you the opportunity to make a strategy decision or two.
Like, are you going to keep going at this point?
Are you going to stop to rest?
Are you going to visit a fort where you could use your money to buy extra provisions?
Are you going to hunt? What are you going to do?
And then, the fateful question of how well are you going to eat?
If you didn't eat very well, you'd probably get sick.
If you ate very well, your health would be great,
but you'd start running out of food faster.
So you had to kind of balance that decision making.
That was then followed by the computer
going into its collection of.
mostly calamities that could befall you
to let you know what had happened.
Your oxen broke his leg, your kid got lost,
somebody got sick.
Well, you're probably familiar with many of these things.
And so you then had to react to a number of them,
and the computer then moving you on to the next turn
would calculate what happened to your resources
and how much you had to start the next turn,
and on this went.
And each turn was set up to represent two weeks in the trip
so the entire trip would take about 10 to 12 turns
on the teletype.
Now this is of course just the general overview,
but underneath that there was a lot more going on.
And I know that you can't read the small print
from this age-old diagram.
That's why I've, down the right-hand side,
I've kind of annotated in larger print.
But what I'm hoping to show here just visually
is that the path that the player takes in each turn,
this is one turn we're diagramming here,
actually had many different options,
many alternative routes, and many different things
that could happen to you.
So again, at the top, your resources are totaled up.
You make some strategy choices.
You could get attacked by strangers.
You could, many things in that big box
are problems that could occur.
You could get ill.
And the computer kept track of your mileage,
and when you reached mile post roughly 950,
you were at the Rocky Mountains,
and so mountain-related problems started to happen to you.
And as you work your way down this chart with the computer
using probability statements to determine
which things happen to you and how often,
when you went through all of that,
then it would take you back to the top
to start the next turn.
So I'm just trying to make the point here that
Well, let me start that over again.
I must confess to you, we did not create the chart
and then program to it.
That would have been too deliberate.
We started programming.
This is Agile, by the way.
We started programming and then when we got it to working the way we thought it should,
then I went in and made this chart so in the future we'd remember how it actually worked.
But as it turned out, it's a fairly sophisticated simulation model,
and because of all the different routes that the computer can take you through in every turn,
virtually no two trips to Oregon ever were exactly the same.
Which means what?
Players will keep coming back because they can't predict exactly what's going to happen.
Now another thing about the model is that even though we set up some probabilities for
how often certain things would happen, we thought that the model would be more accurate
if we pegged those probabilities not just to time passing, but to the terrain of the
trail.
the probability that a certain thing might happen
might be different at the beginning of the trail
or towards the end of the trail.
So how did we build that into the program?
Well, let's take the example of the fact that the pioneers that made this trip often came
into contact with people they didn't know, strangers.
Now these strangers might be friends or they may have mayhem on their mind.
They may want to rob you of your supplies and that kind of thing.
So you had to deal with this.
We figured that it was probably more likely that you would meet up with strangers,
you know, coming upon the trail at the beginning of the trip rather than towards the end.
Because, number one, you weren't so far from civilization at the beginning,
so these people could ride out, try to rob you, and then, you know, go back to Independence, Missouri.
And also, because the geographic terrain at this point is very flat, it's the prairies.
Once you get into the mountains, what self-respecting thief is going to want to try to survive there
for the meager rewards he's going to get for his evil ways?
So we thought that a graph like this was a good depiction
of the probability for this event
as mapped out against the terrain of the trail.
So along the X axis, we have the mileage from zero to 2000
and up the Y axis, we have probabilities from zero to 50%.
The math boys then had to figure out
how we could represent this mathematically.
So a formula, here is the formula.
So at the beginning of each turn,
the computer looked at the mileage you were at
and plugged it into M in this equation,
and that generates the corresponding Y value on the curve.
So if you were at the 400 mile mark,
it might be a 50% chance that you were going to meet up
with some of these riders.
If you were at the 1,600 mile post on the trail,
it'd be more like 5%.
And so by using this method, we would
generate different probabilities,
not just based on what event are we talking about,
but also where we were on the trail.
Now there's another aspect that had to be dealt with,
and that is the use of your firearm,
because there was no images, animation, and so forth.
So how do we do that?
Well, when it was time to use your rifle,
which means you had just chosen to hunt,
or because the computer said, for example,
riders are approaching you, so you pick up your rifle.
The computer would then quickly type out
something like type bang, or type pow, or blam,
something like that.
And you, the player, had to type that phrase in
as quickly as you could and press return.
So how did the computer turn that into the results of using your trusty gun?
Well if you made a typo in your haste, then say for hunting, you got no food.
If you spelled the phrase correctly but you were kind of a slow typist, you got some food.
But if you were a good speller and a good typist,
good eating tonight.
And your food supply was beefed up, if you'll pardon
the expression, for the next turn that you took.
So we didn't have little shooter guys running around
with guns and so forth.
But we might make the claim that Oregon Trail was
the first first-person shooter game in the history of games.
OK.
So this starts to give you an idea of how this worked.
And again, the kids were fascinated.
And we were sure that something could come of this
if we could just find a way to do it.
Well, the game sat dormant for a couple of years until 1974.
when I took a job with a newly formed organization in Minnesota called the Minnesota Educational
Computing Corporation. It was a public agency that had been formed by the state of Minnesota
to help schools come to terms with what it would mean to bring computing into the curriculum
and how to make that operational in the schools.
We take our hats off to Minnesota on this because no other state in the country did
something like this, which meant that the schools in the other states had a kind of
a chaotic situation.
How would they know how to make decisions about hardware to buy and software?
How would they train teachers and so forth?
But Minnesotans
from their Scandinavian background,
like to get things organized.
And so they created MECC, MECC, to help carry that out.
I took a job about four months after MEC started up its operation, and one of the things that
MEC did was it operated one of those big mainframe computers to provide instructional, educational
computing to all the schools in the state, no matter where you were located, by setting
up a telecom network and the mainframe computer.
I noticed when I arrived that in that mainframe computer,
there was a library of applications
that people had created, some good, some not so good.
And I remembered that I had one of these sacred scrolls.
So I asked, would it be OK if I added something
to the library?
Sure, they needed all that they could get.
And so on one long weekend, I typed in 800 lines of code
from my kitchen at home to put the Oregon Trail game
back up on a computer.
And now it would be not just available
to a few schools in Minneapolis,
it would be available to the entire state.
I realized, however, that the Oregon Trail 1.0,
having been created in two weeks,
had not exactly gone through the historical research
that we would probably want it to, to give it credence.
So I went in and started doing some of this research.
I checked out the geography, the mileage of the mileposts,
and made sure that things were happening along the trail
when they should, depending on the geography.
When we had built probabilities into the game
as to how often the various events would happen,
we were making educated guesses.
But I found in the library that there
were books in which were printed the actual text from diaries
of people that made this journey in the 1840s and 50s.
And so I read through some of these diaries and kept score.
Like how many days out of the entire trip was it bad weather?
How often did somebody get ill?
And so on, and turn those into revised probability numbers
that would make the trip on the computer more in line
with what we know from history.
And there was one other thing that needed to be dealt with,
and that was.
the role of Native Americans.
Because in the 1970s and maybe even to today,
you'll know if you go to see a Western at the movie
that we've kind of prolonged the stereotype
of these pioneers traveling in their wagon trains.
the Indians coming down out of the hills and attacking them and burning the wagons and so forth.
Well, it turns out from the diaries, it didn't work that way.
Or at least it only worked that way a lot less than we might think from watching those films.
And as a matter of fact, there were diary entries showing that Native Americans helped the pioneers,
helped them stay on the trail, to know where the trail was going,
helped them understand the plants at the side of the road, so to speak.
This one is nutritious, this one will kill you.
It was kind of helpful information to have, and they had it from years of experience.
So I made sure that there were events that came up in the game that reflected some of those kinds of things.
And also, I created a teacher guide. Do we have any teachers here? I should have asked.
We have a few.
OK.
Well, as any teacher will tell you,
if you're giving me a new thing to use in the classroom,
I've got to have instructions.
I've got to have ideas.
I can't just do this from scratch.
So I created a booklet that MEC published
that had information about the game, about the model,
about the research, a bibliography of books
and so forth that you could bring to the classroom.
And that was, we did that at MECC for all of the applications that we created,
and that's what gave MECC a good reputation with teachers for being educationally sound.
So, for about five years, the Oregon Trail was the most run program
on the Minnesota statewide educational system, like by a long shot.
We used to go into the airtight room where the computer was
to look at the master console to see the number of times
each application had been run that day.
And so the best ones had been run two or 300 times,
but Oregon Trail had been run like 10,000 times.
So it was kind of becoming clear
that this was going to be a popular thing.
And after about five years, something interesting happened.
As you may recall, I don't know,
we were looking through a Radio Shack catalog one day,
and we found that this company was selling computers.
Computers you could buy for less than $1,000
and put in your home.
So personal computers were coming to the marketplace.
And we realized at MEC that that was
going to cause a big change, that schools were really
going to want to buy these kinds of computers
and actually own their computing power,
not, in effect, rent it from a big system.
And so we set up a team who took the best applications from that mainframe system
and recoded them to work on the Apple II and then beyond that other brands that survived the shakeout of the market.
And as a matter of fact, that led to, in 1985, the release of a new and improved version
for the Apple of the Oregon Trail, which is displayed in the little image up there.
This may well be the one you remember from school, the colored version, the one that
played those...
tinny songs on Apple's 2-bit sound card, but the one that introduced you to traveling the
Oregon Trail by computer.
And as the years went on, new versions were released and new technologies were dealt with.
And I put down at the bottom, just referencing that in the 90s,
MECC was purchased, like other educational software companies,
by larger.
Entities, corporate entities, who now found themselves
with educational content, but they didn't quite know
what to do with it.
And in the case of the company that ended up
with the Oregon Trail, they had someone create
an arcade type version for your tablet or phone.
But this was not designed with the actual historical
data in mind and so forth.
So.
If you have run into this version, it's a different kind of game, not the same thing
that we used to sell to schools.
So what made Oregon Trail so popular?
Well for one, for many kids,
in the 80s, this is the first computer they've ever seen, and this was a very popular thing
that many schools owned that could be used on that computer.
And so, you know, you always remember your first experience is best.
Also, I think because we gave the kids an environment
that they could control, or some of the time control,
that that was something they really liked.
They didn't like always going to the computer
and getting asked to do their arithmetic facts
or their spelling lists.
They wanted to be part of something
that they could influence.
And we put them right in the middle
of a first-person adventure.
And when I've talked to game people in the present,
I believe it's fair to say that often the point will be made
if you don't have a good story,
you're not going to have the best game you can have.
The story is really a key component.
And here we gave kids a story to be a part of,
which was not very common back in the 80s.
And so what that means is it was very popular in the schools
in the US and a few other countries.
But that means that today, several decades later,
Oregon Trail is well remembered by people such as yourselves
that used it back then.
For example.
About a year ago, I got on Reddit,
and you may be familiar with their Ask Me Anything feature.
So I introduced myself and co-inventor
of the original Oregon Trail, Ask Me Anything.
Well, in a period of about six hours,
while I stayed at the computer, I got over 2,000 comments.
And these comments were, they were mostly positive.
except for the losers who couldn't get to Oregon because they didn't figure out the strategy.
But most, the most memorable thing to me is that there were more than a few comments that
said I really enjoyed the Oregon Trail.
Of all the things we did in school with the computer, the Oregon Trail is the one I learned
the most from.
And of course, that was the purpose from the very beginning.
I don't know if you watch network TV, but there's a great sitcom on, you might check
out on Wednesday evenings called The Goldbergs.
The Goldbergs is a kind of a wacky family in the 1980s.
The young son, the youngest of the two boys, is a computer nerd, and they often show him
at his Apple II, and in a couple of segments.
the camera swings around to show the screen,
and what do you think is there but the Oregon Trail?
So we're kind of a part of the culture.
Perhaps you're familiar with a tribute version
to the Oregon Trail.
And this is not a typo in the image there.
This is the Oregon Trail, which you may have heard of.
It's similar to the Oregon Trail in that it involves a trip across the country.
However, you take this trip in a car.
And the setting is an apocalyptic US
that's been destroyed a lot.
And your biggest hurdle that you have to get by
is all of the zombies that are running around the landscape
looking for your brains.
I met the young men who make this game.
They're sane.
And to my knowledge, this has been kind of a popular thing.
I mean, they just launched it with a little bit of funding.
But I think a lot of people have played it.
And perhaps most important to me is
that we're in the Hall of Fame.
The Strong National Museum of Play in Rochester, New York
is a place that catalogs and displays all the stuff
that kids have ever had fun with.
It is an amazing place.
You must go there.
And a couple of years ago, the Strong
decided that they wanted to start emphasizing computer
games as part of that, fits in with play.
And to help emphasize that, they created the World Video Game
Hall of Fame.
So in 2015, they inducted six programs, of course,
the iconic Pac-Man, Tetris, World of Warcraft.
Last May, again, they do this every year,
and using their panel of experts and nominations
from the population at large,
they enshrined six more games, computer games,
and one of them was the Oregon Trail,
and proud to say it's the only one of the 12
in there so far that was created
with an educational purpose in mind.
I'm sure more will follow.
I got to be there at the little ceremony that they held, and it is really a special time.
All right.
When we invented the Oregon Trail game, we had no guidance.
We had no examples.
Nobody had written books on how to create effective educational games.
There were no university courses in this.
There were no consultants to consult.
And so all we really had was our instincts as teachers,
as future teachers.
And fortunately, it appears that we got a lot of stuff right
that today you would know from all of your background
and experience are the right things to do with a game.
So just to quickly sum that up.
We gave the player a degree of control.
It wasn't all random.
We put the player in the middle of a story that would engage him or her.
It was a very simple game to use, but there was a very sophisticated model underneath.
The resources were balanced well with the obstacles.
If you give kids something to do on the computer that's too hard, they'll give up.
And if it's too easy, they'll get bored.
So you have to have just the right balance so that it continues to be a challenge and
they come back time and time again.
When we talk about an educational game,
I like to point out that the game becomes much more valuable
and much more successful
if you have multiple layers of learning.
So just to give my examples, what do kids learn from the Oregon Trail?
Well, one thing they learn, it's a game.
And so you learn a strategy by playing the game and replaying the game.
It's a thought process.
Interestingly enough, this actually is another reflection
of what actually happened historically.
When the first settlers took the trail,
those that survived, when they got to the West,
wrote back to the family in the East,
you know, Pony Express or however they got a letter
back there, and they said,
if you're going to come and join us out here,
here's what you need to do because we know
from being in the first wave.
Here's the clothing, here's the cash, here's the thinking about the food, and so forth.
So the more that people made the trip, the more information was built up that would help them be successful.
The mortality rate started to come down.
So that is a reflection, I think, of what happens when you play a game.
And it's the kind of thing that keeps kids interested in it.
You learn about topics.
You learn something about history.
You learn about geography.
You learn about resource management.
These are things that can be matched to the standards
that schools are now being held to in their programs.
And then there's another thing that I experienced
watching kids play this game in the early days
when, because of the teletype shortage,
you had to play as a group.
that there were things that happened in that group activity
that were very interesting.
Kids figured out pretty quickly that there
were going to be lots of decisions that they had
to make in playing this game.
And so how do 10-year-olds, 8-year-olds make decisions
when they have a group?
They yell at each other.
I want it my way, I want it my way.
Well, the kids that I saw playing this game
eventually looked up at the clock in the classroom
and realized if they didn't get this
to be a more organized process,
they were gonna run out of time.
They'd never find out if they got to Oregon.
So what did they do?
They invented democracy.
They invented taking votes.
Forget the hanging chads.
They took votes.
And so they realized that if they
had one person designated to run the voting,
they could take a vote.
Majority rules, that's what we're going to do.
We'll get to Oregon in time.
Another thing they invented, which to me harks back
to Henry Ford about a century ago, is division of labor.
So in the early Ford plant.
You know, one person made the wheels,
and one person made the transmission,
and one person made the seats,
and then they put them all together.
They were very efficient at making cars.
So the kids realized there's lots of stuff to do
when you're playing the game,
and everyone was trying to keep track of everything
until they decided, okay, first of all,
the best typist in our group
needs to be the one sitting at the teletype.
so that they don't do typos and we don't miss out on our hunting.
Someone else watched the map.
Someone else watched the budget.
Somebody else kept track of the voting.
This was all done in the minds of these kids.
And to me is a level of learning that in some respects transcends just picking up content and strategy suggestions.
So if you're making games for the education market, the more levels of learning you can put in there, the more successful the product can be.
And finally, I'm a big fan of collaborative design efforts.
I've always thought that if we had put 10 computer programmers
in a room and said, make a game about history,
we never would have gotten the Oregon Trail.
If we'd put 10 historians in a room and said,
make a computer game, we never would
have gotten the Oregon Trail.
But we had a.
Two math guys, one of whom was well into computers,
and one history guy, and that collection of backgrounds
brought forth all the questions, all the new ideas,
all the suggestions that made Oregon Trail successful.
So if you're forming a team to make a game,
make sure you've got diversity on that team.
Speaking of team, here they are,
25 years after the invention of the game,
which was about 45 years ago.
That is myself, Bill Heinemann, Paul Dillenberger,
Bill holding one of these sacred scrolls
that was printed off the teletype.
I found out recently that he still has that scroll
and that at one point his son asked him,
Dad, because I realize how valuable this thing is,
would it be okay if I took over the sacred scroll?
To which Bill replied, no.
So, anyway, a great pair of colleagues to have gone through this.
And the Oregon Trail, of course, has stuck with us now for over four decades, which kind
of means that for all the learning that people got out of the Oregon Trail about
history, I learned some things about life from the Oregon Trail, from the Oregon Trail
game, and some of these things may apply to your own efforts in creating games.
So let's just say, plan ahead.
There's danger out there.
Be patient.
The journey is long.
If you persevere, you'll find your green valley.
even if the water's deep, sometimes you just have to cock your wagon and head out from shore.
Thank you very much, everybody. Appreciate it.
We do have a few minutes and we can take some questions and I believe there are microphones
in the aisles that could be used if anyone has a question that they're willing to say
publicly.
Hi.
What was, right here, what was the most surprising thing to you with the kind of explosion of
popularity from Oregon Trail?
Well, I guess I kind of struggle with that because
I had nothing to compare it to.
I was happy to see that people liked the game,
and the fact that schools started ultimately purchasing
the game from MEC in its Apple versions and so forth.
It just seemed like kind of a natural thing,
but I will say that if something surprising might be
that at the time that MEC was bought by an investment group
to take it over. Oregon Trail, I think, accounted for about one-third of MECC's annual revenues.
So the MECC group over the years developed about 250 to 300 products, and this one product was
bringing in a third of the money. Wow. Thank you. Yeah, you're welcome. Yes, sir. Amazing talk.
I just wanted to say thank you for the experience of asking my teacher what Dysentery was in
the following explanation.
If I may clarify, Dysentery was not brought up in version 1.0.
That was the Apple version where the team added it.
Yes?
Thank you for the fascinating peek into history.
What are some educational games from modern times that you think are doing it right and
why?
I'm sorry, I'm getting a kind of an echo, so...
I'll yell, is that better?
Well, let's see.
First of all, I may not be as up-to-date as necessary.
But one thing that I'm fascinated with
is that perhaps the most popular educational game today is,
OK, I'm drawing a blank.
What's the one that looks like you're
digging through all the bricks and making?
Minecraft.
Minecraft, thank you.
Sorry.
I've seen notices on the internet where you can buy curriculum guides for the use of Minecraft
and suggestions for activities in the classroom that you can do with Minecraft.
So that's been kind of surprising.
But my sense is that if there was a golden age of educational software in terms of making
programs that were deliberately teaching a particular part in the curriculum, I think
that that was a little bit in the past.
And that since then, there's been a lot more use of the internet by schools
and various tools that help kids be creative and make their own videos,
their own productions, their own science experiments, and so on.
So a particular game doesn't come to mind for me,
but those are some of the things that are going on.
Thank you.
Kind of as a follow-up question, with modern technology, how would you design OrdinChild
today?
Okay, come forward.
I'm sorry, I'm getting the...
With modern technology, how would you design OrdinChild today?
Oh, okay.
Well, the first thing we need is virtual reality.
But you know, but I have another answer to that question.
It's not really related to the technology,
but if we were going to create something like Oregon Trail
today, I would create the Native American version.
What was it like to be on the other side of, you know,
the other side of the wall, so to speak?
That would be kind of fascinating,
especially if they could.
somehow communicate with each other.
I'll bring up one other thing,
and maybe this would be,
today's technology would make it easier.
MEC experimented at one point
with a version of Oregon Trail
that was a networked version,
so that you could have multiple travelers,
and that the decisions they made would affect each other.
And that was not an easy thing to pull off
in the technology of the 80s,
but maybe today it could be done a lot better,
and that would be kind of interesting
to be in a wagon train with people you don't know, maybe,
and to see what kind of social dynamics
would come out of that.
You're very welcome.
I'm from Minnesota and I played Farming Trail,
Old L.A., Number Munchers, all these games,
and somehow I never knew that they were made in Minnesota.
That there was any kind of computing stuff going on there.
I'm really interested to hear about what MET was like.
Specifically, was the fact that it was a state-run,
publicly-owned corporation,
did that make it easier to experiment with educational software
versus maybe a profit-oriented...
Okay, let's see, there were a number of questions there.
But the first thing that I might say is,
you know, why people say,
well, why did this happen in Minnesota?
And the thing that perhaps people are not so aware of
is that before Silicon Valley,
there was a Silicon Valley in Minnesota.
That during the 60s and 70s,
companies like IBM, Univac, Honeywell, Control Data,
and boroughs, some I can't remember,
either had their national headquarters in the Twin Cities
or they had large installations there.
And so Minnesota was kind of the computing capital
of the country right up until the day that, you know,
WSNIAC developed something
that didn't require a big room to put it in.
So it's kind of logical that it would have grown up there.
Now let's see, what was another aspect?
Oh, what was MEC like?
Yeah, well MEC's the only place I've ever worked that I would have paid them.
Because, I mean, in addition to working with a crew of incredible educators, you know,
former teachers who came to do this.
there just was a spirit and a camaraderie there.
And what was so exciting about it was
we were inventing something that hadn't been invented before.
We were the first wave of people
that worked in the educational computing business,
quote unquote.
So it's an experience that most people who worked at MECC
would say they will never forget.
Okay, it's a little after six.
Thank you so much for coming.
I'll stick around if you want to talk.