Welcome to Surviving Vampire Survivors Agile Community Management.
My name is Beth Molloy, and I'm the community manager at Pongal.
I live near Essex in England, and I studied business and finance at college
before having roles in customer service and sales.
And I also ran my own children's party entertainment company.
This is my first role in the games industry, and I started in February of 2022.
I love roller skating, theme parks, playing cozy games,
and I have two cats called Mango and Mochi.
So, I work for a company called Ponkel,
which is based in London in the UK,
and we all work remotely.
It was founded in April of 2022 by Luca Galante,
who is the creator of Vampire Survivors.
We are now a team of 14.
We've grown very quickly over the year.
And you may notice that Ponkel has a lowercase p
in the logo.
And this was Luca's.
He made the decision to do this and he thought it would serve him, serve as a reminder to stay small and humble no matter what.
Which is very relevant considering the success of Vampire Survivors so far.
Just a little background on the community and marketing team.
In February, it was just me and also Luca.
And then in April, we were joined by Future Friends Games,
who are a marketing company.
In August, we hired another community manager and player
support person.
And then in December, we hired a marketing manager.
So in case you haven't heard of Vampire Survivors, Vampire Survivors is a time survival roguelite
game and it has really simple controls.
All you have to do is go around and slay hordes of monsters with one control.
It's inspired by many of Lucas' favorite games and it also has lots of Italian references
and play on words.
So unless you're Italian you probably won't get half of the references but it helps to
make the game really unique.
It's currently on Steam, mobile, Xbox console, PC, and it's on Game Pass.
And we wanted to keep it a really low and fair price.
Um, cause when it first went onto Steam, it was a really small game and there
wasn't much content, so it was a low price.
And since then we've added a lot of content to it, but we've
still kept it a fair price.
And you can get hundreds of hours out of the game.
We love to exceed player expectations.
So today I want to cover a few different topics.
Firstly, how I caught up with our game's existing community,
how I found the voice for vampire survivors on socials,
benefits of early access, and also some challenges as well.
The opportunities and projects of varying success
that we've had, how I increased the reach and engagement,
and how I learned my role and the games industry.
So to start off with, just want to give you a quick timeline of the last year.
So on the 17th of December, 2021, Vampire Survivors launched in early access on Steam.
By the 3rd of January, it was picked up by streamers such as Gorgorra, Splattercat, and Northern Lion,
which really helped to boost the game's popularity and make it go viral.
In January...
Like, from January to April, Luka hired some of his friends to help with the development of Vampire Survivors
because he couldn't do it all on his own.
It went a bit crazy, so he was getting help with the development, fixing bugs,
and also the community side of things.
By April, Ponker was set up officially,
and we started hiring a team.
In May, Vampire Survivors was launched on Xbox Game Pass PC.
And between May and September, we did a lot of content updates.
So we kept publishing new content for the players
and adding new achievements.
And players loved to chase all the achievements.
So, before 1.0, we did a little road to 1.0.
So we did a teaser every day for about two and a half weeks,
I believe.
And that helped to just spread the word of the game.
And it was just our big marketing push for 1.0.
On the 10th of November, Vampire Survivors
launched on Xbox console.
And between the 10th of November and the 8th of December,
the dev team had to start from scratch the mobile version.
And we shadow dropped the trailer for the mobile version
at the Game Awards on the 8th of December.
So it was a very quick turnaround.
Then to finish off the year, we launched our first DLC,
which was Legacy of the Moonspell.
So keeping up with the fast-growing community.
The first thing I did was I had to go and grab all the handles that I wanted on social
media and buy the domains, set everything up, and not only did I set up all the domains,
all the handles on the social medias I wanted to do immediately, I got all of them, just
to make sure we had them for the future.
I then prioritized which ones I thought our audience would be on, so I chose Twitter,
and we already had an existing Discord, so I continued to grow that.
I spent a lot of time on them and made sure I did them properly before we hired new people
and then we could add new socials, so we started doing TikTok.
I wanted to make sure that I wasn't just selling to our community, and I did a lot
of fun and entertaining posts.
We welcome everyone in our community and we like to keep it safe and regulated, so Discord
is our main place for our fans, like all our...
We have community helpers on there so they make sure that the discord is run well and everyone's welcome and listened to.
We also have bots on there too to help filter out some of the negative things.
We make sure we listen to all the feedback that our community has.
comes up with. And we don't ignore negative feedback. We don't just respond to all the
positive feedback. So far we haven't really done any advertising on social media, paid advertising.
It's all been through word of mouth, which is really great. We have a lot of
content creators who like to share vampire survivors.
I like to encourage engagement by doing calls to action,
by doing polls and asking the players
about their favorite things.
So asking them how many achievements they've got,
what their favorite weapon is.
It really helps that the game is consistently updated as well.
At one point, I think we were doing patches every two weeks.
So there was always a lot to post about,
and it made my job a lot easier.
And to make sure we're reaching new audiences, I always check the analytics.
So I've seen from our YouTube that our main player base is males in America, age 25 to 40.
So I need to make my posts apply to them and also try and expand and reach new people.
So did it work?
Let's have a look at the stats.
So as you can see here, in February 2022,
we had 11,000 Discord members and we now have 58,000.
We had 14,000, 14.5,000 Steam reviews
and we now have 178,000.
They are mostly overwhelmingly positive.
So that's amazing.
Our Steam announcements now reach 50 times more people
than they did to start off with.
And our game is the second most reviewed on Steam.
We have now got over 3 million mobile players,
which is great considering it was not launched very long ago.
So that's doing really well.
We're really pleased with that.
And also, we were the top played Steam Deck game
for five months from July.
Finding our voice in socials.
So when I started at Ponkel, I didn't really have a clue what I was doing.
Um, to be honest, I didn't know how to use Twitter properly.
I didn't know how to use discord.
So I had to learn those and work out the best way to use each of those platforms.
I made sure I varied the content that I was posting, um, such as game updates
and polls, um, any, yeah, any bug fixes and all of that kind of thing, um, just
to reach all different people.
And over my time posting over the last year,
I've really worked out what does well
and what doesn't do so well for our posts.
So things that get high engagement
are anything such as big game updates
and interacting with the players
and asking them for their feedback
and what they're enjoying the most
and how many achievements they've got,
if they've 100%ed the game or not.
And the low engagement posts are anything such as
Fan art, unfortunately, and just smaller game updates,
little patches.
I like to try and jump on trends,
but I'm very selective about what trends we jump on.
It's great for visibility and reaching new audiences,
but you want to make sure that you don't
jump on every single trend.
Just choose the ones that fit your brand the best.
I try and use the trending hashtags as well,
just to get you.
to reach new audiences and get better visibility for our posts.
In summary, you've got to be agile.
Study what works and make sure you're looking at your analytics.
For example, for Vampire Survivors, I realized that the players really love Garlic, Flaw
Chicken and our character Poe Racho, who is a stinky old man.
And any post about them, just, they love it.
They love to share it and yeah, it's really fun.
Consistency and timing is really important.
So as I mentioned before, we did the teasers
leading up to the 1.0 launch,
where we posted every single day.
I realized that 4 p.m. is a really good time
for us to post, as we reach people in the UK
and in America, so it gets better visibility.
Once I discovered what kind of tone of voice worked with our audience and the kind of branding
for Pongal and Vampire Survivors, it was a really big turning point for me.
Because to start off with, as I said I wasn't that experienced, I thought I had to be really
serious on social and just post about game updates and bugs and keep it really serious.
But as soon as I started relaxing and
writing more friendly posts like the one you see there, just a bit more fun.
They started doing a lot better and they're a lot more shareable and got a lot better engagement.
It was important for me to pay attention to the player likes and dislikes as mentioned before,
so they really like garlic and floor chicken, whereas things like the character reskins,
all that kind of stuff doesn't really do as well.
If you're hiring a community manager, it's really important to trust them.
Give them space to experiment with different types of posts, to jump on trends,
and also to kind of create their own guidelines.
So, what I mean by this is...
Like they've got to look after their own mental health.
So not responding to really negative hate comments
and all of that is, it makes a big difference,
like if you don't make them respond to those.
So personally, I just ignore those
and also set boundaries such as people,
when you get messages asking constantly for new platforms,
it's a lot of work to respond to all of those.
And yeah, personally I ignore those
because I don't want to say the wrong thing
and give people the wrong impression.
So I find that one of the things that Pongal does best is acknowledge players.
In our Discord we get a lot of feedback and we're always making sure that our players
know that they're listened to.
So we respond to all types of feedback, positive, negative, and any bug reports.
This screenshot here shows a tweet that I received one morning and it...
was basically saying that when you load the game, the file name shows up and that has
the person's actual name in it.
So this showed up on the loading screen of the game.
And it's obviously a big problem for VTubers.
They don't want their name out there.
So when I saw this report, I told the devs straight away.
And they managed to turn it around within about an hour.
Like, they literally fixed it, pushed the patch,
and I responded to this person in an hour.
They were really impressed.
And it just helps to show you that you're listening
and that you actually care about, yeah,
the impact your game has.
So, to summarize our social media, we focus on Discord, Twitter and TikTok.
But it's really important to delegate.
I don't do all of these on my own.
And one social media person, one social media manager can't do everything.
So you've got to make sure you prioritize everything.
So Discord is where all of our VIPs are.
It's our most dedicated player base.
They get game updates first and they also get access to the beta versions.
They, it's a great place for everyone to report bugs and give suggestions
and share challenges that they have.
And it's quite independent now.
When I first started, I spent a lot of time on discord.
I think when at the very beginning, I was reading every single message we were
getting, which was just not working.
Um, but yeah, with bots and also really good community helpers.
Um, it's quite independent now.
Twitter is a really good place for creators and press,
for us to interact with them.
And we also do a lot of giveaways and polls on Twitter.
So we've given away a Steam Deck
and we give away like game keys,
just lots of things to increase engagement.
And it's a great place for trends as well
because it's fast turnaround.
I mainly run the Twitter
and I try to post daily on there now.
Since I started posting daily, it's grown a lot.
TikTok is the other one that we focus on.
And this is really good for us, because since we launched on mobile,
there's obviously a player base there.
It's a younger demographic, and we make really silly, unhinged TikToks.
and try and make the most of memes and trending sounds.
We post every few days, like every two to three days on there.
And this is run by Lucy, who's our other community manager, and also future friends.
Releasing in early access.
There's many benefits to releasing in Early Access.
One of the main ones is you can involve your players
with a development from a really early stage.
So you can listen to their feedback and their suggestions,
and they will help you make your game better,
if you listen to the right ones.
Um, yeah, you can, as I said, you can receive and implement that feedback.
Early on, I made a Trello board, which was a public issue tracker, and we had a
lot of the most common bugs and issues on there and the players could go on there
and see what the progress was with those, whether we were like fixing them or
whether they were fixed yet, which really helped and that helped to prevent a lot
of repeated questions as well, especially in the Discord.
It helps you to build a really strong community and create brand advocates.
And it also helps you to develop your brand image if you're a new company.
So for Ponko, I believe that we're quite quirky, grounded and responsive company.
And making sure you listen to your players creates a lot of goodwill.
Like I feel like they trust us and they know that we're going to
listen to what they have to say.
There's also many challenges of early access, such as constant changes with the game, which
means I was making a lot of content last minute.
It's difficult to schedule, because timelines are constantly changing, and for an overnight
success game like Vampire Survivors...
It's, I don't know, it was really hard to create systems on the go.
So at the moment we have Notion, Trello, Hack and Plan.
We have loads, loads of things going on.
We still haven't worked that out, but we'll get there.
But yeah, trying to stay organized is tough when you have a really fast
growing company and you have no idea what you're going to be doing the next day.
Opportunities and projects are varying success.
So in my first week at Pwncool, I was approached by Discord and they wanted
us to do a French speaking Discord server.
We thought this sounded like a great idea,
and also they had the promise of trialing a Japanese server next.
So, we have a big player base in Japan,
so we thought, okay, that's great, we'll try the French one first and see how it goes.
It was a really good idea, and I believe it would have been really successful, but...
We did know that we didn't have that many French-speaking players,
so it might not go too well.
We spent a lot of time and energy on it,
and as expected, it didn't really pick up.
So I would just say there's a lot of really good opportunities out there,
but just be selective about what you go for,
because you don't have to say yes to everything.
Pick and choose the opportunities that sound best to you.
We shadow dropped the soundtrack during the teasers to 1.0.
And this sounded like a good idea at the time,
but I feel like if we had to put a big marketing push
behind it and done it as its own thing,
instead of just one teaser,
it would have gotten a lot better.
So shadow drops can be really good,
but it has to be the right timing and the right product.
And you want to make the most of something big,
like a soundtrack.
Finally, making merch boxes for 1.0.
As you can see here on the screen,
this is Lyric opening up his merch box on his live stream.
So we wanted to do merch boxes for 1.0,
just to thank creators that had helped
push the game and play it.
And we did look from a merch company for probably two
or three months.
We were on a really tight timeline.
And in my...
Like personally I thought, okay, I could probably do this because it's a really
tight turnaround and I could put some things together in a box and send them out.
Um,
We looked for a merch company, but we weren't really successful
because everyone thought it was way too tight of a timeline.
So I ended up doing it myself anyway.
And it went really well, but it was very stressful
because we had a lot less time than I could have had.
So I would just say, evaluate the situation.
Look at the facts and the timelines,
and just make sure that.
I don't know, just consider all the options.
I probably should have done it myself in the first place,
and it would have been a lot less stressful.
So increasing reach and engagement.
There are many things that you can do to increase reach and engagement, and some of them can
be controlled and some of them can't.
So one of the things that you can control is doing giveaways.
So on Twitter, as I mentioned, we did Steam Key giveaways, and we've also done a Steam
deck to celebrate 1.0.
You can also do press releases.
Future Friends started helping us with press releases in July
and it helped to create a lot more articles
from the press, of course,
which really helped push the game
and advertise the new patches.
Live streams is also another big thing.
So, as you can see here, this is Ellie Joy Panek
and she did a live stream for us
on our Steam page on launch day.
It went really well, and it just helps to expand your audience,
that you're going to show all of your,
you're going to show off your game to all of their audience.
It was really hard to see the exact impact of this
because we did a lot of, we did a big marketing push for 1.0.
However, we do see a lot of people still in our Discord coming to us saying that they
saw Vampire Survivors on Ellie or Lyric's stream.
So it did make an impact, it's just hard to quantify it.
And also doing in real life events, such as EGX and WASD in London.
We've done both of these events so far, and it's really nice to meet players and just
connect with people in real life.
So there are some things that are out of our control as well.
We're really lucky with Vampire Survivors
that it took off in the way it did.
So we were nominated for some awards and we won a couple.
So being in the award shows
has created a lot of exposure for us.
And also we entered the Steam Awards.
So I believe anyone can enter the Steam Awards.
And when people vote for you,
they're encouraged to leave a review.
So just entering that.
We got a lot of reviews, so that was really good for us.
I think at one point we were getting more reviews than Elden Ring for a few days.
So that was really cool.
It doesn't hurt to reach out to platforms.
So if you're working with Xbox or Steam, if you just contact them and ask them their requirements
for what they need in order to retweet your post or anything like that, because they'll
have requirements that they need to meet, then you can make sure you're doing that and
there's a lot more chance that they will help you out and work with you and retweet.
Also, working with creators and companies,
it's really good to work with these.
And you could just ask to collab,
like we asked to collab with Lyric and Ellie.
And the worst thing they can say is no,
so you might as well give it a go.
Learning and growing into my role and into the games
industry.
So, as I said, I'm really new to the games industry,
and also to this role of being a community manager.
So, over the last year, whilst I've been working on Vampire Survivors,
I've had to learn a lot of new skills.
I did this by watching videos and doing courses,
and also attending talks at industry events such as DEVELOP in Brighton last year.
I've been trying to familiarize myself with the industry
by watching showcases and award shows,
such as the Streamr Awards and BAFTA,
and spending a lot of time on Twitter and LinkedIn
to just learn about the people and the companies that are around,
and also about different content creators,
so we know who to work with.
It's really important to stay up to date with...
The algorithms and just news around socials.
So signing up to newsletters has really helped me.
There's Victoria Trans Community Dev Newsletter.
And also there's a TikTok Gaming Newsletter that you can get
and that will help you with all the trending sounds.
And also just watching YouTube videos.
Of course, talking to people.
There's Discord groups that you can join.
I'm in some for indie games.
I'm also in some community manager Discords as well.
Yeah, just spending time on Twitter and meeting up with people in real life, like we're doing now.
And also online gatherings.
Finally, there's podcasts.
So I listen to one called She Plays Games.
That one's really helpful because it's a lot of different women in the gaming industry talking about their roles and their experiences.
So, last year I did Safe in Our World,
which is a mental health training course.
That was really important for me to learn about the impact of community management
for my own mental health, and also to help our players,
so in our Discord.
I also did Limit Break UK, which is a mentorship program, and I was really lucky to get two
mentors who have helped guide me and give me advice throughout the last year.
And also I've just been trying to play more games instead of just spending nearly 400
hours on Animal Crossing.
Um, so yeah, how have I built my confidence and learned to
question processes along the way?
There's been a lot of trial and error over the last year, um,
with all the different posts.
So yeah, just seeing what works and what doesn't, um, when you
find something that works, obviously gives you more confidence to
keep going and try that again.
Um, and yeah, just more knowledge about the industry has given me a
lot more confidence as well.
It helps me make better informed suggestions and decisions in my job.
And it also helps to improve my, like, it helps that I improved my organization.
So the more I learn and the better processes that I made, like using
Notion and everything, I streamlined everything a lot more.
So that helped to free up more time to start new projects.
So yeah, I just want to summarize my talk for you quickly.
So I've learned how important community management is
for growing, nurturing, and entertaining your community.
How a strong tone of voice and branding
will help build your image, your company, and your game.
How being consistent, willing to listen,
reliable, and authentic as a company goes a really long way.
How early...
You can get a lot of player feedback and build your company image and values.
And also that you don't have to say yes to everything.
Not everything will go to plan, but you can always learn from it.
Also that it's really important to keep learning, making connections and developing your skills.
Community management is crucial for your game's success and is definitely worth investing in.
That was Vampire Survivors Agile Community Management.
Thank you for listening. You've been fantastic. Terrible.