Hello, I am Toya Kristen Finley from Schneudel Media LLC,
and this is It's Not in the Writer's Manual.
And this is a crowdsourced panel.
So the content is based upon the questions
that you would like to bring to us.
And I would like to start by everybody
giving a brief introduction of who they are
and how they actually got into game writing.
So I'm Chris Avalone. I got into gaming about 25 years ago because I was a pen and paper D&D game master
because my players were really lazy so I had to make all the stories.
And then I tried to publish those stories and eventually on the 30th submission I got accepted
and then I turned that into an exciting career in game development
because I could prove to somebody that someone would pay something for something that I wrote.
I'm Heidi McDonald. I broke into the gaming industry when I was 41 years old. I was the
oldest intern that Jesse Schell ever hired. The movie The Internship, I didn't have to
watch it because I lived it. My first project with them was an HIV prevention game and if
you want to be thrown into the deep end, try making HIV prevention fun.
I'm very proud of the fact that Orion Trail, our game, just got tagged for Narrative Excellence
by the IGF this year, so that was my big happy for this year.
So, welcome.
Thank you.
I'm Evan Skolnick and I've been in games for about 15 years.
I kind of side slipped into games after having worked in comics at Marvel Comics and other
companies and working in interactive development on CD-ROMs and websites and then eventually
just sliding over to game development, first as a producer and then helping out occasionally
with narrative because of my background and then bit by bit doing more and more narrative
and less and less producing which makes me very happy.
Hi, I'm Michelle Clough. I'll be playing the plucky newbie of the panel because I've actually only been in game
narrative design and writing for I guess maybe two or three years.
I got into it by actually meeting these wonderful lovely people and then getting me in touch with
my first client, which was a visual novel game called
1931 Scheherazade in the Library of Pergamon.
I've also been doing a little bit of the lecturing circuit. Some of you may
remember two years ago I did a talk about male sexuality in games
as well as how to write a healthy, diverse fan service.
And I'm also head of the Romance and Sexuality Special Interest Group for IGDA.
Alright, at the other end of the panel we have the other grizzled ancient of the industry here.
I am that terrible person who is, first and foremost, was a game designer and programmer,
and then was like, I can wrap this stuff too, watch me go.
which usually is the nightmare of most writers and designers.
But I was lucky in college.
I knew a couple of other college students
who had dropped out and started a little game company.
And I went and offered to intern for them.
And they gave me some programming work to do.
And then I noticed they had a game
they weren't going to finish.
And I said, hey, I could finish that thing.
And so eventually, I finished it,
and they let me take it and go publish it somewhere else.
And that company was Bungie Software way back
when they were two guys in their basement.
So that was a great introduction to the industry for me
and game development in general.
And I've always tried to do writing as well as game design
when I've worked on projects.
And a few times, I've done only writing
and then realized how little respect writers
get in the industry and went back to game design jobs.
But now I am running an independent project
where I'm doing.
design writing and programming again,
called The Church in the Darkness,
which is gonna be done in maybe a year, if we're lucky.
So I've been writing and publishing for many years, and about eight years ago, I wondered,
uh, how do you get into game writing? Because I like games and I like writing, and I wonder if I
could do that. So I actually did a Google search for game writing, which usually does not bring up
anything, but in this case, uh, the same indie studio that Michelle started with was looking
for lore writers.
So I started as a lore writer, they liked what I was doing,
they made me an assistant designer,
and at this point in time, I discovered
that game design was a thing.
So that was my start, and I've worked on probably
about 10 projects now, PC, mobile, Facebook,
and probably three or four of them have actually come out,
and the rest you will never ever see,
but such is the game industry.
So with that, let's start with questions.
Please just feel free to come up.
We'll try to get to as many as possible.
Is this thing on?
So as people try to break into the industry,
sometimes it's hard to know what kind of samples
to send when you're asked for them.
So what kind of samples pool should we be working towards?
Mostly in terms of form.
Twine, short stories, screenplay format, stuff like that.
when we do work in screenplay with these writing samples,
is it better to follow the sort of animation screenwriting
where you explain more than writing for live action,
things like that?
Well, first off, I'd probably choose, when you're applying to a company, I would probably
study what type of games they make first.
If they actually have a game editor or a narrative tool set involved with their game design,
open that up, figure out what format actually that tool set uses for the narrative delivery.
And if you're actually going to include writing samples,
just tailor it for the type of game
that those publishers usually make.
So for example, if you're applying to Bethesda,
I mean, study Skyrim, study Fallout 4,
see what the dialogue mechanic flow is for that,
and then just tailor your submission accordingly.
You shouldn't have to explain too much
if you're following their general format.
And sometimes over-explaining can actually
hurt your case a little bit.
But that's just one piece of advice.
I got a really, really good piece of advice from a friend of mine who writes for BioWare
once.
Her advice was to take a scene that has high impact in a game made by the company you want
to apply for.
So let's just say, you know, that you were going to apply for BioWare.
So you take your favorite scene in Mass Effect and you dissect it, dialogue line by dialogue line.
It's going to take you a long time to have to go through all of those different times
and find out all the different responses and where they lead.
And you put a big string of sticky notes on your wall and you see what the structure is
and how the mood plays out and how the dialogue plays out over the structure of that scene
and then just adapt what you're doing to the general structure that you already saw that they used.
I think, I guess it depends heavily on, you know, are we talking about samples for, you know, actually applying for a specific position, in which case I definitely second Chris's point of view, or whether this is stuff that we're doing.
for a portfolio website and I think there, you know, having a diversity is really handy.
Having said that, I got sort of my second big gig when I had nothing on there but like a couple
Twine games and an RPG Maker game and promised to myself that when I had time I was going to sit
down and write some combat barks and the next thing I know I get this email through the website
being like, hey we're looking for game writers, you know, and I'm like, okay, I'm one, I can do that.
The other thing is I'm coming from the freelance end, so a lot of times you have non-developers.
They're new to the industry or they realize that they want to get their message out through
a video game, and so they're not going to know to ask you for samples necessarily.
And so in that case, I pick a few choice samples that show like character design, dialogue.
world building, so I give them kind of a general overview, and then I send that along and say,
is there something that you need specifically? And so that will give you direction as far as
genre, tone, setting goes. So if they don't tell you, send something anyway, because you are more
likely to get a response if you send samples, and if you don't, you may not.
I think somewhere in there you mentioned short story.
I would steer you away from short story or prose in general.
If you have other samples you can show that you're writing for a visual medium because
in nine out of ten cases or more you'll be writing for visuals and not more internal
focus of prose.
So a chapter from a novel you've written or a short story might not be the best choice.
I mean if that's all you've got, we can still, when you do see one of those samples, you
look at them and you can quickly tell within a few paragraphs.
what kind of chops the person might have,
but it's not the kind of writing you generally do in games,
so it's not as applicable as a screenplay format,
for example.
And in general, I agree with what everybody said.
I do like to see if someone does a custom sample for, say,
fancy Studio X you're probably applying for, that's great.
I always looked for another thing, too,
to make sure that wasn't the only thing they had
in their one-trick pony or something.
But I agree that the other thing to think about
is that the people reviewing these
are probably reviewing a lot of them.
So you want to have less is more, like just two or three things, like the custom piece
and a piece of your own.
And you want some of your own personality to come across in like that custom piece probably.
So you can show, I can do work that fits with you, I can do my own stuff too, but it should
be short.
It should be like, I can read it in 10 minutes or something like that.
I echo what Richard's saying,
like sometimes we get like 20 page dialogue submissions
and that's, I don't, we don't need all that
to determine what quality of writing you have
or that you understand the structure of how a dialogue works
like, and again, like Richard's right,
like it just takes too long to read
like a super detailed submission,
just put your best foot forward
and just keep it brief and condensed
because that's also a good quality of a game writer too,
it's like you don't need to expound upon a certain subject.
Because you're going to have dialogue limits, right?
And you know, always.
When I was doing dialogue for Lionel Battle Train,
we had to take localization into account.
And so every single piece of dialogue
that we had in that entire game had
to be 110 characters long.
So we were kind of telling our story in little spurts
of 110 characters.
that will actually help you learning how to do things in a very succinct manner.
Hello. So I wouldn't claim to be a writer myself. I am a game developer, an indie game
developer, and my friend and I are in the early stages of planning out a narrative heavy
game, sort of choose your own adventure style experience. And...
We want to at least make a first attempt of writing it on our own, even though neither of us are writers per se.
And I know it's a lot of work and it's going to be really tough to make it something that people connect to.
I'm curious if you have any advice, resources for people trying to really do something that might be unique,
but need some basic concepts of how to write good dialogue.
And also...
If we do feel the need later on to bring a contractor in, a writer, a game writer, what's the best format for someone to come in later on, whether, you know, to look at a rough draft or something like that and try to punch it up, what would be the best ways to work with someone like that?
I know a bunch of people on this panel have written books. Why don't you guys, no, seriously, have written books about how to do this, so why don't you guys rattle off the title of your book?
Yes, so I wrote the game narrative toolbox with Tobias Hosner and LeMay and Jennifer Brandes Hepler
Which is all about narrative design just the writing of it
But also putting it into production with the entire team so you can find that on Amazon
My book is called Game Design Theory and Practice.
It has a chapter on writing and storytelling,
but it's more generally about game design in total
and the whole development process.
The book I wrote and came out last year
is called Video Game Storytelling.
and the first half is basically a distillation of the basics of Western storytelling structure
seen through the lens of game development. The second half is aimed at different roles on a team
and how you can apply these principles to development. But one thing you said concerns
me a little bit and it seems like you're associating writing with dialogue.
Like, we're going to make the whole game and the game story,
and then if we need, and we're going to write,
then do you have any tips on dialogue?
And dialogue is like the icing on the cake, right?
The question is, how good is the cake, right?
So you ask the question of when to bring in
or how to bring in a writer.
And if you're not confident about your abilities
to tell a story, and yet you're going to structure it,
and structure a choose-your-own-adventure story
game, story game, the earlier, the better is my answer.
Because if you bring a writer on just to write the dialogue,
then you've got a structure that isn't working.
then that writer, they will not be able to help you that much.
And that's a case, that happens to game writers a lot,
is they're brought in at the late stage just to write dialogue
to layer icing on a cake that was not properly baked, possibly.
And we can slap some icing on it, but in the end, you take a bite of it,
and it, you know, more like a stale Twinkie sometimes.
So, yeah, that's what it is.
So I would say the earlier the better if you're not confident in your abilities or at least
be able to backtrack and give the writer the ability to come back in and work on your structure as well as your dialogue.
To sort of briefly follow up on what Evan said,
like, there is a difference.
Because at that point, in a way, you
would be asking them, like, yes, as a game writer,
but also to a certain extent as a copy editor who may not
be able to make substantive changes.
So they might be like, yes, I can do this dialogue for you,
but here's this massive plot hole
that would require an extra six months of development to fix.
And the thing is, there are definitely game editors that are,
that is an actual discipline and is very worth looking into.
But if you want to really integrate it with the story
as early as possible, yeah, there's a difference
between game editing and narrative design.
And as Evan says, earlier the better.
Also, you were talking about hiring a writer.
I would highly suggest doing your research on work
for hire law and looking up work for hire contracts.
Also, please, for the love of God and everybody in this room,
please look up professional rates for writers.
A lot of writers do not know what professional rates are.
And when you understand what the professional rates are
and you say, hey, I can actually pay you what you are worth
and what your job is worth, you will get good writers.
You will attract bad writers if you don't pay them well.
And I guess a final thing I just wanted to say, not to be too harsh I guess, but you say like,
oh we're not, you know, you're a programmer and maybe your friend's an artist or whatever,
and you're like, we're going to take on this narrative game, but we don't feel like you're writers,
why are you taking on a narrative game?
I mean, you should play to your own strengths first, you know, if it's like a first project
that you're venturing into or something like that, you should say, well what can we do,
what are we really good at, let's play with that.
and then maybe write a new book.
Or, but if you really want to do a writing game,
a narrative game, but neither of you feel good about it,
yeah, get someone immediately.
And it doesn't have to be, much as I agree,
get a professional if you can,
but if you're on a budget, look around the community
for someone else who wants to go in
as a partner with you or something
who can be that voice for narrative from day one.
Oh, just one thing, keep in mind
that you can do a lot with narrative without words.
you can have a very visual heavy game that has a lot of environmental narrative.
You would also need a narrative designer for that, but keep that in mind too.
Thank you very much. I appreciate it. I wanted to avoid a lot of those pitfalls
going into it, so thank you.
Hi.
This might be another buy my book question, but...
I am a very strong writer and I'm not a very strong game designer and I'm trying to become,
you know, like you said, a game designer that also writes well.
And I guess my question is how do you take it so that your writing is built around the
mechanic more or less?
Was that last thing you said?
How do you suggest that you take the mechanic of the game and, you know, use your writing
to supplement that as opposed to the other way around?
It's just a story slapped onto a game.
I kind of came at it from the same direction that you did.
I came into the industry as having been a writer and never done any game design before.
And so, you know, that's kind of where I was in the same place.
And what I did was I bought The Art of Game Design by Jesse Schell.
And I didn't just do that because the guy was signing my paychecks.
It really was the most accessible, conversational, entertaining book that I found on game design.
And I learned an awful lot from that.
And you start to look at the story from different angles when you've read that book.
And then when you're on the team that you're with and you're making this game,
you're going to be in a lot of meetings.
And during those meetings, they'll tell you what is and isn't possible.
You know, if you've got this bit of dialogue, you know, about a guy who's talking
about an ancient door that needs a key, but the artist is like, you know,
there's some wacky reason that it can't be a door, it's a gate.
You know, you just, you get that by talking to the other members of your team
and having some understanding of what their constraints are.
I'd agree with Heidi. Basically, what you'd want to do is sit down with the system designer or the gameplay programmers or whoever's actually in charge of the systems for the game,
and just have them walk you through it. It doesn't require a lot of critical analysis to figure out what the core system, the narrative should be supporting.
So, for example, if you're writing a merchant for an RPG, there's certain implied system mechanics there, whether people actually realize it or not.
One is, if you're talking to a merchant, the reason a player is talking to a merchant is because they want to buy and sell something.
So don't have like 15 nodes of dialogue before you actually get to the buy-sell option.
You're smiling, but there are some writers that still make that mistake.
When you talk to a merchant or you talk to the healer in town,
there's a very specific system that you want from them.
Don't let the narrative get in the way of that.
And that's a really easy analysis to do.
And then you can take that analysis and make it even more complicated.
It's like if you're in like Fallout New Vegas, for example,
and they're trying to reinforce the reputation mechanics in that game.
As a narrative designer, you suddenly have an important role
about how you're going to communicate that reputation mechanic in the game,
which has a certain number of narrative conditionals associated with it.
Like, you'd have to have factions, for example, in order for reputations to work.
Or, obviously, the people you talk to need to react
if the reputation is low or high.
And a lot of that stuff, you can just find it by dissecting the systems,
talking to the system designer or the gameplay programmer.
and then figuring out how the story can support all of that.
And actually, it's actually not too complicated
once they lay it out for you.
There's a lot of Excel and spreadsheets involved
with that, usually, too.
Yeah, I've already experienced that.
Thank you.
This might be a dumb question, but what exactly is
the difference between a game writer and a narrative
designer?
So, once upon a time, the Writers Guild Association told me that we couldn't submit work because
we weren't labeled writers where I was working.
I took a little bit of umbrage at that.
I'm like, well, I do a lot of writing, goddammit, blah blah blah.
And then I realized, maybe I don't do writing.
So I think the distinction comes...
So a narrative designer, I think the full job description for that is
they're the guys that also know how to script the logic variables,
they know exactly how to implement the quests in the game
and all those different stages,
what sort of XP rewards they should be getting.
usually their range is a little bit more technical than,
hey, we just brought in a writer to take all the blank nodes
for this particular quest and just write like two lines
for each one of them.
So it kind of depends.
I generally prefer the term narrator designer
because as soon as you're involved
with an interactive experience,
I think you're doing a lot more than just writing
whether you realize it or not, but that's just my opinion.
The definition I've been working with for the most part has been that game writers,
their craft focus is more on words and text.
So they're often doing the dialogue, the lore, sort of the plot,
whereas narrative design encompasses that,
but also can encompass all the more...
I guess abstract ways that the game itself tells story.
You know, things like environmental design, sound design, things like that.
So a writer would be maybe, you know, their day might be like,
I'm going to write this, you know, this dialogue.
Whereas the narrative designer might be like,
I want this area to convey a sense of foreboding.
I'm going to go talk to, you know, the narrative designer to see how can we do that.
Maybe we could have like a corpse hanging somewhere or something.
That's how I differentiate it.
I'd agree with Michelle too.
Sometimes for games, narrative designers would actually do a visual storytelling pass.
They're like, here's the props that I need in this area to communicate that the following thing happened.
But there wouldn't be a single note of dialogue or a journal entry anywhere around there.
You're just asking...
in tandem with the environment artists and the world builders,
like how do I build this campsite so it looks like it was abandoned one week ago
but clearly the turrets and the binoculars are focused at this distant
location over there that I'm trying to draw the player to
and there's no talking about it whatsoever, it's all in the setup.
In a lot of ways, a narrative designer is a facilitator.
As Michelle was saying, the narrative design can help embody the world and the story and
even the gameplay in a lot of different aspects of the game.
And so as a facilitator, the narrative designer is going to work with the level designers
and the game designers and the programmers and the scripters.
and talking to them about, okay,
how can we get this to come across in the gameplay?
Or, you know, how can we get aspects of the world
to come through in the UI design?
To use Mass Effect, for example,
the UI in the menu settings
looks like a console of a spaceship.
Why?
Because you are the commander of a spaceship.
So that's narrative design in just the UI.
You know, it can be sound, it can be art.
So you are really making sure, I like to say it this way,
that the world and the story embody the gameplay.
That's how I think about it.
But you can look at any aspect of the game
and apply narrative design to it.
I like all the, sorry, I'm the bald white guy now.
But.
The sad truth is that all these things are true, but also defined differently at every
company that you might interact with or work with.
And some will not have narrative designers, and the writers will be doing the narrative
design, but not getting credited as that.
Sometimes the narrative design is being done by the level designers, and the writer's really
artist writing the dialogue.
Sometimes there are no writers and they're all called narrative designers.
So it's really variable from place to place.
I like the definitions I'm hearing, is that sort of generally what happens.
But you kind of, again, if you're applying somewhere or something like that,
you'll want to research, well, what do they mean by this?
And it might be that you're applying for narrative design
and all they want to see is writing samples
and they don't even talk to you about gameplay.
Or it might be the opposite.
I've done a whole talk on this very subject back in the past at IGDA, and I would say
that at a very high level, first of all, game writer, narrative designer, they both do both.
They have to.
It's very hard to complete.
If you're a narrative designer, you're almost guaranteed to be doing some game writing of
some kind.
And if you're a game writer, you're implicitly doing narrative design of some kind in the
way you think about the story.
It's almost impossible to completely extricate them from each other.
And in a smaller team, one person will generally be doing all.
But as you get to a larger team, you start to see them separated.
I would say game writer is more focused on content and the creative side,
just the story side more.
And the narrative design is more integration and implementation.
But they both have to be on the same page.
And again, they both have to be able to kind of...
think that way, but when you get a large team, it's useful to separate them to a certain
degree so that one person can be that person in the meetings with the level designers and
with the system designers and the writer has the ability to detach and focus on actually
writing because it's very hard in a large team and a large project to do both those
things at the same time.
To sort of, you know, wrap everybody's thoughts up there,
one of the things I, one of the definitions
I really liked for narrative design
is that you are the champion of the story, you know,
the champion of the theme, of the mood, of the narrative.
And so, and of course you can be that
as the game writer as well.
But I think for me, narrative design, there's a connotation,
there's a sort of an implication of not only are you championing it within the writing sphere,
but you're championing it for the entire team.
You're working with the team to sort of say, like, here is our narrative goal.
How are we all working together to reach that goal?
I was just going to say that when I talk to elementary schools and they ask me what does
a narrative designer do, the simplest answer that I tell them is I'm the one who explains
why the birds are angry.
I just wanted, the point I wanted to make has to do with all the invisible writing that
goes into game writing.
Because every single thing that you see on a screen.
has to be described so that an artist can draw it properly.
There have to be documents that explain backstories.
There have to be lore bibles saying,
you know, these are the rules of our world.
So for all of the text that you see on a screen in the game,
there's a whole lot of text that you never see,
and we have to write all of that stuff too.
So there's a lot of invisible writing
that goes along with the game too, so keep that in mind.
Cool.
Awesome, thanks so much.
So parts of this were kind of covered by the last part of that answer of the previous question.
But how would game writers or game narrative designers market their skills or what they do
to people who may not be aware of what it is that game writers or game narrative designers do
or are aware of their importance?
Well, you point to Half-Life 1.
And you go, once upon a time, first person shooters were all just about shooting people in the face,
but then Half-Life came along and added a story, and they saw it was valuable, it made a lot of money.
Yeah, I mean, if you're looking to convince someone of the value, is that what basically we're talking about?
I mean, there's a survey, I have it linked on my website on the front page,
that showed that in games with a story mode, that reviewers are more concerned with
the story aspect, the narrative aspect,
than other elements like gameplay or art.
Like it's that important.
It drives review scores.
And if you want to try to quantify this
and put it in dollars and cents,
you know, say this is actually can benefit your review scores
which in fact impacts sales.
I mean, it's right there, you know,
in kind of black and white
if you're looking for actual data.
You could also point to Telltale Games and go,
well, apparently there's some studio out there
that makes a lot of money just telling stories in games.
Like, apparently that's working out really well for them.
I would actually go, I would do all of that,
but I'd also go a slightly different route,
and that is have a couple of games in mind
that you can try out that are not explicitly story-heavy
or what we would normally think of story-heavy games.
So, you know, for example, there's lots of people
that say, oh, Five Nights at Freddy's,
that's not got much of a story.
And I'm like, yes, it does.
Here's all the story that's in it.
or some other games that maybe don't even have any text at all,
but you can point to, like, this is how the art, you know,
this is how the art, the music, like everything combines to convey a mood
or convey a story, and hey, narrative design is all about that.
I think your best bet is going to be through networking, when you are talking one-on-one
with someone, and as Michelle was saying, you have your arsenal of examples.
You know, one I like to use is Plague Inc., which has a very specific story and has lots
of dynamic world-building, but a lot of people would look at that game and say, there's no
story and there's no world-building.
Well, yes, it's right in front of you.
You see what's happening in real time.
So
Being here is really great.
Try to find other networking events
because there are a lot of people now who want to make games
and you're probably in the position
where you're probably going to be looking for work soon.
So if you can convince them,
and it's getting a lot easier all the time
because they want to be convinced.
They know they need to make games.
So listen very carefully to what they're saying, because they'll probably tell you a lot about
their project, and based upon what they are telling you, grab an example that is similar
to what they're doing, and explain to them using that example.
Don't explain to them directly, here's how you fix your game, because then they don't
need to hire you.
But, you know, listen very carefully, grab an example that's very illustrative of what
they're trying to do.
as sort of a cynical point of view on this, that if you're, I mean, it sort of depends
on the situation, like if it's your friends who are making a game and you want to tell
them to convince, to convince them they should add more story to it, I think you have a shot.
If you're like going up to a team that's established and is working well and doesn't think they
need story, like...
I don't know. It can be hard to flip them.
And if they say, well, I guess so, and sort of let you in to do some stuff,
they'll probably end up cutting you off at the knees most of the time anyway,
because they never wanted a story in the first place.
Now this person shows up.
And I've certainly been in those situations on big projects at studios
where whoever was in charge of the project
didn't think story was necessary, but someone told him to bring someone in,
and they can continue to undermine them for the entire process and say,
see, we didn't need story. So you got to look at the situation you're going
into. And is it possible to actually convert these people? Or should I just
go look somewhere else where it's going to be more receptive?
Yeah, if you're talking with a team that you're trying to convince of the value, you may be
talking to the wrong team.
Right.
At this point, there's so much evidence everywhere.
They may need to discover this by themselves, which they often do.
You may say, hey, you know, your game might be better with some narrative put in here
and here, but let me know if you need any help.
And just let them go.
And you may get a call in six months when it's hit the fan, and they realize that they
don't...
And could you just come in and write the dialogue?
Well, yeah, but then maybe next time afterward,
they will have learned their lesson, and you will say,
I can fix this dialogue, but you know,
I could have done a lot more if I could change this and this,
which I know I can't because you've already locked it in.
But maybe next time I could help you earlier.
And that may be a long-term relationship.
But sometimes they have to, a lot of times,
they have to discover it for themselves.
They think they know how to write.
They think they can handle it.
Or they think they don't need story at all.
Right, or they don't need story at all.
And someone says, this is really flat, doesn't feel right, what could help?
Maybe a story.
And then suddenly they realize that they're in trouble.
And they call in someone like you or someone like us to try to rescue them.
And we do our best, but we have to explain that the reason we can only do so much is because it waited so long.
And maybe next time there will be one of those studios that does value what a narrative person can bring early on.
But, you know.
Thank you.
Hello. So writing is a process of iteration and reiteration.
And that is important because that's so in your endeavors,
you want your writing to be as polished, as organized as possible.
And.
I mean, every writer has his or her own process when it comes to writing.
So I wanted to ask you folks, you know, what is personally the process that has proven
most effective in your writing endeavors when it comes to creative writing and game writing
overall?
First off, indicate the person on the team who is in charge of the story.
They may not be in charge of the project, but that person is empowered to have all the authority and responsibility over the story changes, as long as it's in accordance with the game systems.
When there's multiple writers in the project, make that hierarchy very clear within the writers as well, so they always know who the creative lead is, or the lead writer is.
and they recognize that they're actually trying to help that lead writer realize the vision for that story.
And he in turn is trying to help the game realize its vision, but he feels the story is the best way to do that.
And the responsibility, the lead writer would usually do the drafts of the story up into a point.
Usually I find by the third draft.
you either need to figure out what the strengths of that story are or scrap it.
Usually by the third draft, the lead writer has come up with,
we feel this is the appropriate spine for the story,
now let's reinforce it and build off of that.
I would say have finite feedback windows because anytime you have a whole team of writers in
a studio...
Oh my God.
If you've ever popped open a document that a hundred people have commented on, you're
just like, I'm done.
There's no way I'm going to get through this.
Like a month has passed.
Why is there a hundred people commenting on this?
Like Jesus effing Christ.
It's like, you know, marketing, your time to look at this and give us feedback is between this date and this date.
And then after that, we're moving with whatever you said at this time.
They're just words. Can't you just reorder them?
You can get yourself into a real situation because if people are making changes all along and all along and all along, it's like, when is this thing ever done?
You have to reach a point.
Because there is a release date, people, right?
There just is.
And you have to be willing to declare it done at some point.
Even if you're not 100% happy with it,
there is going to be a time when you have to declare it done.
And so assigning which groups are
allowed to give feedback at what points
and making those feedback windows finite and
schedule. Yeah, there has to be that cutoff point where the mutation has to stop.
And you're like, this is the form you're going to take. And that's pretty much it.
Because I actually ran into one problem in the studio where I realized that every time I gave feedback,
they'd completely rewrite the story. And at that point I'm like, okay, wow, actually feedback is getting really dangerous now.
It's not actually helping anything.
So I'm like, okay, well, we're just gonna take
this story right now, don't change anything.
Here's some very tiny specific things
you might want to address, but you have to watch
the iteration process too, because sometimes
people can just jump off the deep end.
I found the process, well, I mean, every game is different, every team is different, it's
hard to say there's one process that you could apply to all situations, but one thing I always
make sure I do is really focus on, especially if I'm brought in early enough, is to really
focus on the mechanics of the game, and what is the core of this game, and to play the
game, and to understand, and to read the documentation on the vision for the gameplay.
Because that's what we're trying to make better.
We're trying to support it and enhance it and contextualize it.
And if you just jump in with, well, we thought we were going to do this with the story, just
run with that.
And you don't stop and back up and go, wait, what is your game?
Show me the game.
Show me how it plays.
And sometimes you need to take two steps back and say, you know what?
This story that you've come up with doesn't match your game.
This character you're talking about in the story isn't what you do in the game.
So, and that's more of a narrative design type of angle,
but you've got, you kind of go, maybe you have to go back
one or two steps, possibly, I found,
and really, with a fresh set of eyes,
especially if you're coming in new,
and say, you know, maybe we need to reevaluate
where your story concept is, and let's match it better
to what this game is really about, what you actually do, so.
So I come from the opposite end of the spectrum
because except for two projects,
everything that I have worked on,
I have been the sole narrative designer and or game writer.
So to stop the infinite feedback,
I have very clear milestones
and I have milestones for client feedback.
And then I have milestones for payment
that go along with drafts.
So it's like, if you want more than two revisions,
then you start paying me.
for more revisions. And so with feedback, the feedback milestone, that says to them,
okay, you only have so many chances to give me feedback to change things before you pay
me. And so they know that feedback needs to be excellent and it needs to be on target.
Yeah, I find the financial accountability really causes those comments to sharpen very quickly.
And also, if you're doing game writing, that you're getting feedback from a publisher or another developer,
it's always good to have one person designated as the compiler of all the feedback from the studio,
and that's actually specified in a contract somewhere.
I guess the one thing I would add a little different is I like the expression I heard
somewhere that if you're putting it out there and you're not slightly embarrassed by it,
you've probably worked on it too long and I think that's particularly true in like,
particularly if you're on a big project that's going to have a lot of iterations.
and you need to like write the script for a level or something like that. You want to do a pass of it that's like pretty good but not insanely polished, not like every line agonized over forever because you know you're going to get around to feedback.
And then it will be really interesting to see, oh, these are the things everyone didn't like. I'll work on that. I guess the other stuff is probably fine.
I mean still go back and have your own polish pass to make yourself feel good about it, but don't.
And also, as in the very iterative process, oh, sorry, we cut half the level. So all those lines you polished are now trash.
So better to just get a good version out,
get a pretty good version out there,
but don't kill yourself on it, knowing that you're going
to have time to go back to it.
But if you've got something like a voiceover session coming up,
knowing, oh, god, I guess I better actually polish that
now.
I'm still kind of working out my favorite iteration process because I'm new, so I've
worked on, like, in terms of the projects I've worked on, I've worked on everything
from being the only narrative designer to being in a team where there's like multiple
writers and none of us are allowed to talk to each other.
Spoiler alert, don't do that.
And then the current team I'm with, you know, we have a meeting and we talk about stuff,
and sometimes that's an incredibly useful iterative process, and other times I'm like,
we've been talking about what this character should be named for two hours, oh dear, what happened?
I would take away from that that, like, don't be afraid to ask for more, like, specifics
if they're not giving you enough, because several times I've had, I don't know if you've ever had the feedback,
this is great, it just needs to be tweaked a bit more.
It's like, okay, do you want me to tweak the paper?
What do you want from me?
And the other thing is, I actually am kind of a fan when,
if there's multiple writers, if there's a little bit like,
each writer has their specific task.
You're doing this project, you're doing this part of the project.
As long as there's good communication between the writers,
I think that can actually be a very...
handy way to do things because then, you know, you're not constantly iterating off each other,
but you're able to give feedback to each other on your area of specialization. So I've had good
experiences with that. Yeah, Michelle's right, we used to do that in the Fallout games where what
we'd do is we'd actually segment each area and give each area to a different writer so they
wouldn't be stepping on each other's toes like that. Yeah, that's a great idea.
Also another thing I'd say, in terms of iteration, I do prefer it when one writer gets something out
and then everybody builds on what that writer has done, rather than, hey, we need this idea for this character
and everybody provides their character idea, because now it's like, well now we've got to go through what everyone has done
and figure out what we're going to do, which can be very interesting, but can also be a little time-consuming.
And morally depressing.
All right, thank you very much for the invaluable insight.
Howdy.
Hello.
So one of the things that I found
in talking to a lot of students who
want to get into game writing is that they really
want to write games.
And it's really hard for them to divorce
sort of the game mechanic aspect of game writing
to just look at good writing and interesting writing
and really be excited from writing
because they're not reading anything
that isn't really a game.
And they just don't understand how those things connect.
So I think it would be super duper valuable
if you guys just talked about what you've
been reading recently, what's some really good writing you've
discovered in the last couple of months, and throw that out
so everybody knows what books they should buy and read
after this conference.
I just got done reading The Circle by Dave Eggers.
I loved it.
It was terrifying.
So I recommend that one.
I just started reading a book called Loosed Upon the World.
It's a collection of short stories
about environmental calamity that she wrote a story in.
It's pretty cool.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I admit I tend to have my favorites that I keep coming back to and will basically foist
on anyone who asks me, like, which book should I be reading?
And one of them is, frankly, I reread Pride and Prejudice at least once a year.
I love that book to death.
And actually, one of the best books I've read also in terms of
interesting like integrating the research about a time period into the story was um Pillars of the
Earth which is a novel by Ken Follett about cathedral building in medieval England and it's
just it's got a riveting story and it's like but clearly he wants you to know he knows that he
learned a lot about cathedral building so really good you know uh integration of the plot with the
research that way.
I read Steinbeck's East of Eden recently, a very long book, and one of the classics
that kind of passed me by, I didn't catch the first time, when I was in school or whatever,
they didn't have it, so I checked that out, and now I'm reading a Fred Saberhagen book
called Empire of the East, so I have an East theme, and I'm working in the East right now,
so I have a very East-based theme going right now.
But yeah, your point is taken, that it's important to have influences outside the industry,
just like it's important to have a rich tapestry to draw upon and different influences,
not just books, but movies, great movies and great TV shows,
and just have a variety of things you can draw upon.
I had two sort of on that tip quickly, two interview questions that I would use to rule people out.
One was name some games that are well written.
And I would find a lot of writers who weren't game writers would say they're all terrible, they're out.
Just because they're not paying attention, right?
Like sure, a lot of games are badly written, but there are some good ones. Have you spent any time investigating it?
And then the other one was, oh great, your game stuff is good.
What else are you reading?
What else are you doing?
It's like, oh, well, I read the Halo novel and the thing.
And there's nothing wrong with the Halo novel,
and that's all fine.
But if they're so insular in that world,
it's sort of like this is going to,
they're not broad enough in their knowledge,
exactly what you're saying, basically.
Well, I had one, but I hope manga counts.
And I'm going to butcher the title, Nijigahara Holograph,
which is very David Lynchian and a very interesting style,
very beautiful.
So.
I sort of have a reverse perspective where I punish myself whenever I'm not writing by watching Star Trek Voyager.
And I usually find within 20 minutes I go back to writing.
And the only non-fiction I'm reading right now is Proof, The Science of Booze.
which was fascinating. But what I actually do is I actually do reading in
the reverse in the sense that, so for example when I was writing on Wasteland 2
I wanted to do like the Agricultural Center because I really liked that
location in the first game, but then once I realized I was gonna be like writing an
Agricultural Center that had grown out of control, I immediately went to the
internet and I'm like well what are all the popular sources of fiction that have
already covered this topic? So I'm like okay well I'm gonna watch Day of the
Triffids, I'm gonna read Day of the Triffids.
I'm going to go read, like, you know, Food of the Gods, like all those aspects, like,
because I want to be aware of the range of connections I can possibly draw, and also
be aware of the connections that I don't want to draw because some other source has already
covered it already.
So I sometimes approach reading in reverse, but it's very specific to what I'm writing
on.
Hi, my name's Bridget, I'm from New Zealand.
I'm working on a large transmedia project for young girls, 8 to 12 year olds,
which sits on the core platforms of TV, books and gaming.
And it's the gaming part I'm here for, obviously.
So my question is, do you have any thoughts or resources or...
anything in terms of writing for children. I think young girls, 8 to 12 year olds, it's a very specific time.
It's a really precious end of childhood, not quite adolescence,
and my whole project is all about capturing the innocence and the joy and the wonder of childhood.
And so in terms of writing, that's always my focus. I come from a writing background.
I'm a film and TV person originally, so yeah, any thoughts on that would be really cool.
Yeah, actually eight of my nine titles were for children between the ages of 11 and 15.
And what I found was it would be really easy to write in a way that talks down to them.
And so what I did was two things.
One was focus groups, focus groups, focus groups.
Find out how they feel about the things that you're doing and whether they fly or not.
Because kids, they can smell bullshit from really far away.
And they are not shy about telling you what they like and what they don't like.
And so focus groups are really helpful.
But the first game that I worked on was for 11 to 14-year-old African-American children,
and I'm about as far away from a 12-year-old black girl as one gets.
And I went into the project really recognizing that and wanting to do it right.
So what I did was I wrote the outlines of the story,
and then we went to a boys' and girls' club where there actually were kids in this demographic who the stories were for,
and we had them act out the stories.
And so a lot of the phraseology that I borrowed from when I wrote that dialogue was from when those kids were acting the stories out.
So that it was being done in a way that was, you know, not going to be patronizing or offensive or anything like that.
It was just, my suggestion would be to include the kids in the process.
Yeah, that's really cool. I was a qualitative researcher in a previous incarnation, so I respond well to that. Thank you.
I'd second that.
I usually find, however, that the focus groups will come to me because all my friends have...
kids within that age range, they'll immediately start pitching games to me about dragons and
unicorns and actually it's like ten times better than anything I could think of. I'm
like, wow, this is great. But it often becomes an excuse to go meet and hang out with them
and then I just listen to what the kids are talking about and I'm like, wow, that's pretty
great. That's going to make me rich for a year.
I've written for children, I've also written for children's games, and you had a very interesting
age range there, 8 to 12, because there's a huge difference in maturity and interest
between 8 year olds and 12 year olds.
And also like the technical aspect of it, because writing for kids, I don't know if
you have reading level requirements.
So you have 12 year olds, but it's going to have to be on the reading level for 8 year
olds.
So that's going to be an issue too.
It's got to be interesting enough for 12 year olds, but the language can't be so simple
that they're not interested in it.
But at the same time, it can't be so complex that the 8 year olds can't get into it as
well.
Yeah.
Good point.
And I guess the one thing I would add is...
I don't have any experience doing this at all, so don't listen to my opinion on that,
but the nightmare scenario to be in and to watch out for maybe is if you have, say, a
member of the team or an executive who's got power over the project, who has a kid, who's
this particular age, and suddenly they are the demographic, just that one child, and
then it just can become a nightmare scenario of like, well, Bobby doesn't like it, and
like, well, yeah, but these other 20 kids did, like, doesn't he?
You got to short yourself out.
Bobby doesn't like you either.
Bobby wants you fired.
That's right.
So just be wary of that sort of personal, because you know like an executive will be
really close to their kid and suddenly they're running your project secretly behind the scenes
or something like that.
I'm always convinced they are anyway.
Right.
Thank you very much.
Hi.
I'm a writer, but I currently work
in monetization for a free-to-play game.
And I am going to be transitioning into game design
and more writing on free-to-play games soon.
So my questions are kind of based on that.
I kind of have two facets to the question.
One is general tips for writing to free-to-play games,
where you can use it is a lot more restrictive.
And also, the game's established.
So you kind of have to squeeze it in.
Tips for that.
And also tips for writing for a game
that has the buildup of a narrative,
but based on the way that free-to-play games are,
probably will never have an ending point
because the levels just keep going on.
So tips for both of those things.
So I'm going to say something that's going to crush the hearts of all the writers in the room,
but always make the narrative bits skippable.
Because, you know, a lot of people are playing in short stretches.
They are playing the mobile game because they'll just have a little bit of time.
And so they don't have time for a lot of story.
They want to get right to the gameplay.
The other thing is, think about mobile games
as bits of story, and like, you sprinkle that in.
It doesn't have to be after every level, necessarily.
If you have dialogue, it needs to be super short.
We talked about less is more,
less is really, really, really more with mobile games.
And also, think about smartphone screens
instead of tablet screens.
Because you can play the same games
on the phone and the tablet.
But the smartphone screen is going to be a lot more restrictive.
So write for the smartphone and not for the tablet.
I have actually been working on some free-to-play games at the moment, and I'm also doing a
sort of a career transition at the moment.
One thing I've been trying to do is, whenever possible, like, for example, you've got for
most of these free-to-play games, you might have, for example, a resource that is going
to be purchased through real-world dollars.
I've actually tried to make an effort to actually integrate that within the story that it makes
sense in a way.
Like, you know, for example, okay, well, you're collecting this, this, you know, maybe you're
collecting stars and then there are these special stars that, yes, you do need to pay
money for.
So I've tried to...
make it so that it feels like getting the more powerful resource is actually a part of the narrative of the game.
Another thing I've done, I have been trying to do exactly what Toyo says and keep the writing short.
I don't know how well I've succeeded.
But yeah, definitely keep it skippable.
And make...
I would actually say one thing I would definitely do is try to give the NPCs as much flavor
within that small amount as you can, because I tried several free-to-play games in the
genre I'm writing in, and I'm like, this is just like, there's a character popping up,
and they are literally just giving me exposition and tutorial text, and I'm feeling nothing
for who this person is.
Like, I know you're Kate Upton, I don't know what you, what, who are you?
What are you doing here?
So I would definitely see what you can do to make those,
make the way that you're delivering the tutorial
and the instructions like interesting
on a character level as well.
I'm going to bring the room down even further and say that if you're going to work on a
free-to-play game, also don't sign a non-compete clause where you can't give advice about how
to design or write for free-to-play games for a year after you leave a company.
But in a completely unrelated topic, I've been playing this incredible game called Dungeon
Boss, which doesn't have a lot of text, but there's a story involved there.
hypothetically, it's just crazy.
And the amount that they get away with,
with just the naming of the abilities for each character,
tells a ton about each character,
as well as the animation set they have.
Like, they have this one goblin
who does a lot of, like, cheap shots,
and, like, obviously, like, he's a dirty fighter.
They also have his animations that were like he's kind of a pyromaniac,
but he ends up, his attack move is he actually, he accidentally sets himself on fire,
and then he runs around screaming the entire scream, but he burns all the enemies while he's doing it.
That alone tells me five million words about that character right there.
So look for ways of animation, even the names of abilities,
even the visual effects of how they're presented.
That, that can be almost your entire story right there,
depending on the presentation, and it requires no words whatsoever.
Another thing, I was reminded when Michelle was talking about the dialogue,
if you can get a range of character portraits and emotional states for like, say one character,
maybe you can have up to four emotional states, so you can match the emotional state with the dialogue.
Because usually you don't have voiceover, but if you can show like a neutral state,
happy, frustrated, angry, sad, that visual helps a lot too.
With regard to your question about a story that never ends,
right, think about TV writing and the way
that they just perpetuate character arcs.
And of course, it's much broader and a much larger stage
than what you're talking about.
So you have to scale it down.
But finding out what happens to this character over this arc,
and then as that's resolving, another arc
starts with a different character, for example.
So you can always have something on the go.
as opposed to a big three-act structure
where we're leading to a giant climax
that never comes because we can't resolve the story, right?
So you want to focus more on character arcs
and things resolving on a small scale
and overlapping with each other.
Again, very much a small stage to do it,
but there are ways to kind of thread those things through.
You can think of it as a soap opera model.
Think of it in terms of a soap opera.
You know, things are blowing up with this character
and just before it resolves, something else happens.
Now this one's been diagnosed with some horrible disease.
And the episode always ends with like, you know, I know exactly what you're about to
tell me.
And then like goes, you know, you have to wait till tomorrow.
And then they're like, oh, you're going to tell me that you're going out to the store
to buy some milk.
So don't wait till tomorrow or pay $5 to find out right now.
And actually that also brings up something I kind of wanted to say and maybe I'm going to get, like, you know, attacked by rabid writers.
It doesn't always have to be Shakespeare.
Like, it's okay to occasionally look at something and be like, it's okay to write a very silly story.
Like, you can still write a silly story and still put...
quality and effort into it.
But, like, I remember I had, you know, one project where I was beating myself up about, like,
why am I not, like, integrating all of these, like, deep artistic issues?
And, like, kind of had to come to peace with, like,
it's not that type of game.
It would feel, you know, it would feel kind of forced if I was trying to do it.
It's working better as a narrative to do it this way, even though...
It's a bit of a silly fantasy story, and that's okay.
Hi, I'm a novelist, but in the publishing industry's own words,
adult fiction is anemic and insignificant.
So I'm very interested in getting into games.
So I've made a couple of game proposals
for my published and unpublished books.
I made a couple of text adventures for my website,
but with an eye to the job fair tomorrow.
I'm curious about how I ought to present myself.
I doubt I'm going to be brought on board with the AAA game to be the lead designer.
That doesn't make any sense.
With so many companies, and there's games that I like, but there's many more companies
making good stuff, I'm curious what advice you might have as to how I might match up
with a good team and how I ought to present myself to them.
What's your interest in being a game writer?
Why do you want to be a game writer?
Well, it seems that people always want to get stories.
People love stories, but people aren't getting them from books.
Games have unique interactivity,
but being able to blend cinematic qualities.
of sound and character design and all that.
It seems like a great new medium.
We've been waiting for, there was a hypertext
and that was supposed to be the next thing in storytelling
and that didn't take off because it's not fun to play
and the writing wasn't really up to what it needed to be.
So I'm interested in being on the winning side of things.
Okay, because whenever I talk to someone who's a writer from another industry, I ask them why,
and do they play a lot of games, and what games do they play, and you know, is it just seeing,
is it a question of you're passionate about games, and you love games, you love playing games,
and you're interested in learning about game mechanics, and getting really hip deep in that,
because that's, there's probably no harder, I mean it's just, you know, Rihanna was just
saying next door that writing in games is like writing in a headwind.
compared to other media.
It is just that much more challenging
because there's so many more complications.
And so you've got to have that passion.
You've got to have that interest in getting really into Excel
spreadsheets and tools and technology,
not necessarily becoming a programmer,
but understanding what programs do and what they can and can't
do.
And there's so much involved.
So my core advice is you need to really
be passionate about games.
It can't just be you see this as a frontier, as a writer,
and you feel like you should be there.
It's more like.
you should be passionate about being there because you're competing with those who are passionate
and do play a lot of games and understand how games are made. So that's the top level.
Discovering the Telltale games really opened up my mind to the possibilities. I used to take
apart choose your own adventure books like a budding engineer would take apart a vacuum
cleaner to see how they worked and seeing this now finally come to fruition, I thought I really
love this and I think I could do this and I would like to do this.
And I definitely think start with that as your pitch for yourself of saying like, I
really got into telltale games and I realized this is cool not, oh, I used to be a writer
and obviously that's dying.
So where should I go now?
You know, just to be honest, that's that's going to turn off certain people who are like,
well, forget this guy.
And I would think for your meetings this week where you're pitching your own properties
that you own.
you know, should really view it as an entree
into a conversation about what they actually need written,
maybe, and not, like, think of it like maybe you'll
maybe you'll get one of them interested
in one of your properties or something like that,
but it's kind of unlikely,
but it's more of like a look I can write
and I did this pitch on it
that's really looks like a game already or whatever
and shows that I get it and I'm really into it
and that, oh, and you need this other thing written?
Well, I could do that too, you know,
and that's gonna, I think,
more likely scenarios work out, to be honest.
Thanks, we'll try to get to the last two.
Hello, I'll be really quick.
I'm working as a narrative designer at the moment
on my first game, and one of the things
that I found challenging is I will write a lot,
and the team obviously doesn't want to read it.
So I was just wondering, what are some tips and tricks
and methods that you guys use to communicate your story
and keep that across, or the team across what the story is
and how it's changing?
Bullet points.
Bullet points, flow charts, things like that?
If it's something descriptive,
if it's something that animators
and artists are going to be using,
I put all the descriptive stuff up front
and then the more detailed stuff later
because I know they tend not to like to read a whole lot.
So, you know, like the game designers, the game writers,
they can read the stuff that's at the end,
but keep stuff that's descriptive and upfront and brief.
Yeah, sometimes for projects, it actually does just do a PowerPoint presentation of the main characters and like the plot lines and it did involve a lot of flowcharts, but it also includes things like a lot of reference art for like, here's how here's here's some sources of inspiration for this character. So you know what I'm thinking about when I'm writing them, the artist doesn't have to actually do those specific reference images, but they understand where I'm coming from. So we can sort of meet somewhere in the middle.
And generally, like, yeah, it's generally hard to get anyone else on the team to read a lot of text.
Usually when, like, asking for a specific character look, often with artists, it's doing what Toya says,
where you make a very brief list of bullet points, and then I dump a bunch of reference art in a folder on the net,
and then they go look at it, and they meditate on it for a while, and they come back with a number of variations for that character.
Exactly that.
in any way you can dramatize the story,
like a PowerPoint with art, and you can act it out,
and you can kind of dramatize it and get them excited.
Get up, stand up and use your hands,
and really, if you were there with them,
you know, that's gonna draw them in
much more than any document probably will.
And Evan's right, another way you can sort of
dramatize it too is if some concept art is already done.
I generally find that artists really get excited
about a presentation when they see their images
up being presented before the whole company,
and they're like, oh, that's my art, wow,
that sounds pretty cool.
And this is the final thought, you know, I have a friend Liz England who talks about
writing with the audience in mind any document you create, like you shouldn't just write
a design document, you should write one for the animator, one for the programmer, one
for whatever, and she's doing a talk about this on Friday at 1.30 in the Rules of the
Game session that you might want to check out because she talks about all the ways she's
written different documents for every possible audience on the team.
Awesome.
Some things that's worked for the team I'm working with is one, whenever possible, they
will actually try and embed a writer into one of the other scrums so that there's someone
not necessarily giving them documents but actually able to answer questions on the fly.
And the other thing is, as weird as it sounds, we have a company newsletter where we have
to break down, every scrum has to break down, there are three main points that's important
for the rest of the scrums to know.
And that's actually been really useful to break it down in three points.
This is what the rest of you need to know about what narrative is doing.
Yeah.
Last question and also really quickly we'll be at the wrap-up room right across in 3022.
Hi, I am creating an immersive media game and the thing that is bringing people through is
a creation myth of how the world was created and our purpose here and saving the planet.
And I've never created a game before.
And so my big question is, who do I need to bring on my team?
Or what games would you point to and say, wow,
you want to learn and study this?
But again, my big question is, as I
form this board of advisors and our team members,
who would you recommend as good people to bring on?
I can tell a story.
I've never done it in the form of a game before.
Did you say you've never played a game before?
Oh, I've played a game before, yes.
You've never made a game before?
Like, I've got a great story, I've never gamified it before.
And so we're looking at how do we gamify this so that people go through this game experience
where they get to be a part of saving the world, you know.
I would definitely bring on...
a narrative designer or two, to help you figure out how to integrate the gameplay and the story,
and especially because immersion is really important. So your narrative designer would
figure out how not to break immersion.
And it's interesting that for a while,
there were a lot of movie games that were made,
like say, oh, the new Star Wars movie is coming out,
so we should have a game about that.
And they would try to follow the same plot
as the movie or whatever.
And those were inevitably terrible,
because you really need to write the plot for your game
and not just like, we've got this existing plot,
we can apply it to whatever.
So you'll see a lot of the successful adaptations
these days are really writing a pretty custom plot,
maybe in the same world, same settings,
some of the same characters,
but really changing it substantially.
And that's where a narrative designer could come in
to help you structure that.
I was going to say you might want to expose yourself to a lot of different kinds of storytelling
to see what you can draw from different things.
I recently was in Nashville and did an escape the room experience in Nashville.
And you wouldn't necessarily think that there's story that has to take place with that, but
there really is, right?
And so, you know, maybe just play different types of games and see what kinds of things
you're really drawn to and really work that you can draw from.
And you will find very quickly both what you really like and what you really don't.
I was going to say definitely bring a narrative designer on board, but something you can also
do for yourself to kind of get at least some of the beginnings of understanding how this
sort of, the way game storytelling can work is to actually see if you can experiment and
twine.
It's admittedly, that's a branching, a specific branching type of narrative, but I've actually
found it's a very good visualization of understanding how game style branching narrative works.
You might find, oh I had this one central plot line,
but now there's all these random branches
that are going off into nowhere.
I now need to write a new story for that.
So it's actually, I think, a very good beginner way
to kind of, well maybe beginner's not quite the right word,
but a good intro way to sort of wrap your brain around
context-sensitive storytelling, really.
And that's called Twine?
Yeah, it's a free tool on the internet and there are many very good tutorials for that
on the internet as well.
And Twine 2 has actually gotten reasonably sophisticated with the things that you can
do with it, you know, with visuals and audio and you can build systems into Twines now.
It's pretty, it's a pretty powerful free thing.
And it's great for experimentation too.
Thank you.
Thank you guys so much for coming again.
Some of us will be in the wrap-up room, which
is right across the hall.
Thank you.