All right. Hi. Welcome to our talk, More Feelings, Fewer Features, Showcasing Your Indie Game Through
Messaging and Video. I'm Dana Trebella. I'm the founder of Spoken Wheels Strategy. I do marketing,
PR, and strategy for games.
I founded Spoken Wheel about four and a half years ago,
but I've been doing marketing and PR for games
for the last seven-ish years.
I work on games of all different sizes
across all different platforms,
and these are just some of the games that I've worked with.
All right, and my name is Derek Liu,
and I'm a game trailer editor.
I've been doing this for about five years now,
some in AAA games,
but now full-time doing trailers for indie games.
Before then, I was an editor for about ten years, and these are some of the things that
I've worked on.
So we're going to talk first about what is messaging, why you need a good message, some
common mistakes that we see a lot, things you should do, some examples of good messaging,
some exercises to help you find your message, and then finish up with some lessons and takeaways.
So first, the reason we're doing this talk is we're often the first people to know that
don't know how to talk about their games,
like especially late in the development cycle.
And people frequently hire one of us, but not the other.
And we've also run into situations
where we were both hired for one project,
but we didn't find out we were both on the project
until it was over,
because we were never put in communication.
Which we think is kind of weird,
because PR and marketing and trailers,
they're not separate.
You should think of them as this thing that go together,
because when they're really cohesive,
just the message is much stronger.
And we solve a lot of the same problems,
but through different means.
But first, let's talk a little bit
about just what is messaging.
Messaging is just the hook, the secret sauce,
the elevator pitch, the sort of one-line sentence
which describes your game.
But more importantly, messaging is how you talk
to people about your game.
Like I said, I've had lots of clients
who they come to me for a trailer.
And I say, okay, what's special about your game?
And they're like, ugh.
I'm like, you should work on that first.
But it's really important.
It really drives how you talk about your game
to friends or Twitter, press, streamers, publishers,
and also how you talk to yourself about your game.
And if the message is how you talk about your game,
the trailer is how you show people your game.
Because trailers communicate through visuals,
sound, and music.
It works together with the messaging to just form what people just know about your game
and also how to share it with other people.
And some key components of your message in your trailer include...
Okay, so when you're thinking about your message,
a core component of your message should really be the experience.
So yes, that's like what you do in the game,
but more importantly, that's what do people get from your game
that they literally can't get from anywhere else.
That's kind of why your game is special in the first place.
Similarly, we're going to talk about some feelings.
I love feeling.
So ultimately, people play games for the feelings
that they get from them.
And your game should make people feel something.
Feelings are also what stay with people the longest
after they've played.
So once you've got this great message that
communicates the experience and the feelings,
you can also communicate it in your trailer.
So why do you need a good message?
So we're all hearing about how many games
are launching regularly, and we all
know that it's really, really hard to distinguish yourself
in the marketplace today.
Without a good message, it's just really hard
for people to remember or find your game
or tell people about it.
So why else?
Your messaging also focuses your marketing.
Yes, it can be kind of complicated to find a really good message, but once you find it,
I promise you it's going to make your life so much easier and simpler because it serves
essentially as this central focus of everything that you put out into the world. So, like,
if you're thinking about sending something out, you can ask yourself, does this align with my
message that I want people to know? And that can just be an easy clue as to what you should
actually be putting out there.
Your message is also your filter for marketing.
So just like in development, constraints are really great,
that also can be true for marketing too.
So again, it kind of provides this lens
to decide what you're putting out into the world.
And all of your marketing materials
should really help to communicate this message.
So we touched on this a little bit,
but your message helps people share and advocate
for your game.
So players really love to share the games that they find,
that they're excited about.
They love to be the first to tell other people about a game.
But they really need a clear and concise and easy way to do it.
So if you give them that, that's super helpful.
And if there's no clear message, then sometimes,
Either people will make something up, which may or may not be what you want them to say,
or if it feels really daunting and stressful, they just might not talk about your game at all.
So your message is super important.
It affects all of these things.
And this is just kind of like a basic list.
But essentially, it should be cohesive and across all
of these different things.
So people are actually more likely to remember things
if they see them over and over again.
And people are also more likely to like them
if they see them over and over again too.
So it's super important to do that.
So Derek's going to talk a little bit about some marketing faux pas.
Okay. Yeah. So without a clear and unique message,
your game kind of doesn't sound any different from everything else out there.
For example, all of these games share these things in common.
And if they wanted to, they could have led with these five bullet points here.
But that wouldn't have really distinguished them in any way.
And, you know, maybe it could have worked in the trailers
because their art style is very strong.
But what if we just took away all the art and just left these bullet points?
This is what it would kind of look like.
You know, like, if you look at these, would you think to yourself, oh, that game!
I know exactly what game that is.
So it's really important, the words that you use.
Now fortunately, that's not what they did.
For example, Rogue Legacy made a really big point of the descendants and they all have
kind of different attributes when you die.
And then dead cells went really big on like,
this is hard, you will die,
and also just talking about how good it is to play.
And then also enter the gungeon went just really big
on like guns and there's bullets and the bullets have guns
and they shoot you with bullets.
And flint hook went and highlighted it's a grappling hook
and the pirate part and looting.
And then binding of Isaac.
went really heavy on atmosphere and sense of dread.
And a lot of its trailers didn't even have gameplay.
And then just to, again, clarify the strength of good messaging,
just look at the same style of boring text,
but with language for very specific games.
See, when you look at these now, these probably all
remind you of certain games, because it's very, very specific.
And these could only be used with a lot of these games
that they're from.
And now let's get into some common mistakes.
Okay, cool.
So let's talk a little bit about the things
that I see all the time.
So the first is, don't describe your game using other games.
So the thing that I get most frequently
when I ask people to tell me about their game
is like, my game is if X and Y had a baby,
or like the thing we have here is like,
it's the Dark Souls of Animal Crossing.
So here's why this is a bad idea.
First of all, it requires that your audience
is familiar with those games.
If they're not, then you've probably already lost them.
Let's say that they are.
Well, then they probably have a preconceived notion associated
with it.
And let's say they love those games, right?
Then you're setting the bar pretty high for what
your game needs to live up to.
Also, if your game does elicit a comparison, then players really like to find that on their own,
and you're often kind of like robbing them of that easter egg that they can get.
But most importantly, like, we're all really used to hearing this in a game's context,
but if you take it out of a game's context, then it kind of really doesn't make sense.
So if someone said to you, like, tell me about yourself,
hopefully you wouldn't respond and be like, I'm my mom and my dad.
Right?
Like, I really hope you would give yourself
a characteristic, so do that with games also.
So we already hit on this a little bit,
but a features list is important,
but it's a features list.
It's not your message.
People ultimately aren't playing games just
for this features list, and tons of games
have really similar features.
So it's not really differentiated at all.
don't rely on just game lingo and genre.
So a lot of times when I ask people,
tell me about your game, I get something like,
it's an immersive first person shooter, which is like, okay.
And right, like there's a lot of those.
So yes, it can be part of your message,
but it really should not be the whole thing.
So with lingo in particular,
sometimes it can feel really inaccessible.
People don't necessarily know what those words mean.
And it also can only kind of box you
in to reach a really specific audience that just may or may
not be your target.
With genre, I actually think this
is a bit more problematic, because people
have really, really preconceived notions of what
each genre should be.
Like, if you think about a roguelike or an RPG
or any kind of genre, people have specific ideas
of what that should be.
And if your game kind of veers outside of that at all.
then that can make people unhappy,
and no one likes unhappy people on the internet.
It's also just, again, not differentiated.
Like, yes, some genres are more popular
or have their day in the sun.
But there's lots of games in every genre,
so why should people play yours?
So let's talk about some do's.
Work on your message early.
As soon as you've got a viable idea
that you're super excited about,
start putting together a message
and a clear way to talk about your game.
It can be a really, really good tool
to just see if people are getting your game
and if they're excited about it
and to kind of take the temperature
on how the idea is resonating.
So this is one a lot of people I think don't think about,
but your message can actually help you guide the design.
So we've all seen a Steam trailer or something like that
and then been like, wait, this doesn't feel like that game
at all.
There's a big disparity in how the screenshots
or the trailers are presenting versus what the game actually
is.
But if you think of your message early
and you use that as a checkpoint while you're designing the game,
then this disparity can be caught early.
And if you have a message that you want to share, then you can make sure that you're reflecting that in the design or
go back and kind of iterate on your message.
Which to the next point, iterate on your message.
So yes, you want a cohesive message that goes across all of those things that we showed earlier,
but ultimately before you get there, you want to try some stuff and see what's resonating with people.
So at conventions, with your friends, on Twitter, nothing super formal,
but just kind of test it out and see what people are digging.
describe the game's experience.
So think in terms of the color, the flavor, the tone,
and the feelings.
Ultimately, the experience is really
the subtext and the heartbeat of what a game is.
And again, most importantly, it's
like, what are people getting from your game
that they just literally can't get anywhere else?
So a lot of times when I ask this question,
I get the response like, it's a horror game,
or something very shallow like that.
Um, but what if you could answer something like, oh, it's the hellish nightmare of waking
up over and over to discover that it's finals day and you've missed the whole semester.
Um, or as an example, like
with Boyfriend Dungeon, they could have just called the game
a dungeon crawler.
But instead, they say, romance your swords,
capture the hearts of cuties, and level them up
in this shack and slash dungeon crawling adventure, which
is so much more colorful because you
get an idea for the feel of the game, the overarching tone,
and the experience.
All right, and also.
when you're working on your game,
you should show people video of your game being played.
And I'm not talking about play testing.
I'm talking about just taking video
and showing it to someone.
Their hands aren't on the controllers,
so they actually can't test things around
to see what's going on.
And then this will really help you find out
if your game's visual communication is really strong
or if it's really weak.
Because if people watch the video of your game,
they're like, so what do you do?
Then you know, oh crap.
that is not coming across.
And this is really important down the line
for trailers and GIFs and YouTube and Twitch streaming
because you're in a lot of trouble
if you're posting all these things on social media
to hype things up and then no one knows
what's going on in any of the footage.
Another tip is just tell the player what they'll do,
which
I'm thinking like bird's eye level of what you're doing in the game.
Like what is the goal or the objective?
Not talking about like, oh, you double jump and you fireball things.
It could be something like you're trying to survive in this water planet and build a rocket
to escape the planet.
Or you're trying to find out what happened to your family in your creepy Pacific Northwest
house.
Or you're a goose and you just want to be a jerk.
And your trailer will help you flesh this out.
But having the basic premise...
established for people, just really helps prime them to know what they're going to expect
from the rest of your game.
The other tip is just keep your description short.
One to four sentences, you know, brief and colorful is ideal.
Get to the point quickly.
Because if you just kind of drone on for a little bit too long, then it can kind of be
like if someone's talking to you about their dream that they have and people will be like,
okay, I don't really care anymore.
And it just really has to get to the heart of what people care about,
which is what they do in the game and why.
And also, the message doesn't have to be everything about the game,
and it really, really should not be everything,
because you need to leave people wanting a little bit more.
Just imagine if you're at a convention,
and you tell them your spiel.
You want them to be like,
oh, cool, I'm going to wait in line and play the demo.
But if you tell them everything,
then it might be enough information for them to be like,
Huh, yeah, I think I know exactly what your game is.
No, that's not my thing.
But you kind of like leave it a little bit vague,
and you're like, hmm, that sounds interesting.
I will wait in line, or I'll go read some articles.
And also, these tips are good for your trailer.
Basically the same thing.
Make it short, get to the point, focus on the hook,
and once you kind of get past the hook,
then you can focus on the other things,
maybe which kind of overlap other games.
And then, of course, you want to leave them wanting more,
so they'll actually buy the game.
And as an example of how that can translate into a trailer,
this idea of just focusing on the hook,
is, so this is a game I worked on,
Way of the Passive Fist,
which is a brawler all about parrying attacks,
and then you kind of nudge them over when they're tired.
But more than that, for this trailer,
I just wanted to convey the idea
that you're this sort of untouchable kung fu master
who just defends effortlessly,
and just completely dominates the enemies.
And it's kind of like, if you...
watch like the end of the Matrix or the tea house scene
in Crashing Tiger, Hidden Dragon,
where there's kind of fighting people off with one hand.
I just wanted to show this.
And then for like the middle of the trailer,
then I kind of expand on the gameplay ideas,
show a little bit of variety and then show like the bosses.
And then by the end, I just kind of wanted to bring it
all the way back to the central idea
about being this untouchable Kung Fu master,
where we just have this kind of final pairing montage
just to show that you're this immovable object.
And then, so yeah, this is just one example
of going in hard on one idea,
but next, Dana has some examples
of some messaging that she's worked on.
Okay.
Cool, so this is an example for the game Old Man's Journey.
Usually, we would just lead with the first sentence,
which is, Old Man's Journey, a soul-searching puzzle
adventure, tells a story of life, loss, precious moments,
and changed plans.
I think that this one worked well for us,
because just in this sentence, you
get an idea of the color of the game.
You can tell that it's.
probably narratively driven, that there's some emotions,
and you get a little bit of an idea
of kind of what you'll do.
The next couple sentences we would use
either where appropriate
or when people wanted more information,
which were shape the landscape
to create the old man's path forward.
Experience heartache and hope
as you embark on a heartfelt journey
through a sun-kissed world.
So these lines essentially show you a little bit about the mechanics, which was really unique for this game.
It also talks about the art using this word sun-kiss, which I think is really appropriate and kind of beautiful for the game.
And you learn a lot just about the experience and how you'll feel and the tone of the game just from really like a couple of sentences.
So this one, hold down, a delightful ball bouncing spectacle.
So this is five words.
And it's simple, it's snappy, it's succinct.
And the game was pretty simple and catchy and snappy.
So there's really no need to make it complicated
if it doesn't need to be.
But just in these words, I think you
get an idea for the feeling you should get while playing,
kind of what you do in the game, and the experience of it
overall.
Okay, and then I worked on the story trailer
for this game Heaven's Vault,
which is a new game by Inkle, who made 80 Days.
And so they made the announced trailer by themselves,
and then they brought me in for the story trailer.
And I asked them, what should the new trailer show?
And the things they mentioned
were actually these three things,
which were what the announced trailer focused on.
Open world adventure, every choice matters,
and decipher language.
And I listened to that, and I thought,
okay, one of those things sounds interesting to me.
which was the decipher language,
because I've never done that in the game.
So for the story trailer, we decided just focus only on that
and we kind of expanded from there.
So we have like history as a science,
you're an archeologist, decipher language,
and you put together history.
Whereas like open world adventure and every choice matters,
it kind of describes the how
and it's like the very video gamey aspect.
And this trailer, we really wanted to focus on the what
and the why, which is kind of like the higher level view.
And I don't know if I can take full credit,
but the trailer was well received,
and a lot of the articles that came out afterwards
really talked a lot about being an archaeologist
and translating language.
And next, we just want to share some games we thought
that have very strong messages.
All right, Sunless Skies,
sail the stars, betray your queen, murder a son.
Superhot, the FPS where time moves only when you move.
Neocab, an emotional survival game.
Firewatch, a mystery set in the Wyoming wilderness
where your only emotional lifeline is the person
on the other end of a handheld radio.
Minute, a peculiar little adventure played in 60 seconds.
And Papers, Please, a dystopian document thriller.
Okay, so we've now told you what to do, what not to do.
We've given you some examples and you're probably like,
Cool, but how do I do this?
So we're gonna walk through some exercises
which ultimately are just questions
that I recommend starting with.
and really thinking through to help you find your message.
So the first one is, what are the emotions
that you want the player to feel?
So a lot of times when I ask this question,
I get the answers fun or nostalgic,
which are kind of like, again, really shallow words,
not really saying much and sort of generic.
So think of like richer words here.
Some good examples would be words like,
infuriated, alive, uncertain of the future, skeptical of the people around you.
You really want to go deep and be super specific to your game.
How would you describe the experience of playing the game? A lot of times for this one, I get fun
and I get an escape, which, like, I know you're all going to be shocked,
but that's a lot of the reason that people play games anyway.
So some good examples here would be things like,
the first feeling of being in love,
the awkwardness of being a teenager,
reminded of times in your life when you've had regrets,
kind of things like that.
What makes this game different, really?
And I add the really because again,
I get a lot of like, uh, uh.
like struggles here, but if you can't answer this question, then it's a really good idea to like go
back and potentially either iterate on your game idea or to actually spend some real time thinking
about this. This is again, ultimately, why is your game different than everything else out there?
What did you create that's like totally uniquely yours? And how can you describe that in a way to
people that's understandable and accessible?
So these next two are probably my favorite questions,
which is, can you describe your game in three words?
So this sounds easy, but it's hard
because I'm going to challenge you to not use any words
that you would like to, like 2D, 3D, satisfying, fun,
adventure, roguelike, epic, unique, anything like that.
And then that will help you actually
kind of get to the heart of what your game really is.
What are you most proud of about the game that you're making?
I like this one a lot because it often really reveals
where the soul is of the game and what you've really
put a lot of care and attention into.
So this can be the sound, the music, the art, the design,
anything involving the game.
And it can often be a really good jumping off point
for what your message should focus on.
Why were you motivated to make this game in the first place?
So there's so many ideas that you could have made,
but you picked this one.
So what told you that this was a game worth making
and that you were so excited about it
that you just had to see it come to fruition?
All right, in this exercise, just keep asking why.
Basically just be your own inner five-year-old.
We just won't stop asking you why.
You know, why is this interesting?
Well, because of this.
Why is that interesting?
Just keep on going.
Just see how deep you can go and what you come up with.
And then Dana mentioned a lot of these,
but just a lot of these words, you should just avoid them
because pretty much everyone uses them,
which means everyone's saying the same thing,
which if you don't use them,
then you'll be different from everyone else.
So yeah, just take a picture of that.
But.
So then when you have your message,
you have to think about how to incorporate it
into a trailer, which is a whole topic unto itself.
But my main tip is just focus on the hook
as much as possible and forget everything else
which makes your game similar to others.
And if there's time, then you get to that.
Because I think a lot of people are just afraid
of putting the thing that is new first.
And they're like, oh, you know,
I'll put the things that they know about.
But it makes it a lot less interesting to see in a trailer.
For example.
And yet, also try to show the idea without spelling it out.
If you have to use text,
like, it's probably not as good of an idea.
Just try to have your trailer have no text
as much as you can,
and then people will just remember it much more
than if they have to kind of read exactly what the game is.
And the other thing is, like, in a trailer,
you have all these sorts of unique tools at your disposal.
You have game capture, you have editing,
you have music, all these ways.
other than words.
And if a picture is worth a thousand words,
then just don't put so many in the trailer.
Okay, let's go on to some lessons and takeaways.
Again, messaging, it's a key part of the process.
Do it early, check it often.
It should be one of the very first things that you do.
And it's often the first experience
that people have with your game, just hearing about it.
Messaging simplifies by providing constraints and focus.
If you find that clear, concise message.
It just makes the marketing process and design process,
telling people about your game, a lot less daunting.
So you won't be kind of caught with nothing to say
when people say, what's your game?
And you'll also feel more confident
about why your game is special,
which will get people excited.
And then always refer back to your message.
It's your guide, it's your roadmap
for all your marketing, all these things.
The more cohesive, the more likely folks
are to remember it and repeat it.
Cool.
So workshop your message.
You are at GDC, which is a great place to test and try out
your message on people.
But also, like other conventions, Twitter, forums,
all good places to gauge the temperature.
Show people video of your game early.
So yes, of course, be strategic with it.
But again, an excellent gauge on if people
are understanding what the experience or flavor is
of your game, and if it's resonating.
And please, coordinate your messaging and your videos.
They're much more powerful and impactful
if they go together and tell the same story.
Thanks.
Woo!
Do we have time for questions?
Okay.
Yeah.
Oh.
A little time.
Please line up at the microphones.
Got like three minutes.
Talk fast.
Hello. Something I found really interesting that you're talking about is shaping your message to as concisely a message that you can.
Do you have any recommendations for creating different versions of that message depending on who you're talking to or making it one sentence versus three sentences?
Yeah.
I think, I mean, that's a really good question.
That's a good thing to do.
I mean, I would say generally with like social media,
you want to be super short and succinct.
I would say similarly with like a website,
you want to have a one-liner.
Like, I think it's always a good idea to have just a one-liner
that's easy, simple.
You can always say it out of your mouth and then to have.
two to three more sentences, you can tack on.
And I also think that certain places, like a press kit,
you can be more verbose.
But anything that's a first line of defense,
I'd make super short.
OK, thank you.
No questions?
You're all total wizards.
OK, cool.
Thanks for coming.
I guess that's it.
Thanks.