How are you guys doing today? How are all your GDC hangovers treating you?
I've been there.
Housekeeping, please silence, mute, airplane mode your phones,
close laptop screens if you don't mind.
You will be getting an email about how you can rate me, how I did.
I hope to earn a good review, but you will be getting that
and you are free to describe me as you see fit.
I'd also like to say it's a huge honor to be presenting here at GDC,
and I take it as a personal honor that you all came to see my presentation.
I know there's a lot of cool stuff going on.
I know there's a lot of important meetings.
So I am very flattered that you came here.
And this talk...
Oops, getting a little excited with my buttons.
There we go.
So this talk is about choice.
The choices we make as game developers
and the trade-offs we have to make to get games made
with the constraints we're all under.
And my favorite quote about this comes from Cliff Bosinski.
It's about the trade-offs you decide on as a designer.
It's like playing an RPG where you have 20 points allocated
to strength, dexterity, and intelligence,
and you can't have it all.
And I love this because you're describing the art of game design
in terms of game design.
It's meta.
So, often we make these kind of decisions based on instinct,
which is fine,
but a lot of times we make them because we get backed into them,
because of those restrictions.
We make these choices reactively.
What I want to propose today is that there's a framework that we can make these decisions proactively
based on who our target end user is, what the competitive set looks like, and what our best practices are.
So to open up, I want to start with a tale of two games that are very near and dear to my heart.
Dark Souls and Resident Evil 6.
Both came out in October their respective years.
Both had about two years of development time.
Resident Evil 6 outsold Dark Souls by about 70% in terms of physical units.
And yet history tends to remember Dark Souls as a critical and commercial success,
and Resident Evil 6 as a critical and commercial failure.
So the relevant question then is,
why is the game that sold 70% more units considered the failure of the two?
And that's what I want to talk about today.
In this presentation, I'm calling strategic design,
or why Dark Souls is the IKEA of games.
So who am I?
I started in the industry about 10 years ago as a humble production intern
at Wide Load Games in Chicago, Illinois.
Worked my way up to a studio lead senior producer position
on games like Guilty Party, Avengers Initiative.
And with our sister studio, Avalanche, working on Disney Infinity.
Over that time, I really developed a firm belief that the human cost of making games in terms of layoffs and crunch and health issues and studio closures and uncertainty was a little more than I could stomach.
And I decided the best way for me to be able to positively impact that would be to learn as much about business and management as I could.
So in addition to working full-time and raising kids,
I went to night school and earned an MBA
at Northwestern University.
I'm currently working as a consultant,
notably with my friends at Ragtag,
as they work to finish Raise the Dead.
I'm also trying to get my own company,
Agency Principal, up and running and off the ground.
And I write regularly in my blog, Breaking the Wheel,
where I apply these sort of business theoretical concepts
to game development.
So if you enjoy this talk, there's a lot more material there.
Shameless plug.
All right.
So if you go to business school, you will run into this guy a lot.
This guy's name is Michael Porter from the Harvard Business School.
He's a Ph.D. in economics and a luminary in the field of business strategy.
And he has two major claims to fame.
One is something called a five forces analysis, and the other is codifying what he calls a
true competitive advantage.
To understand a competitive advantage, you have to understand another of his constructs,
which is called the productivity frontier.
This graph compares the value a product has for the end user versus the cost to make it.
That arc represents the line of best practice.
It's the equilibrium point in a market.
You can't do better than that line.
You can't get something that's more valuable for customers without it costing more,
and you can't cut costs without reducing value.
This is like the pinnacle of best practices in an industry.
Eventually a company's gonna figure out how to get past that
through some new process or best practice
or patent or intellectual property or
access to no-sum resource.
And for a while they're gonna have a market advantage.
They're gonna be able to make things faster for cheaper.
But eventually the market will catch up.
And we all as a society
benefit because products overall are
better and cheaper, but everybody benefits except for
that one company. And Porter calls this
shifting the productivity frontier.
The moral of this story is that faster, cheaper, better
is only a temporary advantage.
You cannot derive a sustained market advantage
from operational efficiency alone.
So what do you do?
In his landmark article,
What is Strategy? Harvard Business Review, 1996,
I highly recommend you read it,
Porter offers what he calls a true competitive advantage
based on three things.
Making trade-offs, I'm sorry, being different,
making trade-offs, and achieving fit.
So what do these things mean?
First off, being different.
It means creating something that is unique and valuable.
You can do this in one of three ways according to Porter.
You can be few things to many people.
His example is Jiffy Lube.
They will work on any car, but they will only do car lubricants.
So they don't do body work.
They don't do engine work, just car lubricants.
You can be many things to few people.
His example is Bessemer Trust,
which is a full-featured financial services company
that will handle all your banking needs,
but only if you have at least $250,000 of liquid assets.
Or you can be many things to many people in a narrow market.
Porter's example is Carnal Lake Cinemas,
which is a theater chain, full featured,
but only operates in cities of 150,000 people or less.
Now to understand why being unique and different
is so important, I direct you to the Kawasaki Matrix.
This is something that Guy Kawasaki of Apple fame
brings up in every talk I've ever seen him give on YouTube.
It's a very simple two by two matrix
that compares uniqueness to value.
So if you are valuable but not unique,
you have to compete on your margin.
You have to give...
consumers more for their dollar and get less in return,
which means you have to sell more units to compensate.
Extreme example would be toilet paper.
Very valuable, not unique.
So toilet paper companies have to offer more sheets per roll,
more rolls per dollar than the competition,
and that's why toilet paper companies make about a penny
per package or a penny per roll in terms of profit.
If you're not valuable and not unique,
you're essentially the dot-com boom.
You're creating a bunch of stuff that's not useful
for customers, but makes a lot of money
for hedge fund managers and stock speculators.
If you're unique but not valuable, in Kawasaki's words,
you're just kind of stupid.
You're making something nobody's gonna buy,
and you're spending a lot of time.
Now if you're doing that for your own artistic means,
totally cool, but if you have an intent to sell it
and nobody wants to buy it,
you're kind of wasting a lot of time.
So you want to be here, unique and valuable,
where you can sell things to people that they wanna buy,
you can charge them a price that they think is fair,
but still allows you to maintain a healthy margin.
Kawasaki's mnemonic to remember this is,
you wanna be like George W. Bush, high and to the right.
I don't know exactly what he means by that,
but I remember it, so clearly it works.
Next up, trade-offs.
It's important to recognize that doing everything
is not strategy, it is indecision.
Strategy means often choosing what not to do.
Example here, the production triangle.
Good, cheap, fast, you don't get all three.
It's hard to have a service
that is both luxurious and fast.
It's hard to have a product that has lots of options
and is easy to use.
And you've got to recognize that some activities are incompatible,
like I just mentioned.
Next up is fit.
This is a really key concept for a competitive strategy.
Your activities need to fit each other.
They need to interact and reinforce one another.
So, for example, if you're using multiplayer code,
it behooves you to have mechanics that don't require
a high degree of computational precision.
This is why it's really hard to do net code for Street Fighter.
Now, why is this so important?
Being different allows you to uniquely serve a target audience.
Trade-offs allow you to serve that target audience
at a lower cost than anybody else,
and fit makes it harder for other companies
to compete with you.
They cannot just replicate one part of your value chain.
They have to replicate all of it to replicate your success.
Porter's example was Southwest Airlines.
Now in the 20 years since What Is Strategy came out,
they've since changed their MO a little bit,
but back in 1996, Southwest was many things to few people.
It was a full-service airline
catering to price-sensitive customers
who didn't care about perks
and were going between regional airports.
Southwest made a lot of trade-offs.
They only stuck to regional airports,
so you wouldn't find them in O'Hare or LAX.
They had no frequent flyer program,
they had no first class seating,
they didn't deal with baggage transfers,
and they only used 737 jets,
which meant they couldn't do long-haul flights.
This would seem to put them at a disadvantage
until you consider the element of fit.
The fact that they're in regional airports
meant they had to pay less for gate rights.
They didn't have to negotiate as hard.
The fact that they had no frequent flyer program
meant that they'd streamline ticketing.
The fact that there was no first class seating
and no baggage transfer
meant they could turn around planes in about half the time.
And the fact that they only used 737 jets
means that they only had to train their crews
to service 737 jets
and only had to carry parts for 737 jets,
which reduced their overhead.
And that effect is that Southwest
was faster, cheaper, and better,
but for the target consumer.
They made a choice.
We're gonna target these people over here
at the expense of these people over here,
which is totally fine.
And there's no secret sauce here, there's no trade secret.
They just had very good operational harmony.
Now how effective is this?
1993, Continental launches Continental Light
with the intent of going directly head-to-head
with Southwest Airlines.
But they didn't make the same trade-offs.
They kept their frequent flyer program,
they kept first class seating,
they kept baggage transfers,
they used different kinds of jets.
Total failure.
Such a bad failure, they killed it two years later.
Board of Directors fired the CEO over it.
Porter's other example is IKEA.
Much like Southwest, IKEA is all things to few people.
They are targeting young, price-sensitive customers
who are price-sensitive but not time-sensitive
and have rigid schedules
because they're early in their careers.
They can't dictate their own hours yet.
IKEA makes a lot of trade-offs.
They're often located way the hell out in BFE,
so you gotta drive way out to get to them.
There's no show people.
There's no customization.
You gotta build it yourself.
They offer food court and childcare,
and they are open late.
Much like Southwest, this would seem to put Ikea
at a disadvantage until you consider the element of fit.
So the fact they're in the suburbs means
they can have a really large property for really cheap,
which means they can have bigger parking lots,
which makes it easier to park,
bigger showrooms to show more furniture,
and bigger warehouses so they can have
more on-hand inventory.
Customers don't mind making the trip.
They're not time-sensitive.
They just want a deal.
The fact that there's no show people means
you have less staff.
You have less operational overhead.
And customers are fine showing themselves around because
What you see is what you get.
You don't need salespeople because you can see
the Gajora bed right next to the Norenberg lamp on top of the...
I can't remember all the names of these things,
but you know what I'm saying.
Like, you can just see the furniture right there.
You don't need a salesperson to describe it to you.
And the fact that there's no customization
means they have streamlined manufacturing.
It's really easy to have a streamlined process
if you just have to make one kind of a thing over and over again.
It's easy to store and deliver boxes
because they stack really well in trucks and in cars and in warehouse shelves.
And time-insensitive customers don't mind building
because they have time, they just don't have money.
So those amenities, the food court, the daycare,
the fact that they're open late
would seem like extravagances,
but it means that customers can go straight from work
because there'll be food there.
They don't have to get a sitter
because Ikea will take care of their kids.
And they don't have to rush and stress themselves out
about finding traffic because Ikea's gonna be open late.
The net effect is, once again,
Ikea is better for the target customer
while still being profitable.
But it has reduced appeal to time sensitive,
price insensitive customers who want customization and high quality.
Again, IKEA made a choice.
We're going to target these people over here at the expense of these people over here.
That is the essence of strategy.
So to the meat of the presentation, why is Dark Souls the IKEA of games?
If it's not obvious by now, I mean that as a compliment.
So let's think of the target audience for Dark Souls.
A hardcore gamer, enjoys discovery,
likes pushing the boulder up the hill like Sisyphus.
Wants depth and wants thrilling menacing experiences.
These are gamers who want games that are like badges of honor if they win.
Now, does Dark Souls meet the criteria for a competitive advantage?
Was it different?
Ah, sorry.
Excuse me. Excuse my head.
Was it different?
Did it make trade-offs?
Did it have fit?
Dark Souls is definitely different.
It was a hardcore, unforgiving, no-frills game
in an industry of cinematic mass-market titles.
I'm pretty sure that picture is from one of the later
Dark Souls games, but a $200 million person body count
really kind of emphasizes my point here.
Dark Souls makes a lot of trade-offs.
Few cinematics, almost no tutorial, one difficulty level,
sparse music, limited multiplayer,
and it wasn't exactly using a cutting-edge engine.
Much like Ikea and Southwest, this would seem to put
Dark Souls at a disadvantage until you think about fit.
So the fact that there's few cinematics and very little tutorial
means you had to figure it out for yourself.
Tutorials are a rat's nest of edge cases.
Cinematics can be expensive to produce.
You don't have them to lead somebody by the hand.
That means you got to figure it out for yourself.
That means it is the difficult game that the target audience really wants.
You got to figure out how Dark Souls works.
Or you buy the strategy guide if you're a punk.
I bought the strategy guide.
It was one difficulty level means you have focus balancing.
You don't have to bounce for easy, medium, hard, extra hard.
There's just the Dark Souls level of difficulty.
And that means it's take it or leave it.
If you beat Dark Souls, you have to beat Dark Souls,
which means you're one of the elite,
which means it has that badge of honor
that the target sect was looking for.
Sparse music cuts costs,
but it also makes the world of Dark Souls
feel far more sparse and desolate and menacing.
So it's a cut that made it better.
This is the essence of a competitive advantage.
Limited multiplayer is focused multiplayer.
And the fact that they're reusing the tech from Dark Souls
reduces some of their unknowns.
Known tech, or you know, experience tech is known tech,
is predictable tech, you know, relatively speaking.
These trade-offs combine to create a harsh, uncomfortable,
sink or swim experience, which is exactly what
the target audience was looking for.
And from software genre experts,
they've been making this kind of game since Kingsfield on the PS1.
This really helps them hone their,
hone what they're doing and hone their activities.
The net effect is it felt tailor-made for an audience
that often feels ignored or overlooked
by the AAA games industry.
And these trade-offs allow Dark Souls,
or From Software, to focus effort
without sacrificing quality, again, for the target audience.
And that means that Dark Souls could be more profitable
with a smaller market.
And in deference to Mr. Porter,
I call this notion strategic design.
Now, if we contrast this with the other game
from my introduction, Resident Evil 6,
and I say this as somebody for whom
Resident Evil is my favorite game series ever.
Resident Evil 6 tried to do the opposite.
It tried to take a niche brand to the mass market.
Producer at the time said,
we're making games and we need to have
mass market appeal to survive.
And that mass market design approach,
trying to target as many people as possible,
meant that Resident Evil 6 couldn't cut costs
and had a hurdle rate of seven million units.
In the intro I said,
Resident Evil 6 outsold Dark Souls by 70%.
It would have to have sold an additional 40%
to make its own target.
The net effect is best expressed by Resident Evil 7's producer,
Masashiki Kawata,
by trying to please everyone, you please no one.
And if the direction of Resident Evil 7 is any indication,
this was a lesson painfully learned.
Now, some of you might be asking,
how intentional was this on FromSoftware's part?
How intentional were these designs?
Were they thinking, did they read Michael Porter's article?
Were they thinking in terms of cuts and targeting a target market?
The honest, no bullshit answer is, I don't know.
I tried to find out.
I wrote to Bandai Namco, they couldn't help me.
I reached through a press contract to go through some PR contacts at Bandai Namco, they couldn't
help me.
If you go to FromSoftware's website, they tell you to go to Bandai Namco.
So I ran into a dead end.
But really that's not my point.
My point is not that FromSoftware read Michael Porter's What a Strategy and decided to emulate
it.
My point is that Dark Souls provides a prototype by which you can make these decisions intentionally.
I believe that Dark Souls verifies that this framework can apply to games effectively.
So to that end, recommendations in seven timeless quotes.
First of all, he who defends everything defends nothing,
Friedrich the Great, King of Prussia.
I'm gonna reiterate this because it bears reiterating.
Strategy means making choices,
deciding what to do and deciding what not to do.
And always recognize that trade-offs yield benefits.
They reduce costs and they make it harder
for other companies to compete.
And I see lots of cameras going off and that's cool,
but I'm gonna give you a link to download these slides,
so don't stress about getting every frame.
Good example here is XCOM.
XCOM was XCOM.
If you weren't there to get slapped around
by a really hard turn-based strategy game,
it did not make any compromises for you.
And that is exactly what it should have done.
And that's why it's so successful
and why its fans are so ravenous about it.
Because it served them very well
and it didn't make compromises to dilute the experience
for that target segment.
Next up, know thy enemy and know thyself
and in a hundred battles you will never be in peril.
Sun Tzu.
So get to know your target audience
and figure out what it really wants.
This is basic marketing research stuff.
You can do persona exercises
where you hypothesize a member of the audience,
try to think ahead of what they might be about,
what they're interested in, what their day looks like,
what kind of media they consume.
Go out and actually find some of them,
do one-on-one interviews, talk to them,
see what they're actually about.
You can use more advanced survey techniques
like factor and cluster analysis and conjoined analysis
if you wanna know what the hell that means.
It's in the appendix of these slides which you can download,
but I can also talk about it during Q&A if you're interested,
but you might need a professional survey company to help you with that.
But you want to use this information to pick your trade-offs and prioritize features.
A good example here is Supercell.
Supercell knows how to dial in an audience really well.
They kill off anything that's not going to be a huge hit with their audience,
and they know how to test and test and retest until they have games that are going to be huge hits.
That's why Hay Day and Clash of Clans are still on the top of the charts multiple years later.
If I'd asked people what they want, they would have said faster horses, Henry Ford.
So those last few slides notwithstanding,
I am not advocating design by focus group or design by survey.
That is a road to mediocrity.
And the reason is because people don't know what they want.
It's your job to show them.
This is one case where I think that asshole is absolutely correct.
Now, this sounds pretentious, but I think what Jobs meant is that
most people, most consumers are not professional product developers
and most gamers are not professional game designers.
It is not reasonable to ask them to construct things
and conceive game designs in their head.
That's not what their training is.
They don't know what they want yet.
But they do know what they like,
and that is a very important distinction to draw.
Don't know what they want, but they do know what they like.
So figure out what they're passionate about.
Figure out what needs other games aren't answering.
Tailor your feature set accordingly.
Great example here is Resident Evil 4,
which is my favorite game of all time,
and kind of my apology for shitting on Resident Evil 6 a little bit.
Shinji Mikami had gone to guys like me,
who were huge Resident Evil fans, and said,
what do you want in the next game?
We probably would have said more zombies,
bigger guns, bigger mansions, more puzzles.
Instead, he scrapped that design
and rebirthed both a genre and a game series
with one of the most successful games of the last decade.
I think he knew exactly what he wanted to do.
I think he knew what the audience was interested in,
and he was okay with trusting his instinct
to give them something that met their needs,
but wasn't exactly what they asked for.
Retreat, hell, we are just attacking
in a different direction.
Lieutenant General Chesty Puller.
So, in this concept of strategic design,
I'm not advocating that you resign yourself
to subsistence revenue or hiding from the competition.
I'm not saying you should get used to
scratching a living off bare rocks.
It's not, and it's also not about
compromising quality to save money.
The goal here is to find underserved niches,
make games those niches will love,
and then use trade-offs to make that niche profitable
and make it harder for other companies to compete with you.
Good example here is Gone Home.
Gone Home knew exactly the kind of game it was gonna make.
If you read the design, it would seem very humble,
but their dedication to that idea
and to serving the people who want to play that kind of game
earned them a level of notability and accord
that belied how simple that design was.
And they deserve every bit of that accord, in my opinion.
Music is the space between notes, Claude Debussy.
So when you're considering what cuts to make,
don't just take a hatchet to your design.
Don't just hack things off willy-nilly
without thinking through what you're trying to do.
You want to try to cut things that run contrary
to your target feature set to enable it to be,
to enable yourself to focus on those targets.
Example here, Uncharted.
Uncharted, for lack of a better term,
was trying to make the Indiana Jones video games.
To that end, they had these very beautiful, refined,
well-shot, well-acted, well-motion-captured cinematic scenes.
It's what we all love about that series.
It's easy to forget, and I forgot this
till I replayed it a couple months ago,
that game was about four hours long.
They cut quantity to support quality.
It certainly did not hurt the franchise's
long-term prospects, as we all know.
The enemy of art is the absence of limitations.
Orson Welles.
According to his friend, Henry Yagam.
We don't actually know if he said this, but it's still a good quote.
The idea here is not to constrain creativity.
Don't be a glass half empty person.
The idea is to focus attention, efforts, and resources where they will provide the most value.
Both to your gamers and your company.
Good example here, the Doom reboot.
Now, Doom eschewed a lot of features that prevailing logic would tell you modern shooters need.
There was no romance, there was no ill-advised stealth section,
weren't a ton of cinematics.
It was a very focused design that was all about kill things dead real good.
And that focus did not hurt the game.
That focus made it an exceptional shooter that stands out drastically in the current field.
Finally, the opposite of love is not hate, it's indifference.
Elie Wessel.
Now, a lot of things, a bunch of professional...
entrepreneurs and marketers and product developers get wrong is they get way too hung up about
if people are going to hate their product, or in this case, hate their game.
But in order for one niche to love your game, you have to accept that another niche is probably
going to hate it.
And that shouldn't bother you because if the people who hate your game are diametrically
opposed to your target audience, the fact that those people hate it is perversely supporting
evidence.
It means you're probably on target.
What should freak you out a lot more than hate is indifference,
because indifference means that people can't even be bothered to hate your game.
They don't even care.
So always remember that passionate fans are what create valuable brands.
This is why engagement is far more important than traffic at a website.
A million people showed up to your site.
Who cares?
Did they read anything? Did they buy anything?
Did they sign up for a mailing list?
Did they post about it on Facebook?
Did they tell their friends about it?
Having a thousand people who are highly engaged is way more valuable
than having a million people show up and go,
Now, another thing professional entrepreneurs, marketers, product developers get way too hung up on
is the size of the target audience, whether it's too small.
But it's important to recognize that your target audience is not the same thing as your addressable market.
Your target audience builds your addressable market.
How? Through good old-fashioned word of mouth.
Your fans will evangelize for your game.
And it's important to remember that word of mouth is the most valuable form of marketing there is.
And it's the most valuable because it's the only form of marketing you cannot buy.
You have to earn it.
You can try doing stealth and astroturf things, but you will get caught.
So you can only get word of mouth the old-fashioned way.
But your fans are only going to evangelize for you
if they're passionately engaged because you made something that they love.
So examples here, Abound, Kerbal Space Program, Counter-Strike, League of Legends, Halo,
Minecraft alone demonstrates this point for me.
So, if you want to be the next Ikea or Dark Souls,
or Star Wars, or Apple, or Harry Potter, or Nine Inch Nails.
Don't spend so much time worrying about making something that everybody's going to buy.
Focus instead on making something that a segment of people will really love.
And with that, I will turn it over for questions.
But first, here's my contact info.
If you scan that QR code, you'll get my contact details.
Two underscores, don't forget it on the Twitter.
You don't want to get the one underscore Justin Fisher.
He hasn't tweeted in like seven years.
And that bit.ly link will give you annotated slides
if you're interested.
And I'm sharing them under a Creative Commons 4.0 license,
so distribute them at your studios, amongst your friends.
Just don't sell them or you gotta give me a cut.
And also, if you enjoy my peculiar way
of looking at the world, I'm doing another session
on Friday about applying operation science
to game development.
So if you've got production nerdy friends
who are into production nerdy stuff,
I welcome them with open arms.
So any questions at the mics?
Oh, thank you.
Applause
I see one person walking up.
Hi.
Hello.
I'm just wondering if you think, because Dark Souls is a console game.
Do you think that console exclusivity plays into what you're talking about as far as like a limitation that could be beneficial?
It can be, yeah. I mean it should be where and who you target should be interrelated with your console, your platform choices.
Like Halo is a great example of...
You have one console that would seem to put you at a disadvantage,
but it also allows you to focus your design on what you're trying to make
and focus your technical efforts on what the specific hardware requirements are.
So yeah, definitely that.
If you're doing that in an intelligent way, you can really limit the ability,
the potential for analysis paralysis.
Does that answer your question?
Yep.
Thank you.
What are your thoughts on, like...
identifying these niches based on sort of your own personal experience and anecdotal
evidence versus like market research, because I often find that producers and that they
want that market research.
Yeah.
It's hard to do.
I mean, if you have lots of marketing muscle and dedicated marketing departments, it's
a lot easier to kind of defer that work.
I think it's games to me are not like consumer products.
They're all micro startups.
So to me, it's the same thing as how base level startups in their early phases try to find customers.
You go out and check.
She who are you talking to who you who and whose hands are you putting builds?
Who are you testing with like don't undervalue the ability of shoe leather to start answering these questions for you and.
If you're targeting the right people, if you're looking at those people who are really interested in being
at the ground floor, who like to be at the cutting edge of game development,
don't underestimate the ability of you to flatter them by bringing them in early.
And that's how you can start building that base level of word of mouth.
If somebody's like, hey, these guys brought me in, they asked my opinion, they let me see things,
that can be a great way to start building that following.
Does that make sense?
Yep.
Cool, thank you.
I just have one question about like, if you're...
You're building a game and you launch it and it's sort of like a good minimum viable product.
It's the Dark Souls of whatever you're doing.
If it has success and you continue updating it, you slowly add more and more features
and cruft and it suddenly becomes not that experience.
What do you think about that and how would you manage that type of game design and development?
I think that sort of iteration, and there's plenty of examples of it, there's nothing
wrong with evolving and...
And bringing in more people over time.
I mean, I think that, and especially for like businesses,
that's kind of what you want to do.
So to me, there's nothing bad about it,
as long as you're being intentional about it.
Like, okay, we think this has a broader appeal
to these people, and hopefully this feature set.
But if you don't want to do it as like a panic routine,
like we aren't selling enough,
so let's just rope in more people
without a really strategy.
Let's just make it as mass market as possible.
That's where you're running into trouble.
Or if you're really diluting what...
the core of what your game is, that core value proposition,
and kind of messing it up with putting too much extraneous crap around it.
That's where you can start running into problems.
So, to me, it's an analysis-driven decision.
Like, bringing more people, talk to them, have them play it, see what they think.
Are sales getting better or worse?
You still, like you feel, are honoring the core values of the product.
And that's how I would approach it.
Thanks.
Sure.
This is somewhat related to that, maybe a little bit theoretical, but...
Do you think it's possible to take what Dark Souls did in terms of trade-offs
and refocus that on a different audience, maybe even a larger audience?
If you start selling groceries in an Ikea format, do you get Trader Joe's?
Like, will that work?
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, again, as long as you understand what your targeted audience is looking for
and what trade-offs are either acceptable or in some ways preferable to them,
like the Dark Souls difficulty thing,
then yeah, I don't think the lesson from Dark Souls
is that people want really hard games that are in a medieval setting with monsters.
I think the lesson is that people want games that are made for them.
And that make them feel like somebody is paying attention to them and wants to service them specifically.
So if you can figure out what makes people feel like they're being serviced specifically
and that their needs are being answered, then it could work for any genre, any game.
You just have to balance.
The more people you get, the less...
The more people you're trying to target, the less specific you can get to their needs.
And that's where the balance point is.
And that's where you need to focus on your trade-offs and where your specific value point is.
Does that make sense?
Thanks, yeah.
Sure.
So if you think about Dark Souls in terms of...
strategically delivering a project or product to a niche audience that were kind of forgotten
by the industry.
Do you think that strategical advantage might get lost now that we as an industry are maturing
and not forgetting about audiences and trying to balance out the products and therefore
strategical advantage will only come from creating new genres and new products for audiences
that haven't been catered to at all yet?
No, I don't think it only needs to be new products
because if Dark Souls was a constantly evolving,
constantly new content coming out kind of thing,
like an Uber, like it just constantly persists,
then yeah, I think you would need to constantly find
new things to go to, but
Dark Souls can coexist in a world with Niall.
And those two things, you don't say like,
oh, I'm going to buy fewer copies of Dark Souls
because Niall is not here.
It is scratching the same itch,
it's serving the same audience,
it's got a different bend to it.
At that point, you gotta figure out,
your competitive set is not just everything that's out there,
but what's coming out proximate to your release
and what's gonna get buzzed around the same time as you.
So that's where that strategic plan has to come in too.
Like, whose needs am I servicing?
And not just are there other games,
but are there other games that will be high profile
at the same time?
Does that answer your question?
A little bit.
I guess, you know, this industry's quite known
for fast follow, so Dark Souls does well,
then everyone wants to make a good-sized game,
and no one's making AAA games anymore,
so then 10 years later, oh wait,
we should make a cinematic AAA game,
you know what I mean?
So.
That goes to my point when I was making the other guy of
the lesson of Dark Souls is not like make Dark Souls,
it's make games for people.
And the lesson of Halo was not people want guys in green
shoots blowing up aliens, it's that console gamers
also like to shoot things.
So it's figuring out what needs they're addressing
and not focusing on the topical sort of cosmetic trends
of what made Dark Souls, but really digging into
the strategic nature of it.
The fast fall itself is, you know, it's a investment strategy.
Like, there's less risk here, but there's also less upside
because now you're competing on margin again.
So you have to be aware of that when you're making these decisions.
And one of the best lessons I learned in business school
is that there's not really good or bad decisions usually,
they're all trade-offs.
And you've got to figure out which trade-off is most suitable to you,
most honors your core values, most honors your strategic goals.
So there's a trade-off there between known...
And unknown and compete on margin versus unique and valuable.
And you got to decide what the right balance point is for you
and what's right for your customer base
and your game and your project and your finances.
Does that better answer it?
Yes.
Thank you.
Please.
Hey, great talk.
Thanks.
Thank you.
How important do you think it is, or I guess I'd like to know your thoughts on
changing these design principles from game to game
versus companies that make their whole kind of image in
one style of game over and over.
Yeah, the trick you, so again, that's another trade-off.
If you keep making the same game like From Software, you get to,
you can establish a lot of best practices, you accrue a lot of
intelligence about it, you accrue a lot of, what's the word I'm looking for?
A core competency about what that thing is the trick there though is.
For instance destiny bungee.
It's going to be hard and can take a long time before destiny ever gets mentioned without halo coming up.
It's going to be very hard for like Shinji Mikami.
He made The Evil Within, which is very similar to Resident Evil 4.
He's going to have a hard time making any game like that without them somebody bringing in,
oh, this is the guy who made Resident Evil 4.
So the more you stay within your comfort zone, the more you're going to live in your own shadow.
And that's not, again, that's neither good nor bad, but that's a trade-off you've got to consider.
You know, how much do you want to be beholden to your legacy versus how much do you want to stick within your core competency where you can maximize your efficiencies?
But like IKEA, we all know IKEA's principles,
and they're not starting new businesses or new stores
that have totally different principles.
I'm wondering, do they really succeed
because it's so consistent and we always know?
Or can you make games that are,
I mean obviously you can make games that keep changing it up,
but I just wonder how important it is
to basically know your shtick and own it
and put your stake in the ground
so people stay away from your space.
I mean, yeah, the more formidable you are, the more of an expert you are,
like, it's going to be hard to go head-to-head with Cliff Buzinski on a third-person shooter.
Kind of thing, so, yeah, it does become easier to claim, to stake out your claim.
And make it known that I own this, and the more you show up here, the more
you reinforce my position as the industry leader.
Like, the more somebody, like when Resident Evil was at its heyday in the PlayStation era.
The more games that showed up that were survival horror,
the more they reinforced, A, the name survival horror,
and B, reinforced Resident Evil as the premier game in that genre.
Like, we own it and we define these terms.
And when that market started getting crowded,
they reinvented it and redefined what survival horror is,
but still, you know, Dead Space comes out,
Resident Evil 4 still comes up.
Gears of War came out, Resident Evil 4 came up.
That's, again, that's part of the trade-off.
Like you secure that position and people,
everybody who shows up to your party
reinforces that you're the head of the party,
which is a good thing.
But you also, if you want to go start a new party
that's kind of on the same,
playing the same dance list or music list,
you're also going to be in your own shadow.
Does that answer your question?
Yep, yep, thank you.
Hey, quick one.
Can you think of any games that did appeal
to everyone that said we're going to,
anybody with a screen in front of their face,
whether, you know, whatever they're doing,
they're going to play this game,
they're going to enjoy it.
It definitely works. I mean, Rock Band, Wii Bowling, Super Mario Bros.
Like, there are definitely examples.
And, again, trade-offs.
You should not target a broad spectrum
just because some dork at GDC said so.
It's just be aware of the trade-off you're taking.
You know, the more you make a game for everybody,
the less you make a game for anybody.
And there is a balance point in what your game design is,
how broadly acceptable it is, how big that market is,
the likeliness of that market to buy with a game being
as not specific as it is.
Like, these are all numbers that need to factor
into your calculus.
So it can totally work.
I mean, we've seen it work.
So the goal is not to say, like, you have to do this,
but what I want to reinforce is that you should be intentional
about this decision and really think about the consequences
of your trade-offs.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, thank you.
Sure.
I thank you very much everybody. I really appreciate.