All right, let's get this started.
So, right after this talk,
it's just gonna steamroll right into,
steamroll, you like that?
Plug, into Jaleel's part two, but.
Before that, Tricks of the Trade.
Last year, Tricks of the Trade was the number one rated talk
of the first two days of the bootcamp summit, everything.
It was great, it was amazing.
Alex did a great job setting it up.
The baton was passed this year to Christian,
and he assembled a new group of people
to just rapid fire drop a ton of knowledge
and process into your brain.
So I'm gonna get out of the way
and let them do what they do.
Give it up for the Tricks of the Trade.
Oh my god, okay, alright.
Are you ready?
Okay.
Hi everyone, welcome to the second edition
of Tricks of the Trade.
My name's Christian Jeanjic
and I'm an animation director for Ubisoft.
And I'm gonna be your host today.
I've been lucky enough to work on various different studios
on games such as Assassin's Creed, Splinter Cell,
and Watch Dogs 2, but basically I love gameplay animation,
which is why we're all here, right?
I haven't got time for that.
Sat up here with me is an amazing diverse panel
of industry talent with over 70 years
of combined animation experience.
They're still hungry to learn and eager to share
their tips and tricks with you.
But first, a quick thank you.
You all clearly appreciated the fantastic content
in last year's Tricks of the Trade,
making it the number one animation talk at GDC.
But why?
Well, it's full of bite-sized pieces of animation gold,
tips from industry veterans that you could take
and immediately apply to your work
as soon as you leave this hall.
And of course, the presenters were pretty great as well.
But of course, and then, so this year,
we're returning with even more
in 30 minutes of knowledge sharing
that will hopefully help you level up
your animation and industry skill.
Okay, the only way we're gonna develop as an industry
is if we share and we pay it forward.
These tips have helped us speed up our daily workflow
that we've learned from our peers.
And so in the interest of sharing,
we hope this encourages you to share with us too.
So the format is pretty simple.
Six panelists, three tips each, five minutes a piece,
which means we're gonna be going pretty fast.
So don't worry about taking notes.
Everything's gonna be on the GDC Vault.
So buckle up and enjoy.
First up is gonna be Mario.
This is the Animation Bootcamp.
Tricks of the Trade, let's get started.
Oh my god, okay, I'm back, I'm up here again.
So, hi, I'm Mariel, I'm lead animator
and art director for Lab Zero Games.
We made a game called Skullgirls
and now we're making a game called Invisible.
My experience in game animation has been entirely in 2D,
but I think my tips today can help
all kinds of animators, hopefully.
So, since we're starting, this might be an obvious one,
but we could start with something basic.
This is a question I've gotten before, so I figure we can kind of cover it.
So when I start animating a new game character, the first thing I start with isn't a run,
an attack, or a jump, or anything like that.
It's the idle pose.
This is the root of all your animations.
This is where they start and end.
What should your idol pose look like though?
You can use the opportunity to get some personality in there,
but also you should keep in mind how the idol will connect to the rest of the character's animations.
For example, for our archer Zebe here,
we needed to make sure his moves matched the way he was holding the bow and arrow in his idol.
A lot of the concepts had him switching hands, so we needed to make sure they all lined up.
Did it switch? Okay.
Also important is to remember not just the idle animation itself, but the transition
to and from your idles.
Game animations are actually interrupting each other all the time because different
things are happening, so making sure that you return to that same base is going to help
your animation feel more seamless as they transition.
And especially in 2D, it's important to remember
that the idol itself is also a motion.
I think what can end up happening
if you don't pay attention is that you treat the idol
as a single pose and animate as if you're easing
into that single pose.
But since the idol itself is a motion,
you need to treat the start and ends
of all the animations connecting to it
as a continuous motion.
So you need to be aware of where you're coming from
and where you're going to as you animate moves
stemming from the idol.
So, tip number two.
At our studio, we've gone from making a fighting game
to a platforming RPG.
And they're both like games viewed from the side,
they kinda look the same,
so that means we can animate them the same, right?
But actually, a key thing changed between our two games,
how far away the camera was.
In Skullgirls, our fighting game,
the characters are large on screen
because they essentially are the entire game.
Subtle touches came across in the animations
because they were just so big.
And then we started to animate our second game, Indivisible,
which is a platforming RPG.
And we actually quickly realized that we couldn't approach it
in exactly the same way.
We zoomed out the camera, and a lot of the detail
we had put into Skullgirl's characters
just became noise when viewed from the zoom in Indivisible.
So we had to simplify everything.
Our animations, our characters, we just kind of
had to re-look at what we were doing.
Subtle animations had to be exaggerated a lot more,
just so you could actually see them on the screen.
And this doesn't just apply to us.
What kind of game are you making?
Are you viewing your character from the side,
the top down, is it first person?
If you're working on something like League of Legends
or Diablo where your animations are viewed from above,
you might not see expressions
that you want to animate on the character.
You even need to approach your key poses differently
because your silhouette reads differently from the top.
If you're working on a first-person game and you can run right up to an NPC or a monster,
you might want to put facial animations or subtle idols in there to create better immersion in that
world. Or alternatively, how often are you even going to see the close-ups of the monsters you're
destroying? Do you even need to see that detail if you're always shooting them from 500 feet away?
It all depends on what you're making and how you can get your animation to best
serve how the player is going to be looking at it. Oops, I went too far.
Okay, so try animating something as simple
as turning around in place.
Do you just instinctively know where your feet go
and what they do?
Do you know where your shoulders and hips are?
Do you know where your head's looking?
Are your eyes open?
Are they closed?
If you know all this,
that's kind of amazing,
cause I don't know.
So whenever you can,
you need to act things out.
You need to get up out of your chair.
I know it's hard.
And you need to act out the motion you're trying to make.
It helps so much to really feel the motion you're trying to animate in your own body.
Act out what you're trying to do and feel where you're putting your weight, which is
so so important in animation.
And you can also record yourself or your friends or take photos of poses like this stupid one
of me here.
For example, for this move in particular,
we had an idea of the poses we wanted to hit,
but figuring out how they connected was difficult.
And the solution was just to get up and try it ourselves,
like you see here.
It's things like this that maybe you could figure out
if you just kind of sat at your desk
and thought about it for a long time.
But even then, I still don't think you'd arrive
at a convincing result.
You really need to feel and understand the subtleties of the motion you're trying to recreate on screen,
and to do that you have to get up out of your chair and just do it.
And that's it for me! Next we have Zach!
APPLAUSE
Sorry, I have to make this slightly bigger because I'm going blind.
Uh...
Hello, I'm Zach Lowry.
I'm a senior animator and designer at BossKey Productions,
working on the competitive first-person shooter LawBreakers.
So I've been deemed the guy that's gonna talk
about first-person tips,
and having me follow Matt Boehm today is kinda cruel,
but I'm gonna do my best and probably echo
some of the stuff that he talked about.
So before joining BossKey, I was at Volition for 10 years
and I worked on the entirety of the Saints Row franchise
and that was a third person open world game.
So for the last two years, I've been working
on the majority of first person stuff
and today I want to focus my tips on things
that can help people transitioning from third person
to first person because you definitely have to approach this
from a different perspective.
No, no laughs, all right.
It's, phew.
Yeah, you get it now.
All right, so third person animation setup.
We've all animated typical third person setup.
The root drives the center of mass, the weapon is constrained to the hand, and the hand drives
the weapon.
In third person, you're animating character first and the weapon is secondary.
I'm off already.
You're animating the character first and the weapon is secondary.
Okay, so, but when you set this up in first person,
you get this interesting center of mass
of the weapon is off screen.
So if you're trying to do like, you know,
subtle movements or bounces and things like that,
your center of mass is off screen.
So it throws off your rotations,
and you start having to do a lot of counter animation
to get it to rotate from the correct standpoint.
So Matt kind of touched on some of this.
What you want to do in first person,
is let the weapon drive.
So in a typical first person setup,
what I would recommend is the weapon as the character.
Treat it that way.
It's what you're gonna see on screen.
The hands set them to weapon space.
So when I do my animation,
I'm animating from the weapon center of mass
and I can set that up to be where I want it
relative to the screen.
So that way, when I start doing subtle motions,
like the one that I showed earlier,
you can see that my center of mass is on the screen
and I'm not fighting this as I'm doing like settles
and things like that.
So when I show these things side by side,
you can see that you get a nice,
nice rotation point from the screen.
And then you can play around with this
and you can set up your weapons to be however you want,
but you're not getting this odd rotation from the hand.
And your rotations start off clean
and you don't have your hand angled at some weird thing
and that's your starting pose.
It may seem like a dumb moment, but it's pretty helpful.
So my second one, I came across this quote from J.K. Rieke.
Your job as an animator is to present things clearly as possible for the audience,
so that nothing gets in the way of their entertainment.
It might look very visually interesting to have some fancy camera move
while the character is dashing down a hallway towards impending doom,
but if it loses the audience, the shot will be a failure.
So keep it simple and keep it clear. It will still look cool.
As I read this, it really hit home to me about first person
because as Matt pointed out, we have staging,
which is something that's kind of rare in game animation.
We know where the camera is and we can act,
do our performance to that.
But we need to make sure that we're not making the audience sick
or that we're not doing something that distracts
from what's actually happening.
So keep it simple, keep it clear.
You don't want that.
Do not over design the action.
Don't rush the key information,
and do not put style ahead of readability.
It's something that's really difficult to do.
When you first jump in to first person,
all you wanna do is do the coolest thing possible,
and you've got this gun,
and you're gonna spin it and flip it.
But if you're doing these complex actions
and people can't follow what's happening,
you're gonna lose out on the audience very quickly.
But what you do wanna do
is simplify the action into what I call key beats.
Use holds for understanding.
It typically takes four to six frames
for the viewer to absorb information.
And then apply style to the beats.
And what I mean by style is your character
or the weapon's personality.
And then clarity is king.
It's the most important thing.
So this is an animation that I did
for this like kind of futuristic gunslinger guy.
And I think it kind of represents
everything that I was talking about.
You can see the chamber opening
when the gun's energy core depletes.
The gun winds up to repower the core
and then the chamber closes with a snap.
So what I did is I identified these key beats,
and then with it being this idea of a futuristic gunslinger
and like this techno revolver,
I applied the style to those beats.
So instead of the chord just opening up
and then going back in, he spins it around,
flips it, kind of snaps it back in.
And lastly, layers are for detail.
So this is a simple tip that our lead animator at BossKey
shared with me when I first came on board.
And I was just getting started in first person.
And honestly, I think it applies to first person,
third person, or just animation in general.
It's a simple no-brainer, but sometimes you gloss over
things like this.
But use your layers for the details,
and the details are what brings your animations to life.
So this is an example of a gun that I designed,
worked with a concept artist.
Same character, he's got two guns,
and he's gotta reload them independently
because while this one's reloading, he can shoot,
so he can't use both of his hands.
So we had to design these guns to be reloaded
without touching them with another hand.
So in this animation, it's super simple.
The gun just lifts up, it holds it there
so that you can see that it's got a 3D printer
that's printing a new ammo brick
so that it can continue shooting.
I really dig this, I think it's awesome,
but as far as animation goes, it's really simple.
So what I do is.
I don't have as many layers as Matt.
But this is a super simplified example.
So what I use my base layer for is for my foundational movement on my overall timing,
the big motions, and the base of the idea and getting that across.
I go through that, I get that in, I put it in game because as you probably heard today,
get it in game as soon as possible.
Get it in game, start getting feedback.
But
going back to the animation, is super simple,
but what brought that to life was the details,
how the gun shakes when the ammo prints.
And I knew there was gonna be a lot of iteration
on getting that to feel right.
Does it need to feel heavy?
Does it need to feel like it's rapidly printing?
I was gonna play around with it a lot.
So then, that's my basic, you know,
non-exciting curves for my big motion.
But it gets the job done.
And then I come in with my detail layer,
and I add in these tiny curves that show
how fast it shakes or whatever.
But what this allows me to do is keep my big curves big,
and my little curves little, and then I can go in there,
and I can easily tweak how it's shaking,
or rocking, and things like that.
And I can play around with the overall weight
and feel of the gun without upsetting the timing
and things like that.
So those are my three tips.
They're pretty simple, but when you start getting
into first person, if you've never done it before,
it can be really just overwhelming at times
because as Matt was showing and I learned very quickly,
we're stretching and cheating things all over the place,
but as an animator that's working in third person,
like you don't even know that you can do that.
And then when people are like, oh no, break the arms,
snap the elbow, like do whatever you want,
like it becomes really.
freeing that I don't have to worry about, you know,
two-thirds of the body.
Yeah, that's it, and I'm gonna pass it off to Young.
What's up, guys?
All right, so I'm Young Vo, Animation Lead
for Sparky Pants, not Spanky Pants.
Currently working on Drop Zone.
Check it out, great game.
All right, first tip.
Don't start your hit reacts from the idle.
I learned this when I was working on Reckoning.
So we all know that video game is different from film.
Video games is linear.
I mean, sorry.
Film is linear.
Video game is more like a jigsaw puzzle.
All the animations have to fit within each other, right?
They have to connect.
Now hit reacts are a little unique.
that hit reacts have to, they need to feel satisfying
and responsive, right?
And most new animators will automatically animate
the hit react starting from idle to hit frame
to recovery, settle, back into idle again.
That's how they think they should animate it.
But when you do that, the result is kind of sluggish.
It feels kind of slow, right?
Okay.
So.
As you can see here, the animation right there,
I mean, it's not the fault of the attack
that makes it feel slow.
Because you look, the attack feels like
it's not really making contact.
It feels a little sluggish, right?
But we start the animation for the attack later
at the recovery pose.
Instantly, the player will see the attack.
Visually, the attack is gonna be.
Sorry, the react will be much bigger.
The pose is bigger, you start from the recovery pose.
So it's gonna be a much clearer read, quick and clear.
So as you can see there, same attack,
but a bigger, but the reaction started later,
so it feels bigger, the impact is huge.
The bigger you push the reaction pose,
or the recovery pose, the bigger the action.
I mean, the bigger,
the attack will feel.
And I always tell people,
push this pose as big as you can,
because if you want it to be impactful, make it big.
That's tip number one, you're welcome.
Tip number two.
So this is a typical take that we see all animators do.
We have anticipation, we have an overshoot,
and then an action.
Perfectly normal.
The problem is, the majority of the time when you do this,
you don't know why the character's doing it, right?
This is what we normally see in games.
Character stands around, player comes in,
and he just freaks out.
Like, just freaks out.
Like, why are you here, ah!
Right?
We don't know why he's freaking out.
So.
What I tell young animators is to...
Now this is mainly for NPCs,
and it depends on gameplay, of course.
But if you add a decision pose, a recognition pose,
a pose where basically tells the viewer
why he's reacting this way.
A teacher of mine at CalArts told me
that acting is reaction, is not action.
So how your character reacts to something
tells you who they are.
Now this is very subtle, and depending on gameplay,
you can spend more time in the decision post,
give it more character.
This is where you wanna add personality
and subtext to your character, before the anticipation.
People always ask me,
how do I give it more personality and character?
You do it before the anticipation,
you do it before he actually does something.
All right.
Oh, sorry, you're welcome.
Tip number three, use your hand as reference.
Now I learned this the hard way.
When you get a weird, crazy creature
and you spend all this time trying to find
the perfect reference, you're like,
I need to find an animal with 20 tentacles,
a large mouth, eight horns, and it's like,
can't find that, that just doesn't exist.
And if you guys seen that, run away.
So, use your hand as reference.
And how you want to use your hand as reference is basically
you want to figure out the center of gravity.
You want to figure out the weight.
You want to figure out how it's going to be moving,
how the weight is being pushed, pulled,
how the weight is going to shift, how it's going to settle.
Once you figure that out as animators,
the body mechanics just follows, right?
Because that's the core of animation.
If we figure out the timing and spacing,
we can figure out the rest.
And I use my hands just to block things out a lot,
just so I can get it out of there.
So I figure that out quick,
and then I can just block out the animation.
All right, this is an animation I did for Drop Zone.
And I couldn't find reference for this guy, so yeah.
And yes, those hands are mine.
You're welcome.
I'm gonna hand it off to John.
All right, I'm gonna try to go pretty quickly here,
so bear with me.
My name is Jean-Paul Rheinmiller.
I am the lead Cinematics Animator at Vicarious Visions,
currently working on Insane Trilogy and,
oh, thanks, and Destiny.
So my first tip is a technique I learned
from a supervisor of mine at Rhythm and Hues Studios,
Tim Pixen, and it's called swing sets.
So I'm gonna go and try to do a condensed version
of this process here, so bear with me,
and if you have any questions about it, hit me up later.
This was a traditional technique that they used
in television shows back in the day
where they had a limited number of mouth shapes.
Basic set of 12 shapes here
helps you quickly create organic lip sync
without having to do a ton of cleanup at the end.
You can use more or less than 12,
but the basic idea is to start with 12.
It's important to note here that these are not phonemes.
So they're not individual shapes that are crafted
and then plugged in.
These shapes are built together,
so they move in and out of each other organically.
They feel like they're swinging from one shape to the next.
And with many games not having blend shapes
and a ton of bones in the face,
this process, once it's set up,
can help save a ton of time
and also keep consistency among your animation team.
So if you look at it, the flow of the mouth
from the M to the UR follows the natural arc of the jaw.
And as the mouth opens, the jaw goes back in,
down and back, and as it closes, it goes up and in.
But now's not the time to get cocky.
Sorry, I know that's loud.
Thank you.
So the basic idea here is to listen to your dialogue clip,
find out where your swing set shapes will be.
When writing it down, you know, and looking at my chart,
those are the shapes that I came up with here.
but now's not the time.
And these can vary as well and combine T and L,
but again, this is a great starting point.
To get, but now's not the time.
Now using my pre-built shapes,
go based off of the breakdown sheet that you guys just saw.
I take these in and I put them in for blocking.
It took me a little bit less than five minutes.
Now this is obviously a smaller clip
and you can start to see the value of this
if you get a much larger dialogue clip.
To break this down just a little bit more here.
A quick example would be that I have the O in two
and it goes directly into the TK and to get.
So I look at the chart and I say,
I need a breakdown in between here
because these shapes are too far apart from each other.
So I have to have a breakdown
to make that smooth transition.
I look at this way here and...
I'm not getting it here because the way the jaw is moving,
it's going in or up and in.
And so then I take a look over here,
this is gonna get the drop in the jaw
that I think that I want.
So I'm gonna go with the eye here.
But now's not the time to get cocky.
Super simple, but again, you can see
if this was a much larger dialogue
and you're plopping in your shapes,
how much it could actually help.
So with and without, I don't have the audio here.
Another great thing about this technique here
is that the curves tend to flow really nicely
in your graph editor and potential issues
are really easy to identify.
Tip number two, other great, sorry, here we go.
Keep your shapes simple.
You can communicate wonders with just a few shapes.
Many times, characters will only have a few shapes
that they move through.
Skinner here in Ratatouille really only has three shapes
that he moves through, especially when you pay attention
to the corners of the mouth.
He works within those shapes as he talks throughout the film.
Simplify your shapes.
You don't want to constantly be moving to extremes
with your lip sync.
It should be motivated by an accent
or by an expression change.
And this is a great example here
with the woman even though you can't hear her,
she stays in a certain range
and it's not until she accents that her mouth
actually goes outside of that range.
The corners of the mouth are the first place
that I usually can see it.
So if you move through too many shapes
and constantly go in and out,
it'll look too busy and overcomplicated.
So think of it like you do your performance.
You want a rhythm and a flow to your performance
and your lip sync is just one layer of that performance.
So treat it like that.
Track the arcs of the mouth.
This example from Leica here has a really great flow
to the corners of the mouth as they go in prototype here
and it adds a great level of appeal to your lip sync.
And last tip is change the shape of your blinks
on its way up to help it feel a little bit more fleshed out.
This is a blink with the lids very linear, closed and open.
You can see here on the way down and up, very linear.
With just a small adjustment, lots of times I start
with the center of the lid and I drag that just a little bit.
You can play with that based on the size of your character.
With wider, obviously, eyes or narrower eyes,
you may have to increase that drag a little bit.
Here you can see it with just that subtle change.
It gives the eye region a bit more fleshed out feeling.
It can create a peel effect like you do with your lip sync.
It's a great thing to think about in polish
and obviously you're seeing this very close up
so as your characters get a bit farther away from camera,
it can start to look better on screen.
And next up is Ellie.
Hi, my name is Almudena Soria and I'm a lead animator at Naughty Dog.
I've been making games since 2001.
So my first tip is about how to be more efficient with debugging and problem solving animations in the game.
So programmers are often really busy people.
So before coming to them with a problem, we should make sure we have checked that nothing is obviously wrong with our animations.
Check that your frame ranges are correct,
that you're using the right skeleton,
and that the Maya file exists.
All the obvious things that could be wrong
in your animation pipeline.
So once you check all your assets,
would you go and look for help?
Not yet.
So don't present problems, offer solutions.
It's often more time consuming
of presenting a problem with a no solution.
But to offer solutions,
you need to understand how things work.
So here are just a few things you can do to narrow problems down.
Note what is getting exported into the game.
Not always what you see in Maya is what you export.
Some studios use proxy rigs that drive the skeleton that gets into the game.
Sometimes you don't see this by default.
So make sure you check this skeleton.
Game route, align, route, ground node, trajectory, magic box.
It can have many names, but there is always a node that drives the character.
It's like its parent.
It's usually used to adjust character to the ground,
drive collision, blends.
Animation in this node is really important,
and it can be the main cause of bugs.
Avoid sudden movements with it.
Check for smooth rotations.
Check how many rotation degrees it has.
So most places I've worked on,
I've tried to find an automated solution,
but in my experience, it's always better when it's hand animated.
Disable all procedure animation, ground adjust, weapon, feed IK, physics.
By doing so, step by step, you can narrow the course of the problem
and understand how these things work on top of your animations.
Other things you can do is disable or lower the compression and detach the camera.
My second tip is about layer animations.
Games use layer animations for a lot of features like hit reactions, aim.
Usually design requires this kind of animations because they are not meant to interrupt locomotion.
These animations are not easiest to make pretty.
But I think we should push the use of these animations to help a storytelling and character development.
Partial and additives are a great way of bringing character to life.
You can modify a whole moveset with just an additive and transmit the feelings of that character at that particular time.
You can also give characters their own actions, something they're interesting they would do.
Another great use of partial and additives is to integrate
characters with environment like rain, vegetation,
touching the environment.
And finally, another thing you can use layer animations for is contextual outfit animations.
Here you can see an example of a fight sequence with and without layer animation.
And my last tip is real-time physics.
Considering real-time physics on top of your animations
were never suitable.
Use it as a way of enhancing your animations
and not to replace it.
Physics give a realistic feel to the animations
when they are set up right.
It allows for overlapping and secondary motion
when animations have to be interrupted.
It also provides a layer of realism.
Animators should be involved when setting this physics up
to make sure our animations look the best.
And if you wanna know more about this,
check Michal Mack talk on Thursday.
Next.
Go, go, go.
Go.
I've gotta go really quick.
Hot mic.
Okay, so my first tip is something I learned
from my first animation director in Montreal.
Comfort.
I look for this when reviewing my animator's work.
It isn't about how comfortable the chair is
or if you need a hug.
It's the understanding of body mechanics and readability.
So.
There we go.
Dynamic poses can also be comfortable,
but it is understanding the limits of a limb
and that everything is connected
that determine how far it can be pushed.
What is driving the intention
and the purpose of the movement?
Are you crouching, reaching,
reaching for something, or is it just a reaction?
Unfortunately, this is something
that's gotten a little lost
in many animation reels that I've seen.
So unless we had tons of constraints
on our rigs to automate this,
which can remove control,
our rigs will allow this to happen.
But be careful of extensive handle dragging
to get bones into position.
All too often I see animations that you can tell
have been animated exclusively this way.
Break down your thought process.
Animate through the bones, moving through the chain.
Thinking of what is driving the action.
If you're reaching for something,
drive the joints towards the object.
Don't just pull them.
Use connecting bones such as the shoulder and torso.
Be careful of isolating movements.
Both of these poses get the head to the desired position, but the one on the right feels much more natural.
Now the reason for this is a comfortable pose will dissipate the position through multiple bones,
even down to the arms and the hips providing balance.
A good sense of weight distribution and balance will help bring a subtle quality
that helps make your animation feel much more believable.
Notice a slight lean before the first step and a subtle weight shift from back foot to front foot before the push.
Check out the slight rotation on the hips
and the transfer of weight over to the right foot.
That provides the power to continue the push.
When the hips move down,
the head and shoulders remain stable.
Remember, everything is connected.
So, understanding these mechanics
allows you to break these rules
when something extra is needed,
such as hyperextending joints at a point of impact,
but you should only use this for brief periods of time.
This is backed up by Amy Drobek-Jones' tip
from last year's Tricks Talk, so go check it out.
So gameplay animation also needs to be readable
as the action is supposed to be.
This applies when manipulating mocap
just as much as key framing.
The timing on these animations is almost identical
but the animation on the right benefits
from an animator pushing almost every aspect
whilst maintaining the integrity of the motion.
For example, clear lines of action on attacks.
The left arm through the shoulders to the right hand
highlights the location of where the hit will land.
Combine this with a more aggressive yank
back and to the right, enhancing the pose,
which adds more emphasis to key areas of the move.
Finally, improve contacts,
making a move much more dynamic and readable,
proving that even with great mocap
can be vastly improved by a good animator.
So my second tip is use slow motion.
Now not just because everything looks cool in slow motion,
it also has its practical uses.
I learned this when working on trailers for Assassin's Creed.
The team wanted to capture everything in super slow motion
but it highlighted any tiny errors in the animation
which might usually be covered.
At that point in my career, I found it hard
to see smaller issues during general playback.
So scrubbing back and forth would highlight
some of these errors but wouldn't give
a true representation of what it would look like
in the trailers.
So I started playing animation back at a quarter speed
to emphasize the issues,
and it actually makes it easier to fix,
allowing me to spin around and see everything
much, much clearer.
So for extra clarity, I turn on frames and ticks.
Yeah, I use 3ds Max,
which let you scrub areas in super slow motion.
I'd use this to highlight a point to my team
that was hard to see in real time.
Maybe the arc of a junk locks off,
the weight shift maybe is too aggressive.
Play your animation in super slow motion,
and you'll be surprised at what you actually see.
but be careful of extensive timing changes.
This is a pass I will do more towards polish stage.
So my third and final tip is how does it feel?
Gameplay animation is not just about looking good.
I firmly believe that an animator's job
is only half done when you export an animation.
Working gameplay is rarely about
the animation you're working on.
More often than not, it's about the animation
before and after, and these are just as important,
giving much more context to the current move.
When, with each animation, ask yourself these questions.
How will it be perceived by the player?
Does it read well?
Does it look and feel good when interacting with it?
Does the look match the purpose?
Should I take control away from the player?
If so, when do I get it back?
When can I interrupt the animation and does it feel right?
And what is the most common animation
before and after this one?
Is it worth creating a custom transition?
This will vastly improve how your animation feels.
Block it out, export it, and get it how you think
it will work in the game.
Play it, play it again.
Give the controller to someone else.
Watch how they play it.
Always ask, how does it feel?
Make adjustments, re-export, test, adjust, and repeat.
This applies to any animation or system
you can expect a player to interact with.
Understand what your game designers actually want.
Talk to them.
Gameplay animation is a collaborative process.
Find your natural rhythm and flow
and your game will feel much better for it.
And as many of us said before, get it in the game.
So that's Tricks of the Trade.
Yeah.
We're white.
I know we've gone, I know we've gone super over.
but we have more awesomeness.
And I'm gonna go really quick.
Okay, so we're just gonna do a speed round.
We're gonna just give you a bunch of tips.
This is my channel.
Gwen talked about it before.
It will give you loads of kind of animation goodness
and everything there, so if you want more information,
go check that out.
Also, Pinterest is awesome.
So the great thing about Pinterest,
this came from Darren Randall, an animator of mine in Toronto.
And he uses this for kind of inspiration
and if he's trying to look to find something to do.
And it's just a gold mine of reference.
Anyway, so I'm going to pass over to JP.
I think it's crashed.
It's crashed.
The music's playing, but it's crashed.
So I think they're kicking us out.
That's fine.
Anyway, that's Tricks of the Trade.
Thank you very much.