Welcome back.
This is our second session of the Serious Games Summit
and our Games for Health Day.
Our next presenter, I first met about four years ago
and had read about this wonderful piece of work
where there had been a virus outbreak inside World
of Warcraft due to a design flaw in some new content
that the game was putting out.
And there had been an article published.
by an epidemiologist who had gone back to look at what had actually happened
and try to understand it from their standpoint.
And, you know, I thought that would be a really interesting talk at a Games for Health conference
in that, especially because it was dealing with World of Warcraft, it's always good to,
for content-wise, to associate yourself with the most popular game being played at the
moment.
You can almost never fail there.
But we got a lot more than we bargained for because not only did we get a great talk,
but we met somebody doing some really incredible work,
and it was really it was really apparent that the talk was connecting with people when like all of the senior scientists and
people from all kinds of different groups in the federal government who deal with trying to protect us from
epidemics and other kinds of
similar episodes ran to the front of the room and were like, I'm getting in line first.
So I had promised Nina that we should have this talk at GDC
because I think people should see what can come out of games
even if they're not purposely built for a serious purpose.
And things can actually happen.
And the behaviors of players inside the games that
are being made every day have potentially
interesting opportunities for the rest of the world
to learn from.
So you're going to get a chance to see some of that work
and some other work that's been built off of this.
So please welcome Nina Pfefferman.
Hey guys.
Thanks, Ben.
Every time Ben invites me somewhere, it's somewhere I've never been and somewhere I have a great time.
So you guys look awesome.
Thank you.
Just so I know the lay of the land, this is wonderful for me.
Usually I get to ask the following question and there's maybe one or two hands that go up.
How many of us are gamers?
Woohoo!
Okay, um, sub-question.
How many people are here from Blizzard?
All right, we can say anything we want now.
No, um, okay, so but how many people play WoW?
Okay, that's still, that's still orders of magnitude
above my normal response on this one.
I'm very psyched.
Normally, I give talks like this to epidemiologists
and people from public health and the federal government
and the Department of Homeland Security.
Um, none of whom admit.
to playing WoW even if they do.
So, um, how many, how many, this is going to narrow it down a lot,
how many people were playing WoW in 2005?
Oh.
Okay, what are you guys doing here? You lived this. Okay.
So I'm going to talk to you today predominantly about the corrupted blood plague of 2005 in World of Warcraft and how we're using it.
And as Ben started to tell you, I'm going to take serious games in a whole different way.
Usually when the folks who start talking about serious games mean research into serious games, what they mean is,
how do we make the user experience of the game such that there's a benefit to the user,
and in the context of Games for Health, to their personal well-being?
And now I'm going to step back from that and say, actually, I want the beneficiaries of the research that I do to be everybody, not just the users of the game.
And I'm going to use the game in order to gain insight into how I think public health practice should happen.
And I'm going to do it from the perspective of epidemiology, which is the study of disease epidemics.
And from my perspective, usually it's infectious disease.
But at the end of the talk, I'll sort of tell you about some stuff I'm doing with non-infectious disease.
because of something surprising that came out of some ongoing
work in a virtual world.
So I'm affiliated with way too many places,
but I'm a professor at a medical school.
I'm a professor in a department of evolution and ecology.
I'm a professor of applied mathematics.
And all of them let me have students with me
who play games, which is fantastic.
OK, so I want to make another disclaimer, which
is that I have shamelessly stolen lots of images
from Blizzard's website.
And they're all beautiful, and I own none of them,
and I hope they don't mind.
But yes, all of the pictures of Wow
come just from screen capture or from their website.
OK, so in case you guys don't know, how many of you
know what an infectious epidemiologist does?
That's pretty good, actually.
You guys rock in general.
First of all, actually, in the first session,
I don't know how many of you were also in the first session,
it sounded like the other room was having a lot more fun,
even though the talk in here was awesome and clearly better.
I don't know what was going on in the other room.
But, so I would encourage kind of yelling or screaming
or throwing things if it stops being fun,
because we clearly need to have more fun
than the people in the next room.
Yes, thank you, woohoo!
Okay, so what does an infectious disease epidemiologist do?
Well, we analyze disease risks to a population.
We work on figuring out what the origin
of a particular outbreak was.
We worry about public health strategies that can prevent outbreaks and make populations more robust to threats from the outside and from within.
And we investigate intervention strategies to end already ongoing outbreaks.
And we decide things like when do we make public health emergency announcements?
And what information do we give to the media?
And how do we communicate with the public about health risks?
And each of these things have different levels of feeling of emergency and behaviors that go with them,
especially when you think in your mind, just within the realm of infectious disease,
of the differences between communicating with people about the HIV epidemic and swine flu.
Right? Those are very different timescales of effect. They're very different levels of concern.
And you expect very different behavioral responses, depending on whether or not we, as the epidemiologists, screw up.
So we try very hard not to screw up, but we also worry about, well, if we screw up, how bad can it get?
Okay, so I'm a mathematical infectious disease epidemiologist.
I live in a smaller world than just all the things I told you about what infectious disease epidemiologists do.
I use math to try and answer all of those questions.
And so I try and predict, if outbreaks happen, where will they go?
What will they look like? What will the relative outcomes be? How bad will it get?
And there are a few different types of models.
So I'm going to quickly try and describe to you
all of epidemiological mathematical modeling
in about one and a half minutes.
We have basic models,
they are called the compartmental models,
where we bin people into health compartments.
You, you are healthy, but you could get infected.
You, you are infected and you can infect others.
You, you have recovered from being infected
and are probably immune,
or you're dead, or things like that.
And we think of each of those compartments,
and we think of rates of transferring
among those compartments.
And then we try and come up with measurements for those rates.
And then very much like physicists,
we say, if there were 30 billion people,
then we'd get this completely correct.
And as it scales down from 30 billion,
we're getting it slightly less and less correct,
but it should still apply.
And then unfortunately, there's small town America,
and then it just doesn't work.
And we all know it doesn't work in small town.
And then we've got network models.
In network models, we draw, literally,
a network of everyone who meets everybody else
and has the possibility for transmitting an infection.
And then we try and say, well, if we
have those explicit contacts, what
do we know about the disease?
And then we get to make much more exact measurement about all of these disease transmission rates,
but we need to know a huge amount about the population.
And now in small town America, this works great,
because we actually know a lot about contacts in a very limited range.
But then as soon as you scale up to reasonably sized town,
this breaks down entirely, because you don't know how often someone goes to the grocery store.
And then we get to agent-based models.
And those are the simulations kind
of like the AI controls for the NPCs in a bunch of games.
So these are the ones where we put some algorithms in back
of a particular object.
And then we say, here are the algorithms for decision-making
for that object.
And they look around, and they look
at the other people who are making decisions around them
and their environment and what happened to them
in the last five minutes.
And they go, well, given all of that,
I'm just going home and bolting the door.
And then based on that, we see who comes into contact with whom.
And then on all of that, we model the spread of disease based on the contact patterns.
And in the compartmental models, we're assuming that random mixing happens.
All of the people from one compartment have an equal probability of meeting all the people in the other compartment.
And if we want to break it down a little bit, we can make sub-compartments.
But we really do treat everybody kind of as an average.
And in the network models, everything is very explicit.
And in the agent-based models, the behavior isn't explicit,
but the algorithms for making those behavioral decisions
are explicit.
Everyone with me?
How many people are bored out of their wits already?
All right, I promise I'm getting off the epi now.
OK, so as a disclaimer, you don't need to know this.
I just made everything seem very lovely and easy.
It can all get very complicated.
This is just one, this is actually like three quarters of a model to describe transmission with behavior for one disease.
So, only crazy people like me and my students do this at home for fun.
On the other hand, here's the deal.
What it brings us to is that in all of the models that we're using,
and these really are the models that we use,
when we as a group of epidemiologists decide
what flu strains to put in the vaccine for next year,
when someone says,
what happens if, God forbid, there's a smallpox release
in downtown San Francisco on Tuesday?
What will happen and what can we do to prevent it?
These are the models that we go to, all of us.
And so this brings us to the basic fundamental problem with all of these is that we're assuming the behavior of the people that we're modeling.
And there's a lot of behavioral change that we have to assume is going to happen in the case especially of an epidemic outbreak, when people are likely to be scared.
People are actually very difficult to predict.
We can use math to predict the disease really well,
once we know how people are going to behave.
These models actually, for as much as we can generalize them
and laugh about how simple they sound,
they actually do work really well.
We've got some great testing that says,
if we nailed the behavior part of it,
we've nailed the disease transmission part of it.
But then there's that behavior part,
and that part's really hard.
And right now, we basically guess.
We basically go, I don't know, what would I do
if tomorrow there was smallpox down the street?
I'd probably be scared.
What would I do?
What would I think to do?
The problem is that people are actually very bad
at making these kinds of hypothetical assumptions
about themselves, partially because they're not
in the moment and there's a lot of simply emotion feeding
into the decision making, and partially also
because that sort of scales up from the individual
to not being able to anticipate what
the actual environment around them
is going to be like at the time.
And so there are some really.
deep ethical, behavioral, philosophical questions that
come up that you just can't ask people, well,
what would you do if, and get a good response.
And we can try measuring current behaviors,
but again, that's in a very different context.
And so when we try and figure out
how do those current behaviors change if anything bad
is happening, we don't have a good way to know.
And the only thing that we do know
is that the ways we've tried to scale that in the past
haven't been that great.
So a lot of the times this comes into emergency evacuation modeling, things like people getting
out of the way of hurricanes.
The number of people who tell you they'll evacuate if someone tells them to evacuate
is actually very different from the number of people who actually put their stuff in
the car and leave.
So we know from experience, figuring out even people are bad at determining their own heroism.
There's actually a gap in both directions.
You get false positives and false negatives of would you run into a burning building to
save a child.
There are people who surprise themselves in both directions.
And it's not that they're not thinking really well about how to give you the right answer,
they just don't know the right answer, because it hasn't happened yet.
Okay, so how do we begin to understand these things when you've got to make these really
basic assumptions? And so we just talked about this, we can ask the what would you do if questions,
but...
They get very complicated very quickly.
So just without answering out loud right now,
but think to yourselves, at what point
might you be willing to forego arriving at an emergency room
if you knew that your chance of dying was 98%
and your chance of infecting everyone in the emergency room
was also around 90%?
So would you show up and kill people
for a 2% chance of survival?
Maybe.
But that's a really difficult question to start asking.
What if you didn't know with that level of certainty?
At what point are you willing to stay and care for a sick child?
What happens if it's not your child?
So these have huge impacts on our outcomes
of our behavioral epidemiological modeling.
And so now we get to the fun part.
Now we get to see, OK, how does gaming help?
So in 2005, when some of the people in this room,
including me, were playing World of Warcraft,
There were 6.5 million players worldwide,
which is a number which I believe is now dwarfed
by the current game players.
But what makes it perfect from my perspective
is that WoW had at the time a really unique demographic
composition.
It wasn't just the stereotypical gamer.
It was working moms in the Midwest.
It was students.
It was professionals.
There was a large deployed soldier component
in World of Warcraft.
There still is.
There were scholars working in it, usually from the social sciences, not so much from the epidemiological sciences.
There were politicians. I think a few years ago there was the first real-world political rally in WoW.
Anyone go?
It was pretty cool.
Okay.
So a critical aspect, another critical aspect of WOW that made it a really good platform
for this kind of research is that it's a highly social game by nature.
It's not just that there was an aggregate of a lot of people logged in to a massively
multiplayer online game in parallel tasks.
It's that you had to have social interaction in order to accomplish these tasks.
And that's not unique to WOW by a long shot, but it was bringing all of these things together
that helped.
So one of the things that was critical from our perspective is that there were years and years of social history behind the groups that were interacting.
If you had a party going out or if you had a guild, that was a guild or a party that had been together for a long time before the outbreak happened.
And you also have high levels of interaction among strangers, people you're buying things from, people you're trading from, people who are joining you on quests because you just can't get your power together.
And in 2005...
Blizzard released something brilliant,
and they didn't mean to.
And no fault of their own.
This was not a design flaw.
You would have had to have been God to know that this
was going to happen.
Blizzard occasionally opens up new releases
to keep their high-level players interested
and keep low-level players engaged
without creating a huge disparity between noobs
and wizards, essentially.
So they opened up a new area in 2005 called Zul'Grob.
And as part of the challenge
for high-level players was Hakkar, a beautiful monster.
And as part of the challenge of playing Hakkar,
he cast an area effect spell called Corrupted Blood.
And what it did was cast as an area effect spell,
and if you were affected by it, you re-
part of it was to recast Corrupted Blood periodically.
And if you were a high-enough level player
to have fought your way to Hakkar,
this was kind of an annoyance.
It was meant to add to the challenge of battle,
but it wasn't meant to by itself be a dangerous thing.
because of course this was a high-level area.
To have gotten there in the first place,
you had to have been robust to most of these threats.
And that's Hikari.
And yeah, he was gorgeous.
He's tall, he's red, he's beautiful.
There's a dramatic swooshing noise when he turns around.
I'm easily affected by these things, I'm a gamer.
Okay, so here's where things didn't go as planned
when they opened up this area.
The higher level players didn't necessarily wait for the one of two options that Blizzard had in mind.
The two options being, either you killed Hakkar, in which case no problem, you healed from corrupted blood and everything was fine.
Or, Hakkar killed you, in which case, when you resurrected, no corrupted blood.
On the other hand, there are some other options for this.
Um, you can leave while still infected and run away.
Or you can summon and then banish your pet, and your pet could be infected, and when banished, your pet wasn't healed.
So when you re-summoned your pet, your pet came back with corrupted blood, which is of course a self-recasting area effect spell,
which is an infectious disease process.
So, some of the people who went to fight Hakkar left and went back to the cities carrying infection.
And this is where things didn't go so much as planned.
So here is where players started to die.
And I don't know if you can see.
Can you guys, is the resolution okay for?
Okay, awesome.
First of all, there were skeletons.
This was actually a crucial aspect
from my perspective of the gameplay,
because normally when you've got player deaths in WoW,
no skeletons.
So wandering around with the ground littered
with the bodies of literally player characters
was actually kind of cool.
Also, Corrupted Blood was visually dramatic.
You exploded every few seconds in a little cloud of blood
and it went, pfft.
Yes, I'm big on the sounds.
The public gathering places were instantly shut down.
This is a guild hall or a trading hall.
Guild hall?
Oh, yeah.
That's Ironforge.
You can see, not much normal anything
is happening right now.
People are running around exploding in clouds of blood,
dropping dead, and turning to skeletons.
And the plague spread completely out of control.
So really, if you were logged in, you were affected.
And it was amazing.
There was no normal gameplay happening
on the infected servers.
Blizzard tried to stop it by imposing a quarantine, which
is something we talk about in real-world epidemiology
all the time.
We talk about, OK, what happens if someone releases something
bad in Manhattan, one of the easiest places in the world
to quarantine, because you can only get to it
by bridge, tunnel, or boat.
And usually, we talk about that failing.
This was an example where, within Blizzard,
the quarantine failed.
Blizzard finally had to do something
we don't get to do in real life, which is to reset the servers.
So this went on actually for four or five days before they did this, and they were trying
in real time to fix it.
And some of them were really nice people and took the time out from being really stressed
to talk to me about it.
So I got to hear some of what they were trying to do, and it was brilliant, and none of it
worked in the same ways that we would be if there was an outbreak of something horrible
tomorrow.
A bunch of us would get phone calls from Homeland Security and we'd be scrambling on trying
to figure out what to do, and it would likely not work.
So...
Actually, even the background perspective of the people in charge scrambling was actually a really good analogy for real-world events.
But did we as epidemiologists learn anything from this?
Well, how did the players behave during the plague?
Was it close to how people behaved during the real-world epidemic?
And the answer, actually, somewhat surprisingly at the time, is yes.
So, I was looking at this. I logged in because my student called me and said...
You know how we've been joking about running a disease in a game and using our output from that?
Well, we don't have to run the disease, it's happening.
Log your character in and take a look and do it for research purposes.
On the other hand, we also had people doing that just for fun, which was amazing.
So that's my little...
Curiosity, but I can't get my pointer, but that's the curiosity part that we saw and that for us was the critical thing
We saw all of the things that we thought we would see we saw some courage. We saw some compliance with the imposed
Quarantine we saw fear. We saw some suspicion of the quarantine and of blizzards motives and doing all of this
We saw some public concern the bulletin boards were going mad
I don't know if you guys who are playing this we're reading them the bulletin boards
there was everything from the equivalence of like aliens have landed conspiracy theories
to, oh, it's a glitch, though we set it tomorrow, everyone calm down and just have fun.
And there was everything in between. And there were people like, oh my god, if I,
if I, you know, what happens to my stuff if I can't go back and reclaim it? There were looters,
there were people maliciously running in and infecting guilds. And some of the stuff that
we, so forgetting the griefers, but the griefers are important. Forgetting the griefers, the
important thing to us was to see the diversity of response.
And the ones that we were looking at epidemiologically were the ones,
what are the things we hadn't thought to include in our models?
When we guess in our models, and we say, what should be happening?
What could happen? And we guess.
What did we forget to include?
And that's where things like curiosity really helped us,
because we'd never thought of that.
What happens if people rush into a quarantine?
Clearly, now that it's been pointed out to us, they're going to.
We have news organizations that are going to want to send reporters.
We've got people who are just curious and don't worry about the consequences or think
it's not as severe.
We've got people who are actually there to monitor the situation from an oversight perspective
who are going to need to get in.
We'd never modeled that before.
So it's actually improving our models.
So what did we learn?
It pointed out these behaviors we hadn't considered, which is very important.
But it's not everything we need.
It's a great place to start.
Of course, there are differences between in-game world choices
and real world choices.
And one of the cool things about in-game world choices
is that gamers are actually pretty good at dealing
with probabilities.
Because we have sort of inherently this role of D20
and know what happens ingrained in our souls.
But we also note that only some people are gamers.
So the responses may be different.
We need to figure out what that is.
But so I like to make the analogy of this as being sort of clinical trials in mice for drug development
We know mice aren't people but they're a damn fine place to start
Gamers are probably not exactly regular people, but it's a good place to start
and
Then there's a question of where are we going from here because that was a one
Moment in time brilliant thing that showed us something wonderful. We needed the fact that it was an accident
we actually the wrath of the Lich King expansion later didn't really help because
that was a planned event and everyone knew the effects were temporary and everyone knew
that whatever they were experiencing was meant for this to happen. Corrupted blood by the
fact that it wasn't meant to be there really gave us some great insight. And I'm going
to tell you very quickly about some stuff that is actually because of Ben and Games
for Health. When I came and gave a talk on the corrupted blood plague, I met the folks
at Yville. How many people have seen Yville? Oh, I recommend Yville to you all, especially
for bringing out your inner child. Log in as an adult, play with the kids, they're awesome.
It is a social and science virtual world for tweens,
eight to 14-year-olds.
And what we're doing, there exists with Yville
developing this with Numedi and the company that makes it,
Ypox, which is a disease that you can get in Yville.
And it's been studied really well from an educational side
of what do kids learn about epidemics
by a wonderful professor, Yasmin Kafai at UPenn.
What we're doing now is studying risk perception.
in Weibel and how do the different attributes of the disease and the likelihood of catching it and the prevalence observed and the symptoms that are experienced,
how does that all feed back to the risk and health decisions that they're making as people caring for their own health within that game?
This is what Weipox looks like. You can see she's all speckly. The rest of it I take no responsibility for. With Weipox, that's her fashion sense, somehow to wear a poinsettia.
But you can see that a bunch of people are saying achoo at the beach.
And that was one of the symptoms of WIPOX at the time, to interrupt what you were typing
with the word achoo.
And one of the really cool things that we noticed, and it's not infectious disease,
but it is affecting our research, is that we noticed that some of the kids in Wyville
were typing achoo into their own text.
It wasn't being auto-inserted.
And we stopped for a minute and we went, why on earth are they doing this?
Well, they can't mimic the facial splotches, but lots of people with the facial splotches
were covering up their faces anyway.
They were masks or pretty hats or things like that.
And then they would cover up their faces and say, achoo.
So we thought a lot about faking.
We said, okay, well, what could this be?
Well, it could be that WIPOX is actually perceived as cool or good, right?
And that they were trying to do this.
Well, that wasn't in line with what we were reading in the chat or what they were saying
to each other.
They were saying, no, WIPOX is really annoying,
it's really bad, if nothing else,
it's interfering with typing commands.
So it's really annoying.
If you want to say something in the middle of the word say,
the word achoo comes up, it didn't process.
We thought maybe they were just screwing with the studies,
because there are lots of kids running
their own epidemiological studies of WIPOX and Weyville.
Maybe they're just screwing with the data.
But that didn't actually turn out to be
what we ended up thinking.
What we ended up thinking was that
it's actually a form of empathy.
It's actually an idea of, I'm feeling left out, all of my friends are experiencing this negative thing,
I don't know how to correctly provide empathy to them.
And so this led us to an interesting hypothesis.
And we're winding it up.
Our interesting hypothesis, so this is a teaser for our coming research,
is actually that in looking at kids and addiction behaviors,
we've been focusing as public health people on saying...
Kids are not estimating their risk correctly.
They're trying to get high and they're not realizing
they'll get addicted.
This led us to make the hypothesis, no, no, no.
What if kids are trying to get addicted
because they realize it's something bad
their friends are going through
and they don't know how to provide empathy
appropriately to them?
And this may not be something that kids have to realize
that they're doing in order to do it,
and which would drastically change,
and we're working on this study now,
drastically change how we would try and target
anti-addiction campaigns for youth.
So it's an ongoing study.
Hopefully, I'll have results for you quite soon.
And that's pretty much the end of the talk.
So I don't think this will ruin gameplay.
But if anyone would like to work with me
and has more than 100,000 players?
So yeah, so part of what we're doing
is now taking these insights and going back
into our epidemiological models.
And gaming in the nation's service, ha ha.
So thank you very, very much.