Okay.
So, thank you everyone for coming today.
My name's Joshua Boggs,
and I'm the designer and director of Framed.
We've got a lot to get through, so we'll just
run through it as quickly as possible.
We don't have heaps of time.
So, let's do it.
So, as I said, I'm Joshua Boggs.
I'm a game designer and director.
Prior to Framed, I've been in the industry for about 8 years now.
Some of that time was spent at EA and various other studios,
and I've been independent for about four of them.
I've also been pretty fortunate to have won some awards.
And this talk is a bit about how we did that.
That's obviously not the rules to me.
One thing that's going to become clear in the talk is
I have a talent for, I guess, reading people,
but reading them inside a social system.
Some may call that sociopathic.
I just call it being aware of others and their motives.
So, in case you don't know what Framed is,
Framed is a noir puzzle game
where you rearrange panels of a comic book
to change the outcome of the story.
As you can see, we've done pretty well.
And let's go.
So it all starts with a choice, right?
Every project you make is just a series of choices.
This isn't rocket science.
Those of us that make games know this well.
We make choices that impact the game and its development
every single day.
Things like, what is this game about?
How will people find my game?
how I make money from my game, and something that
Bruce talked about a couple years ago.
What makes my game remarkable?
These are all very valid and important questions.
However, there is one question, one choice, that developers
often don't ask themselves.
And it is this.
How do I want my game to be perceived?
This is an important distinction, because as we know
in game development, we have a large control over many things.
But not necessarily what happens once it's out in the wild.
But that's not entirely true, because
every choice you make about your game during development,
during release, during pre-production,
is you subtly speaking to the public,
to curators, app store editors,
about how they should perceive your game.
This is the essence of what PR and marketing is, right?
Hundreds of billions of dollars are spent every year
to try and create a favorable message,
a favorable reaction to a product.
And your game is no different, obviously.
Sorry.
This talk is about taking control of what you say.
You'll hear me speak a lot about the decisions we made during development
and the particular tactics we used.
But if you pay attention, you'll notice that
even among those development-focused choices
is a common theme.
And that theme is that every choice we made
was deliberately focused on tailoring
the public perception of frames prior to release.
So, what choices did we make?
Well, firstly, we were going to make a very different kind of game, obviously.
Something that could be recognized in a single screenshot.
Something incredibly striking and carefully designed.
It needed to be recognizable at a pub,
on the tram, or on the subway.
It had to get people to come up to you and ask you,
what is that game you're playing, in public?
Secondly, we were going to distinguish ourselves
from the kind of lo-fi fad going on at the time
by...
hand crafting every part of, every piece of art,
every piece of animation for every panel and level.
We felt that this would send a message
that this was a really high quality product
and a really high quality game.
And we doubled down on this by actually focusing
on Apple rather than PC.
PC was the dominant platform at the time,
but we felt that kind of pairing of the interface
and the careful design and just the kind of experience
of using an Apple product would be a great pairing.
And most importantly, we're going to focus our PR efforts on winning awards on the festival circuit.
So, for anyone who's not aware, real quick, what is the Festival Circuit?
Put simply, the Festival Circuit is a season of exhibitions, conferences, and award shows
that you can submit your game to.
These shows take place all around the world, and if you are successful in being picked
as a finalist or a showcase game, you get free booth space and the opportunities to
network with distributors, app store editors, publishers, fans, and obviously journalists.
But that's not the only goal of pursuing this route.
Or I should say, that's not the real goal of committing to the festival circuit.
Because the festival circuit is really about shaping the perception of your game.
By being at festivals, award shows, and official selections,
you do two things.
First, you add that coveted award wreath to your marketing materials.
This further enhances that perception of quality and hypeness around your game.
There it is.
Look at it.
How lovely.
Two, you're marketing directly to tastemakers.
These are your curators, the connoisseurs, YouTubers,
and journalists.
They're at these shows. It's their job to be at these shows.
And their voices are bigger than yours can ever be.
You just don't have the same time and resources as someone like EA or Ubisoft.
So you need to spend your time as effectively as possible.
Everything you're doing needs to be hitting two birds with one stone.
And this is the one-two punch of the festival circuit.
You increase hype and expectations around your game
by frequently appearing at shows as a successful title.
This allows you to bring in those with larger influence
in you to market your game for you to the rest of the world.
But this in turn helps build more hype around your game,
which means that when you do submit to the next show,
chances are that those judges and show curators
have heard about your game and are a lot more
likely to check it out.
This positive PR feedback loop is
pivotal to cutting through the noise
and shaping the perception of your game
as something that is a must-have quality title.
So for those that aren't aware, this is just a quick
run-through of a bunch of events in the festival circuit.
These are the ones that we kind of focused on, but
there's more festivals every year that are opening up.
And I could not recommend more the two URLs at the bottom,
gameconfs.com and promoterapp.com.
uh... promoter app without it
we probably would have missed a lot of this and
we probably wouldn't have done as well as we did
uh... it sends you like really awesome reminders, it's great, really check it out
aside from the main goal of shaping the perception around your game
festival circuits also provide a number of other great benefits
The first one that lets you gauge the public perception of your game.
Have people already heard about the game?
What are people saying about it when they see your logo, your banner?
Do they turn to their friend and say, oh, this is that game framed,
or this is, you know, Hyperlite,
or this is whatever game you're working on?
If they do, then you're on the right track.
Free interviews, obviously.
If you're selected, you're given a free booth,
and that lets journalists and media outlets
just vox pop you right at your booth.
And pretty important is free playtesting.
If you're going to be maintaining that perception of value and quality,
you need to be taking in as much feedback as possible.
This doesn't mean hounding people afterward.
Oftentimes it's just about listening to their faces,
their body language,
and others around them watching them as they play.
Reading these cues and matching them with what's going on
is normally a service you pay a fair amount of money for.
Attending as many shows as possible also allows you to test it among different audiences.
For example, the PAX crowd is very, very different to the SXSW crowd.
SXSW is more like a general mainstream or public event, whereas PAX is clearly PAX.
So, talking about the benefits of the festival circuit,
it's all well and good, but with the bar always rising,
particularly the competition inside the festival circuit,
your game really needs to stand out and cut through the noise.
It needs to be very, very polished.
This means that people often don't start submitting
to shows and competitions
till the game is either finished or in beta.
However, it is possible.
Sorry, so it is possible to maintain that quality throughout development.
Remember, you want to shape that perception of quality
and the best way to do that over a long period of time
is to submit to as many festivals as possible.
So, here are the development strategies that we employed
to allow us to continuously submit frames to competitions
and award shows, allowing us to shape that perception
throughout the entire development.
So, the core tenet we've upheld is to ensure that you're developing your game to a timeline that adheres to the festival circuit's award show.
So, their submissions and their showings.
That means you need to always have a submission quality build on hand, no matter what.
Here are some of the ways we did that.
So, number one.
Your imagination is the best prototype.
Playtest your entire game on paper or Lego
or anything faster than a computer.
You want that turnaround between design and experience
to be as immediate as writing or painting.
Video game creation has a long turnaround time
between creation and experience,
but game design doesn't really need to be.
Simulate it in your mind if possible.
You need to make that turnaround between inception and execution
as fast as physically possible.
Then, once you've done that, playtest it on others.
Let them imagine the world you've left out.
Because you'll be surprised by the results,
and it will force you to ensure that your designs
are very readable and very intuitive.
Number two, this one's a bit controversial,
but assume everything is final
and don't create placeholder assets.
By not using placeholder assets,
the idea is that, sorry.
And surely you're not just using placeholder assets.
The idea is more than the mechanic.
The idea is about how the aesthetics, the themes,
the mechanics all come together.
The magic that happens when they all interplay,
that is the feeling that you have in your imagination.
That is the core idea of your game oftentimes.
So doing work in progress, placeholders often
doesn't give that feeling.
Identify which parts are not essential, and leave them till later.
But make sure you do not discard the feeling that you're trying to capture.
Many people throw out everything except the system of mechanics when they do this,
but doing that is just throwing out the baby with the bathwater.
The game is the feeling you're trying to capture.
For example, The Witness, right?
Is it just a series of puzzles with nice art?
It's more than that. It's a feeling of both mystery and zen,
an idea that logic and spirituality are one and the same thing.
And all the mechanics and things are trying to
give you, you know, a general grasp of that idea.
Number three, the only milestones are submission deadlines.
There's usually about ten weeks between each major expo and award show.
This is how long it should take you to make significant improvements
and add additional content.
If it takes longer, your pipeline's a bit too slow.
You'd be submitting your polished build to as many festivals as possible
while maintaining the trajectory of your project.
The only way to do that is obviously to treat award submissions as your major milestones.
And 10 weeks is the magic number.
It's not some arbitrary, random, optimal time I've plucked out.
It is literally the time between the biggest and most important award shows that you can get into.
And they're all in different parts of the world.
You'll often find them seasonal as well.
IGF, GDC, we are here now.
South by Southwest, PAX East are all in this, you know, earlier part of the year.
and in the middle you've got Gamescom, Eurogamer,
Tokyo Game Show as well, I think, unless it's moved out.
They're all seasonal,
and you usually have about 10 weeks between each major one.
And the other one is to develop the game episodically, if you can,
regardless of if it really is.
What you're really doing here, so for Frame, for example, 30% of our 10-week
turnarounds were spent carefully and quickly designing everything that would happen.
the feeling we were trying to capture.
Mechanics and aesthetics are mechanisms to achieve that feeling,
but not the end goal themselves.
So focus on that higher feeling.
Equality title is really carefully and deliberately designed.
We spent our 10-week deadline as follows.
Three weeks carefully designing all content,
six weeks creating final assets,
and then one week for review and polish.
This allowed us to build in final chunks,
or mini polished prototypes over and over and over again.
By adopting this method, you give yourself the ability
to submit continuously throughout development
whilst building the entirety of your game.
Not only that, it means that when you hit the end,
you're either A, done,
or B, have just one more sprint to do,
one more 10-week turnaround
to bring everything together.
So make a game episodically, regardless of if it is.
Your goal is to finish as many vertical slices
as quickly as possible.
This one's kind of obvious, but everyone's a hipster.
Bring everyone in, bring others in early.
Your goal here isn't just for feedback,
it's to bring in influential people to talk about your game for you,
and for them to become familiar with the game.
For Frame, this actually started back in 2011 or 2012
when we first submitted this super rough prototype to IGF.
it obviously didn't get accepted.
But the point was so that there were a few people,
there were judges or jurors would see the game
and then in future would recognize the game
and that would help us further down the path
of the festival circuit.
This one's a little hack I like.
It's visual polish is important, but not as important as audio.
So the thing with aesthetics is it creates atmosphere
and emotional target.
And great audio design will lift every single aspect
of your game.
So if you have great audio early,
not only does it lift the entire experience,
but the game feels more polished and finished
since audio is usually left at the end of a project.
So once you've nailed your strategies and submission
processes to shows and awards.
Excuse me.
It's time to manage your show floor presence.
Again, this is about shaping that perception of quality.
So the first thing you want to do is control your crowd.
Nothing draws people in like a crowd.
So the first piece of advice is to cycle your devices.
This is so important, particularly if you are
showing a mobile game.
It gives you the unique ability to vary the number of devices
you have out on your booth.
Nothing draws people in like a crowd, like I said.
Start with a device or two out on the table,
then only add more as the crowd becomes too large to manage.
Importantly, you should only remove a device, though,
if the crowd is sort of lessening to a degree
that it's unable to sustain itself.
You always want a little bit of crowd,
and you want players to actually wait a turn
so that they draw in more viewers and more people.
Doing this during the circuit means that when
editors or journalists or anyone comes by,
they'll see the crowd and are a lot more likely
to check your game out.
Always have one more spare build. So, all that said, you never know when someone from developer relations or an editor or anyone or the media will come around.
You want to make sure that you make the most of your time at your booth.
So you want to always make sure that you have a spare device on hand.
And you never hand this out to the public.
This way you can jump in and begin the interview
or begin pitching a game immediately.
One time we were at PAX event,
showing Framed, and Jerry from Penny Arcade walked past.
So knowing that the Comet crossover would work well,
I grabbed our spare device, ran over to him.
That resulted in coverage on the front of Penny Arcade the next day,
and him kind of telling everyone
to go check out Framed the following day.
So, always have a spare build down.
And know who's on the show floor.
but also treat everyone like they could be a tastemaker
because there are a number of people who do walk around without their badges
just so that they don't get hounded.
This is my favorite one, is be a member of the crowd.
It's often really hard to get honest feedback about your game
and some people even carefully manage their facial expressions not to offend you.
So infiltrate the crowd, remove your badge or hide it
and move to the rear or the side of the crowd.
watch them, see how the players react to your game,
and listen to the conversations that bystanders have as well.
You can gain a lot of really, really valuable insight this way.
This one's a bit controversial, but
open dialogue where they can critique the game.
Obviously if you ask someone their opinion,
people like that, and they like to feel smart, so
they'll often tell you what you want.
But if that doesn't work,
you can call them out nicely on their frustration you observed
when you were masquerading as a member of the crowd.
The emotional desire in people to defend themselves
will always kind of outweigh the cognitive practice
of masking their emotions or desires.
So you can use that to your advantage,
but only if you do it in a really nice way that's not confrontational.
So, this process, this systematic approach to the festival circuit was what we employed for Framed.
So, how did it turn out for us?
Well, as you saw before, it went pretty well.
But it's important to remember that the festival circuit, or award circuit, is a system.
And like any system, if you understand how it works, it can be gamed and bent to your advantage.
So, bearing all that in mind, our launch must have been pretty successful, right?
Well, we launched Framed in November 2014,
had significant critical acclaim.
By the time we released, everything seemed to be on track.
Apple were ready.
They wanted to know our release date.
We had translated the game to 14 languages.
And it did go all right.
We got some feature spots in China and Japan and Australia
and sort of just above the fold.
So you know, those first four that you normally
see on the App Store.
We moved 20,000 units in the first weekend.
And by the end of the first week, we'd moved 35,000.
So at $5 a pop for a premium indie title, we
weren't doing half bad.
But we were really underperforming our
expectations quite seriously.
And with a budget of almost half a million Australian dollars,
half of it being salary sacrificed, so it wasn't really that much spent.
Cost and budget are different.
We were looking at only breaking even at cost.
We had a team of four to six people, we had investors to pay back.
And with a game so hyped and so critically acclaimed,
with expectations of success so high,
this was bad news for us.
So, what went wrong with our launch?
Why was our launch internally a failure?
Well, the thing with releasing anything is
there is always a huge amount of luck involved.
Anyone who tells you otherwise,
or who says that they succeeded in launching
because they did x, y, z in a very specific order,
is glossing over a huge fact that they likely don't want to admit.
That they also got extremely lucky.
We don't like to talk about it because it sounds hopeless, right?
If it's all just a gamble, what's the point?
What's the use of shaping that message of quality,
of pouring blood, sweat and tears into your project?
Excuse me, into your baby,
if it's all just a roll of the dice anyway?
And there's certainly one way to look at it.
You are literally taking your entire game budget,
walking into the casino,
and dumping the two, three, even four years of your life onto the table.
But there's a huge element of luck, because in any release,
there are a huge amount of variables that are completely out of your control.
You've done all the preparations,
but you can't really predict the weather.
Now you've just got to hope no storm rolls in.
That a large game franchise doesn't unexpectedly drop on that day,
or make a huge announcement.
Or that the media in general aren't consumed by some other scandal at the time,
or that tastes have changed.
Or that your App Store editor, who's championing your game, suddenly leaves their job.
So, just don't make games.
Honestly, it's not worth it.
OK, jokes aside though.
PR is not a silver bullet.
It's about tipping the odds of success in your favor.
Your goal isn't to have fine-grained control over your release.
It's impossible to do that.
Your goal is to tip those odds of the house in your favor.
Every release is a gamble,
and all the work that you've been doing to make your game great,
to shape that perception of value,
bringing in those tastemakers will help tip the odds further in your favor.
You want to walk into that metaphorical casino
and have all the dealers wanting you to win.
Still a high stakes gamble,
but your end goal is to slowly but surely tip those odds in your favor.
So if everything goes well and you've managed to luck it out,
congratulations.
But what if it doesn't?
What do you do if the odds don't go your way?
Well, the reason I've talked so much about shaping that perception of quality, of value,
is that by doing so, not only do you create a great game, but it's also insurance.
A quality game is the best defense against a bad launch.
Because the long tail of your game will continue to bring in people seeking quality experiences.
For those that aren't aware, just real quick, the long tail is this part in the typical sales graph.
It largely stays steady, and you can earn just as much money from it as your launch, if not more.
And this is, and pricing helps with this,
along with all the messaging and work that you've done prior to release on the circuit.
Trailers, interviews, streams,
and importantly, those award reads.
How many times have you been looking for a quality movie to watch
and made a decision based off of the critical acclaim it has?
I do it all the time. I'm sure many of you do as well.
We make judgments based off the reputation of respected people, of tastemakers.
The festival circuit not only helps in pre-release type,
it's also an essential ingredient in maintaining a sustainable long tail after release.
So if your launch doesn't go your way,
you still have a decent long tail to look forward to.
While we had certain things not go our way during launch,
we also had a lot of things that did go our way.
That's kind of just the nature of luck, right?
Kojima's Game of the Year endorsement was a great example of influential tastemakers weighing in.
It was lucky that he saw it at that point in time.
Apple continually re-feature-framed in smaller features, sales, and bundles.
We're not the only title that has done pretty well in the long tail.
Our friends at Comobius have done similarly well for Duet,
and I'm sure that there's many others who've done well in the long tail.
So the theory of the long tail is obviously that our culture and economy is shifting away from that big spike and towards niches.
And due to how our games are largely digitally distributed,
and how widely accessible our games have become through our phones,
we and many others have made more on our long tail than our launch period spike,
almost 10 times as much.
Currently, we're now sitting at almost 400,000 paid units,
almost 18 months after release.
We get featured regularly in minor feature bundles and sales.
China is actually our top performing country.
Why?
Because we're filling gaps where others don't try to.
We ensure that the design stage of the game
was intuitive and readable.
On the festival circuit, another great thing about it
is that we did travel to many countries, China included,
Japan, and being able to gauge how
people can play a game with their language barrier
or culture barrier.
So premium pricing does still work on iOS, but it's not easy.
To make it work, you need to invest heavily in shaping your
game as a premium experience and ensure it's
accessible to everyone.
You're seeking to fill gaps.
Our audience are connoisseurs.
They want well-crafted, carefully designed experiences.
The premium market does work.
You just need to shift your perspective away from what
everyone else is doing.
You won't get the same numbers as free-to-play, but we're
playing a different game.
We have a different scale of measurement.
For those of us crafting premium titles on mobile,
it's not about quantity, it's about quality.
Thank you.
I'm not sure if we have time for questions.
I think we do.
I think you have five minutes, yeah.
I think you have to line up at the thingy.
Hey, considering the long tail, I'm curious if the festival
circle is relevant after a launch of the game.
I mean, you launched, and then do you still
try to go to these events?
Yeah, that's a really good question.
So the question was, is the festival circuit still
valid after you've released?
Good question. I know a lot of people who have still done it a lot.
Like NecroDancer still go on the circuit and continually do well, it shows well.
We particularly haven't done it, but I can only imagine that it helps bolster that long tail, yeah.
Hey there Joshua, so my question relates to anyone who's interested in making games but maybe doesn't actually have the capital to get to the stage that you are at.
How does the festival circuit enable those type of game designers? Because obviously at GDC we get to see a lot of like Games Jam games and smaller sort of stands.
But is there any way that games like that in your experience have ever achieved those accreditations and should they even be seeking those kind of...
Yeah, so the question was, for people with less money, is the festival circuit still
something that they should pursue?
I'd argue yes, because the goal of the festival circuit is to be submitting these things,
and if you are accepted...
as you know, like a showcase game, or they're gonna give you,
they usually give you a free booth.
So it's a really good way to get free playtesting and free booths.
You still have the problem of travel and everything,
but I guess
that's kind of one of the
you know,
facts about making games, I guess, is that it costs money, or time, and time is money.
But you wouldn't say there's a glass ceiling in the sense that you could come here and...
No, I don't think, yeah, I don't feel there is, no.
Hey, so thanks for a great talk.
So even despite all the hard work
you went into putting the festival circuit
and getting awarded on there, the initial launch
was a little underwhelming, as you said.
And it was only the long-term quality
that helped create the awesome long tail.
Looking back on that, was there something
you misjudged with the initial festival response
that might have contributed to that?
And if so, are you trying to work
on that for your next project?
The question was, was there something wrong I had done?
Or not wrong, but misjudged during the circuit, right?
To contribute to the launch.
It's a good question.
I mean, you can always look back and say,
I wish I did X, Y, or Z better.
But to be honest, I think that we did as well as we could do.
We did do pretty well, but I think sometimes,
like I was saying, when you release something,
there's a huge amount of luck involved.
It's not a nice thing to hear or talk about because it sounds hopeless, but I don't really believe it is
You're just trying to tip the odds in your favor
Sometimes it doesn't go exactly the way you want and that's just kind of a fact of life
Thank you
Cool I think that's it. Thanks for coming everyone