Thank you.
Something about cell phones and forms.
All right, let's start.
All right, so my name is Itay Karen.
I'm the owner of Untame and the creator
of a game called Mushroom 11.
Mushroom 11 is a game about destruction and growth.
And the only way you can move is by destroying
your own cells.
The game was released in October on Steam, GOG, and Humble.
And we're gonna talk a little bit
about the design of the puzzles.
Alright, quick background.
Game started in 2012 at the Global Game Jam at NYU.
The theme was the Ouroboros,
which is the snake eating its tail.
I was thinking about a 2D creature
that has a set of cells,
and you remove the cells and it immediately regrows,
so we have this cycle of destruction and growth.
I called it...
pixel blob and quickly change it to mushroom 11, which is a whole story in itself. This
is how the game looked after 48 hours. It clearly had something interesting going for
it, although it was very slow and clunky.
and even though it was presented in this very naive layout.
I recreated this layout just for the purpose of this talk
and I was trying to think, you know,
what are the reasoning for me to just put this layout?
and this is basically the default layout.
I can clearly see Mario here,
and what would Mario do in this case?
You could either slide or jump over the gap,
and then I just put this interesting mechanics on it,
and even...
Even though I really didn't give any attention
to the layout already,
even though you don't have any jump,
you could do a bunch of different and interesting things
like use the free form pruning and split
and the reattachment and the fact that you have
this cellular level persistence of the physics
to go over all sorts of obstacles.
You can use the rigid skeleton.
to grip and conform to a terrain.
You can use the idea that you can regenerate
from even one cell, which kind of opens the idea
of sacrificing, you can destroy the cells,
but as long as you have even one,
then you're good to go to cross all sorts of obstacles.
The idea that you can shape your set of cells in any way
means it gives you unlimited shape and extent,
but it also shifts the center of mass,
which opens up a whole source of interesting behaviors
and physical effects like gyration, tumbling, and momentum.
But yeah, the risk was that I have this interesting
mechanics, but it's presented in this familiar package.
it took me the longest time to kind of try to figure out
what this game is about.
I call it the NT platform, which represents the mental leap
that I had to go through to kind of understand
what's the nature of this behavior,
and what does it mean, what's the mechanic mean,
what does it need to have.
Also, it also stands for the idea that the main weapon
for any platform, which is jumping,
is completely absent from the vocabulary of this mechanic.
A couple of words on the mechanics design.
So one of the first thing I did was to eliminate growback.
So as you remove cells, they immediately change
the probability for regrowth where you removed it.
So it kind of perpetuates the growth away from the cursor,
allowing you more control over where you're going.
Another thing is that this game is not about walking.
It's not a walking simulator, which means that
It's not just one button or joystick.
There's a lot of attention into just moving.
So making this enhanced gyration
and allowing you to tumble forward.
gives you this opportunity to make this much more enjoyable,
even this very, very basic motion, which is very important.
The idea of eliminating the mid-air growth,
something that's kind of controversial in my own mind,
the fact that you can't grow mid-air
allows you to control your own size,
and by that you control your own weight.
Also, if I did allow mid-air growth,
it means that you can kind of...
eliminate the purity of the puzzles
by just flying over some of the obstacles.
So this was eliminated.
So I'll talk about that further.
And they have the idea of using the size,
and the smaller the mushroom,
the bigger it tries to grow back to its original size,
which means that if you keep it really small,
it grows really fast, you can walk really fast,
but your size is super small,
so you have very small surface area,
so you have less control,
so you have this interesting speed control trade-off,
and if you have a trade-off, you have a game.
So you have this unlimited growth,
which is something that took me a bit to reach.
For a long time I had this energy bar,
and you would pick up these creatures
and gain energy and use their energy to regrow.
But then I realized that I was actually
punishing the players for doing the one thing
that they enjoy the most.
So quickly I just completely split it,
and people ask me what the creatures are.
Well now you know, they're just for points.
And.
the growth is completely unlimited.
And the idea of going from right to left,
if you played this game in 2012, 2013,
you know that this is actually designed for tablets.
And if you try to play this game on a tablet,
you realize that as you go from left to right,
your hand is in the way of anything
that's coming towards you.
So I just thought, why not just make it from right to left?
I mean, I'm talking about right-handed,
who are the grand majority, sorry, lefties.
And, but then it's like the question is,
so why are all the platforms go from left to right?
So I had this interesting discussion
and it went through, you know,
western languages with ink being smudged
if you would go from right to,
if you write from right to left.
And then the Cartesian coordinate system.
And then maybe some lazy developer
trying to use unsigned integer.
to avoid going negative.
Anyway, so why not use power-ups?
I've been thinking about that a lot,
and I had a lot of attempts.
Why not have it bigger, go lighter, faster, invincible?
So yeah, I decided to not go there at all
because it took me the longest time
to figure out the parameters of the growth,
the speed, the number of cells, the weight,
all these things took the longest time
to find that sweet spot.
If it was too small,
you couldn't reach some of the obstacles.
If it was too big,
you have a lot of things to pay attention to
and everything grows.
So if you leave something behind, it grows.
So that actually makes kind of no sense.
It's not an advantage to have more cells necessarily.
And also the idea of invincibility.
What does it even mean when the main control
is to destroy your own self?
So all these things kind of made no sense.
So I decided at some point that the mechanics
is going to stay the same and the entire mechanics
is going to be built into the environment.
The environment is the mechanics.
If you keep minimal character features
and versatile environment,
you end up with a rich experience.
Also, I was stupid enough to submit the game
even back in 2012 to a festival.
And while I did get in, one of the jurors told me
I'm concerned that there isn't much more to be explored with this mechanic.
Challenge accepted.
All right.
So the next few years, I was going with my trusted sketchbook everywhere, as you probably
noticed, and had a bunch of ideas.
I immediately tried to implement them.
And I came up with this set of puzzle mission statements.
Create environments that challenge the mechanics.
Experiment with as many environments
and derived mechanics as possible.
And granted this is completely personal.
This is a personal challenge that I put for myself
to dig deep into this mechanic
and figure out what I can do with it.
I don't think that a game is complete
when every single path is explored.
Build on and combine mechanics,
challenging logic and skill.
And following the core unpredictable nature
of the mechanics,
encourage exploration and open solutions.
and make every challenge unique to Mushroom 11.
Even this puzzle here is,
well, we've all seen platforms in platformers,
but this is almost like a backwards,
ironic implementation of those platforms.
Now, as for the goal design,
this is another thing that I took this decision
very early on.
to have a linear and consequential progression.
Even the side tracks are kind of like
just right on the main path,
so you can just go and explore a little more.
For me, it was a matter of mastery,
just figuring out a lot of the puzzles,
our ideas are based on each other.
It was important for me to have the players being primed by learning all these different
vocabulary pieces and just continue from there.
And also since I'm kind of the product of the 90s, this is the kind of games that I
liked to play as a kid, so I really enjoyed those.
As for the, even the story, the story is told
in a completely passive way, using background images
in order to not interrupt that flow,
so that was a completely conscious decision.
All right, let's go quickly through
some of the puzzle systems.
So even walking in Mushroom 11 is quite a challenge,
you know, so just understanding the fundamentals of control.
Once you understand those, you can go
and start mastering those basic control
when things are starting to move under your feet,
you have some time pressure.
If you go into the idea of balance
and this changing center of mass,
you have unstable foundation,
all of a sudden open up bunch of new ideas.
Excuse.
Come on.
Sorry.
So, by changing your balance and changing your center of mass, you also change the environment
in some way.
Use your friction, the fact that you gain some momentum, you can apply that momentum
on objects on the scene.
Also, you can apply that balance on other objects, and those objects in turn have different
interaction with the environment by themselves, so that's another family of challenges.
splitting another one of the core elements of Mushroom11.
Clearly, the fact that you have distributed growth,
the number of cells stays the same,
but you can cut it to any number of pieces
with no loss of mass.
But as you do so, you have some sort of attention management.
You have a few pieces,
you need to pay attention to each one of them,
but each one of them can be assigned with a different task.
So that opens up, well, a bunch of the ideas
in Mushroom 11 come from that.
And also you can have the environment split it for you,
enabling a bunch of interesting,
at least visually interesting ideas as well.
The structure of Mushroom 11.
You can use it to conform and grip onto objects
and use it to progress further into the level
in various ways.
The structure itself can sustain any physical forces
of gravity and other centrifugal forces
and momentum and all that.
And it's even strong enough to sustain
forces applied by other objects.
So you can use it to stop other machines and whatnot.
Shape, well clearly one of the things you wanna do
is try to shape a certain silhouette as given by,
whatever in this case we've used the shape sensors
which is an entire discussion I could talk about.
What did I do?
But more interestingly,
you can use your shape to change the environment.
or in some way become the solution.
You become a tool, this dynamic tool in the environment
that you can perpetually change
and align to the environment.
A quick word on the physics.
The physics of shape-shifting,
it seems very natural to us now.
If you think about it,
if you change the center of mass,
it means that you expect a negative force
to compensate for that change.
And we don't have that in Mushroom11.
In fact, there is no consequences at all.
we're avoiding the law of conservation of energy
and it feels very, very natural.
It also means that you have no force
applied on the environment.
So what do you do when you don't have a force
on the environment?
You need to find other ways of handling the environment
and solving puzzles.
It also means that you have to grow around objects,
you can't grow into them, you don't have any force,
so you kind of like slime through cracks,
which is pretty much the idea of the dysfunctional organism.
Makes a lot of sense.
That's the main reason why moving in tunnels
is so satisfying.
Alright, so once you have physics,
any physical object combined with the fact
that you have shape shifting and splitting
becomes interesting in any way you put it.
And it's completely unpredictable in some cases.
and the amount of things that you can do
just by placing an arbitrary moving object with mushroom
is almost always fun, at least for me anyway, so I enjoy it.
So a lot of these puzzles just started with me
putting stuff on the screen and seeing what happened.
Add that to the fact that you have this cellular level
persistence, any cell has its own momentum
and that momentum is inherited even between
splits and reattachments.
We talked a little bit before about the changing mass,
the fact that you have some control over your mass.
So sometimes your weight combined with some momentum
is the only way you can solve some puzzles.
But in some cases you would actually have to mitigate that.
changes in a way to keep yourself light.
So using split and mass already looks a little different.
And the fact that you have remote mass shifting,
again, something that doesn't seem very intuitive,
but once you play it, it's level seven,
you kind of understand it intuitively,
that you need to balance the seesaw
while progressing one of the pieces towards the exit.
Applying external forces, well, we've all seen wind
in many platformers, but when you have a shape shifter
that reacts to the wind in different ways
based on the shape, it already is interesting.
We used some turbulence, simulated turbulence here,
and a bunch of other stuff,
but basically this is just wind.
And another little change we have at the same level
is the sticky walls, these plants.
It's slightly similar to the wall climbing
that we've seen before, but in this case,
As you move away from the wall, the center of mass changes,
it means that you need a bigger surface area
to stay on the wall.
It's another little change that makes a lot of difference
and other interesting flavor.
And one of my favorite things is the water
allowing you to have all sorts of interesting effects,
this unrestricted growth underwater.
The fact that you can shift yourself underwater
with no consequences allow you to do all sorts of things
that obviously are not natural,
but they are completely natural
in the world of Mushroom 11.
A couple of words about the hazards of Mushroom 11.
First of all, fireballs, like almost every other game.
They are, I call them the slap on the wrist
because they are pretty much just like your eraser.
They remove cells, so they look very flashy and scary,
but that's just because of what you know about fireballs.
More interestingly, you have the acid infection
that just spreads inside your body
and the only way you can heal yourself
is by completely removing the infected area,
which I think is a nice metaphor
for the story of Mushroom 11, by the way.
And the insta-death, not used a lot,
but another interesting effect,
allowing me to put some interesting obstacles
later on in the game.
The boss is one of my favorite interesting opportunities
in the game, probably the one thing that took me
the longest time to develop.
Every level ends with this ultimate test of acquired skills,
things that you've learned through that level.
So this is kind of this perpetual procedural puzzle system
that just behaves regardless of whether you're there or not
it just lives there and then when you come into their
chamber interrupting their way of life.
It's just a lot of fun just designing those things.
And one of the things we were talking about
the consequential progression of the game,
one thing that I,
don't necessarily enjoy in some games is the idea of key drop that magically after you beat a boss
you have it has a key that you open a door and you magically teleport to someplace else. For me
it was very important to have some sort of consequence. You kill the boss because the boss
is in your way to the next area and sometimes you even use their corpse to progress to the next level.
All right, puzzle types.
Okay, so clear you can use it to have some logical puzzles
and a bunch of exploration and open solutions.
This one is a logical puzzle
with a bunch of different solutions.
One of the things that is important
when you have open solutions
is the idea of avoiding distractions.
I call it the loose brick
because if you have a loose brick,
it probably means that you need to push it.
Once.
the player feels that there's something in there,
they're gonna just stick to that solution
and try it over and over again.
So just make sure that when you have open solutions,
then just don't make things that are taking away
from that experience.
And then you have all sorts of combination of skill, logic, and exploration,
which basically is most of the puzzles in Mushroom 11.
You know, you get to see the entire, all the elements in the puzzle.
You try to figure out what to do, and then you still have some hard time using your own
unpredictable nature of character to get through.
all the way to 100% skill-based puzzles,
timing-based, precision-based,
basically taking something from the general platform world
and putting it in the world of Mushroom11,
and I'm going to talk about that puzzle in a moment.
All right, we should bring this to what went well.
This is a mid-mortem because clearly I'm working
on the tablet version, mobile tablet version
of Mushroom 11, so try and look back, see what happened.
What went well, the game got great reviews,
a bunch of game of the year awards,
best platform of the year,
but that really doesn't mean much.
What is important to me is the depth and detail
that I think I got into this game
with environments, the art.
the story, the music, the audio, and the technology,
I think I'm very proud of what we achieved.
The variety of puzzle and puzzle systems,
the creatures, the bosses, and a lot of secrets,
some of which are not yet discovered, by the way.
The minimalism of the mechanics, clearly,
and the storytelling, which is a talk in itself.
of teaching. I'm extremely proud in the way we give this novel mechanic to the players
and slowly teach them, by the way with the help of my co-designer Julia, my wife, how
to get through and understand it like...
Every new obstacle is kind of taught
and you're primed through these things.
So by the end of level one or two,
players already know how to use this mechanic.
The challenge, clearly the game is very challenging.
If you played it, you know what I mean.
And the depth of emotion as a result.
As someone said, I love Mushroom 11,
I hate Mushroom 11, but I also love it.
Which brings me to what could be improved.
The difficulty curve.
Clearly the game ramps up in the second half of the game.
A lot of skill and time-based puzzles
versus more slow exploration logic-based puzzles.
The length and the density of the later levels as well.
I guess some of it is my ego.
I found all these cool mechanics.
I wanted to put all of them in.
And even the very basic game design elements
that everybody knows that you need to kind of have
something, you challenge the player
and then have some sort of relief.
But all these things were so cool.
I just wanted to put all of them
for the enjoyment of the players.
So it ended up really being long
and very, very dense and very hard.
Limited control, of course, the abundance of timing based
and vertically based in precision control that's required
and the idea of purity versus fun with no growth in midair.
All these things kind of contribute to the idea
of limited control, so limited control.
in some cases caused some frustration, clearly.
And the idea of lingering defeat and lingering triumph,
which is some interesting observation that I had recently,
which brings me back to that puzzle that we've seen before,
the 100% skill-based puzzle.
This is actually the top RQ factor puzzle in the game.
RQ stands for Rage Quit, by the way.
So I have analytics for all the puzzles,
and I have this list of all the puzzles
that did well and did...
Not as well.
And the problems with this puzzle are pretty clear.
It's a limited control based puzzle.
It's very, it's timing based, it's precision,
a lot of vertical motion.
It's surrounded by other very, very hard puzzles as well,
so there's not a lot of relief.
And ultimately, it has the lingering defeat.
If you fall off the platform,
you have this long, extrusioning,
wait until you hit the ground and even then you have some time to go back to where you
were.
So clearly there's something wrong with that specific puzzle.
Although this is all Julia's fault because it's her favorite puzzle.
On the other hand, you have the lingering triumph.
So after you beat a boss, there's this moment of…
just basking the glory of winning and instead what mushroom 11 does because of that purity is to
Introduce another small challenge to just go through to physically go through to the next level
Instead of just enjoying that moment of winning
Which reminded me of one of the biggest changes between Street Fighter 1 and Street Fighter 2
when they introduced this slow motion after you beat your opponent.
So you have that lingering effect of like seeing yourself beating or getting beaten.
So just that emotion is just much stronger.
Which kind of also reminded me of one of my least favorite games in the world, Monopoly,
which is pretty much all based on lingering defeat and lingering triumph.
Which reminds me, a quick take away on this whole thing.
Test early and often.
Everybody knows that my game was out on day two.
It tested often because we went to a bunch of events
so we showed it all the time.
Diverse beta team.
That's very, very important.
I have a bunch of beta testers.
They're all awesome.
I love you all, you're probably here.
But they're all really good players.
They're fans of the game.
and they're pretty much better than me.
And if you see why some of the problems didn't surface,
people wanted the game to be harder and more challenging.
And you know, so just make sure
that you have a very diverse beta team.
All right, so going forward to the tablet mobile version
that I'm working on now.
So featuring clearly touch-based,
which is the original design.
A shorter best of cut.
And the reasons are, we want to enable
the modified puzzle selection as discussed.
A better fit for the intended audience
and expected price point.
And technical constraints like memory and performance
and aspect ratio, a lot of these things kind of dictate
a different selection of puzzles.
And what we're doing now is obviously working
on the difficulty curve, balancing skill, logic,
and exploration, modifying, removing puzzles
with limited and timing based controls
like the ones we've seen.
tweak the general control parameters.
So some of these things like the purity factor
is gonna be altered a little bit,
and maybe also in the other, in the Steam,
in this desktop game as well.
As for the lingering defeat and triumph,
modify some of the layouts, less punishing replay,
and more checkpoints where needed.
And ease the post-boss challenge, or make it a bonus.
We're experimenting with a couple of approaches.
Constraints and capabilities of the device.
So, right to left for lefties.
So, we're thinking of doing a mirrored version,
just for lefties.
And the four by three aspect ratio,
which means that some puzzles are unfit.
There's the idea of exposing.
all the elements in the puzzle in one screen,
which is another discussion, but anyway.
And the idea of multi-touch puzzles are now allowed.
And a lot of puzzles are designed for multi-touch
and they couldn't be in because you only have one mouse.
Imagine you have like a bridge of mushroom
and then you need to cut it with two fingers
so just the center piece just falls down.
Anyway, so any ideas and any feedback is welcome.
Thanks.