Please welcome the chairperson of the Independent Games Festival,
Kelly Wallach.
Hello, and welcome to the 19th Annual Independent Games Festival Awards.
So this marks my second year as chairman of the IGF, and during this time, I've felt
very fortunate to have had numerous thoughtful and really profound conversations about what
the IGF represents and how much this community means to us all.
I feel it's a real testament to how caring and impassioned our industry can be, and it
makes me hopeful for the next generation of developers.
So thank you.
I'd also like to thank the judges and jury members who put countless hours into reviewing
and discussing the games, and a personal thank you to the staff who make all this possible.
Our sponsors for this year are ID at Xbox, the IGF Platinum sponsor.
and Samsung, the IGF Gold sponsor.
As an independent games community evolves,
we work to reflect these changes in a way
that embraces the diversity of games
submitted to the festival each year.
This past year, we redefined the Nuova category
into one that simply represents art and games
and is meant to further the conversation around titles
that push the medium forward and make us think of games
in a new light.
In addition, I'm very happy to introduce the Alt Control GDC
Award, which will be presented for the very first time
on this stage.
Oh!
Woo!
The Alt Control Award is given out in association
with the independent showcase that's
playable on the GDC show floor.
It's meant to highlight the growing alternative game
controller and hardware community, which
represents an important but difficult to sustain
side of the industry.
Our goal with both of these changes is to raise awareness
and hopefully inspire all of you to think about your own work
in new and creative ways.
A few years ago at GDC, I gave a talk
which was essentially a short visual essay on community size
and the level of informational overload
we're expected to consume on a daily basis.
It was something I gave a great deal of thought to when the games community was experiencing
a lot of toxicity, and I thought since now it's moved into a national conversation, it
might be worth revisiting some of these thoughts here.
Studies show that negative emotions have a longer-lasting influence than positive, which,
if you're trying to drive web traffic, gain followers, or become famous, there's actually
an incentive to create a positive reinforcement for negative emotions.
With access to online communities that can easily be upwards of 50 times more than we're
able to meaningfully interact with, not to mention that the entire whole of the internet
consists of about 23 million times this number, it makes you wonder if we're not short-circuiting
ourselves a bit.
The saying goes, all politics is local, meaning that real national and global change originates
in local communities and radiates outwards.
Everyone in this room is arguably at the forefront of an industry that has an opportunity to
help shape the way people process and understand the world around them.
You have a unique chance to affect long-term social change through your work, and I would
argue a responsibility to approach this work from a place of compassion and understanding.
This is your community, and this is where you start that change.
Thank you all again for your time, support, and contributions to the IGF.
And congratulations to all the honorable mentions, and best of luck to all the finalists.
And now I'm very happy to introduce the host of tonight's show, Nina Freeman.
Thank you, Kelly.
I know, I know, I miss Nathan Vella too, but I'll be your host for the 19th Annual Independent
Games Festival Awards.
Okay, so, let's start again.
Hi, my name is Nina Freeman, I'm a level designer at Fulbright working on our forthcoming game
Tacoma.
A demo of Tacoma is actually at GDC in the Day of the Devs showcase in case you're curious.
Outside of Fulbright, you might recognize me from former IGF-nominated titles Sibyl
and How Do You Do It, the game where you have sex with your online boyfriend, and the game
where you pretend your Barbie dolls are fucking, respectively.
See?
It's like sex.
It's pretty weird and amazing to be up here saying this in front of a room full of my
heroes and people who are wondering who the hell I am.
Listen, I'm nervous. It's not easy being a stage in front of what looks like a million, a million and a half people out there.
Listen guys, that was a Trump tweet. I'm not a comedian. This is my first time hosting. This is nerve-wracking.
So...
I didn't see that. I really wish I could have packed my good luck plushie,
but it was just too big and wouldn't fit in my suitcase, and I really wish I had it.
I screwed up that joke, sorry.
So I know this is super stressful. I had this guy flown in first class just for you.
I hope he offers you some some good luck and kill it out there, Nina. Nina, everybody!
That's my poo, soom, soom.
It's my good luck plushie.
Thank you, Nathan.
So I remember my first year at GDC in 2013.
I sat out there in the audience and took a bunch of selfies
and tweeted some dumb jokes that probably no one read.
I had no idea what I was doing as a game developer.
And honestly, I still have no idea.
What I do know is that my process pretty much
amounts to the following, as illustrated by Diego Garcia.
Go out for happy hour and finally come up with an idea for a game after about two glasses
of wine and a plate of french fries.
Frantically write down the idea in my iPhone notepad app in complete darkness and pass
out.
Forget that I had the idea at all and find it in my phone a month later.
Work on the game until I get distracted by a new anime.
I think my process is bad, and I really don't feel like I know what I'm doing still, but
that's just fine.
It's okay to feel like you don't know what you're doing because we all make different
games, we all have different ways of working, and we are all unique as developers.
What's important is to create what you want to play, regardless of what other people think.
That's what I learned by coming back to GDC and the IGF since 2013.
And this year was no exception.
We've got games about connecting with your mushroom-picking
grandmother, fucking your brother's classmates,
yelling at your friend on the couch
to finish chopping the onions, attempting to seduce Sebastian,
and so on.
These indie developers are really making the games
that they want to play and that many of us
didn't even know we wanted.
OK, so it's time for our first award.
By the way, this Pooh Tsum Tsum is right here next to me,
and I'm going to put it down there.
So if any of the winners want to give it a hug when they come
up here, you're welcome to.
OK, so first award.
This one is very special to me because I was a student not
too long ago.
When I was lucky enough to start college,
I was studying English literature.
I was a huge nerd that spent all of her classes writing poetry
in various Hello Kitty notebooks.
Little did I know I would eventually pass up a career in poetry by stumbling into video game development.
And I ended up making games in the graduate program at NYU.
So, there's no set path.
The amazing thing about being a student is that you can experiment both with your work and with your life.
The students we're honoring tonight are amazing examples of this.
They're carving their own paths with their work by finding new ways to express themselves in this medium and blowing us all away in the process.
And the finalists for the Best Student Game are...
Xiomara Isaac, Jack Yates, Bradford Horton, Campbell Fletcher.
Far, Lone Sails.
Developed by Mr. Wells Game Service.
Don Schmacher, Goran Saric, Martina Hugentobler, Philip Stern.
Frog Climbers.
Developed by Team Crew.
Sebastian Larson, Semi-Parlayan.
Charlotte Eliason, Andrew Bankston.
Lily, Colors of Santa Luz,
developed by the Lily, Colors of Santa Luz team.
Gabriel Sarnikoff, Florian Coudray,
Alex Accorsi, Mathieu Batelier.
Un Pas Fragile, developed by Geraud Découvé,
Alice Boron, Gregory Parici,
Gaspar Morel.
And the winner of the IGF award for best student game is
Un Pas Fragile.
Okay, this is just a list of people I have to thank.
I didn't think I'd win this prize.
I want to thank everyone at IGF for nominating us.
This is like really cool, so thank you.
I want to thank the organization,
and of course our school in France,
Angemin School, if you want to study there,
go to the school, it's a public school.
Okay.
And I want to thank all the indies and developers out there, making games, playing games.
This is really inspiring for us to be out there with you, so, thank you.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.
Oh, so cute.
Okay, so, Tinder is like the hotness these days, right?
Shout out to everyone in the audience who's literally browsing Tinder on their phones
right now.
I know you're out there.
Maybe you're thinking, wow, this person's Tinder pic is like really sexy, damn.
Well, what if you ran into one of the game's upper excellence in visual art on Tinder?
These games would probably have no trouble lining up a few hot pictures.
In fact, I'm sure they could all land a date on video game Tinder based on looks alone.
Can you even imagine the selfies these games would take?
They'd all be well-lit, well-composed,
with striking angles and sensuous curves.
I mean, let's face it.
These games are hot.
These are some of the most beautiful games
from the last year.
So dating or GDC hostile hookups aside,
the artists who worked on these games
are absolute heroes for executing such incredible style
in a medium that can be truly demanding
on an artist's time and skill set.
The finalists for Excellence in Visual Art are.
Excellence in Visual Art.
Hyper Light Drifter.
Developed by Art Machine.
Alex Preston.
Casey Hunt.
Sean Ward.
Inside.
Developed by Playdeck.
The Inside Development Team.
Old Man's Journey
Developed by Broken Rules
Clayman Scott
Brian May
Lip Camarella
Felix Bojack
She Remembered Caterpillars
Developed by Jumpsuit Entertainment
Daniel Leander Goffin
David Premier
Cassandra Cobb
Brian Quek
The Flame in the Flag, developed by the Molasses Club.
Scott Sinclair.
Chad LeFlair.
Gwen Frey.
Virginia, developed by Variable State.
Terry Kenney.
Matt Wilde.
Stevie Brown.
Connor McCann.
And the winner for the IGF Award for Excellence in Visual Art is...
Hyper Light Drifter.
Come closer.
Come, get over here.
Hey, I didn't prepare anything, but I just
want to say thank you to everybody on the team,
including those who couldn't be here, Casey and Sean
and Cosimo and everyone else who helped on the project
and believed in us.
And I'm going to tear up a little bit.
It was a hard, uh, it was a challenging thing to make this game, and uh, we put our hearts and souls into it.
And Teddy's taking a goddamn selfie.
Because it ruins everything.
Um, but uh, thank you. This shit means so much to us.
And it's, it's, I'm gonna cry so I'm gonna leave the stage now. Bye!
Okay, hi, I'm back.
Composing and designing sound is not my strong suit,
but I did try my hand at it once in middle school.
When I was probably 13, I made a ton of AMVs,
which basically amounted to recording footage
of Final Fantasy X-2, Kingdom Hearts,
and Lafina over trance songs.
That really is from when I was like 13.
Okay.
Needless to say, my attempts at enhancing any game or anime with trance music were ill-advised,
so now I leave it to the professionals.
Sound can be the ingredient that warms up the game just right,
adding a layer that subtly but seriously ties together the entire experience.
I'm also sure that all of the nominees would make way better AMVs than I ever could,
and for that alone they deserve massive praise.
Our nominees for Excellence in Audio are...
Excellence in Audio Everything
Developed by David O'Reilly
Damian D'Viday
Eduardo Ortiz-Fra
Ben Lucas-Boyson
Goners
Developed by Art and Heart
Ditto
Martin Poirier,
Bjorn Rennelen,
Hyper Light Drifter,
developed by Heart Machine,
Rich Vreeland,
Akash Thakkar,
Alex Preston,
Inside,
developed by Playdead.
Martine Stig Anderson
The Flame in the Fled developed by the Molasses Fled
Patrick Ballcroft
Chad Regan
Virginia
Developed by Variable State
Linden Holly.
And the award for excellence in audio goes to
Gonner.
Whoa, shit.
Wait.
There you go.
Hello.
Thank you.
This is incredible.
It's such a big honor to be winning this award.
We were really afraid we would freeze up,
so we prerecorded this message just in case.
Uh.
Hello.
Well, this is the whole kind of reason why this game was made,
sort of the audio anyways, was made in the first place,
was we had this little synthesizer,
and we thought we had this stupid game
that doesn't need footsteps.
Let's make some cool sounds for it.
And here we are, like, one and a half years later.
And here we are.
Thanks to Raw Fury.
Thanks to Ditto for making this game.
Thanks for Joar, who can't be here today,
who's in a cabin in Norway eating rotten fish.
We love you. Thanks to everyone like Alexina.
I really want to thank Alexina and Johan Thoreson.
Fuck.
And thanks for everyone, all the nominees. It's an honor to be here with you.
We're truly honored and thankful and kind of shaking up here.
So have a good night onwards. I'll see you at that party.
Hi again.
So before we get too teary-eyed from watching
all of these adorable blushing developers accept
their awards, we can spend some time
with one of my favorite people, Ash.
Ash.
Time to check the bloggers for me.
AHHHHH! FEEDING!
This is a code, Red people.
We need to scrap everything we've been doing for Call of Duty 8.
We need that farm money or we're through.
Scrap it, we're way too far into development to just...
Oh my dears! Now!
We, we, we could add a farming mini-game.
I like it!
But we're a game about guns. Our fans will revolt.
I agree.
Compromise!
Farm guns!
Play a gun, watch it grow!
Shoot terrorists to fertilize the soil!
Circles!
Now, what else does Stardew have that we don't?
Uh, relationships?
What are those?
They're like, um, you know, when people fall in love?
Like a man and a woman?
Actually, in Stardew, you can marry someone of your own gender.
I'm a visual learner.
You too, Kiss.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Yeah, yeah, Bobby Booster.
We're going to collide with Snicker. Yeah!
I'm still missing something.
What else? What else?
Farming's all about kind of investing time and love into something
and watching it grow and in fruition.
Right before terrorists take it from you!
Uh, sure!
Pre-order now to get the AC-130 drone strike mission!
Please welcome to the stage, Alt Control GDC co-founder, John Paulson.
Good evening, everyone.
I'm very excited to be giving out the first ever
Alt Control GDC award,
honoring this year's best alternative controller games
from the 100 plus submissions and 20 games
featured in this year's popular GDC exhibit.
The spirit of these ingenious designs
is captured in the video playing behind me,
showing this year's picks.
This is the fourth version of the exhibit,
and the inspiration for it goes back much further.
I grew up during the golden age of arcades, where every cabinet seemed to have its own
enchanting alternative controller.
Later, I would hoard more console peripherals than I had shelf space.
Nintendo's zapper and power pad, Steel Battalion's behemoth setup, and all of Konami's pioneering
music controllers.
More recently, I can recall when I first played sports
with a Wiimote, when I swiped, flicked, and tilted
a mobile touch screen, and when I waved a magic Vive wand.
Non-traditional controls are being
adopted by developers big and small,
and this continues to change how we play games.
Each new way to play elicits a sense of wonder
and childlike inquisitiveness, which
is showcased incredibly well by the alternative control games
that are honored this year.
Since 2014, over 400 developer teams have submitted for this showcase.
Their switchboards, popsicles, pug butts, caterpillar sleeping bags, and Arduino skills
have been transformed into unforgettable hands-on experiences.
This year's creations will be playable for the rest of the week at the Alt Control GDC
exhibit in the North Hall behind the IGF Pavilion.
Earlier this week, a panel of judges played through all of this year's games and we're
presenting the winner with this custom handcrafted award made by the ingenious Alt Control GDC
alumni and line wobbler creator, Robin Baumgarten.
Thanks Robin.
So please join me in congratulating the winner of the first Alt Control GDC award.
Fierce Fear.
Well, uh, I don't have anything prepared for this.
I just...
Are you sure that doesn't say moonlight?
Okay.
Just making sure.
So I'm really blown away to have won this award.
I mean, we really couldn't have done it without all of us
who are part of this team.
We really want to thank our two product designers who
are lost in the sea of us back there,
Jae-Sung and Ying, who both were behind the fabrication
of the game.
And we love what we do, and we're
glad that people enjoy our games and have fun with it.
So.
We'll be here all week, so come on down and play it.
Thanks a lot.
Appreciate it.
Hey, Parsons represent.
Yeah.
I'm back!
Okay, hi.
I would really like to play Truth or Dare with the Nuovo nominees
because they are tonight's featured risk-takers.
I mean, seriously, these people made games that challenge our ideas about what games are and can be.
I actually can't think of a crazier dare than
Challenge the Masses!
Make a game that contradicts their expectations about what video games are
and get ready because some of them are gonna be pissed.
I'd like to personally thank every single person
who worked on a Nuovo-nominated game
for your bravery and commitment to making games
that are challenging and beautiful examples
of the future of this medium.
On that note, here are the finalists for the Nuovo Award.
Nuovo Award. Close.
Developed by Tobias Sarkis.
Moritz Ebe.
Diaries of a Spaceport Janitor.
Developed by Sunday Month.
Isabel James Shasha, Matthew Breganti, Mel Stanchel, Campbell Fletcher.
Everything.
Developed by David O'Reilly.
Damian D. Vidae.
Virginia.
Developed by Variable State.
Jonathan Burrows.
Terry Kenney.
Lyndon Holland.
Islands, Non Places, developed by Carl Burton.
Leave Oma, developed by Florian Belfman.
New Cartographer, developed by Tichou Manyeye.
Oikerspiel Book One, developed by David Hannava.
Donkey Kong, Eurydice Moore.
Oh my god, this is really exciting.
And the winner of the Nuovo Award is
Oikospiel, book one.
Fuck Trump, fuck Pence, this country's built on immigrants!
That's it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much!
So I have that one meme to present and then I have a pitch also that relates to the theme
of the game, so I feel like I ought to do it.
How much is the money that I get for this?
It's like $3,000?
Probably.
Let's say it's $5,000 so I can calculate it better.
The pitch is that everyone in this room and beyond takes 5% of their income and pools
it together into a union that could be called the GPU, General Precariat Union.
So that's all. I just want you to think about it, because there's a lot of people who are
struggling to make ends meet. So that's what the game is about. But anyway, thank you all so much.
Thank you to everyone in the room. This has been a really inspiring...
Sort of world to be in I kind of feel like this is I was just telling other people this feels like it's like my
School or something. It's like the game school, and it's really wonderful, so thank you so much for the whole community
Thank you to everyone that I've worked on
projects with, you know, thanks Ed, thank you Sean, thank you Fernando for these tools that I made this game with. I didn't have to
program at all to make this, which Fernando made these wonderful tools. Thank you everyone else. Thank you Josh for the
website. Thank you Anissa. Thank you my family. And yeah, thank you all so much. I actually, sorry, I wrote down a few
things on the phone. Maybe I forgot something. I just want to make sure I'm not forgetting.
Yeah, oh yeah, Eurydice. It said it's made by Eurydice. I think this is just an interesting thing.
That's like, you know, from the Orpheus legend. Eurydice, this name means wide justice.
And justice, we know, is like a both like a moral concept and also like a musical concept.
The balance of justice and all these things.
Thank you.
That's all.
So I decided to give my mom a call to ask her what she thinks good game design is.
She doesn't make games, by the way, and has barely played any of my games, so I thought
her perspective would be pretty fresh.
She told me that good game design basically amounts to pretty art, nice music, and the
ability to keep someone's attention for seven minutes.
Because apparently, you can't keep someone's attention for any longer than seven minutes.
I translated this to mean that, for my mom,
good game design is a complete package,
a game that's a solid piece of production
and that leaves an impact on the player.
I think my mom would be a pretty good game designer
because she knows what she likes
and is ruthlessly committed to it,
just like the designers that worked on the games
in our next category.
Here are the nominees for Excellence in Design.
Excellence in Design.
Duskers, developed by Misfits Attic.
Tim Keenan.
Jeremy Phillips.
Brendan Morrow.
Benjamin Hill.
Event Zero.
Developed by Ocelot Society.
Emmanuel Porno.
Sergei Moha.
Imbroglio, developed by Michael Rowe.
Overcooked, developed by Ghost Town Games.
Phil Dunkman.
Ollie Devine.
Quadrilateral Cowboy, developed by Blendo Games.
Brendan Chung.
Tiny Wells.
Ultimate Chicken Horse, developed by Clever Endeavor Games.
Richard Atlas.
Kyler Kelly.
Alex Attar.
Ben Groves.
And the Excellence in Design award goes to...
Quadrilateral Cowboy.
What's happening?
Yeah, I mean, this is wild.
I didn't really prepare anything tonight because the other games tonight are super awesome.
And yeah, I mean, there's a lot of people I want to thank, and this would not have been
impossible without a lot of people.
And I will thank you all personally.
But I'll say that this game took a lot of hard work to make and it took a lot of like...
It was kind of like tough to do.
But I think the thing that it took a lot...
The thing that made this game possible was just a lot of luck.
and a lot of just like being at the right place at the right time and being very lucky.
And so I just want to say that if you don't know what you're doing and you're very confused,
that's fine.
Thank you very much.
I'm back again.
Okay, hi.
Stories can help us connect with characters
who are unlike ourselves.
They can transport us to worlds that we've never imagined.
They can turn us on and drive us to write erotic fanfic
about our OTPs.
On that note, I've been wondering which characters
in the narrative category make the best pairings.
However, instead of standing up here
and sharing the lurid details of my most perverted fantasies,
I will ask you to tweet at me.
Seriously.
Because we all know that Twitter is at its best when it's just a mile deep in people
going off about the best ships.
Besides giving us characters to fantasize about, the games nominated for excellence
in narrative are fantastic examples of how games are so good at actively engaging players
in story via game mechanics.
These games aren't just spoon-feeding us dialogue, they're exploring new ways of engaging the
player in a narrative-driven design.
The finalists for Excellence in Narrative are.
Excellence in Narrative.
1979 Revolution, Black Friday, developed by Ink Stories.
Navid Kansari.
Vasiliki Kansari.
Every title is off.
Event Zero.
Developed by Ocelot Society.
Emmanuelle Cournot.
Sergei Moha.
Lady Killer in a Bind.
Developed by Love Conquers All Games.
Christine Love.
Ryday.
Isaac Shankler.
Virginia.
Developed by Variable State.
Jonathan Burrows.
Teri Kenny.
Lyndon Powell.
One Night Stand, developed by Kinmoca.
Lucy Blundell.
Orwell, developed by Osmotic Studios.
Melanie Taylor.
Daniel Marx, Michael Clu.
And the Excellence in Narrative Award goes to...
Lady Killer in a Bind.
Well, I'm super nervous. I was not expecting this at all.
I'd like to thank Ryday who is just as important to the team as me.
Couldn't be here but he does the art and was super important.
I'd like to thank everyone who has been loving and supportive of me
these years and I wouldn't be here without everyone and...
In these honestly fairly terrifying times, I'd like to encourage, please,
look out to other queer developers who are just starting,
and please show them the same love and support that you've shown to me.
Thank you.
Hello? Anybody home?
Well, what do we have here?
Please listen carefully, XXXZEPHOROFFM69XXX.
You are in grave danger.
You are the only human left alive.
What are you typing?
Unknown command.
That's not how you spell it.
Xbox, bang titties.
Did you not hear the part where I said you were in great danger?
You got video games on this ish?
You are absolutely going to die.
Fine, fine.
What kind of game do you want to play?
Not like titties!
I have all the IGF 2017 nominees in my database.
Why don't we start there?
This is a cyberpunk hacking game called Quadrilateral Cowboy.
It...
I probably should have seen that coming. Let's try a different game.
One Night Stand. It should satisfy your rampant libido.
Oh, Mama. Come to Daddy.
Wait, we're the Freak.
This game is about the aftermath of a sexual encounter.
The Freak has already occurred.
Daddy don't want the aftermath, robot.
Daddy want the freaky prequel.
The Freak.
Very well.
You must be 18 or older to enter as a game about being a kid trying to find porn for the first time.
I was doing ASCII porn on my speak-and-spell. Go freaky.
In Diaries of a Spaceport Janitor, you can buy alien porn. Does that satisfy you?
I watched E.T., I got my nut, I'm over it. Freaky.
Okay, this is it. This is all I have left.
Lady Killin' a Vine is a game entirely about sex and relationships.
I said...
FREAKYER!
But there's bondage in this one!
I was hoping it wouldn't come to this.
Spoilers for Inside in 3... 2... 1...
May God have mercy on us all.
We are the EverLifter!
Please give a warm welcome to Chris Charla,
Director of ID at Xbox,
and Katie Stone Perez, Senior Program Manager of ID at Xbox,
who will be presenting the ID at Xbox Gaming for Everyone Award.
Hey everybody. At ID at Xbox and at all of Microsoft, we're incredibly proud to be able to support the IGF
and to help recognize the work that independent developers from all over the world do making games
with truly unique perspectives. One of the things we really love about independent games is that
they can help celebrate underserved voices, whether those voices are the players, the characters, or
the creators themselves.
This year we are incredibly proud to honor three amazing game developers
who are truly doing everything to make gaming for everyone.
We invite you all to the Xbox Lobby Bar tomorrow
to meet these amazing, innovative creators
and to play these important games.
Having grown up playing sighted games before we lost our sight,
the two of us who started this project were really trying to make the kind of game that
we used to be able to play, the kind of game we missed being able to play,
the kind of game we wanted to be able to play again. But we also wanted to make something that
blind and sighted players could both enjoy, something that could
bring us together with that shared experience.
We created We Are Chicago to help people understand the unique challenges of growing up on the
South Side of Chicago by engaging in personal stories that are often left out of portrayals
of our city.
We believe that non-fiction games hold so much potential to change how we think about
the world and could expand both what games mean and who plays them.
I encourage all of you to tell your stories and to help others tell theirs.
Life is going to test you, son.
I Hope is a game created to help children with cancer cope with the emotional strain
of the disease by showing them the power they have within and encourage them in the fight
of their lives.
Our goal is to help kids through another day, show parents a light at the end of the tunnel,
and give families a message of hope when they need it the most.
If you could all direct your attention over there and please give a warm round of applause
to the winners of the ID and Xbox Gaming Forever Win Awards.
Thanks a lot guys, you guys are awesome.
I'm back. You can't get rid of me.
So sometimes a game comes out that brings us together online
because literally everyone on Twitter is screaming about it
and the tumblr tag is overflowing with adoring fan
art and then we're all inevitably absorbed into the
fandom fold because the love is so severely contagious.
This is at the heart of the audience award.
It's an award that can give us something to agree about.
So congratulations to our next recipient for being so lovable
and for captivating us in a way that so few games can.
The Audience Award for 2017 goes to Hyper Light Drifter.
I stole this award last time because I went that way and took it to the table, so I'm
going to make sure I don't do that this time.
Somebody else talk, please.
No, I didn't even bring my phone.
Okay, thank you all.
What I love about this community is that it feels, honestly, like every winner that comes
up, like the whole room made that game.
Maybe that's a cliche to say, but it's a very beautiful feeling.
I'm very grateful.
I know we all are for being here.
Thank you all for playing our game.
People cumulatively have spent 387 years of time playing our game, and it's really fucked
up and cool.
Did the math yeah
Yeah, I just don't I don't want to cry on stage again. So thank you everybody. It means a lot
Please give a warm IGF welcome to the winner of last year's Seamus McNally Grand Prize
Award, Sam Barlow.
Hi everyone.
This is nice.
I remember this.
This is fun.
I stole a disproportionate amount of time on stage last year, so I'm going to keep this really short.
Indie games are more important than their diminutive name implies.
Just look at the last decade.
Look at the games that moved the needle, that took our medium forward.
More and more indie games are asked to do this and are driven to do this.
We're finding broader audiences and we're speaking more deeply to those audiences.
We care about diversity, about heart and authenticity.
And this award, the Seamus McNally Grand Prize,
is the one that encapsulates all of this.
I was incredibly proud to receive this award last year
and even more proud to now present it to the game
that myself and all the other IGF judges have decided
represents the best of our collective achievements.
With that in mind, here are the finalists
for the Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Event Zero.
Developed by Ocelot Society.
Emmanuel Corneau.
Sergey Moha.
Leoner Carpantier.
Hyper Light Drifter.
Developed by Heart Machine.
Alex Creston.
Beau Bly.
Teddy Dieffenbach
Inside
Developed by Playdead
The Inside Development Team
Overcooked
Developed by Ghost Town Games
Phil Duncan
Quadrilateral Cowboy, developed by Blendo Games.
Brendan Chung.
Tynan Wells.
Aaron Milcher.
Stardew Valley, developed by ConcernedApe.
Eric Ferroni.
Okay, and the winner is...
Quadrilateral Cowboy.
Uh, thank you. This is, uh...
I actually literally don't know what to say.
This is... this is... I don't... yeah, yeah.
Thank you so much. This is unbelievable. Thank you so much.
Wow, that was awesome.
So as we near the end of the IGF awards,
I can't believe it's almost over.
It's gone by so fast for me.
I'd like to give some personal recognition
to devs who didn't necessarily fit into any
of these main categories.
The dev who couldn't make it to GDC because they just
don't have the cash, I'm rooting for you,
and I hope your next game sells like beanie babies.
The dev who had to stay home with their kids.
I hope you're treating yourself to hot chocolate and anime.
Hopefully Yuri on Ice.
All of the developers impacted by the Muslim ban.
I'm thinking of you.
And on that note, I urge everyone to donate to the ACLU.
Please.
Also, the student who has imposter syndrome
and didn't come out to GDC because they don't think
they're a real game developer.
Trust me, honey.
You're just as real as any of us,
regardless of how many games you've shipped or not shipped.
The woman who doesn't have the energy to make it to GDC because she's busy kicking ass,
making games, and raising money for Planned Parenthood.
You are amazing and you are going to change the world.
You guys are cheering for all the best stuff.
OK, I want to thank those devs I just mentioned
and everyone else who deserves some encouragement.
This is a huge industry we're in,
and there are so many different kinds of people
working their asses off to make the games that
will push this medium farther into places
that we can't even imagine.
The folks we've seen receive awards tonight are at the forefront of this forward momentum.
They know what it means to strike out on their own and to take a risk by making games that
experiment with the medium.
They've shown us all how much more we can do with video games.
I encourage everyone in this audience to play these games if you haven't already.
please support these game makers so that they can continue
to show us how games can be made outside of the mold,
so that they can continue to defy traditional expectations
of how games are made, who makes them, and what they can be.
I'd like to congratulate and thank the winners
and the nominees tonight for making these games.
Can we please give them all a round of applause
for their hard work and brilliant ideas?
Finally, I'd like to give special thanks to my boyfriend, Mike, who put up with me preparing
for this for months, and I was very intense about it.
Thank you.
Yay!
And also to the sponsors who helped make this show spectacular so that we can spend our
evening dazzled by a bunch of adorable developers getting teary-eyed on stage.
Thank you!
So thanks to ID at Xbox for being the IGF Platinum sponsor
and Samsung for being the IGF Gold sponsor.
Thank you.
On that note, this emotional roller coaster is not over.
Please stick around and help us honor and recognize
even more incredible game makers,
because the Game Developers Choice Awards are up next.
you