Hi, my name is Chris. I am really excited to be at GDC. We are talking about trolling.
Trolling is very important.
It is the basis of the game economy.
Hey, what are we doing? We're doing a video?
Oh, this is the GDC video, right.
Okay, yeah, hi, guys, hey, I'm Chris.
Can't wait to be joining you, everyone, at GDC.
It's gonna be huge. Biggest parties ever.
It's gonna be great. We're all gonna have a great time.
Game industry rocks, except for we have this problem with trolls.
Trolls, toxicity, they're always annoying us.
We're trying to get stuff done, we're trying to make awesome products, have fun,
and there's this one person that just keeps bugging us and driving us crazy.
It's like they have like this mighty sword,
the mighty sword of Alhara!
That they can go and they can yield it all they want
and they destroy the atmosphere every single time
and we need some kind of defense to go against them
otherwise the game is unbalanced and we lose all our money.
Whoa!
But all we need is just something to get rid of them.
And then maybe then we can actually have some more success to this whole thing.
Our games can be profitable and we can have tons more fun and it'd be well-balanced and all that cool stuff.
And all that jazz.
Hey, is there jazz music anywhere?
What happened to this guy? 🎵
Ever feel like you're surrounded, bold-type, by trolls?
Come to the talk and you'll find out how to get rid of them.