Hi.
Do I have any friends here at all?
One or two.
As long as there's just one or two, that's all.
You'll keep my heart alive throughout this very, very,
very boring talk.
I tried, normally I think, maybe I'll put some jokes in.
Wouldn't it be cool to have jokes?
And this time, there's no jokes.
There's just data and information.
I'm just going to try to pour whatever's
in this head into your heads.
And hopefully, things don't dribble out too much.
They'll probably dribble out of my head.
Couple things, turn off your devices that make noise.
Fart machines, just turn those off right now.
Also, there's evaluations.
There's data that is collected on you
and shared with the global internet.
So no, fill out your questionnaires and stuff.
Let me know how I could be a better human being.
All right.
So I'm Daniel Cook.
I've been a game designer for a bunch of years now.
They keep going up.
I'm trying not to update that number anymore.
It's kind of like it's the 39 of 20 is the 39
of game developer years.
I've been writing on lostgarden.com,
a whole bunch of game design writings.
I like to think about.
tools that we can use as game designers to stop making so many. How to put it
stupid mistakes.
Like we tend to make the same mistakes over and over again and wouldn't be cool
to actually have like mental tools that we can approach a problem and solve it
in a smart way versus like flailing around and then going and like blowing
up a few million dollars here and there.
Co-founded a company called Spry Fox, a small game studio.
We've been going for about eight years now.
We've made games like Triple Town.
Initially I got interested, like I kind of did the thing
that game designers do, which is like,
you know it's all about the game mechanics
and we want to do small, elegant, tight games
that have deep, you know, evergreen gameplay.
And so I did that sort of thing for a while.
But then I got into MMOs and I realized that people are actually kind of important.
like people are are cool people are interesting and you can build games with
people that make people's lives better and so this is a cooperative.
Shoot them up online game and people couldn't really grief each other so
there was there was a there was something nice about a game where it's
not about betrayal or negative emotions it's about trying to build community and
that kind of got that that idea seated in my head.
We're working on another one.
So we've been making more and more online games.
We made a sort of a multiplayer Animal Crossing
called Bear-topia.
We make a lot of cute games as well.
Like our games are played by men, women, all ages.
We're really interested in the whole spectrum of humanity
out there and how can you make games for them.
And one of our sort of slogans is making happiness.
Like, as opposed to making money, which is also nice, but that's, you know, like, this
is sort of this, can games contribute to humanity?
So I don't build games because I love games.
Like, that's not...
That's not what I do.
I mean, games are cool, don't get me wrong.
But games are a tool.
As a designer, I think of games as a tool
that can help us bring happiness to the world,
a tool that can make people's lives better.
So I'm always looking for things that can improve happiness.
So it's not enough to just design a game.
Oh, we made a game.
That's great.
It's like, it's like.
driving in a parking lot the first time you get your driver's license.
It's a super cool thing, but it's even better when you're going on a date night and you're
driving to the movie with your date and you're excited and the car empowers you to have this
wonderful life experience.
That's what games should be.
So looking at like, okay, well, what improves people's lives?
Did a bunch of research, looked around,
looked at things for years,
and this is like one of the big findings
that keeps coming up again and again and again
in social psychology.
A small number of deep friendships
leads to greater happiness in life.
People have fulfillment in their lives.
They start thriving when they have lots of,
a small number of very deep friendships.
And then there's a flip side to that.
which is large numbers of shallow status-based friendships
are actually really bad, especially for teenagers.
If you are a teenage girl and you are basically
your entire social network is people sharing images
of each other, how cute you look,
you may be on the road to depression.
It's not a healthy thing to have that.
And so given that sort of finding, I asked myself,
well, what can online games do?
Like, what can games do to increase
this sort of meaningful relationships?
And we all have a fantasy.
I think we all sat around the table
and played games with our family or friends,
and we have this sort of like, oh, you know,
we're hanging out in this face-to-face interactions.
And if someone does something, we all laugh because it's a joke.
It wasn't meant to be mean.
And everything's nice and wonderful.
But the reality is instead we're mostly interacting with strangers, mediated by this very, very
thin pipe of the Internet, where all sorts of nuance is lost, all sorts of miscommunication
happens.
And then we put on top of this, we put on top of that systems and algorithms that are
immensely dehumanizing, that kind of strip.
our ability to act as authentic human beings away from the interaction, from the reciprocation
process.
And bad things happen.
So you get match-based systems, which are this very common thing where we have relationships,
but they're totally throwaway.
We interact with a person and we're like, oh, we're never going to see them again.
Of course I'm going to swear at them.
Because it's like, why not?
Friendship systems that, you know, again, it turns people into a number in some sort
of viral marketing campaign.
Again, dehumanizing.
And we just do these things because they make numbers go up, they make metrics go up, and
that seems like a nice idea.
And those KPIs that are really important to somebody and we made them go up so our salary
might go up.
But we do also things that are just naive.
We are like, chat, chat, people seem to like chat.
So let's just give people chat.
And so you have these things like Twitter,
where you're basically taking people
and firing them at each other at super high velocity.
And some of those people turn into friends.
And you're like, see, Twitter is justified.
And then there's all these sort of mangled heaps of bodies
that are like lying in the gutter someplace
because they didn't form friendship.
They were damaged by this sort of naive implementation
of social systems.
So, can we do better?
I think we know games build friendships.
We know this.
Like there are many people here
who have probably made friendships in games.
Who here has made a friendship in a game that's lasted?
Look at that, look at that.
Games build friendships, so we know that is a fact.
So how can we do that better?
So I went looking again,
because I like
sort of tying together different groups,
different ideas from different fields.
And I'm like, I wonder if anyone's thought
about friendship formation before.
And I found in the 1950s, there were two folks.
This is Schachter, which is an amazing name.
I wish my name was Schachter.
And Festinger, which is also an amazing name.
If I could go by Schachter Festinger,
and like have it in a big like.
name tag, I would do that. That would be pretty cool. So in the 1950s, have you ever heard
of cognitive dissonance? That is Schachter. So these are big names that have done fundamental
research in cognitive psychology, social psychology.
And like I was doing a search on one of their terms and it's still like there's like it since 2010. There's been like 4000 research papers on this topic so they came up with a theory that is actually still super validated. There's immense quantities of research. It's been studied. You name it any field any sort of organization. Their ideas have been applied and validated.
Maybe we should do that for games.
So this is the proven model.
This is what it is.
It's really pretty simple, right?
It's like, how do friendships form?
And it says, well, you need these
you need these four things
for friendships to form.
And if your game doesn't, isn't
designed to cause
these things to happen
friendships are going to form at a dramatically lower rate.
I mean, you may have some people that escape into chat channels
and still form friendships through there.
But in general, if you don't have these things in your game,
your game's not going to be good at forming friendships.
So the rest of this talk is the super boring part.
I've used up all my jokes.
We're going to go through each one of these.
and we're going to say like what is this thing
and then we're going to say here's some examples
in games, some practical
boring game examples, mechanics,
systems that sort of thing that are doing
it and doing it well that we can just say why
don't we do that and do more of it.
Okay proximity.
This is your cool word of the day for pretty.
You can practice that in the bathroom mirror.
Proprinquity, which is essentially social distance.
How far apart are people from one another?
And propinquity is all about,
there's a couple reasons why you want,
the rules of this proximity thing.
You want repeat serendipitous interactions.
So let's assume there's a bunch of people in a room
and they are walking along and they're ignoring each other
but then they happen to face one another
and see one another and they bump into each other
and they say hello.
That's a serendipitous interaction.
They weren't planning on it.
It was just sort of the shape of the room,
the number of the people in the room,
and they saw each other and said hi.
So you need serendipity in your system.
And you need to have repeat interactions.
If those people bump into each other
and then never see each other again,
then they're never gonna become friends.
It's just not gonna happen.
It's logistically impossible for them to become friends.
But if they see each other again and they actually have multiple repeat interactions,
then slowly over time maybe they'll become friends.
And you can sort of combine those ideas together and say,
well, there's this thing called density,
where the number of people in a room probably matters,
or the number of people in an environment probably matters.
Like if you're living in the desert,
and the only things around you are cactuses,
cacti, cacti,
then...
you will probably not make any friends.
I think of, what was it, was it Joe from Snoopy?
He lived in a desert and he was always alone and sad.
Like, you can make games like that if you really want,
but nobody will become a friend.
You can also do the opposite, you can make it too noisy,
you can have people jam-packed in.
We actually had this problem in Realm of the Mad God
where we would have the hub area
and there were so many people in the hub area
that it just became, like, people shut down,
they're like, it's dehumanizing,
I wanna, like, ignore everybody and not pay attention.
So there's a certain density you need.
Now, what I love about this,
this is the sort of thing that just gets me
incredibly excited.
we were talking about social psychology,
and now we're talking about logistics.
And as game designers, we are excellent at logistics.
That's numbers and people and pacing and timing and placement
and all those sort of things.
So if friendship for this factor is just a logistics problem,
we have all sorts of tools to solve that.
So.
This is an example of logistics thinking.
So a lot of people ask, say, well, why not just play
with my existing friends?
I should just be able to play with my existing friends.
I like my existing friends.
I don't want to form new friends,
because that's kind of scary.
Why not just play with existing friends?
So let's look at the logistics.
There's a thing in online games called the concurrency ratio,
where there's a certain number of monthly active users
that you have, there's a certain number of concurrent users,
and there's a certain number who are online at any one time.
So let's say, in the best case, the best case,
10% of your audience is online at any one time.
That's wonderful.
uh... all right let's let's crunch the numbers uh...
so i assume that less than a concurrency ratio of twenty five to one and you have
ten friends
This is a secret, not very many people know this,
but most people do not actually have 10 good friends.
Most people have maybe five to seven.
In online games, it's really, really common
to see friends lists with one or two people
in your friends list.
So 10 is being generous.
You come online and there's only a one in three chance
that someone is actually going to,
your friend is going to be there.
So most of the time, you come online,
you're not gonna know anyone.
And this is in a generous, good situation that doesn't actually occur for the vast amount of humanity in real life.
So we can take some takeaways from that sort of thinking.
We can say, OK, well, it turns out
that old friendships rarely translate to new context,
particularly when you've just launched an online game,
in part because the numbers don't work out.
Like, the friends won't be there.
It's just mathematically not going to happen.
So then the design problem starts to be,
well, I would love to have real friends in there,
but they're not around yet,
so I need to create an environment
where people can form new friendships from strangers.
And that's a completely different design problem
than hanging around the table at a board game
and playing with people you know.
Because it turns out that the psychology
of interacting with strangers is totally different
than the psychology of interacting with friends.
Okay, so theory's awesome.
I like theory, but let's do some tools.
Does anyone here own a hammer?
Aren't hammers awesome?
I think they're great.
Oops.
Screwed up there.
Okay, so here are your basic tools.
You've got things like persistent identity.
If you don't have identity,
if it shifts from game to game
because you're randomly assigning usernames,
people are not going to have repeat encounters.
You can't have friendships.
Events, if you do an event,
you can increase the density in time,
so therefore more people will show up.
So you escape the desert.
you know problem and you can actually have people there if
you have a low concurrency environment daily
incentives encourage people to come back so again you're
trying to get people into your game so you can play
and then offline communities like OK
what if you had an asynchronous community that existed side
by side with your synchronous community such
that people could connect up that way so this is parallel
path that you can do.
So these are all super good basic tools
that work well.
And then you've got anti patterns with that as well.
Anonymous players.
Well, if people are completely anonymous,
they can't make friendships because they don't know
who each other are and they can't have repeat interactions.
The desert huge empty areas. This is when you're getting into competitive
games you're like oh I know I'm gonna have lots of gameplay modes now space is
not simply spatial it's not it's not a problem geography but you can have
abstract space as well when you take your population and you split them
across multiple modes where you're doing is you're basically reducing density.
you're making it so that people, those little molecules of people
don't bounce into each other and interact nearly as often.
The same thing goes with skill.
When you have an MMO and you have the newbies and the experts
and there's this spread of people across either a power
gradient or a skill gradient, what you're doing
is you're actually changing the density equation
in your game of people who can interact with one another.
And it's really easy to do that.
You're like, oh, no, this isn't a social system.
This is merely the leveling system.
It has nothing to do with social.
But by changing these systems,
they actually impact the experience and hurt,
and it can utterly destroy your ability to create friends.
This is sort of the whipping boy of making French matches.
This comes from board games and sports,
it's super popular, it's super problematic.
So matches are, you start a match,
everyone has to be in there at the same time,
you play a game, and then you end a match,
and it ends at the same time,
and you move on to the next match, hopefully, maybe.
So this was a recent recent game that failed they simply didn't have enough
concurrent population to support their matchmaking structure so people would
have to wait too long which kills the retention the retention drops which
makes the problem even worse you get a death spiral.
So you know made millions and millions and millions of dollars of gameplay
screwed up by logistics.
And that's a that's an architectural issue right that's a structural issue
to their game that requires that sort of initial starting conditions for players
have fun.
It does work matches do work matches are super effective
if you have a mega hit if you have a mega hit you have a huge population
matchmaking is easy wait time is easy it all works out so
if you have a mega hit keep doing this I'm not going to argue with you.
But it also sort of locks people away in these rooms
and they don't interact as much.
It's kind of, if you're anyone who has any sort of soul
for risk mitigation and you have a chance
that you might not make a mega hit,
do away with this pattern, consider something else.
Certainly we can do better.
So this is one that I really like.
This sort of comes from MMOs.
This is instead of matches, you do rooms.
And this is a solution that has density management.
You can do repeat encounters and very, very low wait times
so you get less churn, which keeps your concurrency up.
really simple sort of like diagram how I think of rooms and rooms could be a huge
open world they could be like you know an intimate abstract session, you know
there's there's tons of ways to do rooms, but the basic idea is you have people
playing a game there's a certain number of slots for people to play the game in
the room and then ideally you have these 2 other sort of things which is this
idea that you can join in progress in pop in at any point you want to start
playing the game, let's start playing.
And you can leave in progress.
You can leave at any point.
So it's very friendly.
It's respectful of people's time.
It's respectful of their schedules.
It's a nice, nice pattern.
This is one, Slither.io.
So .io games are massively popular right now.
Everyone here should be building one in case you're not.
And there's no matchmaking wait like in order to play the game even including loading the game and entering the URL pressing enter
It took me six seconds to get into a game, and I was instantly playing with a whole bunch of other people
So very effective
In a bigger context, you look at something like Guild Wars, Guild Wars 2, and they have
an interesting pattern, which is an extension of rooms.
So you can take this very simple concept of rooms.
Does anyone here from ArenaNet?
Maybe one or two people.
I see one.
He's wearing the shirt.
You can take the simple room concept and you can extend it and you can start building things
like a Lego block, a social Legos you're building these architectures out of.
So this one, they have a problem where,
what if you pop into a room and there's no one else there?
Well, the typical thing that you do is you leave.
You're like, this is boring, a big empty room,
I'm gonna leave.
So instead, they do, they build out this lovely map
and they have little checkpoints on it
and little quests that you can do.
So those little hearts are like little activities
that you can do if you want.
And they say, why don't you just do these little activities?
And so that's what people do.
And but what that does is that keeps them in the room until other people start to accumulate
in there.
And once the other people are in there, they now have sufficient concurrency to do a much
more engaging, much more social interaction.
So that's when they hit you with a public event.
And now, oh, now we're all playing together when we were just hanging out in a room together.
I think doctors' waiting rooms should totally do this.
This would be awesome.
Like, you're sitting there in the waiting room, there's some magazines to keep you going,
you know, there's like a sticky note and you're like, I wonder what the sticky note is, and
you put on the sticky note, you say, secret, loot, you know, or something on the sticky
note people are looking through and they're like, oh, what's that?
And then all of a sudden, boom, a dragon spawns.
That would be, I think that would make them better.
Now see there's your simple pattern, you know waiting room going to event and
again going back to the theory it.
It's a in create you have you've got you're managing serendipity you're
managing density, you've got this idea of this ideal density that you're aiming
for and so you can you can create that in your game.
We did this on we made a cooperative game,
Rumble of the Mad God,
and we did the same thing here.
This was a slightly different pattern.
This was how do we get to that ideal density?
Is there any mechanism we can do,
sort of like where,
imagine again this idea of these people
bouncing around like air molecules in a space.
Is there any way we can sort of increase the density or shrink the density?
And if you think of a balloon, that's exactly what happens in a balloon, right?
You can kind of increase the balloon and shrink the balloon.
Can we do that sort of managing of density with game servers?
And so here we have these little instant servers that are running,
and you can jump into one.
And you can look up there, and you can say, oh, wait,
there's 14 of 80 people in that room.
So there's 14 slots filled in that room.
And then we've got another one with another number of people in that room.
And then there's a hub area here where everyone's gathering and saying
whether they'll join those things.
Now this is really cool because now we can just go and create the number of instances that we want
to make the ideal density.
And so you kind of have a hub area and then people freely flow back and forth between the hubs and the instances
and then you just add as many instances as you need to create the amount of space you need
for the number of concurrent users.
Math! Right here.
Really simple, right?
Simple load balancing.
Then what happens when the population shrinks?
So we have this idea of garbage collection.
Like, okay, we need to shrink the thing,
but if we just go and shrink it,
maybe people will get upset.
So in Roman The Get Mad God,
we made a gameplay reason for this.
what the each instance has a big bad big bad evil person and the God of that that
area and if you kill him the whole thing gets destroyed in the whole whole world
gets destroyed, but that gives us a nice narrative excuse to just delete that
instance and now we send everyone back the hub and now we can load balance the
sort of like how many how many instances we need.
Guild Wars has a slightly different they were kinder in
some ways than we were we just we just have people in a
permadeath game fight a giant monster they decided.
Maybe we should ask them and give them something nice.
Which is nice so here they bribe people to leave the
server they're like hey.
We're going to like it's kind of boring in here you want to
go someplace else we will give you stuff to go someplace
else.
And if that didn't work they kick you out.
So, the carrot and the stick.
So as I was thinking about this stuff,
I'm like, okay, that's all good.
But the density systems, what they are all doing
is they're basically increasing serendipity.
But what I'm really interested in,
because I want those meaningful relationships,
how can we increase that repeat interaction?
So we worked on this MMO which nobody has played,
I guarantee.
It was on a platform that doesn't,
doesn't travel as well as some of these other ones.
And so this was a this is a multiplayer animal crossing like game and you had little bears and they were running around.
And they were all part of a the same cohort what we do is we stick 40 players together in a village and we say you're going to live in each other's sweat and bile for the next.
3 months, year, doesn't matter.
You're just going to live together in this place,
and you have to get to know each other.
And you've seen this in schools.
Many schools do this, where you have a class, a cohort,
and you stay with the same cohort,
and you either become lifelong enemies or lifelong friends.
And it's this really wonderful, intense, repeat interaction
and increasing pattern.
And we had this whole system for like managing this, you know,
like what if villages fail and how to migrate
and what's the narrative behind it.
And so when you build these things, you think of the flows.
Think of the flows of people and think of how to maximize.
How do you maximize the opportunity
for people to stay together?
Yeah, you can do this in first-person shooters.
So first-person shooters, simple thing.
Like when you're going from one match to the next match,
why don't you keep the same players together,
especially if they're on the same team.
It's the same idea, same exact idea.
So here you know you you start to get tools right you start to get a list of
tools for sort of managing your population of players across servers and
now when you build your game you're thinking about this stuff you're
building all these things in like.
But, Beartopia had all these systems going on simultaneously in the game, and it was
a fundamental part of how we designed the game.
It wasn't something that we thought of naively later.
It was like, oh, wait, we're building this game and we want to encourage friendship.
Let's make sure that every piece of the game, the idea of villages,
the idea that you're staying together,
the idea that you're going to leave.
Like every once in a while, people wander off on a boat adventure to go someplace else,
to explore the old country,
and they come back and then the land is changed afterwards.
So we're building these ideas,
these concepts, these logistical concepts narratively into the gameplay.
Similarity.
This is a short and horrible one.
So first first rule of similarity is people make friends with people like them if you have a group
and you randomly mix up a bunch of different people and they have some sort of attributes to
them people look around the room and they will instinctually make friends with people like them
and this has been studied in all sorts of situations and this is an incredibly powerful
thing.
So, like, oh, those orange things, like, anyone else wearing orange, I'm instantly your friend.
Just like that.
Like, I want to become friends.
Now, what's happening here is we perceive that similar people
are going to be like us, and then as we build friendships, it's going to be cheaper to negotiate
with them and figure out how we could work together.
It's like, oh, if you're like me, we're already talking the same language, we already probably
have the same ideals, the same norms, and we sort of project these benefits to similarity.
This is not always positive.
In many, many, many, many cases, it's incredibly negative.
And it's also a wildly strong filter.
Like, there'll be someone with a piece of cake
sitting there saying, would you like some cake?
And it's obviously amazing cake.
And there'll be someone next to them
with a knife who wants to stab them,
but looks like them.
And they'll go up to the person with the knife
and they'll say, wow, we should become friends.
Like, it's a brutal, brutal thing that has been repeated in thousands of studies.
So this game, which I always mispronounce, Agario is my attempt at it, another one of
these .io games.
So they said, heck, like, people really like this nationalism thing.
And so they allowed people to put stickers basically, skins on their characters of national flags.
And for a while there, what was happening is there was these massive nation versus nation battles going on in this game.
And along with it came all the baggage.
all the baggage of nationalism like it's like you know slurs just just there were denial of service
attacks that's just horrible horrible things because you you took in this like tribal identity
and you applied it within your game.
So how the heck do you use this thing?
This is like, it's really, really strong
and it exists in all of our communities
and if we ignore it, we basically import
the worst elements of modern society into our games
and people create these poisonous communities
based off bad ideals.
And so and the diversity of our population drops,
our populations become like,
we basically start doing gatekeeping
where you're not like us, you don't belong here.
It's harder to acquire players.
It's just a miserable thing.
It's like one of these dark secrets
at the heart of humanity
that makes designing online games really difficult.
You know, you can put people in factions,
you can design these factions,
you can have people have sort of shared experiences,
positive shared experiences,
you can have them do shared goals,
and these things help a little.
They sort of work,
but they're not that effective in general.
The one thing I've seen goes back to the fundamental reason why similarity is so strong.
And the fundamental reason why similarity is so strong goes back to that idea of shared
social norms.
We are
deeply, deeply pattern matching creatures.
And we're not that smart most of the time as individuals.
What we do is we look around us and we say,
what are other people doing?
Particularly people like us.
And then we copy those behaviors.
We start to mimic those behaviors
in this new unknown social context.
We start doing that.
So you can use that to set up positive fictional identities.
You can create a tribe for your players
that is actually super positive.
So in Bear-topia, there was this,
we're like, this is a happy little village
where people are nice to each other.
Everyone's an immigrant, so there's vast diversity.
That's actually a similarity that you're all immigrants.
And you're building things together
and you're working towards these common goals.
And everyone's just really nice.
And what we've noticed is...
it actually works really, really well.
People don't get angry at each other
because that's not the tribe that they're in.
They're not in the get angry at each other tribe.
They're not in the wear black and beat each other
over the head with a stick tribe, right?
That's not this game.
And so by creating these positive identities,
these pro-social player roles,
you end up sort of setting the norm for this is what this place is.
And people will share that identity,
and they'll adopt people into that identity,
and they'll be like, oh, you're like me,
so therefore we should be friends
because we're all in this very strong pro-social identity.
So some some rules there do not reference real strong real world
identities directly like keep that out of it if there's a strong real world
identity sort of separate that from your game.
The yeah and and
it's really effective.
What so we make another game called alpha bear which is a game where you
collect cute bears and.
It's funny because you should read the support emails we get.
The support emails are like, I'm playing this with my child
and I just wanted to let you know.
Or I think I found something that horribly
deletes all my data and I wanted to apologize.
And it's just the sort of game that attracts and presents a viewpoint on the world that
is pleasant and nice.
And we can build those sort of games.
We can make that sort of game.
There's nothing about games that say it has to be about ultraviolence and the fall of
man as we turn into animals.
What if we make games for real human beings being the best that they can be?
I like that.
All right.
Reciprocity.
Anyone asleep yet?
No.
This guy.
Wake him up.
So this is reciprocity.
All right.
We're going to do a simple thing here.
He's fallen asleep.
You're going to punch him in the shoulder gently.
All right.
And then he's going to look at you.
And he's going, what the heck?
Right.
That was reciprocity.
Right there.
Tit for tat.
He could have punched you back.
That would have been an extension of that.
But you make a friendly gesture or offer.
And then in return, the other person
gives a positive response.
And you've got a nice little reciprocation loop right there.
It doesn't have to be material, it can be attention, recognition, two people walking
across the room, one person looks at the other person, the other person responds by meeting
their gaze, that is reciprocity right there.
That is a reciprocation loop.
Now what's interesting about reciprocity is every time you do that interaction loop, you
build this magical resource known as trust.
You're building trust with each other.
It may be just a little bit.
Like, when you meet glances,
you're not building very much trust.
You're building a tiny, tiny little amount,
like, oh, this person seems okay.
They seem to be following basic social norms.
Maybe we can continue this later.
But trust, trust is interesting because it goes back to trust is shared social norms.
Trust is, I know, I can predict what you're going to do in any sort of social situation.
I know what you're going to do and I know how I'm going to react and you know how I'm
going to react and therefore if there's a complicated task or a risky task, I know I
can rely on you.
That's sort of the economic underpinnings of trust.
And if you don't have trust, then there's just a limit to the complexity of things that
you can do in life.
GDC could not have been put on without trust.
There needed to be trust that there would be people here, that we would meet each other,
that we would have good talks.
And if that's broken in any way, then the whole large organized culture just falls apart.
So trust is wildly important.
And reciprocation is how you get it there.
Now, trust is hard.
Trust is super hard.
Trust grows very slowly.
It can take years for people to trust one another.
I come from Maine.
Maine is a cold weather climate, which basically
means that every time winter comes,
there's a 110% chance you are going to die.
That's just fundamental to the culture.
It's going to happen.
And you have limited resources.
And every day is like survival of the most brutal kind.
And it may not actually be like that,
because we have stoves and stuff.
But that's what we're all thinking deep down.
And so trust is like, wait, anytime I ask someone over to dinner, or ask a favor of
somebody, or someone asks a favor of me, I'm giving up scarce resources that could have
been essential to my survival.
And so trust grows very, very slowly.
We slowly say, okay, I suspect that person
is not going to steal my awesome wood pile.
And eventually, over years, you might get to the point
where you wave hello.
That's cold weather climates, trust growing slowly.
But then, the horrible thing about trust
is if someone betrays that trust,
it goes away super, super fast.
Like, if I see that guy taking wood from my wood pile,
he, it's over.
I'm never going to talk to him again.
I'm going to spread rumors to everyone else.
I'm gonna like, this guy, he takes wood from the wood pile.
That's my wood pile.
Eh, right?
And it's like one moment,
and maybe he really needed that wood, whatever.
It's like, trust can drop quickly.
Trust also.
allows us to increase the stakes of each interaction.
Like maybe we get to the point where we're like,
I'm letting him take stuff from my wood pile.
Awesome, that's good, we're trusting each other.
But it's expensive for me to like make dinner
and have the fellow over for dinner.
That's like, what if we don't get along?
What if we're only good at the like saying hi level
and we probably should have kept it there?
So trust, like, as you start interacting and as you build up that history of interactions.
you start being willing to do more for the other person.
You start being willing to take greater risks.
But the flip side of this is deep friendships
are incredibly expensive.
So the end result is you can only end up investing
in a handful of deep friendships.
So we have a lot of shallow friendships
and then a very, very few number of deep friendships.
Okay, so trust.
Source of civilization, very important.
You can tattoo that someplace.
Trust is the source of civilization.
I have many tattoos on the bottom of my feet.
That way, it's like private.
Okay, now there's a downside to this.
We are social creatures and we are wired to reciprocate.
So there's this wonderful experiment where you go and you give a person $1 and then you
ask them to buy like a $20 thing from you and they're total strangers and they absolutely
do not want this $20 thing.
but because you gave them the $1,
they're like, oh, I'm biologically wired to reciprocate.
And then they go and boom,
they'll go and they'll complete the sale with you.
So you can create these reciprocation systems,
but they end up being,
they can actually be kind of manipulative
if you're not doing it with good intent.
Some tools.
Okay, anti-patterns.
Anything that reduces trust.
If you're building a trade system
and people can scam one another,
you're actually actively reducing
the global trust in your community.
If there's hacking that's going on,
you're reducing trust and you're causing people
to not want to become friends with one another.
They start to become defensive,
they start to become like Mainers,
and you don't want that.
power differentials.
Like I think of the nation right now
with the extreme income inequality going on,
and there starts to create this system of mistrust
where people like, you are thinking in a way
you have access to resources that I don't,
you're taking them from me,
and you start to get this sense of distrust.
Now, what's fascinating, this is one of my absolutely favorite things about reciprocation
tools.
We have built an immense number of reciprocation tools.
If you are a startup in this area and have taken VC money, you have engineered reciprocation
loops.
And you just try to get them out there and you try to get people using them as much as
humanly possible because damn they're cool and they have high engagement and people love
them and they're socializing and interaction and all your numbers are going up and it's
super exciting.
Like chat, let's do chat.
let's let's have friends lists let's go and have checklists where we're like
trying to like compete on the number of things that were selling and we're
comparing that with each other in games we can do guilds we can do gifting like
all these things we can dump into a game or app if you're an app person and we
can just do that and then the question is wait wait but
But like we talked about Twitter.
Twitter is the case study of throwing random crap
into a thing and trying to get as many people
to use it as possible and then watching the wreckage
fall out, the human wreckage.
And that's, maybe we could be smarter about it.
I have a, I think we can.
I think we can.
So it turns out that if we go back to that idea of like trust builds up slowly
and there's low-cost interactions early on and then high-cost interactions later on,
maybe we can structure the way we interact, introduce tools to people based off levels
of trust.
This is, sorry that's more than I like to put on the slide,
but this is different levels of friendship in a game.
And you can think of the absolute lowest level of friendship
as someone playing by themself.
Single player games, not commonly known
for their friendship formation capabilities.
The next one is what kids do.
If you ever watch kids play games next to one another,
they'll do this thing called parallel play,
where they'll play next to each other,
they'll kind of glance at each other
out of the corner of their eye to see what they're doing,
but they won't actually interact.
Then you've got ambient co-op.
We're helping each other.
It's like, oh, like in Steambirds.
Here, I'll do some examples here.
But ambient co-op, we help each other without meaning to.
Soft co-op, we're intentionally benefiting others,
but there's no requirement to do that.
There's no requirement to actually help each other,
but you can do it if you want.
And then hard co-op, the Nintendo puzzle,
where someone has to step on the pressure plate
before the door opens.
And if you don't step on the pressure plate,
the door will never open,
the other person won't be able to go through.
And that's that sort of locking key hard co-op.
If you do not co-operate, you will fail.
And then finally we get all the way up to friends where we're spending time together,
we're trusting each other, and we're willing to collaborate and communicate and solve.
We're able to actually interact at all these different levels, but we can do hard cooperation
without backstabbing.
And so that's friendship levels.
This is sort of like a very simple interaction on Discord.
Why is Discord so popular?
They do a lot of smart things, believe it or not,
in terms of friendship formation.
So one of the things they do is they actually pay your bill
when you join a new server.
They pay your social cost of joining the new server
by making you seem funny and witty.
So they introduce, they're like,
oh, this person's here to kick butt and chew bubble gum.
You know, and they make up a little witty thing.
And so they're doing this very simple thing
to sort of like ease you in
and introduce you to the community in a nice way.
And I see people actually respond to these.
Not always, but sometimes they'll respond
and they'll reciprocate to this little thing.
And so at the very lowest end of the friendship ladder,
you can do these things to automate
like the suggestion of how people should interact.
In our MMO Steambirds Alliance,
we do this thing where
if people kill an enemy on the screen,
everyone around them gets the XP.
So it's a form of super ambient co-op, right?
Like we're happening to benefit each other,
we're happening to play together
just by being on the same screen
and someone shoots an enemy.
Now that can move into soft co-op
where we're both actively shooting the same enemy
because then we're like, we're thinking,
oh wait, I'm being totally selfish here.
This is a totally selfish activity,
but by shooting that thing while you're shooting the thing,
we'll kill things faster and get loot and XP faster.
So it's a totally like very low cost interaction
that results in us doing something together
and completing reciprocation loops
and having a shared experience
and now suddenly we have shared goals
and all that is sort of just sort of naturally happening
just by playing the game.
I really love this quote on Destiny 2.
So they have a thing where they have
non-zero-sum guild rewards.
So if someone goes and gets a reward in the game
and they're part of the guild,
then everybody gets a reward.
and the designer on this, Emmy Chung,
is saying, like, the Super Bowl ring philosophy.
When someone wins the Super Bowl ring,
they don't just give it to the people who are on the field.
and who played in that game they give that ring to everybody
and it becomes this sort of like shared like
hey everyone helps do this I'm going
to reward everyone along with us
and even if you're what's nice about that is even
if you were actually in the sort of hard
co-op environment
you were in the hard co-op match where you had to work
really really hard together this is something that benefits
every level.
And there's one of the challenges with degrees of friendship is you've got a mixed audience.
You've got people who are casual friends, people who are deep friends, people who don't
know each other all that well, people who are like amazingly good friends and are probably
going to get married inside your game.
Which happens.
Who here has had a game where someone's married somebody else inside the game?
Yeah?
Yeah.
So that's the level.
You can get pretty intense here.
And you need game mechanics that work for that entire spectrum.
You're not necessarily just developing game mechanics
for one group at a time.
You're looking for game mechanics
that are flexible enough to work for all different levels
of friendship that enable the super, super deep friendships
as well as the more casual ones.
This is a pattern that I love, rolls.
Rolls exist in a lot of things,
but I just like talking about Puzzle Pirates
because it's super cool.
It's a game where you're a pirate and you play puzzles.
I mean, I don't know how you can beat that.
That's what it looks like.
Look at that, pirates playing puzzles.
I just want to take a moment and appreciate that.
You fail if you don't work together.
Everyone's got a different role.
They start relying on one another.
There's a differentiation of roles and capabilities.
There's, as I was building this talk, another talk came out that talks all about trust.
I highly recommend you go check it out.
This is the spectrum of trust, Raf Koster has a copy of this up on his website.
And this is his slide on roles.
So it's this idea that, like, low trust environment, you don't have differentiated roles very much.
like I can do pretty much anything you can do.
In high trust environment,
you allow those roles to spread out.
Now, I need to rely on you.
Again, this goes back to the soft and hard co-op idea.
All right, disclosure.
This is a pretty simple one.
In order to make deep relationships,
you've worked your way up,
you're doing more expensive interactions with another,
you have to become vulnerable to the other person
to reach those maximum levels of trust.
You need to have riskier trust building going on.
The problem here is by revealing things about yourself,
it's actually like, what if the person rejects you?
Everyone here has a fear of rejection.
Someone's going to look at them and say like,
oh, if they tell me about this intimate detail of my life,
that all this work building up this relationship
is going to go away.
But it's the only way it's the only way to get that next level and we need to make games that safely support
vulnerability and disclosure
Because if we don't bad things happen like
If we reveal things too soon you get all sorts of stuff that happens here
So the way I think about it is there's opt-in disclosure
at the right time and place,
and there's premature disclosure.
And if your game causes premature disclosure,
then you get all the negative impacts.
You get horrible, horrible things.
Like this is an example of that.
This is a woman who is playing Overwatch,
and she can't use voice chat
without getting marriage proposals.
Because voice chat reveals that she is a woman,
and it's a premature disclosure,
and it turns out there are a lot of sexist jerks out there
that she didn't actually want to be friends with,
but because she's forced to disclose this information,
they're able to go and put all their horrible nature to work,
making her feel unwelcome.
And so she wants to, like, here he...
I mean, this is a very clear, like, critique of the system that says,
hey, you forced me to disclose something I didn't want to disclose.
And what happens is people turn off chat at that point.
And now your opportunity in the future
for a meaningful moment of vulnerability is lost.
You've killed the opportunity to become friends
at an early point.
And that your community as a whole suffers
because of the systemic things you put in place
with your naive social systems
that caused people to defend themselves, to turtle up.
OK, real names are a horrible idea.
Identity and persistent identity is a good idea.
Real names are a miserable idea
because it forces premature disclosure.
Voice chat, also a bad idea.
Location is a bad idea.
Even if someone's purchased a particular item
is a bad idea.
Like, be very, very careful about what people can share.
And if they want to share, give them tools to share,
but make it an opt-in activity.
So this is where I kind of put things on like where you should start introducing various
interactions.
And you want those private spaces where people can talk to each other so that they can have
those vulnerable moments.
And anyone who says like, oh, no, we can't do chat because chat is risky.
Chat is actually essential.
You need people to be able to talk to one another.
This is the cone of silence idea that we did in rum, mad God.
We have secrets and people can't hear
each other outside the cone of silence.
There's ways of creating these very simple opt-in systems
that the players don't even think about this,
but this is a super simple thing you can do that like
totally changes the ability
for people to control their experiences.
They can watch someone coming towards them and say like,
oh, I'm going to stop talking about that right now.
And of course, you need to give real friends,
which will come up, a way to skip this.
You need people to opt in to skipping this.
Okay, so those are the basic things, you know,
and that's how you design for friendship formation.
This is sort of like where those things map.
So you've got these four sort of like tools
and then where they map onto sort of the level of trust.
And like certain things, like if you're dealing
with like parallel and solitary play,
you probably shouldn't be thinking about disclosure.
In fact, that's a negative thing to have in your game.
but by by the time you're dealing with the hard
co-op and friends that's an important thing and so you
can kind of like think of your game as this
sort of like funnel of like people becoming friends
and how do you support it at every stage.
If you've ever built a match-based game with a large number of people
where the social identity is beating the crap out of one another,
you may have noticed that getting people to be nice to one another
is a hard problem.
This is just hindsight, but it may have been a good idea.
to actually build a positive social structure
into your game from the very beginning.
Because it's crazy hard to retrofit.
I will call out League of Legends here
because they have done heroic work
trying to fix the experience of a really bad architecture.
Heroic work.
I mean, I think we should applaud them
for the work that they've done.
But at the same time, you don't have to live their life of making that mistake, right?
So build it in from the beginning.
This is a design process.
Social is not something that is a separate pillar.
It's not something that's an adjacent system.
It's not tacked on at the end.
It is fundamental to your game.
And you should be thinking about social,
you should be thinking of it honestly
as the reason you're building your game.
You should make games so that people make friends.
Some resources, you can look this up.
I'm totally out of time.
I apologize to all the people who really care about that.
And that's it.
I got no time for questions, but I'll.