So I'll be honest, in my script it says,
oh my gosh, I'm so happy to see so many of you
in the audience today.
But I don't know if I can call this a lot of people.
Either way, I'm so grateful and honored
to be a speaker this year at GDC.
I think the interpreter in the booth is not sure which reaction I was supposed to take
because I didn't tell her, but hopefully she got it right.
So thanks for showing up for my session today, for such a niche creator like myself.
So I'd like to know, did any of you attend the GDC Awards last night?
Oh, cool. So nice to see that. And you are well aware of who the winners are then.
The best narrative at the 13th Annual Game Developers Choice Awards went to...
Drumroll, drumroll...
The Walking Dead!
That's weird, you know.
I think it was supposed to say, Virtue's Last Reward, and now it says The Walking Dead.
I promised my wife that I'd bring home an award, so I don't know what excuse I have
now.
I myself obviously have played The Walking Dead, so I can completely understand why it
won the award, and I'm a huge fan of the game.
Unfortunately, we didn't win for Virtue's Last Reward, a title which I directed and
wrote the story for.
But I'm so honored to have been nominated for such a prestigious award alongside some fantastic titles.
I'd like to thank all of our staff at Spike Chunsoft, the localization staff at Axis, and all of our fans who supported our title.
And thank you all here for your support.
I was fortunate to attend the award ceremony last night, and all the nominated titles are
fantastic in their own way.
Any of them could have taken home an award.
But of those, the ones that I'm most interested in, or I've always been interested in, and
already have played, are Journey, The Walking Dead, and The Greatest Showman.
and the room. Do you know what these three have in common? Yes, they're all adventure
games. So, as we just said, The Walking Dead took home Best Narrative.
The Room took home Best Handheld and Mobile.
And Journey, they were nominated in six categories
and won all of them.
And of course, the Game of the Year award also went to Journey.
As you can see from these results,
adventure games are on a roll.
It seems as though the fun and adventure games were rediscovered last year thanks to these
wonderful games.
So Visual Novel is sort of an adventure game.
It's sort of an adventure game.
as kind of a sub-genre within the adventure game genre.
Our Virtue's Last Reward, or I'm going to say VLR, is, for short, is a visual novel.
Technically speaking, VLR features a lot of puzzles, so it may not be a visual novel in
the purest sense, but it's safe to say that it falls into the genre.
So then, what's a visual novel?
How many of you have played a visual novel?
Oh, great.
So glad to see.
So then perhaps I don't need to explain what a visual novel is,
but for those who may not be familiar, a visual novel is.
The answer is that there isn't a clear definition of a visual novel.
A video game with visuals, sound, and narrative displayed in text-based form.
That could be one possible definition, but even without sound or narrative displayed
in text on screen, you can still call some games a visual novel.
Then what about a game without any visuals?
That wouldn't make any sense.
How can you call a visual novel if it doesn't contain any visuals?
But it is possible.
to create a piece that essentially is the same and
possesses the same principles as a visual novel, even without
using any visuals. Here's an example of a visual novel
without any visual expressions. This is Real Sound, Winds of
Regret, released back in 1997.
This game contains no visuals whatsoever.
The player spends his or her time listening as the story
unfolds.
When there's a fork in the plot, it's up to the player to choose
which course to take.
Once the selection is made, the story continues.
The structure is essentially the same as a visual novel.
And I just use the word essential or essence.
So then what is the essential quality or principle behind a
visual novel?
Watch on screen, the essential quality of a visual novel.
A video game with visual, sound, and narrative displayed in text-based form.
And now, you just saw that the two words that remain are narrative and video game.
Put simply, a video game with narrative is essential quality of a visual novel.
A game with narrative sounds like pretty much any game out there, from Super Mario Brothers
to, I mean, pretty much anything.
Well, maybe Tetris is an exception.
You're all probably thinking.
So then, let me rephrase what I meant.
It's a video game that weighs heavily on narrative.
The essential quality of a visual novel lies in heavy narrative.
However, just because it's narrative heavy, you can't call it a visual novel, since that
would also apply to film, anime, manga, novels, and so on.
At the same time, you can't just add the word game or the game element to something and
call it a visual novel, as would also include things like paperback adventure game books.
In sum, there are two elements that make up the essential
quality of a visual novel, a heavy narrative and a video
game.
So let me step away from visual novels for a second here and
talk about sports. Are football and baseball sports? Of course
they are. Then what about darts?
and pool? How about motor racing, shooting, and fishing? And yes, fishing. What about
lingerie football? I don't know about you guys, but I say these are all sports because
they require to be athletic.
However, some people may disagree in a similar way that some people think visual novels are
not games.
So, is a visual novel a game or not?
If it isn't…
I would have to go back and re-examine the essential qualities of what makes a visual
novel.
I'm going to go ahead and answer the question for us.
A visual novel is a game.
Similar to how darts and fishing are sports, a visual novel is a game.
But why and how and what exactly is a game then?
If being athletic and having great reflexes
defines what a sport is, then what is a game?
A game is something with selectivity, is what I think.
To be more specific.
Something where the selection made by the player's decision
changes the history of events or outcome
that takes place within a given set of rules.
Does that make sense?
Well, let me just give you an example.
In Tetris, the player selects how to move the falling blocks
based on a specific set of rules.
Depending on the selection made by the player,
the blocks below changes its form.
This outcome you see is a result of the player's decision
coming into play with the events
that are displayed on screen.
It's the same with a game of chess.
The player selects how to move the piece based on a given rule, and by doing so, the events
or the history of what's taking place on the board is changed.
So that is why chess is also a game.
Darts, poker, tennis, boxing, Call of Duty, Assassin's Creed, Metal Gear, all these are
games.
Oh, of course, and so is lingerie football.
And why?
Because the selection made by the player's decision
changes the history of events taking place
within a given set of rules.
If that's the case, we can say that life is a game too.
Because in life, there are rules and selectivity.
It looks like you guys made the right choice or decision
because you are here today listening to me speak.
A game specializing in selectivity, that's a visual novel.
In that sense, I believe it's a category of games in its purest form, a primitive game.
As you know, except for some rare ones, the majority of visual novels have some form of
selectivity.
They are generally displayed in the form of a selection or choice.
This is where visual novels differ from film, anime, manga, and novels.
They might all have narratives, but they don't have selectivity.
The viewer or reader is unable to step into the story at will.
This is the biggest strength for visual novels.
In Japan, visual novels have naturally evolved and developed over time.
Similar to the giant tortoise in the Galapagos Islands, it has evolved in its own unique
way domestically in a closed environment.
And like Charles Darwin's theory of evolution, perhaps someone in the audience will uncover
an eccentric idea as well.
The first example is Steins Gate, a visual novel released in 2009 by 5PB Games.
This game does not have any selections or choices.
Instead, there is a selectivity element
where you can either choose to send an email
from your mobile phone or not.
Depending on your selection, the plot changes.
The following year in 2010, our company released a game called Danganronpa, Academy of Hope
and High School Students of Despair.
It is a murder mystery adventure game with a school trial at the center of the story.
The game manages to perfectly blend the action and the heated debates.
And aside from the trial section of the game, the game progresses in a visual novel manner.
There are many other visual novels with great stories,
philosophical ones, emotional ones, well written mysteries and
human drama. So many to name, but there is one work that
pioneered the visual novel movement.
And that is Kamaitachi no Yoru, translated as the night of the
sickle weasel.
This is actually a game developed by Chunsoft before we merged with Spike and became the
current company.
The original release was in 1994, about 20 years ago, on the SNES.
It is a visual novel, and the plot revolves around two characters who are suddenly drawn
into a horrible murder mystery at a skiing lodge.
You are to solve the mystery and find the murderer.
There is one unique thing about this game.
That is that it doesn't use any flags.
I'm sure everyone here knows what I mean by a flag.
Yes, it's the flag used in computer programming.
Are you going to flirt with Naomi?
If yes, the variable is true.
If no, it will be false.
Soon after, you find out Naomi is your boss's mistress.
So if you chose false, you'll be promoted.
But if you chose true, you'll be fired.
That's a quick example of a flag.
After asking around the development team members who worked on Kamaitachi no Yoru,
it looks like they didn't really use any flags.
If so, how were they able to create branching storylines without losing consistency?
Well, in fact, there are a couple different ways to approach this, but today, I'm going
to talk about the most interesting method.
In Kamaitachi no Yoru, the flags were embedded into the player's brain.
So what exactly does this mean, you're probably thinking.
Don't worry, I'll explain what it means.
Here's a snapshot of the branching narrative structure.
At point X, the dead body is discovered.
Next, at point Y, this is where you
enter the name of the murderer.
This comes up pretty early in the game.
If you have the correct answer, in other words,
if you're able to guess the murderer and you're right,
you'll get the good ending, which is A.
However, in most cases, you haven't collect enough clues
to guess the murderer on the first try.
So players will end up passing through Y
and get to endings B, C, D, and so on.
Unfortunately, those have tragic endings where all the characters are murdered, or you end
up killing the heroine by mistake, and even vice versa.
In order to avoid these endings, the players must return to point Y and enter the correct
answer.
But to do that, the player must collect hints and clues along the way that lead to those
tragic B, C, and D endings.
Once you've gathered enough clues and are ready to solve the case, you return to point
Y.
That's the basic flow in Kamaidachi no Yoru.
The interesting thing about this float is that they're not using a flag at point Y.
In any ordinary visual novel, it would work like this.
You have a flag at B, and a flag at C, and a flag at D. Once you've gotten through all
the flags, point Y will unlock, and you'll get the good ending at A.
However, that's not how it works in this game.
In an extreme case, if you're able to guess the correct name during your first playthrough,
you'll get the good A ending without having to have to go through endings B, C, and D.
So if there is no flag at point Y, what took its place?
The answer is the memory that was embedded in the player's brain.
Once the player gathers clues on path.
B, C, and D, the main character of the game was able to go back to point Y and give the
correct answer, thanks to the player's own memory.
Normally in visual novels, that memory is stored onto the computer's memory as a piece
of data.
For example, were the clues picked up in path B?
True.
What about in path C?
And D?
True.
Once those conditions are met, the main character is able to proceed to path A.
However, in this game, the developers of Kaimaitachi no Yoru
use the player's brain to store the memory and not the computer.
Using the player's brain as the computer's memory, this is what's unique about Kamaitachi
no Yoru and what differentiates this game from other visual novels that came after it.
I sense a lot of old school gamers reacting to this, telling me that all adventure games
from the early days did the same thing.
And they're 100% correct.
It is true that back in the days when playing adventure games, you would have to take notes
of passwords or clues or even draw a simple map for yourself.
The memory capacity needed to play those games existed in our own brain.
However, as consoles and technology evolved, that information was stored on the computer.
I mean, who wouldn't want that?
Playing games become a bit easier, less stressful, fun, and accessible.
Don't you think?
For visual novels, we're seeing more games adapt that style, where
they're frequently using flags.
Therefore, from our standpoint, Kamaitachi no Yoru is different, and
at the same time, feels very fresh.
There is a Japanese proverb, Onko Chishin, which means to discover new things by taking
lessons from the past.
Kamaitachi no Yoru is exactly that.
It is a game that teaches us the importance of Onko Chishin.
So I talked in length about Kamaitachi no Yoru,
and you're probably wondering what it has to do with VLR.
Well, there is a connection.
And if you've already played VLR,
you may have already noticed something.
In VLR, you are prompted to enter a password
at certain points, like when you need to start up a computer
or you have to deactivate a bomb, and so on.
Take a look at this flow.
You pick up a password on path B and enter it into device Y.
Do the same on path C and enter into Z1, path D,
and enter into Z2.
Eventually, you'll have unlocked Y and Z's
and proceed further into the game.
This isn't throughout the entire game,
but it comes up plenty of times.
And we're not using any flags at these points.
The player embeds the information he or she collected on these paths as memories in their
brain and enters them into devices Y and Z.
The original idea of this comes from Kamaitachi no Yoru and the method they used.
So, as with that game, if a player ends up searching for passwords for Y and Z somewhere
online or a strategy guide, they can simply enter that and advance in the game without
going through B, C, or D. What do you think?
Pretty interesting.
Since the title of this session is Narrative Design and Virtue's Last Reward, I assume
many of you here today have an interest in story writing and storytelling.
So in using the remaining time, I'd like to share some of my techniques.
It's nothing extraordinary or special.
So I don't know if you call these techniques, but for me,
it begins with a sense of discomfort.
This is what I use as a foundation for whenever I design
a game or write a narrative.
I'm inspired by it and everything begins from here.
I'm going to bring back Kamaitachi no Yoru for a second
here.
Here's a flowchart for Kamaitachi no Yoru.
When I was explaining this earlier, did you notice anything?
I said this, the player will pick up hints and clues along paths B, C, D, and return
to Y and enter the murderer's name.
However, if you think about it, that can't be right.
Point Y exists above Path B, C, and D.
It existed in the past.
Therefore, at Point Y, the main character of the game,
his name is Toru, doesn't know, or rather can't know
what happened in Path B, C, and D.
Those events happen in the future.
But Toru is able to enter the name at point Y when he returns.
Why is that?
I'm sure you know the answer, it's obvious.
It's because the player, not the main character in the game,
knew about the events in paths B, C and D.
Interesting, right?
The player had information that the main character Toru didn't have.
Therefore, Toru, the player's alter ego, knew the answer.
How do you solve this?
It's simple.
What you do is you give the main character in the game
the same ability you have.
In other words, you allow the character
to move freely between the past, future,
and different timelines in the past.
This is how the VLR flowchart came to be.
Well, to be honest, it's the other way around.
In the prequel, 999, nine hours, nine persons, nine doors,
we didn't have a flowchart.
Some of our fans didn't like that.
So we decided from the beginning that VLR would have one.
But it's no fun just including a flow chart just
to have it in there, right?
So I started thinking of ways to incorporate a story
element into the chart.
That's when the confusion or discomfort of Kamaitachi no
Yoru became the source of inspiration.
In addition, in both VLR and 999, there are various elements in the game which were inspired
by this element of discomfort or confusion.
For example, the discomfort you feel in, let's say, first-person perspective and third-person
perspective.
I won't go into the details, as I know not all of you may have played VLR and 999.
However, I will say that the discomfort you get from playing a third-person perspective game
and seeing yourself in the screen is what creates the unique qualities in these games.
You probably know what I mean by this if you played the game.
I hate to keep repeating myself, but that sense of discomfort is very important.
It's a trigger point for me in writing this story.
I suppose you can say it's very similar to having doubts about the conventional thought,
or me telling you, do not blindly trust the common knowledge.
For example, in most action adventure games and RPGs, your main character carries several
weapons along with other gear and equipment, even though visually and on screen, you can
only see one type of what they have equipped.
And in various parts of the map.
You can pick up ammo, healing items, and will get coins or money when you defeat your enemies.
In reality, that doesn't happen, and it's not natural.
But in games, it's typical.
It's a given, and we don't question that.
And that's the standard.
It's right here where there's actually a hidden trick.
Does anyone know who or what I'm talking about?
So, I just said that equipping several weapons and picking up ammo at specific locations
is unnatural in real life.
It just doesn't happen that way.
But players have accepted it without questioning why.
Why is it so in games?
Simple answer, because the game is much more fun that way.
There are people who argue that these settings are not realistic and you wouldn't encounter
such situations in real life.
But I think that's nonsense.
We shouldn't be that obsessed with reality and games where it becomes too excessive.
A real world where true reality exists is the world we live in.
And this world is a world where the level design is broken,
and there are all kinds of bugs all over the place.
Don't you agree that it's a pretty boring world?
What's so entertaining about recreating a world
full of absurdity in games?
Games are fun because they are set in an imaginary world.
What's important to games isn't the real reality,
but a reality for games.
It's the reality that is according to rules in games.
In closing, I like to circle back to the top of this session.
Of the games that were nominated this year at the Game Developers' Choice Awards,
I'm most interested in these three titles, Journey, The Walking Dead, and The Room.
And what do they have in common?
All three are adventure games.
But I think there's one more thing they have in common.
They're all digitally distributed games.
The Room is available on the iPhone and iPad.
The Walking Dead is a multi-platform title that's also available on the iPhone and iPad.
And Journey is a downloadable PS3 game.
I think it's safe to conclude that adventure games work well on smartphones.
Most people these days all own smartphones, and I believe that adventure games is a game
genre that is very well fitted or fitting to smartphones.
Adventure games, similar to novels, films, TV drama, manga, and anime, is a new way to
tell a story.
I'm hopeful that we will see amazing adventure games released across digital platforms in
the future.
I'm looking forward to them.
And hopefully, one of you guys here will help us create that amazing game in the future.
If I can be of any assistance, that would make me very happy.
Thank you for listening to my session today.
So we have about 15 minutes for a Q&A session.
There are two mics.
So please walk up, step up to the mic and ask the question.
Hi, may I start now?
Yes, go ahead.
Hi, I'm a big fan of Chunsoft and I play 428, 999 and VLR. I love all of them.
So my question here is about...
why you decided to make VLR a sequel to 999.
It sounds the...
It seems that the ending of 999 is almost perfect,
but you decided to expand the universe of that game,
and it seems now you're making 999 a trilogy right now.
So what is the reason of that?
Um...
Excuse me, um...
The questions...
Um...
Ah, first...
Thank you very much.
I thought about why I wanted to continue making 999 and VRR games.
First of all, when 999 was released, it received a very high rating, especially in North America.
As a result, we decided to make a sequel.
At the time, we were planning to make a sequel with DS.
I thought that.
If you're going to make it in DS,
it's more efficient to make 2 and 3 at the same time.
So, parallel 2 and 3,
We had the initial idea of making a 3D platform.
But as you all know, 3DS and Vita,
the new platforms have been coming out,
and we had to change the hardware.
So we decided to make 2D alone,
and then make 3D.
This is how we decided to do it.
And...
So when we developed version 2 and 3,
we had already made copies of the first.
2 and 3 were already in my head as a set of things.
So that is one of the reasons why 2 is connected to the sequel.
And 0, the Escape series, is now a series.
I think that is one of the reasons.
I wanted to listen to the entire answer first.
So 999 was released in Japan, both in Japan and North America, and it was very well received
out here in North America, thanks to everyone here and our fans.
And as a result, it was natural for us to start thinking about a sequel.
Originally, we were planning on developing the sequel on the DS, and in doing so...
we had an idea that we would go ahead and sort of work on a second one and a third one
simultaneously that, you know, developing it would be a lot more efficient that way.
And while we were doing that, obviously the 3DS was announced and came out.
The Vita was also announced.
So we had to sort of make a decision as to which platforms we were going to release this
game on.
And at the same time...
even though we had, you know, planned for two and three, slowly but surely we
started thinking of that as a set. And so that was, in my head, two and three sort
of became a two-in-one type of setting or a package, I guess, a combo. And so it
was a natural sort of way for us to say that this was going to be our next step.
And then from there it's...
sort of continue on the same path that, okay, now we can, you know, support this as a series.
Good afternoon. It seems to me that a lot of the more recent visual novel hits,
things like Higurashi no Naku Koro ni come from the doujin scene.
Sort of Japan's equivalent of the indie gaming scene. I'm wondering do you think that?
The observation is accurate and what do you think?
Doujin games can offer to visual novel the whole visual novel genre going into the future
Yes, I understand. First, I will repeat the content of your question.
There is a situation where a doujin game like The Crying Colony is gaining popularity,
It's a situation where both sides are getting excited.
Is there a possibility that such a doujin game will continue to develop in the future?
Uh...
For Visual Novel...
Visual...
Sorry.
Will Visual Novel 2 develop?
It's a long one.
Can I answer this?
I don't want to repeat myself.
In Japan, there is a comic market called Comiket.
There, you can buy Doujin games and magazines.
and many people have participated in making it.
As a result, more and more interesting games and stories have been created in the indie industry.
We hope that more and more indie games will be created in the future.
I'm sure that from now on his business will change.
For example, you can create and distribute your own apps on your phone.
And if you do that, you can create your own apps without the help of a company.
I think we were talking about visual novels.
Not only visual novels, but all other genres, including games,
used to be quite popular, including musicians,
as well as individuals of liberals,
leading to a number of illegal acts against пытки JK.
I think he has a lot of potential.
So in Japan, as you may know, there's a Comiken, the comic market, and you know, the participants
in the community is growing, I think, at a pretty nice pace, and a lot of new ideas and
games and stories are coming out from that community.
And as you just mentioned, you know, the Japanese sort of indie game development scene can probably
work.
that scene is probably getting a lot of influence and maybe even, you know, ideas
are being exchanged. So from there, there may be games, ideas that may even prove
to be commercially successful and not just in a very small, you know, tight-knit
community. In addition to that, you know, as we now know on smartphones, tablets,
and whatnot, we can all...
if we want to release content, we don't have to go the route of finding a large company
or publisher to publish our creations.
And so in that sense, you know, even without a company's support, indies or doujin, whatever
their new creations, new ideas and unique.
you know, games and stories, however they want to push it out, it is becoming a very,
you know, possible scenario for many people.
And so, not limited to visual novels, the genre, I think you'll start to see, I think
we're going to start to see a little bit more movement.
And so with that, yes, I think the visual novel.
genre will grow and see potential, but at the same time, other genres will
hopefully grow and have some new ideas, new fresh ideas come from the doujin
and indie community.
Okay, this is going to be the last question.
The discomfort thing that you were talking about while writing VLR.
My question was, there is a part at the end, without spoiling it,
where you realize an interesting part about the main character.
That and the fact that you also realize something interesting about the previous
game's main character, which is also kind of discomforting to the player.
Was that kind of going in with your theme of discomfort when you were writing about those things?
Well, um...
well, your question was about that there could be spoilers,
so it was at very long distance
Well, um...
I don't know if what he's saying is the same as what I'm thinking, but I think that feeling is correct.
Please look forward to the next one.
The short answer is yes, that was definitely where I wanted to take the players.
That was my intention.
And so if you sense that discomfort and it was communicated, then I've probably done
my job or I've achieved my goal.
So yes, I definitely wanted that to come through.
So, thank you for listening.