Thanks for coming here.
It's really nice to see a full room.
And first of all, I'd like to kind of warm the crowd
by asking a show of hands, how many of you
have played the game I'm going to be talking about today,
Brawl Stars?
Nice.
OK.
How many of you started with the global launch?
Sometime during the soft launch, beta.
Wow.
How many of you played the game in portrait mode,
like this instead of this?
Wow.
OK.
Nice.
I'm sure you have some questions.
I hope this talk is going to answer some of them,
or raise more questions that I can answer later.
All right, so the topic of the talk is a bit whimsical.
So if you don't get it now.
Well, let's say if you don't get it after the talk,
then I didn't do my job.
But by core, I mean some core design element of the game.
And the talk is about how we, during the soft launch, which
went on for a long time, tried a lot of things,
a lot of very fundamental changes in our game
and what the results were.
But first, a little bit about me.
I started at Supercell about eight years ago.
Worked on the very first browser-based MMO.
And also have been working on various fun, small projects,
iterations, and experiments, prototypes.
For example, this one.
This is a world premiere for Forest Ranger, circa 2011.
Just a quick one week prototype with one artist.
And also, after we pivoted to mobile games,
I worked on the very first game that was killed by Supercell.
RIP.
It's appropriately in black and white there, very morose,
called Project Tower.
After that, I worked on Hay Day, Boom Beach,
and early on in Clash Royale.
And now for the last 2 and 1â„2 years,
I've been working on Brawl Stars.
So today, I'm going to be covering these topics.
First of all, how we got into beta.
Yeah, right, OK.
How we got into beta, some, and then getting
into the meat of what I just was talking about a moment ago,
the iterations we did, trying to find the perfect control
scheme, improve player engagement and experience
on the long term with different iterations of the progression
system.
And then stuff we overlooked, social gameplay.
I wouldn't say overlooked, but I certainly have a different perspective now on the kind
of feedback we got from the community.
So let's jump right in.
Back in 2015, there was a lot of excitement at Supercell about Clash Royale.
The game wasn't going to be in beta for several months still, but the promise of a real-time
multiplayer, at least two-player competitive game was definitely in the air, and we thought...
the world is ready for a game that quite a lot of us,
a type of game on mobile that quite a lot of us like to play
and didn't exist yet.
So after Clash Royale went to beta, this was proven.
And we thought, OK, the market is ready as well, not just
the technology.
And but even before Clash Royale went to beta,
We were prototyping with a small team on a multiplayer action
shooter.
And between 2016 and 2017, we had three internal milestones.
We call them, or the target of these milestones
is always a company playable.
Being a relatively small company,
we have the advantage of getting or potentially getting
everybody at the company playing our new game projects,
getting a very wide variety of different backgrounds
from finance to legal to marketing to game teams,
player support.
engaged in our games and giving feedback
from their own perspectives also.
This has been kind of a staple of Supercell game development
for years now.
We also tested with real players.
Because for us, the major worry was fast-paced controls
on a mobile device or any kind of touchscreen device.
And we wanted to see if our designs, control scheme designs
were actually usable by regular people.
We were confident enough to soft launch the game
on June 15th of 2017.
in Canada and on iOS only. And we'll come back to this decision. Actually, we'll talk
about it right now a little bit. So, a lot of you know why games often get soft launched
in Canada. For Supercell, the reasons are pretty much the same. It's a little bit more
It's a smaller market that's quite comparable to the US,
which is one of our major, has historically
been our most important market.
And it also allows us to compare the performance of the beta
to our previous betas and get some insight of how we're doing,
what the target should be.
It's much easier to develop just for one platform,
so an iOS has traditionally been the one
we develop for at Supercell.
For Brawl Stars in particular, matchmaking was a concern.
So we wanted to limit ourselves to one geographic region
at first to have people playing in the same time zone.
So that's our.
beta population wasn't spread out all over the world to make sure that they have good
fast matchmaking experience. And finally, we were concerned about the game spreading,
especially the APK spreading out and...
too many people or more people than we would prefer having
the kind of not finished, not polished soft launch
experience of the game instead of saving it
for the global launch.
It turned out to be the longest beta in Supercell history,
545 days, which was.
a long time for both the players who started early on
and for the game team.
The reasons for that are, well, again, historical.
We have been able to release very popular games before,
and all the new game projects are going to be,
all the new games are going to be compared to these games.
So we already had.
some fairly ambitious goals going into the project.
And in addition, while we're quite
happy to kill poorly performing games in soft launch,
we're committed to support the game for years for the players
once we go global.
OK, now I'm going to show a quick video.
I'm not sure if the sound's going to work or not,
how the game looked when we launched in June 2017.
And if you play the game today, you
might notice that it looks quite similar to, well,
fairly similar to how the game, I mean,
that state almost two years ago and today look fairly similar.
But almost everything has changed under the hood.
Angry noob!
Play-tea?
Angry ball!
You wanna brawl?
Alright.
So let's talk about some of those changes under the hood.
First, I'm going to dial back the time a little bit
before we went to beta and talk about various control scheme
iterations we had before and during.
We are still pretty proud of how we've
been able to innovate.
touch with touchscreen controls.
In Hay Day, in Clash Royale, in Clash of Clans even,
we felt that we really raised the bar to how you,
for the usability of touchscreen games.
And we didn't.
want to go with the default option for an action shooter,
which is dual joystick type of game.
These games were out already, several of them,
but basically none of the team, the early team,
liked dual joystick controls.
So that started a long process of prototyping, experimenting.
With the
main objective of trying to take some of the twitchiness, the fast-paced movement and excessive
tapping or control actions out of the game. This is one of the prototypes where the player
actually only moves the character by tapping on the screen and you can see a faint outline
there.
And that's it.
I hope you enjoyed this video.
If you did, make sure to like, comment, and subscribe.
And I'll see you in the next one.
Bye for now.
that shows the range of the character's weapon.
And once an opponent gets into range,
the character will automatically fire.
This was a fairly fun control scheme,
but we thought we could do better,
and also felt like we should give the players more control.
Also, there were always complaints about the...
slow-paced feeling of all the kind of deliberate pace of the gameplay. Here's the following
iteration. And in terms of the core combat, this is pretty much what ended up in the soft
launch version. Even though you might notice the game looks fairly different, but that's
a topic for a whole other talk.
So in this iteration, you can see the little cursor moving around.
The player taps where they want to move and swipes and releases the fire.
And the place where they release is the targeting point of their attack.
So now we moved from auto-attacking only to pure skill shots.
And we thought this felt like a very good compromise.
It didn't feel too hectic, and the controls
were simple and reasonably easy to learn
until we started user testing.
This is from March 2017, and an actual user.
playing the game for the first time,
about to start their first game.
And immediately we noticed something strange,
or something that was different from the way we play the game.
So in the team, we'd been playing the game.
by holding the device on one hand
and then tapping with the index finger of the other
to execute the controls, movement, and firing.
But this is not how people actually use their cell phones.
So instead of pecking on the screen like an old person,
our testers.
We're using two thumbs, as if texting the regular way
they use their phone.
And also our ideas of deliberate and kind
of low actions per minute gameplay went out the window.
It turned out to be incredibly hectic,
as you can see on the video.
the feedback from shooting wasn't sufficient to let the player know that this is all the
actions they can take for the moment. So, the testers and our co-workers alike reported
feeling like, feeling very overwhelmed by the combat because they felt like they had
to do 250 actions per minute. So based on this testing, um, we decided to do a test
and the feedback we'd been getting.
We did one more iteration before going
to beta for our control scheme.
And this was introducing the dreaded virtual joystick.
So we didn't change the game dramatically,
unlike between the two previous iterations.
Where, by the way, I forgot to mention
that the reason we turned the game into portrait mode
was for that more natural way of holding your handheld device.
We were designing for phones as the primary platform.
And we felt, especially with the experience of Clash Royale,
that this was the way to go.
So there was one virtual stick at the.
Bottom corner, you could customize that
for either left or right-handed.
And then you would tap where you wanted to shoot.
Now, user testing found that this was also
frustrating for players.
And the kind of drifting stick we had designed
ended up drifting all over the screen.
However, one thing we found from both the company playables,
user testing, and our just playing with the team
internally was that when you played together,
when you were in the same room, you
could put three absolute beginners in the same room,
and they would still have fun, even if they
struggled with the controls.
This guy is really enjoying himself.
After playing the game, maybe about 10 or 15 minutes,
and there's good communication going on.
And there is a lot of laughter and overall a really nice
gameplay experience.
We'll come back to this later.
So here are the two control modes we had to choose between.
Tap once again, you hold the device however you hold it, and tap by your chosen finger
to move, and then swipe and release to fire. Whereas the joystick movement was
basically holding the device on one hand, and then with the other hand free
you would tap where you want to shoot. The joystick would control your character.
We couldn't decide.
The user testing was indecisive.
Company playables, I mean, voting after our company
playable gave us no clear winner.
So we decided that let's let the players decide.
We assigned all new players, decided
to assign all new players in the beta with one of these two
control models.
However.
even they couldn't decide.
So looking at the retention, how long players
stick with the game, there was no clear winner
between the two control models.
That left us scratching our heads
until our data scientist dug a bit deeper
and found one clear difference.
players were switching more to the joystick controls
from tap controls than vice versa.
And that led us to eventually phase out the tap controls.
They remained as an option in the menus,
but everybody got joystick controls as the first choice.
Now, there's a twist, and it's this.
Eventually.
About nine months later, we decided to turn the game back to landscape.
Well, back. It had already always been in portrait mode.
And this was more or less a natural progression from that single joystick.
We had also already experimented with double joystick,
even though we hadn't tested it.
But on a portrait mode screen,
you didn't really have room for your two thumbs to maneuver.
if the phone was in portrait mode.
So with the popularity and eventual acceptance
of victory of the single joystick,
it just felt like a more natural method of controlling the game.
Going to one joystick was basically
opening the door for the two joysticks.
And that required this quite.
Big change.
And of course, it had a huge impact on core gameplay.
We had to teach players who had been playing the game, some
of them for nine months, to relearn the shooting
controls all over.
We had to implement a whole new auto-aim or quick-fire feature
where tapping the right joystick would
shoot at the nearest opponent.
And
I'll come back to the fallout from this in the community
feedback section.
All right, so these are the different control mode
iterations we made before and during the beta.
Let's move on to progression.
So when the game went to beta, oh, there's another pun.
upgrade system, well, the upgrade screen looked like this. So we had decided to go with an
upgrade system as something for players to strive for, to give them meaningful progression
from one session to the next or one week to the next when they've been playing more and
more.
And our first iteration of this that actually went out
to players was very much like, say, an RPG game, where
you had points to allocate to different character
traits or attributes.
Now, in a competitive game, this is risky,
because the
Any kind of power progression means that you'll sometimes face players with more powerful characters than you.
So we tried to walk a fine line here by keeping the power scaling.
very small compared to, for example, Clash Royale has,
if you look at the very maximum of scaling
you can have with common cards, it's about 200%.
So we went on the very conservative side.
And if you take into account the fact
that you rarely face, due to matchmaking,
have this maximum difference in any one match.
Anyhow.
it felt like a good compromise.
And in fact, even though we were quite
concerned about this choice, we had good results.
So players weren't complaining about the game
being played to win.
Instead, the progression system, at least in the beginning,
felt meaningful.
So this upgrade resource used for
every kind of upgrade in the game was in loot boxes
and also added much needed content to the loot boxes
so that the box we gave the player
at the end of every session or at least the end of every day
if you played actively would contain something useful
that would make you feel like you're getting ahead
in the game.
However.
It wasn't very satisfying to get a single Elixir bottle.
Anybody remember this screen?
Yeah.
And in fact, even getting massive amounts of Elixir
didn't feel that great.
There was a longstanding misconception among our players
that
Getting 10 elixir cheated you out from getting
a legendary character.
So people felt really bad, missing out on Spike and Crow,
or so they thought, even though the drop rates were
very, very different.
But despite many attempts to communicate that,
the rumor or the misconception just stuck.
We saw that people went sticking around.
And
assumed that a big part of the reason
was that this progression system wasn't satisfying enough.
And we also saw this from the community.
A lot of complaints about getting duplicate brawlers,
which was another thing back then,
and small elixir drops that felt meaningless.
So we decided to iterate the progression system.
So we, six months into the beta, it looked completely different.
And if you don't get what's going on there,
I don't blame you.
We addressed one issue that people
had with the progression system, which was.
having difficulty deciding where to allocate the elixir,
which characters to upgrade.
You would always be second-guessing
which character is going to be nerfed in the coming update,
which character is going to be buffed.
Am I really going to enjoy playing with this guy?
Because once you allocated your resource,
it was gone, or it was permanently allocated
with no chance of respeccing.
We took some of that difficulty of choice
out while keeping the same amount of power scaling.
So instead of a unified upgrade resource,
we now had these pins, badges, medals, and crests,
which were unique items for each character,
improving one of their stats.
And all of these were added to the loot boxes.
So there was a lot more variety now
that you could get when you opened a box
at the end of the session.
And there was even a chance of non-linear upgrades.
So you might get lucky and pick up a crest for attack damage,
for example, from just a random box.
So now there was a.
there was some dynamic range to the boxes you opened,
other than just characters, which were quite few and far
between once you had the common ones and the rare ones.
In addition, we went a step further
by adding a star power to each character, which actually
changed the gameplay.
So as you can see, maybe it's tiny text,
but Shelly's star power gives her the ability
to slow down enemies when she hits them with her super.
There were some downsides to it.
It made balancing between.
characters who do have the star power and don't have it.
A little bit more complicated, you
had to take both into account or just balance for the top level
fully upgraded players.
And also, the
Having the start powers in the game
made the game a little bit harder to understand.
You didn't know exactly what you were facing
when you entered the game.
You might be slowed down by Shelly's super or not.
And also, the whole upgrade screen
was really hard to explain for first-time players.
It did its job, though.
We were able to see a noticeable bump in longer-term retention.
However, here comes the twist.
We were going to have to redo the UI anyway
when we went to landscape.
And as a leap of faith, we decided to try something,
well, tried and true.
So only three months later, we released another progression
system.
Yeah, you can imagine how the players felt.
Some of you felt it too.
This second iteration during the beta
had an upgrade or progression system that was
quite similar to Clash Royale.
So similarly to how cards are stacked
until you can upgrade them, now we had.
In Clash Royale now we had PowerPoints that are character specific and you use coins to
enact the upgrade.
There were some changes because of that.
There was absolutely no choice anymore when it came to choosing.
which character trait to upgrade.
You could only pick which character
to actually finalize the upgrade for with coins.
So to make up for this change, we
introduced 10 different upgrade levels
and increased the power scaling in order
to make each level feel significant.
So this was another kind of leap of faith to see.
And we had to see how the community would react.
But this was the least of the community's worries.
The game still apparently felt fair.
But even though this new interface was much, much nicer
looking and
There was no more confusion about pins, badges, medals,
crests, tokens, et cetera.
We had really simplified everything.
We couldn't improve metrics.
And a bit later on, I'll be talking about how
the players felt about this.
Thanks.
All right, now that I've gone.
over the control scheme iterations, the progression
system iterations, let's talk about something
we didn't improve for a year, which is playing with friends.
So as I said before, we knew the game is fun
when you play it with friends.
That's the best gameplay experience.
But.
actually playing with people you know together
was quite difficult.
We made you jump through quite a hoop.
You either had to be face-to-face
and input this five-character code
to enter your friend's game room,
or you might...
get some people, semi-random people from your clan
that we called bands back then, which are called clubs now.
Yeah, iteration, right?
So you had...
by far, the most fun when you manage
to play with your friends.
And for example, our finance team
is still playing together ever since the early beta,
because they got into the habit of typing in the room code,
even though you don't actually always have to do that.
They play together and have had amazing retention.
You can't say the same for most players.
Even though you get a competitive edge from playing
with your friends, you can figure out the team
composition that you want to play for a certain map,
certain game mode.
For most people, most people ended up playing by themselves,
just trusting the random matchmaking.
And instead of
focusing on some way to get your actual friends in the same room with you, we had this...
We only enabled players to invite band members and band members typically they aren't in
your close circle of friends and basically anybody who happened to be online might join
you.
There was no in-game friends list so if there was somebody...
that you played with, some random person,
there was absolutely no way to connect with them afterwards,
even if you wanted to.
And finally, like I said earlier on,
this was a very fateful decision for us to go with iOS only.
Because.
If you think about a game that is best played with friends,
if you have an iOS device and your friend happens to have an
Android device, you just can't play with them.
And that's a hard stop, unless you get them to buy an iPhone
or iPad just for Brawl Stars.
And that's a hard sell.
So word of mouth and the kind of excitement
a fun multiplayer game can achieve
was definitely dampened by going iOS only.
And also, you can't really tell your friends
to start playing a game if they can't play the game.
All right.
Which kind of gets me to.
community feedback.
So let's start by talking about the way
we handle our community.
Ever since the beginning of the beta,
it's been centered on Reddit.
Even though we have some social media presence and a YouTube
channel, the
We actually direct people from inside the game to our Reddit
with various in-game news posts.
And we've had several thousand active, more or less
active members on Reddit throughout the beta.
And we also communicate with our community
through our subreddit.
In return, we get a lot of suggestions, complaints,
and all kinds of cool stuff like fan art.
However, having a very passionate community
also means that they're going to speak out when.
things are not going well from their perspective.
So all the stuff I've been telling you
about the iterations we made to core functionality
was very jarring for the player community.
So we changed.
The progress system, even though we always refunded everything,
so people got back anything they'd
spent on improving their characters and got to respec,
it was still a big jarring change to relearn.
But even more than that, changing the control model
was really tough for a lot of players.
They had to relearn very basic.
functionality of the game and give up a lot of the skills
they'd learned.
And on top of that, we provided very little content
between these big core gameplay changes.
And the thinking was that we already
know from the early beta that whenever we release something
new, a new brawler, a new game mode, or something like that,
that is exciting for players.
it increases our metrics.
And so now we can focus on something else.
And finally, as hard as it is to say,
there's often been this kind of drop in the bucket mentality
where our beta player base is seen as.
sort of expendable.
Not entirely.
We do listen to them, and we communicate with them
and appreciate their feedback.
However, compared to the global player base,
this is a very small amount of players.
So.
We take the beta stage as a chance
to make big changes and experiment.
And after global launch, those kind of big changes
would be very, very detrimental for the future of the game.
So it's a sacrifice we've been willing to make.
However.
with an active, passionate, and angry community on Reddit,
just two taps away from starting the game, where you can see,
a new player can see a wall of, OK, this is not
a wall of posts, but just a complaint about how
the community sentiment was.
as recently as a year ago.
It's a really big warning sign for somebody
who's starting a new game, checking out the community,
what the game has to offer.
even our content creators were affected by the state of affairs.
So YouTube content creators have been really important for us
historically and currently
as people who drive in new players,
who keep the current player base engaged
and overall sort of positive...
avatars to show what our games are at their most fun.
Here's one of them.
Kairostime has been with us from the very beginning,
and he's one of our most popular YouTubers.
And OK, he looks like he's pretty sad at this point.
But actually, he's acting, because.
We did something different in May 2018.
So this was a stage in the beta where even the game team,
well, the game team was already very frustrated
by the apparent lack of movement in metrics.
We weren't able to improve the game sufficiently
to feel confident that we could globally launch.
And so after these major core gameplay changes,
we decided to focus on something else.
We'd now gotten all that stuff off the plate.
Even the huge previous update had no significant impact
on metrics.
So instead, we released new characters, new game modes,
and crucially, improved social gameplay.
There was now an in-game friends list,
a play again functionality where you could actually
keep playing with the same randoms
if you found them to be a good team,
and improvements to economy and a new focus
on rewarding the player for climbing in trophies,
for getting better.
So we, instead of just...
in rewarding the grind.
Now we very visibly rewarded the players
actually getting better, winning games, and moving ahead.
And for the first time, we kind of reversed course.
We took rewards out of loot boxes
and offered them as rewards for climbing trophies.
And then in June, OK, this is the same lonely spike
in the desert photo pic I showed before.
But actually, it's a teaser for Brawl Stars Android launch.
If I can point your attention to Spike's shadow,
that's where the teaser is.
Ever since Brawl Stars went into beta, every YouTube video
we posted, pretty much every YouTube video,
influencers had posted.
Every Facebook post, pretty much every official Supercell
Reddit post on the Brawl Stars subreddit
had a bunch of, where's Android?
Where's Android?
That was the number one question every time.
We had a lot of followers who didn't even themselves
have an iOS device, but we're either Supercell fans
or just wanted to play the game.
And we're committed enough to come back and ask
for the Android release for months and months and months.
So this smashed down the wall between.
iOS players and their Android friends and Android-owning
friends.
And we actually still have organic growth
ever since this update in some regions
where we don't actually actively acquire new users.
So it's quite amazing what a difference it makes when you
allow people to play together.
We were, for a while before, talking about how well this
game could do in Asia.
And so this was planned as a sort of one-two punch Hail
Mary shot to see if Brawl Stars still had legs
and could be viable.
And yeah, it took us a year.
And what was the result after June 2018?
OK.
I think I broke this slide.
Here we go.
So here's what happened.
We'd been very used to hearing, thank you, Supercell,
on Reddit in a very sarcastic tone.
As you can see in the top comment there,
thank you for ruining such an amazing game.
After the May and June updates, it basically
took a 180 turn, and people were super excited and grateful
for us actually listening to the community
and providing this update.
And with the numbers in Asia looking good,
The game team was energized.
Content creators had a lot more to make videos about.
And everything looked good to go global, take that chance.
But I'm not actually going to talk about that now.
I'm going to leave you there and talk about some takeaways.
from the long beta.
So first of all, I think we made a lot
of nice, innovative designs, both in terms of controls
and in terms of the upgrade progression systems.
And there are still things, you know, people look back on.
Players and game team.
members alike with some nostalgia, there's always a give and take and a compromise when you
decide to iterate and some of the innovations still feel close to heart and might have actually
worked if things turned out differently. However, you shouldn't be
afraid to fall back on proven designs,
as we did both with the controls and the progression.
Everybody in the team agrees that this is the best
Brawl Stars we've had.
The other thing is that looking at retention
to try and gauge how much fun the players are having,
how engaged they are, has its risks,
because.
There's a lot of things that go to such a broad metric
as retention.
And like we experienced with the iterations we made,
we weren't really able to make a big dent or a big bump
with the metrics at any point.
The first metagame iteration was upgrade progression.
Iteration was probably the best we had.
And now this might raise a few questions,
but at least for Supercell games, a lot of players
know that they are playing a beta.
So you have to be cognizant of that.
So player behavior will change if they're unsure about where
the game is going.
If you don't.
release new characters.
That might affect even you cohorts
when they look back at, hey, what's this game like?
A lot of players are very savvy and have been there
before with soft launches, especially
a lot of the more valuable players to you,
the most likely to engage or monetize players.
is.
talked about this, you should implement the most fun features of your game.
The things that you know are the best game experience and try to enhance them
and not just believe that, okay, we've proven this or we know this intrinsically
and we can do something else first and try to bump other stuff first.
These could be such important...
The most important
fun in your game might determine the overall
game experience so much that it ends up masking
other improvements you might make. Now this is an assumption
on my part, but
I firmly believe that if we'd...
focused on social gameplay earlier,
we might have been out of the beta much sooner,
or at least confident that the game is
going to fly much sooner.
And then finally, often when you read posts by your community,
it can seem that they're in an echo chamber,
just shouting out the same thing.
and reacting to minor things that you already know
or you feel like aren't the priority right now.
And this does happen.
But that doesn't mean that the community is always wrong.
Actually, the community was quite right in our case.
So it was a compass that constantly
pointed towards Android.
And it just took us a while to navigate there.
That's my takeaways.
But wait, there's more.
Tomorrow, Frank is going to give a talk on that final push,
well, including the May update, some of the team dynamics.
of how Supercell was able to push Brawl Stars out
and that final push towards global launch and beyond.
So please go and check it out.
Thanks for listening.
All right, any questions?
Yeah, could you go into the friends changes a little bit?
I mean, you said you had room codes and went to friends list,
but it was kind of like you went quick over that.
Could you go into that a little more detail?
Sure, so we added, I kind of quickly mentioned this,
but we added a way to keep playing with friends,
keep playing with strangers
who you'd met in the random matchmaking queue.
and then added them to a suggestion list where you could actually add them as permanent in-game
friends on a friends list and then invite them easily to your game rooms in the future.
Yeah, hi. I have already every Supercell game on this pad.
Oh, but for this, this Brawl Stars game, I'm a dead player already.
Not your fault, maybe. I'm too busy.
Okay. So I was playing your game earlier last year,
and I think there is a period, actually you have advertisement which can double the loot boxes.
and I was there and collected a lot of these rewards but suddenly I think it's cancelled.
Do you think it's unsuccessful or it's like you try to find another way to get income from this
game? So you're talking about the coin or token doublers? Yeah, I think you tried but you cancelled
Yeah, we thought there were two different systems that were overlapping at that stage,
and we decided to keep just one.
The one that was more easily understood by players.
You know, not the time-based, we got rid of the time-based one
and kept the one that had a very clear...
you know, a system where this is how many coins or tokens you'll keep doubling in the future.
So yeah, it was also not that well received by players.
We didn't get so many sales on the time-based one.
Hello, thanks for the talk.
On my side I played a lot of Brawl Stars with Swain locally because I think it's really important to communicate to play effectively.
But you don't have any in-game way of communicating, no emotes, no voice recording.
Is this something that you have tested and cut or is it something that you plan to integrate in the game?
Yeah, it's another thing we've been talking about for a long time.
I think it would go into that social gameplay section that we were very slow in starting to implement or improve.
Thanks.
For me, I had a question about the general vision
and design philosophy towards the Elder game.
Because it's something I found lacking in both Clash Royale
and Brawl Stars, that once you get your cards,
if you don't want to rank on the leaderboard,
you really don't have something to do.
And you definitely see that in your version
of the progression bar, where after about 1,000 trophies,
there's just very little content that you get from it.
So yeah, I just wanted to know your design thoughts
on the Elder game.
I'm not sure if I understood.
Can you rephrase?
Sure.
So after you progress a certain amount in the game,
and you've got all the characters,
maybe you've got a couple of the star powers,
there's really nothing for you to do because you're
kind of done.
All right.
So we're looking at ways to give you more sort of.
More goals when you're climbing in trophies,
instead of focusing just on the stuff you can collect
from loot boxes or buying from the shop.
So ever since the May update with the trophy road,
that's been a focus for us.
And now we're looking at ways to make it more sustainable,
where it doesn't feel like you hit the ceiling.
So we're looking at different options for that.
And definitely the...
the focus is now going to be on the trophies next.
And obviously we're going to add more characters and add more...
Well, obviously with every character there's going to be another star power.
And so the content will keep coming
and also we're looking at ways to improve the trophy grind as well.
Got it. Cool, thank you.
Thanks.
So thank you a lot for your talk, it was very interesting.
I'm Marie, I work on The Elder Scrolls Blades,
and it was really interesting to see all the adventures you had with landscape and portrait.
I kind of gave a talk about that on Monday,
and as you may know, Bethesda decided, because there was no clear winner,
For very similar reasons than the ones you said, we decided to allow players to basically
flip their phones when they want, so we removed the orientation lock, and I was wondering
if you had considered it and why you didn't retain the idea.
Right.
So for Brawl Stars being a competitive multiplayer game, it's...
really important that the players are on a level playing field.
Yeah.
And even now we have to do some compromises when it comes to
very wide aspect ratios,
where some of the screen is covered,
you don't have vision there.
If we had both portrait and landscape at the same time,
we would basically need to have a square in the middle
and lose most of the screen real estate
to be able to make it.
fair and even for everyone. It makes a lot of sense. Thank you. Thanks.
I had a question about your early internal playtesting.
Yes.
How many characters and modes you needed to put in there
before internal playtesting started to be a lot more fun?
Was it probably a lot more than one?
And so that's the question.
Right.
So we went to beta with 16 characters.
I think the early, well, you saw actually the character
selection screen.
there earlier on.
And I could cheat.
But even before beta, internally.
Yeah, so these are both internal playtests here.
We had six characters in this playtest.
And in this one, we had, let me just start it.
Only five.
So.
And this was the game mode in most of the playtests
internally.
We only added a second game mode, I think, for the final
internal playtest.
And one clarification question.
It sounded like you were saying that all of these
changes to the meta and controls barely moved the
metrics, and it was really the social changes that
moved everything.
Yeah.
Well, social we can only assume because, well, even
after we improved the social gameplay, we didn't see a
massive bump in the previous beta country.
So I don't know if we burned out our user base, what
exactly happened there.
But luckily we launched in Asia as well and got a fresh new place,
especially in Singapore where we had amazing numbers compared to before.
So yeah, one of the progression iterations did give a nice bump in day 30 retention though.
Okay, cool. Thank you.
Hi, so if I'm understanding your monetization and progression systems appropriately,
it seems like a core part of it is unlocking new characters and then upgrading those characters,
which seems to be a little bit at odds with, at least for new players,
the gameplay of wanting to master a character,
which for a skill-based game seems like it would be more of an element
than games with the lower skill ceiling in the industry.
Do you guys see that tension as a problem to be solved, something to improve,
or are you happy with where it's at?
So the question is about the amount of skill cap we built in?
The idea that some players are going to want to sort of master a character, play a solo or master, versus unlocking new ones.
I got it, thank you.
One more question, OK.
So I'll try to answer this quickly and give one more.
So we see this happening, and it's not the optimal way
to play the game.
Actually, you'll get a lot less rewards and progression
in the game if you do that.
So we're hoping that the system where you share trophies
Well, each character has individual trophies,
and it's easier to progress early on with every new character.
Eventually, it will drive people not to main a certain character
or focus on a certain character,
but try to play the game in a different way
from maybe what they're used to,
because the game itself has a wide variety of different events,
and you...
should learn to play at least, you know, several, four or five archetypes of character
to be able to be competitive and play in a team game.
Hope that answers your question.
I have more, but I'm going to take it.
OK.
Thank you.
Yeah, hi.
Hi.
Great talk today.
Thanks.
We already know that you have a soft launch for a long time
for these games.
And we also know that you queue a lot of games
before even they come out in your company.
Sure.
And so my question is, when it comes to the decision,
will it continue to?
make adjustment or just give up and move on to another game, what factor do you consider?
Before going into beta, the team decides if they feel like the game has a chance.
Also, the internal testing company playables,
they give very important feedback
from the whole company to the team as a sanity check
to see if the company shares that feeling
or the other employees share that feeling.
But essentially, it's the team who decides to go to beta.
So obviously,
we trust, it has to be based on trust, so we trust every team to be realistic in their
expectations and if the team feels strongly that the game is ready for soft launch, we
go to soft launch and then after that basically the players decide.
Thank you.
Okay, thank you very much for coming.