Hi, everyone.
Oh, good.
Mic's not working.
So yeah, I'm Sebastian.
Thank you, Dave.
Thank you, Dave and Steve, for inviting me to come talk at
GDC.
Like the big text over there says, I'm a senior designer at
BioWare, and I was most recently the lead combat
design on Dragon Age Inquisition.
And a lot of my time I spent working on the AI for the
game.
So before we get really rolling here, can I get a quick show of
hands, who here has played Inquisition? Okay, good, good.
And who's played some of the other Dragon Age games, DA2,
Origin, okay, lots of fans in the crowd. And also this is my
first time at GDC, and I'm just curious, who else is here for
the first time, are there students just trying to get in?
Okay, we're going to have some fun today.
Great to see everyone here. Still a few people coming in at
the back. A disclaimer, because this seems to be a tradition, a
lot of the screen shots and art that you'll see in here are
scratch or they have debug renders in them and are not
representative of shipped game. The game shipped almost a year
and a half ago now. So I don't know if that's a big concern
anymore, but it seems to be a thing that people say when they
do these presentations.
So let's talk about Dragon Age Inquisition. It is a fantasy
RPG from Bioware. And the big thing about Inquisition for us
is that it was our first title on Frostbite.
which is a really neat engine that's an internally a technology.
We moved from our classic Eclipse engine that we used to make DAO and DA2.
And yeah, Dragon Age Inquisition is the first RPG on Frostbite.
It's our first Bioware title on Frostbite.
And...
Who here has been through an engine transition before? Show
of hands. Okay. So yeah. Yeah. So you know what that's like. So
big challenges ahead. When we started working on this back in 2011.
It's also the third game in the Dragon Age series, which meant
that although we were starting fresh with tech, we had already
established a world and a story and characters that players
already knew and loved, and so we had a lot to live up to with
this game.
And we also knew that we were going to be shipping on five
platforms, not just the PC and the Xbox one and PS4, but we
were also going to be targeting the Xbox 360 and the PS3, which
meant that everything we were going to do was going to have to
scale. So...
a lot of constraints, a lot of things that sort of, you know,
influenced us when we were starting development. And from
the player's point of view, the biggest change that we made for
Inquisition was that we were adding open exploration to the
game. So that was going to be a big change for us when we were
developing the game.
as we learn to make the game deal with these big areas.
And that's going to feature prominently
in the challenges that we talk about today.
So, when we talk about building the AI for Inquisition,
the first thing we talk about is building creatures.
Dragon Age has a huge variety of creatures.
Big ones like this dragon, and giants,
and big, big creatures.
We also have a lot of little creatures
like this cute little nug.
Lots of little wilderness creatures
to fill out those big open areas.
Some creatures will fight by your side.
These are some friendly templars.
But most of the creatures we talk about,
they just want to eat your face.
So.
We also need to talk about building AI for party members.
And this is going to be another big theme that we talk about
today. We have a variety of roles and capabilities. Dragon
Age has always been about the party that you travel with. You
don't go alone. You have melee fighters and you have ranged
snipers. You have mages. You have indestructible tanks. A
huge variety of capabilities and powers. 90 some different
unique abilities.
And just like in the previous games, the player has the
ability to switch control between any character in the
party at any time, meaning that from the system's point of view
any character can go from being player controlled to AI
controlled in the space of a heartbeat. And that's a
particular challenge we have to deal with from the system's
point of view. Additionally,
the player can pause the game, pull the camera out, move around
the battlefield and give direct orders to any of the characters
in their party at the same time and watch how that scenario
plays out. And we'll talk about how the A.I. accommodates that
kind of control as well.
And when we're building, because we're starting on a new engine,
in addition to building the content and the creatures and
the party members and the abilities and the combat system,
we also had to build up our tools and workflow. As
developers, we know that iteration speed is key to
improving quality. The faster you can see your changes in the
game, the faster you can evaluate them and see whether
you need to improve further or whether you've achieved what
you're trying to hit.
So we knew that we wanted to take advantage of the engine's
data-driven pipeline to be able to do live tweaking in our
tool set and see those results in-game as we were playing and
editing and iterating on gameplay.
For our AI, there were two related workflows, actually,
that we were working on.
One is for combat designers who are working on building out.
the AI for creatures and party members and building all the
pieces. And we also needed to worry about work flows for our
level designers who had to shape the AI behavior in the
environments that they were building and the plots and
stories that they were trying to tell. So today's focus in this
context.
is going to talk about two big themes, as I mentioned. One is
adapting to big open areas for game play in a way that we've
never done at BioWare or on Dragon Age before. And the other
is looking at how we built up the party AI systems to support
our complex and customizable party members so that they can
support the player.
And this is a retrospective. It's been, as I say, almost a
year and a half since we shipped Inquisition. So I'm going to
try to tell the story of development and some of the
roadblocks we hit and the way that we crossed some of those
challenges.
So hopefully by the end of our talk today, you'll be able to
take some of these solutions to solve your own related problems
and maybe cut out some surprises by taking advantage of the
trial and error that we went through bringing this game up.
So we got a big box labeled frostbite. We cracked it open
and what was inside? Well, thankfully we knew that we
wouldn't have to solve pathfinding.
We got a path finding middleware called nav power that came with
an integration into frostbite. So we have path mesh and
navigation for our characters. You can see that big sea of
green polygons over there on the display. So that gave us a
really good starting point. We could get characters moving
around and following each other around without having to do any
of that base level work for ourselves.
On the other side, we also were able to take advantage of
another EA team who had built a decision tree architecture.
And this is where we would build the vast majority of our
logic from the combat design side.
It came with a nice visual node editor that
we were able to use.
And we, as a game team, as a combat team, we built out a huge
library of conditional evaluations to test things in
the world and to be able to give our AI the information it
needed to make interesting choices. And also a set of
interfaces to drive game systems. And that's primarily in
our game where am I going to move, how am I going to move
there, and then what abilities do I want to use? Well, what's
an ability?
And ability is a concept that we brought forward from past
Dragon Age games that gave us a consistent approach to defining
gameplay actions. So for players and party members, abilities are
explicit. This is something that you buy as you level up. You go
and you buy abilities with points, you put them on your bar
and they're something you can use. And over the course of the
game, you're getting new abilities, you're upgrading them
and these are the things that you do in game.
We also use this, in addition to using it for party members, we
also use the ability framework to define our NPCs. So
everything that an NPC character does is also defined as an
ability even though it doesn't have that player facing
interface in the level up GUI with the ability trees. So this
includes, as I say, obvious things. I'm going to throw a
fireball. I'm going to taunt that guy over there and get his
aggro. I want to dodge out of the way. Those are all active
abilities.
But some things that aren't player facing as abilities like
jumping, drinking a potion, twitches that NPCs would play,
I'm going to yell at you from across the map, those are all
implemented as abilities under the hood. So this gives us a
consistent approach to how we define gameplay actions. And
this is going to be very important when we talk about
ability choosing. So...
We've got our pathfinding system.
We've got a decision tree.
We've got a framework to build our actions and abilities on.
Now we need to actually tackle making all these things go.
We'd never made a game with these Frostbite tools.
We'd never had open our exploration areas.
We knew that we had a big scope, lots of things
that we had to build.
And so we wanted to make sure that we had a consistent
approach to the way that our AI evaluates and the way that
decisions are made so that everyone on the team had the
same idea of how things were going to work at the most basic
level. And we wanted to make sure that, you know, even across
creatures and party members, because everything is running
under the same AI system, we wanted to make sure that
everyone followed the same basic set of rules. And this is what
we came up with. So we'll walk through a little example. So
I'm going to run AI in our example here on this character
who's standing in front. And those four glowy purple fellas
in the back there, those are our enemies. So the first thing our
AI does in the core evaluation loop, the first thing we're
going to do is pick a target. So that guy. That guy right there.
The next thing that's going to happen is that we're going to
choose what ability we want to use. So we picked flanking
strike down there in the right-hand corner. That's a
melee ability, so we know that we're going to have to move,
because we're going to use our daggers, we're going to have to
move in order to be able to execute that. And...
Once we've moved into position, then we can play the animation,
apply the damage, do all the fun stuff of actually using that
ability. So that's the core decision-making loop and action
loop that every AI-controlled character in the game basically
follows. There's a few exceptions, but typically you
pick your target, you pick your ability that you want to use,
you move if you have to to accomplish it, and then you
execute it by firing the animation, and away we go.
So with this in place, as a team, as a development team, we
have a consistent approach to AI evaluation, supports both party
members and creatures. Between party members and creatures, how
they do that choosing. For example,
Party members have a player customization element that they
can use for how they're going to pick targets. Whereas
creatures use an aggro system to determine who they're
targeting. But despite having minor differences in how they do
these steps, everyone follows the same basic logic pattern.
Now, not every ability, not everything you want to do, can
be accomplished by directly moving to your target and
smacking them in the face, as we did in our previous example.
The pathfinding layer, as I mentioned, gave us move to
point and follow leader.
So with that, as long as we know where we want to go,
we've got that solved.
But a lot of our creatures and our party behaviors need more
complex movement.
We wanted to be able to create more interesting patterns,
both to give life to our creatures
and fill out the big open spaces that we had
in a way that meets player expectations,
and also be able to create interesting gameplay challenges
without requiring designers to hand-build
specific location picking and movement behaviors every time.
So we wanted reusable abstractions.
We came up with a system we call Movement Behaviors.
So these are reusable, parameterized, you can see a big
example from the editor over there on the screen.
Parameterized chunks of behavior that a creature can run
one at a time and that gets, excuse me, that puts them in a
position to be able to do interesting things in gameplay
without having the designer to manually specify how they're
going to compute their targets and the move positions
every time.
So, an example of one of these is stay at range,
you can see over there, and it's parameterized
so that the designer can say, that's the guy
or the thing that you want to focus on,
and you're going to pick a position.
somewhere around that object or that character and hang out
there even if that target moves. And it gives the designer the
flexibility even to say, okay, I want you to be in a flanking
position. So you're going to try to move around into the back
arc of that character. Or I want you to, you know, sort of
shuffle around and be a little more dynamic rather than picking
a point and sticking in it.
Additionally, we have a movement behavior
that lets characters find cover objects
that have been marked up in the world
so that, for example, some of our ranged creatures
can respond to their environment a little more
and feel like they're living in the scene
without level designers having given them
specific movement commands.
our prey flee behavior is implemented in the same way
where even if we have a creature,
one of those little nugs who's fleeing
from three different predators,
the creature just needs to run the flee behavior
and it goes and it looks and finds the right path
that's going to take him away from those predators
regardless of where their positions are in the world.
And even hold position.
which you'd think would be pretty simple, it gets a reusable parameterized movement
behavior so it can sit in that slot and we can do things with it like tell someone to
stand in one place but track a target even though that target might be moving around
the level. So with this system in place, we now have
tools that allow creatures to move around in ways that are both interesting for game
plays for game play. And also ‑‑
meet player expectations for wildlife. Predator prey
behaviors, aggression, circling wolves, that kind of thing. The
next problem we had to deal with is around the nature of these
big open zones themselves. In our past games, combat tended to
happen in fairly enclosed spaces. If there were hostile
creatures where you were, there was going to be a fight, and
that fight was going to end with a stack of bodies on one side or
the other.
and open exploration zones change the rules. In DA2 in this
example here, there's no walking away. That train coming over the
hill, they're going to chase you forever until you run into the
area boundary and then you're going to fight them and there's
going to be a stack of bodies on one side or the other. However,
when you're in a big area like one of our explore zones,
The player often has the chance to try to walk away from a
fight, either because creatures, you know, they're
just defending their home. And they'll leave you alone if you
walk away far enough. Or perhaps you don't even want to
get involved in that fight. You need to be able to walk up and
determine whether you want to even engage that battle or not.
In addition to those sort of gameplay facing concerns, we
also had very pragmatic technical reasons for having to
assert more control over where fights could happen. Because we
had to stream these big giant areas. And there's a risk if the
player can kite those hurlocks all the way from their origin
point, then they're going to get streamed out because they belong
to that part of the terrain where the player was. And now
we've streamed them out. We've even streamed out the terrain
underneath where they came in.
We could also get into bad situations where if you can
manage to taunt enough creatures on to you and attract the
attention of enough of these encounters, then you could run
out of memory budget. And remember, we're dealing with
Gen 3 memory budget here. So things were pretty tight.
before we had a solution for dealing with this.
And in addition to being bad for performance,
as I say, this could lead to really frustrating
gameplay situations and we needed level designers
to have tools to be able to control
and build the specific kind of experience
that matches the themes and the story
and the gameplay challenges that we're trying to create.
So.
Here's an example of a very simple encounter that we built
in our level. And there's the tether volume that the designer
has dropped in on top of it. So on the AI side, inside our
tether system, we have three simple rules. And the first
rule, as you can see, is that you can't leave. Any creature
who's attached to a tether, their movement behaviors are
aware of that tether zone.
and they won't pick points. They'll never pick a destination
point that's outside that tether box. So the creature should
never be voluntarily moving outside its tether zone. In
addition, any target inside my tether box is better than any
target outside the tether box. The aggro system is aware of
tethers. So that a creature
is able to choose targets that are less likely to drag them out
of their target box. And if they know that the creature that
they're looking at is outside their tether zone, then they can
choose to do things like walk home rather than continuing to
engage or chase a creature who's outside their area of
operation. And the third rule is that if you ever end up
outside, you can't do anything.
whether it's because the designer changed your active
tether box in game play or if you got knocked out of your
tether zone by a combat effect. If you ever end up outside,
stop what you're doing and run home. Run back toward your spawn
point or your tether point until you're back inside your box
before you can do anything else.
And so with these rules in place and the editor tools to support them, level designers could build encounters with reliable expectations of how creatures were going to behave and how they were going to move around.
And related problem we had was where tether volumes solve the problem of where creatures are allowed to go in a really broad stroke sense.
We had hazards where creatures shouldn't go.
that despite being pathable, despite being things that you
could run through, you really shouldn't be standing in those
areas. You want to avoid those fires on the ground, barriers,
traps, all kinds of stuff that in inquisition with our big
organic environments, we had a lot more of this kind of ambient
hazard.
In DA2 we didn't really have this kind of thing happen a lot.
If there was a fire on the ground it was usually there for
one of two reasons. One is because it was a specific
gameplay challenge that you as the player were expected to
deal with.
So don't stand in the fire. Well, if your guys are in the
fire, pull them out. And the other reason or the other
possibility was that it was something that you had placed
down that creatures should be standing in and taking damage
rather than very smartly running out and negating your AOE
attack. So...
The other twist with inquisition where we have more of these
organic hazards is sometimes they can appear spontaneously.
Things can catch fire. The dragon can light areas of the
ground on fire in combat and something that was safe five
seconds ago, a good place to stand, can become somewhere that
you really don't want to stand for an extended period of time.
So we needed a way to keep AI creatures out of these areas.
The first thing we did was add a pathfinding obstacle. So
You can see that big yellow chunk superimposed on top of
the bright green nav mesh.
And that kept creatures from ambiently wandering into the
fire and going, ow, hot, ow, hot.
And that was OK.
It meant that creatures wouldn't discretionarily walk
in, or they would avoid it on their way around the world.
But we needed something a little bit stronger because as I say,
these things could appear under your feet and we needed a way
to motivate the AI to actually move if they ended up inside one
of these. And so we created this tool we call a fear zone. And
the fear zone, unlike the tether zone, only has one rule. If
you're in the fear zone, go somewhere else. So inside the
prefab editor for our ground fire here, you can see we drop
in a fear zone, which is just a spherical bubble.
that says to the AI, if you're ever inside here, run out.
And you can see in the debug draw there in the middle of
gameplay, it shows up as a kind of a blue sphere.
Hopefully it's contrasting enough on the display that you
can see.
Varek is standing in the middle of the fire there and the AI is
giving him a cue telling him that he should move out of that
fire rather than standing in it despite me having ordered him to
go in there five seconds ago for the purpose of demonstration.
So with fear zones, designers have a tool now to motivate
creatures under AI control to move away from some area of
danger. And this actually works using the same movement
behaviors as the prey flee behavior that I talked about
earlier. So we have a consistent set of tools for saying, okay,
anything that you're trying to get away from, here's a way to
pick a point and move away from that direction.
And as it turned out, this fear zone tool was also very useful
for our open world game play in that it gave us a tool to drop
down around, you know, camps and settlements to keep ambient
hostile wildlife from wandering through the middle of the
village.
And this created a problem that I call standoff in bear town.
So this is going to require a little explanation, a little
background. For those of you who have played inquisition, you
know that bears are tough. And the reason that bears are tough
is that bears are balanced for a four on one fight. Because the
bears have to stand up against a party of four rather than
rolling over like most of the other creatures that are
designed to be encountered in groups.
And there's a corner of the hinterlands explore zone that is
just packed with bears. I called it bear town during
development. And there is luckily there's an inquisition
camp. There's a rest and resupply area in that part of
the map where you can go after fighting a bunch of bears and
getting slapped around and, you know, revive your party members,
resupply your potions, get healed up.
And the bears are kept out of the camp by the fear zone that
we drop in around the camp. So you can see there's a big 30
meter bubble around the camp area in the level editor there
that keeps the bears out. If they try to come inside, they
hit the fear zone and they leave.
but the problem with this is that if they're actually trying
to actively move into the fear zone because you're in there,
then they ended up bouncing off the edge of the fear zone and
oscillating and wobbling back and forth there. That's no good.
Meanwhile, the player, as long as that bear is there and
hostile, he's not going to be able to move into the fear zone
The player is not allowed to interact with any of those
resupply items. They're not allowed to do anything
interesting in camp. So they're stuck there. They're inside. The
bear can't come in, but they can't leave. They can't fast
travel. There's no way. So they're stuck. So
The first thing we did was we changed the AI so that the AI
is blinded to anyone who's in a fear zone that they're
responsible for. So the bear now can no longer see you. The
bear wasn't trying to bounce off the fear zone anymore. You just
sit there. Staring at you. Waiting. So we changed the AI
We ended up having to clarify the game rules so that the
party was allowed to drop out of combat.
Even if there was a hostile bear there, as long as he
wasn't actively targeting somebody in your party, that
you would be allowed to use the camp facilities despite
there being a bear sitting out there waiting for
you to come back.
And by solving these problems, we were able to achieve a
pretty good game play balance between having aggressive,
threatening, dangerous wildlife and basic player
survivability. We had to give them a way out. Now, let's talk
about a problem specific to our player party path finding.
Relative to our previous games, we have a much more open and
permissive movement model. You can jump over gaps. You can
jump onto obstacles. You can scramble your way up onto
things. And in some cases, you can find your way off of path
finding. So you can see an example here, that bright green
nav mesh.
sweeps around and everyone else in my party down in the right
hand side of the screen is standing on the nav mesh, but I
managed to jump my inquisitor in the left hand side up there on
an island where there's no path finding data. Which is good
because it means that the player isn't stuck.
trying to use physics movement to jump up on to obstacles and
get to somewhere that it looks like they should be able to get
the player's movement isn't constrained by the AI
parameters. But this is a problem for us when we're trying
to get everyone else in the party to follow you. Because the
player can go places that the AI just has no way of going. And
so this led to a couple key scenarios that we had to solve.
Here's another example. You can see I'm controlling the
inquisitor there in the middle. And you can see I'm up on a
rock in the middle of the screen where there's no path finding
data. If I switch to another party member, like iron bull
over there on the side, then I can grab control of him, I can
drive away, and I can leave my inquisitor up there on the rock.
And
well, they have no way of getting naturally back down off
that rock because there's no pathing data. So what happens in
our game is when you switch characters, whenever a character
becomes AI controlled, they get teleported. And for the sake of
player experience, usually this gets covered by the camera
transition or in really severe cases, there's a fade through
black to cover that teleport up.
and if you played the game and you never noticed this
happening, success. But this gives us the reliability that we
need to know so that even if I move and switch characters, no
one in my party is left in a situation where they are off the
nav mesh and stuck. So whenever a party member becomes AI
controlled, teleport to the nearest point on the nav mesh
and ideally the player never notices this happening.
The other situation that we can get into involves traversing
terrain that the AI can't cover. So you can see in this
example, I'm down there at the bottom of the screen. I've just
jumped off the cliff. And I left my party members behind.
And what this means is that when I land at the bottom of the
cliff, if you could see them right now, they're up there,
they're behind the cliff wall, they're going to start taking
the path that goes around and coming back down the switch
backs to get back to where I've just gotten to.
I mean, you probably shouldn't jump off that cliff.
You probably take damage.
Hurts when you fall.
But.
still I'm now in a position where I can get a really big
head start and if they get stuck on other path finding data or if
the path is long enough, I can outrun them and I can
potentially run far enough away that they're outside the
streaming chunk and then the ground streams out underneath
them and they're in for a world of pain. So...
If the player ever outruns the AI, we have a leash distance
teleport that we implemented. Party members have a maximum
distance that they're allowed to be. We teleport them in. And
again, when that happens, we try to cover this by bringing them
in behind the camera. Because if I'm running, I'm in front of
the camera. Everyone else, if they're following me, is
probably behind the camera anyway. And so this happens.
Again, if you never saw this happen in the game, success.
And in some situations, we disable or we expand the range
of the tether. If it's a puzzle area that relies on separating
your party members and positioning them in different
parts of the level, typically we know you're going to come in
and go out through a known access so we can gate and say,
okay, it's safe here to turn off the tethering because we know
that you're in this specific area. And in combat, to give
more flexibility for positioning your characters and giving you
more tactical options, we grow that range.
change. But at the end of the day, with these fail safes in
place, as in elegant as they may be, if you notice them
happening, we had confidence that party members couldn't get
stranded by technical weaknesses in the path finding system. The
other problem that I want to talk about here about party in
the big open world is our party aggression rules.
Our party when we started had fairly opportunistic targeting.
They would see somebody who was fightable, based on the rules
from our previous titles, if they're fightable, if they're
in a hostile faction, I'm going to fight them. But, again, we
wanted to give the player control over how they would
engage in these kind of situations without your party
necessarily picking a fight that you weren't interested or ready
to take part in.
in a fairly target rich environment. There's wildlife
everywhere. They're all fightable. You can go hunt nugs
if you really, really need nugskin leather. But what you
probably don't want is your party running off and hunting
nugs on your behalf when you were trying to accomplish
something.
So that's more obnoxious than punishing, bringing the bears
down on your face. But the party shouldn't be spontaneously
attacking things. We need to put that control back in the hands
of the player. So we came up with some rules for party
aggression.
which says that you're not allowed to engage. You're not
allowed to take the first swing or use an offensive power until
someone in the party has done damage. And you can see I can't
do damage until somebody has done damage, which means the
player has to be making that choice. Or if somebody in the
party is taking damage, which means that the fight is already
on me, I've been jumped, and the party is allowed then to engage
spontaneously without waiting for a go order.
There's another test that takes place here to only target
creatures that are targeting someone else in the party.
because again in inquisition, especially in hinterlands if
you play this, when you go into that zone, you see groups of
other creatures that are both hostile to you. There's mages,
there's templars, there's bandits and they'll be fighting
each other. There will be bandits fighting bears, et
cetera. And they're having a little fight out in the distance.
And previously the AI would go, yeah, they're hostile. They're
in combat.
going to go at them. And we need to make sure that even if you
were allowed to engage, even if you were allowed to pick a fight
then once that fight was over, your party members wouldn't take
off and go bloodlust on that group over there if you weren't
ready to engage them. And so with these rules in place, the
player now has the control that they need over how their party
members under AI control engage in these open world zones. Now,
I want to talk about how we solved one of the biggest
challenges with our party AI in Inquisition.
around ability selection by creating what we call the
behavior decision system or BDS. So if you hear me talk about
BDS, behavior decision system, same thing. And the challenge
is that we have a lot of abilities on these creatures.
The party members can have up to 30 some different active
abilities per class and they can have up to eight of them mapped
and loaded on any given character at any given time.
The player is unlocking these as you play through the game.
We're adding and removing abilities from characters.
And when we started building our static decision trees for
building out our party AI, we realized that we had a couple
problems. First, we had a technical problem. So you can
see here, this is an example of something we would have started
with where I have a sequence and I'm going to choose and I'm
going to say, OK, can I do long shot?
Yes, I can do long shot. Long shot is a good idea. Second
choice, can I do stealth? If I didn't want to do long shot, can
I use my stealth ability? And so on down the line. Which, again,
we had a technical problem in that we couldn't add and remove
abilities from this data structure in a really good way
because things had to come in in an order and they had to be
somehow slotted into the hierarchy.
So we tried this next. We said, okay, let's add all the
abilities. So there's a master rogue ability table that says,
you know, that has all of the abilities that this character
could have ever. And then we're going to conditionalize them so
that when they, if they're not loaded, then we're just not
going to take those paths. But we still end up with a
conceptual problem where
Long shot might be a good idea.
It might be a good, you know, it's reasonable,
the right range, whatever.
But we might be in a situation where throwing blades
is actually a better choice to make at this point in time.
And so either we have to be very specific,
we have to build the evaluations in this structure so that.
they're very specific and I'm only using long shot when it's
absolutely the best thing I could do and it's not
potentially worse than anything else that could happen down the
line. Or we need a different approach. And we thought, well,
what we'd really like to be able to do is say, okay, we're just
going to evaluate all of our abilities. We're going to bring
everything in. We're going to rank everything. We're going to
find what the best option is. And then we're going to do that
one.
But this required changing our architecture.
And thus the BDS was born.
So the behavior decision system splits our AI evaluation
into two phases.
The first thing we do is evaluate all our options.
And then the second thing we do is execute
whatever the best choice was.
And so this means that every ability itself specifies two
sets of logic. One is the evaluation, which says why or
when it's a good time to use this ability. And it also
specifies a chunk of execution logic that says, okay, once I've
chosen to do this, I need to move or not to get into range
and then execute.
and we'll walk through an example here. So this is the
evaluation tree taken directly out of the level editor or the
rather the game editor for that long shot ability. And there's
some preamble stuff off to the left-hand side that basically
says is this a viable ability right now? Is it off cool down?
Is it disabled? Is there any reason why it's a bad idea to
use this right now? Okay. We've dealt with that. So we're going
to give ourselves 20 points. Right up.
in the first slot there. We're going to give ourselves 20
points because this is a pretty good ability to use right now.
Now, the next thing that we're going to check, because long
shot in the game rules says that it's better the further away
you are from your target when you're using it. So we're going
to check and say if I'm at medium range for my target, I'm
going to give myself five points. And if I'm even further
away, then I can give myself another five points so that I
give a full 30-point score for this ability. And we'll talk
about what that means in just one second. And then I'm also
going to be able to give myself an additional 10 points.
if my target or rather if this ability has been set for this
character by the player to be something that they prefer this
character to use. So.
Once that happens, we score that ability and we realize that we
needed a set of rules as we were building out these evaluations
so that we could be consistent in how these things are being
applied. So you can see passive movement, things that just move
me around the battlefield are the lowest priority. Basic
attacks are always sort of, you know, they're always a pretty
good idea. If I can use an ability, I should use that over
a basic attack.
support abilities get a bonus score. They get a little bit of
a priority bump. They start at a 25 baseline rather than 20
because typically they're things that either need to respond to a
bad situation that's come up or something that I want to use
ahead of combat at the start of things to repair. And so
they get a little bit of a priority bump to make sure they
come out first or they come out when they need to. And then we
have reaction abilities that really need to be used on time
and we'll cover those specifically. But those are
things like blocks and dodges that have specific frame
requirements around when they need to be used in order to be
useful at all. So you can see this is kind of how things get
ranked and rated and we build all our evaluation trees in this
framework.
Then we break down inside those ranges 10 points, that 10 point
range, 5 points for medium range, 5 points for long range,
for long shot, but we have 10 points of dynamic range for
context, is this a good time or a bad time to use this ability,
and then we have that 10 point tie breaker where the player can
put their thumb on the scale and say I want this one more often.
which means that we have a 20 point range for pretty much all
of the categories of ability. And we've completed our
evaluation now. We've gone off, we've run long shot, we've run
a bunch of other things that we have on this character. Basic
attack comes in at 10. Poison weapons, we ran our evaluator,
it came back at 25. Caltrops came back at 22. And full draw.
is in our ability list, but it's on cool down right now, so it
just evaluates out. It gets clipped by that preamble. Healing
potion, we evaluated it and it just said, no, I don't need to
use this right now. I'm at full health. It's okay. So we can
have evaluations that just punch out early on without even
returning a score. But when we look at the scores, we say,
okay, long shot is the best choice right now.
So let's use that. So we move into execution. So the next
part of the AI update, we start running the execution tree for
long shot, which handles the movement and execution part of
that AI decision loop. We've picked our target, we've picked
our ability, and now we're moving and executing. So we're
going to test to see if we have range.
And if we have line of sight to use the ability, and if we
don't, we're going to move until we get those.
We're just going to move towards the character,
assuming that at some point we're going to achieve line of
sight, and we're going to get into the right range.
Once we get those, then we fall all the way through to
the end there, and we're able to actually fire the ability
itself, play the animation.
fire the projectile, do the impact, all the good stuff that comes with actually using this ability.
And then in the bottom right hand corner,
we just make a note to set ourselves to hold position so that we don't keep moving toward that character once we've achieved line
of sight and the appropriate range to use.
And it's important to note that while this is running, if I
didn't have line of sight and range when I started, while the
execution tree is updating and moving me toward the target, I'm
still able to run that evaluation. I'm constantly
reevaluating all my choices. So if something even better, if
some better option comes up off of cool down or if I end up in a
situation where I need to react quickly, as long as I haven't
actually triggered the animation yet,
I'm still in a position where I'm able to react to those changing circumstances and start evaluating a different execution tree for a different ability on the next update.
So, let's see, where are we at here?
And an added benefit of the way that we implemented BDS
as a general system for scoring behaviors is that we can also
add movement to the priority evaluation. We can use an
evaluator to check whether the character is in combat and apply
different movement parameters by using the behavior tree controls
over movement.
and for example in exploration characters have a tighter
follow so that they stay closer to you so they're there when
you need them whereas in combat characters can hang back a
little more and spread out so that your melee character can
lead and your ranged characters and your casters can fall back
behind.
The other way that this works that was a big advantage is
that we were able to use this for things like tether and fear
zone where those behaviors can come in and they can override
in the priority system anything else that character is doing.
They can come in at priority 100 and just stomp anything else
that that character is doing until their conditions are
resolved. Until I get back inside my tether, I'm doing
nothing else. Fear zones, as I say, work the same way. So
recapping, behavior decision system.
I can add and remove abilities now at run time.
And I can do that without having to pay attention to the
evaluation order, because we've come up with a scoring
system.
that means that the right ability can be scored regardless
of whether it's the first or the last thing that gets
evaluated. And we've done it in a way that leverages the
existing library of functionality. We get a big win
because we've built this library of decision tree evaluators and
task nodes and functionality to build really complex logic and
we can still use that in the exec parts. And we can also, you
know, we have a whole set of target picking.
stuff that happens just in every AI update. So this integrates
directly into the decision tree architecture that we've built.
So we have a powerful tool for AI decision making. It allows
party members to effectively choose between a whole array of
very situational abilities and make pretty good choices.
I did say that I was going to call out reaction abilities
specifically because they had an extra piece of logic that we
needed to build for them.
We introduced this new class of abilities in Inquisition.
We didn't really have these in DA2 or in Origins.
And their active reactions to damage that's coming in
that allows you to actively counter that before you take
that damage. And so there are things like parries, which are
a reaction that gives you an advantage from our point of
view. So I'm going to get a hit back out of it. A block is a
reaction that's going to counter that damage, but it's still
going to leave me in place. And then the most extreme is a
dodge where I'm going to react by actually getting out of the
way of that hit.
before it lands, but it's the most costly in terms of it
loses my battle position and now I'm going to have to
reposition and collect myself. So we want to be able to use
the right reaction for the right kind of incoming hit.
but we still don't necessarily know where that hit's coming
from. So we had to add what we call attack telegraphs. So this
is the actual combat collision that we're looking at here, that
set of green spheres for our canary spearman for one of his
spear thrust attacks.
That's the combat collision that happens on, say, frame 20 of
the attack. And about 10, 15 frames before that happens, we
drop down a really broad collision box in front of him
that allows him to notify any other character who's standing
in the area that's about to be hit.
that there's a hit coming and it's something that you could
maybe you could block it but not necessarily parry it. And in
addition to sending that information, it also includes
the positional data about where he's standing so that the
character who's reacting knows which way to point.
their reaction, so their block or their dodge, which way they
need to be moving to get away from the incoming damage. And
these reactions, as we saw on the priority slide, they come in
at extra high priority. They override anything else that that
character can be doing. And this was very successful.
it was too successful. Because we put this on, for example, our
tank characters who have a nice active shield block, it
completely nullifies most incoming attacks from that front
arc and they were able to use it with frame perfect precision
against big nasty enemies in the game.
and defeat them over a period of time because they had to get
their parries and counterattacks in between guard. But the AI was
able to defeat really tough enemies without taking any
damage. Which sounds great.
We win. We win at AI. My robots are best. But the problem for
the player is that this really incentivizes the player to let
the robots do the fighting instead of participating in the
combat and sandwich sales go up because people put their
controllers down and walk away. So what we ended up having to do
is we added a shared cool down so that every AI controlled
party member.
When the AI is choosing to do these things, there's a two
second wait that they have to do between using one of these
high priority reaction abilities to level the playing
field and to give human players a reason not to just let the AI
do what they're doing.
This is an AI specific cool down. It doesn't affect the in
game cool down system. It doesn't affect a player using
these abilities. It just gives the AI a little bit of a
disadvantage. They're still able to react quickly, but they can't
get into that toe-to-toe perfect parry, frame perfect blocking
situation. So the AI is able to use these reaction abilities
without outclassing the player and creating negative play
patterns.
We also need the player to be able to customize their party
AI.
We've created a pretty good baseline experience, where
the party, as soon as you give them an ability,
They're able to use it fairly competently.
But we want to make sure that the player is supported by
their AI characters in the way that they want, and that when
they customize the AI, the decisions that they're making,
the choices they're making, are going to be observable.
So we wanted to give them big, chunky levers that we could
use so that they can see those results in the game and know
that they're making a difference and getting them to
play the way they want.
And so the first level of control.
as I mentioned, is just what abilities do you put on the
character. You can choose which abilities you map and the AI is
only going to use the ones that are mapped, which is a change
from our previous titles. Those abilities are available both to
the AI and to the player's direct control. So as you're
switching between characters or going into TACCAM, you can use
all of those abilities on the character. And then we give you
an additional layer of granularity that the AI is able
either disable.
so that ability is still available to a player who's
controlling that character or available to take as an order in
TACAM, but the AI is never going to pick this ability for
themselves. So if it's something on a long cool down that you're
saving for an emergency or something that consumes a
depletable resource, you want the AI not to be spending that
on its own discretion. Enable is the default choice where the AI
is going to evaluate it in priority sequence as we just
went through.
And you can also set it, as I mentioned before,
you can set it to prefer.
And that just puts the thumb on the scale
so that that ability, rather, is going to be executed
more often, it's going to come out at higher priority
in the evaluation.
And in some cases, it also widens the AI's rules
for when that's an appropriate ability to choose.
So if an AOE ability perhaps says that I need three targets
around that character in order for this to be a good choice, it
might drop that to two enemy AI characters in that area of
effect. So that ability is going to come out more often. It's
going to be used because the player wants them to use that
ability more often.
And the other interesting setting I want to talk about is
the targeting behavior that the player is able to customize.
Again, choose target, choose ability, move, and execute.
Those are the four important steps in our AI evaluator.
And so the player is able to influence how the AI follows,
or how it picks targets, rather, by choosing between
either following a character.
because we want it to be supporting, typically when the AI is running, it's
supporting a controlled character. So we can either say, track some character's
interactions, either the controlled character, whoever the player is
controlling, chase them around and beat on their target, or look into the aggro
system and defend a specific character.
and counter threats, whoever is targeting that character, we're
going to pick them off in priority. So with these
settings, the player can set how the AI is picking their targets
and picking their abilities in meaningful and visible ways. We
also needed to support the TACAM orders that the player is
giving when they're giving direct commands to their party
followers. So...
either as I say direct commands, use that ability,
move over here, or giving them behavioral orders that modify
how the AI works underneath. So in the direct commands, move
here, use ability, these have a fairly simple execution.
They just run that ability as though it had been chosen by
the AI and the AI decision making is suspended. When the
player gives an order, we're not constantly running the
evaluator in the background. The AI is just going to be hard
on target to follow that ability up until it completes
successfully.
The other side is that we have these behavioral commands that
modify how the AI works under the hood, like attack this
enemy. If you give this order, as bull has in the example
there, it overrides the entire target picking set of their AI
and says that's your target, every frame, every update, get
that guy until he dead.
hold position is more complicated because it has to
affect both the target picking and the ability picking so that
the AI doesn't get stuck trying to use things that would
violate the rule that says they have to stand here. And it also
adds a little miniature tether behavior so that if they get
knocked off of that spot that you told them to hold in combat
then they'll try to regain that position before doing anything
else.
And we also have an order that allows you to basically
implement the defend targeting that I talked about a moment
ago on the fly so that you can adapt to situations on the
battlefield. And it works in exactly the same way. These
commands give the player control over party behavior without
having to micromanage every action, including situally
overriding the way that it picks targets in the big AI hierarchy.
Now...
Having implemented all of these things,
we've put all this stuff together,
we've built out our behavior decision system,
we discovered something that was actually a big win for us.
Behavior decision system wasn't just good for Party,
it was also great for our creature AI designers.
because we didn't have to manage an AI hookup table
for each creature and we didn't have to necessarily
come up with the right evaluation order
and manage each creature's AI individually,
we could iterate much quicker
on how each individual AI ability.
prioritize itself and how it executed itself. And we could
also focus on giving the creatures interesting abilities
and moving them around between characters without having to
maintain a master AI setup. We could pull an ability off one
creature and either add it or remove it from the other
character and swap them around much more quickly using BDS.
Because the AI hookups for that ability come with the ability
itself.
And we were able to create creature variations.
We were able to use this a lot in DLC where we'd taken a
creature archetype that we'd shipped in the game and we'd
give them an extra ability as a little bit of a bonus.
It also meant that we were able to support really complex
creatures like our dragons.
And dragons in our game are big.
They touch every part of the combat system, including parts
of the combat system that aren't used by anything else. They fly.
They do all kinds of crazy stuff. And I'll show you the
in-game debug from the behavior decision system. So you can see
there's 58 different abilities. There's 58 different options
that the dragon is evaluating.
at any given time. And some of them are grayed out because
they're just not applicable. There are things that are state
specific. There's special movement in there depending on
whether they're in the ground or in the air. There's things they
can only use when they're flying. And we were able to use
BDS to manage this complexity and break it down into chunks
that designers could work on without having to necessarily
eat the entire dragon shaped burrito all at once.
So BDS gave us a consistent data driven way to prioritize
behaviors across the game from simplest wildlife creatures to
massive complex dragons while also supporting the complexity
we have for our party members and giving them the ability to
support the player in combat. And on that happy note, that's
my talk. I want to thank everyone here for coming out.
listening to me go on about inquisition for almost an hour
now. And I also want to thank Dave and Steve specifically for
putting this whole AI track together and inviting me to come
talk here. I want to thank the combat team back at BioWare in
Edmonton who came up with so many of the things that I have
the honor of presenting to you folks today. And, yeah, thank
you.
Inquisition is a very big game. And there's more material in
here than I could ever cover in an hour. We've got two minutes
for a couple of questions and then I'll be happy to talk to
people outside in the hall after the talk is over. Over here on
the right-hand side, please, sir.
Have you considered using the player's direct input while
they're controlling that character? Have you considered
using the player's decision while they're controlling that
character as waiting in the decision tree later on when it's
being driven by AI?
We hadn't considered that specifically, but it sounds like
a great idea.
Do you guys do any kind of load balancing of AI behavior
selected decisions get calculated over frames or is
everything always happening frame by frame?
That's a good question. Regarding whether we do load
balancing. And yeah, the AI evaluations are sliced over
frames. Each creature evaluates their AI I think once every
three frames. So we split it up and some creatures get sliced
down to five frame evaluation.
One more question here over here in the yellow shirt, please.
Okay. This is a question about the leash distance and
teleporting the party members. So I was just wondering about
the scenario where you outrun your party and you have your
camera pointed back towards where you came from. Does it
look like the party members outran you?
They come in behind your direction of travel, I think,
in that case. So if you're pointing back in your camera
and we can't solve for a good place behind the camera, then
they will pop in behind your direction of travel. So it
still looks, you know, silly, but it is the unfortunate
reality of dealing with that and making sure that we have to
account for their potentially getting lost behind.
Thank you.