Today I'm going to talk about a concept that has increasingly consumed my time and energy,
which is the topic of gaming addiction.
And I hope to share what I've learned about it in the last five or so years with you.
So first, who am I?
Well, what am I, I guess? I'm an experimental psychologist.
I originally trained as the kind of psychologist that helps people.
But then I was approached by my PhD supervisor who had the idea that maybe we could use empirical
psychology, quantitative psychology to study video games and to study benchmarking and
game development.
So I co-developed the PENs, which is an application of motivational theory to game development
that's a player experience and need satisfaction approach.
I'm most interested in behavior, physiology, and human motivation.
And this kind of encompasses kind of small-scale data,
things in the lab, things you'd think of as playtesting,
and large-scale or big data following tens of thousands
of people over time with behavioral data,
with trace data, with survey data.
And I'm increasingly interested
in evidence-based policymaking.
So basically, if you're a lawmaker,
or if you're a regulator,
or if you're in charge of an education or health system,
how do you make a decision
on the basis of scientific knowledge?
about technology specifically in a way that kind of conforms to or harmonizes
with what we know from science. I was also born in 1982 so I'm really in the
sweet spot for having played the original Nintendo and so this was my
present on my seventh birthday.
So why am I here?
What are the kinds of things I'm gonna talk about?
Well, I'm sure that everyone in the room
has tiny bits or large bits or chunks of an idea
about what gaming addiction is.
I'm gonna try to cover these five topics.
I'm gonna start by trying to offer
somewhat of a historic perspective
on concerns about games and addiction in particular.
I'm going to talk about what is the philosophical or theoretical position that's required to
understand what gaming addiction is. I'm going to talk a little bit about the different classes
and the different kinds of scientific evidence that psychologists, psychiatrists, epidemiologists,
and some kinds of sociologists apply to the question of gaming addiction.
Every time I use the word addiction, you're allowed to just put giant quotes around that word.
I'm going to talk about the direction, the trajectory that I see things going
if nobody in the industry changes their current behavior sets,
what the end game is going to be.
And I'm going to try, time permitting, to be somewhat optimistic
and offer an alternative vision that doesn't involve plowing into the side of a mountain.
So to start, for some historic perspective,
to kind of zoom out in terms of how we see
our concerns about games.
Concerns about games are very certainly not new.
The first documented case I could find
of a relatively popular game was in the New York Times
in the mid-1970s.
There was a game called Death Race.
It was an arcade game, a coin-operated arcade game,
wherein...
I think it was a two-player game.
You drove around killing these gremlins,
and then every time you killed a gremlin,
there was a little tombstone,
and then you had to avoid all the tombstones
of all the gremlins you killed,
and then keep running down gremlins.
Any case, the coverage of this concern,
of this game, is basically the template
for everything that we've observed
in the subsequent 40 years, 40-plus years,
of video game media coverage.
So we have an active ingredient.
for our concern.
And this is a pretty common one for different video game concerns.
It's that games are interactive.
That's the thing that sets them apart
from a different form of media.
That's the thing that makes them qualitatively different.
In some way, when people play games,
they practice and act in a fantasy environment
that generalizes, either through confusion or desensitization.
Their experience in this virtual environment
kind of gets mixed up with or written
over what they would have otherwise developed as
a person if they had never played Death Race 2000.
And then when we're talking about the effects of games on people,
we typically identify a vulnerable party.
They're typically not a 36-year-old straight white guy.
There's some other group of people.
Depending on the kind of media, it might be children, it might be migrants,
it might be women.
Really depending on the different kind of media that we've had a concern about,
there's always a vulnerable group.
If the effects aren't obvious on an individual level,
an argument gets made that on the societal level,
the effect must be significant.
In this one specifically, the expert that they brought in,
he said that this would lead to a higher level
of pedestrian traffic fatalities.
But with these kinds of concerns,
there's always one of these things that,
even if there isn't a clear transitive,
rock A scratches rock B, rock B scratches rock C,
so then A on C, there's some kind of probabilistic notion
that happens across the whole population.
And then I apologize, most of the time
that an expert weighs in, they are a psychologist,
just because we're so fancy.
And they always end in free advertising
for the game developer.
this one closes with
but mister brooks was unfazed every time a story comes out he said we get more
and more orders
so i think these these cabinets sold for about a thousand dollars each
so concerns about violent video games uh... i i i i promise i won't labor this
too much i have a point
uh... depending on how you slice the data you actually could think that
violent video games
were positively associated with youth crime
uh... for some period of time between death race
uh... and and when i got my nintendo
But then other things happened in society.
And so from the mid-90s until the present era,
there's almost a perfect negative correlation
between teen crime and violent video game sales
in the United States.
So there are some classes of evidence
that relate to concerns that in some cases
can ameliorate them, at least for certain parts
of the population.
But addiction's a little bit different.
So when we talk about addiction in technology
or addiction in games, interactivity
is still a feature of it.
But actually, in a weird way, it's
both a younger set of concerns and a more static set
of concerns.
So in the same way that interactivity
is important for both, the mode or the model or the lens
that we see technology addiction or gaming addiction through
is intrinsically different.
Because there is a model that already existed.
for us to think about gaming addiction.
So in the late 1990s, there was a psychiatrist
called Ivan Goldberg.
He was one of New York's leading addiction researchers.
And he was so frustrated with the medical model of addiction
that as an act of satire on a email list, on a list serve,
he actually created gaming he created internet addiction
and he just like i like took the checklist approach
and just like point out how silly psychiatrist had been about
pathologizing all these normal parts of life
uh... in the late nineties apparently internet was still part of life
though maybe it wasn't as fun.
And he was shocked because actually it turned real.
People started coming to him with their imagined or real
problems with technology addiction.
And so really what's going on here, this is kind of one of
many indicators that the challenge that we might face
with dealing with concerns or thinking about concerns about
aggression are very different than what
we see with addiction.
So we can compare these on a direct basis.
So when we talk about violent games,
we actually have a pretty poor fitting model
from social science to describe the effects
that we would expect.
But when we talk about addiction to games,
we have a pre-existing model, a mold.
People have been studying addiction for a very long time.
So there's an easy fit, at least in terms
of a lot of the language and a lot of the assumptions.
For violent games, there's a lot of similarities to other forms of media that have come before.
So we have comic books, we have movies, we have novels that have, you know, like crime
novels.
And a lot of these fears, a lot of these concerns were busted.
So when we think about parallels to our concerns about games and aggression, when we think
about those parallels, it kind of leads us to be like, huh, maybe there's not a there
there.
But when we think about addiction, it's very different with games.
With games, there's a lot of novel factors that other comparison media don't have.
Many of the fears are supported, but in a kind of weird way.
Like, we have anxiety about things like, I don't know, election interference,
or the attention economy, or the monetization of attention.
and they're not really about games or addiction proper,
but because they happen on the same device,
because these things are kind of intrinsically
cross-platform now, our anxieties don't kind of
stay with a console the way they might have
in the mid-90s.
So, you know, there's definitely a,
there's a real qualitative difference
between how a parent or a policymaker sees
a Doom sold on CD-ROM in a box.
in the early 1990s and how they see Call of Duty 4
with endless DLCs and added features
and dynamic challenge generation.
And so the boundaries of the media are very different
and every time that somebody thinks about the limits
or the lack of boundaries on it,
it kind of leads them to think,
oh my goodness, what else could be happening?
So actually, I say this to draw a contrast between the two concerns.
They both involve many of the same actors,
they involve many of the same kind of stakeholders in society,
but they are fundamentally different challenges.
The second thing I want to talk about is kind of the philosophical
or theoretical underpinnings of addiction.
Now I've heard this a few times, Celia is great with this,
a few others are really great with this,
is that we need to be really careful
about how we use the term addiction.
And we have a common use of it,
we kind of, it's kind of the same as saying
something's fun, or it's engaging, or it's immersive.
But how we react to the word addiction
really depends on the thing that we're thinking about,
the substance that we're talking about.
If we say my loved one is addicted to smoking
or to heroin or to gambling.
That's very different than saying,
he plays too much golf on Sundays,
my teenagers just can't stop on Instagram,
or the battery keeps dying on the phone
because there's so much Fortnite being played.
There's something fundamentally different
about how we use the word addiction for these things,
but in English we don't have a lot of really good ways
of discriminating the two.
One way you could discriminate the two, however,
is with the off-the-shelf model that we inherit
from the medical sciences.
So in this model, there's an active ingredient
behind different forms of addiction.
So for smoking, it's nicotine.
For heroin, it's certain classes of opioids.
For gambling, people think it's dopamine,
but they don't really know.
We can see things like when you give Parkinson's patients L-Dopa and they have more free-floating dopamine in their systems.
They might for the first time in their lives become gambling addicts. So there's some treatment effects there, but we're not quite sure.
But the mechanisms for certain kinds of behavioral dysregulations, things like gaming, things like shopping,
it's not very clear what the kind of mechanism would be, what the active ingredient might be.
But there is, in the way that we practice science on this topic,
an assumption that there is some shared commonality.
There's some kind of active ingredient that lives inside of all gambling,
or lives inside of all sports addiction.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Thank you.
So, with that in mind, with the medical model in mind,
all good psychiatrists and epidemiologists begin to build taxonomies.
There are basically two you've heard about, I would imagine.
The first is the American model from the American Psychiatric
Association.
And the second is a model from a working group
at the World Health Organization, working with the World Health Organization.
The American model is, there was a proposal
made for research on a topic of something
called internet gaming disorder.
The internet is not defined.
And games are not defined, but there is a taxonomy of potential symptoms that are identified.
And I'll talk about them a little bit more in a little bit.
But it is kind of like a syndrome without any of the core definitions.
I've emailed people asking them very desperately in industry and in academia and psychiatry,
what the hell is an internet game?
And nobody can tell me.
The World Health Organization has a more general concept.
It is called gaming disorder, so it
doesn't have the internet in it for any reason.
And the basic idea here is instead
of having symptoms or some kind of indicators of what
the illness should be, they basically
say that it's when you do gaming for a year.
and across that year you suffer significant impairment
to something that's important to you.
So it's a bit of a tautology,
it's a little bit of a snake eating itself.
But there's a little disclaimer that says,
but if it's really bad,
if games are super duper disruptive,
then you don't even need to have this problem for a year.
And this is basically where we're at right now.
Because it's a class of argument by analogy,
which is to say that we think there might be a problem here.
We think there might be an active ingredient.
We think that people's lives might be impacted.
This might be the cause of a disorder
or the cause of ill health.
And this is kind of where we are philosophically.
All right, so in some ways,
gambling disorders are jumping off point.
And in some way, different substance abuse disorders
are jumping off point.
But here's really where we're landing.
So according to the American Psychiatric Association,
essentially, they took the checklist of indicators
for gambling disorder, and they took out the word gambling,
and they put in the word internet gaming.
So there are nine possible indicators.
I just counted, actually, I only put eight on this slide.
And the idea is that if you could say yes to five
or more of these, then you might be classified
as having a problem with gaming.
And again, the idea here is that each one of these possible symptoms is,
it's like equally indicative of you having a problem.
And that assumption is kind of supported by the fact, or rather,
that assumption is supported by the idea that there is something in all games,
no matter what type they are, that's analogous to the thing that's inside
all cigarettes, no matter who manufactures them, that is kind of.
generally addictive for those who might be vulnerable.
Does that make sense?
All right.
So in the third bit,
I'm gonna talk a little bit about evidence.
So as a scientist, I love evidence.
As someone who lives in England,
I love that my airplane works and gets me here.
And also, I'm really interested to know
what scientists have been up to for the last 20 years.
So depending on what words you use
when you look up a literature,
on video gaming addiction.
You can call it disordered gaming, problem gaming,
gaming addiction, internet gaming disorder,
gaming disorder.
You kind of have to write a pretty long search string.
There's between 50 and maybe 300 studies
on gaming addiction in the last few decades.
And they fall into one of basically four tranches.
The first is kind of measurement.
So if there's a there there, how do we measure it?
The second is neuroimaging studies.
So in some way, can we learn something
about how typical versus non-typical gamers approach
games based on something that is a signal that we
can detect in an fMRI scanner?
Symptomatology, these are studies
about kind of what would gaming disorder
be correlated with in the world of psychopathology?
How does it kind of fit in the larger, excuse me?
in the larger puzzle of mental illness.
And then treatment.
So this is if somebody has a problem,
how might we help them?
All right?
So,
overwhelmingly,
the great majority of those 250 studies
are measurement studies.
All right.
So these are large, typically large scale,
so maybe between 150 and our work
has upwards of 20,000 participants.
And the idea is that using some form of survey research,
you cast as wide a net as possible
within this medical framework.
And you try to test if those symptoms or those indicators,
if the sniffles and coughs that you
think are related to the underlying problem of gaming
addiction.
if those are actually present in the population?
And how good are those questions at discriminating
a player who's playing out of a sense of choice and volition
from a player who's playing out of a sense of, say, compulsion,
feeling like they have to play instead of feeling
like they want to play?
Unfortunately, the great majority of this research
uses what's called convenience sampling.
So in the rare cases where you actually
get gamers who have problems with play,
it's because the researcher has gone to a gaming addiction subreddit,
or they've gone to a part of the internet where gamers who have problems regulating their play kind of congregate,
and then they conduct this research.
And in some ways this is a bit like researching drug use only outside of a needle exchange.
you don't get a very clear sense of how many people in the population have a
problem
if you're sampling only within certain kind of tranches
in certain parts of certain communities.
But it is the case that of these 250 studies,
not 250, but of about 200 of these studies,
really what's going on are these convenience samples.
So people are running a thesis,
they're doing a project in a high school,
or a school system,
or they're having friends of friends of friends of friends of friends take surveys.
The second class of study are different types of neuroscience studies.
These are much, much smaller studies.
They have small samples because the amount of money
it takes to, it costs at least $1,700 an hour
to give somebody, to prepare someone
and then do an fMRI scan.
So these studies typically have very small samples,
between 10 and 20 people in them.
And the basic idea behind all of these studies
is they give a large number of gamers
in a community a survey.
They try to flag the ones that are like low players
and high players or the ones they think
might have a problem with gaming
and the ones that they think are quote unquote normal.
All right.
And then they have them do tasks in an fMRI
where they show them in many cases,
reminders of their favorite game.
And then they try to see how much activation there is,
relative activation there is between the two groups.
And while this doesn't actually tell you anything about addiction,
you do observe some differences.
And you don't know if that's just because they like the games a whole lot.
But there have been many, many studies like this.
And one of these will come out at least once a month,
every month, for the rest of our lives.
The symptomatology studies, sorry, I'm getting a bit grim.
I should not get grim for another 15 minutes.
All right, the third set is much less common
than it should be, and I consider it
a very interesting set of study, class of studies,
where basically people try to figure out
if you score high on these questionnaires
of gaming disorder, what else do you score high on?
Not thinking necessarily that gaming disorder causes these other problems, but how do different
kind of constellations or how do different kind of clusters of these disorders kind of
relate to each other or interrelate?
Is gaming in some way a coping mechanism?
Is problem gaming in some way a coping mechanism for something that's either organic, going
on in someone's brain, or linked to a social environment or some kind of stressor like
school?
And unfortunately...
This kind of research is really hampered by the medical model.
So there are some gatekeepers in academia who have some very clear ideas about what
gaming addiction is and isn't.
And so if you kind of come with this kind of open-minded exploratory perspective, it's
much harder to publish the papers.
And I don't know how much you know about academic publishing, but it's quite important.
Not as important as getting grants, but it's up there.
Does that make sense?
I thought I saw a hand.
I got really worried for a second there.
All right.
And then by far, thankfully, the rarest class of study
are the treatment studies.
So these are exceedingly rare.
I found three of these.
And I look every few weeks.
I have a search that runs.
And in these studies, basically what happens is either
there is a behavioral or a pharmaceutical intervention
with a population of players who are either self-identified
or a therapist has decided they have a problem with games.
The typical treatment is cognitive behavioral therapy,
which one might think works with a lot of different problems.
But I am quite worried from an ethics perspective
about before we have disorders, a disorder that
has real symptoms and a real course of treatment,
potential course of treatment, that we're giving people
medication for gaming.
Does that make sense?
So those are the four classes.
The great majority of the studies
are these cheap and easy studies where you collect
a load of participants.
You ask them about their favorite hobby.
Some of them say they have a problem.
You do a bunch of statistics.
Second is you con a research agency
into giving you $250,000, and you scan 30 people's brains
and show them pictures of World of Warcraft and Fortnite
dances.
The third is you kind of do some really cool network science,
which I'm sure some people in the room know how to do.
And you try to see how these things constellate over time.
And then you have the island of Dr. Moreau.
So when you look at this literature, kind of by and large,
the data is actually fairly low quality.
the studies aren't done very well,
there isn't a lot of transparency,
nobody has their hypotheses before they collect their data,
you can't see anyone's statistical models
because they don't share their code.
So there have been a few consortiums of researchers,
of which I count myself,
where we kind of try to point these things out.
We try to say, hey, hold on a second,
there are two billion video game players in the world,
these 250 studies are kind of garbage.
We're really going out on a limb here.
If you're running a health system,
this isn't, you know, you wouldn't identify
a new parasite this way.
Why are you talking about a new behavioral disorder?
Well, unfortunately, games are very, very popular.
So does anyone know what the base rate fallacy is?
All right.
What if I told you
that almost all serial killers wear socks.
All right?
If you didn't know how many people in the general population wore socks,
you could interpret this as a pretty good signal
that the person, any given person with socks,
you don't actually have socks,
is a serial killer.
Games are super popular.
This means that a giant slice of young people, upwards of 95%,
depending on how you count, are pretty engaged
with some form of game that kind of hits them at the right.
They bounce off a bunch of stuff,
but it hits them at the right angle.
And they find their game for a few months or a few years.
So when something bad happens in a young person's life, which
is inevitable, there is an unending stream
of anecdotal evidence.
And this anecdotal evidence, I have to tell you,
oh, things are getting grim, is more than enough
for this party to stop.
It is true that there is actually
some evidence of absence.
But because the evidence base is so crap,
we have to fall back on.
the absence of evidence is not evidence of absence.
So we don't know what we don't know
because research isn't being done properly.
And in the meantime, we're going to have monster
of the week, scary story.
And that's more than enough to motivate regulators.
And that's more than enough to motivate people
who run health systems in a way that we would have never seen
with violence and aggression.
So we'll talk a little bit about endgame.
All right.
This is my most optimistic slide.
So, I think best case scenario,
this party's gonna go on for about five more years.
All right?
So, the public, the people who control taxation,
and commerce.
They're that tiny little boat.
Actually, this metaphor breaks down
the more I think about it.
I thought I was very clever when I drew this picture, okay?
I'm just going to go with it.
It's an indestructible boat.
It's in God mode.
OK.
So there is a level of understanding
that the public and policymakers have.
They can intuit a whole bunch of stuff about gaming addiction
or about the larger halo around games
and behavioral dysregulation that
are the obvious salient features.
Very few people like real money transactions.
No one likes pay to win, right?
Loot boxes are like, if I ever hear that word again.
And anti-social behavior on platforms where people don't take, where developers don't take these things seriously and kids come right, rightly
to their parents terrified or or minorly traumatized by a
irresponsible design decision.
There are some things over the surface
that that quote-unquote normal people can see there that are kind of illnesses in the industry. All right, but
as the little boat that's indestructible gets closer to the iceberg,
they're going to be able to see all the other stuff.
And once they start poking around with regulations,
their hands are just going to go into all of these different pies.
There's a lot of booths around this kind of stuff.
I don't know. You should walk around the expo center.
It's kind of cool stuff.
So why is this happening?
Why is this collision inevitable?
Well, there are some things that the people in this room
don't have a lot of control over.
All right?
First, generally, there's been a deterioration
in the quality of science journalism.
So a lot of newsrooms don't have scientists covering science
beats anymore because of just things that are
happening in that profession.
Second, there's been, since the year 2000,
there's been a rise in what could be called
moral entrepreneurs.
So these, it's not necessarily morals
in terms of right or wrong,
but it's morals in terms of norms.
This is an idea from sociology.
So the idea is that there are people who kind of,
listen to, feel the way the wind is blowing,
interpret what the norm is around a technology,
and then what they do is they sell that back to us
in the form of parenting advice
in a kind of a high profile book.
And in the last two decades,
we've gotten this increasingly with social media,
with games.
Does anyone in the audience,
raise your hand if you know who Phil Zimbardo is.
This is good.
Uh-oh, I heard a ringing noise.
Somebody didn't listen to my rule about ringing.
OK, it's not my rule.
Just give me perfect scores, please.
All right.
I don't care.
You can all make noise.
I just need the perfect scores.
So anyway, some of you had your hands up.
Let's assume 11%.
Who knows that Phil Zimbardo wrote a book about video games?
One, two, okay, I might have, yeah,
we've probably talked, you've talked about it.
All right, he did.
He wrote an entire, Phil Zimbardo,
the guy who did the Stanford Prison Experiment,
he wrote a whole book about how
video games are feminizing boys.
This was completely new to me.
I read the book, it was thankfully, it was quite short.
Just type Zimbardo-Shabilsky debate
when you have some free time
and you can watch what happens.
But there is now, there's kind of an economic
thought leader niche around technology.
And so every six or 10 months,
it's kind of like pulling a lever or a loot box,
we get a different new technological demon.
And a lot of them land on games. You don't have a lot of control over that. I do my best as a scientist.
Um, there's a lot of technological anxieties in the air.
So in the same way that we might be very proud about games being able to play on all of these different platforms,
not mentioning any giant company,
it's the case that we also do other things on those devices.
Like our email or our grinder or wait, no, I didn't say that.
But we, and so in our minds when we use this device,
we have a pretty undifferentiated sense
of what it might do for us or to us.
And if games are part of that ecology,
that part of that, kind of that blurring
of our hopes and our anxieties,
then what we might think of as an affordance,
helping somebody play a game on a platform,
it might actually associate our other feelings
about arguing on Twitter
with our lovely games of Fortnite.
And then the final thing is that, and this is absolutely true and I'll speak
autobiographically, there are a lot of really bad psychologists out there, there's a lot of bad
academics and professors out there and I can't control their behavior
and I try to call it out when I can
when I have knowledge of it, but
your industry has some pretty bad actors in it
and they might ruin the party for you
and you don't necessarily have control over that.
Things you do have control over.
All right, I've heard the answer to bad speech
is good speech, more speech,
you just keep pulling that again,
you just keep finding analogies.
One way you can say is the answer to bad science
is good science.
The problem is, is there's no good science.
And that's partly because it's actually very hard
to do good science on gaming addiction
because unlike other things,
if you're a researcher and you want to know
the effects of nicotine on smokers or on mammals,
you can go out to the store and you can buy cigarettes
and you can analyze everything that's in them
as a biochemist.
All right, and then you can synthesize your own thing and you can run your own study.
You actually can't do that with a lot of games because of how they're designed, how they're
updated, how the IP is traced and taken care of.
And so actually, scientists have a much poorer idea, a much less enriched idea of what actually
happens inside of games because so much of it is considered IP, so much of it is considered
So much of it is outside the scope of...
of scientific inquiry.
It's a bit like, imagine that you're coming across,
it's late at night and you come across a drunk
and he's looking furtively around at the ground
underneath the street lamp.
And you say to him, sir, what are you doing?
And he says, I'm looking for the keys to my house.
And you say, why, did you drop them here?
And he says, no, but this is the only place that I can see.
What's happening, part of the reason why the literature
on gaming addiction or on aggression is so irredeemable
is because you all have the data that's required
to actually study it.
And what many academic scientists are left with
are the scraps.
And this is part, I think in some way, of two things.
The first thing is, I know people in the industry
were really burned by the aggression debate.
And the First Amendment's basically the reason why we're not having a very different set
of conversations right now.
And the second is an on-by-default defensive posture, a reactive posture.
And it's true that things are only steadily, slightly getting worse every six months.
And so area under the curve profit, things are fine.
But they are getting irredeemably worse.
There are certain authorities that are looking very closely
at regulating.
I'm on two in the United Kingdom.
And there is blowback.
So a few months ago, so it's very easy
to think of something like the World Health Organization
as an organized body that really has its ducks in a row.
See, I'm in America, so I can use duck idioms.
And they really weren't.
they were really internally quite,
the World Health Organization,
they were really quite fraught
about this gaming disorder thing.
The people who were working in the ICD-11,
they'd really gone out on a limb, all right?
And there was a lot of debate internally in the UN.
And then the ESA decided to publish
a rebuttal to the evidence.
and it cherry-picked some of my research,
just the parts that show games aren't so bad,
not the parts that say that people's thoughts
about them being good are also overblown.
Cherry-picked some stuff about games being great
for cognitive development, yada, yada, yada,
that's bullshit.
And then went to town with a press release.
And you know what everyone woke up to
the next morning in the UN?
A circle the wagons moment.
So now they're much more convinced that they were right the whole time and you're all evil.
I would have warned you not to do that.
So my piece of advice here is I think you probably all should consider bracing for impact.
There are a lot of bad things that can come from this reactive stance, from there not
being good science, from there being monster of the week anecdotal, anecdata, from rightfully
scared parents.
The first is, there's going to be stigmatization, we're going to stigmatize a hobby of more
than a billion people on this planet.
The second is that there's going to be a lot of really dumb regulation coming down the
pipe.
It's going to be inspired, just like the medical metaphor, the medical model metaphor, it's
going to be inspired by that.
So in the EU we have these, I don't know if they're in America yet, like these giant packet
warnings on cigarettes that show you like a lung that got coughed out of a dilophosaurus
or something.
You're going to get that.
There's going to be, depending on the patchwork of markets and regulations, in some places
more aggressive regulators are going to fragment the market, the marketplace, and you're going
to have certain kinds of labeling rules.
There are going to be sin taxes, cost of doing business.
It's going to make the violent video game stuff look like nothing.
And then there's going to be fines.
So there's going to be a lot of compliance, and that's going to have two effects.
The first effect is it's going to start siphoning giant amounts of money out of your organization.
So Google can sustain 4.5 billion euros followed by 1.7 billion euros,
and they can pay really, really clever lawyers to make that follow a diminishing function.
I don't know how many gaming companies can sustain,
I don't even know if the big boys can sustain more than
a few billion dollars of direct fees or fines.
And I don't think they can afford to leave the EU market.
So in a lot of ways, there have been short-term victories
that are going to lead to long-term defeats on this.
I see someone wearing a Nintendo shirt
and I think Nintendo might be fine actually.
So, you know, what can we do?
And I'm going to intentionally try to end a little early
so we can have questions, not comments.
What can you guys possibly do to turn a corner on this
and to turn this defeat into an opportunity?
You need to be proactive.
There needs to be a fundamental shift.
in your approach to something like gaming addiction or gaming and aggression or whatever.
And there'll be other, I promise, there'll be other things that people will make up if
addiction ever goes away to be afraid of.
This is going to involve you considering what are your first principles.
Articulate what do you want to be as developers,
as responsible citizens,
and designers of playgrounds for children.
This is going to involve reading human rights law.
So the UN Charter on the Rights of the Child say that young people have a right to information
and they have a right to play. And if I have my way, they'll also have a right to play video games
and other forms of entertainment when this gets revised because it's from the late 1980s.
The only way that we get there is if you're at the table.
So LEGO has ethical design principles
for their embodied toys.
They check in with those before they build their environments.
And I understand that LEGO environments
are a little bit more constrained
than League of Legends.
But they've got a touchstone.
And the touchstones in this industry are rather fragmented.
I think that you need to be part of good science.
I think you need to promote it.
And there's a lot of ways that you can,
and I'll detail some of them in a minute.
And I think that you probably need to coordinate,
because none of you are as big as a Google or a Facebook.
And I really think that there needs to be,
in the same way that the Free Pla...
Wait.
Fair?
Fair Play Alliance, sorry.
I have a sticker, I should check it.
But in the same way that the Fair Play Alliance
is trying to articulate a certain set of standards,
I think you're gonna need that more broadly
to answer kind of the big questions of play.
So it's not just about reaction.
So I'm gonna close with this.
I think you need to foster and model good science.
I think that involves engaging in tactical and strategic data sharing.
You need to think about...
the kinds of data that you collect to improve your product
or to monetize your product,
you need to think about that in terms of how that could be used
to improve our fundamental understanding
of how billions of people spend tens of billions of hours
of every week of their lives, hopefully having fun.
This can involve data sharing,
hackathons at different levels of education with your data.
You get to figure out which kids are really the ones
who are, you know, potentially hireable.
You might consider funding an actual research organization to study play,
kind of an extension of what's going on in the UX,
UE space or user experience space right now.
Think about collaborations with academics when you do them,
not as like you bring in a Petri dish or not Petri dish,
but like you bring in a sample of an academic or you share data with just him or her.
But actually think about this as more of a team-based activity
about joint knowledge production.
And I think that really the defensiveness needs to stop,
or you'll all go extinct.
There are things about games that are great,
and there are probably things about games that aren't.
And I think it's important that we know what those are,
and we know how, that we're as sure about them
as we are about our reasons for things like airplanes
staying in the air, all right?
Because so much of ourselves are invested in these mediums.
They're so amazing, and we owe it to everyone who plays
to learn as much as we can.
And that means we might find some scary stuff,
but I firmly believe that everyone's
entitled to their own opinions about art
and about this medium, but they're not
entitled to their own facts.
So with that, I'm going to say thank you
for your time and attention.
And please, for the love of God, ask me questions.
Hello.
Hi.
I'm someone with a deep interest in this to begin with.
I work at Valve now as an economist, but prior to that,
I spent about 14 years as a social policy researcher.
So this is very dear to me, and I
see what your point is about the bad evidence that's
out there in the market right now.
You know, obviously you and we are interested in the actual truth about this.
And I'm wondering if we, as game companies, are to fund research or do partnerships, especially
given that, you know, many game organizations are going to have interests in just showing
the positive signs of gaming and not the negative, are we going to be combating bad science that
says that gaming is a bad thing with bad science that says gaming is a good thing?
That's a great question.
And this is not a problem that is specific to games or the games
industry.
I think that it is a natural human instinct
to want to see the positives of the things
that we're most invested in and we love the most.
I think fundamentally this comes down
to whether or not the money, the data, the resources,
the cooperation.
whether or not that's contingent on the findings.
So in the social sciences more broadly,
and the medical sciences, there's
a movement to something called pre-registration
and registered reports.
This is the idea that you write down
what you're going to do before you do it,
or it's peer reviewed before you collect your data.
And that's the only way that this will work.
So basically, this is why it requires
open-mindedness and a certain level of letting go of control.
because there will be things that,
but transparency is the thing that will save us on that.
So you may not be able to share the exact data set
that comes out of one of these collaborations
or the projects, but you can create a simulated data
depending on the class of data,
which other people can question your code or your models.
So well, I'm happy to follow that up, but there's a number of people unless you have one more just very small
Yeah, I agree with everything you said about standards. I'd also advocate for
Transparency and how data sets are created. Yes, because that's an important piece of it. Yes computational reproducibility is something that scientists are horrific
Thank you. Everyone's horrific at it. You're welcome. I think there and then I'll alternate or not alternate obviously
Thank you.
I find that when we act as advocates for games and
ambassadors of our industry, and we have to defend
ourselves against things like the internet gaming disorder
classification and the certain kinds of studies, the bad
science studies, I find there's a real danger and
tendency to dip into dogmaticism and, in some
cases, come off as anti-intellectualism.
What do you recommend, especially if we are not scientists or psychologists, how do we
sort of avoid coming off that way?
I think curiosity is the thing that's missing.
So one of the real tragedies of both of concern-focused research in psychological science and in these
other sciences is that there's actually a very low level of curiosity or interest in
what the hell games are.
And so when I was training as a scientist,
I wanted to do studies on motivation.
And so the way I learn is through examples.
And so I'd have to read other lab studies.
And it really ground me down, the lack of curiosity.
And so I think remembering that you're not
going to lose your job if you listen
to a parent who's flustered, or trying
to identify if the person has, try
to identify what their interest or where their passion comes
from for arguing with you.
uh... and i think that the insights you get i mean it's very banal when you get
to the moral entrepreneurs
for their whole reason for being is to sell a book and a consultancy etc etc
you do not need to listen to those you can
please feel free to argue with them
but uh... i think a lot of people uh... just don't have a lot of clarity on
what exactly they're unhappy about
hope that helps
absolutely thank you
Sorry.
What do you think is the responsibility of conferences
like GDC that host talks that teach dark patterns
and promote the attention economy?
I think in the first instance, we
need to understand the reasons why those things either work
or don't work on a very thorough level.
So.
You talk to, say, Tristan or these guys who are doing
the time well spent movement.
They're kind of like, they've come to their found Jesus
moment.
They've decided that when they worked at Google,
they were evil because they manipulated people.
And now, they've realized that that was wrong.
And now, they'll help.
But when you ask them about the research that
they're thinking that they were these kind of Oppenheimers of social control.
They point at studies that are garbage from the social sciences.
Like there was a Cornell professor, Brian Wansink, who like had this unending soup bowl
experiment, but he's a fraudster.
The experiment never worked.
And these guys who think that they've, you know, fooled the world.
you know, it's possible they still did.
But the evidentiary basis for their claims, for good or bad,
are kind of based on a whole series of assumptions.
So I get tricked by dark patterns.
It makes sense to me that that happens.
But I think that the first duty of an organization
is to actually
document the phenomena closely, because if we regulate it without understanding it, or
if we kind of set rules about it without understanding it, you know, it's a dinosaur's amber scenario.
Is that good?
Yeah, thanks.
Appreciate it.
Hi, hello.
So regarding the iceberg metaphor analogy.
It's a very strong boat, OK?
It's moving quickly.
Well, my question is, why do you think
that the boat will catch up with the iceberg?
Because as it seems to me, like you said, every six months
something new comes up.
So what makes you believe that the regulators will actually
catch up?
Because they haven't been able to catch up.
I mean, that's a.
I don't know.
For one.
So I have two answers.
One is polluted by my own experience, which is that I had years of my life where I wasn't
on parliamentary, I wasn't giving evidence to parliamentary subcommittees on these topics,
and now an increasing amount of my time is spent doing that.
And I think it's just a matter of historic record that, you know.
Different companies and countries different countries are looking more closely at these mechanics now
So is your question is it happening or why is it happening?
I mean will they ever catch up like because it seems to well, but we are developing new ways
How do you do what they'll do the player right? So what they'll do is they'll write a rule that is
Oh, I just remember the second part of an answer that I didn't give they'll write a rule
That is like a catch-all rule
And then when a company that's large enough to step out of line steps out of line, they'll sue it.
Right, or the levy of fine.
And sorry, that was the other thing I wanted to say,
that it's not just the companies can't sustain these fines,
it's that the cost of compliance is very high.
So it may cut out smaller studios from certain markets.
And then that's a real opportunity cost for human play.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, okay, thanks.
I mean, we can talk more about that.
It's really boring, regulatory frameworks for me.
Hi.
Would you say that screen addiction ties into video game
addiction at all, or is that similar in that it is not
entirely properly studied or even classified?
It's entirely the same thing.
Is it?
Yeah, so you just take out, literally you can just take out the word video game and
you can put in smartphone, screen, social media.
It's all the same kind of miasm of social science.
So the fundamental problem is that it's large-scale social data from surveys, and so because one
person fills out the survey.
everything that they reply to has kind of a background level of correlation and
So things like I use a screen a certain number of hours a day, and I feel sad
Those things share one-third of 1% of covariance
And if all you care about is a p-value,
if all you care about is statistical significance,
then you can say something scary.
But I work by Amy Orbin and I on screen impacts.
You will overdose on that if you're interested.
Thank you.
And I think I can actually do the next two
in the next three minutes if they're reasonable, yes.
When it comes to the research organization,
are there any good examples in other industries
where that's actually been not a defensive thing?
Because everyone I'm aware of is a super defensive,
like, makes it worse kind of organization.
Yeah, I don't know.
So I think, in my mind, the model is a,
there's something called
the Psychological Science Accelerator,
which is a coalition of hundreds of psychology labs
all around the world,
and we all run the same experiment at the same time.
And that way we know what we find is either there or not
there.
It's like Science Accelerator.
Unfortunately, all of the collaborations
that I'm aware of in the gambling, gaming industry,
that one, and different kind of health organizations
and governmental organizations, those have all failed.
pretty in different ways though spectacularly in different ways so they're their use cases, but
But yeah, I'm writing a white paper on how it not how it cannot be a dumpster fire
And so it should work with Facebook too. I hope
Okay
All right one last one good a from Rochester
I'm from Yonkers.
Oh, well no one's perfect.
Yeah.
So you talked a lot about, I really
like the slide where you were talking
about when you're addicted to drugs, it shows up.
And I think it really hit a note where we're
trying to isolate this X, right?
This X that is video game addiction.
And let's say 20, 30 years from now, every one of us
in this room knows exactly what makes a game addicting, right?
We've found X.
Yeah.
And I really think that at that point in time,
there's going to be a lot of companies, which I won't name names,
that want to be the Marlboro of games.
They don't care about morality.
They just want to make addicting games so people play them.
And there's going to be a lot of people who just want to make fun games
that are the opposite of whatever this X is, right?
And so how do you think that as, you know, a community,
we can deal with something like that?
Because I feel like that would literally tear,
like, the entire games industry apart.
So this is where I return to my facts versus opinions thing.
So if we actually have good scientific evidence
that this thing is an opioid, let's just
imagine it's a horrible, addictive thing.
It's kryptonite to children, but addictive kryptonite.
I think that if we have clarity on it,
if we have the facts on it, it'll
be very, very easy to regulate.
And it's not gonna be up to mom and pop game studio on a,
I don't know, they're gonna make like 3D augmented
body suits in this future that you have.
But it's not gonna be up to you to police them.
I think that if we have a common set of facts,
it'll be ridiculously easy to regulate them.
Okay. All right.
All right, I think that that is time.
And I thank you all for your time and attention.
I don't know what the scale is, but if it's a 10-point scale, you give me a 10.
And if it's an 8, an 8.
All right?
All right.
Thank you so much.