called the Distributed Art Direction of Edith Finch.
And so how best to kick off the Art Direction Bootcamp
to have me, not an art director, talk to you about it.
So basically, my name is Chelsea Hash.
I was the technical art lead on this project
with Giant Sparrow.
And one of the reasons I'm here talking to you today
is because we didn't really have an art director,
no single art director.
But we did have a group of people
that really loved a project, had their own perspectives,
and worked together to make it happen.
I was also there for very early and stayed for very late.
So,
If I make any mistakes in characterizing people's efforts,
I apologize, but I think this was like the inspiration
for how we ended up going together.
So, this is more of the same.
Oh man, that audio.
Don't worry about it.
So again, this is how an indie game put together an art plan
without a single director.
Part of it was how we built our plan at our own pace
and tried to stay true to a single goal
while still not having it all planned from the beginning.
And then a big part of this takeaway
will be remembering the bits that worked,
even though there were a lot of painful parts
that were hard to deal with at the time.
This is an example of, whoopsies.
I do not know how to operate this thing.
Nope.
So when we got started, we had just three
of the original people from The Unfinished Swan stayed on.
So that was a creative director, technical director,
and one environment artist.
And so some of the early shots of the green light trailer
were evocative and sparse and not quite landing
on this thing.
This is an example of how we went from something like this to something like this.
So to get started, it all started with Ian, creative director.
And we had a little bit of Google image search art direction.
But it wasn't just Google image search.
These were all collections of snapshots from movies,
personal photos from actual houses that we lived in.
All of these pilled with explanations
of exactly what they meant and how they fit in.
We had synopses of, let's see what I got.
These are some scratch from an art direction presentation.
We had some art math where we'd combine looks from one area
with some art inspirations from another
to land on a final experience.
We had no's, we had no's,
definite no's and definite yes's.
And so no one could approach the project
and say we didn't have a goal in mind.
but it was a very big body of inspiration.
We had collages for plans for many, many bits of our work.
And in the end, it was sort of a curation.
These were specific photos,
and yet we were not targeting a photo-real look.
These were evocative,
and they had certain places and spaces,
but they weren't exactly what we were trying to build.
So it was that curation process
that ended up falling to the job on.
the concept artist.
Well, actually, this is another one of my favorites.
All of the hit lists, notes, and plans,
the bulleted lists of things that we were going to work on,
and my favorite, summary images of what was
going on at a given moment.
And so.
We started with some efforts.
We had some specific inspirations.
We were kind of aiming for stylized.
It was very difficult to go from a game
like The Unfinished Swan with its dark,
black and white art style, and then suddenly say,
now we're jumping into a new engine
with expectations much higher.
Like, what are we actually trying to build?
So we have one on the right, which is a color graded forest, and then one which is a custom
concept, kind of combining pictorialism and some art deco.
And so our concept artist, Theo Aredos, was the first person to really say, this isn't
a collage, this is something specific.
You're trying to build together the house.
What did it look like?
We had, you know, this is again, we still could have been making a game that was very flat.
So we had, you know, a bunch of examples of making paintings from some of these collages
and turning them into mock-ups. We had many, many versions of the house, the lighting condition,
and they were all like, you know, for mood and tone. We, you know, we felt good about these things.
we started building.
So this is an example of we had some pretty strong reference.
And in the beginning, a lot of these references
sort of translate very literally into the spaces.
And therefore, Corey, environment artist,
and one of the beginning holdover,
still with us from Unfinished Swan, built our first space.
And so this was like a pretty faithful reproduction.
We were getting areas that went from concepts
into their spaces very specifically,
and not yet knowing exactly the level of detail.
Come on, buddy.
There we go.
So we were able to put together a vertical slice
with this team.
No art direction, we had a lot of inspirations.
We were hitting mood.
But a big part of it was that, you know, as part of the gameplay, we had this experiment,
we had a whole house in addition to stories.
There were so many things to build, it was difficult for one person to do it.
And there are parts of it, you know, the essence is there, you know, but there are parts that
were empty.
We move forward like you saw in this room was empty.
We had areas that we started.
You're interacting with objects as one of our main mechanics.
And you're jumping from inside a house in one person's body
to inside a story in another person's body.
And so this is sort of where I came in
with a team of character artists.
And we sort of asked ourselves a question.
Is this?
I have some duplicates.
Is this a game?
Are we going to be the indie studio that
makes another game with a person without a body?
You look down.
I mean, there's a lot of challenges.
If we're going to have all these interactions,
suddenly we're committing to have to build out
characters for each one.
And yet, for me, I felt very strongly
that having this moment and the repeated essence of seeing
hands and seeing not your hands was very important.
So we started with an outsource,
and these were the first two hands in the game.
We had Edith and Molly, and it was also,
as I was assuring everyone, don't worry,
every kid can use the same small kid hands.
But it translated what was previously
empty, oh, I can't see what it's playing,
into moments like this.
And so, you know, despite the concern that this was not going to be enough time,
or this was not going to be enough bang for the buck, so to speak,
we sort of soldiered on.
You know, we went from moments that had read like this
in the vertical slice, you know, to moments more like this.
And then we have these moments of transition
where it was starting to change the design.
Trying to build something that communicated effectively
went from a purely design problem
or a purely static mesh problem
to like the combination of these elements.
In early versions of the game,
there was no hands in this scene,
which kind of gave us, didn't give us the opportunity,
oops,
to...
silently communicate.
Most people when they play the game
wouldn't necessarily think about who is this person.
But then being able to see them again at the end,
you have these like silent mechanics,
things that we didn't have to call out.
And so suddenly writing is being helped by art,
which is helping design.
And we didn't, this wasn't a preconceived notion.
It was just dealing with what was happening at the moment
with the assets that we had
and the moments that were working.
So sometimes environment art would rise
to meet the challenge.
Sometimes, whoops, sometimes character art would.
And so this is skipping a little bit ahead
in my narrative of how detailed it was,
but being able to start to build the game around this
as having access to it was meaningful.
In addition, those previously empty spaces
started to be filled with people that had impressions
and motivations and styles.
We were still trying to establish
what would be in these scenes, because in early versions,
we just had white sheets over all of the areas.
We knew that we wanted to have a story object in a space,
but we didn't know, are we hiding it?
Are we making it available?
Like, who are these people?
Do they know each other?
And part of that investigation came
through building the characters themselves.
Just show a few of these.
And there are stories actually, sorry,
there are stories like this one where the spindle
at one version just had no hands
and it didn't need an explanation.
But then later, when we iterated on stories like this one,
it would have been much harder
and much less of an experience
had we not committed to that early.
So there were stories that we never would have executed
the way that we did
had we not made these choices in the beginning.
And then.
I think I might have been overboard on our examples of characters.
But there were moments too where we promised there will only ever be hands, and then we
started to include more.
But never more than we could handle.
And so, with that information, level designer Chris Bell could go on and take rough outs
that looked like this, and start to build more bones.
Our previously empty spaces were partially empty
because we didn't have, we weren't sure
what needed to be included.
We knew we didn't want it to be overstuffed
with the wrong kinds of things.
We knew we wanted sort of mundane props.
We knew we wanted to have a sense of having been lived in
and sealed off, but who are these people?
So our level designer went through
and revised each room over and over again
as we built a better understanding of these characters.
and then generated very detailed gray boxes in Maya.
He did lots of temp prop modeling,
just as quick as he could to put something together
that communicated.
And then after searching through his image post history
on Slack, this is like not even 10%.
of the level of specificity that design,
based on the narrative, was providing
to this environment artists.
And then over time, like these gray boxes,
as we had more in the engine, got more sophisticated.
So we had things that looked more and more evocative
of the final product being delivered.
And so now with that level of information,
or this is my fun transition,
we could go and make,
not have to make trailers that look so much like this,
and instead transition to a team that could fill it out.
So we were joined by some AAA talent, Brandon Martynowicz,
and he put together an environment art team
that was ready to take all of these experiments
and all of this definition, and then start to get specific.
rather than just like color and mood studies where, you know,
our environment artists was sort of struggling to say, well, yes,
it's, you know, it's orange or yes, it's blue, but like, you
know, what are those blobs? So, you know, we got more specific
direction from concept art. We had strong tie-ins from
We hadn't lost the spirit of the original photos.
We had photos, we had color studies,
but we also had specifics.
Like these line drawings are very, very close
to what we ended up building.
And that'll let us just to finalize the look of the house.
We have these specific props telling specific stories
about people's lives and not sort of consuming
with a house with generic fill.
You're like, this was a house
that was specifically for the Finches.
Having that kind of specificity as well
provided context for the design team.
Suddenly we had a big machine
that was ready to churn out art.
And so some of these investigations
where we thought maybe it could be one way
or maybe it could be another,
like eventually if the game was gonna get shipped
we had this pressure that you had a team of people
that could make things look amazing
and much higher bar than we had expected before.
But it meant that we had to make some decisions.
So in addition to just increasing the overall quality
and polish, we started to get distinctive features.
We had the ability to really dive deep
on individual characters and locations
and round them out.
We also had
this is not the best representation, but we had time of days within stories,
and we also had a narrative shift with sort of like a behemoth technical effort
prior to bake sets and Unreal to allow the house to actually change
times of day as we move through.
And then also expanded our color palette.
We were building a range of experiences
that weren't just in our dark moody phase,
but turning into what becomes moody
after different snapshots of lives.
So these lives expanded.
And so in addition, another industry veteran, Keith Garrett,
came on with the experience coming from.
Naughty dog.
I don't know if he's here.
As a visual effects specialist, suddenly we
had these gorgeous looking scenes that were
more static than we wanted.
And there were problems, things that
were not even obvious problems that were solved.
But this moment, without the wake behind it,
sort of like a bobbing scene.
Suddenly, with more effect attention,
we get something that was a complete thought.
And so it was invaluable to be able to complete this thought
and also do honor to some of the original inspirations,
which is sort of like the sublime force of nature.
So we had moments in the scene where like,
very like you're finding out intense things in the story.
We also don't want to fill it with words.
So the ability to actually fill it with things
that looked beautiful and were evocative of the theme.
You know, it made a huge difference.
There are things that, you know,
could have been just rushed past through
that suddenly invites the players to stop and look.
We even had small one-off moments
after being able to time,
oh no, video, why?
The confetti comes, come on.
Let's see if I can't get it to work.
where visual effects have specific punctuation.
I have a moment.
So these were all things where we were kind of building this
as a boulder, it was a snowball rolling downhill
where we were grabbing things as they became available to us
and as they became necessary.
Without that, we had lots of hopes.
We had lists, lists and lists and lists of hit lists
on things that we hoped to be able to build in.
But it sort of created a meritocracy of,
or a hierarchy where the things would happen
as quickly as they could happen.
And if you had people that, they really cared about it.
You know, one of the other,
one of the things that came in sort of late to the project
is that we had hands early.
We had characters and we had locations.
But we worked with, towards the end of the project,
we worked with a character, or a illustrator, Holly Rothrock,
on giving the family faces.
We had an original inspiration for the project for the book
100 Years of Solitude.
And part of this thing was that these family members
were such a diverse and similarly named and stretched
out group that we had a family tree.
And some of our original desires were to keep a version of a family tree that looked like
someone had actually drawn and maintained it.
And this was a serious point of contention versus how plain looking could something be
and have us accept it as a final product.
So we went back and forth on how well can Edith really draw, how much energy would she
have put into this moment.
but ended up with a family tree at the end that ended up becoming a big part of the actual
gameplay experience.
We cycled.
We made sure we visited every time.
It reinforced these connections between these people.
And then eventually, at the end of stories, we ended up being able to see these faces
in the shrines.
And so really, there's nothing more evocative of the group effort that it took to put together
this game.
come with the final product in the shrines.
It was the effort of environment artists
to make these specific, carefully crafted props
for characters that grew over time,
originally, you know, bodiless, maybe photographs,
then they developed limbs,
then eventually bodies and painted faces,
into these moments that, you know,
it took an entire five years of development to make.
And so basically, in summary, I've sort of,
oh my gosh, we can't do this.
Can we?
Ooh, sweet.
It stopped.
So in summary, I've sort of like walked us through all of these moments as they,
oh, as they perfectly handed off to each other.
But honestly, there were parts of these that were tense.
It was difficult.
We believed in different things, and we weren't sure things were going to work out.
But in retrospect, I look at all of these choices like exactly the right choice was
made, a very few regrets and these final decisions, and
it comes together as a complete experience.
So my recommendation to art directors is build in some process of not knowing and leaving
space to figure things out just in time.
If we had pre-planned every aspect of these things,
there are whole portions of the game
that just wouldn't exist at all.
And having that space and being comfortable with it,
and then rebuilding over and over again,
I think we come up with some estimates.
We probably made 2 3rds as much material.
It's like we built three times as much
than actually made it into the final version
because we were willing to edit and build the right thing.
And so.
And this is also maybe just my bias, but thinking about hiring people that you trust with the
design of the final product and not necessarily just on the portfolio.
Obviously people have to be able to make the work, but I think it's harder to teach taste
than technique.
So that's my talk.
I think I burned through it.
Thank you.
It looks like I do have plenty of time for questions, so if anybody has a question, they
can come to the...
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
First of all, by the way, guys, in order to motivate you to ask some questions, there's
like a dozen T-shirts there.
So if anybody wants some swag, first 12 people get T-shirts.
But my question for Chelsea was actually, you mentioned that you did have some differences
as you were working through this.
And could you speak a little bit more to the process through which you resolved some of
these differences?
Because obviously a lot of passionate people there, passionate about maybe different things,
but only one can sort of survive through that process.
So how did that go?
I think on some, so the question was how,
speaking more in detail about the differences of opinion.
And I think my summary would be.
On some levels it was a war of attrition.
And on other levels it was just letting the ideas speak for themselves.
There was a lot of prototyping that was made with very
disparate quality levels to try to prove out a concept.
I think I myself put together a series of technical demos.
I think one thing was on the, our original version of the tentacle
was like segmented pieces and we were debating how we were going to procedurally
generate.
And I was like, the artists need to have control
over the tentacle.
This has to work.
So I made this kind of horrific little demo with a capsule
and attaching a physics rope to it
and just pathetically dragging it around
with the character controller.
And I'm like, like this, but good.
And so I went through three or four versions
and kind of built an increasingly horrifyingly
complicated contraption, but then finally convinced
the tech director that it was a reasonable way to go.
I think at the end of the day it was reality was coming down on us.
Things either worked or they didn't, and we really listened to whether or not it was true
to the story.
And so there were some things that we had avoided for a while that ended up being more
necessary.
There was even a moment where the game was going to be...
There were some moments where we weren't going to have a house at all because there wasn't
enough time, and now you're like, oh my God, I can't believe that almost happened.
So yeah.
Hi, great talk.
I was just wondering, when you have mostly creative individuals
who are more worried about creating assets and communicating
their ideas, how did you decide producer roles?
Who made tasks and made sure people were following through
on those tasks?
That's good.
Well, that's easy.
Oh, so the question was, how did we make sure
that work was followed through?
And that was pretty easy.
The creative director, Ian, was very on the current marching orders.
We didn't necessarily have a good sense of if everything was doable.
But then we had area leads of the technical lead
and the art lead that made sure
that those subtasks were organized.
So some indie teams have a completely flat hierarchy
that has no lead roles,
and that's something that I find to be difficult.
You almost have sort of like groups of people
that are pushing together on an effort sometimes,
even if it is a separate prototype.
But yeah, we definitely were organized
via creative direction.
I was just wondering if mechanics influenced art at all.
There are a lot of objects of significance in the stories
and things that you interacted with.
I'm wondering if the thing that you interacted with
specifically was influenced by the mechanic
that you were executing.
Oh man, that's a fantastic question.
So the question was, did mechanics affect the art
direction at all?
Correct?
OK.
They were so one in the same.
I mean, and I think one of the greatest
strengths of our open-ended design
is that we wanted an evocative experience,
and each thing had a hook.
So there was a specific request.
There's some things I could have said but called out,
but like one of.
creative directions ideas was the house was built in a certain timeline and then all further
updates were from items you could have purchased at Home Depot. So to not indulge in the like in
some kind of overly ornate Victorian aesthetic which also sort of extended to our story objects
where it's sort of like this should be a regular looking object. We didn't have crazy ornate keys,
we had uh it's like the
the master lock padlocks that were very simple.
We had, I mean, each of the story objects,
they were very difficult to build,
and we probably built like three times as many,
because the idea was that experience goal,
and we specifically, because like,
there are games that have interaction mechanics
that are, you know, which I respect this commitment,
where you say, you can open drawers, you can open doors,
you can pick things up and spin them around.
I think the only animation that we reused in that game was the walk cycle.
everything was bespoke, and it was that commitment to bespoke
that was, like, to me, a part of the art direction.
I don't, like, since Blur's the lines between design and art and everything else,
but, you know, I think, again, if we had said at the beginning,
no art, like, no animation would be reused, I think we actually could have saved
some time trying to, like, systematize, be like, no, just do a great job once.
because there was definitely a lot of time hoping we'd systematize things.
It was just like commit to bespoke.
Yeah.
One of your conclusions was building in time for not knowing and for free time.
Did you have trouble arguing for
doing that in terms of like finances and a timeline or was it pretty easy or
just how did you go about arguing that that time will be worth it?
I think
Okay.
Okay, I will answer the question in the wrap-up room.
Yes.
Thank you.