Hello.
Hi everyone.
Well, welcome to room 2016,
which is where my talk actually is, not room 2024,
which is where I thought my talk was
and could have caused things to end very, very badly
had a nice tall gentleman not sent me straight.
So I'm glad you're here.
I'm glad I'm here.
Let's do this thing.
But ceremonial housekeeping before we begin,
please turn your phones to silent.
Orbs.
face embarrassment when they play a tune that you're not expecting.
And I think we're good. Has everybody got seats?
It looks like we're maybe perfectly balanced in terms of habitation.
It's pretty cool.
Okay. So, welcome to Dots That Go For Walks.
My name is Margaret Robertson.
I'm a game director at a company called Dots.
See if you can keep up with me here,
but we've made three games,
dots,
two dots,
and then the groundbreaking, dots and co.
And so I'm currently looking after two dots,
and last year, so Judo is our biggest game.
And I'm looking after that at the moment.
Last year I launched Dots & Co, which is our newest game.
And that is what I do all day, every day,
is I look at those screens and I think about
how to make them different or better.
Dots are a big part of my life and my brain.
And that's why I love this quote so much,
which is where the title of the talk comes from.
A line is a dot that went for a walk.
Paul Clay, who you may know,
makes beautiful paintings like this.
I love the, I love the quote
because it encapsulates a thing that I've found
in the last couple of years of working on these games,
which is that even if you start
with this incredibly simplistic object,
hardly get more primal in terms of a shape in a circle,
the minute you start.
pushing at the question of what it can do
and where it can take you,
it can grow into far more exciting and interesting objects
than you ever dreamed possible.
But I also love the,
this is unbelievably exciting for me
that that quote isn't just a cute line,
it's a line from Paul Klee who I admire so enormously.
I'm not enough of an art historian to give you a kind of full breakdown of where his work fits into
various 20th century trends of obstruction and minimalism, but I am enough of a fan of art that
fits those descriptors to know that a lot of what is precious to me about that art, the way
that it can accomplish so much with such a restrained toolkit,
such a limited use of shape, abandonment
of representative, figurative elements,
this really meticulous and dynamic use of color.
Those are things, although it's not a,
a set of kind of resources that we necessarily look at very much in game, the game sphere,
perhaps spend as much time in modern art galleries as we should, but I know that whenever I kind of
go and spend some time in those environments, I come back with a whole bunch of ideas of things
that I would like to see kind of brought to life in the games that I'm making, because I think that's
an important note to hit before we kind of get into the guts of what does it take to do minimalist design well
in a game context and particularly in a commercial game context,
which is to make sure that you're really clear about what you're trying to accomplish and why it's worth accomplishing.
So I wouldn't want anyone to come away.
with a kind of, with the thought that
I'm suggesting any kind of hierarchy here.
I get excited about very, very minimalist design approaches.
I think there's a lot of admirable
disciplines they require of you
in terms of how you work and how you design.
But I'm also an enormous fan of
stupid, massive maximalist design.
I had a bit that I cut because we haven't got time about how
good the UI design in Ascension Chronicle of the God Slayer is.
I don't know if we have any Ascension fans in.
But it's an absolute, I was trying
to think of the least minimal UI I could think of in games,
and that's a strong candidate.
And it's absolutely masterful.
So if you can face the learning curve,
I'd quietly start downloading that now
because it'll take most of the session.
So these are the things that I find so resonant.
in work by Paul Klee or Richard Serra or Sol LeWitt or whoever else we might be looking at as a kind of art inspiration for this kind of design.
You know, these feel like the kind of bones,
the things that I'm really trying to feel out
in whatever it is I'm making,
that I want my games to have these hallmarks,
to have this feeling that they've been made
with restraint, with self-discipline,
that whatever elements I put in front of you
have this kind of total clarity and crispness
so that you feel their edges really cleanly.
I fundamentally like working in an abstract
rather than a figurative or a narrative environment.
And all of that needs to be delivered
with a very high degree of care,
or you just end up with something that feels inert
and cheap and flat.
So.
I spent a bunch of time looking at our own games,
looking at other games that I admire
that I think do this well,
and tried to put together a little kind of shopping list
of advice that I found useful.
So I thought I should start
by trying to live up to this list, right?
Okay, this is all nice, fine and dandy list,
but can I show you something
that really delivers those hallmarks?
Can I find a design approach
where I just with a few strokes,
with just the lightest of touch,
using all of this restraint,
reaching for all of this clarity,
I can add an element visually to the game
that gives me this impact.
So I gave it a go,
I put something together just before this talk.
So you'll have to tell me how I did.
This is what I came up with.
It's the word boat.
I'm not, it's funny, I'm not quite getting the applause
that I was hoping.
But you should be applauding.
Look at this thing, look at that thing.
It's a few beautiful lines, it's some perfect curves,
the verticals, it looks great.
It's a really beautiful pattern.
If you didn't know what that was,
and I duplicated it on a.
beautiful piece of fabric and made a dress out of it,
you would think it was the best thing you'd ever seen.
It's a complete abstraction and yet entirely represents
the entire concept and visualization of boat.
It is boat, but it is not boat.
It is the map, not the landscape.
It's extraordinary.
The more I look at it, the happier I get.
Because type.
does this really well.
Type is a very, very restrained mode of visual communication.
It has absolute clarity.
It delivers that abstraction, and it
delivers that precision.
But.
A boat is a boat is a boat.
And because I know that my stupid boat slide
wasn't gonna impress you enough,
it's all right, I had something up my sleeve.
Have you been seeing this guy's work on Twitter?
This popped up last week
and I fell in love with it so powerfully.
He's a designer who makes these amazing illustrations
out of the Arabic script for the word that they...
for the word for the thing.
So if you look in the bottom right of that panel,
there's the Arabic script for whale,
and then he draws out of that these gorgeous illustrations.
There's a whole collection of them.
There's foxes and monkeys and castles and crowns,
and it's the best.
And it just was a really useful reminder to me
of just how much a visual design element type is.
And it wasn't surprising that it was in my mind
because it turns out that other designers
of minimalist games also seem to think
that type is a good place to start
when you're trying to do this job well.
So this is the very initial onboarding tutorial screen
from three different games.
In the middle is Two Dots, which I currently work on,
but I didn't design this screen.
On the left is Sputnik Eyes, which is a super cute little spatial puzzler that's hard to
explain, but you should try.
And on the right is Noodles, that's Noodles, because it has an exclamation mark, which
is a pipe.
pipe them up.
I don't know what the genre is for those.
Also great, super satisfying.
And we all clearly kind of arrived
at the same conclusion here, which
is that we wanted to use type to make,
you know, kind of to set the tone of voice of the game
and define our initial interactions with the player.
And that's interesting to me, because there's
two super good reasons.
not to rely heavily on typography in games.
One is that games
aren't always the best type.
I don't mean to be mean,
but I was trying to think about games
where I felt strongly about the typography in them,
and it made me think of desktop dungeons.
And desktop dungeons is an absolute masterpiece.
I've put hours and hours and hours and hours and hours into it.
But the, um...
The type in this game is so bad. It's really, really bad.
There's so many... Just look at...
Just keep looking at it and seeing more things you don't like about how...
Oh!
The things that don't line up and things that aren't...
They have to have black outlines because they don't...
Oh! It's... So it's just not...
It's... And it's... It's not...
Not good because nobody cared, it's because it's hard,
because you're asking that kind of content
to do a whole bunch of different things at once,
and you've got a real chance of falling short
somewhere along the way.
And here's the other reason that it's a scary, weird thing
to put your faith in.
It's like the second thing you learn in this job
or whatever species of this job that you have.
Right, people don't read, nobody reads.
And I...
obeyed that rule for a really long time.
But I've now spent enough time in in-house user tests,
watching people play, talking to them after they play,
looking at screens like the ones we just looked at,
that I think I've invented a new variation of the rule, maybe
rule 2.5, which is this.
Writing is probably at the bottom of most players'
visual priority list.
If you give them anything else juicier to look at,
they're going to look at that.
So the reason that these three screens have all
ended up looking so similar is that if you're
going to get this to work, it has to be pretty much
the only game in town.
You have to make the text this big, pleasing, eye-catching,
attention-grabber that's going to pull people's attention.
I in and their attention in and then hopefully
they will tap the thing with the thing,
which is really all you're ever trying to tell anyone to do.
Please, please tap the thing with the thing.
And that, of all the things I just said
is why it felt like a really good starting point
for things to talk about today.
Because type is powerful.
I love how it looks, I want to use it.
If I'm going to use it well, it needs to own the screen.
If it's going to own the screen, I need to make space.
And making space is probably your single biggest job
if you're trying to do good, minimalist user experience
design in games.
You're taking these very, hopefully, beautiful, simple,
refined elements.
You need to give them room to breathe.
You need to.
Games can be such cluttered, busy, noisy places.
You need to find a way to just push all of that to one side,
find that space and that emptiness, the calm
and the clarity that your design is
going to be able to sit inside.
So when I'm trying to get myself in the right frame of mind
to do that job, I look for inspiration
to someone whose work I'm just a huge admirer of.
I don't think it'll surprise you to know
that I'm thinking of Arnold Schwarzenegger in Predator.
There is a man who knows how to get things done.
He's got some good advice for us.
Stay with me on this one,
because it's going to work out.
So, you're in that situation
where you are simultaneously trying to defeat
a kind of cyborg alien bounty hunter in the jungle
and overhaul the UI of your minimalist puzzle game,
the first verb that you might need to think about
is hiding.
Crucial strategy that I learned from Predator.
It's a really easy tool to make space.
There's a bunch of stuff that is on your screen.
It all needs to be on your screen
because it's all important.
Maybe it doesn't all need to be on your screen all the time
because maybe it isn't important at different moments.
So this is the beautiful Mini Metro.
I kind of think, right, everyone in this room
must be playing Mini Metro,
otherwise you're in the wrong room.
Who's a Mini Metro person?
Guys, come on.
Super good.
It's maybe extra super good if you lived in London
for a long time, but it's super good.
So this is a very, very simple real-time puzzle game
where you're trying to build and service
a continually growing network of subway stations.
So you have some limited resources
in terms of carriages and lines and trains, bridges.
But you have an ever-growing pile of passengers
and an ever-growing number of stations.
And you need to keep trying to find the best fit solution.
And then the game does gorgeous things
about drawing and routing the train lines that you're
putting in place as if it were as a real beautiful map.
And to help you do that well, you can speed up and slow down time, as is often the case in games of this sort.
But they just quietly hide that UI in the top right.
So if you tap on the clock, those controls drop down, then they go away again.
With a really lovely treatment on the clock.
where the clock is doing, the clock is great,
it's a button that's also a status readout
of whether it's day or night,
and it's also your time readout
in terms of how fast time is passing,
and it also shows you whether or not time is paused.
And it does all of that in a lovely little circle
that is also a cute joke about the famous
Swiss railway clock design that
rail design people love to make jokes about.
It's super simple, but this game would feel,
if it loops around again,
this game would feel so different
if that whole right-hand wall was just blocked off
all the time with all of those icons.
It needs that space to give you that curve
in the top corner so much.
This game has a bunch of really nice tricks up its sleeve.
I haven't got time to talk about them all today,
but the way it handles.
What happens to you when you lose,
which is a thing you'll find out very quickly
when you try it for the first time.
This is really nicely handled.
So, R&E tip number one, hide.
It's a good way of making space.
R&E tip number two, merge.
By which I mean,
you'll remember that the absolute crucial maneuver
in Predator was that he discovered
if he glooped himself all the way into the mud,
then the Predator couldn't see him.
which was at the forefront of my mind
when we were trying to figure out
how to do hard currency purchase design for Dotson Co.
So Dotson Co. came out in the middle of last year.
It was the first hard currency game
that the studio had done.
And so we spent a bunch of time trying to figure out
how to do it well.
Oh, I need to go quite fast now.
And to begin with, we were really flailing, I think.
A bunch of talented smart people worked really hard on these screens, but I don't think they
would mind me saying that they are suboptimal in a lot of their designs.
The thing on the far left is just so inert and sad.
and playing we try to live in a bit with better illustrations in the middle but
now the whole thing is just super busy the flashes and workers flashes
it's not there is isn't about and everything that is bad
three through it all and started again which is what you have on the far right
and things are getting better but there's still a bunch of
dislocation between what is an interactive
and
It's visually overwhelming, there's too many colors,
everything's tricksy.
And the thing that was holding us back
was we hadn't listened to Warny.
Merging saved us.
So this is pretty much the same content,
but now all of the visual elements are just merged
with the actual button elements.
So each of those two pink panels is a giant button.
And once we saved ourselves, just the lines,
the physical lines of trying to delineate
all of these different things of like,
here's an illustration and here's a button
and here's an informational panel
that's gonna sit next to the button,
was killing us.
You squidge it all into one thing.
And it doesn't always feel like a very minimalist instinct
because...
piling things on top of each other
doesn't seem like a minimal idea,
but if they're the right things,
you can kind of collapse space
and they all land neatly on top of each other
and then you can give yourself far more space,
space to actually enjoy those illustrations
and then the clarity to really cut down on that color load,
which is much, much better.
TouchTone does this really nicely as well.
I don't know, I bet fewer people have played TouchTone.
Super nice.
It's like a laser angler reflector game.
Also don't know the genre for that one.
With a super weird sly story
that is gonna feel horribly resonant now
in a way that it didn't before
about the surveillance state.
But they do the super simple thing that their
That color illustration, that thing that's giving you
a sense of being in the city, is the button.
So that's the play button.
And each time you go to a new place,
that's the vision that you have of the new thing.
And it's smart.
It's so simple, it would have taken me forever to see it.
I would have ruined that screen trying
to figure out how to embed the play button around
or on top of the bit of illustration
that I was trying to add to kind of be evocative of how
the thing was going to work.
Hide, merge.
I'm not doing a get to the chopper or any impression
because it's not my strong suit.
But evacuation, key part of a strategy,
take the things you don't need
that aren't mission critical, get them out of the way.
Here's another Dotson Co example.
This is like early, we're like midway
on the branding work that we did on Dotson Co.
We'd been a little bit lost
and we were so
pleased to get here to this really strong, simple shape.
There's so much smart thinking in this.
We've got the solid O's in Dots & Co.
or a callback to the two dots logo.
So we had that nice brand cohesion that went through.
The shape of the whole thing reinforces
the shape of the virtual currency object
that we have, which is a token.
The compass motif in the top was then an element
that we were gonna be able to repeat
in a whole bunch of...
like narrative settings elsewhere in the game
that we were kind of building out
this little adventure club idea around it.
The needle in the middle of the compass
is the shape of the special triangular dot
that is invented in Dots & Co.
It's genius, it's just so,
it's so much smart thinking has gone into that.
So we killed it, because it was so busy being clever,
it wasn't any good.
Because it was just too much, it was far, far, far too much.
So despite the fact that we had a bunch of good.
strategic thought behind it.
It just wasn't adding up to anything
that really captured the spirit of what we were trying to do.
So what you're seeing on the right
is basically the current login screen.
The map behind it changes depending
on where you are in the world.
So that's constantly evolving.
But that and the Facebook button, if you're not logged in,
is the only screen for it that we have.
And we ended up going with this incredibly typographic approach
for the logo because it was just the most bang for buck.
It was the biggest impact that we could have with the least.
detail that got in the way of us doing anything else.
So we threw that stuff out.
Sometimes it's stuff we didn't,
we threw out that we didn't even realize that we threw out.
So this is also a Dotson Co screenshot.
Every now and again, our games get cloned.
And so you get strange situations where
somebody will put a game in the app store
with just like screenshots stolen from your app store.
but then in a weird effort to try and make it,
I don't know why, but in a weird effort,
they sometimes change the screenshots a bit
to try and disguise the fact that they've stolen them.
So we found this the other day,
and initially all we could notice
was that basically what they'd done
was it looked like they'd taken
one of the characters from MuJo
and stuck it on top of our companion.
Now MuJo, side note, is an iOS game
made by these guys, Oink Games.
I think their digital work is really good.
I think their paper and tabletop work is spectacular.
They make basically, I think, the coolest looking tabletop
and board games anywhere in the world right now.
I love their stuff so much.
You should go and follow them on Twitter.
So yeah, it was weird.
It was like somebody just pulled out a bit of their art
and stuck it on top of ours.
And that distracted us for a bit.
And it distracted us for so long that we didn't notice this.
But the other thing they'd done.
was they put eyes on the turtles.
And that was really interesting because we'd never
thought about putting eyes on the turtles.
And now we realize that it was right
because it's weird and terrible and they don't need eyes.
And it's a kind of useful question
as to whether or not we should.
Give me a different perspective on the concept
of feature culling when we start asking
whether or not things needed eyes or noses.
This is another good example of that.
This is Reigns, which again you should play if you haven't.
It's a super cute like.
lightweight choice based RPG, you're the king of a country
and advisors come to you and get over and over and over
with a simple question and you make a binary choice,
left or right, and then your country prospers
or doesn't accordingly.
This is the Archbishop of Kotaburi, not Canterbury,
have to say that carefully.
He doesn't have a nose or a mouth, poor Archbishop.
And that made me wonder, maybe he doesn't need eyes.
If turtles don't need eyes,
why do archbishops need eyes?
And I think it's a really interesting thing,
which is he does need eyes,
because he still reads as a human character right now.
He still probably even reads as an archbishop,
but
Without the eyes, you lose that sense of connection
and you lose that sense of his snarky, untrustworthy frame
of mind.
And so that, as you're evacuating all of the stuff
out of your game that you think you don't need,
that's.
definitely a way to be on, you know,
the need is to watch out for have you gone too far.
The turtles don't need eyes,
because the eyes aren't helping,
but they do need to be turtles,
because them being turtles tells you a huge amount
about what to expect out of them as game objects.
They move on their own.
They go into their shells.
When you hit them, they come back out of their shells
after you hit them.
A turtle is a hell of a way to communicate.
What would otherwise be the world's biggest tool tip
to take you through all of that?
So they don't need eyes, but they do need to be turtles.
He does need eyes, but he doesn't need a nose.
Any questions?
Archbishop's nose.
Okay, perfect.
Also, if you're obeying your irony rules,
look at the nice merge they've done in the top of the UI.
So the four icons are kind of the four different estates.
the church, the army, the coffers.
Each time you make a choice, they're impacted.
And the degree to which they're impacted
is shown by the size of the change
and the nature of the change
is shown by the color of the change.
So green means better and red means worse.
And then the icons represent the things themselves.
And it's just super great.
They could have garbage that up
with a ton of like bars and texts
and a whole bunch of things,
but they found a really, really simple way to do it.
Orny, hide, merge, evacuate, you'll recall, kill.
Last, I think, Dotson Co. example,
just because I know a lot about it.
This was the original character select screen.
In Dotson Co., you have a little companion
who goes with you into the game and helps you out each level.
The original concept was that you would have
a rookie and an expert companion available each level.
The rookie was free, the expert cost hard currency,
but was more powerful.
And we put a ton of work into finding the right way to make this choice clean.
And we stuck button upon button upon button and tried swiping paradigm upon swiping paradigm.
Just got into a situation where we could, you know, you were, you were.
chasing your tail, you would fix this problem
and then cause a new problem and run and run and run.
You would go.
And where we ended up was here.
So it's the same mono button solution.
So again, rather than having to navigate button
plus illustrative element plus informational element,
everything's bundled together.
But the other thing you'll notice
is we basically killed the feature.
This is a different take on the same feature.
So there's still an option to make a hard currency
purchase to up your chances of beating the level.
But we lost the idea that there would
be two separate characters that you were choosing between,
because it was just too much of an information
burden at a moment in the game where
you want things to be smooth and fast and about anticipation.
So we killed the, well, we didn't kill the penguin,
but sort of.
Sorry, Anita.
She's wearing a scarf.
OK, I'm definitely over time, so these
are going to go crazy fast.
Orny wouldn't be Orny without some kind of secret weapon.
This is our secret weapon.
I can't recommend this strongly enough.
Everything we make is 100% colorblind playable.
And it's an enormous amount of work.
And it's prodigiously worthwhile.
So this is a pretty complex Docks and Coast screen.
We've got a bunch of stuff going on.
We've got dots that explode into squares.
We've got dots that auto-connect to other dots.
We've got dots that auto-connect to other dots that are inside.
Dots that only open when you match next to them.
And there's balloons that are going up
to the top of the screen.
There's panels that change the color
of dots that fall into them.
It's all moderately overwhelming from a design perspective
if you're just playing.
But if you turn colorblind on, now all of that
has to function successfully.
with the shape system that we have on top of that.
And every single mechanic that we put in the game,
even if it seems like we don't know how to do it,
we won't put in unless we can make colorblind work.
And we do that because it's nice.
You wouldn't believe how many letters we get from people.
You wouldn't believe how many people
don't think they're colorblind,
but still find it incredibly useful
to have that kind of facility within a game.
Super, super worthwhile.
It's an incredibly good discipline for us as designers.
It just forces you to be incredibly restrained
and precise in how you work.
And...
Because you figured out all of your colorblind design
at a formal level, it gives you the freedom
to do whatever the hell you want with color anywhere else.
And that maybe is the thing that is the most vital tool
in our toolbox for doing good minimal design,
which is that we invest a wildly high proportion
of our energy into color.
So we redo the palette of the game.
Every, this is two dots so far,
Dots & Co also does this.
It's a huge amount of work to settle on those palettes
and then make sure everything works against everything else.
It's unbelievably worthwhile because it is a way
of giving the game a sense of richness and luxury
without adding detail or texture or complex illustration.
And so that kind of double whammy of using colorblind
as an opportunity to make sure that our designs
are really, really, really restrained.
and then being able to do things with color was fantastic.
I got one thing that's cooler than rainbow ink.
Invisible ink.
These are the design elements that we use
to make our minimal design work
that don't show up on screen.
This is the biggest one.
Music and sound.
If you're trying to do minimal design
and you're not including these as a cornerstone
of how your design is gonna work,
you're making life way harder for yourself
than it needs to be.
We're unbelievably reliant on how smart our sound team are
for supporting the work that we try and do
in terms of the aesthetic that we're trying to hit.
And then that also goes for things like vibration.
Did that buzz?
Yeah, one of the best bits of visual design we have in the game is that when you make a square, it buzzes.
And because it buzzes, we don't have to do anything else.
We actually do do some other things,
but we have to do so much less
because we have that vibration in there.
So when you're hitting a ceiling visually,
you're like, there's more I need to communicate,
but my screen's getting too busy,
this thing's starting to feel noisy and not minimal enough,
remember that you have other tools at your disposal
that aren't visual.
Because I think that's the thing
that I've been most conscious of
coming to work at this company.
We're 50 people now.
And...
If everyone doesn't buy into the virtue
of a minimal aesthetic, you're gonna have
a really hard time holding onto it,
especially in a commercial setting.
Minimalist is fragile.
You can ruin it real quick just by sticking
an extra button in there, or a new texture,
or a dumb keynote animation transition
that I should.
not use but I can't resist.
You need everybody to be invested in keeping things clear
and keeping things clean,
in figuring out how their discipline,
whether they're game designers or product managers
or musicians or whatever else they do,
can hold the line and let the work stay clean and beautiful
as you want it to be.