We'd like to welcome our speaker today, Kevin Aguazza.
He's a gameplay programmer at Studio Gobo out of Brighton, UK,
working on an unannounced AAA game.
A treasurer at Game Workers Unite, UK.
In chat, you can ask Kevin about the state of unionization
in the global games industry, how unions may affect the game
industry, things like that.
So we're going to try to steer clear away
from topics that involve very specific country-based labor
laws.
So if you could just keep that in mind.
So Kevin, if you're ready, you want to take the first question?
All right, the first one comes from Grant Chen, who says,
uh, I'm okay with my working conditions, but I'm worried about the industry as a whole.
Should I be trying to push for unions at my current job,
or should I try to help others unionize? What actions should I take? Great question.
Right. Um, so I think it's very, very good that you want to like,
help make the industry a better place.
And I think in your situation, the first thing you might do is to just go to your
work colleagues and speak to them and ask them how they feel about their job, what
their problems are, how things are going, and just try to get an oversight, an
overview of what the problems and positive things are that your colleagues have to
say about your work and sort of get an overview about their particular
Particular groups of people that have particular issues, you know, certain minorities or women or other, or a particular department, like maybe, you know, the team lead of the programmers is very different management style, let's say, than maybe the game designer.
And so trying to figure out in your own company, speaking just to your colleagues sort of casually, you know, how they feel about work, what are the issues and what might they be able to do about it.
As somebody in the past tried to like.
Improve something or go to HR or start a, like, maybe a group for women or something like that.
Did something like that happen in the past? How did it go? Why did it fail? Why did it succeed?
And sort of try to work out how your workplace is structured and what the issues are and
how, trying to figure out how you can improve it with your colleagues. And then
that's sort of the very, very first step of organizing. At some point you might decide,
hey, I need help with, like, legal advice on manpower or...
You know, capacities, you might get in contact with union or set to join a union with your colleagues.
And then that union will help you do that, what I just described, more effectively and more streamlined.
Great.
We have another question from Kabir Seth.
How do you feel about game developers not being given overtime pay due to them being exempt from FLSA?
Would the union try to make changes to this law?
I'll be citing the specific law a bit.
Okay.
But it's fine.
But like in general,
so that most of the time in this use,
some paid, I think it was like three quarters out of,
at in 2017 in a survey, but it might be slightly off there.
And also, so it depends the country and local labor laws.
Right?
Some countries, overtime is mandatory,
and some countries it's not.
But I want...
situation we run into, particularly in the UK, is that we have workers that are wrongly classified,
for example, as zero-hour contractors or just contractors, when really they should be classified as an
Employees can get the full benefits. One of the things you went into is situations where you might
fight to get you reclassified from being, you know, an outside contractor with no overtime pay
into being a full employee with maybe statutory overtime pay. There's one avenue you might go
about doing that. All these other things that might be happening, especially with like huge
long periods of overtime you can run into in the UK for example into super hard labor law violations on break time and rest periods like for example in a 14 day time span you need to have at least one
An entire day we're not working at all.
If you come in the office for six, sorry, seven days straight, Monday to
Sunday, then you do the same day the next week, it's a hard, hard break time
violation in the UK and, you know, there are legal avenues, so we usually
don't start with like the full lawsuit legal avenue, you know.
We tried to talk to other people at the company and said, and it's very
difficult, are other people working overtime?
Is it unpaid?
How much do you work?
Do some people get paid and other people not?
Um, do some people get paid more overtime than others?
We then see a case where in a language translation,
sort of Nordic, Nord,
Nord-European languages were paid at a higher rate
than South-European languages,
which there were cases in the past
where that was a basis for like a discriminatory suit
based on self-discrimination towards more believer
in southern languages being paid differently in like rates.
But sort of the puzzle would be trying to figure out,
try to get an overview of what's happening in the tech company
who got overtime pay.
Then approach management just informally.
Probably you might do that.
Then the union approaching management informally.
Then say, okay, this is the state and we might,
and we think there might be a case for a lawsuit.
or another avenue, or there has been an accumulation in the past,
and here's what we will do if you don't fix it.
Then, you know, we slightly escalate bit by bit into maybe doing a full-blown lawsuit
or something else.
Maybe, you know, sometimes even bosses don't really know labor law.
All that well, especially in big international companies.
So sometimes they're like, Oh, I didn't know that you couldn't do that.
So I just need to sort of focus and say, Hey, what you're doing here is really not
okay.
And then they're like, Oh, sometimes that does happen.
Bosses don't know everything.
Let's keep that in mind.
Olivia Schwerz asks, any best practices for someone new to the industry who has
concerns about reported working conditions?
Mm-hmm. I mean, I think if, like, sort of before your first job,
you're looking for a first job, and you don't have, like, many
industry contacts, it's hard to, like, get access to the Zoom
memo, right, where people are just sort of casually at
conferences that, you know, in corona times don't really exist
in the same way. Or local meetups, they just, you know,
talk about the workplace. And usually I'd say that if
you finish it in a job or a location, you know.
Go to local events, go to conferences, try to speak to people, figure out what they think
about the employer.
And usually, after a beer or two, they will tell you a lot, probably more than they should.
It's a little bit harder to do.
It's corona.
People don't usually just gather in large masses anymore.
So you can...
And this happened to me.
Someone just hit me up on LinkedIn and I was like, hey, can I ask you a couple of questions
about your company?
Do you like it there?
And I was like, sure.
I have that personality. I can try to identify people that work there, try to speak to them,
see what they think. If you're already working there, it's a larger company,
as I said, it might be entirely possible that certain apartments or locations or buildings or
other sort of splits have very different conditions and issues than other ones.
So it's always good to speak to your colleagues, especially more diverse ones.
If you're a man, try to speak to some women.
If you're a white person, try to speak to some people of color and see what their
experience is like at a company to get a better overview of parts of the
entire company culture.
Great.
Great questions so far.
Keep them coming.
I'll try to get them all in here.
This one's from Becky Grady.
There are so many different roles in the games industry,
developers, designers, project managers, community, et cetera,
who have very different needs and challenges.
Are current initiatives looking to unionize
games industry workers as a whole
or focusing on one area, specifically one discipline?
And how will that choice affect the contracts, expectations, timelines, etc.?
Sure.
I think the situation at least was that the sort of small bits of the games in the Swedish
international unit have been unionized for a longer time.
Usually very specific roles that are sort of coming from other industries, like after
before the emergence of SEG to become SEG-AFTRA in the US.
They had their first interactive media agreement, right?
They didn't even use the term video games back then, in 1993, sort of laying
out the conditions for voice actors to work in interactive media, slash the
games industry, and that's nearly 30 years ago.
Oh my God.
Wow.
It's nearly 30 years ago.
Um, but it's a long time ago and you know, you have voice actors.
motion capture artists, sometimes writers, or other like more specific, you know, people
that have specific skills that are applicable to modern games industry, usually oftentimes
come from outside group existing union experience of membership into the games industry.
And I think that has worked to some degree for, you know, if you happen to have that
very specific skill set.
But the plan of what you see, the new unions coming up,
GamesWorks UK in the UK,
Sparta AWGB,
GamesWorks United Ireland in Ireland,
as part of the Financial Services Union,
GamesWorks Finland as part of
I finished on that I forgot and as well as the union, which
popped up recently in France, they all aim to unionize the
entire industry across disciplines. To a certain
degree, we had discussions about like, what about people in
eSports, professional eSports players, game journalists,
contractors, people working in finance, people working in the
cafeteria of your building.
you know, helping to make the environment conductive to making good games.
Where do we sort of draw the line? And at least in the UK we said,
okay, everybody who works at a company that makes games
or a department that makes games predominantly, they can join the union.
So they could be a writer, an artist, a programmer like I am, or whatever.
The idea being that
First of all, there's strength in solidarity.
The more people across the company, the more employees across the company, trying to achieve
something, the easier it gets, right?
There's strength in being part of a large group.
But also, there are some concerns about people, different disciplines, can have very, very
different experiences.
An external contractor working in QA for a company that may be slightly above minimum
wage, hopefully, is a very different experience to a very highly paid programmer.
But if they are part of the same union, they're pulling or pushing in the same direction.
And they can lift each other up.
And it's very important to us that especially the roles that have,
you know, are traditionally a little bit more pushed aside,
are being empowered by the people who traditionally have a little bit more power and like
bargaining room with the company.
So that's why we, that's why I think recent initiatives
all are starting out trying to go for as wide
of a group of people working against as possible to get as
much power to negotiate and to not leave anyone behind that has
already traditionally been left behind.
Excellent. Next one comes from Joanna Thomas, who asks, will unions help the issues concerning lack of diversity in the games industry, including like harassment issues and hiring diversity issues.
That's a good question. And
I don't think it's a sad answer, but I think they can if they set out to do it, right?
You know, there have been unions in the past.
If you look at, let's say, early 1900s in America,
there were no unions where unions were perpetuating white supremacy
and didn't allow any black people to join,
while still getting benefits for the white union members.
So there can definitely be a tool that sort of...
Circles in a privileged group to give them more benefits while leaving other people out.
But if you try to avoid it, if you try to push for a structure, for a union that actually plans to do
and increase diversity and stuff, there's lots of things you can do. I'm looking for example at
a lot of the organization that has been happening in games writing.
Vice or other places in the US were in the buy-in contract
that pushed very hard to get the company to spend more money on diversity
or have better reporting processes for sexual harassment.
Or I think Singapore's vice media,
where they especially pushed to give trans employees a better healthcare
because they usually have...
higher medical needs than non-trans employees.
And if it's a goal that you set, it's a priority for the union as a whole, then I think it
can be a very strong tool to achieve that.
But they don't necessarily have to be.
There are bad examples.
A police union will not probably make the US police much more diverse and friendly.
But it still gives this particular group of police officers a lot of power that maybe they shouldn't have.
But it's a different discussion.
But I think, yeah, unions are a tool to achieve something.
And what you achieve with them really depends on how the union is made up and who's in it and who's not.
Great. Moving on next one, getting some upvotes.
One from Andrew Ross, who asks,
what can press and players do to help workers unionize?
That's interesting.
So I think in recent years, since maybe 2017,
we really started going and sort of to international gamers first,
reporting on labor conditions, you know,
at Rockstar or Riot Games or other places.
Yeah.
And I think that's very good and supporting people know that, but to some degree, lots of people in the game industry do already know that.
So it's really, so that really helps like bring these issues to the players, the people who play games, to be more informed.
Now, I don't think that will sort of result.
necessarily in like boycotts or anything like that.
I don't think boycotts based on labour conditions are a viable strategy in this industry, but
it helps raise awareness and particularly in this age of brands and branding, nobody
wants to be associated with a bad brand.
So that can help, that awareness can push companies to do better, to preserve the brand
image.
Translated into brand image goes directly to profit margins to some degree, right?
So that is good.
But it's also, I personally fear the idea that you just keep reporting month
for month on this company is bad condition, this company is bad conditions
and people will sort of just accept that as the baseline.
And this should be expected.
Like when you get to the point where people aren't surprised anymore
that they are bad condition, they just sort of accepted them.
Because that's the only thing they hear about.
That might lead to sort of people getting numb to the problems.
Which, that's why I think it's important to also not only sort of focus on the
problems, but sort of focus on the people who are trying to solve them.
I very much enjoyed the reporting on the Riot Games walkout and the whole sort of
movement and happening around that.
And you can compare that one to one to, I think, five years earlier.
2015, when there was a walkout at Crytek because Crytek, I think, in England, did not pay wages
for a bit.
So we just didn't shop to work.
They walked out of Crytek because they weren't getting paid to work.
And it was reporting sort of on that.
But if you compare that reporting to reporting with the walkout at Riot Games, it's night
and day on focus on the people doing the actual organizing on the ground.
You might hear that in the background, something's going on here.
But just setting a focus on the people affected and the people trying to help themselves,
rather than just the issue of sort of, well, there is an issue that exists.
End of article.
Yeah.
Great. How about this one is interesting. It's from Gabe Pofker.
What role can worker-owned cooperative studios play in supporting unions and unionization?
Do you have any thoughts on that, Kevin?
Yeah, I mean, I think work on cooperatives is, in my opinion,
for at least small-sized companies of the ideal form.
I also don't think that in the next decade or two, everybody's
going to switch to being a worker on cooperative. I don't
see the worker on DA coming without a grander sort of
cultural or labor revolution driving them towards that. So I
think that if you're starting out trying to form a new company,
that it might be a very viable model you want to look at to a
have a fairer company structure, but also be a more attractive company structure because
getting direct part ownership of a company, part ownership of the profit, that makes people
more invested.
And if people are more invested, I think they will do better work.
But also, if you're in a very big company or an international company or a company,
it's just too unwieldy to have everyone be a part owner.
Then I think it's where a union would slot in with a collective bargaining agreement, right?
Where the wider employees, the wider employeeship is part of the union that sets out
or negotiates a collective bargaining agreement with the company that sets out
working conditions, reimbursements, bonus pay, and that kind of stuff
for everybody working at the company.
So, and sort of applies for everybody, slightly depending on which country, but
rectifying agreements can just apply to everybody working at a location,
and even new people joining and that kind of stuff.
I remember talking once to the owner of a small indie company, he said like,
you're talking about like, yeah, what happens if your product,
your small product just blows up and becomes hyper successful?
How much if a small company is just, you know, based on gentleman's agreements?
And sort of vacant ascending said, things should be fine.
But you know, you saw a million dollars at any group of people.
And you know, these sort of gentlemen, nice, nice social
rules and regulations start breaking down.
So, so I said to him that maybe he wants to just
It might be a benefit in having a union with a collective bargaining agreement
because A, now the union can worry about making sure people are happy and he
doesn't have to worry as much about making sure people are happy and figuring
out what their issues are, the union will do that for him and negotiate with him
to make sure people get what they want.
But also if the collective bargaining agreement contains rules about, hey,
profit shares or things like that, that the people, that the employees discuss
themselves and worked out the bargain for.
That sort of means that the employees will feel like that
is sort of fair and a feeling of fairness that you have if
you're part of a work on cooperative, cooperative can
software replicated by adding these sorts of things into a
collectifying agreement of the company as a whole.
Great. Tobias Eisner asks, as the industry is quite global and unions usually are bound to national laws, how could this problem be addressed for our industry, creating one international standard and avoiding the fragmentation as it is common in other industries?
So how can this be more of an international movement and not be fragmented?
So I go point, there are some few unions that try to operate entirely globally.
Uh, international workers of the world, the AWW is one that tries to do that.
But you know, as a person said in specific countries, you've got specific
labor laws and you need to incorporate in specific things, probably membership
and probably membership currency are split.
So, uh, uh, it's not really like one entirely global organization, but they
try as much as they can to push towards that.
Which I think is an interesting idea.
But, um...
Um...
I've already spoken a lot about, like,
how we think about unions often as...
If an industry is global,
and we think of unions often as also global
or maybe national.
It's entirely possible to have a union for
a company of
20 people in the UK.
A union is just for that one company.
And we're always about that one company.
Um...
Lots of unions now spring up.
Back in the day, where like particular companies or, you know, miners in one mine had issues.
So they unionized to make the issues at that mine be better.
And I think on that level, you maybe don't need to worry about the international, you
can just worry about your own particular issues at the workplace.
But of course, in this globalized economy, there's the threat of outsourcing or, you
know.
If you're part of a big international company, then they might decide to shut that location
down and outsource it somewhere else as a threat that a lot of people have.
Or if you push too far, if you demand too much, you might just make the whole thing
go away.
To which I say, well, nobody opens up an office building in San Francisco and hires highly
paid engineers.
to then immediately throw the whole thing away once they start demanding a little bit more.
Maybe start demanding a little bit more for the people who aren't as highly paid as they are.
But I've been going around Europe a bit in the recent couple of years,
being to unions in Sweden, Denmark, France, Finland.
And I remember I was talking to
I'm a member of Unionen, which is sort of the biggest Swedish union as a whole.
And Sweden being a very unionist country in general, big union membership.
And it's starting to make me think that they have enough money in their wall chest so that
every single member of the union could go on strike for multiple years and not get paid
anything.
They have their wall chest that allows them to have a lot of bargaining power because
they can literally strike for forever, essentially.
versus we, as a very new union, we do not have a watch that big
where you can pay everybody salaries in full for years. But
again, going slightly back to the Riot Games walkout, you know,
did see the solidarity of people working at other locations. And
I think in Dublin, in Ireland, there was also a walkout by
people, but they are on solidarity. And
And I think in this more globally connected world, it's much easier for struggles in one
region or one arm of the company to reach people working in other regions or other parts
of a company and to have solidarity action across the globe.
It's much easier than it was, you know, before the digital age.
So I think there's definitely possibilities to coordinate and cooperate across borders.
And again, just as we said, okay, we want to get as much
different people inside of a union. So the more privileged
people that can help the less privileged people, whatever the
particular privilege may be. Same is true for cross borders.
If multiple unions across borders of a company cooperate,
then if the highly paid engineers in San Francisco can
send them solidarity with them, maybe definitely not as highly
paid QA testers in India.
That very much can help with bargaining power and improving the situation.
Great. All right, we have about two minutes left. Let's try to get two more in.
There's one from, just came in from Ryan Lippert.
What, if anything, could I do between now
and when this person graduates law school shortly? What can they do
between now and then to get some relevant experience in this area?
And are there any specific reading recommendations this person's interested
in getting into this subject?
Hmm, reading recommendations and law school. I just assumed from
the term law school that it's about us. In which case, what
you should do as a lawyer in the US sort of outside of my, my
knowledge, but when it comes to sort of general reading
recommendations. And now we can show a book in camera. Secret.
Nope.
I think it's a successful organizer by labor notes.
This book that sort of lays out okay, how do I approach how to
approach organizing my workplace? I'll sort of start
to finish what I think to look out for what are you know,
things that organizers have learned over the decades of
organizing. And this book as well as like other books by
labor notes are very good resources about organizing. When
it comes to legal resources, well, I guess.
Become familiar with the National Labor Relationship Act.
As I said in the beginning, that's sort of outside of my realm of knowledge.
I think that's probably all they need. They want a little resource. And then we'll go over where
you can find Kevin and his organization online. Let's try to get this one in. Gabriel Mikl,
sorry, pronunciation. I don't have the temperament to organize or lead a union.
However, I would like to join one.
Am I doomed to a unionless country if most everyone is like me?
Uh, what can I do to still contribute?
Unionist country.
I would say there's no country that is entirely unionist.
If you want to join a union, there's only one in your country that would accept you.
And it could maybe help you get started on doing more.
But you know, in general, if it's a union, you can join.
You know, money does definitely help people to do stuff.
I know that very much as a treasurer, having money allows, you know, allows us to take on pro bono cases.
I work with lawyers and do all kinds of stuff.
So, just, you know, joining a union and paying the membership fees will definitely help them.
If everybody thinks like that, I think that's something that's
definitely changing across the industry. More and more people
are firstly becoming aware of unionization and be becoming
positive unionization. And I think as the decade will go on,
you will see a huge shift in public industry opinion about
unionization.
All right, great.
Kevin, thank you so much for joining us.
It's been really insightful for me as well.
Thank you to everyone who showed up
and asked these great questions.
If people want to contact you or GW UK for more info,
what's the best way to do it, Kevin?
I think the GCScription has a Twitter handle.
Yeah, yeah, check out the description down there.
Yeah, so I might like sort of speak about my Twitter handle or, you know, just googling my name.
It's kind of a unique name apparently, so you'll probably find me. When it comes to, like,
contacting us, I used to again say, we've got local meetings over the country, come to one,
but not during corona. So, now go to our website and you can contact us there, or, you know, hit
up the GameXplain UK Twitter. Yeah, no, anywhere you want.
Yeah, all right. Great SEO. So thanks again and I'll see you all around. Thanks. Bye.