So thanks for coming out to Influences, y'all.
We appreciate you coming.
I'm John Sharp.
I'm Colleen Macklin.
And Colleen is sitting in a chair not because she is lazy,
but rather she has a broken foot.
When somebody says, like, break a leg at your panel,
you can just literally do it.
She did it.
So Colleen and I collaborate a lot together on things like
conference sessions.
We're part of a company, Local Number 12, with
Eric Zimmerman.
Our game, MetaGame, it's on Kickstarter right now.
We'd appreciate support.
We're also faculty at Parsons, the new school for design.
We teach games inside a program that is very much not
about games.
Perhaps that leads us to why we would do a
session like this.
Yeah. So, up until now,
most of this conference has been about games. We focused our conversations on
games, how we make them,
what we're playing, how to get people to know about them,
how to sustain ourselves and our companies, how to monetize
free-to-play, how to monetize and free-to-play.
et cetera, et cetera.
But we forget that games are part of a much larger universe.
We have done extensive research in our roles as faculty,
and we have identified exactly where games are in the galaxy.
So that's the primary takeaway, I think, from this talk.
Thank you very much.
But what about all the other things
we can learn from and be inspired by,
like film, music, spelunking?
for example. So this is a session
about everything but games that influences
the work of a group of four game developers.
Colleen and I also draw from many things outside of games.
I, for some reason, have a PhD in art history.
One of the things that I learned from,
one of the artists I learned from is Giotto,
14th century Italian painter.
And from him, I learned the power of minimalism
and of focus.
How can you distill things down to their minimal essence
to intensify an experience?
How can you remove and prune and refine
to get down to where you can really enhance?
and draw attention exactly where you want it to be.
So while John was getting his PhD, I was hanging out in raves.
I have my foundation, my doctorate in rave culture
in New York City. So as a... I was a VJ. I would DJ sometimes too, but in New York
City
there was weekly iteration of coding. I was doing a lot of coding, learning how
to make things interactive. So
for the people who didn't want to dance...
they could play with the visuals or change the environment.
We were part of a learning community. We shared a lot of knowledge.
And I feel like there's a real parallel to this scene in the 90s
to where we are today in sharing knowledge as a game design community.
For me, Samuel Beckett and this quote,
ever tried, ever failed, no matter, try again, fail again, fail better.
I literally have it tattooed on my chest.
For me, it's meant a lot, personally and professionally, that it's okay to fail.
It's a huge part of what we do as game designers, right?
Any of us who subscribe to a play-centric way of making our games, we live by this every day.
This is the mantra for me.
Helps you remember that failure is essential, and without it, I'll never be better.
John might show you that tattoo later if you ask him.
So I also currently I'm really influenced by
by writing and by different authors. These are some quotes from George Saunders
who...
I would kind of call a David Foster Wallace with soul.
So he's incredible, his writing makes me
feel so many different things, but I think a lot of it's about surrealism and
random perceptual
connections that illuminate how weird it is to be a human.
And also he talks a lot about death and deals a lot with mortality.
So I think there is some relationship to human fallibility, failure, and his writings that as designers of failure, as game designers, we can learn a lot from.
So yeah, there's lots and lots of ways for us to be influenced by things outside of games, to enhance our games, to make them better, to make us better practitioners of whatever part of game development.
we happen to be involved in. We've got four awesome people here today that have agreed
to share some of their external influences. Richard LaMarchion, Kelly Santiago, Ben Esposito,
and Brenda Romero.
we've got Richard Lemarchand. Come on up, Rich.
So Rich is probably best known for his work on the Uncharted series.
More recently he has joined the ranks of the professors
at the University of Southern California in their interactive media and games
program.
He's also a DJ. You've got a little rave in you, Richard.
He's been found spinning at
several different game-oriented parties under names like DJ Philippe Lemarchand.
and DJ Cerberus, of which we're part of,
the three-headed beast.
My fellow DJs.
Take it away, Rich.
Thanks, Colleen.
And thank you for that lovely introduction.
It's a real honor to be on a panel like this today
among such esteemed company.
It says in the program that I was going to talk about
Georgians and Victorians, but I'll
have to tell you about my heroes, Mary Wollstonecraft
and William Morris another time.
I decided to narrow my focus.
Because I'm very interested in realism in video games.
Now for what I want to talk about today, I don't mean realism in the sense of improved physics or better lighting,
though I am very interested in those things too.
Today I mean realism in the sense of the realist artistic movements,
in painting, literary fiction and film,
which emerged in the middle of the 19th century and which have been present in the arts ever since.
The original goal of realism was to show what life is like for ordinary people
without any kind of romantic idealization or
sentimentality or over-dramatization.
Of course, for hundreds of years, most of the pictures that got painted
were portraits of kings and popes, the ruling classes.
All those paintings were related to their lifestyles.
And when other kinds of people were shown, it was usually through some kind of
ideological lens that really distorted how those people were shown.
Now realism wanted to redress that imbalance.
I think it's fair to say that when games draw narratively from film and literature,
they usually draw from genre film and genre fiction,
mostly science fiction, fantasy, and horror.
Now, I loved genre fiction with a passion as a kid, and I still really love it.
In high school, I fell in love with the films of Terry Gilliam and David Cronenberg,
who have mainly made genre movies,
but whose works are transcendent in the way that all great art is.
But as much as I love genre fiction, I think that if you're really paying attention to the world around you,
there comes a point when you realize that real life is even more interesting than these kinds of fantasy worlds.
So later in my teenage years, I started to see films by David Lynch, Mike Lee, Ken Loach, and Nick Roeg.
And by the time I got to college, I'd become a fully-fledged arthouse cinema fan.
I saw a lot of weird, experimental film, a lot of international cinema, and a lot of great drama.
And eventually, I realized that many of the films I liked best, which had the deepest emotion,
and that were most helpful to me in figuring out what life is all about,
were set in the real world and were about the extraordinary situations that we
regularly encounter
in everyday life. Now what do we mean when we talk about realism in cinema?
Well, there are probably lots of ways to trace that history, but here's just one of them.
A good starting point, I think, is Jean Renoir, a French writer and director.
He was the son of the impressionist painter Pierre-Auguste Renoir.
In 1937, Renoir released a film called Grand Illusion.
It's about the relationship between a group of people in a prisoner of war camp during
World War I as they work together on an escape plan across the boundaries of their nationality,
their social class, and ethnicity.
Now Orson Welles cited this as one of his favorite films of all time.
And it has an authenticity and a kind of a generous attitude to its characters
that was pretty rare in film at that time.
Um, and it's an amazing film.
It's one of those films where two hours just flies by like that.
I can't recommend it highly enough.
So jumping forward a decade to the end of World War II,
and the Italian film industry had suddenly been freed from the censorship
imposed on it by Mussolini's fascist government.
Influenced by Jean Renoir,
a group of film critics took advantage of their newfound creative freedom
to kickstart the cinematic movement now known as Neo-Realism.
They began to make films about the lives of regular people,
often using non-actors, and filmed on location against the beautiful
but poverty-stricken background of post-war Italy.
Now one amazing film to come out of this movement is Bicycle Thieves, from 1948.
It's about a father searching Rome for his stolen bicycle,
a bicycle without which he will lose the job that feeds his young family.
A few years later, Italian neorealism lit the fuse for the French New Wave of cinema,
which was also founded by young film critics longing for innovation
and working in collaboration with older French filmmakers
who wanted to bring their experience to do something new.
I'm sure you guys have heard of the French New Wave and its key directors Jean-Luc Godard and François Truffaut.
My personal favorite film from this time is Truffaut's The 400 Blows.
It's a loosely autobiographical story about a misunderstood kid getting into trouble with the system.
By the way, I think it's really interesting to note that in both of these historically important film movements,
critics that had been writing about film became filmmakers themselves.
And their work caused tremendous change all throughout the world.
So even though the directors of the French New Wave were often reacting against a lot of Hollywood convention,
they ended up being massively influential on the next generation of Hollywood filmmakers,
everyone from Steven Spielberg to Martin Scorsese.
And in just the same way, in games right now, critics and writers like Matty Bryce, Cara
Ellison and Tom Francis are becoming game designers.
And the work that they're making is feeding right back into the mainstream of games in
many positive and very healthy ways.
Anyway, so that's some historical setup for realist film. There are lots more reference points that you guys probably know about,
from the 1960s kitchen sink dramas of the British new wave,
to the gritty realism of the 60s and 70s American filmmaking,
and of course there were lots of similar movements in international cinema.
As just one example, the work of Indian directors like Chetan Anand.
But now I want to tell you about a few great recent realist films that have had a big influence on me...
...and that I think might not be very well known in our community of game makers.
In 1999, the Scottish director Lynne Ramsay released this moving film called Rat Catcher.
The movie's innovative cinematography and editing was described as immersive
by some critics, which I think is interesting in relation to games,
and it showed that you can always find new things to do with an artistic form if you
work at it. In games, I think we've barely begun to push cinematography
in the way that this film does, in terms of unconventional framing and
impressionistic use of
light and unconventional editing, stuff like that.
The movie's set in Glasgow in the early 70s, and like several of the films I want to tell you about,
it's about a kid from a challenging background, this boy James.
He's patiently waiting for his family to be relocated to a new public housing project
as he tries to deal with the fallout from something bad that recently happened to him.
Coincidentally, another of the films I want to tell you about is set in Glasgow.
One of two films that I'll tell you about by another British director, Andrea Arnold.
Red Road from 2006 was made in response to a game-like project
where a group of Danish and German film producers challenged three different filmmakers
to use a number of the same predefined characters in three different movies.
Red Road was the first movie to be made in response to this challenge.
It's about a woman who works monitoring police closed-circuit television feeds
from public housing projects, and in doing so she encounters
a man from a very bad part of her past. These issues around voyeurism and
surveillance have been explored a bit by games,
and I think they're an interesting fit for interactivity. Maybe this film shows
us some new
creative ways forward.
The main character in this film, by the way, you might recognize.
She's played by the brilliant Kate Dickey,
who also plays Lyssa Arryn in Game of Thrones.
Andrea Arnold's next film, Fish Tank,
is one of those rare films that manages to be both funny and heart-rending.
It's about an isolated teenage girl whose only real passion is hip-hop dance,
as she struggles to find her way through life and to try and connect with the world.
It's got Michael Fassbender in it, I'm sure you know.
He's done a lot of amazing work, including his turn as Archie Hickox in
Inglourious Bastards,
and first-time actor Katie Jarvis is really brilliant in the main role.
Another British realist film that I think some of you might have seen is
Weekend, directed by Andrew Hay.
This is a very powerful and moving film
about two men who hook up on a Friday night, beginning what
initially just seems like a casual sexual encounter.
But as the relationship unfolds over the course of the weekend,
the film manages to explore big issues around intimacy and commitment,
as well as leading a political discussion about what life is like for gay people
in contemporary society.
And like a number of other realist films, this movie has great
sort of documentary feel that comes from its camera work, its lighting,
and its naturalized dialogue, some of which was improvised.
As game storytelling matures, I think we're going to see these kinds of
techniques coming more and more to the fore in various kinds of cinematic games.
Now I'd be remiss if I didn't quickly tell you about two star directors of contemporary realist film,
these guys, Jean-Pierre and Luc Dardenne, better known as the Dardenne Brothers.
This Belgian duo started out making features and documentaries in the 70s,
and then began to build an international following with a sequence of very naturalistic films
about people struggling to get by in contemporary Belgian society.
Any of their films would make a really great starting point for you guys, but The Kid With A Bike
from a couple of years ago is incredibly powerful
and it's available to stream on your favorite digital movie service.
Also, if you are looking out carefully, there's an Uncharted 2 poster on
a bedroom wall in one of the scenes. That's not why I chose this, but I couldn't resist telling you about that.
And finally, I want to tell you about a really amazing movie that I saw in the
theater just a few weeks ago.
It's a groundbreaking film set in a part of the world that we don't often get a
very clear view of, I think.
It's called Wajda, directed by Haifa Al-Mansur,
and it's the first Saudi Arabian film in history to be directed by a woman.
Funnily enough, it's another realist film that prominently features bicycles.
I don't know what's going on there.
It's about the title character Wajda's dream of buying a bike
when everyone around her tells her that she shouldn't have one
because she's a girl.
This is a really understated and subtle movie
and it's also very funny and moving, so check it out.
Hopefully it'll come out online soon.
So what kind of influence do these films have on me?
Well, they make me long for more realist games.
Games about our day-to-day lives and experiences.
Something you might notice about these films,
many of them are about women, young people, and children.
And these are groups that don't often receive
very detailed or nuanced portraits
in either films or games.
And I don't think I'm the only one who's interested in this stuff.
Some of the most interesting and impactful games of the past few years
could be seen as realist games.
Games like Ananthropy's Dysphoria,
Richard Hoffmeier's Cart Life,
Gone Home by the Fulbright Company,
and I Get This Call Every Day by David S. Gallant.
Now, these games are about regular people
struggling with the circumstances of their lives.
And that makes these artworks valuable to us
as individuals and as a society.
So I'm very interested in emotion in games, and I think that we, as game designers, have a lot to learn from realist movies like the ones I've told you about today.
These films work because they slow their pace, and they take the time to show the nuance in the dynamics of the relationships between their characters.
And as a result, they offer emotional experiences that are as deep and as strong as any that we can find in the arts.
So check out some of these films.
I'm going to tweet the list and a few more
that I didn't get time to talk about today.
And I'll look forward to seeing how
they might influence your guys' game design practice.
Thanks very much for your time.
Cheers.
Awesome.
Thanks a lot, Rich.
Next up, we've got Kelly Santiago.
You probably know she was a big part of Journey.
You probably know she is now the developer's best friend
at OUYA.
However, did you know she performed in a high school
competition show choir, just like we see on Glee
every week?
A little known fact about Kelly.
So come on up, Kelly.
I said send two facts to say I didn't know what they meant.
So he spoke.
I'm kind of nervous about this.
Whoa, the font is super small.
So when Colleen and John approached me about this panel,
there was an artist that immediately came to mind.
The work of this artist has been with me so long,
as long as I can remember.
And I feel that many, many times over the course
of my artistic life and my career in video games.
His work has resurfaced again and again, and each time I find something new to take away from it.
It's as though his work, while it remains somewhat...
the same kind of evolves along with me.
And I think it must mean that's a really deep ingrained
part of myself.
And I think it's led to some of the main guiding principles
I bring to my work, that they actually stem directly
from his body of work.
But I thought instead of trying to describe its impact,
I think it's best to witness a sample
so you can experience its potential impact on society.
Let's wait.
The link didn't work, though.
Should I just go over?
OK.
Not the Atlantic.
Where's my, anybody see my mouse?
Oh, it's still on this screen.
There.
There you go.
Oh, great.
Perfect.
Mee Mee Mee Mee
Mee Mee, Mee Mee Mee
Mee Mee, Mee Mee
Mee Mee Mee Mee
So, as you figured out, it's Jim Henson and the Muppets.
So yes, while I was sort of setting up a joke there,
my introduction is still true.
I revisit his work and his life over and over again
and keep finding things that resonate with me
and the things I've learned in my work.
So I thought I'd share some of those themes and ideas
with you.
So one of my guiding principles I credit to Jim Henson
is that it is about the journey.
Yes, pun not intended maybe, but not the destination.
Goals are awesome and drive us to challenge ourselves and one another to achieve great things,
but you can't gloss over those days in between deliverables.
I don't believe that the ends justify the means.
and it's the means, those day-to-day experiences
that really comprise the majority
of our existence here on Earth.
And I think that's important to remember.
Jim Henson really strived to create a working environment
for his artists that was just as enjoyable to work in
as the material that they were working on.
And he wanted the people on his team
to feel good day-to-day and that translates into their work.
And I do believe that the experience you have while
creating a work impacts the emotions felt through that work.
I think audiences have an ability to perceive heart
through a game.
We often really get too focused on that next deliverable
and not on the days we spend getting there.
We spend most of our days with one another
as co-developers on a game.
And sometimes we spend more time with one another
than we do with our family members and significant others.
And please remember that as I say this, that I am a huge advocate for the power of video games as a medium,
for video games as art, and that games play a hugely impactful role in our society.
But at the end of the day, we work on fucking games.
Like, there's nothing about that and what we do
that's worth hurting ourselves, hurting one another,
or the ones that we love.
So we should definitely incorporate more musical numbers
into our data rate process as well.
So second is to be creative, you have to take risks.
And in order to take risks, you have
to feel that you're in an environment which
is safe to fail.
This was really a motto of Henson's
and certainly came out through many of the trials
and tribulations that the Muppets faced
in putting on a show every night.
It's also one of the biggest mistakes I see happening in our industry, which somehow I feel has perpetuated this notion that everyone thrives better in a really competitive, hostile environment in which you're asked to prove yourself every day.
And I think it's why we drive many brilliant, creative people away from making games professionally, and especially in the commercial marketplace.
So this statement right here, it's the key to innovation. It's everything.
So now I'm not saying that you have to create an environment
in which everyone is pampered and everyone wins all the time.
I think you want to put together the right team for your game
from the start.
But once I've decided to work with someone,
I give them enough rope to hang themselves with.
Because that's when I think creative people
produce their best work.
You want a team of people that push and challenge one another
because they come from different backgrounds,
they're bringing different ideas to the table,
and all of those ideas can be heard.
That's how you get the best ideas,
not by pitting a homogenous group of people
against one another.
And this point might seem a bit dodgy based
on what I just said.
But going back to my second point,
the people you work with, you might as well be dating,
really.
You're in a totally committed relationship with them
of ups and downs.
And you have to work through problems.
And at times, you're really stuck with each other.
So you spend at least as much time with them
as you would a significant other.
And sometimes, that person.
is the person that is perfect on paper to do the job that you want them to do,
or that you need to get done on your project, won't actually help you get your game done,
because working with them is such a chore or a challenge for, you know, whatever reason.
I have never successfully just handed off a chunk of work on a game to someone and just have them
go away and do the work and come back. It's always required some back and forth and a relationship
there.
So conversely, I would rather change some of the aspects
of my game that I'm working on in order to incorporate
a person on my team who I think is brilliant
and that I want to work with,
but may not have those exact skill sets
that I needed to get the game done as I was envisioning it.
So that makes sense.
I would rather kind of curve the design of the game
to incorporate a person onto my team
that I really want to work with,
because ultimately I think that game is way better.
Moving away from team process, this aspect of the creative process has always been one I've held dear, and it's been shown to me time and time again to be true.
I actually wrestled between talking about David Lynch and Jim Henson for this reason, because I've found it to be so core.
For those of you familiar with my talks on game design process
at that game company, yes, it's important to have
a core focus or theme for your project.
And it's important to weigh features and work
against whether or not they will achieve
your goal for your game.
But sometimes I think you get that inspiration, or if you're not the lead creative on the project, the person you're working with will get that inspiration.
And I believe you just got to go with it sometimes. It may not always make logical sense, but you can feel that it's right.
And I say at those moments, you know, let the critical studies students make sense of this later.
Well, they will.
You know, Hinson was inspired to create Dark Crystal,
despite its obvious departures from the work that he was most famous for.
And initial testings of the films were so bad,
that the distribution company was pulling so much of their confidence and support out of the project,
that Hinson bought the film from them to distribute himself.
Initial box office was bad and initial reviews were bad.
But of course, we know it went on to become
one of the top 20 grossing films in America that year
and has grown in critical and financial success ever since.
So confession, you know, sometimes when Jenova and I
are talking about our design process
on one of the games that we published on PlayStation Network
It sounds so neat, our journey from inspiration into application in the game and how it ended up,
but it really looks at times a lot messier than that. And sometimes it is just, you kind of wake
up and you see the scene and you know that's the scene, that you know that's how it's got to be.
And you kind of, in 20-20 hindsight, can string the pieces together. But in the moment,
you just, you're going on your gut.
And in the end, sometimes you just can't take yourself too seriously.
And silliness is a virtue.
Thank you.
All right.
Thank you, Kelly.
That was awesome.
I want to see like the comparison between Henson and David Lynch.
I want to see that mashup.
That just sounds incredible.
So next up we have Ben Esposito.
So Ben was a level designer for the PS3 game, The Unfinished
Swan, awesome game, and used to run a basement music
venue in upstate New York.
Was that your basement, Ben?
It was not my basement.
All right, cool.
Take it away, Ben.
All right, hey.
I wanted to talk to you.
OK, so I first wanted to say that I think film definitely
influences my work a lot, but I would say music probably does
more.
My background is, a lot of it is from music and electronic music.
And so I want to talk about Brian Eno, who
is one of the most influential electronic musicians,
or like, did whatever, like synthesizer
and electronic music.
So he's also the most quotable guy on the planet.
So I'm going to show you quotes.
And I'm going to, if you talk to me afterwards,
I'll give you some resources for awesome stuff, like interviews
and stuff that he says.
So kind of the main idea I wanted to start with
was this one quote, which says, the idea
is to produce things that are strange and mysterious to you
as the first music you ever heard.
And to me, that's kind of a goal with a lot of my work,
is to reproduce those kind of magical experiences
that you didn't quite understand at first.
So I'm going to try to tie that back up.
So if you're not familiar with Brian Eno's work,
he's known for working with David Bowie and Devo
in Talking Heads.
He also produced Coldplay and U2 for More Contemporary.
He popularized the term ambient music,
and he also popularized the term generative music
with his album Discrete Music that I'm going to talk about
a little bit later.
which was kind of both ambient and generative.
He's also known for some video and installation art.
77 Million Paintings was one of his generative works
that is kind of like generative paintings set
to generative music.
And the idea is that there's 77 million possible combinations.
And it would take you like 450 years of watching it
to see all of them.
OK, so first I wanted to talk about how I was introduced
to Brian Eno.
So I'll play you the first piece that I ever heard,
and it was pretty influential to me.
And so I want to make sure sound's on.
All right, and so you might have heard this song too.
So I'll play it.
So it's six seconds long.
If you don't know where it's from,
it's the Windows 95 startup sound.
So Microsoft commissioned him to produce a piece of music
that was kind of like, they used every possible adjective
to describe this piece of music.
futuristic and nostalgic and sentimental.
And so he wasn't a big fan of Microsoft,
but he did think the challenge of making
a three-second piece of music was incredible and kind of funny.
So I think that's a good encapsulation
of a lot of the stuff he talks about.
So what's important to Brian Eno is theory over practice.
And it's something that I kind of subscribe to, too.
Where there is certainly a craft to music,
and there's a craft to developing games.
and any form of art.
But in terms of being an artist, I
think process is the most important thing to me.
So Brian Eno, all of his work is informed
by a specific theory or process that he wants to explore.
And so he says, even though the viewer or the listener
or the player might not.
understand or be aware of the theory behind what they're
experiencing.
It's the fact that it informed it meant that it could create
an experience that they might not have otherwise seen.
So the next thing I want to talk about is constraint.
So he's got this other great quote.
There's a reason that guitar players invariably produce
more interesting music than synth players.
And it's that you can go through the options on a guitar
in a minute.
After that, you have to make aesthetic and stylistic
decisions.
And so I think this applies to digital artists,
because when the synthesizer came out.
It's got all these knobs and you kind of have an infinite amount of options.
And that often makes it way more difficult for you to produce anything interesting.
And so, yeah, this quote kind of ties it up nicely where he says,
what you need are fewer possibilities that are more interesting.
And so, what he wants to create are constraints that allow you
to be making aesthetic and stylistic decisions rather than technical decisions.
So I want to talk about one of his most famous works,
Discrete Music.
It's a piece of ambient music, and it's
a piece of generative music.
And I'll describe what ambient music means.
You probably are familiar with it now.
But the story behind the album is that Brian Eno
got into a car crash.
And he was.
recovering in bed, and he wanted to listen to music.
And so he had a record of classical harp music.
And so he got up, and he mustered all his strength
to put the record on.
And he moved the needle on, and he went back and laid in bed.
And then couldn't really hear the music.
And it turns out the volume was down.
to an almost imperceptible level,
but he felt too weak to go and turn the volume up.
So he decided to listen to the music
at this almost imperceptible volume.
And so it kind of came in and out of consciousness.
And that was, this is his quote,
this presented what was for me a new way of hearing music
as part of the ambience of the environment,
just as the color of the light and the sound of the rain
were parts of that ambience.
So ambient music is about the gray area between attention
and background.
And so that's an area I really enjoy exploring in my work,
where instead of upfront systems and game mechanics,
I think creating environments and worlds that
dance between things that are worthy of attention,
things that are the background, are the most interesting places
to explore.
And then the other part of discrete music
is that it's generative.
And what that means is that the piece is started with a seed,
and then some other process that is set up by the artist
finishes the work for you.
And so you don't necessarily have control
over the final product.
You just started it.
And that's kind of video games.
software does this really well, but it kind of was being
explored for generations and generations before that in
other forms of art.
And so on the back of Discrete Music, he generously
reproduced the diagram of how the work was produced.
It's a 30-minute piece.
And the idea is that it starts on a synthesizer and then goes
into a tape recorder.
And then that tape goes to a tape player.
which goes back into the tape recorder,
and then gets recorded.
And so the idea is he starts with a synth line,
and there's kind of like a melodic idea behind it.
And then it feeds back onto itself
at a different point in time.
And he can stretch the delay and make it shorter or longer
to kind of create new results that were unexpected.
And that was.
and amazing at the time, and the technology allowed that.
But it's something that we can do now,
where we can plant the seeds and have an intention behind it.
But I think letting the viewer take hold of what that means
and how the system affected it is really
important to digital works.
So I want to talk a little bit about.
This game is in Finish Swan.
If you don't know it, it starts and it's all white,
and you throw black paint to reveal the environment.
And this was, for me, an ambient game in a lot of ways.
So there's not much gameplay other than getting
from point A to point B.
And a lot of the level design.
Like, the focus for me on the level design
were things that were ambient.
So because there is no gameplay per se,
interacting with other agents in the system,
I wanted all the details and objects and backgrounds
to take the place of that and kind of be
able to go in and out of your consciousness
and your attention.
So this is a deck of cards called Oblique Strategies.
This has more to do with his idea of constraint,
and I think has helped inform my process a lot.
Oblique strategies is a deck of cards
that's a bunch of challenges or dilemmas
to help you get over blocks in your work.
These are a couple of examples, like honor thy error
as a hidden intention.
An idea is when you're blocked, you can take the card out.
And a lot of them are kind of funny and will make you laugh.
And that's really important to the idea
because you can't just block.
I think, and what Brian says, is when you react to something
with a laugh, it kind of means that there's
some truth to it that you probably hadn't considered.
It's a subversion of expectations.
And so I think these are really useful literally,
but also just in the sense of creating a constraint that you
maybe didn't have control over will help
you become way more creative.
So this is my current game.
It's called Kachina.
You control this hole in the ground, and you move it around,
and stuff falls inside.
And it gets bigger every time.
So this came out of a game jam.
And I think game jams are really important to game
development, not necessarily as a way of starting a game,
but just in terms of having a constraint for your process
that will help you come up with brand new ideas and
innovative solutions.
So in the case of a game jam, your artistic constraint is
time.
And the time constraint led me to this art style,
because it's so simple.
And it's 3D, but it's all flat-shaded.
There's no lighting.
And then also the mechanic and focusing on one thing
that I found interesting.
For me, this game is interesting because you
don't control an avatar.
You control a hole, which is negative space.
And the entire game is physics driven.
So all these objects are physically simulated,
and the characters have their own very simple, rudimentary AI.
And all you're doing is just playing with that system.
And there's a couple puzzles, but a lot of it
is just seeing what happens when you remove things from a scene
and when you add them back and if they change or not.
And so the whole, so Brian Eno started in like pop music,
and then he started to do ambient music
and removed his own voice.
And he thought removing his voice
was really important to the work
because the voice is, if you put a voice in music,
it kind of focuses all your attention on it.
And so this is his quote about removing the voice.
He says, if I'm not there taking them through,
the audience, then it's an empty space for them.
They can move into it.
and they can go through in their own way.
And so that's kind of a framework for me
in terms of design.
So in this case, I remove a lot of authorial control
in terms of the physics simulation.
But I also remove your avatar and any kind of thing
to hold onto within that simulation.
And I think it allows you to kind of be
inside of that system.
instantly, rather than having to rely on a lot of narrative
immersion that I don't think is necessarily important.
So I wanted to talk one more time about the Windows 95
sound, how it encapsulates everything.
So the challenge was to create this three and one-fourth
second song.
And so he said, this was really funny,
because to make that piece of music that
contained all those ideas was an incredibly silly challenge.
But he took it up.
So and he used these three ideas of having a guiding theory,
having an incredibly.
incredibly rigid constraint of three seconds,
although he did produce this song that was six seconds.
But also that his reaction to it,
his gut reaction of it being kind of like a ridiculous idea,
helped guide him towards producing
like much more interesting work, because he never would have
explored that kind of like super compressed time
space without that.
So I'm Ben Esposito again.
This is my Twitter.
If you want to talk to me about some more materials, like
documentaries and interviews and stuff, I'd be totally
happy to share.
So thank you very much.
All right.
And next up, we've got Brenda Romero.
serious OG in the game industry. 32 years
inside and out games that are plugged in and are not plugged in.
An amazing variety of work. Right now she's the program director at UC Santa Cruz
Masters Program in Games and Playable Media. Come on up Brenda.
Hi everybody.
I'm gonna move this back.
I talk fast. I've only had two cups of coffee this morning. It could be a little slower.
Okay, it doesn't want to go back.
All right, so today I'm going to talk about Jackson Pollock.
Jackson Pollock, he's a huge inspiration of mine. He's a painter.
I'm not sure, actually, when I first become aware of Jackson Pollock.
My guess is that even my first...
knowledge that he even exists as an artist was probably not this, that Jackson Pollock was a great artist,
which is certainly something I believe today. My guess is that I heard about it like this,
much more obviously. Jackson Pollock was someone who threw paint at a canvas and would have been excellent in Unfinished Swan, in fact.
It's a nice setup.
I don't know if you paired those together on purpose.
But of course, anybody can make a Jackson Pollock painting.
And we all know, good job, mom and dad.
You can do Jackson Pollock on your nails if you'd like to.
The kids can do Jackson Pollock in the backyard.
And there's this fucking idiot on YouTube
telling how everybody can, this guy's such a tool,
how everybody can be Jackson Pollock.
And then you can have accidental Pollocks on your shoes
if you really get involved in it.
But absolutely none of them,
so this is a piece called Number 11.
Absolutely none of them has the beauty and the passion and the movement, the intensity of a real Pollock.
A real Pollock is breathtaking. A real Pollock can bring me literally to tears just being there in their presence.
They're beautiful, beautiful works.
And when I first start to study Pollock, it's not a way you would think, but it's through level design.
And let me tell you why.
It occurs to me that Pollock's process is not unlike a game designer's process.
He's circling the canvas again and again,
much like we might circle a level again and again,
fine-tuning it here or there,
creating the actual thing, the exact thing that we hope to create.
And as he's moving around the canvas, so are we.
Our canvas, of course, comes in a whole variety of different ways, be it digital or non-digital.
And what we're looking at when we see a Pollock painting isn't so much a painting,
but the artifact of a painting experience.
And to me, I feel like a game is an artifact of a game designer's play experience.
And the thing I love about Pollock is Pollock was the fucking paint.
He was literally the pedal to the metal. It doesn't get any better than that.
He isolated and elevated the paint.
If you see a painting of a house, if you see paintings of people, you see paintings of angels, whatever,
you've lost sight of the purity of the paint. That's what he deeply cares about.
And for me, Pollock was all about action.
It was all about the movement, the motion, the depth,
the rage and the joy.
In every single line of a Pollock painting,
you can see how he was feeling.
You can see, it's just like I mentioned before,
an artifact of his painting experience.
And the paint, even when it's dry,
even when Pollock is long since dead,
even when it's hanging on a museum wall,
the painting is as real.
It is still as moving.
It's still as alive as it was before.
And for me, Pollock is as pure as it gets,
as far as painting goes.
And Pollock is also super alone.
This is a piece called Number 9A.
And Pollock, when he was doing this,
nobody else was doing these things.
I mean, granted, there was a lot of abstract expressionism
happening and those were who his peers were
in the New York scene,
but he wasn't doing this with lots of other people.
In fact, he was not doing it with anybody.
And he faced harsh criticism from his contemporaries.
This particular line, it is easy to detect the following things in all of his paintings.
This is an Italian critic in Time Magazine.
Chaos, absolute lack of harmony, complete lack of structural organization, total absence of technique,
however rudimentary, once again chaos.
If this had been a review in GameSpot, it would have been a zero out of ten.
And so Pollock replied to the author and just wrote, no chaos, damn it.
You know, maybe at the time, Pollock actually, you know, as much as he faced criticism,
and in part he just felt really alone because nobody was doing what he was doing.
And he, so he actually had a lot of supporters, including Peggy Guggenheim,
and a lot of prominent critics who were saying, this guy's on to something.
But he still never felt secure in his work, ever.
And then he got a break that many of us as game developers would kill for.
Life Magazine ran an article in 1949 asking if he was the greatest painter in the United States.
And whatever your profession is, is John Sharp the greatest game designer in the United States?
And of course there'd be this moment where you'd think like...
That's me mentioned in time,
I'm going to immediately show my parents, right?
But then, there's the other 100 people in the room
who are going, John Sharp's not the greatest game designer
in the United States, what the hell is this?
I'm gonna go to Twitter and start, you know?
So for him, fortunately he didn't have Twitter, right?
He didn't have to deal with Twitter rage.
But this is what the real world,
of course my perfectly scientific estimation there,
Pollack got a lot of praise,
but the way he really saw it was much more like this.
And because he painted the drip method from 1947 until 1951,
and at the peak of his fame, he walked away from it.
So when people had known him,
when they actually revered the work that he was doing,
when people who said anybody could make a Pollock
actually tried to reproduce a Pollock
and tried to get in there some of the mathematical movements
and moments that are in his paintings,
they were unable to do it.
And so at the peak of his style, he walked away.
Pollock was an alcoholic, he'd been sober for a while,
but he resumed drinking at some point,
and within six years he died.
He created another, he tried to mess around
with a lot of different styles,
but man, none of them had the beauty,
the intensity, and the purity.
None of them had the hymn, none of them had the Jackson
that those four beautiful years had.
This is a piece, when I was at a really fucked up point in my life, a lot of bad shit had happened.
And I'd finished my level design study of Pollock quite a while before.
And I was at a really fucked up point in my life, like I said, a lot of bad shit had happened.
And there's this painting, it's called The Deep.
And to this day, I don't know why I would stare at this painting.
It's part of my process as a game designer.
I just stare at shit.
I am working, goddammit.
But I would stare at this painting and I think, like, am I looking at the white?
Am I trying to see what's through it?
You know, what's happening in this painting?
And to this day, you know, there's a lot of blue poles is often thought of,
which is number 11 I showed you before.
It's often thought of as one of his best pieces.
But to me, this is his most nuanced piece, man.
It's just him and white and black.
And it is just breathtaking.
And I still don't even know really what it means, but it was at this very low point in my life.
And out of that low point in my life came a series of games that I'm still working on now.
This is one of them called Train.
And I wasn't intending, I was just doing these things because I had to, because I still have to.
And for me, maybe this is what it looked like.
Maybe, like, even as I put this up here,
I'm suffering a whole hell of a lot of imposter syndrome
with the word amazing.
So let's just put the word work there.
And stop making games.
And that was some stuff people said.
You know, Brenda Brathwaite, which was my name at the time,
you need to stop making games.
You're hurting games.
And so it looked like that, probably,
but it felt a whole hell of a lot like that.
And the detractors seemed so incredibly loud.
And so what at one point in time was me studying Pollock
and looking at how his work could influence
the work of level design in general,
then somehow turned to be about me researching
what I would need to know about Pollock many years later
when I was at a breaking point.
And Pollock, he became my inspiration and my support.
Pollock felt about paint the way I felt and still feel about game mechanics.
And this is one of my favorite quotes of his.
On the floor I am more at ease. I feel nearer more a part of the painting,
since I can walk around it, work from the four sides, and literally be in the painting.
What the hell happened there?
Okay, just the, so it's supposed to...
There it is. That's art. Do it.
I'm supposed to say I'm on the table. I'm more at ease. I feel nearer to the game.
And this way I can walk around the work from all four sides and literally be in the game.
And I remember when the PS4 conference happened, the big event, and I had this horrible feeling.
I was saying to my husband, I'm like, I should be there, why am I not there?
And because I was not there, somehow I'm a failure, somehow I fucked up, somehow I'm not part of mainstream games, where I have been since the beginning.
And I'm looking at the work that my friends are doing, and my friends' games are, you know, some of my closest, dearest friends are getting Game of the Year nods, you know?
and I'm not doing this. I'm doing something that doesn't even match a box that they're in.
And I feel like I'm outside of the actual game industry, right?
Instead of thinking, maybe I'm pushing the fucking boundaries of the edge of that industry.
And Kropotkin tells me that it's okay to be there, right? Like, it's absolutely okay to be outside.
I'm not missing anything by not being at the PS4 launch event.
And I find myself again and again referencing him when people say,
well you have to make copies of Train, you have to.
No I don't.
No and I'm still not going to.
Pollock's not making 20 lavender mists for all the housewives
and househusbands who want it.
Pollock, I love his brutal compression of exactly what it is he deeply loves.
You know, I don't care so much about graphics and cut scenes or story or audio.
I just want to deal right now with the mechanics.
And there's something I'm still puzzling about with Pollock. He actually got rid of names at some point in his painting.
And he called this number 11. He didn't even want the names to color what that paint could possibly be.
He just wanted it as pure as it could conceivably be in his world.
Pollock basically gives me permission.
And he gives me permission to be here or to go even further if I want to.
That I can do what I like to do and not worry about whether I'm going to be accepted.
And that it's all right to do stuff that none of my other peers are doing
and that I don't necessarily need their approval or even my own
because clearly I sometimes feel anxious about the stuff that I am working on.
Pollock inspires me to match his dedication.
He inspires me to think about painting, a painting, designing in ways that I've never designed before.
He inspires me to keep going, to keep exploring, and to keep doing what I feel called to do.
Thank you.
Thank you, Brenda. That was great. Awesome. You should do this part.
Alright, so we talked a little bit about Brian Eno,
Jackson Pollock, that's where he lives now,
on that star after the wreck.
Of course, the Muppets.
Nothing more important than the Muppets.
George Saunders, the rave scene,
Samuel Beckett, who I always want to call
either Thomas Aquinas or Thomas Beckett for some reason.
I managed to do it correctly today.
Realist Cinema, Jotto.
But what about you all?
What are your influences?
What are the things that inspire you?
If you take anything away from this,
I think it's go back and think about something
that isn't a game that's really meaningful in your work
and how can you bring that into the process?
How can that help change you
and make you better as a developer?
So thanks very much you all.
Thanks everybody.