Hello, that's nice.
It's like a little friendly group of us.
You're gonna get to hang out right now.
How is everybody doing?
It's the end of a long week.
It's good to hear.
Thank you for being here
and not either at the experimental gameplay workshop
or face down in a bucket of margaritas,
which is where I intend to be in,
you know, 68 minutes or something.
Selling my soul.
That's why we're here.
This is a slightly different from any talk I've given before.
The nice folk at GDC got in touch earlier in the year and said,
would you be interested in giving a talk about what it's been like going from
kind of deep art house indie to commercial free-to-play,
which is the change that I've made over the last couple of years.
And I thought it sounded great.
It's interesting, there's been, you know...
I've learned a lot in the course of doing that.
Would be fun to share some of those conclusions
with you guys.
But then I realized that really what that talk added up to
was something a little bit less palatable
because there's no way of,
there's certainly no way of talking truthfully
about how I got from there to here
and what that journey has been like
without exposing the realities
of some of the bumps along the way.
So,
I'm Margaret, and you're about to discover more
about my career and my life
than you were perhaps bargaining for.
So let's start out by kind of giving you your bearings a bit
in terms of how that journey stacks up.
So I think what was in people's minds
when they were asking me to do this talk
was the time that I spent at Hide and Seek.
Hide and Seek was a experimental game studio
founded in London.
We branched out and had a New York studio
that I moved over and ran.
And we were kind of best known for very hybrid games.
So often that meant digital worlds with a,
digital games with a real world component
or collaborations between digital game makers
and artists or choreographers,
kind of all points in between.
So here's a super quick survey of some of our projects
that people may have heard of.
Board game remix kit was an early independent project that we did that we designed in the
middle of having a depressing conversation about how much we were all dreading going
home for Christmas, because when you go home at Christmas, somebody pulls out that mostly
broken awful board game from the top of a cabinet and you all have to play Monopoly
or Trivial Pursuits with the cards that are 25 years out of date, so nobody knows any
of the answers anymore.
So Board Game Remix Kit was a physical card set and smartphone app that kind of mashed
up and remixed a bunch of games that you are likely to have, Monopoly, Clue, Druid Pursuit,
Scrabble, and gave you new rule sets or new kind of combined ways of playing them.
Some super, super nice stuff in there.
That was fun.
We made an iPhone game called The Show Must Go On, which is the world's first opera platformer.
This was in collaboration with the Royal Opera House.
Cast you as a put-upon stage manager who was trying to get the show...
up and running, but it was in the course of finding out that everything had gone wrong.
The costumes had got messed up, the set hadn't been built, the sheet music for the orchestra
had blown away, and you'd play a bunch of kind of one step above WarioWare little puzzle
games to solve those problems.
And then at the end of it you would watch the performance that happened as a result of your preparations.
If you played well, then you got a little nice animation where everything went great.
If you messed up, then you got a little dynamically generated animation where things went wrong depending on which games you had failed in.
So if you found all the sheet music, then you got a gorgeous orchestral recording of the real Royal Opera House Orchestra playing the score.
If you didn't, you got a terrible...
janky chiptune version that we made.
The stunts go wrong, the costumes change around.
Cute, fun, nice thing.
This is Newer Games, which was a city-wide game
that we ran on New Year's Eve in Edinburgh a few years ago.
New Year's Eve is a massive celebration in Edinburgh
and they wanted to follow it up with another huge public.
event the next day and so we ran a series of distributed games across the whole city
where you could play and collect tokens. We put you in a team and you were
trying to win the... whichever team won, that team earned the right to set the...
give a blessing to the city for the rest of the year, give a tone for the city for the rest of the year.
So the
National Poet of Scotland wrote two blessings, one for each of the two teams and then depending on which one won that was going
to set the tone for the rest of the year. So you collect tokens and did things and danced in the streets and wore ribbons.
And then the hub of the game was this huge central square underneath Edinburgh Castle
where we would play mass, mass, mass multiplayer real world games.
So that culminated in a 5,000 player game of basketball in which nobody was hospitalized.
So that's a game design claim to fame.
This is Tiny Games, which some people might just remember.
We kick-started it a few years ago.
This was born out of a series of giant vinyl stickers
that we stuck on sidewalks all over London that kind of gave
you, in a sentence, a game that you could play using
the surroundings immediately around you.
They were a surprisingly big hit on the streets,
so we decided to make them digital.
And then this was just a very simple system
where you could play.
you tell the game where you are, what kind of mood you're in, how many people are there,
if you've got a particular prop that might help, and then the engine serves you the perfect little game that you could play there and then.
Most of these are no longer currently available, which is a thing we can talk about later.
But even before and after that, I was doing a bunch of crazy stuff.
If anyone's interested in any of these, I can tell you more after.
I don't want to bog us down too much in these.
But before I was at Hide and Seek, I was on the team behind Papa Sangre, which was an
iPhone 3D dungeon explorer.
It's a revival game, except with no visuals.
So you had a completely black screen,
and everything about the world was presented
via binaural 3D audio.
So you were navigating by sound alone,
which is an experiment that started out as a question
about whether or not we could make a horror game
that was as accessible to non-sighted players
as sighted players.
And Drunk Dungeon is a thing I made after I came to New York, which is a game built
out of drinks coasters.
It's designed for a whole party to play together.
You get put into a team when you arrive and then every time you get a drink, you get a
coaster with the drink and the coaster is a play piece that either helps you build out
the dungeon that the game is happening in, or lets you fight battles or move pieces around.
And you have to kind of find the right way to coordinate with every other drunk person
in the bar to figure out how to make that work.
So that, I did that for a long time.
And I'm game director at a company called Dot.
We're in New York.
There's about 50 of us.
One of those is me, but you don't win a prize for figuring out which.
Maybe you do.
It's harder than it looks.
You should check us out.
We're on the internet with that improbably short URL.
We're also on the socials, if you're a fan of the socials.
Our Instagram is particularly pretty.
Recommend our Instagram to you.
And we're called Dots because our first game was this game.
This game is called Dots.
It was about connecting dots.
This kind of came out of a kind of incubator,
skunk worksy thing at a tech startup in New York.
To everyone's surprise, it was a pretty colossal hit.
Got a lot of attention and a lot of players.
And so we followed it up with this game,
which was called Two Dots.
which is exactly the same mechanic but kind of expanded out a little bit bigger
library of game mechanics got into it and much more configured to be a
profitable free-to-play game and then last year we released this game which is
called
Dots and Co, because I wasn't...
I couldn't go with three dots, couldn't do it.
Because when you go next, you can't do four dots.
You've got to call time on it somewhere,
so we call time on it.
And this is what we make.
We're lucky that they're popular,
and that means we make enough money
to have 50 people in New York making them.
But it's obviously pretty different
from where I was spending my time before then.
So I thought I'd pick up on a couple of key areas,
and just poke at that question of what is different
between doing that thing in an indie or house environment
versus a highly commercialized environment.
So, speaking of highly commercialized,
let's start with the money.
And I do start with the money.
This is the first thing I look at every day.
These are our, this is our company-wide KPI email
that comes out every day.
Don't get excited.
I've deleted all of the interesting numbers.
Not sharing anything that should get me into trouble
that I shouldn't be sharing at GDC.
But it's true.
Every day you get up and you look at where those numbers are sitting.
Every single design choice that I make, I'm getting feedback on in terms of the metrics
that our analytics team feedback to me.
I'm very conscious of every decision that I make.
from a production perspective, an artistic perspective,
a game design perspective,
has specific financial ramifications.
And that feels a lot like it comes with the territory,
with being not just in a commercial company,
but a commercial company where you're getting
minute to minute feedback on whether or not
the thing you're doing is hitting the financial targets
that you hope that it will hit.
Except, this is a thing called the COD.
I can't remember why it's called the COD.
No one can remember why it's called the COD,
but it was a thing we used at Hide and Seek
to track all of our spending and all of our income.
This is it.
I haven't hidden any of the numbers here
because there's no exciting numbers to hide.
But you'll see at the top there's some nicely dynamically formatted cells that go pink,
in this case on the 18th of March.
And they go pink because that's our go bus date, as some people would call it.
We tended to call it our go bus date because that's really what it was.
We were a bootstrapped company.
We had no resources.
we could only pay ourselves the next month
if we got paid the previous month.
And especially for the people
you know, who were kind of mostly concerned
with running the company if Humor was won.
it dominated your waking hour to an extent that I could never really articulate at the time.
Because you knew that you couldn't pay rent next month if this didn't happen,
but also that a bunch of people who you adored, who you had lured away from possibly perfectly
successful, sensible person jobs to come and work with you, wouldn't get paid.
And that pressure was super intense. So that pressure was a waking up at two in the morning
intense pressure, not just a rolling out of bed and checking my KPIs.
So the amount of time I spend thinking about money, now that I work for a free-to-play company, is much reduced.
And certainly the amount of energy and friction that I'm dealing with in terms of money is radically reduced.
It's much nicer.
But you saw those screenshots at the beginning.
seems like a fair question to ask whether or not that has come at the expense of abandoning
interesting, unpredictable work for...
I mean...
I don't want to say boring, but you can see how similar those three screenshots are to each other.
This is the same game three times.
And that's what I do.
And...
What I found is...
a thing I wasn't expecting to find.
So these are...
Don't worry, they don't make sense.
These are early prototypes for the last new puzzle mechanic
we introduced in two dots.
They're called paddles.
The kind of idea here is that if you clear dots along,
so they're a set of tiles that function together.
Along one side is a hinge.
If you clear dots along the hinge, then they flip,
and then whatever they land on, they squish.
And then if you clear dots on the other side of the hinge,
then they flip back.
And while they're not flipping,
they act like gaps and dots can fall through them.
It's a relatively simple idea,
but two dots is three years old nearly.
We're coming up on our third anniversary in May.
And that means there's a huge amount of stuff
in the game already.
This is level 1000, which we just released.
And this has every mechanic in the game so far.
So you make those two connections
that are the only two connections you can make.
which then drops the cloud, which triggers the cloud,
which lets the lotuses trigger, which hits the gems.
The gems explode, they hit the bombs, the bomb goes off.
That hits the slime, the train triggers,
that connects the magnets, the magnets trigger,
and that explodes the, oh, the monster dot fell,
then the thing went, and now the paddle is gonna trigger.
And that was your first move in that level.
I've never got to play with something so intricate in my life.
The interactions between all these different mechanics are currently endlessly interesting.
The joy of getting to drop a new one into that every month or two and see what it changes
and what it enables and how it inflects the flavor of the game is incredibly satisfying.
A hesitation that I had when I took the decision
to join the company was how am I gonna feel?
Like it's literally spots before your eyes.
There's a point where can you really look at this
all day every day for however long?
Well I've been doing it for two and a half years
and I'm nowhere near done with enjoying looking
at this particular set of things.
And that's partly because at Hide and Seek,
this was us, this was our logo.
This was our tagline.
This is what we did.
We invented new kinds of play.
Number of problems with that, even as a claim.
It's also just so dumb.
It's such a.
bad purgatorial way of being a game designer.
We would iterate, well, iterating is even the word.
We were ideating so many new projects
in so many crazy configurations
where every single thing was on the table.
We're, oh no, we're gonna do this with motion sensors.
No, we're not, we're gonna do it with
super weird targeted speakers that know where you are.
a partnership with Nike.
No, we're not, we're gonna do it with whoever.
Everything was possible.
And you very rapidly stop being a good...
or you risk stopping being a good game designer
and just being a good game describer at that.
That becomes your job, that you just show up in a room
and you say a bunch of stuff that sounds good
about a thing that doesn't exist.
And then maybe you get to make it, but if you do get to make it, you're going to spend three months making it,
and you're not going to have time to get it right,
but it doesn't really matter because everybody's going to be on to the next thing three weeks after that.
And it's invigorating, and there are, I think, serious merits to going through that process,
but it certainly put me in a position where I'm...
now could not be happier to have this really, really precisely defined puzzle box that I have
this, you know, I feel like a jeweler trying to perfect a gemstone rather than somebody trying to
whatever it was we were trying to do that whole time. But I thought for sure I was leaving art
behind. So I still feel a bit weird about this but...
Hide and Seek was fundamentally conceived of as an art studio, as an arts institution.
We were artists in residence at the Southbank Centre in London, which is one of, if not
the biggest, arts centres in London.
We made work like this.
I did a talk about this at GDC a while ago, so I won't take you through it, because you
can vault it if you care.
But this was a piece that we made as a counterpoint to a documentary film about a very distressing story of the discovery in a London apartment of the body of a 36-year-old woman who had lain undiscovered for three years.
And a woman called Carol Morley made a searing...
emotional, amazing documentary about it.
And we got asked to make a partner piece
so that people could kind of extend and explore
the issues in the story that the film told online.
Making it was hard and beautiful and weird,
and I've never seen anything like it.
And I don't know if we got it right, but it was,
you know, it definitely felt like being an artist,
even if I don't know if I wanted to call myself an artist.
And that was a huge amount of how we thought about ourselves
and what we thought we did.
A year later, this company came to us.
They're called Capgemini.
I don't know what they do,
but apparently it's consulting technology and outsourcing.
They wanted, I think,
to do.
make a mobile web thing that would tell their clients,
or convince their clients, that buying smart mobile devices for
their client's employees would overall up company productivity
more than the devices would cost.
And we said we've got just the thing.
And so we took the game that had been that beautiful documentary piece
and we stuck a bunch of...
I stock photos in it.
This is, I draw your attention to the fact
this photo is literally called
Adult People Having a Business Lunch.
And then with Captain Devino's help,
we wrote a lot of choose your own adventure,
business productivity dialogue.
I suggest you don't read all of this
because it's too gruesome,
but there's some highlights
that you might want to dwell on.
And that was a project for us because it pushed that go bus date a couple months down the road
It was a thing we could do it felt good to be building on the technology that we'd already developed
but it's a really stark contrast to the stuff that we wanted to do and the stuff that we cared about doing and
Because I'm lucky enough to be at a game studio that's
Founded by a bunch of people who care about culture beyond the culture of games
it hasn't necessarily meant leaving this behind.
So this is contemporary magic.
This is a side project that DOTS put out last year,
a collaboration with a woman called Stacey Engman
who had put together a collection of commissioned.
interpretations of tarot cards from artists around the world.
So she had the cards, but she wanted to make a digital version of the cards.
And she was looking for a good partner to do it.
And for us, we're at the scale that that's not a scary decision to say, well, this is
a pretty simple little standalone thing that we can put together.
And so, although I have in theory left all of this behind,
to my surprise, it's amazing how much of it
you can take with you if you're in an environment
with the right kind of people,
which we'll talk about more.
Similar thing.
This has really surprised me
and I feel a bit torn about it.
Part of why I wanted to...
work with Hide and Seek, where I wanted to stay at Hide and Seek was...
I can't remember, did I? I don't know. Are either Alex or Holly here?
I don't think they made it.
There's other very good Hide and Seek people here this week.
If you find them, you should talk to them,
because it'll be fun.
This was a thing I was super proud of.
Well, stay with me.
This was the ARG we made for the launch of the Green Lantern movie,
starring Ryan Reynolds.
which none of you saw.
Right, it's terrible.
But they wanted an ARG and that's the kind of thing we did.
So we felt we could have some fun with it.
And part of how we had fun with it was
with this project. I knew some folks at Cambridge University who were trying to run some citizen
science digital tools to deal with a weird problem that now apparently exists in astronomy,
which is we have really good photographic resources of space now. This picture that
you're looking at here is from the Spitzer Space Telescope.
So we have this huge amount of raw material of images of space, but computers are still pretty bad at
doing visual analysis or photographs. They were certainly even worse
whenever this was six or seven years ago that we were doing it.
So what actually ends up happening is that grad students are just expected to invest hours of extra time in
manually going through all of these photos to see if they can see anything that looks interesting.
And this project was specifically about trying to find
photographic evidence of the birth of new stars.
And what happens when,
like if anybody who actually understands
any of this stuff is here, just do this for now,
because I'm on shaky ground here,
but for the sake of the talk.
What happens when a star is born is there's a huge explosion.
All this stuff, sorry, all this stuff,
not that there's much space stuff,
but there's some space stuff that was around the star
when it explodes gets pushed out.
and you end up with a globe of stuff which to a 2D camera looks like a ring
and then it's hard to see because the colors are the pictures have any color
in them so you tint them the way this one is tinted to make it look spacey and
cool. What you get what you get is a green ring in space for the Green
Lantern movie!
I was pretty pleased.
So we had this cute thing that if you played the ARG,
it would take you through,
we re-skinned their citizen science tool
to be within the game fiction,
then you do it amongst yourself,
you would maybe find a star
that no one had ever found before,
and then you got a certificate from NASA at the end
saying thank you for being a scientist.
And that seemed,
this was like high on the job satisfaction score, right?
That seems like a really nice thing to put together.
The truth is, it's utterly eclipsed by a thing that I had a much smaller hand in,
which is that when the travel ban hit a few weeks ago,
led by former FIRA CEO, but with just enough of support of a ton of people in the company
who were on Slack over the weekend, we put an announcement in all our games,
kind of stating our opposition to anything that was limiting free and fair immigration
and directing people to the ACLU donation page.
and that pushed half a million visitors through from us to the ACLU.
Can't then track the onward donation because the technology wasn't in place, but it was there.
Thank you.
We got a bunch of unbelievably nice letters.
We got a bunch of mean letters, and in the interests of balance,
I was going to also put those on screen,
but the truth is they are so ugly and hate-filled and racist
that I'm not willing to give them the oxygen.
So you're just going to get the nice ones.
But it was a real, you know, we, as a commercial company,
we had to stop and think about what we might be looking at
in terms of the repercussions, and we were able to do that
and determine that it was worth doing.
And there is a kind of numbers game reality
that Hide and Seek had a huge amount of freedom,
but we just had this really tiny reach,
even when we were trying to surf,
you know, we were trying to find cool ways
to hitch the ideas that we wanted to do
up to a major movie release.
And now being at a studio
that has hundreds of millions of installs,
when we want to have this kind of impact,
we have a capability to do it
that we wouldn't otherwise have.
And some of that is just to do with this kind of weird, simple bit of math I didn't do
until fairly recently.
There's lots of things about working for a commercial free-to-play company that only
really makes one kind of game that doesn't seem very exciting or enlivening.
But what is true is I'm now in a place where...
All everyone in that room cares about all day,
every day is games.
And all the people who are our customers want from us
all day, every day is games.
I just, I live in this delicious game bubble.
And my old job, I got to do a bunch of cool stuff,
but it was nearly always in collaboration
with somebody else.
And those organizations were full of wonderful people
and they were doing great and interesting things,
but they mostly cared about chocolate or opera
or prescription prices.
And they didn't.
They didn't even not like games as much.
They didn't, they just, they didn't, games didn't,
they didn't know about them.
They didn't believe in them.
They didn't know how to interface with them.
They didn't know how to write contracts for them.
They just, they just, it, you know,
there was just a real boundary there
that was hard to cross.
And I spent so much more of my time defending
and explaining and, and,
lobbying for games than I ever spent actively making them.
Whereas when I walk in now to my office every morning,
I'm not, there's no friction.
I'm just walking with a bunch of other people
who want to do game stuff.
I should say in all this, I'm painfully aware
that there are lots of different ways
to be a commercial free-to-play company,
lots of different ways to be an indie,
and I know indies who don't do anything like this.
So, please don't think that I'm suggesting
this is the only way around it is,
but this is the bit of it that I know about,
so I thought it made sense to start there.
It's rainbow.
Because here's the thing, maybe this whole premise,
this whole question about the transition from...
indie to commercial is just a big pile of rainbow poop.
Maybe it's not really a meaningful transition at all.
Because I think what I found, and I spoke to a few people
who've been through similar changes
before coming into this today,
they're kind of saying the same thing.
What doesn't change is the work is the work.
If you make Games for a Living, what you're up against in terms of all of the weird technical, psychological, artistic, commercial challenges that you face,
of like starting with nothing and trying to get to a thing.
four weeks, four months, four years later, that people will understand and know how to use and stick with and derive a sense of accomplishment from
and doesn't fall over all the time, whatever else might go wrong with it. It just doesn't change. This is an awesome
collection of Richard Serra
ink drawings
from an exhibition called Work Comes Out of Work, and that phrase gets stuck in my head a lot
even though it's a bit hard to explain because I
Feels like what it means to me is that the,
you know, you think of work in terms of an artwork,
the work is like this finished object
that you see in a gallery.
But the way you get to that thing is through the work,
is through the daily, boring, stupid,
trudgy work that you do.
And you can't get there without here.
And in fact, you can't directly make that.
You just need to do this stuff
and you do enough of it for long enough
and then the thing emerges at the end of it.
And that just feels the same.
I mean, the truth is,
I probably burst into tears a little less often,
but working on a new mechanic for Dots
doesn't feel fundamentally different
from working on a game about death.
I still have a bunch of logic flows I can't resolve,
and I need a bigger piece of paper
because I always need a bigger piece of paper,
and then I sit there for three hours
until I figure it out, and then I figure it out,
and then I go and talk to an engineer,
and then the next day we play it,
and then hopefully it's better.
That's just the same.
It just doesn't change.
So for all that it looks like,
I've been through this kind of massive career U-turn.
It in practice doesn't feel like it at all.
But I think there are some things
that came out of being in that crazy indie environment
that I brought into commercial free-to-play
that I wouldn't have come any other way.
This is one of them.
This is a crying child.
My work used to involve a lot more crying children.
When you make real-world games, physical world games,
really often, especially when you're developing them,
when they're still being designed,
your players and your playtesters are...
They're in the room with you, but they are so in the room with you,
you probably...
There's no mediated thing where you give them a screen and you get to sit back.
You're probably going to say stuff.
If you're me, you're standing on a chair because you're 5'2 and no one can see you.
You're going to tell a bunch of people to do things,
and they are trusting you that doing them is going to be fun.
And they do them and it stinks because the game is still in development.
And then they come back and they yell at you.
And that is what making games is like.
And that's bad enough.
What's worse is when they're three years old,
we did a, the tiny games project I mentioned earlier,
we followed up with a collaboration with Sesame Street,
which was an amazing, delightful experience.
But we did a bunch of similar tiny games
for sort of three and four year olds,
and their parents were caregivers.
And you have to playtest those things.
and not wreak psychological catastrophe on the children who are playtesting them in the course of doing that.
Not always easy.
Turns out that one three-year-old is better at cup stacking than her four-year-old sister,
and the four-year-old isn't okay with that, and a whole thing happens.
And so I think the intimacy and the immediacy of the playtesting experience that I had in an experimental, real-world play-focused studio
taught me things that I never would have learned working just in a digital studio and just in a casual digital studio.
I talked earlier about the downside of the inventing new kinds of play thing,
where you never get to the bottom of an idea,
but there's a pretty big upside.
Can I show you this for half a second, because there's preparatory stuff on it?
That was pulled out of a real email, a team email.
We do a team email each week, I think, of all the things we're working on,
that just listed out all of our projects,
and that was one from a few months before we took the decision to close.
This is a kind of translation of what we were doing.
So on the left is the stuff that was live,
that was actively in production or release.
So the Sesame Street thing I just showed you,
the tiny games we just talked about,
we were making prototypes with Leap Motion
for an in-house project that we wanted to do.
We were installing seven foot playable carrots
at the Royal Botanic Gardens in London.
We had a thing going with the Government Policy Research
Unit that I can't remember much about.
Those plastic, those vinyl stickers
were going down somewhere.
We were doing a movie marketing thing that wasn't.
Green Lantern, Holly, if she was here, was writing a twine game of philosophy for the
Open University, that terrible.
Capgemini device thing was happening, we were making a
iPhone, an iPad app for young learners of the violin
that would listen to them play and then tell them
what to do to correct in this kind of music course
that we were putting together for them.
And we had a large installation at Kensington Palace
where you played a bunch of games.
It was a very, very, very
astonishing kind of medieval museum in London. We had games installed throughout the palace and you
played things and you collected things. Then when you got to the end, it was for Christmas, kind of
aimed at kids and their families. We got to the end, if you played well enough you became king
or queen, you got to choose your royal name, you built a big placard for yourself that had your
name on it, and then we had a smart throne. You sat on the throne, it could feel that you sat down
and it read your board because your board was full of RFIDs and then it played a fanfare.
a dynamically generated fanfare that was just for you and your name,
so that your dad could take a photo of you.
It was kind of nice.
So that was live that week.
That was the stuff we were doing live that week.
And then the stuff that we were pitching on that week was
a therapy app with a major dementia charity,
who was interested in whether or not
occupational therapy could be extended to digital play therapy.
It was in the middle of the gamification of money stuff,
so we had an investment management company who thought we could help them,
we had a pension company who thought we could help them.
A thing was happening that I can't remember about,
some guys who, a big slot machine company,
thought maybe that there should be an experiential real-world game
that sat around the slot machine experience,
so we were trying to help them with that.
The UK government wanted a bunch of people to go to a tourist destination
that everybody was going to, and they thought an ARG could help.
There was a lightly pornographic movie,
I'll leave it up to you to guess which one it was,
that wanted a text adventure.
I still think I did some of my best game design for it,
different question.
There was a stupendously enormous movie deal
that I still can't talk about, but,
oh, we're taking Tiny Games to Indicade,
which was a long way away.
One of the companies that did the,
you know when you go to a museum,
you can like hire a digital,
guide that tells you a bunch of stuff about where you are, the people who make those were
interested in doing tiny games for one of those, a mall wanted a three-story playable
sculpture thing that was kind of half a helter-skelter and half an escape the room.
that we would charge people money to go into.
There was another movie that wanted a thing,
there was another government thing that wanted a thing,
and a major Hollywood visual effects studio
was wondering if they should stop just making
visual effects for movies
and start making games of their own,
so we were in development with a major new project for that.
Six people worked at the London office,
and every week was like that.
and you get really good at having ideas fast
in that environment.
Because we needed to chase all of those things
because only every 30th would turn into a thing
because most of them, as you can see, are bonkers
and should never have happened.
And so the fluidity and the fastness of feet
that you need to develop to kind of survive that stuff
is really profound.
And you also need to get really, really good at,
oh, hang on, I skipped a slide.
Social is another thing that you design for differently when you're in that environment.
If you live only in the digital social world, I think you tend to have these kind of creepy
kind of virology.
analogies for social spread.
I know we don't talk about K-factor anymore,
but there is this kind of like creepy sense
that things spread without any kind of real autonomy,
that this isn't about any of the particular individuals,
it's just if you package it right
and you incentivize it correctly,
then you can count on a certain percentage of people
to press the button and a certain percentage of the people
that button goes to to press the button.
If you're designing physical space social games,
you have a much, much clearer understanding
that the...
the unit of social interaction is one-to-one and one-to-one between two individuals with their own dynamic and preferences and priorities.
So this was probably the most successful social feature that I designed,
and one that I think I never would have designed if I hadn't come out of that feature.
This was a crazy text adventure we did for Skyfall, the Bond movie.
with a natural language chatbot.
So the hook was that you were going through
your initial test to find out whether or not
you could be a good MI6 agent.
So you got hooked up to the system that was,
the conceit, I guess, was kind of that MI6 agents
have like codecs that they type into
when they're having a bad day.
that would fly, and so you hook in and they're like,
oh, this has all gone wrong, I don't know what to do,
I'm stuck, help me, and you would type your way through it,
figure out how to solve their problem,
and if you won out, you would get an email,
psychological analysis that told you
the fake MI6's assessment of how you played
and what kind of person you were.
So in this one, I played manipulatively.
But then we would tell you that you were looking
for a different kind of agent.
So a ruthless agent or an unpredictable agent
or an impetuous agent.
And so in this recruit friends box,
we would ask you to nominate somebody.
So we'd hook you through to your Facebook friends,
but you could only pick one.
And it was kind of fun.
When you get a thing that says,
who is your most manipulative friend,
and you look through your list of Facebook friends.
You can't help but kind of go, oh no, not her, but him.
And what we got was through the roof rates
for both this share, but then also the response rate
from the people that we shared it to
because they felt like they were getting
something meaningful.
We also, this was a collaboration with Ryan and Kennedy,
and they had a super cute idea
that if you tried to circumvent that
and share it more widely,
it showed up on your Facebook feed as redacted.
So you could share the URL, but everything showed up with a text blacked out.
It looked super cool.
So we just said, no, you don't, you have to, one person, pick one person.
And it worked so well.
I know I never would have done it if I hadn't made a bunch of real-world social games
that operate kind of very differently.
So that still feels different and better.
That's that.
And then...
When I started out working in games and as a game designer, I'd come up as a game journalist and a game designer,
and if you asked me to express myself, I would write you an essay.
I would do a nice design document, with headings, and that's what you would get.
And I went from that to being smashed into a room with people from Widen and Kennedy,
or RGA, or Mother, or whatever else, or people from Tate Modern, or Royal Opera House.
The expectation of your ability to communicate visually,
and the expectation of your ability to present your ideas
kind of to the best of their capabilities,
was a lot of pressure very fast.
And I mean, you guys are...
going to be the judge of it, but I'm hoping that I'm a little bit better at presenting
my ideas than I was when I started out with those endless Word documents.
So I'm contractually obliged to give you takeaways.
I think I might actually be contractually obliged to give you takeaways.
That joke doesn't work in America, does it?
Have we got any Brits who can give me a takeaway laugh?
No?
All right.
You're lucky you didn't get a picture of a munchie box, which
sounds like you shouldn't Google, but you can Google, but then you'll still kind of wish you hadn't Googled.
Um...
So I try to think about...
Can I give any advice that's actually real useful advice
and advice that I can imagine myself having followed
either at the indie studio when I was helping run that
or at the commercial studio that I'm helping run now?
And I decided that in both cases,
it's all about the three Fs.
I'm lucky to be in the studio that I'm at now
and a big part of...
What's enabled that is just the people that we have.
We have a weird mix of people,
and we are very unprejudicial
about what people's backgrounds are.
We don't care about experience,
and we don't care about industry background.
What we do care about, or certainly what I care about when I'm looking to hire game designers,
is that kind of fundamental fluency.
Are you fast? Are you used to having to undergo a bunch of playtesting?
Are you good at taking that kind of feedback?
Are you good at communicating your ideas effectively and visually to a team?
I do not care how you've come by that experience.
I don't care whether you've got a degree. I don't care.
I don't care if you do have experience and you're bringing it to me out of a free-to-play studio,
I don't care if it's a bunch of game jams that you've done,
I don't care if it's some skills that you can transfer across from having been working in advertising or whatever else,
I don't care. If I feel like you can do it, that's my number one concern.
I do care a bit about your degree of familiarity with the space that I'm in.
Free-to-play has a bunch of weird habits and...
best practices that it's very useful to know,
but I don't care whether you know them
as a player or a designer.
If you have some degree of fluency with what that takes,
or how that works and how it fits together,
then that's all you need to make it on my list.
And then the third F is experience.
Because it helps, you know, I think that thing that I talked about earlier in terms of knowing what it takes to take something over the line does matter.
Knowing, you know, there is an amount of grit and a kind of breadth of focus that you need as you come to the end of a project to make sure that it debuts fulfilling all of the hopes that you had for it.
But again, I don't necessarily care about whether or not that's strictly speaking in games.
And I think...
The value for doing that is there's a different talk I could have been giving today.
If I was at a different studio, I wouldn't have been able to say so many of the nice things that I said about,
oh, hey, we did this ACLU thing, or hey, we got to do this artist collaboration.
I know that not everybody who's working in free-to-play is in that sphere.
But...
In a successful business, there just is the scope.
I know that from being in a absolutely down to the bones, impoverished indie studio.
We never had the scope to do those kind of things.
And in a bigger studio, you can if there is the institutional will.
And the institutional will is built out of the people who make up the studio.
And so the more you bring in people who are gonna help you
stay connected to a wider cultural sphere
and a more diverse set of attitudes and beliefs,
the more it becomes credible that you can start to
kind of incubate those kinds of projects and activities
within that commercial environment.
For any of these, it's also the three Fs.
Actually, or three Fs this time.
Last year, I made a sequel.
I made Dots and Co, it's a sequel to Two Dots.
It was unbelievably hard.
So hard, kinda hated it.
Learned so much, super proud of it.
I never did that as an indie.
You never make a sequel as an indie, are you crazy?
You're lucky if you survive releasing anything once ever,
and then even if you make it that far,
you probably have to do something different the next time.
And so the design education I got
out of really, really tearing down,
an existing successful game. It was such a hard challenge because it
often when you make a sequel you made a game and you released it and it did or
didn't do okay and then time passed and now you're going to make another version
of it. That's cool. In the modern games and
services age that's not how it works. Two Dots
isn't going anywhere. It's wildly successful.
It's iterating incredibly fast. Month on month on month it gets better and cooler
and grander. Coming in on top of that to say well
how do I make a sister game that sits next to that meaningfully?
meant I had to go through a process of deconstructing
all of the stuff about how 2Dots works,
but also where it's going,
but also where this could go that's different.
It was just like no design challenge I'd ever had.
So, I exhort anybody out there
who's working in an indie or art house space
to see if they can find a way to make a follow-up.
Now, I know that's not necessarily simple.
I know enough about being an indie
to know you don't always get an awful lot of choice
about what you do next.
If you can't make a follow-up for real,
And just pretend.
Just do a thought experiment.
Just sit down with a thing that you made six months ago.
It's a very different process than doing a post-mortem.
Go back to a thing that was finished
and imagine that you were gonna do a sequel to it.
You were gonna release a new version of it
three months, six months, a year from now,
and see what it teaches you.
Yeah, because you may not realize that there's a whole kind of design thinking that you're never confronting
if you're working in a way that's more free-form and independent.
And then this is maybe one of the toughest takeaways for me.
I loved working independently, I loved the crazy things that I got to do.
But I'm seeing now what being at a more focused studio is enabling me to do.
you know, reveling in that opportunity.
Alex Fleetwood, who isn't here,
my business partner in Hide and Seek,
in the time, we shut out Hide and Seek
three years ago, I think, maybe three and a bit.
In the time since then, he's caught his breath
and then come back with a project that was inspired by
a very, very, very embryonic project we did at Hide and Seek
maybe six or seven years ago.
And he's spent...
two and a bit years, and is now focusing energy
of five or six people, and one thing and one thing only,
which is this, this is Beast of Balance, his new game.
He's been, he showed it at the last two GDCs,
he just told me earlier, today was the first time,
this GDC was the first time where he came to show the game,
instead of having to bring it in a suitcase,
when he got to San Francisco, he just went to the store,
and he bought a copy of it in the store,
and then brought it to the thing,
and it's a great and proud moment.
And I look at that, and,
It looks to me like two things.
It looks to me like a thing we could have made at Hide and Seek.
It's so much.
You should check it out.
It's super cool and crazy and weird.
It's so much the kind of thing we love to make there.
It's like one part game, one part poem, one part educational app,
one part sculpture.
It's exactly the kind of thing that we love to do.
And it's also exactly the kind of thing
that we would never have accomplished.
Because the way you do this is you do nothing else for two years.
And I think.
If I had it all to do again, I think as an indie,
we got bounced so much into trying to do everything
because we never wanted to turn anything down
and we never had the confidence
to just try and pick one thing.
And I do now really wonder what, you know,
some of those ideas I showed at the beginning
were cute ideas, that board game remix kit was a cute idea,
Tiny Games was a cute idea.
But we put this much focus into it
and then had to transfer it to something else.
And I think,
I think if I've learned anything moving into the commercial world,
actually, it's not about following the money,
and it's not about worrying about the margins,
but it's about what a commercial,
the focus that a commercial structure can enable
that you struggle to get elsewhere.
Because that's really the thing, this, I opened with this,
this is Uncle Death, any Uncle Death fans?
I can't see you, but there you go.
So this is Uncle Death, he's your,
I don't know what he is, he's your mentor,
he's your bully, he's your something or other
in Let It Die, which is Suda51's weird,
free-to-play console brawler.
And that's interesting because...
I mean, I picked him just because he was my favorite Grim Reaper I could find in games.
I try to find good devils in games, and it's a weird space.
Once you decide you don't want to do a Diablo thing, you don't know what else you're going to do.
His site's a golf club.
But yeah, so I picked him because he's cool.
But also, I mean, there is somebody who has...
whose career has taken him from making things that are very much on the margins
and very much kind of creatively auteur-style defined and delivered,
through to a point where, you know, I make free-to-play games,
and he makes free-to-play games now, and they're pretty different,
and, you know, we have nothing to do with each other,
but it seemed like an interesting end.
But, so he's a cute choice of Grim Reaper, but he's not really appropriate,
because this is more about rebirth, I think.
We work in a super volatile industry.
I don't...
There's probably nobody here, or functionally nobody here,
who's been cozy and happy in the same company
for the last 25 years making the same kind of games.
That's not how it works for us.
There's too many winds of change blowing around.
games. It's part of what we love about games. The technology changes or the business model changes
or the audience changes or we uncover some kind of new control mechanism or new paradigm.
We're all dodging all of your stuff out there right now. It's never going to let us rest easy.
And so for me the biggest thing I've learned in this transition is those fundamentals, that kind
of the work is the work core practice stuff, comes with you. Like even if everything else
falls apart and we, Hide and Seek had an elegant end.
We never hit that go bust date,
despite the fact it tried its best.
And we were able to find the right moment to say,
this isn't gonna work anymore and finish our projects,
close things down elegantly,
treat everybody who worked there, I hope well.
We believe that we did that well.
Still felt god awful.
It felt absolutely excruciatingly miserable.
And I know that I'm not necessarily safe from that again in the future.
Right now I'm at a happy, successful company that all our expectations are,
we'll continue to be happy and successful, but I've done this long enough to know that,
you know, there are fates that await game companies.
They get bought by less friendly game companies, or their fourth sequel doesn't do as well,
or they back the wrong horse in terms of a technology platform,
or an input mechanism, or whatever it is.
So I probably won't be here forever either, but now I've got a clearer sense of how translatable
the skills that I have are, not necessarily to different industries, but just to different places
within the same industry. And I think we'll do better if we recognize that in each other,
that rather than just ending up with a much more kind of closed circle where indies know how to
talk to indies but are skeptical about people who've come from a free-to-play background,
or vice versa, we...
recognize that there are fundamental capabilities
that transcend those categories.
That is what I have for you.
We're hiring.
That's it, you're done, GDC's over!
Your questions are welcome.
So the topic that was most interesting to me about the
transition, a lot of what you're describing to me feels
like going from a consulting environment in some ways,
because you're also doing projects for these corporate
clients.
Going to free-to-play, the thing that has struck me,
like coming to GDC over the last five years,
was there was a lot of discussion about free-to-play
where it was whales and it's about paywalls
and ads and offers and skinner boxes, frankly,
where it felt very skeevy to me.
So for me, when I'm thinking about free-to-play,
that's the part that creeps me out, to be perfectly honest,
is that.
Obviously, Dots has a model.
How much does that influence your design work,
how you feel about what you do, when you look at free-to-play
and what you associate with?
So it's sort of a broad question.
No, I got it.
Got it.
I, what's, DODS is a very classic free-to-play approach.
And a thing that makes my life very easy
is that we don't, we don't do anything
we would be uncomfortable if our players knew about.
That's kind of our litmus is, would we feel okay
about if someone who loved our game came in
and said, how does this work?
And we went, oh, well, it's like this.
Would they feel like we'd been tricking them?
There's a couple things that we're not super public about
just because they're complicated,
but we'd very happily talk anyone through them at length.
It's just hard to put it in a tweet
in a way that won't misconstrue.
There's like a bunch of like super dense
spawning rules around objects
to make sure that the games stay fun
even when players do weird things.
And so those are hard to explain,
but they're designed only to make sure
people continue to have happy game experiences.
They're not revenue focused.
It's weird. I've made games that are just supposed to be about joy.
I've made games that are in a consulting or educational environment
where you're taking people to a point where there's some kind of threshold
you have to cross. Where they have to learn a thing or do a thing.
Sometimes that thing is they have to click on a link to go to the Green Lantern trailer.
And sometimes they have to prove that they've learned a Greek verb
or sometimes whatever they are. And now I'm in this place where...
We have a sumptuous, expensive game that we give away for free,
and then we get people to a point where we say,
if you want to keep going right now, you need to put your hand in your pocket.
And those things just feel super identical to me.
Like it's definitely not harder or weirder
to get somebody to give me a dollar
than it is to get them to watch the Green Lantern trailer.
And it's actually not that different.
In fact, maybe quite a lot easier
than when I'm designing a street game for Edinburgh,
where what I'm trying to construct
is a set of gaming incentives
where you will go and hold the hand of a stranger.
And frankly, if you give me the design challenge to make you give me a dollar,
versus the one where you have to hold hands with a stranger, I'll take the dollar, right?
That's easier.
So I think that the design challenge doesn't feel any different.
It's about...
motivating your player and then restricting the resources
that they have to reach the thing that you've motivated
them to reach, and then giving them interesting options
to resolve that restriction, and then spending
is one of them, but you're always gonna wanna offer
your player that choice anyway, and so it's just
what you swap in and out of those categories.
That doesn't, it just feels exactly the same.
Where it would feel different is if there was stuff
that I thought was exploitative or underhanded,
or designed to mislead or trick people.
We just don't have any of that, so it seems easy.
Is that at all helpful?
Yeah, I think if I was going to try to replay it,
the real core is, as long as you're
transparent with the users and you
feel ethical about what you're producing, it's OK.
And that might be part of that design process,
too, about where do you put in your loops
and how do you construct them?
Are these things feeling ethical or not?
If you feel good about it, then, well, you can sleep at night.
That's kind of what I think I'm hearing.
I think that's right.
That doesn't feel at all controversial to me.
And I think some of it definitely comes from designing face-to-face with players.
The model that I always have in my head is that an individual human is going to want to sit down and ask me questions
about any design choice that I make.
Yeah, it kind of just makes it trivially easy.
It's like, do I know how to answer that person's questions?
Cool, then I'm doing the right thing.
If I'm uncomfortable, then we do something else.
It's easy.
Yeah, that's helpful, because that also will allow me to,
one of the things I'm struggling,
I'm sorry, you guys have a question,
is how do I test out my monetization strategy?
And so if I can sit with somebody and face-to-face and.
know that they're going to say, okay, well, no, that's skewier, that's good.
That also gives me a design.
Well, I do, I, I, I pen and paper test all my monetization stuff.
Well, I pen and money test all my monetization stuff.
I have a cup of dollar bills on my desk and, and tokens and
everything gets tested like that.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hi.
So there was another talk today.
There's a researcher who is surveying game designers
to get their definition of success.
So what's your definition of success,
and did it change when you moved from one studio to the other?
You didn't have to answer.
Um, yeah, I've...
I have so far been 100% unsuccessful, I would say.
I've never, like, I feel like I'd maybe be successful if I
made a thing that I felt was good and that I was proud of.
I don't really feel like that.
Everything is full of compromises and missed opportunities.
The games that I love...
have a essentialism about them that you know that you couldn't, you can't change a single
rule of that game because it's just right, it's just perfect. And I'm fascinated by those games
and in all of them and I know I've not come close to making anything that good. So there's like,
I guess, yeah, I guess I have two definitions of success. There's that one which I haven't hit and
maybe I'll never hit.
Keep trying.
And the other one is, oh my god, I make games for a living.
Any year where I can pull that together is a success.
And I've done it for 10, and maybe I'll
get to do it for more.
And I think as long as I'm within that ethical territory,
I'm not that fussy about what it is,
because it's this weird, wonderful, absorbing task
that I'm nowhere near tired of yet.
I just want to say I really loved your talk and the really personal, wander-y style you
used.
I think it's fantastic and very honest and I appreciate that.
Now for my question.
You've talked a lot about, or hinted at your design process,
and it seems to be pretty rigorous and rational.
But also, I think a lot of people in free-to-play,
especially in mobile, feel that there's an element of luck
to a game becoming a smash hit.
And I would like your thoughts on that.
Do you believe, for example, Dots was mostly genius
with a bit of luck?
Do you feel like it was a lot of luck with a bit of genius,
or hard work, or good process, or, you know?
coming from a good design thing.
Yeah, that's my ill-formed question for you.
I mean, the cheat answer to that is
it's always about the work,
and the work needs to be perfect,
and then luck is the thing on top of that.
But I don't think you believe that,
and I know I don't believe that.
I mean, I'll tell you this.
The last game I launched was Dots & Co.,
and we launched it two weeks after a thing.
Was it?
Pokemon Go was that game?
Yeah, so that just changes the fundamental dynamics
of the App Store charts in a way
that you have no control over.
And that was very different from when
we launched our previous game, where the App Store wins
blue in our direction, not against us.
And so that kind of thing.
It's like a really identifiable quantifiable kind of luck.
Like that's not some weird, you know,
touchy feely, don't know.
Here's, I guess,
maybe my slightly more sophisticated cheat answer here,
is we are really bad at clearly differentiating
between luck and capital.
One of the reasons that nothing we did at Hide and Seek
ever got off the ground was it was partly because
we had too many things going on,
and in some cases I'm sure it was probably
because we were bad at our jobs.
But we could never afford more than one roll of the dice.
We'd put this thing out there and if it didn't work,
we weren't gonna eat that month,
so we had to run and do something else instead.
Big companies.
get lucky, because they can try over and over.
And that doesn't even necessarily look like
launching a thing that doesn't work
and then launching a new thing
and then launching a new thing.
2Dots has been alive for three years.
Over the course of that three years,
we've been able to make all kinds of additions
and amends and alterations to it.
We've been able to bring it out on extra platforms,
we've been able to do all of these things.
You know, that's a game that's been commercially successful
all the way through,
but...
if we hadn't been a studio with income,
if we hadn't been a studio with investment,
had we hit more bumps in the road,
they would have killed us dead
and we wouldn't have been able to do anything about it.
I'm not saying luck still isn't a factor, but when you look at a specific thing and
think well those specific people got lucky, it's worth broadening your examination of
the odds to say well how many rolls of the dice did they get, and how many rolls of the
dice am I going to get, and how do I sustain myself through those things.
And then you just try and get smart about the other stuff.
We couldn't...
We couldn't quite have navigated around Pokemon Go,
but we were navigating around a bunch of other stuff
in the app store that we did know about,
that we had researched, that we had kept our ears open for.
You can certainly mitigate that kind of risk.
And similarly with how you're handling
market testing of visual assets,
or you know you love them,
but is anyone else gonna love them?
You can amortize a bunch of that stuff,
but never all of it.
Slightly less cheaty answer?
Absolutely, I think that's a really great model
for thinking about it, thank you.
Thank you.
We're done, it's all over.
Margarita time, thank you everyone.