Hello, and thank you for attending this presentation,
What Wikipedia Doesn't Know Can Hurt You,
Writer Research Skills.
So a little bit about who I am.
My name's Chris Hepler.
I've been writing professionally since the 1990s
when I first got published in the field
of tabletop role-playing games.
I then tried my hand at television
for a CBS show called The Agency.
I then worked at Bioware on projects such as
Star Wars The Old Republic and Mass Effect 2 and 3.
Since then, I've been working for story-based mobile games.
First at a company called Fable Labs,
just down the street from this convention center.
And now I'm at CSUN Incorporated on an epic fantasy MOBA
called Relics of Gods.
Now, this list of credits doesn't have much in common.
That's kind of the point.
I've had to jump from techno thriller to space fantasy
to a game about the afterlife, like Hell,
and then to comedy aimed at kids, like The Dreadnought Kids.
And whenever I had to make those transitions, I wound up doing research.
So, why do I think you might need research skills?
I noticed a particular need for them during my transition from Star Wars The Old Republic to Mass Effect 2.
Well, that's the polite way of saying it.
The real story is, on Star Wars, our lead writer kept telling me,
Chris, stop trying to put science in Star Wars.
Star Wars isn't actually science fiction.
Lightsabers don't work.
Planets made of swamps don't work.
Act like the humanities major you are.
The extent of science in Star Wars is, direct quote,
blasters and turbo lasers and BOOM!
A year later, I get a call from our design department director who says,
Hi Chris, you're going to be working on Mass Effect 2
because three of our six writers just left
and the fourth one broke his shoulder.
So we need you to write the galaxy map and the codex entries.
And I said, sure, I like space stories, fine, bring me up to speed, how do I make a planet?
And so they handed me this.
This is a table of the minimum molecular weights of gases retained by a heavenly body.
You just figure out the density of the planet compared to Earth and then the diameter in
kilometers, and you cross-reference the molecular weights of gases like hydrogen or argon, which
are on another page.
Or you could refer to your handy chemistry textbook.
And if you want the planet to support life,
you need to have a proper mix of nitrogen and oxygen.
And good god, Chris, get to the point already.
So I asked, does your audience really care about this stuff?
And the answer was, probably a handful of them do.
But more to the point, this is part
of what made Mass Effect 1 hard science fiction.
And if you take that away from players in Mass Effect 2,
they're going to complain.
So Chris, can you write hard SF, even though you've never
done it before?
And I suspect questions like that will come up for some of the writers in this room.
Because not every writer finds a niche in one genre and stays with it throughout their whole lives.
Often, writers get hired because their dialogue samples were good,
and their list of credits are good, or because they're good in a room.
And the writer has to learn on the job.
That means research.
And that's what this talk's about.
So let's break this subject down by first examining types of research.
The first type I could think of is if you haven't just heard of your subject, you've lived it.
Say you're writing space opera and you've got a degree in astrophysics, like Catherine Asaro.
For those who are unaware, Dr. Asaro is a science fiction novelist who once wrote a book
that used as its plot structure an equation for the behavior of quantum particles.
Like the particles, the characters get attracted up to a certain point,
then they repel each other, and then they stay apart, but they still influence each other.
The entire concept for the novel came out of her first-hand knowledge of subatomic physics.
You may not have that skill set.
But you might have something else in your biography.
Have you traveled to Hong Kong so you
can write it into your crime game?
Were you in the army and drove a tank,
so your vehicle levels might be interesting?
Are you a practicing druid and writing epic fantasy?
Or are you basically just a guy or a girl
with an English degree?
Because if you are, you might want
to consider expanding your first-hand knowledge somehow.
So first-hand knowledge is great,
but like anything, it's got pros and cons.
On the pro side.
you will know a wealth of detail about your subject,
so you're more likely to create a more original story
than a writer who's just going by the numbers.
Frequently, you'll be able to win arguments
with the rest of the dev team,
because you know what you're talking about.
And you'll have the perspective to know
when something isn't important to the player experience.
Your knowledge also won't depend on anyone else's schedule.
So if you're in production and you need a question answered,
it'll be right there.
Lastly, it goes with you.
Any job you take, you have your knowledge base to draw from.
Disadvantages.
Well, you're highly unlikely to be a nuclear scientist slash Navy SEAL slash gang member
slash cowboy slash medieval knight.
Second, just because you know more than the rest of the team doesn't mean you know everything.
You could have expertise as a cop because you were one for 20 years, but if it was 10
years ago, maybe you don't know much about criminals using smartphones today.
Third, some knowledge comes with a price.
If you want to fly off to Ecuador for three weeks to research ruins for the next Tomb Raider, you're going to need money.
If you want a master's in astrophysics from Harvard, you're going to need a lot of money and also a few years.
For this last reason, first-hand knowledge is the sort of thing you get well before your game is in production.
During production, your butt stays in that chair.
So the next obvious step is to dig up every friend of a friend you can to find an expert.
I tried to come up with a list that would help most genres of game writers, but the
list is just too long, so I'm going to recommend two sites.
One is the aptly named Expertise Finder.
It's free, and it's dedicated to hooking up writers with university professors of many
different subjects.
Not only can you ask for their opinions, you can ask for their contacts.
It's great to talk to a criminologist, but don't forget, the criminologist might be able
to introduce you to actual criminals behind bars.
Next up is a site called Journalist's Toolbox.
And as much as we all boo journalists when they get something wrong about video games,
you have to realize journalists are extroverted writers.
They are called upon to digest large amounts of information from experts
and repeat it back in as little as a day, every day.
So their links can be your links.
Lastly, there are mailing lists and hobbyist forums.
On Mass Effect 2 and 3, these saved my life.
One of the first things I did was create a new email account
and hook it up to a group called SFConSim,
or the Science Fiction Conflict Simulation Mailing List,
which is populated by hard SF creators.
They were a great help and never dismissed any of my concerns.
So the upsides of experts are fairly obvious.
First, most productions that try to take themselves seriously
try to have some form of technical consultant.
Now, there are some awesome productions out there that don't take themselves seriously,
but if you're writing games about cops or war or spies or a historical period piece,
you should check in with an expert. This also goes for writing characters that are out of
your comfort zone. Maybe you're writing a character that has a different ethnicity,
is from another part of the world, or has a different sexual preference.
You probably want to run your ideas by someone before you end up writing The Phantom Menace.
Experts are also usually free, at least until you
are at a large company and are trying to have somebody
on staff all the time.
Usually, you can get all you need from a free deal.
Because if you say, hey, I'm writing a video game.
Please tell me about your job, and I'll try to work it in.
Most people are happy to talk for hours.
You give them a special thanks credit, and everyone wins.
Third, like with first-hand knowledge,
experts can give you perspective.
What looks good on paper and in movies
could totally not work in the real world
for very elementary reasons.
If you remember the molecular weights of gases retained table,
in plain English, told by an expert,
that table answers a really basic question
about space travel.
It's why you can't terraform the moon.
If the heavenly body you're talking about is small enough,
it doesn't matter how much air you pump in,
doesn't matter how many trees you plant.
It's gravity is so weak, all the air you add
is going to float away into space.
Downsides, your expert may not be good about checking their email,
and they could also be in a vastly different time zone.
Sometimes questions pop up, you can't get an answer, you've got to make a judgment call.
Second, experts aren't foolproof, and they can disagree.
On Mass Effect, I referred to a physics teacher of mine, who now works for NASA,
and I asked him questions about technology based on string theory.
And his answer was,
String theory is bunk.
So, either he's wrong, or the whole sub-discipline of string theorists are wrong.
And I'm really not qualified to tell you which.
So we didn't rely on string theory for any of the tech
in Mass Effect.
It also goes without saying you need to formulate
your questions right in order to get accurate results
from your expert.
Lastly, sometimes an expert will have conflicting interests
with you.
This happened to me most prominently
on the TV show The Agency, where our technical consultants
were former CIA agents.
If they gave away sources or methods and we put it on TV,
that means all the spies in the field couldn't
use those techniques anymore.
So when we questioned these people who were professionally trained at giving misinformation,
sometimes we hit a wall and our fictional spies had to use public domain methods dating back to
World War II. Then there's searching for reliable information online, also known as drinking from
the fire hose. The reporter's maxim is to find two independent sources before declaring anything
as fact. That's usually plenty enough due diligence to get your argument a fair shot when you run it
by other devs.
There are academic and scientific papers out there, but you frequently have to be a subscriber
to look at the actual data in things like the Journal of the AMA.
It was like $125 or so every 12 months.
Even when trying to come up with alien biology for Mass Effect, I never needed the results
of a paper that badly.
You know, the summaries are usually sufficient.
Television shows and reporters often make use of something called LexisNexis
to research legal cases and news articles, but their subject matter is frequently
cops and lawyers and people who need to know what's going on in
illegal cases right now. It's much less frequent in video games,
unless you all want to make some video games about that, so go right ahead.
Where video games rule
is fan wikis.
They can tell you scads of details about all kinds of media properties.
And then there's the last resort, which is flinging a question at Yahoo Answers and hoping
some complete stranger is passing by with the knowledge you need in the time you need.
You can usually do better than that.
So you're undoubtedly familiar with the power of electronic sources.
There are websites and enthusiast groups for almost everything.
They're extremely fast and convenient.
You can access most sources with your phone while you're sitting in the audience at a
lecture hall listening to some narrative designer tell you things you already know.
As for other advantages, what more do you need?
I googled it, I checked Wikipedia, boom, we're done, time for chocolate!
Right?
Now, there are many downsides to electronic sources.
Because crawling down the rabbit hole is fun, you can end up with a head full of TV tropes
and info totally irrelevant to your game, and you can make crazy assumptions about your
subject matter with no one to call you on it.
You also get in the habit of searching for answers instead of working around your shortcomings.
Wikipedia in particular has a hidden trap.
It has enough editors working on it
that if you find a fact, put it in, and then three months
later you want to double check the fact,
you may find the fact has disappeared.
And then you have to guess whether it's from an edit
or if your memory is suspect.
This inevitably happens late in production
when you're wanting to double check stuff before lockdown,
and you don't want to spend time searching
for a revision that may never have existed.
So watch out.
Lastly, I want to speak a little about Google Image Search.
Since at Faber Labs, it was invaluable for trying
to give references to our art department.
If you pick something out of the ordinary,
like pretty far out of the ordinary as your subject
matter, image search is not always going to be your friend.
At Faber Labs, our afterlife game, Like Hell,
had characters from all different times and places
in history showing up in the afterlife.
And I wanted a major NPC, Akaba, here, to be from West Africa,
specifically the Ashanti of Ghana.
And I said she lived around 1895 in the late colonial period.
And then because we were a hidden object game,
I had to come up with object images for 150 hidden objects
from Akaba's house in rural Ghana in 1895.
And what you get in Google Image Search,
if you're looking for a house in Ghana,
is photos of the colonial period in black and white,
so our artists didn't know what colors to use.
wrong time period stuff, modern westernized Ghana,
hi guys, and Guinean cuisine.
And unsurprisingly if you look at the settings of our competition in hidden
object games, you get two settings. You get 20th century America
and Victorian London where there are mountains more image references.
I filled out my 150 objects but let's just say there's more pangolin soups in
those scenes than anybody expected.
Then there's books and magazines.
Nonfiction books can be the product of decades of labor and conveniently sum up hundreds of scientific studies in an accessible format.
Print can also introduce you to subcultures that you didn't know existed.
If you want to find people who know what to do when your plane goes down over Siberia
and you have to make a bow and arrow from scratch so you can hunt on the tundra,
Expertise Finder won't help.
But I found Primitive Archer magazine.
You can find it at newsstands.
Not in libraries, newsstands.
So it led me to the subculture of flintknappers,
the hobbyists who make knives and arrowheads
like they did in the Stone Age
by banging moose antlers against rocks.
Far Cry Primal, anyone?
And then there's stealing from printed fiction.
Lots of game devs will talk about
what they saw on TV last night or at the movies,
but everyone's stealing from that already.
This is not just about being derivative,
it's about providing variety.
When I was coming up with the Thanix Cannon Codex for Mass Effect 2,
I had to pick out a new weapon that improved on your ship's main gun.
It had to have physics that worked, but it couldn't be a laser.
Lasers are boring.
It couldn't be a railgun or coilgun.
That's what it was replacing.
Couldn't be a particle beam weapon.
We had one of those.
Couldn't be a plasma weapon, because, fun fact, plasma weapons don't really work.
And I didn't know a lot of hard science, but Arthur C. Clarke did,
and he came up with something called the stiletto beam.
So I'm actually curious about this.
Has anyone ever heard of the stiletto beam?
Two people.
Cool.
It's similar to a rail gun, where
you use magnets to fire the projectile,
except the projectile is molten metal.
It's a self-forging fragment, and you really
don't want to get hit with it.
And it wasn't on TV last night.
It was published in a novel called Earth Flight back
in 1951.
It's right there on the cover.
Some print material becomes dated.
Newtonian physics, not so much.
So fiction and nonfiction can be great, but the bad news is they're slow at two points.
One is when you're searching for the ideas.
The other is when you're actually doing the writing and need to double check the details before your deadline.
Relying on your memory is not a good idea.
Details get lost, so mark the pages with sticky notes labels.
Another strike against print is that it looks authoritative,
but some books that are marketed as the real deal simply aren't.
There's, for example, the Hitman Manual, probably not written by a hitman.
Anarchist Cookbook?
Don't try it at home.
If you found a book in the science section, that's no guarantee that it's settled science.
And then there's just omission.
You can read a book like Codename Mule, a perfectly reasonable account of the CIA's
secret war in Laos during the Vietnam conflict by a guy who was there.
Analysts be generous.
probably not a lie in the book.
He just has to tell his own experiences.
But if that's the only book you read on the war in Laos,
you never hear all the other sources
accusing the CIA of running heroin
to help finance the war effort.
That's like the juiciest detail ever,
and he's basically saying the government party
is lying about it.
I don't know the truth about it.
I just know a single book should not
be your only source either.
So, now let's try to get into some specific techniques to try to save you all some time.
The first step is the big strategic one. I've encountered basically two ways writer teams
approach research. Approach one is the writer's research all they can, and they write up a ton
of lore, then they build their plots, and they pitch and design game levels based on what works
in this universe. Approach two is you research only as needed. You spitball ideas for game levels,
once they sound entertaining, you do the research to work out the details. So both approaches work,
but the first one...
Well, it requires the writers to have enough power to nix some level design ideas, which is not a given depending on what company you're at.
It also means you're shutting out other departments at the concept stage.
The second approach will probably make you more popular due to more team input.
It's also faster.
Time is money.
Importantly, lore is also usually easier to change than everything else downstream of the writer.
So lots of lore usually gets thrown out during production anyway.
Or at least revised.
The downside is that your finished product
could look patched together unless you are out there
evangelizing to your team constantly.
Okay, now for the elephant in the room,
which is why are we so worried about getting it right?
Sometimes it is actually more efficient
to write in a way that doesn't require research.
I'm gonna hit you with a wall of text here,
don't freak, it's just broken down
into two examples of the same scene.
Let's say someone just got poisoned on our space opera.
The dialogue on the left is fact-filled.
It mentions the name of the poisonous fish he ate.
It draws a parallel to fugu, an earth fish.
It says what part is toxic and why.
And it says two rules for the IP that the other writers
on the team now have to remember.
By comparison, the rewritten example on the right
just gets across the main point.
We have a poison crew member.
Then it throws in some humor and some sass
and puts the pressure on the player to make a decision.
And it only really gives them the essential information.
Everything else is characterization.
If you want to look at that for just a second.
Okay, let's move on.
Okay, sometimes you don't want to fudge it.
That is where I personally use a technique I call one slice.
Its point is to impart one single fact to the player.
You serve the player this one fact, like one slice of pizza,
and you create the illusion that there is more,
in other words, the rest of the pizza.
Why just one fact?
Because if you want to base any kind of plot structure on a fact,
you want just one per scene.
So whoever your most knowledgeable character is about the subject,
They communicate this fact.
They don't have to be a nerd.
They just have to have a stronger handle on the subject
matter than whoever they're talking to.
Other characters can doubt them, but ultimately, it
proves to be true.
Now, when you research that fact,
you've given yourself a simpler task.
You now have just one fact to confirm,
rather than going on a fishing expedition.
The end result is less time wasted on the internet
and fewer emails back and forth with your expert.
So let's apply the one slice to a plot.
Say we're doing a modern world setting and we need a clue for your protagonist to find when they're on the trail of some robbers.
The robbers are tough, smart opponents, and at this point in the game you want a fact for your player to see they have military experience.
So we can have plenty of filler or dead ends depending on gameplay needs,
but the story advances when we hit one fact that our experts pick up on that screams,
military.
So let's say the robbers took out a guard silently with a knife, because that takes training.
So we ask our technical consultants for our one fact, and we find out this could actually be a good one.
because the way Hollywood shows it in every movie
is different from the way Army manuals tell you to do it.
The Hollywood way, and I'm gonna get morbid here,
it's so common we even have a hand gesture for it.
But in Army manuals, it looks more like this.
You sort of stab in and then you push forward.
So we have one key clue that our expert character,
maybe a forensics guy, the medical examiner,
something like that, or maybe somebody
who was in the military,
their expert character can recognize it,
which gives the expert the illusion of competence.
Often, that's all you're really going for.
The primary goal is not to show
that you've done your research.
The primary goal in commercial video games anyway
is to entertain the audience, not educate them.
Our core fact is not there for show.
It gives us a step forward in the plot
because now that the protagonists have this clue,
they're closer to the antagonist.
Mission complete, next scene.
So now we should get specific about some major pitfalls
in video game development, starting with, not this one.
This one, chaos, because video game writers are inevitably dealing with a team environment.
The rest of your team will be making content at the same time you are, downstream from
you.
So your facts and your lore rules better be learnable, and you better be teaching them.
But wait, you say, if I codify lore rules before the art and gameplay are created, they
might get thrown out.
But if I create them after the art and gameplay are created, like in codex entries or in-game
books that get written after VO lockdown, I can't teach them to anyone until it's too
late.
Yeah.
This is why writers need to evangelize the IP
to the rest of the team on a regular basis.
Every week you go without evangelizing
is a week of work that might have to get thrown out.
I find email blasts saying IP rules created
and a list of bullet points work okay.
Anything longer, nobody reads it.
This helps enforce your rules,
and if there's new hires halfway through the project,
you can open up your sent file and have a folder
and send all the emails to them,
bring them up to speed quickly.
Otherwise, well, chaos.
Contradicting the team brings up a question.
How many rules of the universe do you really want to have?
Everybody starts out saying our lore will be consistent, but over time I see two schools
of thought on the approach to lore rules. The first is what I call an exclusive universe.
Exclusive universes try to build their lore with a lot of specific
research rules saying we have no X because Y.
For example, according to some research codex entries, no one fires missiles at ships in the Mass Effect universe
because the dominant ship technology in the future includes a system of anti-missile lasers.
So instead, everybody uses weapons that are incredibly high-velocity guns.
So, let me find my next image here.
Ah yeah, here's some people firing missiles at a Reaper ship in the Mass Effect universe.
Totally my fault, long story.
The point is, in almost all future military IPs,
missiles are common.
Rules of no missiles are not common.
Having rules based in research that aren't intuitive
can bite you in your exclusive universe.
By contrast, there's the inclusive universe,
the universe where the guiding principle is,
yeah, we have that too.
They have thunder gods next to dudes with spider DNA
who were clones from an alternate universe, and so on.
They just want to tell attention-grabbing stories,
and they do pretty well with them.
The problem is, every now and then, the franchise gets so bizarre, it's hard on newcomers' brains,
and you have to reboot it with a simpler approach.
Then there's the pitfall of becoming the unrelatable expert.
Because you immersed yourself in a world to learn all about it,
and because you see that there's at least a handful of people that know about it,
you assume the fact is common knowledge.
And it is, for some people, but almost certainly not a large portion of your demographic.
This is compounded if the person who is your usual safety valve is as big a nerd about a subject as you are.
And in our industry, there might be some nerds there, so high likelihood of that.
I refer to this as a two enthusiasts effect.
How do you get around this?
Well, you remember the point of research is in case a player has done their homework,
but you can't expect them to do their homework.
And sometimes the bar for being an unrelatable expert is very low.
For example, this hidden object scene is from Wuga's very fun game, Agent Alice.
Like every hidden object game I've ever played, the hidden objects are kind of loopy.
You're in a casino vault.
Why is there a chameleon here?
And a Siamese cat, and a gun, and a golden spade symbol on the door, and I think that's
King Tut in the background.
So at Fable Labs, I was determined, we're going to make our game differently.
So I was paired with an artist who loved a lot of my ideas.
We said our hidden objects would be based on a theme.
There would be narrative told through the objects.
If they didn't make sense, we wouldn't have them.
And so I picked out hidden objects
for this chamber of science, in which the player goes
through the possession of a lost soul who is a chemistry
professor in life.
And one of the hidden objects is a Florence flask.
Please raise your hand if you've heard of a Florence flask.
Not a ton of people.
Please raise your hand or keep your hand up if you remember what a Florence flask looks like off the top of your head.
Okay, and if you can you spot the Florence flask in the table full of glassware? Okay, there's our problem.
Playtesters had no idea what the search image in their head should look like. A Florence flask looks like this, by the way.
In Agent Alice, when you find objects in a scene, it's like, go, get your iPad.
Boom, boom, boom, boom, find that one, find that one.
Boom, boom, boom, boom, boom.
Cool. And then you replay it for more points.
And it's like, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom.
I know where everything is.
Boom, boom, boom, boom, boom.
Because you can easily ID a chameleon, a cat, or a gun.
In our gameplay, it was more like, hmm.
Blink. Blink.
Maybe I should Google that one.
Which is what I did when creating it.
I did one Google image search and became
an unrelatable expert.
And the artist I gave the reference to,
his first exposure to the idea was a captioned art reference.
He already had his homework done for him,
so he couldn't be a stopgap.
As a matter of fact, congratulations.
I think I just made you all into unrelatable experts
as far as this scene is concerned.
So last research pitfall, being imprisoned by the real world.
I talked earlier about getting in the habit of searching
for answers instead of getting in the habit of creating them.
Knowing how things work in the real world
can start you down the road to being no fun at all.
For if you resemble, excuse me, if you remember that example
I had a little while ago about the right way to take out
a sentry with a knife, yeah, the real professionals
don't advocate that anymore.
Melee weapons are pretty much obsolete in modern warfare,
and that's unlikely to change in the future.
This chart here from icasualties.org.
is for Afghanistan, where over about 14 years, knives and bare hands together came to 0.13%
of U.S. combat deaths. Most of the time, modern armies don't need to take out a sentry quietly.
They go in with overwhelming force, artillery, sniper cover, and special operations guys
who have higher likelihoods of sentry scenarios, they commission this silenced pistol, specifically
for killing sentries, because they want maximum results with minimum risk.
But in video games, risk is fun.
Melee weapons are fun.
Sure, I want a pistol like this in my future video game,
but I also want this and this.
And more to the point, the combat designers on my team
want them.
And if you say, nope, we don't do that, the lore says so,
and I'm sticking to it, when you get voted down,
they're probably going to do it anyway.
And then you, writer and lore expert, better retcon it,
or else you have inconsistent lore.
On that note.
I wanted to say that despite all your efforts, you will probably at some point get it wrong.
Facts become dated.
It's sort of the nature of many facts.
Your name will be on something that has gone out wide, and the error will seem glaring
to a certain subsection of your audience.
To some degree, this is normal.
Name any franchise you want.
The more products it puts out, the more chances it has to vary in quality.
And when it happens to you, you will have the urge to get out your side of the story.
This gives you three commonly used options.
The first option is to try to stay above the spray.
This is a good instinct because fans take screenshots of dev posts,
and anything thrown out onto the Internet can be considered there forever,
including any attempt you make to retract your statement.
Whatever the fan heat is, it can wait a day while you talk with your co-workers
and figure out how to present to United Front.
It also means you can make a note to address the concern in your next product,
at which point you can consider the problem in a sober manner.
The second option is to get out there on forums, fan wikis, interviews, convention appearances.
Depending on which corner of the internet you go to,
your experience may be positive, or it
could entail a ridiculous amount of personal risk,
because these are fans.
And that enormous subject aside, it
does have some actual benefits to you as a researcher.
Meeting fans will sometimes lead you
to meeting new experts who have an interest in your material.
Then there's the third option, which I've tried the most,
which is to hide under the bed thinking
you're a human garbage person.
I don't recommend this strategy.
mostly because the clearance on most beds
is actually about 6 and 12 to 7 inches.
And the average chest thickness of adult humans is 9 and 12.
So odds are you won't fit.
In conclusion, there's two recommendations
I can really give you.
Either know your craft well enough
that you can tell a good story, regardless of the fact,
or get out there and do some research in ways
that you can turn into material.
There's hobbyists out there who can teach you how to pick locks.
There are pilots who can show you how to land a plane when the engines catch fire.
There are survivors of cults who can tell you how they were indoctrinated.
There are nurses and patients who will let you know what it's like to be locked in a mental ward.
Each of these could feed scenes that have been in video games before,
but when you write them, they could have a different focus or a clearer ring of truth.
So tell the truth, not the facts, and when people play your scenes,
their experience might cause them to say,
Huh, I got it right.
Thank you for your time and attention.
Time for chocolate.