My name is Tim Fowers and I'm here for creating Bruegel Bros. or Bruegel Brothers, it's still
undecided.
Fantasy of the Heist.
All right.
Is this going to focus?
Okay, how do I...
Do I have to give focus to this thing to move?
There we go.
OK.
All right.
So I'm an indie developer.
I started about 10 years ago.
And I made a couple indie games on my own and with some
friends, and one was called Now Boarding.
And
We did that for a couple of years.
And over time, I wasn't always working out long term.
Well, let's head it over to the industry.
So I worked at Amazon Game Studios in Southern California
for three or four years.
And then during all these processes on the side,
I was working on board games.
Because I fell in love with making video games and board
games at the same time.
And I really see them as kind of two sides of the same coin.
So I made a game called Paperback and a game called
Virgo Brothers.
And both have done really, really well.
And I've been trying to take that indie aesthetic, that's
the skills you learn being an indie and doing these really
kind of quality games, and bring it over to board games.
And it's proven to work out really, really well.
And
So I'm going to talk about the differences between board games and video games.
Because they're similar, but the difference is that board games are software that run on people.
So you're writing this code and people have to like ingest this all, have this going in their brain,
and you don't want to break the compiler, you don't have too many rules,
and they're the ones that they're experiencing these rules, but it's all transparent.
Because video games are like this black box, right?
You're giving it inputs and you're getting certain outputs,
and you're trying to figure out what the rules are inside that box.
And you get kind of a sense of what's going on, but it still
surprises you in certain ways.
But the ways that board games surprise you are through, you
know all the rules.
All the rules are in your head, and they're
combined in new ways.
And you're like, oh, that's a combination.
I didn't think of using that card and that card together,
or powers together, or whatever.
And so it's this delight through emergence, not through
finding out a new rule of what's going on under the hood.
And the other thing about board games is its very raw design.
You, as a designer, you've got a box of parts and instructions,
and it's got to sing.
It's got to entertain and pull all these emotions out
of people.
And we talk about a lot of emotions in video games,
but there's a lot of emotion in board games.
And I want to talk about some of the range of emotions you can have here.
So you've got your werewolf mafia, and that's about, you know, and Secret Hiller.
It's about deceit.
Like what's the key moment in that game when you're like, it's when everyone believes you
and you've got them all fooled.
If you want to turn it up higher, I don't know if many of you have played this, but diplomacy is literally you have to stab all your friends in the back to win one at a time.
Gain their trust, and then it's like Survivor. You're voting them off at the last minute and it's tragic.
And do not play it. It will end friendships.
Because that's the level of emotion that board games can create.
And then there's, you know, Settlers. It's about reciprocity and trade.
To get to Rideware, it's about prioritizing, you know, building your network.
But in cooperative game, it's about altruism.
It's about sacrificing for each other and collectively problem solving.
And there's all these positive emotions around it and that's why I've been drawn to it.
Because in board games, you test a lot and you test live.
And I get driven by the energy that comes off of cooperative games.
So where do we derive our emotions from?
And a lot of times it's from other media.
Let's see, there we go.
Other media, so we watch these movies, TV shows, books,
and they all have these moments, right,
that we want to capture.
And so often in video games, we think literally.
We're like, okay, well, let's capture the scene
or the visual or the cinematography.
But.
I think that what we really want, what we can get to with video games and with board
games is the emotion at the core of it.
And, because really what it comes down to
is these scenarios, you know, am I doing a heist?
Am I, you know, surviving on an island?
Am I learning Kung Fu?
You know, they get to the point of
what would I do in that situation?
Like, that's when I talk about the fantasy of the heist
is like, we really ask ourselves this
when we're looking at different media
and you're like, yeah, if I could fly, I would do X.
Or, you know, there's all these kind of scenarios
we put ourselves through.
And so,
Through developing burgle bros, I've kind of got a system now that I use, and this wasn't
all intentional, but this is the method that I came to, was that...
You take a scene or a moment in what you're trying to,
your source material, whatever that material is,
and you peel it back, and you peel back,
and you find at the nugget,
what is the, at the best moment of that scene,
what are you actually feeling?
And then you try systems to recreate it.
You try choices, and you try game systems,
game mechanics to reproduce it.
And it takes a lot of iteration to find something
that can get the emotion that you want.
Because anytime you create a system, there's going to be other things that, unintended consequences.
So you gotta clean it up, and you gotta have to mitigate certain parts of that system that you don't really want.
And then you tie it back into the theme. You're like, okay, if we have the system, what else would happen in that mechanic?
And weave it back into your theme.
And this is the method that I've kind of discovered with Bruegel Bros.
So...
I started with a hybrid game.
I was working on an app that you interacted with a board game, and it was about a heist.
And I went to Gen Con, I'm like, I'm demoing this game, and I'm like, because you go and
you get people to playtest when you're a board game creator.
You're like, okay, come play my game, and you've got to convince this guy that doesn't
know who you are that this game is awesome.
And I'm like, okay, it's like Ocean's Eleven, the board game.
And their eyes lit up, and they're like, I want to play that game.
And they'd come over and they'd play it, and the game was horrible, and I apologized to
everybody that played it.
Because it didn't fulfill that.
But that put this bug in my head.
I'm like, this is something people want.
People want to live out a heist, and they want to know what choices they would make
in that situation.
So...
Um...
So I came up with Burgle Bros.
And Burgle Bros. was this,
I'm gonna talk about the process of how we got there.
But the high level is, it's a cooperative heist.
And this is a fun tower that you can play it on,
but you normally play it flat.
And it's, you have these three floors.
that you're exploring.
Now, if anybody gets caught, it's over.
It's kind of to have the high stakes.
Because you know, if you get caught, you're going to rat
on your friends so you don't go to jail.
And so it's three floors.
And there's a safe on each one.
And there's a whole sequence of how you open the safe and
find the combination to the safe.
But on top of everything is all these tiles are alarms
and traps with different rules about how you can get
through them and whether they trigger an alarm.
And then on top of that, there's this guard patrolling
on each floor and he's using a waypoint system.
And so you have these three stealth tokens
and everyone has three stealth and if you lose all three
of your stealth, you're caught.
So that's the stakes.
So going back to the source material,
let's look at a heist, right?
These are the tropes of a heist,
and these aren't all of them,
but these are some high points, right?
So we're gonna assemble the team,
we're gonna get all the, you know,
we're gonna get out of jail or whatever,
we're gonna assemble the players, right?
And then we're going to make a plan,
we're gonna pick our target, make a plan,
and there's always a montage of all the different alarms
and guards we have to get through and how impossible it is.
And then you start the plan and you're evading the guards
and getting through all the alarms
and everything's going according to plan.
You need to get to the safe and you're cracking the safe
or you're downloading the thing and little bars going
and you're sweating bullets and then something goes wrong.
Like there's always something that goes wrong.
There's a twist, right?
And then...
You pull off a miracle.
Or maybe you had a plan all along.
You had a backup plan and it comes into effect.
And then there's the grand exit.
It's like, yeah, we made it out.
And high fives and go spend our money.
So let's break this out.
So assembling a team, the core emotion here is...
How am I going to contribute to this team?
So it's partially contribution, but I think there's something underneath there.
When you're picking a character, you're often like,
okay, well what powers does he have?
Like, what can he do?
And often when you're designing these kind of roles,
you want to think, like, how can everybody break one rule of the game?
Because that makes you feel powerful and special in a group.
And that's interesting, but underneath there's a character
to each one of these.
And so I had these different personas we developed.
And because you're really, you're putting on a mask
when you're playing a character.
And this is in a lot of games.
And this is part of the whole,
what would I do in this situation?
And so now you're taking on a character
of what I would do in that situation
and experimenting and seeing what you would do.
How does this reflect on who I am?
So that's just assembling the team.
So putting on the mask.
So then making a plan.
So early on in the design of Burgle Bros,
it was about like, okay, what's going on?
Where are the guards gonna be?
Let's plan the whole thing out.
Because that's a big part of the fantasy,
but it really ended up conflicting with
the ability to make kind of tactical decisions and whatnot.
Because if you think about it,
like if you had to plan the whole thing,
and then if you were wrong,
you kind of just have to play the game again.
Like it wasn't, it didn't make an interesting loop.
And so there's some counterintuitive things
that I had to move away from the trope.
And this is one of them.
It was, because people are like,
so you're breaking into this building
and you know there's a safe there,
but you literally know where none of the alarms are.
Like you guys are not well-educated thieves
going into this place.
But it was an important decision.
And how this kind of works is the motion that was more important to me was the perfect prediction.
And this is the moment where the guard's walking by and I'm perfectly stepping behind every statue.
I'm doing everything in sync and I'm totally predicting everything the guard is going to
do and I feel awesome because there's no way he's going to find me.
That led to a couple of different systems.
One is these tiles, so you're exploring and you have to take certain risks.
These tiles start face down and you can decide to run into a tile.
and see what it is and hope that it's not bad.
Or you can peek, but that takes, it's slower.
So you have to decide how quickly you want to do this.
And that gives an information horizon.
You're like, okay, I know I've already seen
some of these tiles, I don't know what that could be,
but I'm gonna take a risk.
And then on top of it is the waypoint system for the guard.
The guard, he moves towards the next waypoint,
but then after that, he's gonna draw a card
and you don't know if he's gonna go left or right.
You know, you gotta take a guess.
And so this creates these smaller moments,
these small dynamic puzzles between the static puzzle
of the tiles and the walls you have to move around
and the dynamic puzzle where the guard is at the time,
to you have to take a guess.
And by making the players take a risk,
if it pays off, then like, oh, I knew it.
I knew he'd go that way.
And you feel like that prediction, right?
You feel like I pulled it off correctly.
And if he doesn't we had to create the other end because a big part of stealth is that it's high stakes
I mean, that's the thing about stealth games often in stealth games you get caught you're shot or you're go to jail or whatever
And so I was I wasn't sure how to do this
I wanted to have high stakes and and this is where you don't really design alone
I mean people in board games probably design more alone than they do in video games
But I went to my friend and I'm like
I don't know what to do.
I want people to lose, I want to have high stakes,
but he's just like, well, just give them hit points.
They can get, you know, and so we came up
with these stealth tokens and he like,
you disappear and you get three chances
to hide from the guard and then you don't have any more
and next time he catches you.
And what it introduces is soft loss
because you don't get the stealth back,
but you have this definite progress towards losing
anytime you're in the same tile as one of the guards.
All right, so perfect prediction is the fantasy.
So cracking the safe.
So cracking the safe is you're trying to do it
quickly as you can, but it's this unknown.
You're like, I can't do anything.
It's only going to crack so fast.
Or I've got to guess numbers.
And you feel this pressure because you don't know when
the guard's going to come.
So the emotion here is you're going to get caught.
Right? And so I definitely wanted some randomness.
And you know, you really got to watch the randomness, though,
because when we first did it, we're like, oh,
if you roll the right numbers, you get in.
And it was just kind of like quick.
Like sometimes it was really quick, and sometimes it was,
you know, too long, and it was frustrating.
And again, you know, I went to a friend, and I'm just like,
well, how do I, how do you mitigate this luck problem?
Because I want it to be random.
Because then when you roll the six, there's this cheer.
But, you know, so, you know, came up with a system and it was like, you can invest in
more dice so you can make a safer, you know, you can roll more dice when you do roll dice
and it makes the whole thing safer.
Or you can be risky, ah, we can do it with like one die or two die, we're lucky, and
then, you know, but it might take you twice as long.
And that certainly happens.
And then the other part of like, I'm working on the safe and I don't know how long that's
going to take, and then there's the guard, the guard is coming.
When we first played it, there was this moment where
after every player's turn, the guard on that floor moves.
And so somebody's like, so if I go upstairs,
only that guard will move?
And I'm like, well, yeah, it's kind of like the movie
where the action is only where the camera is.
So if the camera's up here,
you assume that nothing's happening on this other floor.
So would it allow it as a side effect?
So he's like, so if I go upstairs, he won't get caught.
He's like, well, I'm like, I guess not.
So now a whole part of the game is manipulating the guard through which floor are you going to activate, so where are you going to end your turn.
And some people even didn't like that. They're like, that's unrealistic. Why aren't the other guards moving?
And I'm like, it works as a tool to give the players to solve their problems.
And it also gives us another thing,
and little side note is about vulnerability.
And the TED talk about vulnerability
and how it's how we form relationships as humans,
it's core to cooperative experiences.
And if you think about Left 4 Dead, right?
Left 4 Dead, you know, you get pinned, right?
And a zombie's on you and you literally can do nothing.
And then one of your friends comes over
and kicks the zombie off and shoots him,
and he reaches down and he pulls you up.
And he's accepted you as a friend, but also as,
you're important to this mission,
you're important to this team.
And sacrificing for each other,
and giving these moments where I can save someone else
is how relationships are formed.
And I just think it's really important, sorry, side note.
So something always goes wrong, right?
So this is the best laid plans,
and it's tricky in a board game.
Like, I didn't know how to have the twist
where something goes wrong,
and how do I get that paced in the game,
and how does that even fit in?
And it actually came from
kind of the most benign part of the game.
There was this moment where one of my friends was playing and he's like on the bottom floor
and he's like, so there's a guard outside, so I'm literally going to do nothing on my
turn.
And I'm like, well, yeah.
And we came up with this thing where when you don't use a certain number of actions,
you roll a dice.
And that can be something good or something bad, but it's an unknown.
And then eventually it became like a deck of cards.
And it actually, if you think about it,
like the moment that you're hiding in the closet
and the guard is coming by
is exactly when something is going to crash.
And something, you know,
or a cat's gonna spook something
or something good or bad is gonna happen.
And so we call it the event deck
and it ended up being this great way
to both mitigate kind of the boring moments of the game,
but also it only happens a couple times per game.
And so it was a nice way to.
parse out these moments that could be plot twists.
And sometimes it'll save you too.
It's a variable.
So all these things are happening, right?
The guards are speeding up over time.
We crack open a safe.
Now, when you get a safe open, you get two things.
You get a loot.
This is what you came to steal.
And it could be like a Chihuahua that randomly barks
and sets off alarms or something.
They're silly things that you came here to steal.
And then you get tools.
It's a one-shot ability.
So these tools are like an EMP or a crowbar.
And they give you one chance to do something really cool.
And.
And so all these things are moving towards the climax
of like, okay, the guards are moving super fast,
we're all low on stealth, how are we gonna do,
and how are we gonna get out of this?
And this is where the tension is the core emotion here.
And this forced players into a corner of sorts,
like in a, it's more of an emotional corner
than a physical corner,
but sometimes it's a physical corner.
But it was that they're stuck.
They're like, okay, we're gonna lose.
And I'm like, no, no, no.
Just, you know, you can figure out something.
And they would surprise me, and they're like,
ah, I got it.
If I do, if I go here and trigger this alarm,
or I use my gadget, I use my tool,
or I use my player power,
and they started really thinking laterally,
and coming up with really creative solutions
of how to get out of these problems.
And it surprised me.
I was just creating a system and turning up the heat,
and people were like pulling off these crazy moves,
and I'm like, okay, that's a really good solution to that.
And it doesn't always pan out either.
Sometimes they fail, right?
And looking at failure is part of it as well.
And how people see failure, like after a game,
you really don't want people being like,
that was arbitrary.
You want people saying like,
I could have done...
I could have done another thing that would have let me win.
And so having that couch, having that emotional scapegoat really helps people want to reengage
and want to retry a game.
And often cooperative games, people want a challenge.
They often don't want to win on their first game.
So they can feel like, okay, I know what's going on now.
We're going to win this one.
And they'll get back into it.
So yeah.
Then there's the grand exit, right?
So we got past the hardest problem in the game
and we got the loot and we're headed out.
And this emotion is the relief.
So we had all the tension and the problem solving
and the relief is that we made it out.
And this is where you really want the dramatic exit.
This is like drop the mic, smash the guitar,
do a victory lap.
It's like you wanna feel awesome
and you wanna leave a mess.
You just like, you're like, you know what?
And so we have this dramatic exit where you're leaving in a helicopter on the roof. And there
was another side effect of the whole guard rules was, oh, if I go to the roof, there's no
guards up there, so no guard moves on my turn. And so there's this moment where, oh, yeah,
we're out of here. And everyone gets to leave and the guard doesn't get a move and you feel
like it takes the pressure off when all of a sudden you have an easy out.
And then there was also other moments where people surprised me.
They're like, so I have this tool that can make a staircase anywhere.
I say we leave here.
And the roof comes out and grappling hooks go up.
And they're like, we're just going to leave right here and exit to our helicopter.
And it surprised me.
And it was a great moment.
So the overall emotion, right?
So how do these all add up?
You know, you're creating all these individual moments,
but how do they sum together into the takeaway?
Like when I talked about these other board games,
and it kind of took me a while to realize what it was.
And for Briggle Bros, it was cleverness.
That I feel shrewd and clever and I outwitted them in a noncombative way.
And this is where you want to decide where you're going to spend your money.
And so this is where you evaluate. You're like, okay.
I'm looking back at my game and what moments or emotional beats from the source material
did I reflect in my game?
And which ones didn't?
Because they're not going to all make it in.
But you have to look at which ones are pushing towards the overall emotion you're shooting
for.
And remember that there's short term emotions,
so there's like a crisis, like I have to make a decision,
I'm rolling a die, I'm drawing a card,
and there's a moment, right?
But there's also longer emotions, there's dramatic,
there's the, is my character transforming,
am I getting stronger, are the waters rising,
is the pressure getting higher,
is there a climactic battle, you know,
are these moving towards an overall more dramatic arc?
And that's satisfying from a storytelling perspective.
So.
Coming back to games as a personality test.
So this is, I think, at the core of what games are.
So you've had this mask on and now you take the mask off.
And you're like, how did it feel to be that character?
Is that who I am?
You know, is that me?
Do I want to be more of that person?
And, you know, and then you see all these other masks,
and you're like, oh, I want to try that one next time.
And I think there's a lot of self-discovery, you know,
going on, because in the end, you're
answering the question of what would I do in that situation?
If I was on an island, you know, yes, I would, you know, I'd figure out fire and I'd make a hut or whatever.
And each of these is games or systems that let us answer these questions.
And the bigger thing is when I talk about all these unintended consequences that came out of things,
it's like I was shooting for emotions through these systems,
but then the real output of these was actually stories.
So when people tell me about Burgle Bros, they're like,
OK, this one time.
And then they go through the whole story of the sequence
events that happened, and what they did, and what the guards
did, and everything.
And it's their story.
It's the game reflected back on them and they were able to tell a story about who they were in that situation.
And so the bigger thing about what would I do in a situation is when you have an answer, you now have something that you're going to tell.
And more often, the failure is the better story.
Like, the spectacular failure is the one that people tell.
And so games as story generators, I think, is what we're getting at when we're saying emotion.
It's not just that you want them to,
you know, like a movie is gonna make you feel
a particular way, and a game can make you feel
a lot of different ways,
because it's through the lens of yourself.
And that's it.
Thank you for your time.
And.
Hey, big fan of Burgle Brothers, but one thing I was wondering about when you talk about the emotion and controlling that is there's so much randomness between the setup and the cars that players get.
How much effort did you spend in the design to not let things get too easy or too hard?
I had to, because it's basically a roguelike board game, right? There's all these variables.
Very early on I locked in the guard system and a lot of the tiles.
And I just played it a lot. It was almost a brute force. I mean sometimes you can Monte Carlo.
There's all ways you can simulate board games.
But I had to literally get a sense of
Even right after the Kickstarter, I was like,
okay, it's a little too easy,
and I just changed just a couple of card distributions,
and it ended up pretty good.
But it was a lot of work, just to get a sense of it.
But it was, I guess, work.
I can't say that there's a specific thing.
I mean, I try to make each individual obstacle
not insurmountable.
So like every event that comes up
or every tile that comes up,
you know, there is a way around it
or multiple ways around it.
But not just like you're hosed
because anything that feels super arbitrary
and you get stuck at that point
can throw off both your distribution
but also just throw off the experience.
So.
Thanks.
Hello. So this might be a little bit of a negative space question,
but you mentioned that you had given up on planning,
like the planning aspect. Yeah. Right.
And I worked on the stealth game in the past and we ran into similar issues like
planning's really hard,
but it really feels like that is a core part of most heists things. Yeah.
We gave up on as well. So I was wondering, uh, what,
what were the iterations that you tried if you tried more and if,
was there anything that remotely worked and,
If something did, why?
It was mostly conceptual.
So this is why, I mean, to repeat the question,
why not have the planning phase in the stealth?
It was just that we started to break out,
like, okay, what information could you have?
Would that information be useful?
How much of a plan could you make?
And we started, you know, so I had a friend
that we were kind of brainstorming this idea with,
and he's like, yeah, I had this idea for a planning game,
and I had my horrible...
hybrid game.
And we started brainstorming,
and then I started getting on this thread where I'm like,
oh, and then once I figured out how the guards moved
and whatnot, and then I did 15 pages before he came back,
he's like, I think you're just running with this idea.
And it just bore fruit, right?
It's just like sometimes in design,
like there is kind of the,
The system that seems to be clicking and working,
and there certainly is another game.
I'd love to make a prequel that's like,
it sets up a game of Burgl,
and there's other games to be made.
Thank you.
All right, thanks guys.
Yeah, I'm happy to talk individually.