the world. Welcome everyone to
Game Developers Conference.
2022 Great to be together.
Virtually This panel is build
your career in games like it's
an RPG. Um a lot of people
think about their careers in a
little bit weird.
We're going to talk today a bit about how to take the road less traveled and meander
onto new areas of the map and take a side quest or two.
So first, let's introduce the panelists.
So I'm Gordon Bellamy, full professor, USC Games
and CEO of Gay Gaming Professionals and in some direction.
Hey, Anne, who are you?
Hi, I'm Angie Bo.
I'm product head and creative director right now at Phoenix Labs Montreal.
I started in the industry around 20 years ago as a 3D animator,
and I went through lots of different careers and paths
to get to to being a creative director right now.
Welcome, Anne. How about you, Connie?
Yes, I'm Connie Griffith and I am content lead on State of Decay 3 over at Undead Labs.
And yeah, I've been in the industry, this is going on my 19th year and I got my start as a QA tester
on World of Warcraft the first time it launched. And I've...
done a lot of things, but I've ended up as a designer
focusing on storytelling experiences.
But in my as I'm sure we'll explore on the panel, I've been a producer.
I've been a game writer.
I've done business development.
And so I'm happy to be here and share my experiences with everyone.
Welcome, Connie. And hello, Brian.
Hey, thanks for having me.
Yeah, I'm Brian Corrigan.
I'm the head of Americas for Krafton PUBG.
Probably most people know better by PUBG.
I do a little bit of work with Convoy Ventures,
which is a venture capital company.
So investing and advising.
I got my career started out a long time ago
working on Guitar Hero 3 networking services,
actually as an engineer.
And kind of just like Anne said,
we've my way through a weird past to get where I am today.
and last and most special thanks to you, Jing, for bringing us together.
First and foremost, was going to be possible as a conversation.
But also, please introduce yourself.
Hey, I'm Jing.
Most recently, I was a general manager at Phoenix Labs
heading up their L.A. and Bay Area studios.
That was a very strategy and operations focused role.
But I actually got my start in games in.
branding and marketing first working with Nintendo and then at Riot Games.
And then during my time at Riot, I started to look for ways to expand
my skill set further and took an opportunity to join the merchandising team,
which was forming up at the time.
So through that experience got like.
a tour through everything from apparel development to web platform to global channel management,
e-commerce events, player support, all of that. And then after that, I went on an adventure with
a couple of engineering friends where we started an educational game startup. And then a little
ways down the road, Phoenix Labs acquired our studio and then I worked on special projects.
before taking on the GM role.
So I've gotten, I kind of gotten to experience a lot
of interesting stuff on the business
and product side of games.
And right now I'm focusing on some personal projects
that let me delve into the art, design
and engineering aspects of games and technology.
And I've loved having a multi-class career.
It's been such a continuous journey of learning and growing.
And I'm so excited to speak with all of you today.
Wow. I just as I think about it, wow, it's like over 100 years of experience,
all these max level characters. But that's not where this RPG began. Right. So just taking
your metaphor back a bit. We understand where you're at, but let's talk about how you began.
Let's let's visualize your character sheet as it were. Let's talk a little bit about that and
maybe go into like an origin story. So Connie, take us in. Where were you?
10 years ago, like where were you thinking about what you dream of?
Paint us all a picture.
Oh, wow. OK.
10 years ago, it's actually like the midpoint, so not quite an origin story.
But I would say baby Connie did not know what baby Connie wanted,
which I don't think is that unusual for a lot of folks.
That was the first time that I hit reset on my career.
I was having a bit of a quarter life crisis.
I'd previously done sort of like business development.
I was an executive assistant.
I was doing production.
I'd only worked for one studio at that time, which was Blizzard.
And I just came to this realization that even though I was working
for my dream company and, you know, people were telling me,
oh, you're doing a great job, you're awesome.
I realized I really, I really wasn't very happy.
In fact, I was very unhappy.
And that was a very hard thing for me
to sort of struggle with because
you know, when you're successful
and you're climbing your career ladder
and you're going, no, no, this is where I belong.
And I think I originally just had a hard time
where I never even saw myself in games.
I loved video games.
I just didn't know I wasn't a programmer.
I wasn't an artist, right?
I was like, what exactly could I do?
And so that's kind of why I fell into sort of production.
I was like, oh, that I can do.
I'm good with people, right?
People like me, I can do this job.
I can contribute.
But I think that was the source of my unhappiness, which I
didn't sort of internalize until later, was that I actually was
creative that I actually wanted to
go and make games of my own.
I didn't want to just run meetings and take notes
and help people organize their work and schedule stuff.
I still, it's funny because I've gone full circle
where I do a lot of the facilitation work
that I did 10 years ago, but it's different, right?
And I think 10 years ago is when I.
basically decided to leave Blizzard.
I'd been there for eight years and I started over as a game writer.
And that that's kind of my origin story on my path
to pursuing being on the other side of the fence for game development.
That's fantastic.
I think along this path, we've all found that moment
of where it's time to start being the game industry versus
exploring the opportunity that was given to us.
Maybe, Jing.
Can you talk about a point when you knew you wanted to make a major change?
Those are born out of you, not just the opportunities provided to you.
Yeah, absolutely.
So about seven, eight years into.
So I started off in marketing and branding, right?
And so I kind of had experienced a lot in that realm.
And I had been about seven or eight years into my career there.
And I remember having a conversation with one of my mentors at the time.
And he asked me the typical question of,
hey, where do you see yourself in five, 10 years?
Like, what do you see yourself doing?
And I realized at that moment, a couple of things.
One, that I didn't see myself.
continuing to do marketing and branding as kind of my day-to-day, everyday focus.
And the second was that I couldn't exactly put words to an exact title or role. Instead,
I just, as I thought about it,
All I really wanted was to make sure that whatever was ahead of me in the future, I felt like I had
a high degree of confidence that I would be an asset to my team, that I'd be able to tackle
any kind of problem, learn anything, learn any role that I wanted to learn. And
this desire to be endlessly useful.
And I wanted to be this kind of Swiss army knife
of different skills and be of course,
very proud of the things that I've worked on
and proud of the effect that I have on the team around me.
And so the moment that I realized
that I just didn't have like a,
particular thing or role in mind and instead wanted to build this multifaceted skill set,
it really opened up the way I thought about what do I want to do next and it became less like I
felt myself getting off of like the the career ladder and instead looking across the different
kind of branches of skill trees that I could be developing in and looking at where do I want to
double down on existing strengths.
where do I want to shore up weaknesses?
And, you know, kind of pointing back
to what Connie was saying,
like there were also some strength areas
that just because I was good at those things
didn't mean that I needed to continue to do that job
if it was not going to be a thing
that was going to be fulfilling for me in the longterm.
And so, yeah, I think that moment
and that deep introspection about seven, eight years
into my career was what set everything else into motion.
That's so interesting.
I play a lot of Age of Empires,
so I think a lot about pathfinding,
but also what you brought up, which is skill tree, right?
Skill tree is to do like wondrous moments in your career
and the steps you take when you have choices to do so.
Let's bring you into the conversation, Brian.
Like, did you always know that you wanted to run a studio?
Or where did you make compromises?
to get there, like in your skill tree and your in your pathfinding or in your skill tree to get to run a studio.
Yeah, I love that idea you're talking about with skill trees, because, you know, I feel like like you kind of always have to know your character sheet at any time.
And I think like sometimes people are not honest about about that.
You know, you kind of have this idea of who you are, but only you can't always get it by looking in the mirror.
Right. You have to have friends who you can talk to and who.
you can kind of be honest about to tell you maybe what you're good at and what you're missing.
And for me, it was always about the entrepreneurship side.
I always knew I wanted to.
I'd be an entrepreneur. My dad was an entrepreneur. My grandfather was an entrepreneur. I just
had it in me as a kid. And I went to school for computer engineering, got out of school
and got a job at a casino company. I don't know anything about gambling. Don't like gambling.
Don't know anything about it at all.
But I knew eventually, at some point in my life, I kind of wanted to run my own company.
So I was looking at my skill sheet and saying, what could I bring?
Maybe I'm a half-decent programmer.
First thing is learn to be a manager or leader.
So I spent some time with that and I knew that was a deficit for me.
So early on, that's what I tried to learn a little bit and find good people to look
up to.
And as you get older, you just kind of find like, well, these things that you're spending
your time thinking about, all of a sudden, are these things that you kind of end up doing.
Um, and I think like, you know, eventually it kind of got to be that point where it was like,
well, if I'm going to do this, there's no better time. You know, we were thinking about having
kids and, and that sort of thing. Um, and you know, so the folks on the call know, but, uh,
I live in upstate New York, which is not exactly known to be like the Mecca of,
of game development that like, you know, LA or Seattle or.
Austin or Montreal for sure with Anne. For sure, Montreal, right?
So, for me, it was like, well, if I want to get into the industry
and I want to kind of be an entrepreneur,
you know, the idea of like going out and starting your own game studio and making games, it
just really wouldn't happen.
I mean, the funding wasn't there.
I didn't have the experience.
So I tried to leverage the skill that I thought I had, which was, you know, this, you know,
knowledge of like backend and kind of big data systems like cloud.
This was brand new.
And so I kind of started a contract studio around bringing games kind of like into the
cloud and online.
This was the same time that the Xbox was kind of like just coming online.
And I was lucky enough to have one of the first games I worked on be Guitar Hero with a local
studio, the only local studio here called Vicarious Visions. They're amazing. And I don't
know why they trusted us. They shouldn't, but we worked really hard and I think we did a good job.
And yeah, kind of leveraged that later into a few more steps. But eventually I did get to where I
wanted, which was to run my own studio. So I kind of always had the dream of being an entrepreneur,
but it's just a little...
It's tough to sometimes see that far ahead, knowing how much you have to do.
But, you know, I did my best that I did make it so.
Well, that's so cool.
I mean, so, Brian, you just spoke very powerfully to like the
your internal sense, your internal truth, right, would prove it for it,
but also listening to the world around you
to recognize what might be special in relationship to others.
Let's bring and into the conversation and I've known you for a lifetime.
I do a number through a number of roles and evolutions.
However, there is a truth or dare I say it, transformer spark inside of you.
When did you like discover, you know, the truth, like that
you were going to be in games and this is what you want to bring to the table?
Will that be sort of in your heart, like just in your bones like Brian spoke up?
or in your relationship with others, like your spark that would be true
no matter what the role is going forward.
I like humans.
I always like human interactions and building something together
as a team is always the most important thing.
whatever the role, whatever the position, whatever the project is,
the people you work with at the end, that is important.
So the path I had, I worked for like over 11 years at Ubisoft Montreal,
which is a very big studio.
There's always at least 17 projects going on at the same time.
So the opportunities of doing whatever is there,
if you have certain skills, of course, I couldn't.
claim myself being I want to be a programmer tomorrow.
So I don't have those skills.
But in terms of management and, you know, like video game
development for me is a second career.
I went back to school at 30.
So it gives you my age. I'm over 50 now.
It's a second career.
So before that, I manage people.
I discovered a lot of things.
I worked in music stores and I worked in.
in survey on the phone and I did tons of crappy jobs before this. So for me,
game dev, whatever the role, it's like, wow, okay, I'm ready to go to Mars or wherever you're
going to send me. I'm just happy to be there surrounded by wonderful people working on games,
you know? So for me at the start being a 3D animator, it was the craft itself that I really,
really enjoyed. I really love the craft of animating in 3D.
But very rapidly, like the second project, people at Ubisoft Montreal said,
you know what, we think you're ready to be a manager about a team of animation.
I said, OK, I'm going to try it out.
So I kind of stopped animating after only like two years.
It's this little like sad thing about dropping the animation.
But I discovered so many much.
more things. And I did discover along the way that, OK, people are important.
Like this is key. It's still true today.
But what do I bring over being able to work with people and being good to work with people?
What can I bring to the to the table right now?
And I want to work on product and I want to I want to invest myself in doing amazing games.
So like I said, the question you asked, Eugene, like what made a change like ten years ago?
For me, 10 years ago, it's when I took the decision.
I actually stopped working in the games industry for about six months.
I wanted to write a novel, a sci-fi novel, and I just stopped working for six months.
I created this universe, the context, the characters about that novel and started
talking about it to some friends that most of them are working in a game industry.
So they were telling me, ah, forget about the novel.
Just do a game about it.
We're in.
If you start your own company, I'm in.
And it's like this.
A year after that, we started our own studio.
And from there, it's I'm way more into gaming than I was like 10 years ago.
Wow, that's the spark if you're not getting it,
you're getting it now, the spark, right?
I ask great questions.
I wanna bring it back to you, Connie,
you sort of take us down this path as RPG.
I want people to have specificity, right?
So I want to take us to the moment, okay?
Like what for you was the critical point, okay?
When you really were what you wanted changed,
like...
take us into detail. We know that it moves, but what was the moment when you're like,
this is the change, it's happening going forward? Oh man. Okay. So,
There is so much in that question, and I'm going to try hard not to like
tear up on camera because this is a deeply emotional question for me.
I think it's for everyone, because we all know being in games is very hard, right?
This industry is not always kind to everyone. And
I mean, OK, so first and foremost, I have.
I got into this industry because of the people and I stayed here because of the people and I continue to be here because.
I just love the people in games, I love the people I work with, I love the people that I get to meet,
and it's just when you when you meet other folks that love to play and make games,
there's just this instant connection about problem solving and creativity and so that is a huge.
spark for me. I've actually tried to leave games at least twice, and it's not been entirely
successful, but this is sort of a personal story where, so I lost my first husband to cancer,
and at one point when he was still fighting his cancer, we were
We had to fly to Germany to get treatment.
It was a procedure that's not approved here in the United States.
It's like laser resection.
There's one hospital in rural Germany, right,
where they do this.
And we're sitting there.
It's a tiny hospital in the middle of like these woods.
And there was a teenage boy from Finland sitting next to us.
And my husband, who is an artist, he was an artist at Blizzard.
And so he was just sketching different things.
And this kid looks over and both him and his parents, you know, their English was
was was OK, right?
And they just go over.
And this kid, his eyes just light up. Right.
And him, my husband had the same rare cancer.
They bonded. My husband drew things for him.
And I think.
That was the moment when I was like, we do more than make games.
Absolutely.
We we we sorry we connect people.
We give.
We give people a shared.
Thing to love.
Right. Yeah, well, that's
well, wow.
Thank you for trusting and sharing with us Connie.
That was beautiful.
And meaningful. Thank you.
I want to, I want to also return to what and what you were saying, because you were sort of alluding to a moment for you it felt like when your community rallied around you and said, and we are down, you know, to work with you, but that sort of propelled
you forward into the next phase of your career. So maybe.
Talk about.
that group, your party, right? That group that you were running those dungeons with who were like,
who showed up, right, as they could to be with you. Yeah, talk about that experience
when they came together and then you turn that into professional action.
Actually, I think that the people I talked to about this project kind of had a similar path and a similar delusion, maybe, about the industry and working in a big, big, huge,
structure to make games, like when you're like 500, like my artistic director, it's not mine,
but the artistic director at Epsilon Games, Nancy, was a great character modeler. She was
a lead character modeler at that time at Ubisoft, but she was working mainly on Excel sheets.
managing the team, making the 3D models.
And after a few years, it was that kind of decision
that everybody had to make, like I'm good at what I'm doing at the craft.
And now I'm becoming only a manager.
Is that really what I want to do?
Some people, yes, and it's OK to be a manager.
I was a manager for.
15 years in the games industry.
So it's totally OK. It's not a judgment, but it's just
it's just a personal decision at one point saying like, OK, I started
as a craft woman or a craft man.
And now what do I do? Do I manage people? Do I?
become a better HR person because a manager involves a lot managing people, not only tasks
and projects. So it's a question of, you know, of decision and where you want to go. And
do I still want to continue on that path for like the next 10 years, 15 years, 20 years?
So the people I was talking to were like all over 35 and were in the industry for about 15 years.
And
The idea of let's make a game together.
We're going to be maximum 10 because we don't have any resources.
So we're going to be poor.
Are you OK about being poor for the next like three years
and make the game that we want to make and have fun at least?
And they gave it a shot.
And I'm I'm I'm so humbled about that because it was a bumpy road.
It was not all, you know, like very happy people every day.
That's for sure.
The stress level of having to pay for your mortgage and everything
and not money coming in and, you know, all those things.
It's kind of the stress was intense, but I would never.
go back and not redo it. I would redo it like in a heartbeat because this experience actually
today if I'm in this position at Phoenix Lab it's because I did that and I do understand
what it is to start a studio and to have people and to inspire people.
and going on board and it's going to work and we're going to do it together and we're doing it together.
So for me, this experience is like it's key.
And and I'm again, I'm really I'm really touched that my associates and the employees that we had all decided to jump at the same time.
We were in the same position, actually in the same mind space and.
They all said, and now nobody is working like as a freelancer or they own the studio.
We're all back in bigger structure.
What we learned in those years that we went together, it's enormous and nobody regrets.
And we were all in the same headspace at that time saying like, let's try it.
We won't try it when we're like 65, 35, 40. It's the, let's do it right now.
And just the last thing, I give classes to a university in Montreal,
Design and Animation University. And I tell the students, it's like,
If ever you're feeling a little entrepreneur and you really want to start a game,
if you live at your parents' house, now is the time.
You don't have kids. You don't have anything to pay.
Do it. Do it now.
Take two, three years. Do the game you want to do.
It's the good timing.
Wow. And I'm just going to invite you now
because we have a new fine arts program games at USC
and you are my first invitee.
But that's not what we're talking about today.
I want to, you were born into this cauldron of development,
this hub in Montreal,
thousands of people making games together.
Brian, you were in the heartland of America, okay?
In upstate New York, probably, you know,
not a stone's throw from your next developer.
How did you find your guild, right?
In a very, very different setting.
than where I am.
Yeah, it was really tough.
You know, and especially early,
it's not like, you know,
we're all playing.
You know, multiplayer games together.
I mean, I guess we were
actually to some degree
just just older games.
But, you know, it's like.
I always kind of picture that like little scene from Zelda where it says it's dangerous to go it alone.
Like you have to have this team.
And I think for me, anyway, like slowly kind of over the years, you know, you meet like minded people.
And, you know, these days, you know.
I play games with a lot of people online that I've just been friends with over the years.
And, you know, I think I think we kind of have this like built in advantage
because we make things that we love and we love them forever.
I mean, you know, something you work on, it's your art.
And, you know, you kind of want to play it forever.
So, you know, Jing and I were talking the other day and I was saying that,
you know, I still play games with some of the folks that I used to work with
at Riot when when her and I first met,
because League of Legends is an amazing game and I absolutely love it.
And we had a lot of fun and it's just like a great way to stay connected.
But I think, yeah, you do kind of collect, you know, these folks over the years.
And this is another great thing about the gaming industry is once
once you kind of like claw your way in a little bit, which I understand
sometimes people think it's a little bit hard to kind of claw your way in.
But once you're in, it's actually really welcoming.
I would say like it's just in general to me anyway.
It's always been a really supporting community.
So.
Even those folks that I met all those years ago, 2005, 2006 or whatever it was, like Guitar
Hero, I still talk with a lot of them.
Like you said, the area is small.
I actually still work with a few of them.
It's been that all these years.
Earlier, you were asking about kind of like route planning and like how people figure out where they want to go.
So like I'm the guy when I play an open world game,
who gets just completely distracted running through the woods, you know, like,
like I'll never get there because I just I love just going off and exploring.
But I think like what makes that fun is, you know, when you're doing it with
with other people, right, it's really fun.
And all those little things just become,
you know, fun moments that you're kind of like hanging out together.
But more specifically, I think, just to give people some good specific action items or whatever on this one,
there are a lot of gaming slacks, gaming discords of game developers and people in the game industry.
And there's a bunch I kind of have joined and left a bunch over the years.
But there's a couple that I'm in right now that are sort of people that are.
you know, in similar and really different types of jobs around the industry and around
the world.
And that's been really great.
You know, just being in there, listening to what people are kind of thinking about and
working on and, you know, watching people talk about news.
I think you just get more from like a Discord or Slack than you really do on Twitter because
you don't have that, you know, built-in like megaphone effect that you get on Twitter where
everyone's just kind of shouting.
So...
you know, like specifically, you know, some of the, the discords and slacks, I mean, have
been, you know, absolutely incredible. And when I meet people, you know, I just met Connie
for the first time last week, but asked her the same thing, you know, what, where, where
do you hang out when you're online and you're locked in your house, you're in your work
Slack, you know, do you, do you have anything else? And so we were sort of trading links
for stuff like that. But I definitely would recommend that everybody, you know, find something,
whether it's the IGDA, you know, local IGDA group.
or colleges have groups. Somehow I sneak secretly snuck into the Stanford games mailing list. I
didn't go to Stanford, just to be clear. Somehow I snuck on it. So if anyone's watching, please
don't kick me off. But there's things like that I think that are really good and definitely
recommend everybody find a couple of these things and just kind of join up and try to
contribute a little bit. Awesome. It's funny. You remind me of Elder Scrolls.
I remember turning it on and just running off into the woods.
I didn't know there was a whole game.
I just heard you got to play on this world.
And I just ran off in the woods and never began the original quest for like
two days because I didn't know maybe I was still in that game.
I was like, what are you sure that game was the worst?
But I digress before I think it's too far down a side, but to my own.
I mean, we're here on this quest because of Jake.
Jake, you brought us together, right?
You assembled us at this this moment.
you know, in your career, could you maybe just frame how you view
networking, trust building, paint as a picture?
Yeah, absolutely.
Actually, I kind of have a little bit of an allergic reaction to the word
networking, because I think that there are so many
more unsavory connotations
because there's something transactional about the concept of networking.
But I do think a lot about.
building relationships, building really authentic connections with folks and how important that
is both in our industry as a whole, because the games industry is very connected. It can
be very welcoming, very supportive. But also, especially if you're building a
an atypical career, one that doesn't look kind of like others that have already been established,
having a strong support group of your guild, like you put it earlier, Gordon, like having your guilds
and having those relationships be ones that you have.
you know, contributed to grown, cultivated, like really, really grown over the years
helps be able helps you be able to actually navigate through
having a more of a multi-class career, because so much of of being able to move
from one role to the other, at least from my experience, has been working
from this already established trust with folks.
So in the last, you know, whether it was shifting.
entire disciplines and teams in my time at Riot,
or starting my startup, or ending up at Phoenix Labs,
or even the things I was doing within Phoenix Labs,
a lot of those would have been infinitely harder,
or not even possible in the first place,
if I didn't already have established trust
with some of the key folks along the way.
And so, I'll give you the example of,
with my co-founders, my two co-founders for Bot School,
the three of us had not actually worked directly together
with one another until we started our entrepreneurial journey
but we had had years of friendship that had built up
through a combination of just kind of being there
for each other.
our CEO at the time, Chris Cobb, he was one of the engineering leads on a team in League
of Legends. And I've worked with his team a couple of times to help them be able to better
tell the story of what Riot and League was trying to do around player behavior.
And through that, we just kind of kept in touch and were a sounding board for one another. And
because of that relationship that had built up over the course of years,
when time came to want to go on a founding journey, there was already like, we'd had all those years
of established relationships to be able to go back to and understanding how we worked and how
we could be helping with each other on this journey. And then when I looked at, you know,
putting together this panel, in recent years, I've had, you know, I do some mentorship and
I talk with both folks that are in the games industry and outside of it.
And I've had a lot of folks, you know, reach out when they see kind of the weird career
that I've had and want to know more about what it takes to multi-class.
And the question had come up enough times in the last few years that when time came
around for GDC this year.
I thought, hey, maybe it'd be good to do a talk around this.
In bringing together the panel,
I looked at the really interesting multifaceted folks
that I had encountered in my time in games,
which is all of you,
and thought about who else have I encountered along the way
that I think would have a really interesting perspective,
who've had these really...
fascinating journeys and have navigated their way through so many different kinds of circumstances,
teams, and work on a variety of different types of games, teams, companies. And, you know, I
was really happy that we were able to bring everyone together. So.
Yeah, I think, I think, you know, like Brian was saying earlier, like when you,
when you spend time with folks, um, as you encounter them, having those moments
of really authentic connection and continuing to like, take that seed and
cultivate it by, uh, just kind of caring about what other folks are working
on, wanting to support each other.
I think when you have that kind of two way relationship that happens again,
authentically, you know, over the course of.
weeks and months and years, it just,
it makes everything so much brighter and better.
No, for sure.
Thank you for putting a framework to this.
And as I sort of think about what you were saying
about authenticity, I think about Anne assembling
like these warriors of development in Montreal
and Brian talking about the magic of play together.
I think about you, Connie.
Tell you why.
because you're like a paladin, okay?
Because you bring together both the magic
of rich game experiences,
but also you're deep in the Seattle community,
this community of all these students
where everyone's working and spinning off of like,
you know, Microsoft Bungie and all these studios,
but you have to do it all.
And especially now in these times, right?
Where we've been displaced a little bit, right?
You have to maybe lean a little more into the magic
sometimes than into the physical proximity
and things we share as student experience.
Could you maybe talk about that, Connie, like the life of a paladin?
Yeah, I'm happy to.
So, you know, I actually moved to Seattle in late 2015, 2016,
and I actually didn't really know anybody up here.
I'd come. This is my first attempt to leave games.
I had gone to work for like a publisher, some startup,
and it ended the way most, you know, startups end.
But to really build on what Jing was saying is I really think that.
You know, if you're like baby Connie and don't really know what you want to do,
and you just know that you love games, you want to be part of that magic, right?
And you're not quite sure what to do.
I think the most important thing is to.
You know, build authentic relationships, be sincere, right?
You you you get to enjoy the flowers in the garden that you grow
and how your garden grows is what do you nurture, right?
And I think I went from really not knowing anyone other than
like one or two like personal friends up here in Seattle to
having a really wonderful network of like professional
friends. We're also now personal friends, right? And I think
being willing to ask for help, being willing to put yourself
out there. In Seattle, I can't tell you how many people that I
just ended up becoming good friends with. I was like,
Hey, right, do you wanna grab coffee sometime?
Or, hey, I would really like to chat with you sometime
about some work thing, right?
I'm just curious about your thoughts, right?
And I think that's hard there.
Seattle has a bad rep, the Seattle freeze
where people are like cold and talk a lot
about wanting to hang out
but no one ever actually shows up, right?
But even though that's a little bit true, sorry, Seattle,
I also think that
If you really want to put yourself out there,
you need to also be willing to just be resilient, right?
I can't tell you how many number of times, right?
Like the connections that I built, where did they start?
They just started for me asking someone that.
And not everybody said yes,
not everybody was friendly and welcoming, right?
A lot of times, in fact, I would say the majority of time,
it's not personal.
People are busy, people have things that are going on,
right, it's not the right time for you two to connect.
But.
I think having intentionality, having sincerity, wanting to build those authentic relationships
and reach out and not being too hard on other people or yourself if somebody says no or
is not there or is not interested in talking, it opens up so many opportunities to learn.
to make new friends.
And I really view it's a side benefit where it's like,
oh, and also we happen to be in the same industry.
And now I have people I can call
if I have questions about things,
or as is often the case,
especially once you get to the leadership level, right?
Having people you can turn to and just go,
look, I have a really challenging problem
and I don't know what the right way forward is.
And I don't even know that there is a right answer,
but I would appreciate
what people's thoughts are and that's vulnerability.
That's opening yourself up, right?
That's talking about your mistakes.
It's talking about that saying, I don't know.
I'm in charge and I should know and I don't know.
And, um.
You know, it's been true both for rebuilding, right?
My professional network in Seattle, and I think it's true throughout my career,
which is, you know, come up and just ask the worst things.
The worst thing that someone can say is no.
So I think so in our careers, there have been at least, I'd say a third revolution.
So for me, the first revolution was online play.
OK, the ability to play from my home and connect with friends, colleagues,
so on and so forth from my computer.
The second one was mobile play.
And by that, I meant that play could be with me 24 seven.
wherever I was, I could be farming or doing or playing, connecting, chatting,
so on and so forth.
I'd offer that we're in the midst of a third revolution.
OK, and that third revolution is around video streaming.
And by that, I mean that personally, professionally
and both commerce and interaction, video streaming is something now
that everyone. Has been a part of, and so.
I want to talk to you, Jing.
I want to talk to you, Brian,
because you just two different perspectives.
Jing, I want to talk about like how in this age of remote,
like what sort of new strategies have been helpful to you
to thinking about navigating professionally.
And then Brian, while I queue you up here,
I want to talk about it as a profession, like in this craft,
like how has it changed your ability to be a part of games
that video streaming has become a thing?
So let me start with you, Jing.
So I think the remote world that we've been in for the last couple of years has come with a lot of interesting trade-offs.
I think in general, we think about continuing to forge connections and building those authentic relationships and like building that sense of community.
in some facets has gotten harder because, you know, you're not able to spend in-person time,
you get kind of like less ambient connection and magic that happens between people,
but at the same time, it closes the distance between folks. So, you know, Anne and I are on,
you know, opposite sides of the continent from one another, but she and I got to, I think,
have a conversation her first couple of weeks that she was at Phoenix Labs at a time that
worked for both of us. And it was something where we got to talk to one another about
our respective journeys. And I got to know her and became friends with her. And that
was a thing that would have been much harder in a time.
before it became so commonplace to be able to have these video calls.
I think the other thing that's been really interesting is that with video conferencing,
you get to work together with people and pair with other folks
and learn from other folks in a way that just is so much more
so much more deep, you can get more slices of people's actual day-to-day lives as a result.
But going back to what I was saying earlier around the trade-offs, the investment that
an individual has to make in being able to forge those connections goes up higher
because you can't take for granted that you can just run into someone and you can
see them in the office with you, that you can swing by someone's desk.
You know, I used to do this a lot with some of the engineers that I would work with where,
you know, we just get those like 15 minutes of time when we look at a thing together because
I happen to be next to their desk or walking by an artist's desk and seeing the stuff that
they've got posted up on the wall around them and to be able to have those like
five minutes, 10 minutes of exchanges,
those have to be a lot more deliberate now
in our current world than they were a few years prior.
So I think if you want to forge those relationships,
if you want to cultivate them,
you have to put in a lot more.
direct personal effort and proactiveness toward it.
I think the other thing too is,
in the last couple of years,
I think it's been really important to think about
what kinds of communication is the best suited for
the other folks that you're trying to build a relationship with because not everyone like
some folks take two video calls swimmingly. They're fine being on calls all day long,
not a problem. And others it's torture to be on a call for even just like 30 minutes to an hour,
right? Some folks are really strong when it comes to real-time
written communication and others really need things to be written in longer form
with more time to digest, more time to think about their response.
And so I think I think it's really sharpened the need for folks
to invest in their communication skills, as well as their communication empathy.
Wow. It's a lot of food for thought there.
You know, by video, we're all experiencing this content right now.
Brian, I mean, video streaming became part of your professional life.
Talk about that.
Talk about taking a brief journey into this world
where we're actually all natively residing right now.
Yeah, it's funny.
we were talking earlier about like character sheets and sort of like where you want to end up.
And I mentioned, I had always just dreamed of being an entrepreneur.
But again, Albany, New York, right? It's not Silicon Valley. It's not Seattle.
It's not LA. You guys grew up with this and understanding things like...
You're seeing this all the time. For us, it was like starting a business was the tire shop right
up the road or somebody going out and being an accountant. So I knew I wanted to understand this.
And...
And I had been growing my network a little bit. And like Chang said, I also hate the
word networking. I met a buddy at a Game Jam hackathon and we just hit it off.
And it turned out he was doing some kind of investing and he was just complaining that
nobody understands game investing and all this kind of stuff. And so we started talking about it.
And I said, well, if I'm going to be honest, dude, I don't actually understand this investing thing
at all.
none, I don't get it. I don't understand any of the words you're saying. I'm faking it
because I just, you know, I don't want to look like I'm dumb." And, you know, he said,
oh, well, you know, let me teach you. So, probably one of my best friends still to this
day. But anyway, so yeah, I had this opportunity probably 2015 when kind of like the streaming
services were coming out 2014, you know, the Netflix and the prime video that, um,
We had put this tool set together for games, and we had sold this like back end stuff to games,
where you'd sort of like spin your game up on our software. And we said, well, shoot, like,
you could kind of like spin a whole video platform up on this software. Let's go see
if we can raise some money for this. So I think of this as like my side quests, you know,
do I like video streaming? I mean,
Not that much. I like video games. But I wanted to get this on my character sheet. I knew I wanted
to get this. And so we spent a year pitching venture capital companies and being told no
a thousand times. And again, you got to understand, I didn't understand any of this.
I remember pitching one of the really big VCs now, like Andreessen Orowitz and them just being
Who is this guy?
Like, you know, he doesn't get the slightest what's going on.
You know, and it's sort of like funny to look back at, but this is how careers are.
You know, everybody looks back at how naive they were.
Nobody's bored knowing anything.
You have to just learn it and be humble and ask, just like Connie said.
So so I always think of this as my side quest because I did spend
a couple of years doing this.
The company was not successful, but, you know, in this weird path of life
and like getting lost in the woods and coming back.
You know, that friend that I made, we're still, you know, best friends, basically to these days.
He took some of that.
He was able to get kind of a company off the ground.
Was it one of these like, you know, venture backed startups? No.
But he had a company and he's been successful and he's still open
and he's doing a great job and his company's grown to 40 people.
And he took all that work we did seven years ago into that.
And for myself, I had a chance to meet all these VCs.
And honestly, back then, there really was nobody investing in gaming.
But along the way, a couple of them said, oh, this guy doesn't know anything
about VC, but knows a lot about games.
And so I got asked to be a venture partner with Convoy Ventures,
which I work at now.
And that's how I met all these folks is by.
you know, probably embarrassing myself a couple of times.
So I always think of this as my side quest, but it's like any side quest,
you know, you sort of complete it and you go back to the main quest.
And that's kind of like where, you know, I kind of ended up.
But, you know, out of that, you know, my character sheet at this point
has a lot of experience on this.
And, you know, I've vetted 100 companies and I know how these deals work now.
And, you know, I've had a chance to see this more than a lot of people have.
And and but that's how I picked it up.
That's so cool.
I mean, something that that.
all of you share now is that you have the vantage point of career, not just job or role.
And now you have some more perspective on how important it was to take the shots when you took them,
but also of how many shots you may have to take.
Right. And and perhaps for everyone at home who may be like, OK, I came to this talk.
Right.
I don't know if I want to take my next shot now,
or in 10 years, if I want to get promoted,
or I want to herd the troops right now.
I'll go to you, Jing, first.
Okay?
I mean, you were on a pretty well-defined career path.
Riot games, okay?
Externalities aside,
why did you decide to risk that stable job
and take your shot, right, with bot school.
Oh, man. I've done that actually a couple times. I did it earlier
this year when I when I decided to say goodbye for now from
Phoenix Labs and spend time on my personal projects. But yeah,
like the the experience with with Riot.
It was because I had a clear understanding that I wanted to do broader skill acquisition
and that there was a pocket of skills that I knew I could only experience if I started my own company.
I could read all I wanted about, you know, fundraising with VCs and setting up a business.
And I got to do a little bit of a proxy of the starting a business component with the Riot
merch team because it was like a, it was a separate business unit within Riot Games and
learned a lot of that, but that, that was, you know, I equated that experience so that.
skydiving with a tandem instructor strapped to your back.
And I just wanted to jump out of the plane one time at least by myself.
So I would know what it would feel like to, you know, handle that adrenaline
to have to pull the cords.
I don't know. I only know this much about skydiving.
I've only ever been actually tandem skydiving one time.
So this this analogy is going to fade away really quickly.
But essentially, I knew I wanted to do it at least once.
so that I would be able to learn all of those things and really experience them.
Because knowing that, you know, I would look at what I would regret
if I didn't do it versus what I would regret if I did do it.
And if
I did do it. The thing I might regret is a loss of financial security for a chunk of time.
My pride in not being able to build a company. But the amount that both those things were things that
I could overcome. And I knew that I would learn so much that you just can't get out of a textbook
that you can't get by going to school by just going through and experiencing it.
Um, and
Whereas if I flipped it around and I thought about,
well, what I regret if I stayed?
It's like, I just, I would give up a chance
to really learn and flesh out this entire portion
of this entire branch of my skill tree
that I can't, I wouldn't be able to earn in some other way
by staying at the company.
And I also, you know, like Anne was saying earlier,
there is, there are some things that are easier
to be able to do at certain.
points in your life. And it's in my life circumstance at that
time was I did not have to think about a mortgage and I did not
have to think about kids. And so I could have I had a higher
appetite for taking on some of the financial risks. And I also
just said to myself, I thought of it as like, as if I were
doing a self study MBA.
Like that was the equivalent, right? I'm going to go learn some of this stuff.
And when I have looked at any of these kinds of decisions, one of the frameworks I typically use
is like, I really list out all the different things that I care about from a value standpoint
and the things that I'm feeling.
you know, fearful about or excited about as I'm looking at the opportunity. And then I try to
prioritize between what are these things in terms of priority and importance to me? And if I stay
versus if I go, how would I actually, you know,
rate how true or how present or, you know,
what would I score each of these different options?
And then that doesn't necessarily give me a final answer,
but it prompts a lot of good introspection
and internal conversation.
And I came up the other end of that exercise, like, you know,
and just thought, you know,
I have so much more to lose if I don't try this right now
than if I do.
Yeah, that's how I got there.
What I love about what all of you talk about,
that all of you are acting on the world.
You're all having a plan, you're assessing,
developing skills, taking side quests,
but all of you talking about your agency.
So I wanna ask you now, like, I'll go to you first, Anne.
Are you where you wanna be?
right now and if yes or if no, like what is the planning you're doing now? What are the
skills you're developing now for your next phase?
Currently, I'm not even looking at the next phase because I'm really happy where I'm at.
It's it's really I I I'm really happy.
It's every day I wake up and I'm happy to work with the team I'm working with within the company I'm working in.
And it's it's I'm just grateful.
So right now, it's just I want to do the best.
And one thing that Connie, I think you're the first one that mentioned it, that how much.
We have to show us as vulnerable because this is what we are, everybody as humans.
And I'm sure it's the same for for you guys also.
But at every changes, it's it's really scary.
It's a leap of faith.
And it's it's only you when sometimes the faith you have in yourself
is not at the highest point, you know, so it's it's really uncomfortable.
But.
I would just suggest to everybody, just do it because all the things that you learn
and the things that you have as a baggage, as a background, is not going to go away.
Like when I moved to my first associate producer in narrative for Far Cry 3,
I was an animation trade director at UB Stuff in the HR department,
which was far away from the associate producer for narratives.
But then I did a study about the the state of animation and cinematics and scripted event at Ubisoft Montreal.
And I became after the presentation kind of a specialist about narrative at Ubisoft.
And I was like, no, I'm not.
It's like, yeah, I know.
I was not in production doing narratives or cinematics and whatnot.
It's like, yeah, but you have that perspective now that nobody has.
So there you go and do the job and help us ship Far Cry 3.
And it's like, OK.
And it was scary, but I've learned so much in that process.
And we all learn so much in that process doing this thing.
So it's always it's really different than somebody that is becoming an expert.
So the knowledge is just accumulating in one or multiple areas, but it's really bland and it's really bold.
When you change course, it's like, oh, I'm I'm kind of losing something.
No, you're gaining.
It's just not in the same area, just widening.
And we have to to see this to to be able to to make that step, actually,
because like I said, it's a scary thing.
It's like starting a new job very often.
It's a new adventure.
So it's a lot of things that you don't know.
And you have to ask all the time to everybody.
I don't know. I'm new to that. Can you help me?
Yes. All right. Everybody is there to help.
Well, speaking of right, the people in this crowd
who are watching this talk,
they're finding their own paths
and they're going to want to hopefully
continue to connect with us, right, because all of us agree,
you know, that we're here to help and to lift each other up
and lift up our craft.
And I actually want to start with you, Anne, because we're right.
Because.
Now we know where you are and people want to vibe like you're vibing.
How do people stay in touch with you?
And you both my Twitter keys
and you both you can join me on
a mile on the Discord channel.
Aside from the job, I have my personal server,
but I think that Twitter would be the best way to to to link with me.
Perfect.
Connie, I'll ask you the same thing.
Same thing for all the mad smack talk
we've said about Twitter, right?
I love it, right?
Like I don't use it that much.
Well, okay, I'm casually active.
So absolutely, I believe that our Twitter handles
are in our bios, our speaker bios.
So please feel free to reach out.
I'm always happy to answer questions
and chat with folks and share my dog pics.
Amazing.
Brian, same question.
Yeah, I said, I don't like Twitter,
but probably the same thing.
Also, like I'm on LinkedIn a lot,
even though I think nobody sort of loves LinkedIn,
but you sort of have to be there.
You definitely have to be there.
So I'm there too.
I'm working on building.
I bought a firehouse and I'm working on building a training center here
for people who want to get into games so that future
Bryans of the world don't have the same trouble networking as anyone else.
So if you want to move to the great Mecca of upstate New York,
come hang out with me and the training center when it's done in like six
or eight months.
And you, too, can be sitting in negative 15 degree weather
on an afternoon on a Tuesday.
So, yeah, we actually also have a gaming firehouse in L.A., but I digress.
Nice.
who brought us together.
How can people keep this going?
They're like, I wanna be on this chain.
How do they connect?
Yeah, hit me up on Twitter.
I'm also on LinkedIn as well.
I'm on Twitter infrequently,
but I'm always open to chatting with folks
who are interested in learning more about the industry
or navigating their careers in it.
I'm on Twitter too.
Thank you for joining us for our panel.
Yeah.
You