Hello, I'm Nick and I made a game called Move or Die.
It's a four player friendship ruining game and it turns out it's objectively considered successful.
Now, I'm going to have a talk at this exact GDC about why Move or Die was successful
and how we managed to still sell copies even though it came out two years ago.
Now, here's a bunch of things that happened since the game came out.
We made an infomercial update and we actually bought a hotline number so players could leave us voicemails.
We managed to convince the creators of Rick and Morty to let us use their characters in our game.
Some people tried to sell our business cards on eBay,
and we ended up collaborating with several hardware companies for cross-promotion.
A Chinese publisher wanted to buy the IP from us,
so they can make Move or Die into a loading screen minigame for one of their bigger games.
We ended up on the front page of Twitch, above Call of Duty and Minecraft.
We got so many community-made characters that I could literally wallpaper my room with them.
And also we got Shaq playing Move or Die on stage while Snoop Dogg was watching.
Now, as I said, I'm going to have a talk about all this and the overall success of Move or Die,
but the funny thing is, while I'm recording this video, whether or not these things made the game sell better?
I don't know.
So join me during my talk and watch me try to figure out why Move or Die did as well as it did and why it
ended up being successful, because right now, I don't know. But I will know by the time I have my talk.
So, see you there.