Hello, everyone.
Welcome to my talk from Assassin's Creed to the Dark
Eye, The Importance of Themes.
My name's Winifred Phillips, and I compose music for games.
You might know me from my work on the franchises Total War,
Little Big Planet, The Sims, God of War, and Assassin's Creed.
Some of you might have heard my music performed recently
in the Assassin's Creed Symphony concert tour.
And some of you might know me from my book,
Composer's Guide to Gay Music, published by the MIT Press.
Today we're going to be talking about musical themes.
And I'm going to be sharing some stories about my work
composing music for various projects of mine.
But before we dig into practical examples,
let's first take a quick look at one of the most iconic themes
in the history of music for media.
I'm going to play an example for you now. Notice how we hear a short melodic phrase once
and then we hear it again. And it's exactly the same as it was before,
as if the music's saying, hey, you like that? Here, have another.
Okay, so this is everybody's go-to composition for talking about musical themes.
It's one that everybody can identify within the first few bars,
and that's part of why it's such a great example.
Let's briefly consider this theme in terms of its hook.
Now, we all know that a hook in musical composition is a thematic element that's
designed to catch the mind. In Star Wars, it takes the form of that four-bar melody,
and right away we can see one of the core design features of the Star Wars theme.
It's built around repetition.
In the Star Wars theme, we hear full statements of that main melody, complete with its internal
repetition. And then we get a contrast section or a bridge, and then we're right back to another
full statement of that same internally repeating main melody. And this pattern happens five times
over the course of the Star Wars theme.
So it's no wonder we remember the Star Wars main theme melody so well.
By the time we're finished listening to it, it's literally been drummed right into our heads.
The music, well, it's a big part of what makes Star Wars what it is.
It's essentially the musical signature of Star Wars.
So how does the idea of musical signatures fit into our work as game composers?
Well, in games, music has a particularly interesting and fundamentally important role to play.
It seems that according to some really cool research conducted at the University of Geneva,
music has a special power.
Music is a super mnemonic.
It makes us remember things, and it does this better than, well, almost anything else.
Just like smells can bring back really vivid memories, music can do the same thing.
And the fact that we hear game music while we're participating in something active and engaging
means that music has an even better chance of being remembered.
active experiences are better remembered than passive ones.
So this means that game music has a unique ability to define the identity of a game
and help players to remember it. But in order for the music to help remind players of the game,
the music itself has to be as memorable as possible. So that's where themes come in.
In this talk, we're going to be discussing what makes musical themes memorable,
including the importance of repetition.
We'll look at composition strategies that are designed to keep things fresh,
including variation and fragmentation.
We'll check out how musical themes hold up inside interactive music constructs,
and we'll discuss some of the different kinds of gameplay
that can benefit from a thematic musical approach.
Along the way, I'm going to be sharing some of my personal experiences composing thematic
music for my projects.
So, let's start with one of my most recent games, the latest entry in the award-winning
Dark Eye video game franchise, which is about to be released this spring.
I was really excited to compose the music for the Dark Eye Book of Heroes video game.
The Dark Eye Book of Heroes is an RPG fantasy video game based on the Dark Eye fantasy world,
which is the most popular fantasy RPG in Europe with over 35 years of fantasy lore and millions
of fans.
So, let's get started.
Right from the start, the developers and I decided that we would focus on a four-minute main theme
that would strongly assert the musical signature for the Dark Eye Book of Heroes.
Now, to make it memorable, I restated that theme in six distinct variations.
As game composers, we want that hook to grab hold and stick in the mind.
So while the Dark Eye Book of Heroes main theme does include development of its ideas
and it includes secondary sections and bridges, that main hook melody keeps on coming back.
Let's see how that works.
you
As you could hear, it's an overt strategy that's designed to ensure a melody is going
to be remembered.
Of course, that was a pretty dynamic foreground melody, so what if we want to take a more
subtle approach?
When I was hired to compose the music for Assassin's Creed Liberation, one of the first
requested tracks was the main theme melody for the game, so I'm sitting there in front
of my keyboard and I'm trying to start composing a main theme for an Assassin's Creed game.
And I'm thinking about what makes Assassin's Creed unique.
The surreal nature of being in the animus.
A virtual world that exists kind of like an altered mental state, like dreaming or hypnosis.
What could I do as the composer to evoke this particular feeling?
Now, around that time, there was a lot of discussion of the four-chord technique that
Hans Zimmer popularized in movies like Inception.
Of course, the four-chord technique wasn't unique to him.
It actually owes a lot to pop music construction, but Hans Zimmer brought a lot of attention
to it.
Something about a simple repeating four-chord pattern feels very hypnotic.
And so I thought, well, why not?
Let's figure out a four chord progression, something that sounds interesting, and then
base the entire track off of it. I'd never done anything like that before and it could work.
So, here it is. The four chords of the Assassin's Creed Liberation main theme.
It took a little while to settle on them and then I recorded them using a really mellow synth pad.
I played them over and over and over again for about two minutes. So, here's what that was like.
The four chords became the foundation of the main theme.
And then it was just a matter of adding things to it.
Lots of things.
So while there is plenty of melodic material in the Assassin's Creed Liberation main theme,
the element that gets the most repetition is that sequence of four chords.
We hear that four chord pattern 14 times in the main theme alone.
Now this gives that four chord sequence some mnemonic heft within the body of the Assassin's
Creed Liberation score.
It's going to feel familiar when we hear it again.
And that allows it to be meaningful when it reappears as a broken chord sequence during
stealth gameplay.
or when that same four-chord sequence shows up during the game's main user interface menus.
Repetition can serve as a powerful musical signature, whether by virtue of a bold and
dynamic melody line or, in this case, a subtle chord progression.
If an element pops up during our music composition that seems perfect for recurrence,
we have to be ready to recognize that and act on it. For instance, in my music for the first
person shooter Homefront the Revolution, I composed an emotional theme for when an unlikely hero
suddenly delivers a remarkably inspiring speech about fighting back against oppression.
Now, since the whole idea of the game centers around that concept, that musical signature
took on a really iconic character, and I privately named it the Stand With Me theme from a phrase
that that character used during that speech.
Afterwards, I made a mental note to use the Stand With Me theme again if I ever saw the
chance to do so.
It turns out there were quite a few chances.
Here it is as it was used in three different story missions.
If you want to be safe, you gotta save yourselves!
You gotta take responsibility.
You want your home back? Take it!
You want your life back? Get it back!
You have to breathe. Get him up there.
It's for a reason.
He's done.
You have a brother to make.
You saved me.
People of America, we stand today facing a new dawn.
Thanks to the immense sacrifices of the resistance
and the loyalty of our European allies,
we have one final chance at freedom.
It must not slip through our fingers.
We have to ready ourselves once more
and stand shoulder to shoulder with our allies.
So now we've talked about the importance of repetition.
but we all know that repetition can get pretty stale if we don't approach it creatively. So
that brings us to the topic of variation. How we keep our themes feeling fresh.
Let's approach this subject from a much more cheerful perspective.
To date, I've worked on six LittleBigPlanet games,
four in the main franchise, and two downloadable content games.
And while the music in LittleBigPlanet can be very melodic,
the melodies don't tend to be repeated from one level to another.
Because of this, the music has a very episodic quality,
which actually suits gameplay in LittleBigPlanet pretty well.
Sackboy moves from one world to another, and the music completely changes.
However, there are a few exceptions to this rule,
and it's actually a good example of theme and variation in the LittleBigPlanet universe.
In Little Big Planet PS Vita, developed by Tarsier Studios for Sony Computer Entertainment
Europe, Sackboy explores a world called the Land of Odd, which includes Marianne's garden
of living puppets and clockworks.
The music I composed for this level included a melody featuring the sound of clockworks
and an ingenue voice.
Now later on in the game, that same melody returns during a boat race, except now it's twice as hyper
and it's carried by a zany trumpet. So let's see what that was like.
While repeating melodies are few in the LittleBigPlanet universe, they definitely stand out and get
noticed when they appear, especially when they're expressed in dramatically different
instrumental arrangements.
Now, not all projects are going to offer the opportunity
to introduce such extreme variation.
It's an example of how far the variation technique can go.
And when variation isn't enough
and we need to go further than that,
we can actually break our themes apart
and use fragments instead of the whole.
Now, the music I composed for the video game Spore Hero was very thematic,
including lots of repeating melodies.
One of the most important of these melodies
figured prominently in the main theme of the game.
And it was actually a pretty long melody that took a while to fully state.
So it was kind of a puzzle trying to figure out
how to make such an extended melody recur in the body of the game.
Now, when it wasn't possible to state that melody in its entirety,
I used it as a highly recognizable fragment that consisted of these five notes.
This five-note fragment was really useful in the body of the Spore Hero score.
Now, here is that five-note fragment as it was used in the game's opening menu.
And here's that same melodic fragment as it was used in the character creation menu.
Likewise, here's that five-note fragment again as it appeared
in the game's most important and frequently used stinger.
And finally, here's a little fun fact.
The Spore Hero theme gets really dramatic and epic
as you get towards the end of the game.
And it was actually this version of that melody
that was licensed from the publisher
and was used in a trailer for Avengers Endgame.
So here's what that was like.
It just goes to show that a flexible theme can be used in a lot of different ways, especially
when we break it down into fragments.
So now that we've taken a look at theme fragmentation, let's briefly consider how themes can enhance
different kinds of gameplay types.
We typically see recurring themes used frequently in story-driven narrative moments, especially
during cutscenes in cinematics.
For instance, I composed the music for the Legend of the Guardians video game,
and I made sure in that musical score that that main theme melody was prevalent
during the game's start sequence and in its cinematic opening credits.
However, the role of music goes beyond cinematic uses.
While themes, well, they can propel a storyline,
using themes more frequently than that
can also reinforce the identity of the game we're scoring
and serve as a musical signature for it.
For instance, while the main theme
was important during cinematic sequences,
the main theme melody also appeared prominently
during combat as well.
Themes can work during action, even in a game that isn't particularly narrative-focused.
A good example of this is the Speed Racer video game based on the Wachowskis movie.
Now, it's really not a story-driven game, but nevertheless, my main theme melody is
just all over the place, in the opening cinema, during the races, and even in the end credits.
These kind of recurring thematic uses can be employed during exploration, too.
In some of my music for the original God of War from Sony Computer Entertainment, I composed
an atmospheric choral theme that was used in some of the grander locations in the game.
As game composers working to incorporate themes into our scores, repetition really is our friend.
Repetition makes a musical theme more memorable. Now with that in mind,
it can be useful for us to create a rationale for why a musical theme is recurring.
You'll remember the Stand With Me theme
that I composed for Homefront the Revolution.
It was used in moments of inspiring patriotism
and self-sacrifice.
So that became the underlying meaning
that that musical theme was meant to convey.
And it guided me in terms of choosing
when that theme should be repeated.
For the four-chord theme from Assassin's Creed Liberation, I knew that I had a memorable hook
that could help to reinforce the identity of the game and provide a strong musical signature for it,
but I did want a clear narrative association that was going to guide me when choosing when that
theme should recur. With that in mind, I decided to use the four-chord theme in moments of
revelation, when mysteries were solved and secrets were discovered.
Here are a couple of examples of how the four chord theme functioned as a truth revealed.
But look at me now in the light of truth.
You, who know so well the pain of a life lived in secret,
shrouding your power in petticoats and lace,
pretending obedience to men who deny you the right to your own abilities.
Am I really so strange to you?
Foxglove, you killed my father with your care and your tonic.
Why? Because he never truly loved you?
And Jeanne, my mother?
So now we've discussed the importance of repeating musical themes
using the variation technique and also fragmentation
to support different gameplay types.
So now let's explore what happens when musical themes
are employed within more complex
interactive music constructs.
Interactive music systems are fantastic ways
to make music feel more responsive to player choice.
However, these interactive music systems can throw up big roadblocks when it comes to thematic
composition choices.
Here are a couple of examples within two different systems, one where a thematic approach encountered
some roadblocks, and another in which the going was a bit smoother.
First, let's talk about horizontal resequencing.
Imagine a piece of music as a deck of cards, with each card representing a short section of music.
Now imagine that the game can shuffle those cards whenever it wants,
changing the order of musical events. Now that's horizontal resequencing in a nutshell.
As a composer, it can kind of feel like we're constantly drawing a joker or a wild card.
It makes things really unpredictable, which makes thematic writing hard to pull off.
Here's an example. In Spore Hero there is a dancing mini-game that has your character
competing against other non-player characters. The music is structured so that it can switch
smoothly from generalized dancing to more special moves.
When I originally composed the dancing music, I incorporated the main theme melody into
it. Here's what that sounded like.
Unfortunately, when the game switched over to the specialized move, that melody would be abruptly cut off.
And, well, that just really didn't work.
So we ended up just removing that main melody altogether.
Now here's what the final dancing minigame was like.
The final result, it worked well.
And the interactive music system functioned the way it should,
but it also temporarily stopped reinforcing
the musical identity of the game.
Now fortunately, as we've previously discussed,
there were lots of other opportunities in Spore Hero
to assert that defined musical signature.
Now, in another project, I tackled a similar issue
from within a very different interactive music system,
vertical layering.
So let's imagine music as a game of Jenga.
Picture a tower of wooden blocks.
Now, imagine the game can pull blocks out of that tower
or add blocks to the top of the tower at any time.
And that's what vertical layering really is all about.
The music is stacked in simultaneous layers,
and the system adds or subtracts those layers.
This can pose challenges when we're trying to compose thematically.
Case in point, during my work on Little Big Planet 2, I composed a jazz track that featured
an extensive melody that was carried by scat vocals.
The scat vocal layering allowed me to write a well-defined, extended melody line.
However, I did have to account for the fact that the system could just shut this melody
off at any time.
like pulling a block out of that tower of Jenga, I had to make sure that my whole tower wasn't just
going to fall down. So I structured the supporting instruments so that they would carry a subtle
melodic line that felt like a simplified version of the foreground theme. That way the main melody
could be stripped out and the music would still work. So here's a taste of that.
Oh
Thematic writing for interactive systems,
it can be tricky.
Sometimes it really works and sometimes it just doesn't.
When it doesn't work, we have to be ready
to discard the thematic hook
in favor of the interactive construct
so that it can properly function
if that seems like the right decision.
Now, conversely, we can set aside some interactivity
in favor of satisfying thematic content
if that seems like the right choice.
The choice is never really an easy one.
So now we've discussed the nature of musical themes.
We've considered how a thematic hook can grab our listeners' attention.
We've looked at how overtly melodic lines can soar
above their arrangements and how more subtle thematic elements can insistently
burrow into our minds. We've explored the power of repetition.
We've thought about variation and fragmentation that can help keep things
feeling fresh.
When they recur, we've pondered the role of themes in different types of gameplay scenarios,
and we've examined the pros and the cons of using thematic material within interactive music systems.
Themes can serve as the musical signatures for the games for which they were written.
As game composers, if we decide to compose thematically, then we have to commit to that
approach and use every technique and tool at our disposal to maximize the effectiveness and
the power of our themes. I hope you've enjoyed my talk today. Thanks very much for watching.