Welcome everyone and thank you for joining on the Friday of GDC.
No easy task.
I actually wasn't sure how many folks were going to make it, but then I started thinking maybe this is kind of like when a grocery store puts the important stuff all the way in the back and you have to like navigate your way.
So I'm hoping this is the important part of GDC.
And yeah, hopefully you're able to take away some cool insights from it.
So identifying indie, a study of who plays what and why.
So I'm Phil from Humble Games, which is the publishing arm of Humble Bundle, which some of you may be familiar with.
And a little while back, we did a study alongside our partners at Interpret.
about indie gamers.
And yeah, I think it's also really nice to be able to put some data behind the voice of indie gamers and really be able to continue to deliver experiences that surprise and delight them.
So before we get into the findings themselves a little bit about the research that we did, we did both quantitative and qualitative research, so surveys and focus groups, and we surveyed over 4,800 respondents across ages 18 to 45, across six countries, including the US, Germany, and Brazil, amongst others.
And all of this was with the goal of understanding indie gamers and specifically people that buy indie games.
And so you might be thinking, well, how did you define indie games?
Which is an excellent question.
And actually a question that we asked as well, and it could probably be its own entire separate talk.
We saw a lot of responses ranging from size of the team to budget of the game.
to whether or not you have a publisher.
For our purposes, we found, at least for premium titles, that Pricepoint was a pretty good proxy for a lot of those things.
And we also provided examples to survey respondents as well.
But indie buyers, we wanted to learn more about them and specifically who they are, what is their ideal indie experience, and then how do they buy.
And so we started out with who they are and while we did collect demographic information, I think the more interesting piece of it is more about their habits, their attitudes, their motivations.
So that's kind of where we started this whole journey.
And to dig into it more, we actually separated our respondents into three different segments.
And this is a really important slide because I'm going to reference this throughout the entire rest of the presentation, so good one to focus on.
But we segmented our respondents into three groups.
First, regular indie buyers were folks that had purchased five or more indie titles within the prior 12 months from when the study was run.
Light indie buyers purchased 1-4 indie titles in the prior 12 months.
Traditional game buyers bought no indie titles in the prior 12 months, but purchased at least one AA or AAA title.
Actually, 40% of the respondents had purchased at least one indie title within the prior 12 months, which I thought was really cool to see.
It's a pretty significant audience, and I don't know that I would have guessed that beforehand.
So that was really nice to see.
But I actually want to dive into the habits of each of these gamers.
And we're going to start with traditional gamers, just so we can set a foundation and compare and contrast against indie buyers.
So looking at traditional game buyers, they play both PC and console.
And I should mention that this study is largely PC and console focused, so not a lot of mobile reference throughout the rest of this talk.
So just a good note to have.
They game for about 12 hours per week.
And on the right-hand side, you can see some of their top genres, including things like shooters, open-world action, action-adventure, sports, battle royale.
And then on the bottom right, you can see how they index any genres where they may over index when compared to indie game buyers.
So in this case, sports being a genre where they over index anything over 100 means they over index if it's over 120, that was statistically significant.
Now let's take a look at Light Indie Buyers.
Again, these were 1-4 indie titles in the prior 12 months.
This group is heavier PC players.
We still do see they play console as well, but skew a bit more towards PC.
the game for about 20% more per week when compared to traditional gamers.
And then top genres are actually really similar to what you saw in the last slide.
With one exception, we do see that RPGs creep into the top five here, coming in at the third most popular genre or most played recently.
And then on the bottom right, you see a lot of genres that
are typically more associated with indie titles, things like roguelikes, metroidvanias, collectible card games.
This group is way more likely to play those games and those genres than traditional game buyers.
They still don't make it to the top five of their overall genres played, but definitely way more likely than traditional gamers.
And then lastly, regular indie buyers.
These were folks who had purchased five or more indie titles in the prior 12 months.
This is the heaviest PC playing group of the entire audience.
They game about 50% more per week when compared to traditional gamers.
And again, on the right-hand side, you can see top genres played really similar, with the exception RPGs jumping to their number one most played recent genre.
And then on the bottom right, you can see, very similar to the last slide, just kind of on steroids, they're way more likely to play a lot of these genres that I mentioned previously.
So what we did then was we took each of those three groups and we asked, OK, how many AAA games do you buy?
How many AA games do you buy?
And how many indie games do you buy?
So going into it, we kind of had this thought that maybe indie gamers are only playing indie games or mostly playing indie games and they're not really playing a lot of triple or double A stuff.
Turns out that this data says, at least in Western territories, that's not the case.
These folks are avid gamers across the board.
They actually buy more AAA games than traditional gamers.
They buy more AAA games than traditional gamers.
And they also buy quite a few indie games, which I think if you've seen a lot of people's Steam libraries, you can attest to this fact.
But also looking at light indie buyers, it was a similar case but a lot less pronounced than those regular indie buyers.
They do play AAA games.
They also play AA games.
Again, just a lower quantity than those regular indie buyers.
And then traditional gamers buying both AAA and AA titles, and by definition, they're not buying any indie games.
And we did ask about that, and we'll talk about it more in a couple of slides, but kind of the short answer there is they view AAA and AA as higher quality and better value than indie titles, and they generally like playing big franchises.
OK, so this is an eye chart.
I will try and break it down for you a little bit.
So we asked a bunch of questions about the attitudes of each of these gamers.
And you can see on the bottom, there's a few questions where the respondents or the three segments are really close together.
So they have very similar views on some of these questions that we asked.
So for example, gaming is a laid back activity that I use for unwinding.
preferring games where I can explore areas in the order that I want.
These were common things amongst all of our respondents.
So there actually are a decent amount of similarities.
But let's jump into or drill into some of the differences.
So the first three items on here, gaming as a key part of my identity.
Regular indie buyers were more likely to view gaming as a key part of their identity, whereas traditional gamers kind of view it as just one of the things that they do, and light indie buyers kind of splitting the difference there in between.
Having a preference for playing a variety of genres and franchises, all three groups had a preference for that, but you can see it's much more pronounced with regular indie buyers as compared to those traditional buyers.
And then lastly in this section, playing with friends.
So regular indie buyers were more likely to be okay playing games that their friends are not playing, whereas traditional gamers are more likely to be playing games that their friends are playing.
Again, with light indie buyers kind of splitting that difference in between.
And last slide in this section is we asked how each of these three groups would describe indie games.
So indie games specifically.
And you can see regular and light indie buyers really similar across the board, maybe a little more pronounced for regular indie buyers, but very likely to describe indie games as things like unique, experimental, innovative, passionate
And then you can contrast that to traditional gamers who are much more muted in their responses across the board on kind of all of these descriptors.
And while it wasn't super common, you do see some traditional game buyers that tend to view indie games as lower quality.
And again, this speaks to the fact that I mentioned earlier that they're not purchasing any indie titles.
So that's a little bit about who these gamers are.
This next section is kind of the bulk of the talk here.
What is their ideal indie experience?
And I do want to caveat before we go into this section that there's a lot of information here, and I don't want the takeaway to be that my game needs to have all of these elements or all of these aspects to succeed, because I think that's very much not the takeaway.
I would argue it actually should be more about trying something different and innovative and unique.
But this is a good glimpse into general preferences for indie gamers.
So keep that in mind when we're going through this section.
So this slide is looking at gaming aspect priorities.
And in the blue, we asked indie gamers why they play all games.
And in the red, we asked traditional gamers why they play all games.
So this is all games.
This is not specific to indie games.
Basically, why are you playing these games?
Right off the bat, you can see there's some similarities across these groups.
Story and narrative is first and foremost the number one driver.
This is something that we've seen across the board with a lot of studies that we've done.
It's a pretty consistent result.
We'll talk about how it might actually be different for indie games in a little bit, but story and narrative are important to both groups.
Gameplay controls and feel also really important.
And then amount of content is also important to both groups.
Although, again, we'll talk about that a little bit more when we look at indie games specifically.
A couple of key differences.
So indie gamers are more likely to focus on innovation and uniqueness when they're playing all games.
And again, when we talk about indie games specifically, you'll see that number jump quite a bit.
And then graphics and art.
It's important to both groups, but traditional gamers put a much heavier emphasis on graphics and art than indie game buyers do.
OK, so this slide is taking indie game buyers specifically.
And in the blue, we're still looking at why they play all games.
But now in the yellow, we're actually looking at why they play indie games specifically.
And so there's a couple things that kind of remain the same.
Story and narrative still important.
Gameplay controls and feel.
But I want to point out a couple of the differences.
So innovation and uniqueness, it was important before, but now it actually skyrockets to be the number two driver for gaming aspects in terms of indie gamers when they play indie games.
Similarly,
expression and creativity, that jumps quite a bit.
And then the third one I want to call out is amount of content, which I felt was a little interesting.
So it's still important, but it actually is de-emphasized in importance when these gamers are playing indie games.
And I think these three sections kind of tell a little bit of a story when gamers are playing, or when indie gamers are playing indie games, they're not necessarily there because they want an endless experience.
They're there for something that's different and unique.
And remembering back to that earlier slide, they play a ton of games.
They're probably playing multiple games.
at the same time.
So having the ability to kind of beat a game and check it off your list, that was actually something that we found indie gamers found satisfying.
We also looked at a bunch of theme preferences.
And going back to my earlier caveat, this is not saying if you have a theme in a certain area that is one way or the other, it's a good or bad thing.
This is not predictive.
But this is general preferences.
So we asked each of the three cohorts, which themes are your favorite?
Which themes do you find overused?
And I won't go through all these, because you'll be able to reference them online later.
but just a couple call outs so fantasy and sci-fi those were the top themes across all the cohorts but you can see it's more pronounced again with regular and light indie buyers
And then in terms of overused themes, post-apocalyptic and warfare, indie buyers were more likely to say those themes were overused as compared to traditional gamers.
Again, I can think of many successful warfare theme titles, so this is not prescriptive about purchase behaviors, but rather kind of stated preferences.
And then there's a bunch more here.
I won't go through all of them.
I did highlight superhero because that is pretty prevalent in today's media.
But you can see regular and light indie buyers more likely to view this category as overused, whereas traditional gamers are more likely to kind of see it as their favorite as compared to indie buyers.
All right, this is the last slide in this section.
It is a pretty dense slide, so I'm going to try and break it down and keep it digestible.
But we asked indie buyers, what are your ideal features when playing an indie game?
And this also goes back to what I stated earlier.
This doesn't mean that your game has to have all these features.
Otherwise, it's doomed to failure.
That's not the case.
So story and narrative, we talked about how important that is.
Indie gamers like seeing original IP with deep storylines, and they also like this idea of nonlinear storytelling.
So it doesn't have to be a cinematic or traditional kind of cut scene style of storytelling.
It can be nonlinear world building, maybe something you might see in some of those genres I mentioned earlier, for example, Metroidvania.
The ability to tell a story in a different way goes a long way with this audience.
Innovation and uniqueness, they really like the idea that designers took a risk.
And even if it doesn't 100% pay off, just the fact that you took a risk is really important.
I will say it's better if the risk pays off, but just the idea that you took a risk will go a long way.
The other thing here is that taking a risk doesn't mean trying an entirely new genre necessarily or kind of revolutionizing a particular genre or theme, but it can be taking one unique aspect of the game, whether it's a mechanic or storytelling, and putting your own spin, trying something a little different.
We've seen that just even the fact that you're trying something really goes a long way with these gamers.
In terms of controls and modes, there was a preference for third person perspective, and also a slower pace that allows for time to kind of plan things out, as opposed to traditional gamers who did have a bit more of a preference for that kind of fast twitch reflex.
Again, single player over multiplayer.
This does not mean that if you have a multiplayer game, it can't do well.
Of course, that's not the case.
But just a general preference, again, for indie gamers towards single player.
If you do go multiplayer, the mode that popped the most was online co-op.
That was more so than things like online PVP or local co-op.
In terms of graphics and art, there was a preference for stylized art styles with bright and bold colors.
2D or 3D were both good in these gamers' books.
If you do go 2D, the idea of it being hand-drawn was compelling to this audience.
And then in terms of audio, we saw that the music and the soundtrack can be a really big differentiator and was probably the most important thing over things like VO or sound effects.
Creativity and expression we saw in an earlier slide was something that popped when these gamers came to indie games specifically.
So any opportunities to build in expression, things like character customization will go a long way.
And then also having the ability to develop a unique play style and maybe approach a problem in a different way, not only a one-size-fits-all solution, but having the ability to figure things out in different ways resonates with this audience.
And then lastly, amount of content.
So we talked about it a little bit before.
There was a preference for a vast world to explore and longer play sessions as compared to shorter ones.
And then I realized there's a little bit of dissonance with this last point because I said earlier, amount of content is less important when you play indie games.
And now here we're saying, yeah, but can we have 20 to 100 hours?
of content.
So I am aware of the dissonance there.
To me, the way I read that is more content is always going to be a good thing.
No one's ever going to complain that your game is too long.
I think just the idea that it's not, it doesn't have to be an endless experience.
They want to focus on
those creativity, those innovative aspects, that's okay.
So content's still important, but it's not going to be the top determinant of someone playing your game.
All right, and the last section here is diving into a little bit more about how do they buy, so purchase habits and behaviors of indie buyers in each of the three groups.
So we did look at monetization models, lots of different monetization models, probably even more than we have listed here, but we did look at some of the more popular monetization models over the course of the last several years in gaming.
And not a huge surprise here, but people kind of had a preference for fully paid upfront games.
That preference was more pronounced with regular and light indie buyers.
But then free-to-play, we actually do see that the indie audience is okay with free-to-play, especially if it is cosmetic-only MTX or even Battle Pass or Season Pass.
Where you start to see a little bit more aversion is where you get into free-to-play, either with advertisements or with gameplay affecting microtransactions in the game.
And then purchase timing.
So I just stated that indie gamers do have a preference for fully paid games up front.
This is looking at when in the lifecycle of your game they are likely to purchase.
And you can see between regular and light indie buyers, they're actually less likely to purchase right at release as compared to traditional gamers.
And they're more likely to purchase during a future sale, whether it's an initial sale or a deep sale later on.
And I think there's a couple of reasons for that.
So first it goes back to how many games they're playing.
They have a ton of stuff and they physically can't play all of them at the same time.
So they're OK waiting a little bit more.
And then I think the second thing is price sensitivity.
We actually also asked about kind of if there's a sweet spot for pricing your game.
And certainly there are exceptions, but we did see between $15 and $25 US was kind of a sweet spot.
When you go below, there can be questions about quality of the game.
Although again, there's games that price below that that have done really well in their
Great games.
And then if you go above 25, we do see a little bit more of a focus on content.
So you're starting to compete with some of those double and triple A titles.
And so expectations around amount of content will go up as that price point does go up.
The last thing I want to mention on this slide is, you know, traditionally in the industry and certainly
jobs that I've had, there's been a lot of emphasis on launch, and very understandably so.
You want to do the best you can, come out of the gates as strong as possible.
I think this is nice to see this data because it does say that even if you come out of the gates a little bit slower than you had initially anticipated, there are still opportunities down the road to gain a bigger audience, especially if you're updating your game or continuing to improve your game.
Having that in conjunction with the sale can bring a lot of people in down the road.
And then lastly, I kind of want to look at a sample path to purchase.
This would be for an indie gamer buying on PC.
I know a lot of folks are PC-first or centric.
So we wanted to look at how do gamers discover games, how do they research them, and ultimately what makes them pull the trigger in terms of a purchase decision.
First, where do you hear about a game?
YouTube, super influential.
We see Steam and Family and Friends.
And the one thing to call out too with Steam or really any first-party platform is there was a lot of discoverability when you partake in a platform sale.
So if it's a platform-wide sale or a theme sale, there's actually a lot of discovery that happens because players will kind of be looking for a specific genre and may stumble upon your game.
And then conducting research.
So I think anecdotally, a lot of us might have guessed that gamers like to see gameplay.
And it's nice to put a little data behind that.
But our research did kind of confirm that gameplay is really important when it comes to conducting research, as well as things like screenshots and official trailers.
And then lastly, when they actually decide to make the purchase, what is really impacting them?
Again, it goes back to gameplay.
I think if you're thinking about where do you want to spend marketing dollars, focusing on gameplay videos is always going to be a good choice to consider.
Sales and discounts we talked about on the last slide, but that's another great way to kind of convert people and get them over the hump.
And then lastly, player reviews.
I haven't mentioned it a ton yet, but quality is still really important.
And we did find that having evangelists and other players who are supporting your game and reviewing it highly, that can be a really influential factor for a purchase decision.
So those are kind of the big takeaways.
I do want to just quickly recap each of the three areas that we talked about just so you can kind of see the big points.
But indie buyers, who are they?
So gaming is a key part of their identity.
But they don't only play indie games, they actually play a ton of games.
And when they come to play indie games, they are looking for a different experience than what they might be looking for with AAA or AA.
They're looking for something that's more innovative, more creative, maybe takes more risks than you might typically see with those bigger titles.
And so to that point, don't be afraid to take a risk.
It doesn't have to be reinventing the wheel or revolutionizing an entire genre, but it could be focusing on one specific aspect, trying something new, putting your own twist on it.
Creative storytelling goes a really long way.
And it, again, does not have to be a super expensive cinematic or cut scene.
It can be building the world and lore in different unique styles.
And then lastly, those artistic touches can go a long way.
We talked about some of the different art style choices, as well as that music and soundtrack that can really elevate a game and kind of tie the experience together for gamers.
And then purchase habits, so back to basics.
Fully paid, upfront games was the preference.
Free to play is becoming more and more acceptable, if done right.
And even though fully paid is kind of the gold standard for these folks, patience is still a virtue because they're playing lots of games and you still have the ability to get people into the funnel after your initial launch.
with me.
So that's all I had for you.
Thank you everyone for making it on a Friday.
I know it's been a long week, but I hope everyone has safe travels and just a couple of housekeeping things.
So one, I think you should have had your badge scanned on the way in.
Please let them know what you thought.
If it was terrible and you never want me to come back, that's okay.
You can tell them.
If it was good, you can also tell them that too.
So thanks everyone.
I don't think I have time for questions right now, but I will stick around outside in case anyone wants to chat.
so