Good morning everyone. My name is Alexander Bruce and I'm the creator of Antichamber,
a mind-bending psychological exploration game that was released on Steam at the beginning of last year.
Before I begin I want to say thank you to the IGS organizers for inviting me here today because
GDC, the IGS, the IGF were very important to my development. Five years ago I was sitting in this
room for the first time as someone just starting out and I was looking at the people on stage
thinking these guys have made it and I want to know what they did.
And I'm happy to share my story with you today of how I went from there to where I am now,
which is here.
Prior to the game's release, it was the IGF 2012 winner for technical excellence.
The game was backed by the Indie Fund.
It had been covered many, many times by most major news sites.
After the game was released on the 31st of January,
The game went on to sell 100,000 copies within 7 weeks.
And lifetime sales are now at around 750,000 copies,
with around $5 million gross revenue.
So the question that I'm here to talk about today
is how this happened.
You know, was it just a good idea?
Did I know the right people?
Or was I just very, very lucky?
This is going to come up a couple of times throughout the talk,
but I'm going to start this talk by just giving you some of my philosophy on luck
that was driving a lot of my decision making.
And it's that first and foremost, if luck isn't everything,
then it made sense to me to factor it out of everything.
That's not to say that it doesn't exist,
but it's something that I don't control.
And so I'm going to factor it out of all my business decisions.
And when you do that, it means that you have to take
all of the other things on this slide much more seriously.
And I believe if you do a good job of that,
you should at least be able to be successful.
And then if you get lucky, whatever that means,
you're then more successful.
Luck is a multiplier on your efforts.
I don't believe it should be the thing
that makes or breaks your success.
And one of the reasons that I want to say that is when we're looking at other people's
successes or failures, we don't have all of the information.
And we use luck to describe things that we don't completely understand.
And I realize that there's a very big difference between the public perception of what happened
and the reality of what happened.
So today I'm here to talk about reality.
And I want to do this because five years ago, this is where I started.
I was a student.
I came from Melbourne, Australia, which is not an area that was known for making independent
hits.
This was my first independent game, and I was working on it alone from a bedroom.
But I did have one question that set me apart from the rest of my cohort at the time,
and that was this.
What makes me different to people that I would deem to be successful?
This was not an entitled question like,
oh, why aren't I successful?
This was a genuinely curious question like,
what did these people do, and is that something that I can do as well?
But it would actually be a bit unfair to say that this was the starting point,
because even this question had to come from somewhere.
I did not just wake up one day and wonder what made me different.
So I'm going to jump back very briefly to nine years ago,
when I first got into anything games-related at all.
I was a student starting out in university and I went into that with a very simple philosophy.
Pick any individual skill and I can guarantee that I will not be the best person at it.
I am not the best artist because I've not been drawing since I was 10.
I'm not the best programmer because I don't do it as a day job.
My skill set is a very technical, creative, analytical person.
is to be very very different as a strategic decision.
And I was doing this so that I could stand out in university,
so that I could then get into industry.
And then I was going to stand out in industry,
so that I could get promoted and get hired overseas,
which is where I actually wanted to work.
And so in 2006, when I was introduced to modding tools for Unreal Tournament 2004,
I made things like this.
I made a world full of tiles that I called dynamic geometry,
that I could sweep complex algorithms across
and get them to respond in all kinds of interesting ways.
And I turned this into a multiplayer arena combat game.
It was very violent, and I decided to call this thing Hazard.
But when I tried to run this across a network,
way too much stuff was going on,
and I was not a network programmer at the time, so I put it down.
In 2007, that other one got way too big, way too fast,
so I thought, I'm just gonna start small again.
I just want to see what asteroids would look like in 3D,
which meant that when I have to deal with the screen wrapping,
I then have to deal with rendering perspective
through the screen wrapping as well.
So I made this thing called Recursive Space.
And again, it was an interesting system,
but I didn't know what to do with it at the time,
so I put it down.
But what these systems did was they got me hired to work in industry two and a half years through a four year degree.
So my plan of standing out was definitely working.
But working in industry actually made me quite jaded.
Because one of the first things that happened was my Unreal Engine 3 game that I was hired for got cancelled.
Which took a lot of the core skills and just threw them out the window.
And I then had the opportunity to move on to an infrastructure team,
which was a great learning experience because I was there as a junior in my first year,
and there were four seniors, the lead programmer and the technical director of the company,
which at the time had about 180 people.
But the whole time I was there, I thought,
how am I supposed to compete with these guys?
And obviously no one was expecting that, but from a self-satisfaction level,
it was really demotivating and it just made me feel inadequate,
and I started to doubt whether or not I was actually a programmer.
Towards the end of the year, I also had to go through months of crunch on a game that I ultimately didn't think was very good.
And the situation wasn't much better elsewhere in Australia.
2008, 2009 is when the Australian industry started folding in on itself.
But it's also the year that I discovered independent development.
And I was looking at some of these guys, particularly the Nebacula Drop guys, thinking,
these guys have figured it out. They've circumvented the system.
It's a team of students who made a game that was very good, they went through some festivals,
they got hired by Valve.
And then they made Portal. They went straight from the bottom to the top.
And so I was looking at all of these guys, thinking,
what makes me different to them?
They circumvented the system. How can I do this as well?
And one of the things that I noticed about all of these guys
was they went through festivals.
So I thought, all right, that's the answer.
I'm going to go through festivals.
And one of the festivals that was very applicable to me
was this thing called Make Something Unreal.
Now, I'd actually found out about this four years earlier.
randomly one day when I walked into my brother's room and he was looking at the
list of grand prize winners
and he said man wouldn't it be cool to be one of these guys and I was like well
yes but
I know nothing about modding I don't know how to make a game
and here I was four years later I still didn't consider myself a modder
whatever that meant but I did have an unusual game I did know how to make
things in Unreal
And I decided I'm going to play this the same way that I play the education system.
I'm going to submit something radically different,
and I'm going to wait until the very end of the year,
and then I'm going to submit something, and I'm going to surprise people.
And that was this thing that I'd been working on called Hazard the Journey of Life,
which was...
I started off with my geometry and space prototypes,
and then I added a branching map structure, I removed death.
I made all kinds of weird choices,
and it was ultimately something that was just for me.
It was this little philosophical art piece
that I was using as a diary as I was working out
what I was doing in my life.
And I decided that if I wanted to stand out,
the visuals were going to be one of the first things
that people saw.
And one advantage that I had was everything else
that was going through the competition
ultimately still looked like an Unreal game.
And you could see AAA games also just looked like
Unreal Engine 3 games, and I thought,
They're all differentiating themselves with art, but they use similar lights and shaders.
I don't have the time, resources, or skill to compete on that level,
so I'm going to go completely down the other end of the spectrum
and submit something that looks absolutely nothing like something that was made with Unreal.
And in 2009, Sense of Wonder Night was another competition that announced its second year.
And I found out about Sense of Wonder Night...
the previous year, because Ian Dulles went through this as well.
So I was looking at Ian Dulles, thinking,
what makes him, the creator of the Unfinished Swan, different to me?
He's a student from USC, I'm a student from Melbourne.
His game has an interesting art style and theme, so does mine.
His game's about exploration and discovery, as is mine.
So I entered Sense of Wonder Night as well.
And fortunately for me, I got picked,
which represented a very large opportunity.
You know, I'd never been outside of Australia,
and I'd never been to one of these big gaming conventions,
and here I was presenting something that I'd made in Japan.
And so I thought, I may never be in this position again.
If an opportunity comes up, whether that's speaking with someone,
attending a session, using a piece of technology, I have two options.
If I do nothing, I know exactly what will happen.
Absolutely nothing will happen because I didn't try to make something happen.
If I do follow up on an opportunity, something might happen.
Maybe something good, maybe something bad.
But the fact that I don't know is the reason that I must follow up on every single opportunity.
And one of those opportunities was talking with this guy,
Mike Capps, the president of Epic Games.
He gave a keynote there, and when it ended, I walked up to him and I handed over a business card.
I hesitated and I said,
Hi, my name is Alexander Bruce.
I've created this mod for Unreal Tournament.
I'm presenting it at this thing called Sense of Wonder Night.
I was just wondering, do you have a solution for independent developers?
And his answer was, well, yes, actually, we have this thing called the Unreal Development Kit.
It's not announced yet, but I will put you onto Mark Raine, and we will find a solution to your problem.
And this response really surprised me, because here's the president of a very large international corporation
reaching out to me, some random student.
And this taught me that everyone in this industry is just another person.
At some stage in this guy's career, he was where I was that day starting out.
I also had the chance to talk with Steve Swink, who was presenting his game Shadow Physics
there and he was one of the co-chairs of the IGF at the time.
And as we were having a conversation one day, he said, you should join the indie community.
And I said, I don't know, like I couldn't write my own engine.
And he said, you could totally write your own engine.
You should go to GDC and you should meet these people because you'd fit right in.
And what these kinds of conversations did was they reaffirmed my belief that festivals were a great way to get noticed.
I never had the opportunity to speak to some of these people back home in Australia,
so I thought, I'm going to enter every festival that exists just so I can keep on talking to all of these people.
I got selected for Make Something Unreal, and I won an Australian competition,
so I started to get a bit confident, thinking, alright, I'll figure this out.
I'm the same as those people from 2008, and I didn't get in.
I got an honorable mention and my first reaction was like,
what, why aren't I in there?
Surely my game is as good as all of the other games that got picked.
Then I decided, like, what makes me different?
Like, what have I missed?
So I went back and I looked at some of my other successes
and I said, well, clearly something is different here.
Clearly I'm missing something.
I looked at Sense of Wonder Knight, and I said, all right, Sense of Wonder Knight was
a new competition.
66 games were entered, and of them, 11 of them were picked.
That's a one in six chance.
It's not a guarantee, but those are very good odds.
And I did well in Make Something Unreal, because Epic didn't expect such an unconventional
game.
And when I spoke to them later about it, they were like, honestly, man, we have no idea
what the hell you did with our engine, but it was really good, so we thought you should
get a prize.
Whereas the IGF was very used to showcasing different and exceptional games.
And this taught me that being different in amongst a sea of other different games
is just a different kind of same.
You're not going to stand out that way.
I later learned a more useful term.
which was remarkable.
Not fun, not innovative, not polished, remarkable.
Worth making a remark about.
This could either mean that you're conventional
and absolutely exceptional,
or it could mean you're different
and executed very, very well,
or it could mean that you are so completely insane
that people are just like,
I don't know, this could be the future of games.
So I picked myself up,
and starting out in 2010, I'm like,
alright, this is just the start of my independent career.
I was one of the grand finals winners in Make Something Unreal, which gave me around $25,000,
which I just invested straight back into the game over the next couple of years.
I could use the Unreal Development Kit to make a commercial version, so my mod, which
was worth nothing, could now be worth something.
And in February 2010, I was contacted by Valve to put the game on Steam.
And this confused me a bit, because I didn't reach out to them,
and I certainly hadn't had a lot of press at this stage.
So I sent an email to Epic, and I said,
do you guys know anything about this?
And they said, well, yeah, we thought your game was really good,
so we told Valve that they should take it.
And this taught me the power of advocates.
I didn't have to make the connection with Valve at that stage myself,
because I had a connection with Epic,
and they could close that connection for me.
So with all of these new circumstances,
I decided to take Steve Swink's advice
and go to the Game Developers Conference.
And at the GDC I did what you would expect from someone at their first conference.
I ran around having a lot of short conversations with people,
handing out business cards to as many people as I could,
trying to spread my name around.
Because I realized I'm not the first person to try and make a successful game.
And I wanted to learn from what other people had done.
I didn't want to make all of my own mistakes.
And I was also invited to speak at this thing called the Nuovo Sessions.
And I was invited because of my honorable mention at the IGF,
but also because I'd been keeping in touch with Steve Swink since Sense of Wonder Night,
and him and Matthew Wagner were the people who organized this thing,
and they thought I had some interesting things to say.
So going into this, I thought, all right, once again, I may never be in this position again.
I may never get the chance to speak at GDC again, but I want people to remember me.
So I'm going to give them three things.
to remember me by and I don't care which one they remember.
They're going to see either a crazy passionate speech about risk and experimentation,
or they're going to see a very weird abstract game,
or they're going to remember that someone wore a pink suit, and I didn't care which.
And this taught me that being different can be very polarizing.
Some people were totally on board with my eccentricity,
and they thought that the presentation was very theatrical.
Other people looked at me and were like, what a fucking weirdo.
And this was something that I was going to have to be careful about,
because I wanted to stand out, but I also wanted to be taken seriously.
I also had some interesting conversations at GDC.
On the final day, there was a party, and it was a secret party,
and a bunch of my new friends were going to it.
And I kept on asking,
can I come? And they were like,
oh, I don't know, like, you know, it's not really my thing, I'm not sure.
And as we were hanging out in the park,
just before a bunch of people were going,
I asked Heather Kelly, I was like, can I come?
And she said,
I think you can bring a friend, let me check the invite.
She checked and she said, yep, you can come as my plus one.
And I thought about what other people had said
and how it seemed like a bit of a secret.
And I said, you know, I don't really know the hosts
and I'm not really anyone,
so I'm just going to go back to my hotel.
And she said, I think you need to familiarize yourself
with the phrase, fake it till you make it.
Now, this is a totally cliched thing to say,
but at that point in time,
those were the exact words that I needed to hear, you know.
Stop doubting yourself.
Stop saying, I'm not indie, I'm not a model,
I'm not a programmer, I'm not a designer,
and say, if you want to be someone,
stop being someone right now.
At this party, I also had the chance to speak with Mare Shepard,
who was one of the people who helped make M+.
And she was one of the people who was on the Nuovo jury.
And I was lamenting the fact that I didn't get in.
And she said,
I really enjoyed playing your game.
It was exactly the kind of puzzly thing that I like.
I encourage you to not get discouraged
and keep in mind that the jury changes every year.
So here's someone who's been through this before,
who knows what they're talking about, saying,
you're almost there, just try again next time.
And all of these conversations taught me the value of real networking.
Most of the cards that I'd handed out randomly to people didn't do anything at all.
I never heard back from any of them.
Whereas real networking was building genuine relationships with people.
You caring about them, them caring about you,
so that over time you can both help each other out and help each other rise up to the top.
So after GDC I thought, right, this is a very big change in circumstances, I know way more
now than I did going into it, so I'm going to take another three months to continue working
on my game.
And in that three months, I got selected for IndieCade at E3, and I know that this pink
suit was polarizing, but I thought, once is not a science, so I'm going to find the day
with the most cameras around, and I'm going to wear it again.
And I immediately noticed in the morning when I did this,
that people were coming up to me saying,
I loved your GDC talk, I want to try and play your game.
And this taught me that I was very good at getting people interested
in wanting to try my game.
And then at E3, they'd sit down, they'd play it for five minutes,
and then they'd get up and they'd leave.
Because the game wasn't holding people's interest.
And I could have justified this at the time by saying,
well, you know, it's E3, this is a big event,
there's so much interesting stuff around.
I didn't do that, because I thought,
when I'm trying to get press about this game,
when I release the game on Steam,
this is all going to, these are all going to be
very crowded markets.
My game should be able to hold people's interest
more than everything else around.
I need to solve this problem.
And I also learned a bunch of marketing lessons.
Standing around for three days trying to explain
what the hell I was making, despite having a very difficult
problem to begin with, was extremely difficult.
And I learned over time that the reason this is difficult
is because you need to get good at explaining your game
in a way that people who have no context will understand.
You have all the context, they have none,
and that's what you have to get good at.
And you need to get good at it if you want people to care,
because you're going to have to make trailers later.
You're gonna have to talk with the press later.
You're gonna have to make interesting store pages.
and that takes a lot of practice and experience
to get good at.
So after the show, when I was looking at what kind of press coverage I got,
there was a feature on IGN,
and there was about how to stand out at E3,
and there were some other mentions,
but there wasn't this, like, immediate explosion of interest
and everyone caring about me.
So I'm looking at these other games that did seem to have all of this coverage,
and I was like, what did they do? Like, what have I missed out on?
And I thought, all right, well, one of the most obvious ones is,
is that people weren't playing the game for long.
It wasn't holding their interest.
They couldn't see all of the things that I found were so interesting about it.
And watching people directly revealed a hell of a lot of issues to me.
I knew exactly what I needed to fix.
And so, from this point, I then continued testing the game constantly,
on people at home, sending it to festivals,
watching people at conferences, etc.
Because I wanted to understand how people thought.
I wanted to understand what would make this game interesting to people.
And this taught me a lesson about refinement.
The higher in quality any individual aspect of your game gets,
the more other areas start to stick out as wrong.
And so the fact that my design was now getting much, much better
meant that the absence of sound design was becoming a real problem.
Throughout the rest of 2010 I continued trying to enter these competitions.
And after a string of good fortune, I then had a lot of misfortune.
I didn't get into the PAX 10, I didn't get into the IndieCade Festival.
And I was crunching constantly because all of these deadlines were really close together.
And this was making me very, very physically sick doing this.
I wasn't getting enough done, so I was working longer,
which meant I was sleeping less, which meant I was becoming sick,
which meant I was ultimately getting less work done.
And I was struggling at this stage, and I'm thinking...
What makes me different to these other people?
Am I struggling because I'm not good?
Or am I struggling because this is hard?
So I thought, I have to go to Indicade
despite not getting into the festival,
because I need to know the answer to that.
I need to talk to people about this.
On the way to Indicator, I also had to stop off at GDC Online
for another competition, and this one had a $100,000 prize.
Trying to not set any expectations about a prize
that ultimately has $100,000 is pretty difficult.
And so I didn't win, and I just got really burned by expectations again.
It's a very difficult lesson to learn not to do that.
But I was seeing signs of progress.
Earlier issues that I'd seen at E3 were now gone,
but then I was just seeing later issues.
Now I was just seeing issues 20 minutes through
rather than 5 minutes through.
I met Robin Arnett, my sound design,
so we could get the sound design up to the same quality
as everything else.
And I was also getting increasing interest from publishers,
and I thought, all right, maybe these guys could help out
because, you know, there are things I'm struggling with.
They're used to dealing with this kind of stuff.
And maybe they could help with consoles,
which were becoming more of a big deal at the time.
And when I went to IndieCade to talk to people about this,
Ron Carmel said, don't go with a publisher.
If you can get this game greenlit on a console,
I will fund you myself.
Now, this was after the IndieFund announcement,
as they were working out what kinds of games
they should fund.
And I think this was him looking at the game, saying,
publishers are just going to ruin what you're
trying to make with this game.
So I will fund you myself if necessary.
And I also spoke with Daniel Ben-Mergui.
And after IndyCade, I said I was going to go to Japan
to try and have some time off, because Sense of Wonderland
was really refreshing for my mental state.
And he said, going to Japan alone won't solve your problem.
You're doing really well, but you need to slow down
or you will just keep making yourself sick.
You need to change your mindset about this.
You know, this was a marathon,
and I was sprinting the entire time.
So I went to Japan, I came back, and then things started to turn around.
I got into the IGF China, I got into the IGF,
I'd upgraded my honorable mention for the Nuovo up to a finalist for the Nuovo,
and I got nominated in the Indie Game Challenge,
another $100,000 competition, which I also didn't win.
But DICE was interesting because it was an executive conference
and a lot of important people were there.
So knowing that Ron said he would fund me,
I would also have to deal with an engine license.
And so I spoke with Mike Camps and Mark Rain again,
who I'd spoken with several times throughout the year.
And I told them this problem.
They said, Mark said,
well, we can give you an engine license.
And I said, I can't afford that.
And he was like, it doesn't matter.
We'll use the UDK to filter people.
We'll just give you a license under the same terms.
And then that solves that problem.
So knowing I've got funding and a license,
I then started following up things very seriously
with Sony and Microsoft, trying to make something happen.
I was also making some good connections
with the press at this time.
And these were all editor-in-chiefs of various websites.
most of them.
And I started having some interesting questions come up,
because some of these guys were like,
how are you going to appeal to the Call of Duty crowd?
Or, my daughter loves Minecraft, why would she play this?
And these were obviously very frustrating questions,
because I wasn't trying to aim at the Call of Duty crowd.
But the fact that people were asking these questions
was very interesting, because people were no longer just
dismissing this game as some artistic thing.
Now they're actually concerned about how I was going to find an audience for it.
And Dino Patti was there with Limbo, and he could see that I was obviously very frustrated
by some of these questions.
And he said, ignore everything those guys said.
We were getting asked the same questions before Limbo was released.
You're doing fine, keep doing what you're doing.
So like with Steve, like with me, these are people who know what they're talking about,
who've been through this before, saying you're on the right track, just stay on target.
And Jamie Cheng was one of the judges of the Indie Game Challenge.
And he enjoyed playing the game, but he said,
why is it called Hazard?
And I justified it to him, and he said,
hmm, that's interesting, but the title didn't match
the experience I had playing the game.
And this was more feedback than people would give me previously.
People would just be like, I hate the name, it's pretentious.
And I was like, I can't do anything with that.
You know, you're not actually helping me solve the problem.
Whereas here was someone who actually wanted to know more.
But I had bigger fish to fry at that stage because I was in the IGF.
And if this was going to be when I was going to get all of the interest,
this was going to make me the same as those games from 2008.
And I thought, my game is so new over,
I've got such a good chance of winning this thing, and I didn't win.
And this was the last time that I was going to let myself
get burned by these expectations.
I was not going to set any expectations from that moment on.
And I also didn't get any explosion in interest,
because I thought just being in the IGF would be enough,
and so I didn't contact anyone.
I didn't contact any press.
And I got some coverage on the show floor,
but I certainly didn't get as much coverage
as some of the other games that were around.
And I thought, what makes me different to the people who,
you know, what makes me different to the people
from 2008 and 2009 that I knew about?
And then I started thinking.
Actually, what happened to all of the other people who also got forgotten in the IGF?
What didn't they do?
And also what happened to all of the people who never went through festivals
but still had successes and still had failures?
And this taught me that just looking at the successful people
was making me miss out on half of the story.
I was having some more signs of progress, though.
Now at the IGF pavilion, where there was lots of interesting stuff around,
people were sitting and playing my game for an average of 40 to 90 minutes,
which was a very good sign.
And I was also trying to negotiate console versions with Sony and Microsoft,
and so I thought, this is going to take at least another six months.
And then this started to come up. More and more and more.
And these were people that I respected greatly,
who were wanting to help me solve this problem
and understand why it was going to be such an issue.
So Jonathan was looking at it, and he was saying,
I understand how you ended up here.
I understand that the theme has helped you work out
what you're actually creating, but this is a game
that I think a lot of people are really going to want to play,
and you need to make sure that you get your first impressions right.
And not only is Hazard not the right name,
it's actually a counterproductive name,
because it makes it sound like it's in the same vein
as games like Killzone and Bulletstorm,
and not only are you not going to be able to compete
on marketing budgets with those games,
but that's not even the audience that you want.
And the subtitle, The Journey of Life, obviously there's problems there.
So, this is why you need to change this.
And I said, well, I can't change it now, because, like, now I've got all of this exposure,
and I've just been through the IJF, like, that seems super risky.
Like, how am I going to build up all of that exposure again?
And he said, I know it seems like you have a whole lot of interest in this game right now,
but that's going to be completely insignificant relative to the amount of interest that you could get
if you get all of these decisions right.
So this was a massive leap of faith.
And it took a number of weeks of dealing with these guys.
to decide to rename the game to Anti-Chamber.
And when I said this either in text or in speech,
it brought all the right connotations to mind immediately.
People thought inverse chamber, against chamber,
and entrance to a larger space.
This was exactly what I needed.
And I thought, if I'm going to pull this off,
I need something big.
And fortunately for me, I got into the PAX 10.
So I announced the name change immediately after I got that notification,
ahead of when they were going to announce the finalists.
And only one site posted about it.
And I'm pretty sure that only Joystick did this
because I'd met Alexander Sluinski at Dice
and he thought I was interesting and he wanted to help me out.
And this taught me that what's big news to you
may be nothing to someone else.
If I was going to get people to care,
I needed to go into overdrive on this thing.
So I submitted footage to Indie Game The Movie.
I backed their Kickstarter for $300
on the off chance that that went off and became a big success.
I got into Indiecade, I went through a couple of Australian festivals again,
and I started sending the game off to festivals all around the world,
and art galleries, and schools,
so that anyone who wanted the game could just take it and spread word of it.
And as I'm running around doing all of this, I've got people saying,
why are you trying so hard?
Like, why didn't you just give up and move on to your next thing?
And I said, I'm trying to get something up to the same quality
as games like Raiden World of Goo.
And they'd be like, well, that's a big call for an Indian.
I said, what are you talking about?
Brayden and World of Goo were both independent games.
They were both made by two people.
And I'd be like, well, yeah, but those guys had experience.
And I said, Ron and Kyle have their set of experiences
that helped make that specific game.
Jonathan had his experiences. I have my experiences.
An introspective, psychological person.
This is what I'm funneling into the game.
And they'd be like, well yeah, but those games cost hundreds of thousands of dollars.
And I'm like, if you cost my game effectively, my game also costs hundreds of thousands of dollars,
I have just solved that problem in another way.
And I realized that the answer to what makes me different by this stage was actually nothing.
But I only understood this having gone through doing the same thing as all of these other people.
And then I realized there's actually another question that I need here.
Which is how do I not mess this up?
Half of my success was finding out what it took to be successful.
The other half was not making mistakes.
And one of those would have been the name,
because it's the first impressions that people see.
The other one would have been if I continued chasing up consoles,
because these were taking up a hell of a lot of time.
And that was time that was being taken away from the design.
So I didn't follow up with Microsoft,
and I was in negotiations with Sony for a long time.
And they did offer me a large sum of money at one stage,
but I thought,
A worse game on more consoles is not a net benefit to anyone.
This is such a risk for a design.
I need the best game on the platform.
It fits most.
It fits for Steam.
That's the audience I knew.
And I also thought when I made that decision, I don't even own a PS3 or an Xbox 360, so
why the hell am I trying to make something for a market I don't understand?
So then I went off to the PAX 10, and I'd learned a hell of a lot from the IGF.
This time I went in with no expectations.
Honestly, I thought Fez was going to get all of the attention, or Jamestown, or something else.
I just wanted to have a good show.
I knew how hard it was to get attention by this stage.
And then this happened.
Steven Tuttillo from Kotaku said,
My favorite game of PAX.
Griffin McElroy wrote the best preview of the game.
Ryan Davis from Giant Bomb covered the whole PAX 10,
and the comments started going crazy about my game.
G4TV and Machinima also picked it as like one of their favorite things of the show,
and I met Notch, and he also really enjoyed it.
So this was exactly the kind of reception I'd been chasing,
and I responded to it with depression, because now that I had all of these rising expectations,
I thought, my game is still months away from being done,
and now I have to actually live up to all of these people that are excited about this
thing.
And I was running out of shows, and I was running out of money.
So I thought, I have to get this thing finished, so I'm going to give myself IGF 2012.
as a deadline for this and then I'm just going to release it.
And then I got nominated again for the technical excellence category.
And this time I'd learned from all of my mistakes from the iGIF.
I'd learned from my mistakes from the PAX 10 as well.
And one of the things I'd noticed at the PAX 10 is that there was a lot of shaky cam footage
of the game because I didn't actually release any new footage of the game after I announced
the name change.
I just released teaser screenshots.
So I thought, alright, I will need good, solid footage that I've made that really shows off
the game for the IGF for PAX East.
And in order to do this, I got help from other people who are experts at doing this.
Kurt Gartner makes a bunch of independent trailers, and Antoine Fortier-Auclair was
someone that I'd met at PAX who is the person who cuts the trailers for Assassin's Creed
at Ubisoft.
And this time when I sent this out to the press, it also came with a call to action.
Come interview me at PAX. Come preview my game at PAX.
Tell your readers that they can come find the game at PAX East.
And I picked a very quiet day to release this thing.
And what happened was this saturated the news.
Because I'd sent it to so many contacts who were now really interested in me,
they all posted about it. And because they were all posting about it,
a whole lot of other news sites just started catching wind of it and posting about it as well.
And then Notch retweeted it. Epic posted about it.
A whole lot of other people with...
with a reach way larger than me,
were also posting about it.
So going into the IGF,
again, no expectations of anything.
I thought Fez was going to win the award for technical excellence,
and then I won the award for technical excellence,
which was an absolute shock.
And...
APPLAUSE
I also signed with the Indy Fund at this stage.
And at this stage I wasn't seeing any issues in the game anymore.
And I also had some really good coverage.
And this wasn't just because the game was better.
This wasn't just because I won.
This was because I had done a hell of a lot more work
in the months leading up to this to try and get all of this attention.
And I responded to this after the show by making statements like this.
My game still isn't done. I feel worse than I've ever felt.
I don't have anything to work towards now. They took away my goal.
This doesn't sound like someone who just received an award they'd been chasing for three years.
This sounds like someone who's having a mental breakdown.
And at this stage, I couldn't quit because that would have been a waste of several years of my life.
And I couldn't release an unfinished game because that definitely wouldn't have lived up
to the expectations that I'd built.
Now, fortunately...
Indie Game, the movie came out and it was very reassuring that other people were going through this as well.
Now I know that this movie got a hell of a lot of criticism because people were like,
making games isn't like that, making games is fun.
I'm watching these people struggle.
And I'm watching this, you know, watching Phil Fish have a terrible PAX East,
I'm thinking I'm showing at PAX East for the first booth that I've actually paid for in three weeks.
By 2012, I knew what I was doing and things just started to snowball.
So I was just trying desperately to finish this game.
And I was starting to become very jealous of all of these other games that were releasing.
And I was thinking, oh, what makes me different?
Obviously, it's that they could finish their games and I couldn't at this stage.
But I was also getting very paranoid about failure
because some of the other people that had been through these festivals
and come up alongside me released their games
and they had very quiet launches and they just went away.
And I thought, how do I make sure that that doesn't happen to me?
So I thought, I have to give myself PAX East,
and PAX Prime will definitely be my last show.
And YouTube streamers were becoming more and more of a big deal
throughout 2011, 2012.
And in the lead-up to PAX Prime,
I see this tweet from TotalBiscuitGoOut that says,
for your information, we're almost booked out of slots for PAX,
so if you want to get your game looked at, contact this PR company.
So straight away I jumped on it.
And I recorded a really good video with TotalBiscuit.
And after we stopped recording, I thought,
this is the best possible marketing material that I could make.
It's the experience that people had at shows,
it's someone playing the game for the first time, giving their impressions,
and then I can step in and keep giving a whole lot of the really interesting...
background information and talk about psychology and puzzle design, etc.
And so I said to him, when are you going to release these videos?
And he said, we're going to release these as a PAX roundup in the weeks after PAX.
And I thought, hmm, that could be a bit of a problem because
my game is still like a couple of months away.
And he's like, no, no, no, don't worry about it.
We'll talk about your game.
again when it releases. And I'm like, okay.
So then I run around the Indie Mega booth where I was showing the game
and I talk with as many developers as I can.
And I'm like, I just made this fantastic video with TotalBiscuit.
And they're like, oh, awesome. The day that he released his video of our game
was one of our biggest spikes in sales.
And I'm like, oh, fuck. This is going to be such a mistake
if this video goes out months before my game is released.
People are just going to forget about it.
So I sent him an email describing all of this, and I said,
my game is so hard to explain, we've just made the best marketing material.
All these other people said this was always their biggest spike in sales.
Can you please hold this until the day that I release?
And he said, we wouldn't normally do it for people,
but we understand your problem.
We agree it was a good video, so we'll hold it off for you.
So this was like, I was then aiming for October.
I'd missed October.
I knew that December was totally out,
because that's when the summer sales were probably going to happen,
and they were a black hole if you're not in them.
So I was like, alright, I have to release in November, I guess,
because this had to come out in 2012.
And so I spoke with my contact at Valve,
and I said, what are good dates in November?
And he said, the week of the 5th, the 14th, and the 28th of November look really good.
And so when I spoke with the Indie Fund about this...
One of them said, well, Halo comes out on the 2nd.
And you know, it's a console game, but you just want to be aware of that.
And so then I looked at the other dates, and the 14th was after Call of Duty,
and Assassin's Creed was right near the 28th.
And I thought, this is also going to be such a problem.
Yes, I'm just some indie game, and I'm not competing directly with those guys,
but I'm ultimately going to be competing.
for media attention. And if I release my game in amongst when everyone else is just talking
about Halo and Call of Duty and Assassin's Creed, I will have spent years and then just
throw it all away at the last minute. And at this stage I did not trust any of my own
decision making, so I just spoke with the Indie Fund and I said, can you please just
tell me what I should do? And this was the feedback I got.
Nathan Vela said, wait until late January or early February.
You'll make more revenue releasing at a good time
than you will lose via the delay.
Ron Carmel said, delaying will also give you time to plan
and execute a launch PR plan.
Alan Isaacson said, you've spent so many years on this,
I think you want to give people some time to get ready for its final release.
And Kelly Santiago said, Journey was on a similar schedule,
and I think we really benefited from the added time to do a proper PR lead-up.
So here was my answer.
This was why I wanted these guys to be invested in the game.
If for nothing else, if not for the funding,
these were very smart people who had been through all of this before,
who could give me feedback like this at a time when I needed it most,
and it was absolutely vital.
So I took all of January 2013 to work on assets, the trailer,
work out the pricing, release dates, et cetera.
And I wanted to leave none of this to chance.
I'm talking with developer friends.
I'm talking with press friends.
I'm talking with QA friends.
Trying to leave nothing about this release to chance.
And I was carefully coordinating release coverage
with as many people.
as I could. I asked a friend from Polygon, I said,
rather than relying on what Valve had said, I asked
a friend from Polygon, I said, can you tell me
when the release calendar is just dead? And he
did this for me because he was a friend and
someone that I knew.
And he said, the middle of January and the end of January
look pretty dead at the moment.
So I thought, this is fantastic.
I wanted to announce two weeks before anyway.
So I'm going to announce in the middle of January, when
nothing else is around.
And then I'm going to release at the end of January.
Which meant that when I announced my release date,
that was able to saturate the news.
And that was all leading up to this.
On the 30th of January, I released my
Antechamber launch trailer.
And I did this a day ahead of time because I thought,
on the launch day, I'm going to have enough other coverage.
I'm probably going to have some YouTube streamers.
I'm going to have the TotalBiscuit video.
I'm going to get all of the, um...
the views and stuff. So I thought, I'll release this a day early just to
start winding up the hype cycle again.
And because that went up, and because my Steam page went up,
Giant Bomb posted their Quick Look video.
And because they posted that, Total Biscuits sent me an email saying,
why is one of my competitors posting a video?
And I'm like, oh, I'm so sorry, like I've messed up.
And he's like, it's not your fault, you're not meant to know that, but...
I'm sorry, I have to release this right now,
if you want to get the views that you deserve.
And this, in hindsight,
ended up being a fantastic decision,
because this was 14 hours before the game released,
and no one could step in at this stage and be like,
you know, I played it, it wasn't very good,
you know, there were going to be critics.
And so that was 14 hours of the YouTube comments going absolutely crazy about this.
And I was sending off keys to everyone. I sent like 40 keys to Mojang.
I sent off keys to Penny Arcade. Just as many people as I could.
And then Notch was posting about it a lot.
And because of all of that, on January 31st, when I finally released,
within the first hour, I was number one.
Within 24 hours, I'd passed 25,000 sales.
I had over 40 reviews from eight and nine.
Some low ones, but I can't control that.
I got lots of high profile.
YouTube coverage and non-stop Twitter discussion all week.
At this stage, the game just was completely out of my hands
and it just absolutely, absolutely ran off.
So let's get to some takeaways.
Number one, none of this happened quickly.
This slide was nine years of decision making,
seven years of work, three years of obsession for one day.
And if you just look at this one day,
or when I won the IGF, or when an announcement was made,
you're missing out on 2,500 other days
that led to this thing.
And I talk about this because all throughout
the development, I would bang on about
luck versus opportunity.
This whole presentation is opportunity,
opportunity, opportunity, opportunity.
And from the outside, people are looking in saying,
very, very lucky.
And the reason I'm talking about this is,
an example is the TotalBiscuit video that goes up.
People look at that and they're like,
oh, you're lucky that, you know, you got that TotalBiscuit video.
And I'm like, what are you talking about?
That was work, you know.
That was three months earlier when I made this video
and when I decided to, you know, get him to hold it off.
And the concession here is that there was a little element of luck here.
I could have been watching TotalBiscuit's tweet stream 24-7.
And if this tweet doesn't go out, absolutely,
the rest of the story, as I've just described, it does not happen.
But here's why that is completely irrelevant.
This tweet is a very insignificant thing,
and these kinds of things, these tweets,
these random conversations that we have with people,
are going by a thousand times a day, every single day.
That tweet went out to 250,000 people.
That's how many followers he had at the time, minus retweets.
Of those 250,000 people, a smaller subset were developers.
A smaller subset were going to PAX.
A smaller subset had something ready to show.
A smaller subset contacted him.
A smaller subset recorded a video.
And a smaller subset recorded a very good video.
And another tweet from TotalBiscuit several months
later said, actually, most of the developer commentary
videos that we record at shows like these are received very,
very negatively because either the developers don't know how
to talk about their game.
or there's shaky cam footage, or people would just rather hear TotalBiscuit talk.
He said, except for the antechamber video and another video.
And it's not luck that I happened to record a good video with TotalBiscuit,
because prior to making that video, I had done nothing other than talk about my game
for three years to work out how to talk about it most effectively.
And the other reason I'm talking about this is because...
Luck and opportunity are talking about exactly the same thing.
Opportunity is future focused.
These things can happen.
Luck is always in hindsight.
These things did happen.
Once something happens, you don't need to continue looking for it again.
which is why I talk about development philosophy so much.
What I did is not actually the important part of the story.
It's why I made all of these decisions,
all of the strategy that went into it,
looking at other successes and trying to analyze
what all of them did so that I could work out
what were the right decisions for my specific game.
And doing this requires brutal self-awareness.
The reason that I was destroying myself doing this
is because I was taking this to the absolute extreme.
I did not care about my health.
All I cared about was this game.
And doing this brutal self-awareness means that you have to constantly question all of
your assumptions and course correct all along the way.
It's not that I didn't make mistakes, it's that I made a thousand mistakes, learned from
all of them, picked myself up and then corrected them before it was too late.
And the other takeaway that I don't talk about much,
that I didn't talk about much at all throughout the development,
is that none of this happened in isolation.
I understand spin, I understand talking with the press,
and so it was a really good story to say,
I'm the guy. Me. Me, me, me, me, me.
All of these decisions, the successes and the failures,
they're all on me.
The reality is, although I would have done around 80-90% of the development,
I absolutely could not have had the success
without the sound design, the composition, the modeling, the illustration,
and all the other people helping me with business acumen, and PR, and strategy, and testing.
Hundreds, if not thousands of other people
were necessary to make this success happen.
I did not make it in a bubble.
And finally, making games is hard.
I don't look at any of this stuff.
I don't look at independent development through rose-colored glasses.
This is honestly the hardest thing that I've ever done.
and it absolutely destroyed me.
And the reason that I wanted to give this talk
is so that people could see that, yes, this is very hard,
and if you're struggling, that's what it takes sometimes.
There's a lot of people who are struggling about this in private.
I don't actually care about my public perception
because my public perception was being open and candid
about all of this stuff the whole time.
So I hope this talk has been inspiring,
and if this all seems like something that you don't want to do,
then I hope I've helped you make that decision as well.
Thank you.
So.
That was process, and I know that a number of you probably don't have main conference
passes.
If any of you do, tomorrow I'm presenting the other half of this, which is what I was
actually doing with the design throughout all of those three years.
So if you do have a main conference pass, you can come and see that tomorrow.
And we're very early, but I needed more than 25 minutes, so thank you.
And if there are any questions, I don't know if we're taking them or going off in the ready
room.
Matt?
I can take some questions?
Cool.
Hey, Alexander.
Hey, Matt.
Hey Alexander, over here to your right.
So you talked an awful lot and it was really awesome
about how your personality and your PR strategy
and your iterations led to the success of your game.
You only talked a little bit about how the nature
of your game itself led to the success of the game.
Is there anything that you would sort of like
in high concept add that like, on that point basically?
Yes, this is what this next talk is about.
There was way too much to talk about today.
I had a lot of people who, like with the luck thing, would be looking at my game
as I'm talking about chasing opportunities, as I'm talking about going through festivals and stuff.
And they'd be like, well yeah, but come on, you just had a good game.
But actually back in 2009, I didn't have a really good game.
A lot of the feedback that I was getting on that version, it worked as a mod.
It worked as a free mod.
And it worked for things like Make Something Unreal.
And it worked for things like Sense of Wonder Knight,
which were looking for these really abstract, unconventional things.
But when I decided to take that and turn it into a standalone thing,
The feedback that I got from absolutely everyone was like,
I'm always lost, there's too many dead ends,
I don't know where to go, puzzles should flash red if I can't do them,
you know, the whole game should be restructured.
And I had people asking this question,
when I'm trying to solve some of this stuff,
they'd be like, yeah, but well, do you want to make something new,
or do you want to make something that can sell?
And I was like, no, I actually want both.
And so by going through things like E3,
and watching people play the game,
I was able to identify all of the issues that were coming up and that were problems,
and then just be spot-fixing them all, and then I'd put it in front of people again,
and I'd watch all of those things. I'd see what they thought was interesting.
I'd remove the parts they thought were uninteresting.
And part of my talk tomorrow is about designing this balance
between making something remarkable and making something commercial.
Ultimately, one of the takeaways there is that the further you decide to go
in the remarkable direction, away from what the industry supports,
the more work you have to do to bring it back and make people understand
why they should care about this thing, which is a lot of work.
But the flip side of that is that it's also a lot of work to start with something
that you think will be commercial because you're attacking a market that already exists.
Now you need to do all of the work of proving why people should care about your game
more than some of these other games that have bigger marketing budgets,
that have executed things better, that have sequels to...
you know, things like that.
And so for me, it made sense to try and just push
in this remarkable direction and then work out
what I had to do there.
And I was doing it.
I brought up examples of Braid and World of Goo and Portal.
And I did that because they were also games
that happened to meet these balance.
And I wanted to understand not just what the games did,
but what led them to making all of those decisions
and do the same thing.
That was great, man. Thanks.
Thank you.
Go ahead.
Was it worth it?
Honestly, for a long time,
the answer to that question was,
I'm not so sure.
I posted about how much of a success this thing was,
and one of the fastest lessons that you learn
is that having a large bank account does absolutely nothing
to solve a lot of your problems,
and in fact it just gives you a hell of a lot more problems.
It affected relationships with a bunch of people.
I was obviously going through some pretty big mental issues
going through all of this,
and then when I'm talking with people,
if I'm not the kind of person that's always...
very candid and honest about my problems
and suddenly my problems revolve around money
then you start getting people being like man I wish I had your problems and I'd be like
really like you want to be completely physically sick and have mental health issues and
be screaming at yourself in the mirror and
you know fuck up your relationship with people I don't know why the hell you would want that
But, you know, the fault isn't on them for that.
Obviously they can't understand these circumstances.
And so, what I decided to do, having gone through all of this,
and having struggled through this,
the answer now is obviously,
it took a long time, but I am now in a much better position.
I am in the position I wanted to be.
be in when I decided to do this.
But now when other people are releasing their games,
or when they do have these big successes,
I'm there day one to try and talk to them
and help them out and say,
this is what the future could be like for you,
so they don't have to go through the same problems I did.
Thanks for all your honesty.
How did...
Me in the middle here.
How did you support yourself financially while doing this?
So I went into this with $17,000 in savings, and I had that, all of this is like five-year
plan stuff.
So when I was working in industry, I was just in, like a junior or an intern, whatever,
and I was on like a $28,000 salary.
Some of that would have gone into tax, and then I would have only spent about a couple of thousand dollars throughout that year,
thinking, I don't need any of this now, and I'm not very materialistic,
so I'm just going to put all of this in the bank, if I happen to need it one day.
So when I needed to go to things like Sense of Wonder Night,
I just had this $17,000 there, that I could use.
And then when I got the money from Make Something Unreal,
that gave me another $25,000, so I could continue extending things out.
And then as I continued going through these competitions,
some of them came with money, but most of them came with, like, free booth space.
So I was never paying for most of my booths around all of this.
And being from Australia, there was also some government grants,
which weren't for, like, outright funding.
There were things like, if you go to an event
and you need to recoup some of your expenses,
you can get a grant that will recoup, like, $2,500.
So, for example, when I went to the PAX 10 in 2011,
I was actually really out of money at that stage.
But going to that, it cost me $2,300 in flights,
and I spent $300 while I was there,
but I stayed with friends.
I always stayed with friends when I was traveling,
because that means I don't have to pay for accommodation,
and I didn't have to pay for my booth,
because it was covered by packs.
which meant that I was able to then go to the government and recoup two and a half thousand dollars
in expenses, which happened to make that whole trip just completely free.
So I was being as frugal as I could.
I was also living at home with parents, which kept my burn rate very low.
And I understand that, you know, not everyone is in that position,
but honestly, funding is one of the most solved problems in independent development.
You can go to publishers, you can get kickstarted.
There is government grants, there is, you know, private, private funding.
There's pre-orders, etc.
If people look at funding and say,
oh, but you just lived with parents,
that was an active decision on my behalf
to stay doing that to keep my burn rate very low.
Thank you much.
Um, so my question is,
uh, you talk about how, um, a lot of the promotion
and, like, meeting people,
you had to go to all these conferences,
um, and festivals and everything.
I wanted to know how you were able to structure
your, uh, development cycle around that
so that it didn't really mess with, um...
you didn't go away for a week and come back and that didn't really disrupt you.
So the thing that festivals were solving is when I was just alone in my bedroom,
that's actually when things were the most difficult.
And every time I went off to a festival, I would be completely refreshed
and I was still working the whole time.
I was networking, I was doing business, I was...
testing the game constantly and that was the most valuable work that I did and it's also
what refreshed my mental state so that then I could come back and work on the problems
that were real problems, you know. After a couple of months you start thinking these
are the most significant problems, I really need to fix these things. You'd go to a festival
and realize actually none of that work matters, no one cares about any of that stuff. And
so it was also making me much more efficient because it stopped me working on things that
just didn't matter in the long run.
I'm not sure if you can talk about them or to the extent you can talk about them,
but from someone who went through a seven-year development cycle and had so many problems
and went through so much, where do you... I'm just curious, where do you go from here?
You know, is it difficult to like think about having another seven-year development cycle,
have another game that, you know, is that difficult? What do you... what's your thoughts now?
This is part of why some of this was problematic.
You know, after releasing this,
a whole lot of people were like,
oh man, what are you going to work on next?
And I'm like, if this is how I feel
after the one that just pulled off absolutely everything,
I don't want to do this again.
You know, fuck that.
And so...
That lost all of my creative drive.
And if I was also doing this for the career drive,
and for like the financial side, and I've just solved that,
I lost all of my financial drive as well.
Which means that you've taken a very driven person
and you've removed any reason for them to have drive.
And honestly, that just took a whole lot of time.
It would have taken eight months
before I started becoming interested in anything again.
And that was something that I couldn't force.
I can't intensely problem-solve
being interested about the world.
I just have to...
I just had to live more existentially day to day
and just find other things that would interest me.
Thank you. You're welcome.
Hey, Alex. I'm Hamish.
My question is, what...
and you might be addressing this tomorrow,
but I feel like I have to know now.
What percentage of your development time
were you spending on this kind of stuff,
on marketing, basically?
On marketing and testing? So I would have gone through...
No, just marketing.
they were kind of the same.
Like, going to events was testing as well.
So, on marketing and stuff.
So, it was primarily through events.
So, I went through like 15 to 20 events
before I'd released the game.
And that, those things are only very short bursts.
Maybe they're three days, maybe they're a week.
And then between all of those, I was just straight back on the development.
And as I was submitting builds to festivals,
then I would have to do a little bit more work,
then, on, like, information about the game,
and I'd have to be sending out press releases and stuff.
But those were all, like, you know, days here and there.
And most of them were just talking with people
that I'd already met around the place.
You know, some, like, I had a lot of,
I met a lot of people in the press.
And so I could just have a lot of candid conversations
off the record on things like Facebook.
with those people to work out what I was doing.
And so it was then much faster to work out
what kinds of assets I need.
And taking things like Rami's, you know, doPressKit,
I don't have to work out what a good press kit looks like.
I just take that and, you know, fill that out.
So it was a long time
because of all of the investment into festivals,
but most of the development while I was at home
was just pure development.
Thanks very much. And by the way,
your game was really, really good in 2009.
Thank you.
That's it. Thank you guys.