All right, so welcome everyone.
Thank you for joining us today here in person.
Oh my goodness.
I'm Nicole Minka, the recruiting manager at Crystal Dynamics
and I'm gonna be your moderator for the panel today.
So welcome to our panel, Tips from the Trenches.
In this panel, we will be talking about hiring
in the gaming industry.
So there's hundreds of job openings
in the gaming industry right now
and there's a lot that goes on behind the scenes.
We'll be looking at this from a few different sides.
Those who are looking to get into games,
those who are looking to make a shift, maybe from one studio to another,
or different types of industries,
and then tips for hiring for your own team if you're a hiring manager.
So how I want to start this off is just
kind of getting a feel for who's out there in the room at the moment.
So how many people here are already employed
at a game development studio, AR, VR?
Okay, perfect.
And then keep or re raise your hands if you are somebody that has helped interview on
your team.
Have you been that person before?
All right.
And then keep your hands up if you're the hiring manager, like the one calling the shots,
making decisions.
Okay.
And is there anybody here that's looking to break into the industry or students?
All right.
And
This is for both hiring managers and for those who are looking for work.
Have you ever partnered with a recruiter on either side to help you in that search?
Either for a person or for yourself?
Not one.
Okay.
Just a few.
So.
Now we'll move on to our panel.
So we have a mix of internal recruiters,
agency recruiters, and hiring managers.
So the recruiters play a critical role
in building the teams of successful studios
as do the hiring managers that they partner with
to build those strong teams.
So what does that entail?
What happens when a job gets posted as a hiring manager?
How do you get strong applicants?
How do you, as an applicant,
make sure that your resume stands out from the bunch?
So maybe you've got interviews,
we'll touch a bit on that.
How do you make sure that those run smoothly?
And then maybe it's time to make an offer.
What do you need to know so that things
don't fall apart at the end?
So hear what it is from people in the trenches,
and we will kick things off with our panelists.
So first up, we have Nellie Hughes,
who is the Design Director at Xbox Game Studios Publishing.
Nellie, can you tell us a bit about yourself?
Sure, I'm a 17-year game design veteran who's done all types of design, including game design,
design leadership, and design management.
Along that road, I've done lots of departmental hiring.
I'm here today because one of my loves is just to help folks break into the industry
and help folks who are experienced get the jobs that they're going for.
Awesome. It is nice to have you here, Nelly.
Thank you.
Next, we have Alejandro Rodriguez down at the end,
who is a principal recruiter at Probably Monsters.
Alejandro?
Thank you. My name is Alejandro Rodriguez,
and I'm the recruiter supporting Probably Monsters
and the Plethora Studios within our org.
It is my goal to support an encouraging environment
that is inclusive, professional, and respectful to all within.
Before, Probably Monsters used to be a re-init,
343, Google Mobile, WB for a bit.
Yeah.
Alright, thank you Alejandro. And before I move on to the next two panelists, I want to point out
that Nelly Alejandro and myself work internally at Game Development Studios.
The following panelists are from an agency, so they support studios externally. So Iris
Moon, I'm going to have you introduce yourself, but can you also tell us a little bit about what that means?
Sure. First of all, it's great to see everybody back in person.
Thanks for coming to our panel.
I'm Iris Moon. I'm the managing director at GGLocators.
If you haven't heard of us or you haven't heard from me on LinkedIn,
we're a boutique staffing firm and we specialize in recruitment
for the video game industry.
We, unlike Nicole, Nelly and Alejandro, we don't work for one studio.
We partner with multiple studios.
across this industry to help them fill all types of roles within the gaming industry.
We, part of the reason a studio would reach out to us is, you know, there's multiple reasons,
but some of the main ones are maybe they don't have an internal recruiting firm or an internal
recruiting team. They might not have the capacity, if they do have an internal team, to fill all the
roles that are on their plate, especially in the current market.
or they might be ramping up to grow the studio excessively.
And so they'll reach out to us and we will form a partnership and help them fill jobs.
Awesome. And last but certainly not least, we have Cami, who is a recruiter at GG Locators,
but has also worked at a few gaming colleges in the past.
Yeah, thanks, Nicole. Yeah, it's really great to see you guys in person. You have no idea.
So yes, I work at Gigi Locators, but I have spent 12 plus years, 15 years, I've lost track now,
working at colleges like Full Sail, working in the career track,
helping, you know, helping coach students with resumes, portfolios, soft skills,
whatever it takes to prepare them to get into the industry.
but also my job was to build relationships with the industry so they would look to me
or our school when they're looking to hire.
So relationships are really critical.
I've probably helped, I don't know, thousands of grads get launched in their first jobs,
but what's really cool is now those grads, since you heard me say 12 to 15 years,
those grads now own their own studios or their leadership at Snapchat or whatever.
So it's like having your children grow up and I'm working with a lot of them now at Gigi Locators.
All right, so what happens first?
First comes, there's a job opening.
So studio realizes that they need to hire.
Now what happens?
Nellie, can you tell us from your perspective?
Sure, so the first thing that I do
is I work with the leads to get to know
the role extremely well.
I need to...
just like buckle down and understand exactly what the short term and the long term goals
are.
And then I write a job description.
And in the job description, I have to get really detailed and just kind of get down
to the nitty gritty to just, you know, do that.
Sorry.
And then once I'm done with that, I hand it off to these guys and, you know, let them
kind of take over.
So on that note, Alejandro, pass it off to a recruiter.
We take your ball.
Once the team puts in a request, the hiring manager as well, for a job opening, the recruiter meets with the hiring manager to determine the needs of the studio and create a sourcing strategy to best build this opening.
And on our side, we don't always get the ball thrown at us.
Sometimes we have to go out and find the ball.
But once we connect with a studio on an opening,
we'll have an initial call, talk to them about their needs,
find out what they're looking for in terms of the role,
in terms of candidate, a good culture fit for the studio.
And then we'll typically request to hop on with the hiring manager.
That way we can really dig in and know who we're going
to be submitting candidates directly to.
And have that relationship going.
And then we get out there and start looking.
Awesome.
And I know we had a few hiring managers in the crowd as well.
So I'm curious to know what sort of things are the hiring managers telling you
and getting you as a recruiter set up for success?
So Alejandro?
First and foremost, really, is just have a good intake meeting, right?
At the beginning of the process.
Really work together to have an effective recruiting strategy.
A recruiter really is a force multiplier to you.
And so really it's just work together in tandem to understand what it is.
And so the hiring managers have a clear expectation for the studio's hiring needs.
And work to have keywords or anything that will help them on their search on LinkedIn
or any sourcing they can have.
I always like to make sure I nail down very specifically.
I like to, when I talk to our clients or the hiring managers,
you know, give me your top three skills
that you must see with a candidate
that we're presenting to them.
I always like to have examples. I'm very visual, so if they can send me
a portfolio from their team so I can get an idea of the style
or a video that I can really focus on, that way I can
narrow the aperture when it comes to helping them,
helping us find them the type of candidate they want.
Yeah, and I'll just add one last thing.
It's always really helpful if you're a hiring manager in the audience for external recruiters,
if you can somehow be involved in the process, that way we can connect directly with you
and really learn what you're looking for and be able to get you the right people faster.
And so, as you can hear, it's really important for the recruiters to understand the...
pieces of the role and the job descriptions so that they can help attract the right candidates,
get the job descriptions out there so that people can apply.
And then as they apply, they're talking to these candidates, like yourselves, and we're
hearing a lot about what's going on in the industry right now from candidates.
So some of you might relate to a lot of these things, but what do you all think are some
of the things that you've heard candidates are looking for?
You know, since COVID, a lot of it is work from home or a hybrid work situation.
You need to, you know, a lot of people are moving away from the typical tech, you know,
locations.
You know, comp is another one.
There are some companies out there that are basically taking a dump truck full of cash
and kind of backing up and dumping it on people.
So those are really the two biggest ones that I'm hearing right now.
Yeah, for us, remote is huge after COVID.
The last two years, most people have gotten comfortable working from home.
Most people can do their jobs from home.
So a lot of people are currently looking for that.
And then creative flexibility is another one.
Growth opportunity is something we see a lot.
We also definitely in this industry, work life balance is huge.
no more crunch. I don't think I think most studios aren't doing it anymore. So, you know,
people are excited about that. But each candidate is very unique. So I usually try to do my,
my thinking, like listening to them, what's their motivating factor? Is it compensation?
Is it working remote? Or are the growth expectations of that studio? You know,
what what's their order of priority?
and honestly, really a respectful and inclusive environment.
So, you mentioned inclusivity and I just was curious if you could tell us all a little bit more about that.
Well, yes.
Well, honestly, game studios are making games for diverse markets
and in order for them to make games
in order for them to make games that resonate within those markets
they really should themselves reflect that diversity within the team compositions.
So all of this happens before the job's even posted out
on a website.
So the hiring managers try to make it straightforward for us
so that we can put that out there.
And if they've got a job description already made,
that makes things a little bit easier for us
so that we can formulate that job description
and get it out to you all.
But maybe it's something that the team hasn't hired before,
or maybe it's a new role or something
that they haven't hired for in a long time.
So there's a lot that goes on behind the scenes
to make sure that what we're putting out there to you all
is.
in line with what the team is actually looking for.
So I just want to touch a little bit more on how hiring managers and recruiters
partner together to make sure that those job descriptions are out there and accurate.
So, Nellie, what do you all do with your team?
Lots of communication.
You know, we spend a lot of time with recruiters
and going over in great detail about what the job itself is,
what the goals and the needs are for the role.
And, you know, we need to be available as much as possible
because, you know, we need to just be nimble.
Right now, the job market is really, really hot.
And if you can't be there to answer those questions,
that candidate may get away.
Well said.
Honestly, really, it's fine. Previous examples of these jobs clearly determine the specific
needs of the team. For example, do you need to know Unreal? Do you have other expectations
for C++? But honestly, what are the quantifiables? And let these job descriptions be as concise
as they can be.
And hiring managers don't always have job descriptions
from previous roles, so part of what we will do
is help you write up that job description and get it posted.
And I'm a visual person.
I like to see examples of the artwork, the style.
I mentioned that before.
And really listen to what the hiring team or studio
is specifically looking for in their next candidate.
A lot of listening is important.
Awesome, and I'm gonna poll the audience again really quick.
So once the job's out there,
you see the job description on there,
I'm curious to know where you all are applying.
Are you going directly to the company's website
and applying on their sites?
If you are, raise your hand for that.
All right, what about if you're using,
are you using anything like Indeed?
Okay, or any other, for your set monster.
How many of you are on LinkedIn keeping that updated
and you're using that for networking to find jobs?
All right.
What about something like ArtStation,
for those of you who might be artists using that?
Cool.
And then anywhere else, maybe like a Discord
or a forum, Reddit?
Cool.
Is there anything that I haven't mentioned yet
that people have done other than events
that we haven't done in three years?
I...
Google.
Okay.
Yeah.
Google.
Thank you.
Oh, yeah.
Alright, so now that I just mentioned a whole bunch of them that once it's created and it's posted,
is there anywhere else? Alejandro, I mentioned a lot of ones that you posted,
but anywhere else you can think of? Well, honestly, us as a company,
we post our roles on the Career site, on Indeed, LinkedIn, ArtStation, but really we go into
Discord, into forums. Honestly, wherever you are at, we're going to get there eventually.
Right. We share our jobs out on socials. I'm a social media nerd. I have specific groups
that I've, since my early days at Full Sail, on Facebook. There's a lot of great Facebook
things going on.
Also, of course, on Twitter and Discord.
I have a lot of grads and friends that I reach out directly to and see if they can give me
any ideas or contacts that they might share with me for the job.
Yeah, friends, relationships.
Yep.
Usually, you know, I end up hitting my network and my team usually does the same thing.
Oh, yeah.
So definitely a lot of places where we're posting a job,
but I know Cammie mentioned outreach,
and you're obviously talking to some recruiters here too,
so we're doing the outreach
and reaching out to candidates as well.
So are you all finding better candidates from postings?
Are you finding them somewhere else?
We are classic headhunters.
We'll go out there and find the right person for the job.
We do look at our station.
We look at a lot of portfolios,
a lot of candidate background,
skill sets, technical skill sets.
Then another great thing about this industry is it
is really intimate in a lot of ways.
So we've been around for three years now,
so we've built a lot of relationships,
and just a lot of referrals come through our door.
From people we've either worked with,
or placed, or...
even clients we've worked with.
So I really want to underline LinkedIn.
LinkedIn has a great AI.
So just to give you an example, we put all our words in for skills in the filter.
It spits out to us, you know, a list of candidates all over the country or wherever we filtered
it down to.
But here's my favorite part.
I go to bed at night.
LinkedIn's AI is still working.
So when I get up in the morning,
LinkedIn has populated another 40, 50 people
in my search section.
So honestly, I can't emphasize enough
how important your LinkedIn profile,
if you're seeing a job,
make sure you weave those words into your profile
and just keep it active.
It doesn't mean you have to post a lot of stuff.
It just means keep your own profile active.
Well said, Canon.
Honestly, we find our best candidates within the industry communities, discord and social media.
You.
Yeah, so.
Get yourself out there, network, make sure things are updated.
And like they all said, the SEO on LinkedIn, that's where they're finding some of your
profiles is through those keyword searches.
So, all right, we're going to move on to when we identify a candidate.
So we're going to dive a little bit deeper into the channels that we use for finding
talent. But before we do,
I have one last thing about those job postings.
So, say a hiring manager, some of you may be out here,
who don't have a recruiter, you don't have an HR team,
what are some things that you can do to get more applicants
other than, you know, networking with this group?
Well, you know, I'm gonna beat the drum of LinkedIn,
get a LinkedIn Pro, you know, account.
But I just, it's a job within itself,
so you really kinda need to count that into your schedule.
So, you know, I think I'm just really gonna,
you know, stress that, because you, it's a lot of work.
But, you know, just user network and word of mouth
is a lot of it, and just make sure to,
continue to, you know, just get it out there.
I mean, naturally, I'm going to say call GD locators.
Yeah, we work with studios big and small.
I mean, the small studios, I always have a soft spot in my heart because I know how much
energy it takes to source and pre-interview people.
So if there's only one person at that studio, you have to be so, you want to swoop in and
help them out, right?
But we work with big studios too, and their hiring numbers are so huge that even their
most coordinated teams can't keep up.
So it's always great to be a recruiter like us.
So as a candidate, you might be thinking,
hey, what, the market's so hot,
all these people are hiring, I applied, I never heard back.
If there's so few applicants
and you guys are having to do all this outreach,
how come nobody's answering me?
So do you all have any advice for the applicants
to make sure that their applications
are getting noticed when they apply?
to quote our talented director of recruitment,
make sure your resume looks like a job description.
Tailor your resume to create trust within the hiring manager
by aligning your experience
with exactly what they're looking for.
Make sure they don't have to jump and make leaps of trust
where you don't understand what you do.
Use the keywords in the job description itself
in your resume.
Most resumes are first also filtered by an ATS, an AI,
that really uses those keywords to filter them out
and allow me to see them first.
I always, you know, I've worked with a lot of students and grads and I'm really a big
advocate for making your resume very easy for the hiring managers.
They're getting, they may get a hundred to a thousand resumes, they don't have time to
read everything.
Make it very clear. Don't give a long objective. They don't give a rip what your objective is,
right? They're there because they need to get their team up and running. So don't care about
that stuff. Use bullet points. You want them to be able to skim that resume really quickly,
and you want them to be able to see your skills.
Honestly, there's a lot of stuff that doesn't get read in a resume, so make the most important
stuff easy with live links.
Make sure your live links work before you send that resume in.
I've had a lot of resumes where I've tested a live link and it's taken, and I know that
person has a great live link, but it doesn't work.
So every single time, make sure those live links are working.
Make it stupid easy for recruiters to help you.
And I'd like to go off of a little bit of what they said to applicant tracking system.
Make sure that there's not a bunch of crazy graphics on your resume because when it uploads,
it's going to totally make it wonky if there's too much stuff on there.
So keep it simple.
And then also...
If you are matching things to the job description, you want to be like, yes, I checked these boxes,
but also make sure that you can speak to the experience that you have, because hiring managers
are going to dig into that. And they're going to make sure that if you're saying, yes, I've done
this required skill, that you actually can do it and speak to it. So align it, but make sure that
it's also staying truthful and accurate. So what about job descriptions that require portfolios?
We'll go to the design director on this one.
Alright, well, you know, I guess I'm going to start kind of general and then hone in.
So, you know, make sure that your portfolio looks like you put effort into it.
You know, flashy sites and elaborate portfolios don't mean much if, you know, it doesn't have
the content that is good.
Put your best stuff in there and only your best stuff.
You know, I got to stop saying I'm sorry.
Take the old stuff out as you grow.
Keep it up to date.
Show versatility.
If you're not sure if your best stuff is, ask others.
Get feedback all the time, you know.
Curate that shit.
Sorry, I swore.
Be picky.
So we're going to be picky, so you should be well.
You should be as well.
Keep it super friendly.
keep the career track that you are going for.
So some of the things that I've seen,
especially with people who are kind of starting out
in the industry, is there's like a smorgasbord
of things in there.
You've got design work, you've got art stuff,
and I think if you're trying to go for a couple
of different tracks, that you should make
a different portfolio for each track you're going for,
or decide maybe what track you are going for
and focus on that.
Oh my gosh, I got lost.
Anyways, yeah, that's where I was going.
That was really well said, Nellie. Thank you for that.
Yes.
To continue, make sure your art aligns to the work of the studio you want to be hired at.
Your portfolio should honestly look like you've already done the work that you're...
I'm sorry, you've already done the job that you're applying to do.
You know, and to kind of hone in a little bit,
if you're an artist, one of my artist managers
basically said, avoid the T&A.
Fine art nudes are great, you know, drawing one thing,
but exploitive of creepy anime is another,
and kind of just don't do that.
In design, show your thought process.
You know, I want to see how you have solved problems.
You know, write examples, post mortems,
on all of your examples that you're showing
of, you know, your game design stuff.
And it's really important to just make sure
that you have quality, not quantity.
Just make sure that's, make that your mantra, quality not quantity.
Absolutely.
And I know some people might be wondering, well, like, how do I, how do I make my portfolio look?
How do I know what it's supposed to look like?
So Alejandro, I know you touched on that a little bit, but are, there should be people that they
can look at that work on these games or the games themselves, right?
Like, can you, can you elaborate a little bit more on, on how they can find what they're supposed to be?
Absolutely. I mean, it'll be very simple. Just go on LinkedIn and see who is working in the studio
you want to work at. Like see those artists that you really want to emulate or beat and
look at their work and just if you may reach out to them for advice or if you're not look on go on Discord or
forums and
and just get the advice from there too.
But honestly your work should be able to be at that caliber of those artists you aspire to be.
And
So we talked a little bit about you all looking for jobs and making sure that your portfolio
matches the roles that you're looking for, your skill sets match what you're looking for.
But from a hiring manager perspective, I'm curious too, is there anywhere that you all can recommend
that a hiring manager can look for talent? Maybe if they're not working with a recruiter,
how can they find some people too?
See, we've done that.
No, you want to jump into?
You want to jump in?
Oh.
see I'm just like oops you know you can have your team help you out you know I think everywhere
that I've ever worked all of my teams have been really excited about where they work so they've
kind of just continued to pass on all the job openings to their friends they linked in again
sorry and places like Facebook and everywhere else that you know they can kind of just spread the
word and you know you
I've never asked them to, it's just something that if you're excited about where you work,
that's kind of, you know, you want your friends and other people to work with you.
Yeah, I mean, I've already said some of these. There's some great, I know not all this generation,
you guys that are here now are on Facebook, but there's some great diversity game Facebook pages
that I really rely on. Of course, Discord groups for sure. Twitter, we were working with an eSports
company and I had to really source a lot on Twitter, because that's where they were. We
try to go to where they are and dig deep in that space.
And I know it sounds like we've touched on that a couple times too, is that a lot of
the places that we're reaching out to or we're looking for people, it's like they're already
in games, they're already working games.
So is there anything that you can suggest to people that aren't in the industry yet?
What if they're just starting out in their search?
I would say go to events, go to game jams, career fairs, find a mentor.
You know, this helps you in a few ways.
It helps you network, it gets you new portfolio pieces, it helps you practice interviewing
skills and it helps you build relationships.
Relationships are key, right?
For everything you'll ever do, right?
So I always say show up to any game events.
If you don't have any in the town you're in,
start a game meetup.
There's a lot of people who probably would appreciate that.
If you're an introvert, that's really your superpower because you can really focus on
what you're doing.
But when you go to any of these meetups or game jams, I always say, you know, come prepared
with maybe in your head three questions that you can be ready to ask at any time.
Because if you're in a situation where you don't know who's sitting next to you, you
can come up with like, oh, what game are you working on?
or, you know, what, are you using Unity or Unreal, you know, just get the conversation started.
And a lot of times that's a relief for everybody in the room or anybody you're next to talking.
I also like to go to, you know, to events and kind of force myself and go,
okay, here are my three questions I'm going to ask.
you know, just to have in my back pocket.
But also I'm gonna give myself,
I'm gonna meet six people before I leave this thing tonight.
So I kind of, I'm competitive with myself
and try to come up with the six people I've met at that.
that event. That's awesome advice, even at any level, I think.
Yeah, definitely. So next I want to touch on the interview process.
So what's it like when, you know, there's a match, there's a job you get,
the recruiter wants to have a call.
What is it like when you're ready to start the interview process?
So how does it start off?
Absolutely. Internally, it really is recruiting first.
We do the whole verbal checkbox, the actual human being.
And then from there, the hiring manager.
And then if that goes well, then we go into a panel interview,
which will be a full interview, mostly five hours, depending on the studio.
And then from there, it'll be a hire and no hire decision.
Yeah, and Alejandro mentioned the five hour interview.
That's after four other interviews, usually,
in this industry.
So we like to try to be as thorough as possible
in our pre-screen, our initial conversation with candidates,
so that we can at least skip one step when submitting
to our client and get the process moving a little more
quickly.
And if the client wants to set up the interview, which happens every day, we like to prep our
candidates beforehand.
We go through a list of questions.
Even the most seasoned developers or whatever, it just really helps ease the interview process.
I don't care how smart you are, in the interview process your brain freezes.
That's just human.
So it's always good to practice and we try to do that.
And then afterwards we...
have a debrief so we can keep, you know, kind of hear what they're thinking,
if they have new ideas or, you know, questions about that company they just interviewed.
Yeah, we just kind of make sure we're aligning the whole process every step of the way.
I think that brings up a good point.
What can the candidate do to prepare for the interview?
So it sounds like some people do some preps.
I'm curious what else could be suggested to a candidate
to make sure that the interview goes smoothly.
And are there any sort of things
that hiring managers are looking for?
Absolutely. I mean, before anything, Kami, that's really well said.
Honestly, as you as an interviewer, it's like much like public speaking. So
practice and hone in your interview key talking points. You should be able to succinctly answer
your questions through your experience. Practice explaining the challenges you've had, right?
And how your company or how you as a person have grown into something better after that.
You know, find out as much as you can about the role.
I've had a couple people who have just shown up
to the interview and not even really known
what they were there for, and that's an instant downer.
So, you know, just absolutely do your research.
Yep, and I'll say just some of the things I thought were obvious, but maybe not.
Everything's been on video for the last couple of years, so look professional, don't vape,
don't eat.
Believe me, these things have happened, so yeah, just make sure you show up like you
would to an in-person interview.
So there's a couple other things, besides the obvious things, do your research on the
company itself, understand the culture, understand the project or the company's product, know
the games, play the games, do your research on the interviewers that you're going to be
talking to, go to LinkedIn, again, LinkedIn, sorry, we're definitely plugging them today.
Have excitement for the role.
Be there, be jazzed, pay full attention, turn off discord, turn off your phone,
you know, slack, everything. Definitely be yourself.
You know, just you're going to be working with these people for 40 hours a week.
So, you know, you want you want to be your genuine self.
And there's also additional things.
Speak to your experiences in general.
Wrap your answers up in a past story if you can.
This helps see the context of something you've done personally
and allows us to dig deeper if we want details.
And play up your successes.
This is really important.
You have done awesome things, and you should be proud of that.
So just brag about it.
What this does is help me look for character traits
and competencies.
So just for an example, did you build a custom engine
just because?
This shows me that you've got a growth mindset,
that you're driven, that you're curious.
Do you work with artists, engineers, and producers?
This shows me that you can cross communicate
and you can work in groups.
It's not just can you do the job that we're hiring for,
but how can you compliment and add
to the studio's team and value?
Oops.
Yeah, adding value, that one's huge.
So I always suggest that people write things down the night before,
because bringing things back from their long term memory can be really hard.
So if you prepare for it, then you'll have all of those top of mind
when you go into the interview.
And also, one other thing I want to add is ask questions, be curious.
So at the end, you never want to go, do you have any questions for me?
And then you're like, no.
And then that's it.
prepare some questions before as well.
So that's super important.
I can't stress how much you need to ask questions.
Yes.
And so I want to bring up testing.
Tests can be a reality in the industry.
Some studios do them, some studios don't.
So this is actually geared more towards hiring managers.
So what advice do you have for hiring managers
that come to you and say,
hey, I wanna give a test for this role?
I would actually ask that you think about if you really need to test at all, because
many companies are ditching them and a lot of candidates won't take them anymore.
And you know, if you really feel that you do need to give them, you need to let recruiters
and candidates know that you're going to give a test right away because it's, you know,
it's just a waste of your time if you get through a phone screen and they just won't
test it and they won't take it and you've just wasted both parties' times.
And so what if a test is part of the process?
How should a candidate prepare if they have to take one?
Well, I think that, you know, the best way to do that is to understand the product that they make
and understand, again, the position that you're going for very well.
Do the research on the position because you may be able to, you know, combine the two
and it would help you give you an advantage possibly.
I'd like to follow up with that.
Ask questions, again.
If you're taking a test and you don't know,
lawyers don't know, ask questions.
If they can't answer it, then they can't answer it for you.
And if they can, then you've got an answer to the question.
So be curious.
Can I just jump in there?
You should never be afraid to ask a hiring manager
and or a recruiter a question,
because that's just really good.
Don't be, yeah, just don't be afraid.
It shows that you're interested in the job.
Absolutely. Really well said.
All right, so candidates interviewed, they've taken the test, the team is deliberating on next
steps. Maybe they're talking to a couple other candidates as well about the same role. So how
do you all make sure that a candidate has a good experience as they interview? What are some things
that you all do personally for candidate experience? A lot of communication, give a 48
hour turnaround time on a decision if they're the only candidate.
If they're not the only candidate, it comes down to transparency.
Let them know.
You don't want to basically dangle a carrot and, you know, let's just not
communicate with them.
It's really disrespectful for you to, you know, just for people's time, for
them not to have it.
And as Nellie already mentioned, communication is key.
Just keeping candidates in the loop.
We will not ghost you.
We'll make sure that we're following up regularly.
If we haven't heard from a studio,
we'll let you know we haven't heard
and that we'll have feedback as soon as we do here.
We will share it with you.
And if we end up hearing from the client
after you've interviewed and the interview didn't go
as well as you'd hoped, we will still let you know.
And we'll keep moving forward,
keep pushing for the next opportunity.
So that brings me to the awkward piece that none of us like,
is what do we have to do when we have to reject the candidate?
Either skill set didn't align or just, I guess,
how do you reject a candidate?
Is there anything that can be done to make sure
that that's a constructive learning experience
as opposed to a generic email?
You know, I always collect feedback after an interview from the people that have interviewed
them and I curate it and I send it to the recruiter and it depends if the person wants
feedback or not.
If they do, I'm always willing to give it to them.
I as a recruiter really appreciate what you just said.
It is really important for people to be able to interview
and grow from their experiences.
Normally, most companies can never really send you
a spoiler-free email saying,
hey, it didn't work out this time,
I want another candidate.
But I ask you, every time you receive one of those emails,
go back and ask, hey, is there any feedback we can have?
And normally, we're asking to go on the phone with them.
Normally, we can talk to you about the experience,
and over the phone we can share with you what we can.
All right, so the flip side of that.
Interviews go really well, you're gonna get an offer.
So, woo!
But before we dig into that,
I think it's important to talk a little bit more
about what the market's like right now.
So, Cammie, can you tell us a little bit
about what you're seeing?
Yeah, the market is hot.
It's really active.
It's almost exhausting.
Studios have a lot of hires across the board.
We're seeing that all over.
But when we work with studios, when
we sign up working with the studio,
we really emphasize that they're ready to make the offer quickly.
If they interview someone and they wait for weeks
to come back with an offer, they're
going to lose the candidate.
Candidates don't have to wait anymore.
If you're a tech artist, you can blink and someone will want to hire you,
but you can probably have two or three offers by the end of a week.
So if the first studio is taking its time, maybe they want to do another test,
they're going to lose out.
Yeah, and candidates are getting higher offers than we've seen, especially with, you know,
multiple years of industry experience.
So be adaptable.
Like I mentioned earlier, remote work is huge.
If a studio is able to accommodate that, you know, some people are willing to take a little
little less on their base salary to get that other perk.
And obviously that's from the agency side.
So I'm curious for those that are internal, what sort of things are you seeing?
you know, people are getting the asks that they want.
We have to be really flexible
and we have to be willing to work with them
when it comes to work situations and salary asks, you know.
Very much so.
COVID has really changed the market.
There is a lot more power to determine where we work from.
It's really shifted the landscape in our end.
Yeah, so it sounds like we have to...
We have to move fast on Canvas, and so if you're not getting the responses, feel free to follow up with your job postings.
Be curious, ask questions.
We touched on flexibility.
What are some things that you all do to make sure that things do keep moving along quickly?
Well, after an interview, you know, I try to make sure that I have a follow-up meeting
with the entire interview circuit the day after to get that feedback from them.
I work with the recruiter instantly after that to try to give them an answer within,
you know, a day.
24 hours is almost my personal limit.
Within two days is almost too much.
And then, you know, we move from there.
Exactly as it should be.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
As a recruiter, thank you so much.
Oh no, you're fine.
Thank you.
Good candidate experience is key.
Good candidate experience is pretty much a metric for us.
It's how we judge what a good studio or good recruiting experience is.
And so, yeah, for us it's really important to get back to you as soon as possible.
And it's a goal of ours to make sure you have a good candidate experience.
And I know I touched on being curious and following up,
but is there anything else that you all can recommend that a candidate do to help move things along?
Yeah, yes, if we're working with you and we're, you know, by the time this process is over,
we've gotten to know each other pretty well, because we've connected over the course of
those four to five interviews before and after every call. If you are interviewing multiple
places at one time, just keeping us in the loop as recruiters, letting us know if you're getting
close to an offer, what your top choice studio looks like, and that way we can push on our side
to get things moving faster in the process.
and just being transparent.
Transparency is key.
All right, so on that note, I said that we're moving to the offer phase.
You touched on transparency.
So let's talk money.
What does everybody need to know when it comes to making an offer?
Iris, you want to kick that one off?
Our goal is to have no surprises by the time we get to the offer.
The first time I talk to you, if you're my candidate, we are going to talk money.
We're going to ask what you're looking for.
where you, we can't legally ask where you are currently.
Some people volunteer that information.
But you know, we ask what you're looking for.
If it's completely out of left field,
they'll be like, that's not really what we're seeing
in the market.
Most people know where they're at
and what they need to take a little step up.
So, you know, it's important not to go way out of range.
but also not to, you know, undersell yourself. Make sure you're asking for what you're worth
in the market. And, you know, every step of the way, we're going to talk about this money. Every
time I, every time I prep you for an interview, every time I debrief you for an interview,
I'm going to ask and make sure, hey, this is the compensation we discuss. And then I'm going to
you know, reiterating that to the client. That way when we do get to the offer, there are no
surprises. It's the offer you were asking for, the client knew from the beginning, you knew,
and hopefully it's a done deal and everyone can celebrate the win.
Definitely important to celebrate and every studio is going to be a little bit different,
but the resounding be curious, ask questions, transparency.
Anyone else, any other things that we want to touch on on that piece?
Definitely, I agree with you. Starting the conversation in the beginning,
a lot of these negotiations or just being able to develop a good offer package takes a while.
It's not like we can just flip it over and switch. Really, definitely do your research on your end.
Every state has different laws for when it when asking for compensation.
I recommend you looking at those. California has a million good ones.
Honestly, us recruiters, we can't really ask you, what are you making right now?
So really, we're going to be asking you is what is your target?
What are you hoping to achieve out of this?
And I know another part of compensation is benefits.
So does anyone want to talk a little bit about how those can play a factor?
Yeah, well, maybe the, you know, what...
401k? Is it matching? What health benefits? Is it pay your
spouse? Is there relocation money? Is there a signing
bonus? What are the what is the bonus structure like annually
across that? Some studio, I mean, some startups are going
to offer stock options. Lately, I've been seeing NF T's be part
of the package. You just have to know what your motivating factor
is, be real clear and, and communicate that to
whoever you're working with.
And then we always get a couple of questions after everything's said and
done, the offers out, signed, everybody's good and ready to go.
They got their start date.
There are some common questions like, like PTO and I've got this wedding coming up
and I only accrue it at this rate.
How do I take the time off?
So that's when I get a lot.
Do you want to touch on that one?
Like what's the.
Just ask.
Just, you know, it's okay and nobody's going to be mad.
Just be upfront about what you need off before you get the job.
Nobody's going to be mad.
Just ask and be transparent.
Same things have happened with holidays,
like they're not fully written out in the benefits package,
but you can always ask like what holidays do I get?
And we can send you those kind of lists.
All right.
So we've got about 10 minutes left.
I am going to wrap this up with final words for those who
are looking in their job search.
If anyone has questions after this,
we welcome you to come up here and ask us.
So feel free, we'll all be up here.
And you can come up and.
Be curious and ask whatever you'd like.
But so, final parting words for those
who are starting their search.
Any practical advice that you'd like to share
with the group before we wrap up?
I'll just say, don't beat yourself up.
It's a tough industry to break into.
But there are a lot of resources out there.
Find a mentor, connect with us.
Maybe we can connect you with a mentor.
And just keep trying.
You'll land somewhere eventually.
The industry needs you.
Yeah, keep building that, working on that portfolio, keep doing game jams.
A lot of times companies will go, we want to see what they're doing outside of their...
work, you know, they want to know that you're still really obsessed with making games, right?
But also take advantage of, if you went to college or, you know, wherever you went,
go to LinkedIn. They have that alumni button on that college website and you can click it,
click on the alumni and filter it out to see who might be in the industry that you might reach out
to.
They may not respond, but you never know.
It's a way to say,
hey, would you mind taking a half hour
to just give me some feedback on my resume
or my portfolio or my Git, whatever.
But build those relationships up.
Well said.
It is a marathon, not a sprint.
Make sure that you keep yourself fed, motivated, and make sure to improve yourself.
From my experience, it takes people about two to three years after school to be able
to ramp themselves up to a place where I can hire them.
Schools are really there to make sure you know the foundation of what you're getting
into, but it's going to be up to you to put yourself in a position where someone like
me can say, yeah, please bring this person over here.
And I would say, you know, just continue to network, hone your craft.
I mean, everything that these folks said is absolutely true.
And, you know, just be yourself and continue to march forward.
You know, we need you all in the industry.
And, you know, it's exciting that we have new blood all the time.
And you're going to make awesome stuff.
So I can't wait to work with you all.
Absolutely.
Awesome.
Thank you, everybody.
Thank you for coming to our talk.
You