Hey everyone, good afternoon, thanks for making it down to GDC Narrative Summit day one.
I'm guessing that you're all That Game Company fans, maybe?
Thanks for making it down, everyone.
I feel like I'm presenting this slightly prematurely.
We did actually have a big beta release recently,
but I wanted to do a quick sense check before I dove into the presentation
to see how many of you guys have actually read or seen or even played New Games Guy.
Oh, a handful.
OK, great.
OK.
For the rest of you guys in the room,
there's actually a lot of surprises
that I won't be covering in this talk today.
So don't be afraid.
Don't shut your ears down when there's
spoilers in the presentation.
I think that hopefully everyone in this room
will walk away with something as well.
So let me make a start.
So my name is Jenny Kong.
I am the story writer at That Game Company studio
based out in Santa Monica.
And I'm really thrilled to be sharing with you
the presentation, Evolving Emotional Storytelling
in our New Game Sky.
For those who don't know me, I'm also a narrative writer
for a couple of indie studios who are showcasing
the games out here at GDC this week.
And most recently, I actually directed and shot
a docu-series.
around storytelling in video games.
It follows 15 iconic and indie game creators
and it's currently streaming on Comcast and YouTube
if you haven't had the chance to check it out yet.
And just taking a step even further back,
I've been working in the video games industry
for around 15 years or so now.
I began my career on the publishing side
back at Sony PlayStation UK,
working on a number of titles there.
So I've been working at that game company since 2013.
Sky, the new game, is probably the studio's most ambitious
project to date.
I would say that because not only are we developing the
game, but we're also publishing the game for the
most part as well.
We announced the title back in
late 2017 at the Apple Keynote stage,
and over the past year we've been aggressively beta testing
two key components of the game,
the multiplayer aspect and also the emotional aspect.
We want to get both of these right.
I think we're in the home stretch now, we're nearly finished with the game and ready to
kind of launch the global release.
But I'm so passionate about this area that I feel that over the past decade, emotional
storytelling has really seen some highlights over the past few years, primarily in the
linear game experience.
And what I hope today will do is to offer additional conversation to explore emotional
storytelling in the multiplayer domain as well.
So I would say that Sky is a spiritual successor
to some of the previous games that the studio have made.
I studied screenwriting at school,
but boy, this studio does things very, very differently.
But they did break from tradition
compared to their previous games.
So Sky is the first fully-fledged multiplayer experience
that they've launched.
It's gonna be multi-format, coming on iOS first.
The world itself is wholly online.
And then the game itself will touch upon both aspects of non-linear story as well as more
MMO type storytelling.
The big vision really is that we want to launch the game and have Sky appeal to as many people
as possible and we've tried to do that really with this next release.
Sky's been in development for the last six years.
It's a very long time, I don't wish six years of development and production to any of you guys in the room.
There's been a lot of starts and stops, U-turns, etc.
And my hope today is to really share with you some of the creative processes internally at the studio,
providing a top-level case study and analysis of how the story had changed over the six-year period.
I would say we're a team of 25, everybody in the studio interfaces with story at some
point, we're highly collaborative.
But I do want to give a shout out to my boss personally, Junova Chen, he's been a true
inspiration for my work in this game, as well as my colleagues Chris Bell and the design
team and Yui Tanabe and the art team.
Both of these guys have really put a lot into the emotion of Sky 2.
So that game company, how do we best define
emotional storytelling and the approach?
I would say that our goal is to connect players globally
through a positive emotional experience
in interactive entertainment.
We are an emotion-first studio.
What does that mean?
So for other studios, a green light project could look like, oh hey, there's a new piece
of technology, let's explore that and green light that project.
Someone has a great idea from a design perspective, let's kind of flesh that out.
Or someone might want to translate an IP, a film IP for example, into a game, let's
go for it.
We don't do any of that.
We are very much about focusing on what that positive emotion will feel like for the audience
and advocate that forward.
So what that means is that we will iterate and iterate across the other disciplines.
So whether it's design, story, art, music, we will keep recalibrating.
time and time again to make sure that the emotional experience is spot on.
We also focus very heavily on non-competitive play.
This has been kind of our domain over the past few titles.
And as we push forward with our next release,
we want to advocate that more genres and narrative
are explored, because if we touch upon different genres
rather than the ones we've seen in the past two decades,
let's say, we can possibly procure different kind
of emotions in the games.
And what kind of games and narratives can we explore
that will nourish and enrich our emotional selves as a player?
We want to see games accepted as an art form alongside the other forms of entertainment.
So let me talk about some emotional storytelling tools
that we work towards at TGC.
Let me highlight three core tenets.
The first is emotion through universal language.
So a lot of other developers may lean on voiceover
or a flashback or a character dialogue piece,
even a text kind of popping up on screen
to hint and maybe explore what the exposition
of the story world is.
We don't do any of that.
I kind of wish we did sometimes, it would make my job easier.
Instead, we focus on prospectively looking towards the universal language of visual,
of themes, of music.
Why is that?
Because if you think about these elements of language across the world,
sometimes all it takes is a little piece of music to evoke a certain kind of emotion.
We don't need words, we just need that piece of music.
And so we've kind of been developing this area a lot more
and focusing on this too.
I would say that our previous game, Journey,
did lean on the Joseph Campbell model
of the hero's journey.
And with our next game, Sky, we touched upon that
as we made a start on the development process.
The second tenet I would like to explore is emotion through the environment.
You know, we're all familiar with environmental storytelling here.
One of the kind of aesthetics that we've kind of approached in the past,
again with other titles like Flower and Journey,
is that our artists like to work within a minimalist design space.
What does that mean?
So rather than try to reveal story through an object
or an item or a person, we try to remove these obstacles
out of the way because we feel possibly it might get
in the way of the emotional interaction
that we have as a player and the subject at hand.
Sometimes maybe something off screen is more powerful
as an emotional trigger than something that's on screen.
Genova talks quite candidly about inviting players into the game as though they were
archaeologists.
The idea that maybe backstory, hint of character, portrayal could be buried and or hidden within
the environment.
It's a playground and we invite you to join.
and kind of showcase what the story could be there.
It's more rewarding to unearth a piece of story item
than it is just to sit and watch another cut scene.
And the final tenet is emotion through action.
And what I mean by that is, you know,
let's think about, if you can imagine,
redefining what player actions and the moveset
could be within a game.
So if you are player A, and you have a sword,
and you're walking around, this is an adventure game,
you're wielding your sword, or you're player B,
and you're carrying a candle instead.
Now I'm praying that none of you are going to be carrying the candle and pyro-ing the
sky world once you get in because I don't think we have enough budget to rebuild the
world again.
Granted, the actions of each are very different, and therefore the emotions of each are going
to be very, very different.
So again, player A has a sword.
He's going to be destroying stuff maybe.
Player B has a candle with light.
Maybe he or she is illuminating things in the world.
So let me talk a little bit more about Sky.
What is Sky?
Sky is a social adventure set above the clouds.
You play as one Sky descendant of many
that flies across this mysterious kingdom
looking to spread light back into the world.
The end goal is that once light is restored,
the constellation will come back alive.
It's a very fantastical world.
And very early on, we wanted to ground it.
and kind of thematically how could we do that?
Rather than portraying Sky as a fantasy game,
we wanted to portray it as a coming-of-age game instead.
We liked the idea that the character could be growing up
throughout the game's time.
We felt it was a very positive message to send out.
We liked the inclusivity of this genre too.
And I think the feeling that we wanted to explore also was the idea of childhood wonder as you explored this magical sky kingdom.
A lot of us, we've all had childhoods, we understand what that means, we remember some nostalgic feelings of this world and of this time.
And so we wanted to leverage maybe some language and motifs around childhood.
And I think that's why the characters were designed as children, you play a child.
and you primarily remain a child through the course of the game.
But this was a perfect entryway into the world that is pretty fantastical.
So I actually have a lot to cover,
but I will focus on how story changed in these three areas.
Over the course of the six years, I want to share with you how we adapted to a different
story structure.
I want to explore with you how we developed an emotional engine to explore the user story
in the game.
And finally, how we ended up testing emotion in the live community space.
So the first two years of Sky, we had a very small team
that explored prototyping the world, as you can see.
We wanted to feel the way that flight could be for a player.
We wanted to see how the traversal would work.
We had an awesome engineering team
that developed cool new technology
to make the cloud robust and fun to fly within.
And we also looked at the scope of gameplay
as well in this early stage.
For the next year or two, we started
with a very small story development team.
That included Jenova, myself, and a couple of other artists.
And there's no difference to maybe if you've
studied writing in the past.
We generated a lot of traditional story materials.
And what that meant is that we would use a whiteboard,
we would hash out what the emotional flow could be
at each point in the game.
We developed mini story bibles in Google Doc
and drafted out what the player's background were,
what the characters' motives were.
and again looking at the different kind of pinpoints of the story that you yourself would be developing.
And finally we also looked at, prospectively, how we could visualise the Sky Wall system.
But this was kind of early stages, so we wanted to kind of park that until a later stage.
At this time I also revisited some coming of age classics,
re-watching Wizard of Oz, Stand By Me,
even some of the more recent coming of age stories
Spirited Away, and re-reading The Little Prince.
That was one of the things that inspired us.
So as we started moving into the development phase,
this is a pretty large map that the art team drew out
around the kind of the grandeur of the Skyworld.
We would start out in number one,
around the Avery area and the Isle area,
moved to number two, which was the Prairie realm,
and then the forest number three, so on and so forth.
And we devised a multiplayer linear story path
across each realm within the Sky Kingdom.
And then in between development, we
would kind of map out almost like a mini three-act structure.
So for the Prairie Realm, what would happen in the first act,
second act, third act in terms of the story beats,
how the player moved, what was the obstacles.
Myself and the concept art with Jenova
would kind of feel these elements out.
But a big mandate from Genova was like,
hey, we want players to repeat and play the game again.
And I'm like, so we've already gone to number seven,
so you want them to kind of start again at number one
and play through again with the same emotional beats
and the same things that are happening?
It was really tough to justify the current kind of setting that we have.
So we kind of banked it, we put it to a side and asked ourselves, okay, so what emotions
would spur a multiplayer group of people to revisit the Skyworld?
And kind of just progressing further on each realm, we start to look at the linear progression
of each area.
So we started with the Isle and the Prairie.
And the idea is, if you can think about it, the idea is that with each of these realms,
we would...
kind of showcase or unlock a new emotion.
So let's say for instance you and your sky friends,
you go into the prairie area,
and the idea is that this is kind of like
the first burst of childhood memories.
You feel freedom, you feel joy,
and then you would meet a character at the end
that would kind of compound that emotion.
And then through each realm,
as we kind of navigate through all the way to the end,
we wanted to ultimately
showcased the emotion of sacrifice.
Now how can we do that?
So we did a quick test in the forest area,
and the idea is that you and your friends
would kind of fly into this enchanted forest,
and then the further down into the woods you would get,
things aren't kind of looking so great,
and you actually lose your friends.
This is where we separate you from the friends
for the first time.
You would be confused,
you're not really sure what's going on.
You'd feel uncertain, right?
This felt very contrived.
It was like, I don't know how we're gonna do this.
We're retro-engineering and refitting emotions into levels.
And so, another try, another crack at emotion,
we set this plan aside too.
And we decided to keep some of these emotions in place
for the art team to develop the look and feel of each realm.
But they were kind of more like mood boards at this point.
The art team also started thinking about the design of the character and the design team
and Genova agreed that the player should really be showcased as a very plain character at
the beginning, kind of going back to that minimalist design if you will, so that any
people jumping onto the game.
they could almost connect to the avatar a lot quicker
because it's not customized yet.
They can kind of see themselves within that character.
Just as your character is getting kind of, you know,
all the garb and the masks as you see in the final picture,
the idea is that, you know, if you visited certain lands
and met certain characters, you would unlock masks,
power capes, items along the way,
and other people would kind of understand that,
oh, hey, you've actually been to that area.
I see that you have that item.
Concurrently, we spent some time developing the backstory.
I created a lot of mini documents
around each of the characters, the personalities,
the motives, and the concepts around these eight
elder characters in the Skyworld that you would meet.
And at this point, we leaned against the archetypes
that you would see in a lot of the storytelling books.
But it felt very cliché, even when I was writing them, the idea that, hey, here's a
child of light, look at them, they're holier than thou, they're here to help the world,
and here's these elder dudes that have just ruined everything and somehow they're evil.
I felt it was a very tragic story.
I wanted to share that feeling of emotion of tragedy and the history of what they'd
done, how they cared about the world and what happened.
And so we started looking at maybe elders as antiheroes rather than villains, I suppose.
And during this time, we kind of went one step further
and looked at the hero's journey again.
I just felt like the model was doing the game
a slight disservice in terms of not explaining
the narrative fully.
How could we account for the range of players coming in
to join the multiplayer group?
How can we showcase the variance of characteristics
in each of the NPCs?
and how do we include a replayable story loop in here?
Conflicts was something that we looked at time and time again.
We looked at stakes in the story. We went back and forth.
And, you know, we asked ourselves,
OK, is Sky a world that's driven by conflict,
or is it a world that's driven by purpose?
Do we see good and evil in this world?
Or do we see and celebrate the beauty of light and dark
and the duality that we are all in ourselves, light and dark?
I did some additional research and I want to share with you if you guys haven't read
up on this yet.
This is a new initiative called The Collective Journey by Jeff Gomez, the brilliant Jeff
Gomez and his team at Starlight Runner.
He's not trying to replace the hero's journey, he's trying to kind of add an extra layer
to basically say that hey, modern day story structure in the digital age is very different.
You see it online, you see it in politics every day.
People want to get involved, it's not about one person saving the world.
We like this model, we like that empowered and activated communities coming together in the Skyworld.
Communities that wanted to not bring down one big bad villain,
but to seek systematic change that would change the world inside out.
And to showcase the multiple sides and the voices of people involved.
So Genova and I, we all got excited about this TV structure,
of this ensemble storytelling, you know, looking at Game of Thrones, etc.
And this side migrating into some of our brainstorms,
that we were actually now thinking more of the story as TV,
episodic maybe, rather than kind of one big story.
So the collective journey really redefines
some of the emotional qualities of Sky
and the nuances of our game,
and it starts to shift emphasis
towards more of a multiplayer non-linear experience.
What I like is points 10 and 11,
the idea that in this model,
we're celebrating vulnerability in the character
and also sacrifice, and again,
we have all a part to play in this world.
Again, not just one person's gonna save the day.
So we now start moving into the pre-production build,
and you're gonna see this map time and time again.
It's getting a bit crazy there, I think.
But kind of building off the first playthrough where we started with the aviary, the prairie,
the forest.
Once as a player you've locked those areas, you can actually fly to those areas at any
time.
You don't have to play through the entire map to kind of get back to it.
And we like this idea of zigzagging back through the different realms because Encourage
group exploration, you can go back and delve into an area of a realm that maybe you've
forgotten to take a different path, or maybe there's hidden areas of story and items that
you didn't see.
And I was getting really worried at this point, I was like, I don't want to, I want to protect
the Ace story, I don't want to start impacting and messing with that.
But it actually didn't.
The players that tried the game actually...
enjoyed the A-story mythology, they wanted to learn more,
they can't wait to kind of finish the game
and play the global release.
But the B-story components of seasonal content
and the world events allowed a bit more
of a breathing space within the world.
And it really pushed the design team and the story team
to think a little bit more about
what the core gameplay loop would be.
So, just to track this through, what it meant was that as you travel through each realm,
it was a looser kind of structure.
The group would be moving from one realm to another, solving puzzles, flying through new
areas, meeting these elder characters, and spreading light.
Right?
It sounds great.
It's collaborative.
No, no, it wasn't.
So the pre-production build, it didn't, when we played it as a team and we did many trials,
I don't think it moved us emotionally as we thought it would be.
Like, we're spreading light, we're doing great things in this world.
We had a lot of internal playtesters too.
It was really funny actually, in one survey with a playtester,
a woman was playing with another woman, she was sat opposite her.
And she actually thought it was all NPCs in the world at some point, and I'm just like,
wow, we really have not done our job if she felt it was all NPCs in this world.
So we could see the players, you know, physically traveling together through each of the realms,
but they weren't emotionally connected.
So if they're not going to be emotionally connected, they're not going to do the other
stuff that we want to, you know, see if they'll be gravitating towards.
The one thing that did happen during some of these playtests
was Jenova explored the element of including a tool,
the idea of the candle, which was a breakthrough
in some of the story work that we did.
And I like the candle because it actually
forges the player to have both a physical
and emotional relationship and connection with the world.
So the idea that you would be going around lighting things,
helping the NPCs and the world out.
But not only that, that it was connecting player on player as well.
So the idea is if I have a candle and I want to hold it out to you, you have a candle that's not lit
and I'm lighting your candle and giving energy back to you, wouldn't that be a great thing?
And so as we were moving very sluggishly through this pre-production build,
we kind of, I think, had a eureka moment.
Okay, well, we've zeroed in, we've exhausted all the emotions we can.
Maybe let's start looking at what an emotional engine could look like.
And we focus on altruism as an element, and also connection as an element.
What do I mean by an emotional engine?
So before we were looking at emotional moments
in each of the realms, and that would help drive us through
and build us through to the end of the game,
we scrapped that.
We decided to focus on an engine that
would power the gameplay and the story
through from beginning to the end.
The big question was, was this enough, really,
to sustain positive experience with the entire world
and to invite people back into the game
and for them to enjoy it?
So as we were ramping up to the beta build,
we started looking at the friendship connection.
This is something that you might have seen before in Journey.
We started to kind of build off of that.
And we liked the idea of the candle moment.
So the team and design team started
looking at how can we leverage the gifting of candles
to each other.
the idea that you can unlock friendship functions.
So if I give you three candles, we can unlock the capacity
to hold hands, and then I can lead you around the world
and share with you some of my favorite parts of Sky.
Or maybe you want to gift me three candles,
and then we will unlock the hugging function.
People like to hug in the game.
You'll see why when you play.
And then so on and so forth.
A chat functionality and other things is pretty cool.
We also experimented and pushed the needle a little bit to see, hey, can we leverage
candle currency?
Maybe people can buy candles and if they haven't found a cape yet or a mask, they can leverage
some of this.
It's not necessarily like I will buy the candles and then I'll buy things for myself.
The idea is that I will gift you candles and you can gift me candles.
So that we have that exchange and depending on what you want to do with your candles,
you can buy some things or unlock some things and vice versa as well.
So this was the big one.
We went into beta testing over a year ago
and really, you know, testing emotion at scale.
We had over 20,000 plus players global.
Some of you guys in here,
you've had a chance to check it out.
And these are the kind of key areas
that we began to test in.
So what was the emotional feedback of the game,
multiplayer dynamic, friendship, replay value.
That's the big one.
And in the beta test, I would say that we kind of leveraged around 6 to 8 builds, again
focusing on each time, alright, what was the emotional experience of the game, and looking
at the engine of altruism and connection.
With each of the builds, we would get feedback, and then we'd slowly tweak controls.
game mechanics, a story, cooperative play,
some of the quests in the game,
and even move things around in the world
if it helped people to be more generous with each other.
We used a tool called Firebase,
which sees when players drop out of the game.
It's a terrible thing, don't use Firebase.
You're just like, hey, they're having fun.
Oh, no, they're not, they hate the game.
And we also followed up each build with in-game surveys.
Let's find out what you think about the game.
We read feedback on Discord, Twitter, Facebook.
We opened up our inboxes to the world and said,
send us your long emails, tell us what you think, pretty please.
And this was great, we really wanted that feedback.
And so we built upon this narrative gameplay of altruism
spreading light to the world,
and this was pretty much what was in the beta build.
Again, this was a time to refocus and recalibrate around friendship again.
The team spent a lot of time on this area because we felt this would be the key to the
replay value and this was a big focus during the time.
Okay, so six months to nine months of iteration, lots of qualitative and quantitative data.
We're all piling, you know, reading through every team member.
And my god, people were harsh on this game.
These are the things that we don't want to share, but here I am sharing them.
The players, as you can see, struggled to understand what was going on in the game.
They didn't understand the user goal.
Story wasn't clear to them, sure, there was some placeholder cinematics.
Some players didn't even want to help other people.
They were not compelled.
They were just doing their own thing and that was it.
And then certain, the vocal members,
they were just outright rejecting multiplayer altogether.
Like this guy.
He was like,
I don't like that I'm forced to do this for some stuff.
Let me be free to choose.
Alright, okay.
And we had this consistently
for the first portion of the beta trials.
it was very clear that we hadn't built enough
into the story world to earn the player's compassionate
or friendship behavior.
But the biggest complaint really was that players felt
the friendship component of the game was imbalanced.
And this is harsh because we're trying to make a game
that connects people, right?
So one guy was like, I'm leveraging my friendship points
to unlock content and collectibles in this world.
You're giving me candles, I'm giving you candles.
I want your candles just to unlock the cool stuff, you know?
And it felt very inauthentic and at times very, very greedy.
And we're TGC, we don't do greedy.
I don't know how to do greedy.
And this was really tough on us.
So we took a bit of a break, we took a step back
and began to shift focus and reiterate on this emotional engine
and try and look at different ways to represent altruism instead.
Instead of building friendships around the act of altruism,
could we actually leverage altruism first
and then see if people come to it,
and then form lasting friendships?
So what that meant was we didn't focus so much
on the friendship-building component.
We just had to trust that it was going to happen.
People are going to be friends in this world.
We instead focused on building out moments of altruistic play
across the NPCs and also between players.
We redesigned some of the creature and civilian saving quests,
but you had to do it in a multiplayer setting.
The idea that four players would come together
and kind of shepherd light back into the soul of a creature.
We began thinking about how we can make multiplayer more fun
and start designing and releasing musical instruments in Sky.
People loved it, even the people that didn't like to play instruments,
didn't know how to play it, they were jiving, it was awesome for them.
And then we started also looking at new areas in the game
that had nothing to do with story, so we built out things like an ice rink,
we had a crab cave,
pit. I don't know why we would have a crab pit, but there they are holding two crabs on the left.
They love that area, by the way.
And this was just promoting, you know, friendship play. It's nothing to do with the story.
And the main focus is not progression through friendship, but progression through altruism.
We talked about hugging and holding hands.
Those abilities became unlockable very, very quickly in the game,
very soon after.
You could just spend one candle and you had that ability.
And finally, we started to look at multiplayer challenges,
where the players would have to protect each other
during certain sequences in the game.
So over the next six months we found that there was a slow but somewhat drastic change
in some of the player feedback we were getting.
People were beginning to understand some of the story elements that we were trying to
get through and we were starting to see compassionate community driven behaviours within.
some of the beta players, a lot of the beta players
stuck around and played the game every day.
And what was interesting was that they were,
once they had like, you know,
played all the A story content and the B story content.
They were making adventures and stories on their own,
unprompted.
That's what they were coming back for in Sky.
It wasn't necessarily the stories that we relayed to them.
And somehow the unexpected replay value
that we'd been seeking all this time
actually came from the players themselves.
Instead of preparing content to put out into the world,
the world actually had became theirs already.
So it's still a work in progress, but this is kind of the chaotic map of the different
story structures we've been kind of playing around with.
We still have the kind of main A mythology story, the seasonal event content, and then
what I call the user-generated multiplayer stories peppered throughout the world as well.
I want to share with you a letter that encapsulates what's possible with positive interactions
in games, and to really emphasise that the community themselves has redefined the trajectory
of storytelling in Sky.
We owe a lot to them, and that's why we're working so hard to finish the game.
Here's the team.
They're hustling.
I'm at GDC.
Thank you very much.
The global release will be hopefully with you guys very soon.
So in conclusion, just some tips as to how to approach emotional storytelling,
more so in a multiplayer setting rather than a linear setting.
I would advocate that storytellers and developers look outside the conventional
tropes and structures to find and explore new ideas of what emotional storytelling can be.
You can't dictate emotion at any point, it's very hard.
Instead, experiment extensively how to uncover and reveal
what this emotional engine could look like.
Keep testing, keep working at it,
and see what drives the player from beginning to end.
That emotion might not be what you think it is.
Treat your community very well.
Their feedback is completely invaluable
and probably the most authentic it can be.
and stay open to what could be available emotionally.
Some of the emotions we saw in the game are happy accidents
and actually reveal the true nature of what Sky can be.
So I started the talk advocating more genres of narrative in video games can evoke more
emotions in video games and I hope that there's some ideas that I've shared with you today
that you can go back to your teams or your studios to experiment with.
This topic is very, very important to me.
I wholly advocate building out emotional storytelling in games and thank you so much for your time
today.
Thank you.