Okay, thanks so much for being here first thing in the morning.
I think we're going to get started.
We're right at 10.
So I am Bonnie Rueberg.
I go by Bo.
I use they, them pronouns.
And I'm going to be talking to you about what to do when toxic gamer culture enters the
classroom.
A quick note, I'm not going to be talking explicitly about details of violence, but
I will be discussing experiences of harassment.
By the way, it's totally fine to tweet this talk.
I am at my own Valeria on Twitter.
I just ask that you please don't use hashtags
that are there to alert specific harassment groups.
I think I know, you know what I mean.
So a little bit about me and where I'm coming from.
I'm currently an assistant professor
at the University of California, Irvine.
Previously, I've worked at the University
of Southern California and also at Berkeley.
As an educator, I tend to teach courses that are about games and culture,
primarily for undergrad programs where students are learning to become
game designers or game programmers.
So I'm thinking about the kind of cultural, social side,
but my students are often there for more technical or development skills.
I'm also a queer person and a gender non-binary person.
This is the bumper sticker that's currently on the back of my car.
I'm pretty sure it's the world's best bumper sticker.
My research is also on LGBT issues in games.
I believe in intersectional feminism and social justice.
So I'm telling you these things because they shape
how I approach games education,
but also because they shape how students interact with me,
how they react to me.
This is a quick, totally shameless plug for my book,
which just came out like two days ago.
It's called Video Games Have Always Been Queer.
Thank you, I will take all the applause I can get.
So it is about how video games,
even when they don't seem to include LGBT representation,
can be understood queerly through interpretation,
through play, and through design.
If that sounds like something you're into,
or something you think your students might be into,
come say hi, I'd love to tell you more about it.
So here's the big question that I wanna tackle today.
How do we, as game educators, teach students who are skeptical, resistant, or even hostile
towards diversity?
So when I say hostile towards diversity, I mean hostile towards either diverse instructors
or towards learning about diversity issues in the classroom.
We all care about our students.
I think we're here because we care about education,
and we really want to think the best of them.
But the reality right now is that,
for many university-level game instructors,
especially folks who have been marginalized
in games cultures, so people like women,
non-binary folks, queer folks, folks of color,
we're finding ourselves facing identity-based discrimination
and even harassment from our own students.
We all know that games culture can be toxic.
But toxic gamer culture isn't just something that exists somewhere out there on the internet.
It's also in our classrooms.
More and more, I find that when I teach new students about discriminatory online culture,
I'm also teaching students who are participating in discriminatory online culture.
So what do we do when we experience problematic interactions with students around these issues
and how do we thrive as instructors in the face of potential harm?
There's a lot to talk about here.
This is a really big issue.
I'm gonna just talk you through some kind of main points,
so here's what I'm gonna cover.
I'll give you a quick primer on toxic gamer culture,
which basically boils down to it is totally a thing.
I'll talk about what happens when that toxicity intersects
with games education, so how it manifests in the classroom,
but also outside of the classroom.
To illustrate some of this in action, I'm going to walk you
through a kind of quick post-mortem of a course
that I taught last year where my TAs and I really wrestled
with these issues.
I'll talk about some of the particular challenges and potential negative effects of dealing
with toxic gamer students, so these are things that I learned through teaching this course.
And I'm going to bring us around to actionable steps, what we can do to make sure that being
diverse or encouraging students to think about culture in diverse ways isn't grounds to turn
a teacher into a target.
And more specifically, those actionable steps
are going to be oriented towards educators
who are affecting or who are experiencing
this toxic environment, the colleagues
of marginalized educators who are affected by this,
and then also folks who are in charge of game programs
or even institutions at a sort of higher level.
I'm going to be drawing from my experience teaching at three different institutions.
I've also had a ton of kind of behind the scenes, off the record, anonymous conversations
with colleagues at other institutions, many of the institutions that you may represent
here in the room.
So this is not just a me problem.
This is a broader problem.
You may be thinking already, I'm not really a diversity person.
I teach technical classes, and this isn't my thing.
Maybe not, because you're here first thing in the morning
to hear about this, which I appreciate.
But whoever you are and whatever you teach, this is your thing.
It's everybody's thing.
It's a thing for educators on the front lines,
but it's also a thing for the colleagues of those educators,
especially colleagues who think about themselves as allies.
So let's get into this first topic, toxic gamer culture.
I'm gonna start with a fun fact.
I am probably going to get harassed for giving this talk.
I don't know what form that harassment is gonna take.
It might be a flood of angry social media posts.
It might be menacing emails from strangers.
I've been doing this for a long time.
I've been working in this area for 14 years,
so I have seen it all.
But what's notable is that I'm not just going to get harassed for being a feminist
or being a queer activist who works in games,
I'm going to be harassed for being a games educator.
I gave a short talk two years ago here in the Educator Summit
about how we need to teach our students not just to make games that are technically strong,
but that are socially engaged and politically aware.
And if we think about any other medium, how we would teach it,
that's a totally obvious statement.
But because I was talking about games,
and specifically because I was talking about how to teach games,
the internet got pissed.
For a whole bunch of days...
Following that talk, my Twitter notifications were just a fire hose of angry people,
a number of whom identified themselves as students,
raging at this idea that video games could be taught as objects of culture.
That's toxic gamer culture.
So what do I mean when I say that?
I mean this culture that has grown up around video games,
a kind of dominant culture that's grown up around video games.
that privileges players who fit this mold of the traditional gamer.
White, straight, cisgender men and boys who play hardcore games.
At the same time, this culture devalues and often actively discriminates against
those of us who are seen as different, who don't fit that mold.
Toxic gamer culture insists that video games need protecting
from social justice warriors who will spoil them
with cultural analysis and diverse representation.
It also longs for this imagined time past
when men were men and video games were video games.
Toxic gamer culture has been around for a really long time.
It's not a new thing.
But it's kind of come to the fore and come to a head
in recent years alongside major online harassment campaigns
and the rise of certain affiliated political groups.
It's more prominent, prevalent, and insidious now than ever.
If you want to learn more about toxic gamer culture,
or if you're feeling skeptical about what I'm saying to you,
and you want some research to back it up,
there are tons of folks doing work on this area.
These are just three recent books that I recommend.
Gaming Masculinity by Megan Condis,
Toxic Geek Masculinity by Anastasia Salter
and Bridget Blodgett,
and The Toxic Meritocracy of Video Games by Christopher Paul.
All of them are great.
I also know that there are plenty of you in this audience
who don't need to be convinced that toxic gamer culture
is a thing because you're experiencing it firsthand.
And I just want you to know that I see you, right?
I value you and I see that you're having that experience.
For a lot of us, toxic gamer culture,
this kind of looming threat of the potential of harassment,
is the background to making, playing, studying,
or teaching video games.
It's there constantly.
It's like a background radiation almost,
except that sometimes it explodes
and comes into the foreground.
Okay, so let's talk about the relationship between toxic gamer culture and games education.
And just a note, my focus here is on the experience that educators have with toxic students, or
students who are behaving in toxic ways.
But there are whole other parts of this conversation we could have that are also important.
So peer-to-peer toxicity, student-to-student, or we could also talk about toxicity between
colleagues, right, between faculty or admins within a games education program.
So before we dig into this intersection of toxicity
in games education, I want to ask you a couple questions.
You don't have to answer these questions out loud.
I just want to give you a moment to ponder them.
Here's the first one.
Have you ever felt unsafe in the classroom?
So unsafe might mean physically unsafe,
or it might mean that the classroom felt
like an actively hostile, emotional, or social
environment.
Here's the second one.
Has a student ever acted negatively towards you
because of your identity?
So not just negatively in general.
I think we all run into students who are feeling grumpy,
or they've got things going on in their lives,
but they act negatively towards you because of your identity.
So that would be a negative interaction with a student
that you're pretty sure was motivated in part
by your gender, or your race, or your sexuality, or disability,
or body type, things like that.
So, is that something that's happened?
For some of you, the answers to those questions were yes.
Yes, I felt unsafe.
Yes, I've been discriminated against.
But for some of you, the answer is no.
And for those of you who answered no,
it's particularly important to confront the fact
that even if you're not personally experiencing
this behavior, there is toxicity in our classrooms.
It's happening even if it's not happening to you.
I know this is uncomfortable to admit.
I for one really love teaching.
So I think one of the things that I find just emotionally really hard about this issue is
that I love teaching students.
I love teaching undergrads.
And when the environment is right, when you have a diverse group in a small enough classroom,
you can have a real conversation, you have these awesome, amazing students who are willing
to dig into big issues.
But for a lot of us, we don't teach in these small, intimate classrooms.
We teach at large universities like I do.
And we often find ourselves teaching these kind of big, faceless rooms of people.
We heard at the HFGA event last night that we're seeing more and more women
come out of games programs. That's awesome.
But the overwhelming majority is still male.
So the folks who we're teaching are still often tied to this toxic gamer population.
Many of our students see themselves as technical.
I think that's a big part of this education track as well,
that we're thinking about how to give students
technical or design skills.
But when they see themselves as purely technical,
they often resent the idea of learning
about games and culture.
And I've encountered this firsthand a ton.
They feel like those classes are requirements,
they have to get out of the way,
and they resent that their time is being wasted
thinking about the cultural implications of games.
So in that environment, when we try to teach these students,
we're often met with hostility.
This is true in lots of areas of education today.
It's not just a games thing.
So we've seen folks who've been called out by their students
and had their information sent off to right-wing news sources.
We've seen professors kind of driven off campus.
We've seen bomb threats.
But games are a lightning rod for this.
It's not that games aren't tied to larger cultural issues.
It's that games are this kind of microcosm
where the larger cultural issues have just exploded.
Here's how Emma Vossen, who's a fellow feminist game scholar and an educator, talks about this.
And I'm really indebted to Emma because she's been really bold and really brave and really
like emotionally open about what she's experienced in the classroom. She says,
I've become more and more nervous around my students.
Any one of them could write a Reddit thread about their professor being a social justice warrior,
or they could be recording you, waiting for you to give them a bad grade to retaliate against you.
The hate mob that looms around you is like a giant weapon that any of your students could wield.
This is more than just tough students.
This is being in the same room with someone who would probably send you death threats
if you weren't their teacher.
And I think what's important to point out about that beyond just the intensity of that,
right, that's very real, is also that this is not just tough students.
This is a broader cultural issue that these students are being sucked into and they're
kind of repeating back to us.
So I want to make a radical statement, right, which is that teaching games
teaching game students about diversity or teaching game students while being
diverse should not be grounds for harassment.
And at this point,
I love the clap.
Y'all clap for strange things.
At this point you might be thinking of some objections, right?
You might be thinking.
This sounds rough, right, that sucks for you,
but it's not a problem at my game program.
It's not a problem at my game program, right?
My program is different,
my program doesn't have these issues.
Let me tell you something,
no game program is exempt from this.
It is true to some extent of all schools,
and it's true that if you have a larger student body,
if you have a more technical student body,
if your gender ratio is different,
it may well be different,
but no game program is exempt from this.
Even if your student body is diverse, right, this is still the air that our students breathe.
So when they go online, this is the culture that they take in, so this is the culture
they have to give back to us.
You may also be thinking.
Isn't this just the same thing as when students speak up
because they are offended about something
that you assigned to read, right?
They want content warnings.
They want trigger warnings.
They seem to be using these weird they, them pronouns.
Aren't you also being oppressed because
of that as an instructor?
And the answer is no.
This is about vectors of power, right?
This is about students who hold positions of privilege
trying to be hostile towards or even harass
teachers who are in marginalized positions.
So no, when your students speak up,
they want more social justice, they want better readings,
they want better representation,
that is definitely a different thing.
To be able to address this, we need to start to see it.
So especially for those of you
this might not be happening to,
you might not be able to see all the ways it's playing out
because it doesn't always look like
what you might expect harassment to look like.
There are a few places that it plays out primarily.
The first one is in the classroom itself.
I've added cupcakes to these because,
screw it, it sucks, right?
So we might as well have cupcakes.
is my feeling.
So the first place that this manifests
is in bad faith questions.
So what I mean is, you may be giving a talk
about the cultural meaning of games,
and you may have a student at the back of the room
who raises their hand and says,
yeah, but aren't games really just for fun?
Do they even mean anything?
And in some ways, that's a valid question,
but you can often tell, you develop a sense
when that question is sincere,
when that question is in bad faith,
and it's trying to rouse a fight.
Cred checking.
So this most often happens, unsurprisingly,
to women, non-binary folks, folks of color,
but the idea here is to challenge you and say,
you're my professor, but you don't really look like a gamer,
which is a sentence that gets uttered verbatim
very frequently.
Can you prove it, right?
What are you playing right now?
Did you play that game all the way to the end?
So that's cred checking.
Disruptive behavior.
You might have a large room of people and you have students who are sitting there talking
loudly to each other or they're using kind of aggressive body language to try and disrupt
the classroom.
Inappropriate comments about the instructor.
So this comes from an anecdote that sounds really unpleasant from a colleague who was
using one of the pieces of software that allows your students to anonymously respond to questions
that you pose while you're teaching.
And when she showed the answers up on the board, they were all comments about her body.
So they said things like, she's too hot to know anything about games.
in the middle of the classroom, right?
So what do you do when that's the reality
of the people sitting in front of you
and you didn't even know it
until they start putting those comments up?
Sometimes you get walkouts.
So you'll be talking about something
and a student will sort of in a huff,
stand up and walk out,
which is a kind of physical display of displeasure.
It's a performance.
But then this hostility also bleeds outside of the classroom.
So we see it, oh, there are dolphins this time.
I also like dolphins.
So we see it on essays and tests, anywhere that the students write comments.
So I've had a test question that was thinking about intersectional identities and asked
about is whiteness part of an intersectional identity, and the answer is yes.
Any identities that intersect we could talk about is intersectional.
And the student was very angry, and we got a long screed, me and the TAs, that was cursing
at us about this question.
So it appears places like that.
Disrespecting TAs, so TAs are another big part of this.
If you're teaching large classes,
if you're in an institution with grad students,
you may well be responsible for your TAs.
So how to protect them from this hostile behavior.
One-on-one meeting, so sometimes students will come to your office and kind of use physical
hostility, use verbal hostility to try and intimidate you.
So this is one where I highly recommend always leaving your office door open.
I had a student once come to my office and tell me he was just so angry about all the
LGBT people, he wanted to hurt someone.
And what do you do with that as an instructor sitting across, you know, from someone in
a room?
Sometimes you get this kind of peer to peer trash talk that's also meant to be performative,
so a student will very vocally go around to their peers and be like, that Professor Rueberg,
they're horrible.
And the point is to circulate it within the program.
And then teacher evaluations.
So this is a particularly tricky one,
especially for those of you who rely on these
for like your personnel reviews, for your tenure reviews.
They will leave comments on evaluations
that are things like, and you can hear a lot of my examples
are from LGBT stuff, because that's what I teach,
but things like, this professor has a gay agenda.
They are a bad professor, because they didn't give
equal weight to the other side of the argument,
which is that gay people are bad.
I am just totally unwilling to give equal weight to an argument that gay people are
bad.
And that sometimes they post online.
So sites like Rate My Professor, they might go on Reddit, like the quote from Emma Vossen
suggested, these public forums.
But then there's a place where this hostility
in the classroom, out of the classroom,
which is always kind of fuzzy, right?
Like what constitutes harassment is always kind of fuzzy.
But there are moments when that line gets less blurry
and it very clearly transitions into harassment.
You get pizza this time.
This is the last of them.
You got cupcakes.
Oh, there's like a food thing.
Anyway.
So sometimes you end up with threatening messages, right?
So direct contact from students, sometimes anonymized,
but very clearly from students.
I got one last year that said, I'll try not to curse at you.
You are a communist, and it's disgusting, right?
Am I a communist?
I don't know.
That's interesting.
But apparently it's disgusting.
Sometimes you get physical intimidation.
So people very clearly using being in small spaces with you.
I had a student who was very prone to come up to me, stand kind of square, look at me
with like dead eyes and say almost nothing.
And that is clearly an intimidation tactic.
And then things start to blow up from there.
So when students start reaching out intentionally to online harassers.
things can very quickly escalate.
So there is a culture of students sending syllabi
to larger harassment campaigns or notifying folks,
you know, there's a day in class
where we're gonna talk about feminism.
Come and help out.
And what happens is they send agents into your classroom.
So this is a kind of organized harassment campaign technique.
where folks show up in your classroom who are not enrolled,
and they try to document you and intimidate you,
and I'll talk more about that in a sec.
So it becomes this whole big muddle of different techniques,
and you can see how together they're a broader picture
of toxic behavior, hostile behavior,
even though each one individually
may not seem like such a big deal.
So let's see how this played out in this particular course.
I was making this slide yesterday
when I was sitting in another session
and the person behind me like visibly groaned.
Which I'm really happy about.
So, my first quarter teaching at my current institution,
which was the fall of 2017, I was given this class.
It's not a class I designed,
but it's a class that's regularly taught.
It's called Games and Society.
So that's a big thing, right?
all of games, all of society.
We teach on the quarter system, so all of those things
in a 10-week course.
This is kind of the basic information about it.
This is what I knew, right?
We had 260 students, quite a lot of students.
We had three TAs and one reader,
so I intentionally picked TAs and a reader
who were women or non-binary folks.
I wanted the students to see that the experts in the room
were not necessarily cis men, which is great.
They were wonderful, but it opens up
a whole other host of ethical questions.
The majority of them were computer science majors, or what we call at UCI, computer game science majors.
So they were very technical students.
75% of them were freshmen, since it was a fall class, and 90% of them were men.
So that's quite a breakdown.
But there were other things that I didn't realize were going to affect how the course
worked and things that you might want to think about as well.
So it was a required course.
It's actually their required intro course.
So it was their very first introduction to being there and they felt like they were just
forced into it, right?
It started them off on a bad foot.
It was also the only course that they were going to take in their entire education in
this major that was about culture.
So it was a like, check off the box, get out, get your EZA,
get out the other side.
When I was prepping to teach this course, I kind of knew
there were going to be problems.
Like I said, I've been doing this for a while.
I've always had problem students here or there at
other institutions.
So I started asking around for resources.
What happens if I have a student who's aggressive in
the classroom?
What happens?
If the students are generally kind of toxic,
like, what are these students like?
Right, what should I do with this new group of students
I'm getting to know?
And the response I got from my super well-intentioned, super
lovely colleagues, who I am thrilled to work with,
was amazingly unhelpful.
I had one professor, who I respect a ton, say to me,
kind of look at me like, I don't really
know what you're talking about.
But just be nice to your students,
and they'll be nice to you.
If anybody has experienced harassment on the internet
or in your classroom, you know that this is not correct,
right, it's not about being mean.
Often, actually, when we're nice,
that's when we open ourselves up,
we make ourselves vulnerable,
especially as people who read as women in the classroom.
I was also trying to find resources
for what to do with students who were being disruptive,
right, and the university had all these resources
for what to do if your student
is having a mental health crisis.
like one solo student having a mental health crisis.
But this is not a mental health crisis.
This is a broader cultural issue.
It's a systemic issue.
And there were no resources in place
for dealing with something like that.
So what it meant is that when I went into the classroom,
I had this experience I've never had before
in about a decade of teaching,
which is that when I looked out at this room,
it was just a sea.
It was a sea of dudes.
And it was a sea of hostile faces.
And I think that that's probably an overreaction
to a certain extent, right?
It's a kind of vocal minority,
but a very present minority.
And it's hard when you're standing in front of a room,
you wanna be generous, you wanna be present,
you're there for them to learn,
to be seeing the faces that are scowling at you
and kind of shooting hate at you.
So we wrestled with that, me and my TAs,
until we hit a day where it just felt like
this is too much, right?
This has gone beyond.
And what happened is we had a day on the syllabus
that was the gender day, right?
We kind of, in 10 weeks, you can't do a whole lot,
so we just had little smatterings of things, right?
Day on disability, day on race, day on this,
and we had one gender day.
I've got lots of radical,
pain-in-the-ass feelings about gender,
This class was not about that, right?
This was like the world's tamest gender class.
Designed not to like get me harassed.
And yet.
When I stood up in front of the podium, something was weird, because I had a policy of not wanting
students to use screens, and I've kind of backed off of that, but that's a separate
pedagogical thing.
And there were all these people in the audience holding up their phones and clearly actively
recording.
And I said something to them from the podium, and I said, like, hey, folks, remember, we
don't have, we have a policy of not doing that.
And they just didn't stop.
And it started to feel like the room was fuller
than it normally was.
So I had my TAs do a head count.
And it turned out that there were 11 extra people
in the room.
And we know it was precisely 11 people who weren't enrolled
because they took a pop quiz that day.
And the people who were there filming us
took the damn pop quiz.
They took the quiz but they all put pseudonyms on it.
So I was able to go through the whole directory for UCI
and figure out that none of those were real names.
So this was a coordinated effort.
Somebody had notified a larger system of harassers
and they had sent 11 people into the classroom
to be there both to record
so they could share this material online
and also to intimidate.
I gotta be honest, this really messed with me.
So I live in a place, and some of you may as well,
where our students and our faculty live very close together.
I live on a campus where there's student housing,
there's a whole faculty suburb,
and you go to the supermarket at midnight to buy some milk
and it's like they're all there, right?
Your lives are very close.
But because it was such a large class,
I couldn't get to know them all.
I couldn't get to know their faces.
So I didn't know who all of my toxic students were.
Some of them who I would call active harassers.
So it made me very anxious.
It made me kind of paranoid
that when I would look around at the sea of students
there at UCI, which is a large campus,
it felt like they were everywhere.
And I know that's not true,
but I just point that out to say
that this is not just a logistical problem,
this harassment issue.
It's also an...
problem of feeling, right?
It's a problem of how it kind of eats away at you,
this sense that your own students want to do you harm.
So from this experience, there were some things
that I learned are very specific challenges and effects
that come from the combination of toxic gamer culture
and the classroom, and games education.
I like to think of these challenges as kind of this bouncy house gauntlet of things that
you have to do to get from one side to the other to deal with it.
It's not just one obstacle, it's like a whole obstacle course that you go through.
So one thing is that your problems aren't visible to your privileged colleagues.
You may have wonderful colleagues who want to be supportive, but they just literally
don't see it because they're not in the classrooms where it's happening.
They're not the ones getting those evaluations.
It's just not visible to them.
So not only are you experiencing it, you're always trying to convince your colleagues
that it's happening.
People outside of games don't get it.
So you might have other communities.
For me, my work is very interdisciplinary.
So I'll often be at conferences or things like that
that aren't game-specific.
And trying to talk to folks, they're just like,
I literally have no idea what you're talking about.
When you talk to games people,
especially women and non-binary folks who teach games,
they're like, oh my God, this is my life every day.
So it's hard to find support networks outside of games
because games are a kind of different environment.
you end up in this pedagogy catch-22,
which is that you're there
because you care about diversity, right?
You're there because you live in a body
that is seen as diverse,
and so you have a stake in changing games
and games education.
And if you put that in your teaching,
you're gonna get, at best, hostile responses,
at worst, harassed, right?
But if you don't put it in your teaching,
then you've backed off your politics,
and you might not make games better, right?
So do you try and make it better?
Or do you back off?
And then this is the kind of larger question, right?
Because people will say to you, you're doing such great work.
You're converting the next generation.
Thank you.
Because there's a balance between converting folks
and trying to support your personal well-being.
So given this, there are also some very specific effects.
Some of these are obvious, right?
But they're worth thinking about,
especially if you run a games program,
especially if you have this concern in mind,
like I want to make the best games education I can,
how is this affecting me?
It has a direct effect on your program
and its efficacy for teaching.
So to start with, you have less happy, less engaged teachers.
One way to deal with feeling like your students are hostile
is to check out.
You walk into the room, you give a lecture, you peace.
I'm not saying that's a bad way to teach,
but that's a different way to teach than being interactive.
Because it shields you, and I understand that.
You get less teaching about culture.
I'd like to think that all our games programs
are slowly moving towards incorporating more of this,
but if you hire folks who can teach culture and games
and they are facing this issue,
they're gonna back off of that too.
That also hurts your program.
You get a less diverse student body.
And this takes a few steps to explain,
but I think this is important to a lot of folks
who run these programs, to have a diverse student body.
So the reason is that.
If you are getting hostile responses or harassment in the classroom, that means that you are
less likely to keep working there as a marginalized instructor, and also that you're less likely
to keep teaching these courses that explicitly engage with culture.
Those two things, having diverse instructors, teaching diverse topics, are the things that
kind of hail diverse students.
They're the things that show diverse students you care about them.
They show them that they're role models.
that they can see themselves in the program.
So when you start to lose those instructors
or lose those courses, you lose the comfortability
that your diverse students started to feel.
you end up with all this extra labor
for your marginalized instructors.
So some of that is time, right?
You get an email that tells you
that you're a disgusting communist, right?
And then you gotta do something, right?
You forward it to your chair,
you notify the appropriate person.
There's just work that goes into dealing
with this kind of behavior.
But there's also emotional work, right?
If you have been harassed in the past,
and you can get harassed and then go home and feel good
and be productive and write a research paper, Godspeed.
I know that when this happens to me,
even though it's been a long time
that I've been facing things like this,
it gets to you, it gets under your skin,
and it takes the time away from being productive
to have to deal with that set of feelings.
And then there's this whole promotion thing.
So I come up for my tenure soon, so it's like feeling
super close to home.
Which is that when your students leave you these
negative bits of feedback on your evaluations, it directly
affects your tenure track faculty.
Because it can come up in their promotion cases, it can
affect their tenure review, and it can actually in a very
real way affect their whole career, just to have these
students acting this way.
Okay, so let's jump to actionable steps.
So like I said, this falls into three areas, steps for marginalized educators, steps for
colleagues, steps for programs, so let's start with that first one.
There are things you can do before you even start a class.
So let's say you're starting in a new institution, it's an institution you suspect from getting
the kind of temperature of the student body, you suspect this might be an issue, you can
do things before the class even begins.
You can assemble a toolkit.
So like I said, this isn't always easy,
but finding the resources on campus,
what do I do with a disruptive student?
What do I do if I feel unsafe?
What's the reporting process?
As much as you can assemble,
so that if you're in a moment of crisis, you have it,
I recommend it.
cultivating the right teaching personality.
So I know this sounds a little like calculated.
I think we all want to think that we get up
in front of our students and we're sincere and we're present,
but for folks who are marginalized,
it's worth thinking carefully.
So for me, I've always been the kind of teacher
who's like a big smile and is like,
you're all awesome, thank you for being here.
I want to hear your thoughts.
And it turns out that backfires a lot of the time
for people who are read in the way that I'm read
in these big classrooms where we see this toxicity.
So, I would actually recommend if that's your teaching style, thinking about what you can
do to take a step back, right?
It's in how you hold your body.
It's in what your students call you, right?
Could be doctor something, professor something instead of your first name.
And that personality can help shield you from this behavior.
So that's what you can do when you're right at the beginning.
What do you do when you're sort of in the middle of it, in the middle of the course
and you're seeing problems?
I highly recommend embracing ambivalence.
So here's what I mean.
Some days you may wake up and be like,
my mission is to educate the misguided youth.
I will make them think differently about games
and about the world, and it may take time,
but I'm on a mission, right?
And there are days you may wake up and be like,
I am so tired of trying to beat my head against the wall
to educate the misguided youth.
Because often it takes time.
They may be jerks all the way through your class.
And then three years later, wake up and be like,
oh, that was so useful.
But they're long gone.
And you're long gone.
And so you have to, I don't know that there's
one answer or another.
But I think sitting with that, sitting with the fact
that it can be both important and it can suck,
that's really important.
Giving yourself the permission to do self-care.
So if you need to walk away from a situation,
you need to go hang out in your tub
and pet your cat or whatever.
People don't really pet cats in tubs,
but that seemed like two comforting things at once.
That it is your right to have that time for self-care.
And I think for those of us who do research
as well as teaching, it's really hard to feel like
you have the right to take time for yourself.
What do you do when things are on fire, right?
Not at the beginning, not in the middle,
but when there's an active crisis.
Don't keep quiet.
There's a sort of sense of shame and unspeakability
around this stuff.
And this is one of the reasons that I wanted to give this talk
is that it feels like you can't talk about it.
Because we're supposed to want to support our students,
because we think this is just an issue that's happening to us.
But I highly recommend telling people.
They may not always be receptive,
but it's going to go better in the long run for you
if they know.
document the hell out of everything.
So if you get an email from a student,
make sure that you've saved it.
If you have an incident in class,
do a little write up of it and send it to your chair.
And you can even send it and say,
not asking for any action,
I just want to document this while it's fresh
and let you know this happened.
And that creates a paper trail.
So if there's a larger issue.
So let's say you're tenure track and you go up for your tenure review and they say,
all you students hate that you teach feminist and queer stuff.
You can say, let me show you the paper trail that demonstrates that
there is systemic discrimination going on here.
You may encounter very well-meaning people who say,
don't write that down, let's just chat in my office.
Don't do that. I'm sure they mean well,
but it is in your best interest to have a trail.
And then what do you do for the long haul?
So you've made it through the trash fire.
How do you just keep going?
I recommend building a community of folks
who know what you're talking about.
So it can be amazingly, amazingly helpful
just to talk to someone else who's like,
that happens to you, that happens to me.
Because again, we feel like we're alone with it.
We feel like it's really overwhelming.
And that community may well be outside your institution.
So in moments like this, where we have other educators
around us from other institutions,
I recommend just like scooting up next to somebody and be like,
is that happening to you?
And then when it happens, text them and be like, what?
What just happened to me?
And it really actually helps.
This is a technique that I learned from Alex Agloro, who
used to teach at WPI and is now at ASU.
I feel mixed about it, but the idea is to teach the students who are there for the right
reasons, to teach the students who you want to teach.
So that means look out at a room at 260 people and find the five that really care and think
about teaching to them.
Now it's tricky, right, because you're not trying to jettison all the other students,
you're not saying they don't matter, but it helps you sustain, it helps you survive and
thrive if your intended audience is people who want to be there.
So what can you do if you are colleagues of folks going through this?
We're going to do this one as kind of do's and don'ts.
And I'm going to ask you again to take a second before we do this and sort of ponder.
So, do you think of yourself as an ally?
If you think of yourself as an ally,
when was the last time you actively advocated
for a marginalized person in your program, right?
So not just in private said, oh yeah, that's hard for you,
but actively went to bat for somebody.
That's what we need, right?
This is what we need, is active advocates.
This is true in all of diversity issues,
not just in education.
We don't need just allies, we need advocates.
We need your help as our colleagues who have more privilege
and who aren't facing these same issues.
So when you're trying to address things, right?
Maybe you're like, yes, I'm an advocate now.
I'm gonna take a stand.
Here's what I recommend not doing.
Don't give advice without knowing what you're talking about.
And that's going to take some active education.
That might take going online and reading about things.
That might take having conversations with your colleagues,
if they're up for it, right?
You don't want to be like,
can I pick your brain about how people are mean to you?
That sucks too.
But before you tell people what to do,
make sure you understand the situation.
Don't dismiss the concerns by saying,
oh, you're making students better.
Yeah, maybe.
But that doesn't mean that all these other issues aren't true.
please do not debate us or interrogate us, right?
If someone comes to you and says,
gosh, I could really use your help, I'm being harassed,
or I'm facing a hostile environment.
If you ask us 20 questions to make us prove it,
or you try and play devil's advocate, we're done, right?
It doesn't feel like you're there to support us.
Like, we live these experiences, you have to trust us.
Don't ask marginalized colleagues for extra labor.
So for example, another very well-intentioned colleague
said to me, gosh, you had such a hard experience
in that games and society class.
Wouldn't you like to do a tour of all the other classes
in our department and go and tell all the students
about how hurtful it is when you're harassed?
And that'll help them realize that you're a person too.
Yeah, I bet so.
But you know what you don't wanna do
when you've just stared?
Remember the thing where I'm like really paranoid now?
Like to go and be emotionally vulnerable in that way
is not the best way to support your colleagues.
So here's what you can do, the flip side.
Believe your marginalized colleagues.
I can't stress enough how much this is really important.
So seriously, just making us feel like you believe us
is a huge step.
Teach diversity in your own classrooms.
So there is literally no class you can teach.
I mean this absolutely.
Where cultural issues and social issues are not relevant.
That doesn't mean that you have to have half a semester
on those things, but they are always present.
And the more that you normalize teaching them,
the more that it doesn't make us the weird ones, right?
They can't be like, oh, that professor,
that's where we did the weird queer stuff.
If it is spread out across your program,
if you're modeling for them
that privileged people also care about this,
it helps tone down the hostility across the board.
Be an advocate, not just an ally.
and show the heck up, right?
So let's say there's a diversity event in your department.
It's about working with students,
it's about diversifying your faculty, whatever it is.
If you do not think of yourself as a diverse person,
or like diversity's not really the thing you work on,
you need to be there, right?
Often it's the people who are already working
on these issues who show up to those things.
And we need to be on the same page.
You need to see these things for any real change to happen.
So I'm going to close by thinking about this broader question, programs and institutions.
Those of you who are currently running game programs, those of you who are spinning up
game programs, I think we know that more and more are popping up all over.
So it's actually a really important moment to get these things in on the ground floor.
Hire multiple diverse instructors.
So when you have one person.
It all falls on them, right?
And I know this isn't always easy, right?
You have budget constraints,
you have tenure line constraints.
Like this is easier said than done, I get that.
But I came into UCI with a colleague, Aaron Trammell,
who was in my position too,
that has been amazingly helpful.
Because when these things are happening,
someone is there with me.
Offer multiple courses that address culture.
So like I said with that Games and Society class,
when it's just one class and they take it off
and they try and get the heck out,
They don't engage thoroughly.
If you can incorporate these concerns
across your curriculum, then it becomes normal for them
and they know they have to confront it.
Educate your students about how to act with their faculty,
and how to act in the classroom.
This isn't just about me wanting them to be nicer to me.
This is a professionalization skill.
This is something that's going to serve them
in their team building, in their teamwork.
Simple things like how to write a polite email.
Actually, it goes a long way.
I do a workshop at the beginning of every class
on how to write a polite email.
And it gets a breakdown of like, write this sentence,
then write this sentence, then write this sentence.
And oh my god, they get so much nicer after that.
Because you don't get those 3 AM emails.
They're like, what's the assignment?
I don't know it.
Reply ASAP.
I highly recommend it.
If you're working on the program level,
or this is kind of the institution level,
recognize the labor that goes into these issues.
So if you're doing a review, for example,
of someone who's been facing harassment,
recognize that you may need to take into account
that they've been able to produce less work
because they've been dealing with these issues.
And then have your own resources at the ready.
So have a kind of packet for this stuff, right?
It shouldn't be professors who have to figure it out
and reinvent the wheel,
especially if you're hiring folks who haven't worked
as professors before, educators before,
or folks who are brand new to the institution, right?
It's hard to navigate that.
So do it once, share it with folks, and it'll be there.
Tell your instructors that you support them.
and then actually support them.
It's really easy to say, we're here for diversity,
we're here for you, but you have to actually put your money
where your mouth is and do it.
So I'll just wrap up by saying that if we are serious
about diversifying games education,
and I think that's something that does matter
to a lot of us, we need to be serious
about addressing student toxicity.
We need to create an environment where diverse educators
and culturally engaged education
can not just be part of our community, but can thrive.
Thanks.
Thanks very much.
So I think we've got like 10 or 11 minutes for questions
and I'm told that you should come up to the mic.
And also I totally forgot to tell you at the beginning
to silence your cell phones.
Little late for that.
And also to fill out your e-mails.
Hi, my name is Brian. I teach game development at a high school in California.
Yeah.
And it's kind of contextually different high school to college,
but my main interaction with toxic gamer culture is student to student.
Yeah.
And invariably my best students are my young ladies.
And I'm pretty good being reactionary about issues, you know,
starts cred checking and sometimes ramps all the way up to full-blown sexual harassment.
Yeah.
I feel like I'm good at being reactive to those issues.
Do you have any tips on kind of proactively
heading those things off before they show up?
Yeah.
It kind of depends on the structure of how you're teaching them, but I would go back
to this thing of setting expectations ahead of time.
Like, if there's a way to have a workshop about that ahead of time, so that they know
that something is on your mind and something that you expect of them.
I was also just having a conversation about toxicity in eSports the other day.
And this great suggestion that came up is to try and promote the value of sportsmanship.
Right? Like, I'm not a sporty person,
but people who play sports often care about the value
of being good community members.
So if it's possible to kind of foster that
and get them enthusiastic,
like have a sportsman of the month or something, right?
If there's some reward for being a good community member,
then that might model for them
that that's something they're striving for.
Thank you. Yeah, thanks.
Hi. Hey.
I'm Naomi and I teach
and I'm currently running the game program at NYU.
So my question is about the the curriculum aspect and specifically the course that you were teaching which like you said
It's a required first year course, right?
I'm wondering after having taught that course in the experiences you talked about
How do you feel about the idea of requiring a games and culture
course as part of the curriculum as opposed
to other approaches, some of which you mentioned, right?
Like, rather than having a required course,
having these topics spread throughout the curriculum
as a sort of required part of multiple syllabi,
or having an elective that goes deeper into these areas,
or multiple electives, where then you might mostly
be getting the students who want to be there.
I think it's a great question, right?
Because the advantage, I mean, the fact that it was required wasn't a mistake, right?
It was a pedagogical decision that all students coming in, and the fact that it was their
first class also wasn't a mistake.
Someone put real thought into that, right?
Which is that they come in the door, they're required to think about games and culture
right off the bat.
And when you make it an elective, then the people who opt in, and I've totally seen this
at other institutions, the people who opt in are already on board, right?
I think it's a kind of both and approach, right?
That if there's some element where it's required, but also some element where they can opt into
more or even if there's multiple courses that at least address culture in some way that
are required, right?
There's something about it being that one token class that they get out of the way as
opposed to something they are really expected to engage with throughout.
I think that's where that attitude, that dismissive, yeah, that dismissive attitude comes from.
So, I know not every program has a ton of space for new courses, but if there's a way
to bring it in at multiple points, I think it helps.
So would you favor something like you have to take at least one course within the area
and you have a number of choices, or like take this many credits of this type of course
during your
Yeah, I think that's actually a really smart answer, which
is like, let's say you have three different courses that
are games and culture courses, and they have
to pick one of the three.
What's nice about that is that they still have to do it,
but they feel like they've made a choice.
And they have made a choice.
But they feel like they've opted in in some way
that they have agency over.
And I think that would actually really help.
OK, thank you.
Yeah, thanks.
Hey.
Hi.
I'm a game student.
What would be your advice for underrepresented group
students, especially in a class where there's
like no courses about genders or something like that,
where they have to be the teachers for their other
students, while also being afraid of being judged
by the others because the class just started
and they're here for three years with other game students?
Yeah, so just to make sure I understand your question,
it's what do you do when you are yourself a marginalized
student in a class where these things aren't being addressed
and you kind of are in the role of needing to educate your
peers at the same time, plus you feel nervous about it
because you're worried people will respond badly.
Yeah, that is.
Yeah, I mean I think it's a big issue, right?
And right now when we don't have these classes
that address things, when it's not on the table,
then it does fall to our marginalized students
and they get pushed further and further out.
Like that extra labor falls on them,
but also then they feel like farther marginalized.
So I would say to whatever extent.
those students have the bandwidth to build community,
it helps.
Like it's sort of like being a professor,
being an educator and finding other folks
who have similar experiences.
I have an undergrad who's amazing
and she felt really pushed out of our games major
for just that reason.
So she switched majors but she built this amazing team
of like queer women of color who make badass games,
who don't come out of our games program
and I think it's really helped her.
So that's, I would say one thing is,
I'm not saying exit the games major.
I'm just saying like.
If you can build community, it helps.
I would also say identify the faculty who are your allies and your advocates.
That might mean looking to other departments.
That might mean looking for folks who aren't your instructors.
Now on the instructor side, that's extra labor that you take on to work with those students,
but I've seen it be really helpful for students themselves.
Yeah, I've seen situations where there's only one teacher who could be an ally.
It's always going to be an extra labor for them.
The students that are from this group are not going to be checking on them because they
know that there's going to be extra labor.
You're absolutely right.
I think it's a big system of problems.
I guess my feeling is that privilege...
I'm thinking about these vectors of privilege, right?
And like, an undergrad isn't gonna solve
the larger systemic problem.
An undergrad has the right to be supported.
So I would rather that an undergrad come to someone like me
and look for assistance, and then I go up the next, right?
But different faculty may feel differently.
I just feel a lot of responsibility to those students
because they don't have the power to change that, you know?
Okay, thanks.
Yeah, thanks.
Hi, I have a similar question.
My game design program that I'm enrolled in is very small.
We're growing, but we certainly lack diversity in the students
and especially in the faculty.
I'm not convinced that.
my teachers, my professors, the upper faculty are aware
of this issue and how it's affecting students.
Yeah. I like to think of myself as a leader in my program
and I would like to know how can I personally try to shape
and change the atmosphere in my program before I graduate.
That's a great question and also thank you for doing that work.
That's really hard to do on the student level.
Thank you.
Yeah, I think this thing of finding allies who can be an ear,
and sometimes what an ally can do is even if they don't have the power to change things,
they can go up the ladder, right?
They can go to the chair, they can go to somebody like that and be your advocate in that direction.
The other thing I would say is if you feel comfortable talking to someone like whoever runs your program or your chair
I'm not sure what kind of program you're in and I know that doesn't always feel comfortable the more that you can make your voice heard
it's helpful, at least then they can't say
they didn't know it was happening.
And the third piece of it sounds like
what you're already doing,
which is organizing your student community,
because then let's say a new student comes in,
and let's say a woman student, right,
and she sees you, right?
She sees you as a role model,
she sees your community as a role model.
So it's a slow process,
but I think you're doing pieces of it really right.
All right, thank you for your time, Bo.
Yeah, thanks.
Hi, thank you for your talk.
This is great.
My name's Price Jones, I'm the MFA director
at the Academy of Arts School of Game Development.
And my question's more about
how do you address your colleagues?
Do you do it always one-on-one,
or do you ever set up workshops
to have these kind of conversations?
Yeah, that's a super good question because it's touchy.
I think, again, there are a lot of well-intentioned people
who it can be hard to have these conversations,
even colleague to colleague.
And academia, especially on the tenure track,
is super hierarchical.
We like to think that it's flat, but it's super hierarchical.
So especially if you're coming from a position,
a more junior position like myself, it can be hard.
I think having one-on-one conversations, in my experience,
has been the most effective.
Or if there are moments like in a faculty meeting to shout out something small, it kind
of depends what the affordances are in your program.
So where I work right now, the preference of my chair is that we don't do like a big
group workshop.
When I worked at USC, we had opportunities to do stuff for faculty specifically, which
was really nice.
So I would say finding the opportunities that you have and also finding what feels comfortable
to you where it's not going to be, you're not going to then become the...
target of hostility, right?
Right.
Yeah.
Great.
Yeah, it's kind of dependent on the program.
That makes sense.
Thank you.
Thanks.
OK, I think we've got time for one more question,
if anybody has one.
Hi, thank you very much for this talk.
I teach in a small games area in a larger interactive media
program.
And my
This feels like a really problematic question,
but I've been having it, so I'm kind of curious
to hear how you respond.
We do have a lot of LGBTQ students in our program
and marginalized students.
And what I'm curious about, because of how our faculty
aren't very diverse, and because of how I present,
I'm sure there's toxicity in the program,
but I don't know about it.
So my question is sort of.
how and should I want to surface it in order to address it?
I would say yes.
How?
Do you have any recommendations for how to approach that?
Yeah, I would say two things.
One is town halls I found really useful.
So it's where you, at the end of a semester or whatever, you get the students together
and you just open the floor and say, please feel free to share what your experience is
like and the faculty just listen.
The faculty don't talk.
And often that stuff will bubble to the surface.
The other thing is identifying students who you think maybe could use some support and
just...
being like, hey, come to office hours.
I'd love to chat with you about what school's like.
Not to pressure them, not to tokenize them,
but then sometimes those things will start to come
to the surface there, too.
OK, thank you.
Thanks.
OK, I think that's time.
Thanks very much for your questions.
Thanks for listening.