It's not so warm because apparently I brought the weather with me.
So I apologize for bringing the depressing weather.
And also some numbers.
So here's the thing.
In February, around 850 games launched on Steam, which is about 40 a day, and about
82% of those didn't even make minimum wage.
Now later in the talk I'm going to explain where these numbers are coming from, but by
this I mean that a singular person, the money that came out of 82% of the games that came
out on Steam would not support a singular person on American minimum wage, which I had
to Google.
And of every other game, 7% of those games that launched on Steam actually made enough
money that the studio would survive.
Again, this surviving thing is kind of my opinion of how much money you would need to
survive, but yeah, roughly about 7% could actually go on and make another game.
So anyway, hello, I am Mike.
I have been writing about games for a very long time.
If you know me already, you maybe know me from when I was at IndieGames.com many moons
ago, Gamasutra, and other places.
I then joined publisher TinyBuild several years ago.
We did a bunch of cool stuff.
And then last year, because I'm an egotistical maniac,
I decided I had to start my own publishing label
because I need to control everything.
And that has been going all right, actually.
Thank you very much for asking.
We released Descenders last month.
The developers, RageSquid, indeed, woo!
They made Action Henk before, which was an incredible game.
And then they stepped it up for Descenders, made a downhill mountain biking game,
and it has done pretty well for us.
It's made more money in the first month
than Rage Squid made in the lifetime of Action Hank.
So, I'm obviously a marketing genius, but it's been really good.
It means that all of us, we can all continue to publish slash develop games for a while
now.
And I have other games, I've just not announced them yet, because I like to keep things close
to my chest, so we're actually announcing the second No More Robots game next week,
and maybe if you're polite I'll show it to you.
So yeah, as you probably knew going into this talk,
I don't know why you're here.
This is gonna be horrible.
I'm gonna just give you loads of numbers now.
Some of them are going to be more meaningful than others.
I'll say that straight up front now.
I'm giving you all the numbers
so that you can then decide afterwards,
well, I think those ones were bull
and all this kind of stuff.
But I felt like if I gave you everything,
then it might help.
So I'm gonna tell you what the average game
is selling on Steam now,
how much money you can actually hope to make,
because obviously the average game on Steam
is cack. Whether being in early access does anything, whether having a publisher does
anything, whether pricing your game, like the price that you choose for your game makes
any difference, and whether there are certain genres that just seem to sell better, in case
you want to try and do that.
So, before I start showing numbers, this is the reason why I need to give this talk.
This is a genuine email that I've received, and I receive emails like this all the time.
The problem is that games aren't selling on Steam anymore.
I mean, not on many platforms, but specifically Steam, but a lot of developers still think
they are.
And that's kind of because developers are looking at these three things here.
A lot of people are coming to me saying things like,
oh well, our game's a bit like Limbo,
and Limbo sold millions of copies, so my game will as well.
Oh, God, that's not how it works.
But I get that all the time, genuinely, weekly.
I get people talking about games that came out two years ago.
Even games that came out one year ago,
you can't even use them for comparison anymore.
Because a lot has happened in the last year, right?
Video games are all over the place.
Especially with Steam Direct opening up.
Anyone can put a game on Steam now.
And you can't rely on just being on Steam
to sell your game.
A year ago you couldn't.
Now you are, you're gonna not do well if you're doing that.
And I really need to drill this home
because a lot of people do not listen.
So I'm going to show you numbers now.
So all of these numbers are estimates.
I don't have some magic backdoor to Steam, OK?
However, I have been doing this for a while.
Even back from when I was writing about games,
I was working out sales figures, et cetera.
In fact, if you were here three years ago,
I gave a talk about sales figures across all platforms.
And that was, as far as I understand, pretty close to the right numbers.
So, I've been doing this for a while.
I think these numbers are pretty spot on.
Let's just do it, shall we?
So a year ago, a year ago, this is kind of how games were selling.
And it was bad a year ago.
It wasn't good.
On average, games that were coming out on Steam round about February to March in 2017
were selling about 500 copies and making about $2,000 in their first month.
And I include the average price there as well because I think the price is going to be an interesting thing.
Maybe you want to take some things away from how much people are pricing their games at
and how much money they actually get out of that.
This is now, so this is me taking every single game that came out on Steam in February,
working out pretty close estimates for how much they made.
I'll say that I've been optimistic.
I would say there's a lot of games that sold zero copies, but I can't prove if they sold
zero copies or not, because it's a difficult thing to check.
On average, the average game on Steam now is selling about 50 copies in its first month
and making about $250 in revenue.
I'm using all the medians here because there's also some big launches, right?
That's not to say there aren't massive games that come out.
It's just that they are a very small piece of the pie, really.
The average price is $5.
which I think is just ridiculous.
But yeah, basically Steam is very rapidly
just becoming like the App Store before it and everything.
And it means that you haven't been able to rely
on Steam to sell your game for a while now,
but now especially, please, though,
I see a lot of new developers coming in and thinking,
if I put my game on Steam, people will just buy it.
It's not gonna happen.
Being on Steam means nothing now.
It hasn't for a while and now it does not at all.
So yeah, Steam Direct launched last summer.
It means anyone can pay $100 to put their game on Steam.
We're getting nearly 900 games.
I imagine it's going to break 1,000 games a month soon.
So on the day, like we launched Ascenders last month.
I think there were like 45 games that came out that day.
And not even small ones, there was a couple of other games which were big names.
So it's a problem.
So yeah, this is horrible, but I'm sure a lot of you right now are sitting thinking,
yeah, but they're all crap though, aren't they?
and I'm not going to put out a crap game.
And you know what, you are right.
A vast majority of these games
that I'm using to put these numbers together
are just Unity Store asset flips
or just rubbish.
I think the day the Descendants came out
I worked out that like
about 35 out of the 45 games that came out
One of them was like a clone of, you remember that helicopter game where you hold the space bar?
And made the helicopter go like that.
Um...
You're not competing with MRE, let's be honest.
You're not competing with those games.
So those numbers I just showed you, remove them from your brain immediately.
I don't even know why I showed them to you.
Um, let's look at some proper ones.
Now this is incredibly objective because this is, uh...
Is that the right word?
This is me removing the crap.
Your idea of crap might be different to mine, so maybe these numbers will look slightly different to yours.
This is when I am trying to decide how my games are going to sell, I am using these numbers right here.
So these, once I have taken that over average, and then I have removed all the games that I think were never going to sell in the first place,
and only left the ones that I think have a shot of doing well.
It looks a bit better.
2,000 copies on average in the first month.
12,500 in revenue.
And you see that average price is like double now.
The average price is $12.
Again, I'm going to talk a little bit more about this
later, but I think price is important.
And anybody who stupidly follows me on Twitter knows
that every now and again I'll go off about people pricing
their games too low.
Let me get to that.
So this guy, Jake, he's been doing some interesting,
cool stuff, he's British as well.
I don't know why I had to tell you that.
And he has essentially worked out
this incredibly rough formula.
I say it's incredibly rough,
but it's matched Descenders perfectly up to now,
and a bunch of other people I've talked to as well
have said it's matched them pretty well.
So essentially, you take your first week of sales,
times that by two and you get roughly your first month,
times it by five and you get roughly your first year.
So again, this is an even super rougher estimate
than things I've been giving you.
But taking my numbers and using his formula,
you're looking at about $30,000 in revenue on average
for the first year.
So, then what I've done is I've gone through, I've been, I've not just been taking how much
games sell and how much revenue they make, I've been then just pulling together all information
about what kind of games they are, whether they're an early access, etc.
Early Access is just a funny one.
We did Early Access with Descenders.
And I think for a while now, the perception of Early Access,
I think sometimes we get a little bit worried
that people aren't going to buy it because it's in Early Access
and it will put them off.
From what I can see, it's just not true at all.
It seems like, if anything, sometimes a lot
of the biggest releases in February were Early Access
games.
People, a lot of players are used to being involved in the development of games now and
actually find it a bit of a turn on when a game is early access.
So the numbers aren't that much bigger, but you can see if anybody has been worrying about
putting their game in early access and thinking, what if no one wants to buy it, I don't think
that's the case at all.
And I don't think you should worry about that kind of thing.
Does having a publisher help?
So, the answer seems to be yes.
It's a tricky one, right?
Because it depends as well on so many factors.
It depends on the kind of deal you get with the publisher.
Being a publisher myself, I know what some of those deals look like.
So the numbers are higher, the numbers are making five times as much money,
but of course then the publisher's taking their cut,
and I don't know what else they're taking.
Your dignity.
But you've got to keep that in mind, right?
And you'll see as well, the publishers on average price their games higher as well.
I keep going on about price, so let's talk about it.
When we were launching Descenders and we were talking about the price of it, Rage Squid
was scared to go with a higher price.
And I don't blame them because it looks like, when you look at the price of games, it looks
like you players aren't buying games that are higher prices.
I did a horrible publisher thing and thought, no I didn't, I just talked them into a higher price.
We launched it for $25, and that higher price point has honestly done incredible things for the game.
Now, that's not to say that that translates perfectly to your game, I'm not saying...
I'd just knock it up by $5. That's not how it works.
If your game is worth $15, then it's worth $15.
All I would say to you is that people are paying more for games.
They are. They absolutely are.
And I honestly, sometimes when I talk to people in our community, for example,
a lot of players will say that...
when they're looking at all the games that are coming out on Steam that day,
the ones that are higher priced will actually jump out at them
because they're like, well, why do they think they can charge more than everybody else?
So, in a really weird way,
if your game, if you think, you know what, my game might be worth
more than I'm giving it credit for.
It makes such a big difference.
Because as well, down the line, you know, when it comes to sales,
when we eventually, far, far, far down the line,
do a half-price sale for Descenders now,
it's basically like a full-price launch for the average game on Steam.
which is amazing for us.
But yeah, this is one of those situations where
maybe you know what your game should be priced
but do have a think about it.
I really urge you to because I talk to developers all the time
who are just pricing themselves lower
and it makes a massive difference, you know.
I did one of these word clouds. I've not done one of these in years and I thought it might be funny.
So I took all the genres of the top 100 games and turned them into one of these word cloud things.
I mean, survival and crafting are big, did you know? I couldn't believe it.
And shooters, who would have thought? I like that bikes was there.
I feel like I was doing one for the team.
I mean, there was a couple of other bike games that came out as well, but ours was best.
And then there's a few smaller ones as well, which were interesting.
Visual novels do pretty well.
I don't know how many of you play that many visual novels and stuff, but
visual novels rarely explode,
but they, a lot of the time, do pretty darn well.
So, yeah, it's...
This is probably the least useful slide in the whole thing, don't worry, but
I just thought it was pretty, so I don't care.
Right, I talked really fast and showed you a bunch of numbers.
So here's a bit of a recap.
About 93% of people who are releasing games on Steam
right now, they don't make enough money
that after they've released that game,
they can go make another money.
Another money?
Another game.
And I mean, of course, you got to be, you know, I'm sure a lot of people are doing it while also having a full-time job or whatever.
So that's not taking that into consideration. This is, I'm talking doing games full-time.
So ignore me if you're not one of those people.
But the average PC game, even after you cut out all the crap,
is making about $30,000 in the first year.
What you should take away from that is that you should have a plan, basically.
You need to have a plan.
Myself and RageSquid, we planned for what if no one cares about mountain biking.
There was every chance no one was going to care.
So we planned what happens if this game tanks.
and we had backup plans for what we were going to do.
You need to have one of those,
because you don't want to get caught in a horrible situation
where you release your game,
it doesn't do as well as you were hoping,
you feel like crap,
because everybody does.
Even if your game does well, you feel like crap, right?
So you're going to feel like crap.
And then you just, you know,
you just spiral because you don't know what to do.
So I just urge you to please look at this number
and think, what happens if I make that in year one?
Will I be okay?
What can I do on the side?
What can I do about it?
So things you can do about it,
you can come to one of these talks.
There's not enough time for me to talk,
you know, in this talk,
about how you actually do be in that top 7%.
However, I am giving talks tomorrow and then the same talk on Friday, so if you can't make
it tomorrow, then you can come to the Friday one.
Don't go to both.
That would be silly.
But it's going to be a talk that doesn't cover all of the things you've already heard before.
I'm not going to be talking about how to write a press release or make a trailer or talk
to YouTubers or anything like that.
I'm going to be talking about what I...
found were the most important things that
guaranteed us success with Descenders.
That no one ever talks about.
Just the sort of image of your game
and the way that you, the way your approach deals with the game and all that kind of
stuff that maybe you haven't thought about, but you really should be.
Because it's the kind of stuff that actually makes games sell now.
Cool, that's it.
Thank you.
I hope you're okay.