All right, I think we'll get started.
These blinding lights, so, okay, yeah.
Welcome to the next session in what I think is turning out to be a really fantastic day about e-sports.
And I think Frank and Pat deserve tremendous credit for curating today,
because I don't know about you, but I think we're hearing from some of the most interesting folks so far
who are doing really fantastic dynamic stuff.
And I think for me, so I've been studying e-sports for a while now,
and for me one of the most exciting things about what we've been hearing so far
is how much it's getting away from just kind of the mainstream hype conversations
and really digging into what's happening in the grassroots
and how organizations are working through this stuff.
So I'm really excited about today.
So thanks to Frank and Pat for curating today.
My name is TL Taylor.
I'm a sociologist. I'm an academic.
I'm a professor at MIT.
I've written a few books,
one of which was on eSports, came out in 2012.
It's a history book.
It was a history book the moment it came out.
in part because live streaming broke before I finished the manuscript.
After I finish the manuscript, so I'm currently finishing a book on live streaming right now to kind of bring that conversation up to date.
You can find a lot of my work online.
I'm on Twitter, so there's some ways to follow me.
And I also keep it for the more academic folks in the audience. I keep a literature page at my website on eSports literature.
There's actually lots of academic research being done in that field. I maintain a page that links to lots of academic research.
So if you're interested in that.
So today I'm actually going to talk about the roots of esports in particular,
and the powerful role communities have played in the scene,
and the transformative work they do.
And I actually think it's a really important thread to filter up right now,
and I loved how it came up in some of the other conversations today.
because we are at such a huge commercialization push and hype
that I think it's really important to think historically
and what are the lessons we can learn from those early moments of eSports.
I'm going to show you a variety of photos, a lot of them, most of them are from
I started doing research on eSports in 2003, way before the hype bubble, and sort of lived
through, you know, followed it through a kind of first crash, and now we're on this interesting
resurgence point.
So I want to start by just very briefly talking a little bit about the roots of eSports in
hobbyist and enthusiast communities.
This is really where eSports comes from.
For those of you who may be new to the scene, you know, you may be used to thinking of eSports
as like maybe League of Legends and live streaming.
The roots are quite different and I think both Nick Allen this morning and Tom Cannon
when he was talking about the fighting game scene.
gave us glimpses of that right now.
Gave us glimpses of that.
Historically, communities have been where
titles get identified as
competitive, and the scenes that are developed
up around them, and
those titles get worked over and through
by competitive communities, and I think
One of the lessons we can take from the early days of eSports history is really thinking
about how play and competition is not a static thing.
Play evolves over time.
It often evolves in conversation with new hardware that comes out.
So those of you who witnessed the transformation from LCDs to CRTs may remember how entire
ways of playing in the competitive scene had to be tweaked to accommodate for that.
So play is not a static thing and communities are the places where this gets worked over.
So the history of esports, you know, I trace it all the way back, of course, to the arcade period.
Probably some of you have seen King of Kong, so you may be familiar with some of that stuff.
But the other really important note when you think historically about communities are lands
and where people were dragging their machines together to play together and competition
emerged really naturally in those spaces.
Of course, lands have also long been a place where eSports has been commercialized, but
this kind of interesting mix of emergent community enthusiasm and excitement around competitive
gaming has always been there.
So these are some older photos.
This is the first eSports event I ever attended in 2003.
It was a Danish national final, but 30 people in the room
for a national final.
And again, super enthusiast community
that was really working hard to make that come together.
And I think one of the things that's so interesting
about that early moment in eSports
is how you had people who were kind of always working
to professionalize the scene,
but within community frameworks.
And in fact, I think we're at a moment right now too where we're hearing a lot about collegiate
esports, which I am super excited about.
Collegiate esports is another great example of a place where
Something like the Collegiate Star League actually formed because handfuls of students got together and said,
let's have matches where we're battling each other.
And so a whole scene and organization arose up around that.
And one of the things I think that's important about thinking about these hobbyist and enthusiast networks
is the role of the social in it.
It's not about individuals making independent decisions about competitive gaming.
But building play in conversation with each other and in competition with each other.
And I think, you know, one of the things that's interesting right now is I know I have over
the last few years certainly had, you know, random game developers come up and say like,
oh, why don't we turn X into a pro game or X into eSports.
And I'm like, well...
That's a good ambition, but do the communities want that title?
Communities are really good at sussing out whether or not a title is going to be good
for competitive play and in what ways.
So I think considering the work that folks on the ground are doing to make sense of high-end
play or competitive play is pretty important.
And in this regard, I don't know if any of you have been to DreamHack, but I think DreamHack
is a kind of great exemplar of
The kind of passion that goes into communities to produce playful spaces.
DreamHack is essentially mostly a volunteer organization.
If you've ever been to it, it's a massive LAN party.
It's now also a huge eSports event.
But you know, thousands of people come together, they drag their machines there,
hundreds of volunteers build up that space over the period of time.
And I think one of the things we can learn from some of these early roots of eSports
is the power of something we often call serious leisure.
People who are willing to invest time and money and energy, they may not be pros.
But they're willing to invest a lot in this space.
And that folks who are engaged there are also always finding a way around barriers.
I think very much of the early eSports scene as a kind of DIY hacking ethic that's important to consider.
I think one of the most interesting examples where we can see this...
Push to innovate practices, push to find new ways of organizing things, push to new forms
of professionalization in esports has been in broadcasting.
And so again, right now we're in a moment where we're seeing a lot of hype and excitement
about bringing esports to television or developing the live streaming scene.
But there are actually a number of ground breakers early on that were doing important
work.
in eSports broadcasting that I think we can learn a lot from.
We can learn a lot from the attempts that they've made along the way,
the kinds of practices they've been engaged in.
So this is a picture of Paul Chaloner, maybe some of you know him, red eye.
He's a long time eSports broadcaster. This is when I met him at DreamHack
in 2006 and in 2006 at DreamHack this was the only media eSports thing
happening. Paul was set up.
with a laptop and was audio broadcasting.
And I think some of these early broadcasters were an interesting testament to people just
taking whatever tools were at hand and trying to make something more of it.
So at the time it was things like shoutcasting.
Do we have audio? Can I broadcast over an audio feed something that's happening in the game?
And when you look at the kinds of work they were doing then, again, 2006, 2007,
dragging together machines, trying to figure out how do we create media production in this space.
And these were passionate, kind of committed folks.
They were not only creating jobs, but creating services that I think we're now building on and extending.
They were also coming up with ways to think about eSports that hadn't been thought of before.
So, how do you think about in-camera observing?
What's the role of the in-game camera observer?
The role of commentating, building storylines.
All of this was innovative work that was coming up from the grassroots at the time.
Some of the most important early organizations founded around media, GotFrag, Team Sportscast
Network, and Radio ITG, I think were early foreshadowings of some of the media stuff
we're seeing right now.
This is one of the favorite quotes I have from one of the people I interviewed for the
current book on live streaming, talking to them about kind of what it looked like on
the grassroots, on the forefront, building a media space around eSports.
He said, I think in some regards this world is pushing technology or using tools
that traditional broadcasting uses in a very set way and jackknifing it
and doing stuff it was never meant to do.
Little things like the basic ATM switcher you can buy from Black Magic and a lot of churches
and other public service things have certain limitations, that's the way it is.
But if you're a nerd, you can get around those things.
You can make hacks and macros.
and things that they don't tell you about.
It's not an add-on you buy.
So there's nerds that build computers.
We have all these guys that are nerding out on capture cards.
And I think that hacking, DIY aesthetic,
that so informs the e-sports industry,
whether it's from the player side
or the media production side,
is important to not get lost
as we start commercializing more as more.
Mainstream media companies are becoming interested as sports entities are becoming interested.
How do we retain this DIY hacking mentality because it has been so transformational in
pushing eSports to where it is now.
We wouldn't have the media space in the same way if we didn't have these folks working
ten plus years ago.
The other thing that I think is really important to keep in mind if you're thinking about esports,
especially those of you on the development and design side, is thinking about the ways
esports is constructed in relation to communities and not just computation.
Computation is a really important component of eSports,
but humans and communities lend a very powerful,
have a very powerful role in constructing what the digital playing field is.
And I think one of the things that's hard for developers sometimes
is that they overly privilege designed systems.
And sort of imagine that the game off the shelf
or the machine can take care.
a lot of the messy work.
So this is, and I love him, I don't think he's here, I love him dearly, Ernest Adams
and his colleague talking about video games do not require written rules, but the machine
implements and enforces them for the players.
The computer is the thing that sets the boundaries.
And as a sociologist, you may guess that my...
pitch after many years of studying competitive communities is this is not at all how it works.
And in fact, it was one of the funny things, the first work I did, my first book was on
MMOs and I saw a lot of this emergent and iterative behavior in the MMO space.
And when I started turning to esports, a couple people would say to me, you know, maybe though
the stakes are so high in esports, things will get formalized more in the machine.
Maybe the computer, the system, will lock it down a little bit more because the stakes will be so high.
In fact, that wasn't the case at all.
And when you look at eSports communities, they are regularly
debating, tweaking, iterating the conditions of play
with an eye towards skill, virtuosity, and even aesthetics.
What counts as beautiful play sometimes matters.
So this means that if you actually sort of start looking at
competitive communities in practice,
What you see are lots of conversations over things like maps, characters that can be used
or can't be used, cards that work well or don't, weapons, the number of rounds, configuration
settings, mods, exploits, bug use, moves that are preferred or not preferred.
What kind of gets validated as legitimate, skillful, virtuosic play?
And that's stuff that, while the computer, while the design system,
certainly is a part of that conversation, it's really important to understand
how communities are also extreme interrogators of competitive systems
and will tweak and modify and work with them to make them something that they want them to be.
And so I would say in my experience, spending a lot of time at esports events and watching
tournaments and competitions, you know, paying attention to the ways communities are doing
that work is really important.
Again, I think we're at an interesting moment where, you know, game developers used to...
If they didn't shun eSports, they didn't care.
They didn't pay much attention.
And so communities were also, you know, were often pretty free to kind of iterate in ways
that made sense to them.
And I think we're at an interesting junction right now where developers are getting more
interested in eSports.
The question for me is how do we not lose the value of the social work that the communities
do to make games playable.
And I would say this ties to a kind of meta point I want to make, a final meta point,
which is that we really need to understand that play is a form of transformative work.
It's not simply that players, including professional players, including eSports players, take a
system as given.
In fact, transformation, if you think about it legally, means things like adding new expression
or meaning, or producing value by creating new information, new aesthetics, new insights
and understandings.
And what I want to argue to you is that games and eSports
are always doing that.
And I think that raises the bar both for designers and how they're thinking about what
they're building, but also for us culturally and what we understand eSports can be.
It's not just rules that players are debating, but they're also making decisions all the time about preferred modes of play,
what's aesthetically pleasing. I remember once a long time ago
talking to Counter-Strike players about a move that was typically prohibited in tournaments, the duck jump, and
asking them why that was prohibited, and time and again they would say, it's ugly.
It doesn't really look good.
It doesn't have a feel of skillful play.
That's a really nuanced assessment
of what virtuosic play can and should be.
And I think for designers,
there's an interesting challenge there
about how do you put out artifacts into the world
and let them still be iterated by communities.
So this close connection, I think,
between communities and their competitive artifacts is something that we risk losing
sight of if we think too narrowly about things like intellectual property.
In fact, competitive communities have been powerful developers of some of the most important
spaces in the scene.
A very long-standing, hugely popular map in Counter-Strike, Dust.
goes back to a modding community, and in fact Counter-Strike itself has its roots in modding.
Dota, which we now take for granted as a title and a genre, again has its roots in the modding community.
And then there's also really fascinating projects like
Project M, where players are trying to again weave together iterations of other games
to present, to have a space, to do the kind of play that they find most competitively satisfying.
Now the risk with talking about transformative play and transformative work, of course, is
that we also have a climate of very narrow intellectual property boundaries.
And we, in the MMO period, we saw skirmishes around IP, for example, when players would
say things like, well, I own my avatar, shouldn't I be allowed to sell it on eBay?
And companies got very nervous about that.
I think we're...
Entering a new period around intellectual property debates where it's often third parties and not individuals.
So it's game developers and third-party organizations who feel they also have a stake.
My call today, my challenge to you, especially if you're developers and designers, is how do we have,
how do we think about a much more robust and nuanced understanding of the role of communities and IP
that understands it's sort of a co-creative process between the two?
Of course, game developers, you know, pick your favorite game, you can go and find the
guidelines in terms of service and use that guides using those.
Again, they're often about non-commercialism or content regulation.
I think generally they're too narrow an intellectual property frame for the transformative work
that we're seeing in these spaces.
And as I mentioned, I'm working now to update the eSports book to take into account live
streaming and I think when you start looking at the impact live streaming has had, and
I don't just mean the big tournaments, I mean everyday people broadcasting their play, transforming
private play into public entertainment.
This question of
You know, co-creation, who owns what, is really important.
But you can also just, quite frankly, watch on the ground.
People iterate strategies.
Communities produce preferred modes of play together, collectively.
So I'll leave on one very big meta, which is, I actually think...
My call is broad because it's not just a kind of quirky design question or a thing about
development.
I really think we need to understand eSports as cultural products with real stakes.
They matter to the culture.
And that means we have to take them seriously as transformative spaces, that they're not
owned by any one person, that communities play a powerful role in constructing what
they want their play to be.
And I think if you're...
interested in understanding how to make a
eSports space that is actually going to be vibrant. You'll be thinking about communities and iteration from the get-go.
All right, I'll end there. Thanks.
There's a lot of time for questions.
Thank you.
Just a quick question about where do you see speed running fitting into all of this and
the sort of growth in that area?
Yeah, I think speed running is fantastic.
Again, it's one of those things, there's a history, right, to it, but it's another great
example of people taking the bounds of the system.
pushing them to their limits and exploring what they can do.
And I think it's really fascinating to see the way speed running has garnered now an
audience through live streaming and a spectatorship where people are participating in that form
of play.
And of course, depending on if it's utilizing glitchiness too, you know.
Designers, I mean, not all, but some designers can be very precious about their objects.
And I think there's something quite lovely when players go in and kind of push and play
in ways that weren't always intended.
So I don't know if that gets at what you're...
Hi, I'm Sam Ellsburn, a student.
So one of the things that I think about mostly with competitive games is sort of the morbid
reality that depending on how a developer might change either a certain mechanic or
take away a skill from a certain character, that that might...
ruin a professional eSports player career, either because they can't compete anymore
or they just aren't as viable as another player.
So I just want to know what is your thought on that.
Yeah, no, I think it's a great point.
And we of course see this happen all the time when developers roll out patches that the
community isn't prepared for.
Sometimes right before a tournament.
So you're right.
I mean in some ways it's a very precarious playing field.
Of course it's worth keeping in mind that in traditional sports,
equipment also changes and can change the shape of play.
But I think one of the key things there is that
especially as developers decide that they want to be more involved in eSports,
that they have to be sensitive for the ways those ripple effects kind of work through the community.
Thank you.
It was a great talk and I really like the line as well about thinking about sort of beautiful players, that act of creativity.
And I wanted to ask you, you kind of said in regards to sort of legal frameworks that you perhaps perceived some of the,
I'm assuming some of the larger commercial companies as being a little bit too restrictive.
But the need for companies and for competitive eSports to come out of those creative and
that history of modern communities, do you perceive, I guess, a lot of the large heavyweights
in that space at the moment to be too restrictive with their games and how tenable that situation
might be?
And if so or if not, where are the spaces you might see other titles coming from?
So, my feeling right now when it comes to the IP stuff in games is that
developers are generally happy if people tinker,
as long as it's non-commercial and or doesn't affect the brand.
And I think both of those are insufficient models for cultural production.
So I both think people have a right to make money off of remix-reuse,
that that is the work of culture.
We are always working over artifacts.
And that if you really want to take games seriously as a cultural product or a sports product,
that you can't always control the brand.
So, I think the battles around this are, we're probably much more likely to see them through the live streaming stuff that's happening.
But yeah, I'd like to see, I would like to see co-creative models really flourish a lot more than they do right now.
Hi, thank you for the talk. It's nice to hear from an academic background.
I'm checking your website right now, it's a podcast and everything, it's very interesting.
My question is, how do you...
What do you think eSport is?
For me, I do competitive gaming.
Is it for glory that you're better than other people?
And eSport, right now, there's a lot of money flowing around.
So it's got a lot of media attention.
Is it because of...
Is it for money?
Is it for glory?
Or like what you were saying, there's a social aspect for it.
Is this for the bromance?
So what do you think eSport is?
All of the above and in different iterations.
So I think it can vary over the life of a player.
I think it can vary over the context of a scene.
So in my experience interviewing pro players over the years,
at the root of it is a fundamental passion for...
not just competition, but getting and being better.
And it is the thing, it's the thing that when I did MMO work, I sort of distinguished
power gamers, like the folks who are willing to fail and go over and over and over again,
that fundamentally it's that. It's a thing I don't have. It's why I would give up after
a handful of tries. But I think as people inhabit eSports spaces, of course you know,
The fame, the glory, the satisfaction, that can all play a role.
But fundamentally, at the root, I think it is something about this,
usually a deep passion for the game and a deep passion to keep getting better.
And it's part of, one of the earlier talks today,
it may have been echoed in a couple of them.
I think it's really important to think about the socialization process of
an e-sports player.
You don't just start as a pro.
And often the trajectory is you kind of start beating everybody in your friends and family network,
and then maybe it's everybody in your town, and then maybe it's everybody at the local sort of level, regional level,
and you keep going up. But I think that's often what drives folks.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Oh, this is really hot.
So, hi. I was just wondering, you were mentioning about, obviously now companies are sort of eyeing
eSports and their games as eSports in that sort of,
oh, maybe we should be doing more or getting more involved.
I was interested in which companies you think are doing that in healthy ways or in interesting
ways, because I mean, you know, you can just sort of throw a kind of, well, here's an API,
do something.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah, that's a good question.
I don't know that I have a name to name for you in that regard.
I think there are companies who are trying to work, for example, with teams.
So like the expert users become the teams and they solicit feedback.
But I think, you know, again, if you heard the team owners panel earlier, I think you
can begin to sense that it's, you know, these aren't flat systems.
They're still like who owns the stuff and where do we get feedback from?
What are the layers in which we say, okay, we're not going to listen to that, but we're
going to listen to this.
So I think, yeah, so as I mentioned, there's, I think that, you know, there are interesting
projects out there trying to do stuff, but I don't know that I would say any one company
has it perfect.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Firstly, thank you for your great talk.
I'm a professor from Taiwan as well.
My question is, you mentioned the community does matter, right?
And can you see the Xbox hand moving from the PC to mobile?
Can you see the difference between the community on traditional eSports and the community on
mobile?
It's a great question.
I was in India this last year and it was the first time I started thinking more about that
question because in India they just simply don't have the same infrastructures of play
that we do here.
And so mobile is a thing that they were thinking a lot about.
And I think this is exactly where the power of communities to figure out how to piece
together a system that's going to work for them is going to be really important.
So if folks are developing in those spaces, watching the emergent practices that are already
bubbling up is going to be pretty key.
It's not a model that we've had so much here, in part because of the dominance of PCs and consoles, but I tend to not be a purist.
Like, people find ways, you know, so I wouldn't, I would not be surprised if that becomes a viable path.
But what it looks like is going to matter a lot to how networks are configured, the context of play, and the kind of organizations that are already on the ground.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, sure.
What do you think of fantasy leagues in the whole context of esports?
Yeah, makes perfect sense to me, right?
I mean, people love fantasy sports.
It's a huge industry when it comes to traditional gaming.
I think it makes perfect sense.
Probably the most interesting thing right now is around the regulation of that stuff.
The same way with like skins gambling.
But it makes perfect sense to me. I think probably the trickier bit will be the churn issue in eSports.
So whereas in fantasy sports people may be pretty assured that they have a player or a team
that they're following year in and year out or there's some fandom that's continuous.
We know there's a lot of churn in eSports and that may be a trickier thing to have to navigate when it comes to fantasy stuff.
All right, I think that's time, unless I'm, yep.
Thank you all for coming.
Stay for the remaining eSports stuff.
It'll be good.
All right, thanks.