You are here for a panel called,
How Do You Make VR for Everyone?
I hope that's why you're here.
I'm Doug Northcook.
I'm a professor of immersive media
at Chatham University in Pittsburgh,
where we are starting a four-year undergraduate program
specifically focused on immersive technology.
And I also do various other things.
And with me today are the best people that I know.
I'll let them introduce themselves.
My name is Robin Hunnecke.
I'm on the advisory board for VRDC.
Please fill out your forms after you see the session.
It's a great way to get feedback.
And please silence your cell phone.
And if you're going to ask questions,
use the mic so that we get it on the record.
I have to say those things because that's for GEC.
I'm a professor and also CEO and game designer.
I run a program at UC Santa Cruz, which is an undergraduate Bachelor of the Arts in Games
and Playable Media, and also a master's program there, which is in digital arts and new media,
both of which help lots of people from all walks of life get access to emerging technologies
and make games for them.
And then I also am the CEO of Phenomena,
which is local here in San Francisco.
We're 30 people and we make weird games like Wattam,
which is coming out on the PlayStation this summer.
And Luna, which is also coming out on the PlayStation
in PSVR and will be at PAX.
So that's what I've been doing lately.
I'm really glad to see all of you here.
Thanks for coming.
Hi new friends.
I'm Sai. I'm previously the studio director of Alchemy Labs. We did Job Simulator and
Rick and Morty and I have left to start a super secret stealth new project and that's
basically where I'm at right now.
Hi, everybody.
I'm Kat Harris.
I previously, where Kat Harris was, at Microsoft,
doing awesome R&D design development for now,
I can say like, ooh, HoloLens 2 is out, yay!
And cool, like, Azure Spatial Anchors,
you should check it out,
because they're freaking awesome.
But now, currently, I am a designer and prototyper
at a company called Magnopus,
who did Cocoa VR and
Blade Runner VR game and also does cool VR production stuff.
So that is where I am currently at.
Yay.
Okay, great.
So today's panel comes out of a very special event
that I was honored to host back in the fall,
which is called The Convening,
which is an event that...
at Fallingwater, which is pictured here,
which is an iconic Frank Lloyd Wright designed house
outside of Pittsburgh where I live.
And the curators at Fallingwater and their directors
were gracious enough to offer me the convening for 2018,
which is a funded event to work
on a difficult design problem.
And I was like, I've got a lot of those.
So I invited a group of designers, developers, people working in VR,
specifically to ask the question that is this panel, which is,
how do we make VR something that is for everybody?
And that weekend was really great.
It was really productive.
And we've seen a lot of really interesting movement
come out of those conversations
and go back into the companies that were a part of that.
And so we wanted to come and share
some of those conversations.
And for us, this is also a chance to continue
some of those conversations with each other.
And the thing that I'm maybe the most excited about is that right after that,
Robin came back out to Fallingwater and we worked with an amazing zine artist in Chicago named Gage Linston.
And Fallingwater funded the creation of a zine that we actually have the first print run here today for all of you to take home with you.
Hopefully we have enough. If we run out, just follow me on Twitter and I'll make sure that...
a copy gets to you digitally or otherwise.
And the zine is an imagining of the future
in the year 2050, where students from all over the world
go to high school together in VR.
And it is an attempt to imagine a bright future
where we are more global and more connected and more fun
and it's really weird.
And it will be in the museum store at Fallingwater,
which is a laugh for me.
So.
So when we got up to the convening, where there's no internet and no cell phone service,
we spent part of our initial time going up to the studio space that's there, taking a
piece of butcher paper, wrapping the entire studio in it, and listing all of our problems.
And I'll tell you...
There were many.
This is one section of one part of one wall with a list of problems,
ranging from problems with content,
problem with the ability of creators to share meaningful work,
the inability of creators to work on broader use cases,
social problems, ethical problems,
people getting sick the first time they try VR and then never doing it again.
I mean, this was hours and hours of just listing problems.
But it felt so good.
It felt so good.
It was a really great moment of catharsis.
We needed to purge.
We needed to purge and just put that out there so we could like touch it.
Like, oh, these are the problems.
It was also great to just see them because then you're like, oh, now we can like tackle
them now that they're all out there.
Or just drink.
Yeah.
And so after just vomiting all of these problems
onto the wall, we spent part of the next day
kind of sifting through those problems and identifying for us
what were the themes that we were seeing
and what were the things that all
of our companies and institutions
have identified as.
the most meaningful areas to move this forward,
which is not just how do we get more users into VR,
but how do we get more kinds of users into VR.
And so we're gonna talk through a few of those pieces today
and talk through some of the things that we're working on
and some of the things that we're seeing
and also some of the things that we are hoping
that you all will work on,
because there's only four of us and there's a lot of you.
And so the first thing that we worked on up there
was talking about accessibility for users.
And that was a really broad-reaching conversation,
going from access for people with a wider range of abilities,
access related to economics, and finance.
And so we're going to kind of start there and give each of us
an opportunity to kind of talk about.
what we took away from that part of the conversation and ask each other some questions.
Yeah, and I was gonna say that I think that one of the best things about the convening was that it was people from all
walks of the creative and
sort of implementation pipeline of VR and AR and mixed reality. So we had people there that work on tools,
we have people there that work on software,
we have people that were working on the hardware and then demo content for this new stuff that's coming out.
But also people who are thinking more and more about the
the harder, longer-term problems of living in a society where this is a reality.
Where it's not like, what if there's a market or what if there's an option,
but just like five years from now or ten years from now, when it's a reality,
what is our experience going to be?
And I think that Kat was really good at talking about accessibility issues
from the perspective of trying to build like a second-gen headset, you know?
And so I was just curious to hear some of your thoughts about that stuff.
Yeah, so again, I came from the Microsoft side, so tools from hardware from trying, especially nowadays, Microsoft is very open source and trying to create this.
open foundation for a lot of different types of realities to be developed for.
And so a lot of the accessibility is, okay, everyone, especially with new facial tracking
and new sensors, we're all trying to rebuild our own systems from the ground up, and there
isn't a lot of sharing, which is the exact opposite of accessibility and being able to
get new people into the space.
And so a lot of what I have seen in the past and what a lot of developers now are learning is that if we do have these walled gardens, all of a sudden we have fragmentation everywhere.
And the whole point of open source is to, okay, we have these protocols now or we have a design foundation where
Okay, if I'm holding an object in VR, now if Sai wants to grab that object from me,
and she has a different headset or a different set of controllers, what does that look like? How do we
have that foundation of at least ideas of how that will work? And for our phones,
we all know that pinching means zoom.
like that is in any phone and any sort of tablet,
we know that that's the functionality that is expected.
But we don't have any of that for VR,
because no one's talking about it.
Or some people are talking about it,
but we still haven't explored enough.
And it's still so new.
And we can't have these divides in our foundation
for different hardwares if we expect that whole, like,
generation of adoption to be like, hey, everyone is using this now,
how do we get to that next step?
I think also just in terms of working together as a group, you know, one of the
things that has come up in a lot of these conversations is the fact that
while there are these little pockets of funding and there are little ways in
which you can engage with a particular hardware
and that creator's group inside that hardware
and stuff like that, we're a really small community.
Like you could probably reach out
and poke someone in the audience
who's either working on something
that's similar to what you're doing
or is interested in a problem that you have.
our ability to spend the weekend together talking about these problems,
it made it very clear to us that accessibility is a lot about
how much we share in terms of our design language and our problems.
And that idea of just putting the problems out there,
like this is not the first time people have made VR, you know?
Yeah.
I see you, Brenda.
Like, you know, I mean, these are not new questions.
But it's significant that at every turn,
the way that the system is designed
to have us make innovative, capitalistic decisions that,
like, make someone rich.
means that the actual research part of it is, it's not as open.
And so I think one of the things that we talked about a lot of this beginning of the
convening was just like, let's talk to each other more and like let's be honest when
we're not
really solving the problem. Like pretending that you're solving the problem is kind of
shitty for everyone.
And it also, just remind me, it also reminded all of us that like
which problems are actually problems
and which ones that we think are problems but aren't actually like
important to solve yet and just laying it all out and talking to all the different people it was like,
oh, I'm working on this and it's like, oh, why are you working on that?
Like why do you think this is a problem? And why should we tackle that one first? Because
like you saw that butcher paper again, it went all the way around the room. Some problems are very much dependent on other problems.
So it's like you have to figure out which ones we wanted to tackle first. Yeah, and in which order. Yeah.
Well, a big part of the conversation about accessibility went not just to making content
and making tools more accessible to developers, but also making content more accessible to
a wider range of users, which I know is something, Sai, that you've done many talks on.
A lot.
That's kind of my jam.
So I'm wondering if you can just speak to that part of the conversation.
Yeah.
You know, I think about that a lot in terms of like, what's the widest?
The VR is for everyone, that is a deeply feeling thing in me.
I deeply believe that VR is the most human technology we have, period.
So you have to make it for as many humans as possible and really expand that definition
of what human is, which is.
you know, not just me and what I would like to see and what I want to make.
So like a lot of what we did, like especially with Alchemy Labs content, is
again, try and make it for a wide range of human beings. And this was
both in terms of interest, age,
and also like ability level. So like, so for example,
a lot of the things that we did is we thought about like in
Rick and Morty, we thought a lot about making
everything one-handed interactions because we had failed with that with one… there
was one interaction in Job Simulator that required two hands.
It was just one.
And if we… no, that's not… that's bad.
I mean, but like the fact that you knew that it was just one and that like, oh, we fixed
it next time.
Yeah, and we worked on that. And that was another thing, like, you know,
a lot of the games I like to make are the games that, like, you know, are very, I like
to move around a lot, right? Like, I like to bend down and pick out and navigate with
a space and walk around a space. But we also had to make it, you know, a smaller space
so you could have standing room only or sitting room only. We put in
In Rick and Morty, which is we took a lot of lessons
from Jobs later and then went to Rick and Morty,
we did something where if something was on the ground,
we actually had it hover a little bit
so you didn't have to bend over to pick it up as much.
Because we found some users who had some mobility issues,
like back issues, whatever, it just sort of helped them.
And so that was something that was really important
for us to do in terms of our game content.
In addition to that, the actual game itself
was made for as many humans and beings as possible.
We didn't want you to have to be, say, a gamer.
to come in and play this. Like VR is for everyone. I want to be able to give it to
a tiny child. Although I would never do that because VR is for people who are over the age of 13 only.
But were a child to play it.
We're a five year old to grab the headset.
This comes up all the time, right?
Like if you, you know, VR is an experiential sale, right?
You don't get into VR because you thought it would be cool and then you're gonna dump
a bunch of money on a VR headset and a computer to run it or whatever.
It's the thing that you go and you try it and you experience it.
And we all know this.
It's something that we don't talk about a lot in the community.
And kids just get it.
They just get it.
Like, you put the headset on the kid, they're immediately there.
They're doing what… they don't care about looking stupid.
And it's the same as with the Wii, you know?
Like, you would give the Wii controller to someone and tell them to throw a ball in the
blue box and they would just go…
I do think that.
Like, embarrassing.
But like, our best audience is coming up now, right?
They're technically not supposed to be in the headset because, I don't know, eyes grow
or something.
Or something, yeah.
They budge.
Whatever.
I just published this article with the Oculus developer blog about universal design, which
is an architectural principle that basically says that if you design something for everyone,
you're designing something for yourself because at some point, you will be someone else.
Yeah, I think that's something that a lot of developers and designers really miss is that they design for themselves in a specific moment.
This is a temporary situation. Like many things are going to change over the years. I get very rowdy. I hurt myself. You know, my abilities change rapidly. And then there's the long term.
Yeah, I can guarantee at some point I will be.
My vision will change, my hearing will change, and my ability to play super hot and bend
like all the way backwards into like balancing half moon will change.
I hope not.
I believe in you.
Yeah, but I think, you know, it's a really easy thing to miss.
And I think a lot of people think about designing for other, they're like, oh, well, I don't,
that's not my user.
And it's like, well.
It will be at some point.
At some point, your users will change.
Your users will age.
And we're trying to think about developing
a platform and experiences that have longevity
and that are adaptable.
And a perfect example, one of my colleagues
came to my office last week.
And he is in his late 50s.
And he loves VR.
He has a Rift at his house.
His kids think he's a weirdo.
And he…
I was like, well, have you tried Beat Saber?
And he was like, no.
He's like, I had shoulder surgery last year so I can't raise my left arm above here
so I didn't get it.
And I was like, well, there's actually one-handed modes that you can totally play.
And he went and got it and then he played it and he was like, oh my gosh, I had no idea.
Thank you so much.
And I was like, don't thank me, thank Yaroslav and Jan.
But I think Beat Saber specifically is a great example of any, you can play one-handed,
they actually are, they just released a video where they're working with Subpac
to make a deaf mode for Beat Saber where you play with a haptic vest.
And that kind of thinking where that's not just a really great experience for the deaf community
and for deaf gamers, but that's also a really great experience for...
people who have full range of hearing to be able to have haptic feedback when they're
playing. So it's about, you know, creating the broadest range of experiences and adaptability.
And when we started making newer technologies that are now no longer considered new, like your
phone or even the game console or the internet, you know, even television,
When we made these media a while back, we were not that aware of the implicit bias in
our design patterns and in the ways that we think about people as a community of developers
and designers back then.
And this is the first time that we as a community have an opportunity to design for everybody
in a way that really is awake and really is aware of the fact that...
as it becomes more accessible to use a device to see the world differently, whether you're
holding it or wearing it, and that the cost of goods goes down, the explosion in use cases
and like what someone's environment is.
is huge, right? And it's really important to think about it now
and to sort of to think about the bias that you have
just even like it will be a living room with a couch
in it is a bias, right? Like some people don't sit on couches.
You know, some people don't have that kind of furniture in their living space.
Some people have sleeping mats that they roll up and then they sit on floors on
the chair.
are chairs on the floor that are actually more like a mat. You know, like there's
very different ways of living
that, you know, if you consider these things ahead of time
and you get at your unconscious bias now before the explosion of
adoption actually happens, you're in a much better place
to build stuff that's human. And this goes into making content too. Not everyone
interacts with the world
in the exact same way. People have different expectations of how the world should work.
I use an example a lot about making tea.
I make tea the correct way, which is I heat up water.
No! That is literally, you're a monster!
How could you? But like, no, but this is the thing, right? There are so many ways to make tea.
I put my, like a civilized human, I put my tea bag in a cup
and then make my water in a kettle.
And then I pour the water over the tea, and then I put the milk in afterward, after it
steeps for four and a half minutes.
But the thing is that there are other people who put their teabag in the kettle when they're
on the stove.
Yeah, I know, monstrous.
Some people put their milk in first and put the teabag in the milk, turning it into some
trash fluid, and then pour the hot water over it.
But the thing is that these are the expectations people have.
They have expectations with their world.
And when you're making content you have to understand the myriad of human beings
are going to interact with it
because then it stops being a world and it starts becoming kind of like a
tech or a game, right? Like it's not, you lose that magic.
So I'm an aggressive demoer. Like I do demos
at every conference and not just gaming conferences. I actually go to like
museums like I did...
Try Becca once.
Like, you know, I try and go places
where not necessarily all gamers,
because I want the people who don't have a ready
understanding of, like, controllers, for example.
And I watch them very, very closely.
I'm the one that people, when I talk about how I test
and how I...
get feedback, people are like, oh well that's just completely infeasible and I'm like, yes,
that's what I want. I want to hear people's tiny sighs of disappointment. They won't remember it
afterward when you ask them about it, right? When you ask them like, oh, do you remember when you
sighed in disappointment? They're like, no, I can't remember that one, that one thing, because
then they got distracted by something else and was throwing something and put their face in a
wall or whatever it was they were doing.
But I have to look for that and I have to... because that's where the world breaks, right?
And that's where I haven't thought about everything that every human might possibly do.
We have a unique skill set to design the next way that people see reality where we can decide what
physics is like and what time is like and what presence means. And that's a huge amount of power.
Like you just have a lot more power in that situation than you realize.
And it doesn't sound like genius,
the stuff we're talking about,
but it was really, really good to sit down
and just to really hammer on like,
what does it really mean to build accessible content?
What does it really mean to think about,
you know, this becoming the way people live?
And I think that's a great segue into our next section,
which is a big part of the problem sets
that we identified is both the lack of more diverse creators
and also more diverse content,
which gets back to this issue
of there's so many ways to make tea,
which is that if you're making an experience
that is about making tea
and everyone on your team makes tea the same way,
your experience is broken.
And I think that was a big point of the discussion for us,
was really talking about the value of diverse teams
because of this need for a variety of perspectives.
And that conversation went a lot of different ways.
So we can kind of jump in.
Yeah, I was gonna say that I think that this community,
I've been making games for 20 plus years,
and I've seen this community, in particular GDC,
like I first came to GDC in 1999.
So I've seen this community completely transform.
in the last 10 years, you know?
But I mean, it's just been, it's an asymptotic curve, right?
Like the more difference you get,
the more difference you support,
the more difference you see,
the more it becomes comfortable and pretty soon.
Like this room is incredibly diverse
compared to what like an experimental gameplay workshop
room would look like in 1990, you know, or 2001.
So, like, there is already, we have a leg up in this case, that we already have more
female creators, we have more creators of color, we have more international creators
in this community than any other community that has made games before and has made interactive
content before.
Like, now it's better than it ever has been.
And that is a huge...
That's a huge benefit.
And because I think we're used to not necessarily
being represented, we're much more open and sharing.
So I think this community already
has a leg up in that space.
But this idea that content can be made by anyone
is also possible now.
The ecosystem has changed so dramatically for tools and.
sort of pipelines that
it's just it's a completely different realm.
If you looked at the International Women's Day page
you know Oculus had five games by female CEOs and five games by female leads
that's 10 games.
showcased on International Women's Day. That wasn't an accident, that happened
because Facebook, Oculus has
consistently worked to promote
and support and pay for the work of women in VR.
And that storefront is a testament to the fact that they made that a
priority in their funding structures.
And that's the kind of stuff that I think we started talking about. It's like, okay,
how are we...
You know, we're all kind of at the cusp of being, you know, connected and we're relatively
around the same age, but there's an entire group of people coming up behind us.
How do we make sure that they get connected and get access?
And just coming from the opposite side of things, in like the enterprise world, they
are not gamers.
So they all look exactly the same.
They're all back-end developers, some are front-end developers.
Even at Microsoft, it was funny to see like,
oh, there's so many more people with tattoos
and colored hair everywhere and piercings everywhere.
When I first started as an evangelist,
it was funny because we were all like,
okay, no, can't dye our hair.
And then Satya got hired and we were like,
cool, we're all dying our hair purple
and we went to a hackathon and the students came up
and they were like, oh, can you tell us
who the Microsoft people are?
And the person was like,
oh, anyone with purple hair and piercings.
go find them. They know all about Azure cloud development and gaming as well.
And it was just like, what?
And it's very interesting because now you see all these enterprise
companies having to have to change because
this is not their world and it is very difficult for very
old systems to incorporate
new cultures, new ideas of, oh, you need a game designer.
Like, you have to have someone who can actually.
figure out the problems of interaction and
figure out how this enterprise application is going to
be interesting and fun and useful
for people. And so, again,
the problem is, well then, these enterprise people don't know who to hire
because they're like, I don't know who is a game... Exactly, and so then they start
coming to GDC and interacting and it starts to
evolve and change, but it's...
slow and hard.
And so it's like very encouraging when you see all these big companies like, oh, okay,
I have to hire like a game studio.
That makes sense to make my corporate internal training application because now it is.
a game, like now it is a game, it can have a 2D component, it can have a virtual
component,
AR component, and it's like, cool, we're gonna start doing this now.
It's an actual hire, it's not diversity salad. Like I've said this before
publicly and I'll say it again, like I've eaten a whole fuckload of diversity salad.
Let's get together and have a salad and talk about women in gaming.
Like, let's not.
Yep.
Like, schmoney.
You know what I mean?
I don't really need any more salad, but my studio needs to be funded and people that
work for me need jobs.
And if you're in the position to fund in VR, fund diverse people.
Just do it, right?
and fund content that isn't all the same stuff
that people think will work that kind of doesn't scale
and doesn't engage a broad, I mean like,
how many people were just like, whoa, Tilt Brush,
what an idea, being creative in a virtual space
with glowy stuff, who knew?
You know what I mean? It's like...
Tilt Brush is the best though.
This is what I'm saying.
A lot of people were like, wow, I had no idea that
virtual painting would be a thing.
That's amazing to me, like how could you possibly not?
Right? But this is the thing, if you're in the space and you're doing this
stuff, like
you make a concrete difference by being available to design, but you also make a
difference by being the one that puts the money on the table for that diverse
creator.
Yeah, and that was a big part of our conversation and a takeaway for a lot of
us was a commitment from everyone in our group to
help move that bar as far as we're able to within our own companies and institutions
and taking the responsibility of being advocates for just better content made by more different
kinds of people.
Yeah, we all sort of said could we each like this year could we each try to focus on at
least one person who's coming up in the industry.
that needs a mentor, that we can connect either with funding
or some kind of a partnership that we think could do good work in this space.
Right? And if we all just committed to just helping one person
and then that person as a result was successful and then they could commit to
helping one person
that would grow, you know, it's basically the rising tide that floats all boats.
And we think about this sort of stuff a lot.
The VR community, especially like in the very early days,
was very, very communicative and very supportive of each other.
We all talked to each other.
We're all on the same Slack channels and Skype channels
and talking constantly and sharing information
and constantly talking.
But it is that sort of thing where
we're trying to sort of reproduce that culture.
And you have to think about the culture we're reproducing.
I am planting a flag here.
for like weird, interesting, awesome content that is not content that I would make
and not content that I would see. And I'm like highly, highly committed to that. And the way we do that is sort of
building this community of
VR developers and say, well this is what we're going to do
and we're going to support each other and we're going to lift each other up. And you do that by
acting
out yourself, right? The change you want to see in the world,
being aware of the culture you want to reproduce and like putting that out.
And if you don't know how to do that, if you are like,
I would like to help do that, I would like to mentor some or fund
someone, if you're like, I don't know how to get started,
you just ask us and we will tell you.
There are microphones.
This is an invitation, I think, to the whole community
to really think about building the future of what
it means to be a person and exist in digital space
and physical space.
And that is an incredible responsibility.
And if you don't feel a little bit of that,
you've got to open your eyes a little wider
because it's happening.
And we're building.
We're building something really insane right now.
People will look back and remember this time, and some of the paradigms like the pinch are
going to be invented in the next few years.
You could be the person that invents that.
You could literally save the wrist muscles and hand trauma of thousands of people an
hour, right?
By inventing stuff that's more actually physically feasible for everyone, you could actually
be making a huge impact.
When I first started working in games, I left a PhD to work on The Sims.
So I got recruited out of grad school because I didn't want to make drones and I wanted to work on games instead.
So I was working on The Sims and there was an editor for The Sims called Edith and we called it The Crippler.
because it was like it had a bunch of clicky interface stuff in it and like little sliders and
I developed severe carpal tunnel within six months of working on it and had to get like
the ergo lady to come to my desk. I mean it was like a physically painful thing to use this editor
and it was just because some people just designed it thinking like you just need some
some sliders and some check boxes right like.
We're way beyond that now, but what you're talking about now is programming the whole
body, right?
And so when you have a body that's different or you sit differently in your living room,
you're bringing that aspect into this design conversation.
That is diversity in action, and it's really important.
And I think about this a lot because, and I hope this isn't an unpopular opinion at
Game Developers Conference, but when we bring these concepts from games into VR.
Like, we have these paradigms that we sort of have expectations for and we bring them
from games.
You know, a lot of the clicking, you know, a lot of the button mashing and the abstractions
between yourself and how to interact with this virtual world.
It's kind of doing a bit of a disservice to VR.
It is a beautiful, wonderful technology of its own.
And so what we need right now is so much experimentation and then so much sharing.
So, like, things like this are so important, especially for VR, just in terms of trying
new things and then talking about it.
Or yelling on Twitter.
I mean, Twitter's another amazing forum for screaming about the things that you experiment.
But it is this.
Like, we won't find any of these new… what's the new pinch in VR, for example?
I'm still up with the edible menu system, by the way, like picking up menu items and
eating them.
Quit the game with the burrito.
I think that's going somewhere.
I feel deeply about it.
Well, what I love about…
you specifically, I just fangirl over Cy all the time, is that you talk about all the random
shit you try and that failed and why.
But with love.
Yeah, but with love.
Because it's interesting because, again, you were saying literally outside, like, what
is love?
What is love?
we're all smart and we might actually be doing the exact same problem, like running into the exact same design issues
that someone else already ran into and already proved out and spent hours and time and money and resources
that we, like, they already knew, they just didn't share their failures, they shared what they did right.
And so you have all these people redoing experiments.
that it's like, no, we already did those experiments.
Try it with a different graphics card.
Try it with a different headset.
Like change it slightly, but because we aren't talking,
it gets rehashed and rehashed and rehashed.
And it's like, okay, we've solidified this, it's good.
Let's maybe try something new or change the experiment.
We're all very smart.
I will make the exact same mistake that you made.
Like, it's not like, oh, no, I was dumb.
I made this dumb mistake.
No, no, no.
I will make the exact same mistake.
So I love things like failure workshops or talking about like, here is a garbage thing
that I made and like putting it out and talking about it and why it failed and why it didn't
feel...
Oh, my God, if you could actually...
I've thought about like compiling like experiments of like just things that feel terrible but
like everyone...
But everyone else would do it.
Like, you know, content warning, bad.
Right?
But like, and then putting that out and like, here, let's experience these bad things and
we can talk about why it doesn't work.
And that's okay.
It's okay.
We've learned.
Yeah.
So what I, what was interesting is I also went to, I forget, this was probably like
a year ago.
And for...
this developer created locomotion and they were experimenting.
And they were like, oh yeah, if you move your arms,
you're just going to like parallax slide everywhere.
And it's because all of the games that they had played
used really good teleportation and really good locomotion
that they were like, oh, well,
we want to try something different.
And it's like,
Oh, honey, that has been tried.
It's just the games that you have played that are popular don't use it.
Exactly.
And it's like, again, we need to have more of that celebrating like,
hey, remember when we all used to puke because of this thing?
Because new people that are coming into this
this new industry don't have that background yet.
Oh, my gosh. Speaking of.
What a great segue.
The next generation.
It's like we talked about this before.
I think what you're bringing up is really important and you know what
what Robin and I both do at the university level is trying to think
think through a lot of these things and think through how can you solidify
things that aren't solidified and how can you teach students how to do things
in a way that's meaningful and applicable.
Yeah.
teach them how to take risks. I mean I think one of the things that's great
terrible about being like a VR developer or an AR developer or a mixed reality
developer right now is that there's not a lot of money to be made.
Like it's not a huge industry right now. You're not like
the number of sort of huge hits like Grand Theft Auto style
installs you know that you're gonna get like it's virtually zero.
Like, you don't have to be in this industry pretending that you're the one that's going
to make all the money because suddenly you're going to discover something that blows it
out of the water.
You know, the install bases are what they are, right?
So that takes one of the layers of like faking it till you make it out and then you can just
really be faking it and be like, well, uh.
Maybe it'd be cool to, like, slice through music.
I don't know.
Give it a shot.
Let's do that.
And I tell this to my students all the time, like, you're definitely not going to make
any money with what you make unless it's a, you know, it'll be a black swan as they say
if you do.
So, hey.
Do the thing that feels exceptionally interesting
and strange to work on that you wouldn't ever be able to do if you worked
at a company and had to pay people.
And now's the time. Just do it. You've got three, four years where you could do
anything you want.
You could smoke a lot of weed and watch Game of Thrones or you could make
Beat Saber.
You know? You choose. You know? Maybe you could do both.
Yeah. I was like, 4K Nostos.
Yeah, I remember being at a fireside chat that you did at oculus connect this year
And I remember a student came up and asked like this exact question. They were like I'm working on this game
How do I make money and you were just like you don't don't try to make money
you're a student do something that you're really passionate about and if if you're really passionate about it that will
something cool might come out of it. Well, and if you have the privilege to be a student in one of these programs,
which is like, it's a huge amount of privilege, like
you're already in a situation where you're developing skills,
you're creating relationships, you're experimenting, you're learning your own
throughput, like
that in and of itself is such a privilege, right? Like I am...
I listened to a recently, On Being, which is one of my favorite podcasts,
listened to the interview with Teju Cole, who's like a fantastic photographer and poet.
And he said something really interesting to me, which I think is relevant.
He said that if you're a person living today and you're like awake, you know.
You're experiencing kind of a level of constant rage,
just by how shitty everything is.
And the reason that Teju does the work that he does
is because he can.
It's because he has the privilege to have hope,
was the way that he put it.
And I thought that was amazing.
The privilege to have hope.
This room is filled with people with the privilege
to imagine a hopeful future for VR,
to imagine an accessible future.
and to educate the next generation with that capability,
which is like, that's pretty awesome.
So it's not like you're just saying,
here's the VR, learn how to do it.
I think what our programs try to do is,
hey, wouldn't it be cool if you were an ethical,
integrated, intersectional creator
who was thinking about this as a human problem, right?
Which is, I guess it's a little woo, but whatever.
I do sort of the similar thing but with jokes and shitposting.
So I do, it's true, I do a panel at PAX,
which is sort of like the different, another way of doing it. It's called you VR or VRnt,
which is a, it's a
thing that Andy Moore was caught saying in a roundtable interview for
Steam. So, but anyway, so I took that. And basically the whole idea is like pitch
the worst VR ideas to each other.
And it sounds really shitposty and awful, but it's actually supposedly...
It's good.
It's basically we all pitch our worst ideas to each other and then we riff on it until
they're truly garbage.
And then what we start doing is we invite the audience, and I always do these at consumer
shows, it's usually PAX, and they come up and they give us their terrible VR ideas and
then we riff on it with them.
What this does is kind of in this weird sort of subversive way, it's like trying to onboard
people into like VR ideas and welcoming them into the joke and welcoming them into...
have this conversation with us about like what works and what doesn't.
Early VR, I'm sure we all heard this, what I really want
oh, what's the, can I use a different one? No I can't. What I really want is Skyrim in VR.
And I tried to tell them I don't think
you want
that, I think you want something and I know you're looking for like
a larger more immersive world but what you're looking for is not necessarily
this
Skyrim is very empty, it's made for games right? It's made for games, it's long
walking distance like there's a lot of stuff to change here
and then you get into the like you don't know what I want, you can't tell me what
I want
You know, and then it's like, because that's you talking down to people in some ways, but
like trying to bring them in and educating them and bringing people into this thought
process about VR and then they can riff on it.
And it's always a ton of fun.
And by the end they have sort of a greater understanding about VR and what works in this.
But it's not just, it's not cheap to get started.
You can just get some assets and put them in a room
and then put the headset on and walk around in it
and like, then you're in VR.
Like, Everybody's Sad is a game that came out of my program.
And it's a game where you walk around a room
and all the objects in it are sad.
It's really great.
You open a drawer and there's like a sad toothbrush.
Aw.
Just like bummed out.
And you're like, you know, just like, it's about being sad,
right?
But like, it's funny, you know?
It's just interesting.
Am I?
when they were like, we're going to make a game of virtual objects that are overly depressed.
I was like, sounds awesome. Yeah, do it. Give it a shot.
The other thing that I'll say about this, about education specifically,
and this is something we talked about a lot at the convening, is, and
for us working at the university level, is that
education related to immersive technology or even just
computer programming, game engines, 3D, is something that
almost no one gets to touch until they arrive at a university.
unless you're in a very, very privileged community that has dedicated government
funding to buy
computers. There's a public high school in my region that has
a Unity lab. Wow. That's amazing. It's amazing.
It's like the best place I've ever been. I was like, I want to come here. Because you're giving them the tools
early so they know that that's a tool that they can use. Yeah, it's aspirational.
It's aspirational.
But those are really rare.
Those are really rare moments.
But I think this kind of hits on all of this is,
there are opportunities for all of us
to be involved in those processes.
So I go twice a year to that high school
and review student projects, mentor a student, give a talk.
And that is not something that is recorded or publicized.
I'm talking about it right now, but it's not like a glamorous thing.
It's not. I'm on the stage at VRDC at GDC. It's like, no,
I'm at a high school in the suburbs talking to a bunch of really weird kids.
I've done it for like small, like day camps and stuff like for various
populations.
It was great. I was just like,
I can't wait to talk about game development for girl scouts.
This panel is mostly a list of things that we're doing that we're like, don't you want to do these things too?
But, I mean, seriously,
I can guarantee that in most of the areas where you live there is a high
school program that would really love to hear from you
as someone doing this work and that that's where really meaningful change
happens at a systematic large-scale level with a lot of people involved
in very small places.
It's funny because like...
You can use technology to fix lots of problems.
I have a friend whose child had really intense early onset
diabetes.
And they developed a bunch of technologies
that work with the Apple Watch.
so they can monitor their child's blood sugar level at all times.
And that's created a community of people that are working at being parents and having lives
around children that are really at risk.
Those kinds of ideas happen when you're faced with a challenge in your life and then you
engage.
if you have the idea that you can just hack something and fix a problem,
you can make a huge impact on the world. And this is a place now where
you can
you can get a store asset for free,
you can put it in a world and put the headset on and see it. As long as you have access.
It's that simple in some ways. There are really easy ways to do this.
And it's just as simple as reaching out to a high school locally and saying,
can I bring my PSVR by and show them Beat Saber,
show them this Unity thing that I made.
It's not that hard to do and they will love you.
Like you will change their lives.
Literally.
Oh, yeah.
Introducing them also to like GitHub and being like, oh, by the way, this is literally repository
upon repository upon repository of free code and like with some of them nice documentation,
usually not.
Please write better documentation.
Please.
I'm begging everyone in this room.
I'm like, hey Addison, remember when I used to tell everyone to write documentation?
Hey, I got Microsoft.
Because I was like, it was insane.
I was just like, we should be writing documentation all the time
and sharing it with each other internally as well as externally.
But it's very fun because I'm like, I'll go on GitHub and be like,
oh, this is great. How do I use it?
nothing. So it's like cool, but the great thing about GitHub too is that you can say,
oh I figured out how to use this thing that had no documentation, do a pull request that is just
documentation to that thing and be like, hey dude I wrote up how to do this with a cool example,
please integrate, thanks. But like that will help kids be like, oh it's free,
I can just drag this into Unity, the free assets, like the asset store.
great resource, just like going online and being like royalty free asset.
The other education thing is when you do demo in locations that are not,
they're not normally going to see these things, you know,
like take it to a party, a birthday party, whatever, like give normal people,
muggles, you know, access to this technology. Cause you have it.
If you have it at home,
like how many of you have a VR headset at home that you could take somewhere
else?
See, that's a lot of you already, right? I know that's not everybody, but it's still a lot.
How many of you have grandparents that live in retirement communities?
It's like a handful of people, right? There are so many places where if you took
some really cool new exciting technology and showed it to people who've never seen it before...
When I had my grandfather, who at the time was 94,
try Tilt Brush. It was like the first time in my life that I've seen him like
completely just...
not, no, there was like no stone.
It was just, he was just like a little boy drawing in light.
That is worth everything.
Like if you don't wanna do it for the good,
just do it to like see the like bright eyes
on people's faces and the screaming,
like the wonder and the joy and the delight.
Like, oh my gosh, I vicariously lived
through every single person who I put in VR
for the first time.
I'm like, I remember.
I remember this moment.
I remember that.
I remember having that moment.
I've had so many people that I put in demo.
I love demoing because they come out
and they just look at me, especially first-time users.
They're like, did you see what I was doing?
And I go, yes, I saw what you were doing.
And then they were like, it was like real.
Like, it's not real, but it was real.
And I'm like, let's sit down.
Here's a couch, let's sit down.
Let's talk about this.
Let's unpack.
It's really magical.
And like every time.
every time you get the opportunity to do that like that's just a personal like
just hobby. It's a good hobby.
We could rant all day. Isn't VR great?
Yeah so we're gonna stop there and
leave some time for questions. If you have a question you can come up to the
microphone and we'll stick around and do that for a little bit and
make sure to get your zine on the way
out. There's some red-shirted people with zines
for you.
Go ahead.
Hi.
Hi, humans.
My name is Katie.
I lead the AltSpace team.
So I'm wondering, what would you give advice to for people
working on social communities?
You talked a lot about how people interact
in a VR environment, but what about when
you interact with people?
Yeah.
So the question is, what advice do we have for interacting in social spaces in VR?
We talked a lot about the fact that having standards across all these platforms would
really help, and specifically being able to sort of enforce boundaries.
A lot of what I think about in VR spaces and this kind of social engagement
also because I work on a social game,
is the fact that you really want to be able to sort of say yes or no to someone.
You want to be able to say, like, I appear to you this way,
and you want that to be safe.
And I think Timony was really great at representing this stuff.
I think a lot of the work that she's been doing at Unity is related to this.
notion that you should have ownership over your data and your profile and you should be able to control how it's used by different applications and
just the basics of setting boundaries and sharing space is something that a lot of people
are going to need to do a lot of work on until we come up with the right solution.
So that's like, you know, square one, just like
it's really important to be able to feel safe in that space.
I'll just say really quickly, I think the biggest thing for me with most social VR is that it is
it's a really difficult space to curate and to moderate and as the user base has grown in the
last couple years, especially with PSVR and more affordable Windows headsets that get a lot of
like young boys.
running wild in social VR.
They're rowdy.
It's a pretty scary place.
Like, I get terrified.
of just there's just like a group of 13-year-old boys just like chasing me around
and I'm just like I'm just like I I'm done.
Where did all these money the bees come from?
Also real quick, South by Southwest we
I also had a talk with a bunch people and one of them was from high-fidelity Liv
Erickson she's great
working at Mozilla now but she was like consent
based tools like bake it into any interaction with multiplayer
if you bake it into the beginning tool set of what you're creating
then it's not like a, oh, we have all of these issues and we don't have a system to easily
integrate or modify or build upon in the future. It's like if you have the system in the gameplay
system already embedded into whatever else you're doing, it's so easy then to be like,
oh, we have a mute button. Oh, we have a bubble button. Oh, now we have like block. Oh, you can
use this hand gesture. So like build the tool set and then share.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, Sarah too.
Yeah, Rob Koster gave a really good talk last year
about all these issues as well, looking back at MMOs
and early social design in MMOs
and how it's all really relevant now.
It's a great talk.
Oh yeah.
Okay, we'll take one from over here.
Hello, I show what buildings look like
before they get built using VR.
Yay! Heck yeah, heck yes.
Very cool.
I get to do a lot of demos
and I also get to a lot of watch of VR noobs
like try VR for the first time.
So it's like really awesome.
Bye.
Also, I found that, you know, de-gamifying things has been a big challenge and also coming at it
from that game designer perspective. So I wanted to see what your thoughts are and like sort of
where you think the industry is moving towards for like the best experiences for people both,
you know, that can walk around a room and that, you know, are paralyzed. So what do you think is
the best like technologies coming up and how would you design using them?
I'm really excited about the Quest because it has no cables.
And on the projects that we work on with Oculus,
both for the Quest and also for the Rift,
we spent a lot of time thinking about seated
versus standing and one-handed and all that stuff.
I'll be honest with you, a lot of people are leaning into the same stuff.
Like a lot of people are leaning into the sort of the super hot style experience, which
is, you know, or Beat Saber, you know, which are high action and high aggression as a result.
Like the very first time I showed Luna to a woman over 50, she was awesome.
She played the game for like two hours straight basically and at a frame rate that was not
great.
And I was like, what's your thing?
She's like, well, VR.
And then she stopped and she said, actually, I can't say that.
She said, I've only had one other VR experience,
so I shouldn't characterize all VR by it.
I said, which one was it?
And she was like, the one where the music attacks your face.
Oh, wow.
And I was like, oh, yeah, that one's really popular.
Yeah.
So I think that chill experiences, like Bri and myself,
I think there are several lady designers that
are interested in Tendon Befriend games, and collection,
and growing stuff, and chilling out.
Luna's a chill game.
There are people that are working in that space, but I wish there were more of you,
to be totally honest.
Yeah.
So you said how to de-gamify it, and I just want to be very clear about one thing in particular,
is that actually game developers are really great for VR because we look at interactions
a lot, and VR is all interactions.
So that's why we're kind of really good at this whole thing, and why we're going into
VR and why we're so good, is because we think about...
how people interact with the technology.
Now, that said, I'm also very, very excited about Quest.
But I also wanted to mention I was on a panel at OC5
this year with Josh Straub with the Dagger system, who
does a lot of accessibility.
And he actually has one really valid point,
which is that the controller systems that we've been using,
and the touch controls and things,
they make your hand conform.
to these controllers. So while the Quest is fantastic in terms of the lack of wires and
you know we can do a lot of things in terms of content, we do need hardware developers to also
pay attention to people of various ways of interacting physically with these controllers
and systems. And the more we focus on like games and high action and the hardware developers are
building controllers and hardware for that, like it does come with its own.
back. Even just the very first Oculus, like if you had black hair you just couldn't get the thing
on your head. Oh yeah. You know, like I had two developers on my team that would like have to
like do all the stuff just to get the thing big enough, you know, to go over their hair and it's
like the stuff like that, you know, like there we have problems on a fundamental level with some of
the hardware. Yeah.
I mean, just a quick note too, and there's been a little bit of talk about this if you already see in general, but as legislation starts to change, like it has for the web, where if you have, if you run a certain type of organization, you have accessibility standards that you must meet, you are obligated to do that by the government, or you can be sued.
And I think as VR moves more towards a mass-adopted, public-scale application,
I think we'll see standards, at least for certain kinds of applications, become stricter.
I actually like looking at a lot of the ADA-compliant stuff for buildings and things,
just to sort of give me an idea of how I'm making a space and what...
So much research has gone into space design for people of various abilities,
and I can learn from that.
all my own new research. There's a lot of research, especially in VR for beaches.
Yeah, architecture has been around for thousands of years, you guys. We need to hire more architects
into this space because they literally thousands of years of learnings and designs of how to make
spaces for people to work together, to be in spaces, to look beautiful.
All right. Kat mentioned that there were some ideas that... Hi, Kat.
There were some problems that we shouldn't be solving right now and that we should be
prioritizing other things.
I was curious if each of you have different perspectives on what are those visible problems
that aren't important to be addressing and where should we be shifting our focus to address
the things that are urgent.
I have a somewhat unpopular opinion.
I'm totally happy.
A lot of people are talking to, like, and ask me, they're like, oh, we have to put in
best practices.
And they're trying to do that now.
And so this is, so we're talking about like the pinch thing, like the pinch gesture.
And yes, we want to get that.
But to try and put together best practices right now is a mistake.
We are not done experimenting and especially when we're talking about all of these new
people coming in behind us, if we put out best practices docs, this is how you teleport.
And they're like, okay, that is the way you teleport.
And then it does become not the best practice, but the only practice.
People stop experimenting and looking.
So I'm very much like, not best practices.
I think for me, I was in a...
panel yesterday maybe and this is just me I'll disagree with somebody at GDC
that's cool
but the idea that we need AAA content
to move towards mass adoption and AAA games
I'm just like...
It's just, in my opinion, those are not the killer apps of immersive technology.
The killer applications are social, they're creative, and they're weird.
Because being a human is really weird, and this is a really human technology.
Traditional gaming is not a human technology.
It is a sedentary, isolated endeavor where you control things like this.
That's not what it means to be.
out and engaged and engaged.
I mean, I play a lot of games, so don't take that.
But I think this idea that we need AAA games to make VR work,
I'm just like, I don't know.
I don't think so.
Yeah, I mean, if you think about the adoption profile
of something like a phone, like what
was it that made people want to buy an iPhone, right?
It was that you could have a better MP3 player, kind of.
Right?
Like, the thing that I always talk about is like,
I would really love it if I had a pair of glasses that
showed me where to go.
Like, I just don't know where I'm going all the time.
Like, just this week, I mean, I'm
sure you can all imagine what my calendar looks like.
It's like, just even figuring out where my next meeting is
from here is going to be a pain in my ass, right?
Like, if I could just pop on a pair of glasses
and it told me where to walk.
I would do it. I'm not saying that the technology doesn't have its problems and that there aren't
massive volumes of science fiction written about the world that that becomes,
but we better solve it rather than just letting Apple implement it.
You know what I'm saying? Like this is one of the things that will happen is that if we
don't have active conversations about
non-best practices and all the stuff we're talking about is one
company will just sit on the one thing and then suddenly
we'll all have iTunes.
In your face, you know?
And like, I'm not, that's totally a diss on iTunes,
but like, you know what I'm saying?
Like some little cabal of designers
should not be designing the future of the world, right?
And so I think that like, the things
that you don't want to engage in are like,
this is gonna blow up the market,
or this is gonna blow up the market.
What you really want to be doing is thinking about
whatever you're building, whatever weird thing that is.
What are the two or three things in it that make it interesting and easy to use?
Because that's going to revolutionize the way things go.
So it's not like areas so much as your focus should be really, really about making the
best thing you can make right now.
Yeah.
One of the problems specifically is like people are like, what Robin said earlier, I want
to make money.
It's like that's not a problem you should be solving right now.
We have other problems.
Like making money is dependent on like us getting a foundation, us eventually figuring
out how to build worlds well and in a social way.
Yeah, it's a loss leading industry for a while.
Yeah.
that other problem of, oh, now that we have all that,
what is the killer app, how do we make money?
Okay, that comes after, but it's also like,
okay, not how do we make money,
but then how do we fund other people?
So shifting from this question to that question.
Yeah. Okay.
I think we're gonna have to cut questions there.
We'll, oh.
No, I was just sad.
I was like, oh.
I was just sad.
But we'll stick around for a couple minutes.
Make sure you get a zine on your way out,
and thanks everybody.
Yeah, thanks for coming.
For coming so much.
Have a great GDC.