This is episode one of the GDC podcast.
Hey guys.
So we're going to wait.
I like your radio voice.
Sometimes it just comes out.
I'm your host, or co-host, I suppose.
Chris Graft, I'm editor-in-chief of Gamasutra, and I'm joined by...
Oh, Alyssa McAloon.
I am the news editor and associate publisher who frequently forgets her titles at Gamasutra.
That's good, that sounds important.
It's really embarrassing.
Yeah.
We actually have a guest but he, we told him just to lurk in the background for the next
few minutes and then we're gonna bring him out like a big surprise as if his name isn't
gonna be in the description of this podcast.
Ruining all the mystery of the podcast production.
But you can...
Thanks for watching.
If you enjoyed this, please subscribe to our channel.
If you want to see more of our content, you can click the link in the description.
We'll see you next time.
Bye!
You can hear him giggling in the background.
So yeah, this is the GDC podcast, so maybe for a couple of minutes we should
talk about GDC and let's just talk about this podcast.
This is the first one. I mean, GDC is what, Alyssa, is it
100th anniversary? Oh yeah, at least. Okay, yeah, so the GDC
podcast, I mean, I think that we kind of were like, hey,
we want to do a podcast. It's what, uh, we want to get
into radio.
Well, there's a lot of interesting developments in GDC this month.
There's a lot of interesting GDC-adjacent people that you wouldn't otherwise get to
talk to unless you tune into a stream or read one of GDC's many blog posts.
So this gives you a more portable medium to do that.
Oh my gosh, that was really good.
Yeah, off the cuff too.
Yeah, that was way better than my explanation.
Yeah, so Game Developers Conference, even though it only comes around once a year, it's
something that, believe it or not, people are working on it all the time, all year round.
People's entire careers are based on this one week.
Isn't that absolutely mind boggling?
It sure is. It is mind-boggling. What are we doing with our lives?
So yeah, but it's practically here, right? It's March 16th to the 21st, so mark that down. 2020.
Clear your calendars for GDC 2020. I don't even like saying 2020, like the year. It doesn't roll
off the tongue at all. Yeah, and it just feels like so past the year 2000. I'm looking forward
to 2021. It's exciting. That just sounds like...
Yeah, yeah, yeah. And it's sequential too. Yeah, I mean, once you get to 2020, I feel like
you can start saying, legitimately saying, 2000 was the turn of the century. Like,
I was wearing JNCO jeans at the turn of the century. That type of thing.
I don't want to talk about what I was doing. Because I was eight years old.
Yeah, yeah. Oh yeah, geez. I'll let you all try to figure out if I was joking about wearing
JNCO jeans. Real quick, some GDC stuff that's actually going on. Things are starting to
ramp up, right? You've got IGF submissions are open now for the 2020 IGF, right? So you
should submit to that. I think you can find where to do that with a quick Google.
Yeah, accepted now through September 30th, 2019.
Oh my gosh, you are like ready.
I got the links, yeah.
Oh my gosh, yeah, and this is like the,
yeah, this is the first time we're doing this too.
Okay, only downhill from here.
So ramping up, we're also gonna be XRDC.
It's like a sibling event.
It's for VR, not just VR games,
but other stuff that you do with visual computing.
That is happening in October.
So yeah, we should come to that.
October 14 through October 16, looks like.
Oh, that's good.
Here with the notes, I'm here to cover.
No, this is working out great for me.
I don't have to hardly prepare.
Oh, we also opened up...
This is important.
So we're opening up our coffer papers for...
Actually, we already opened it up.
For our core concepts line of GDC talks and don't be afraid of core concepts.
That's just another word.
We've, uh, we've renamed, uh, the discipline based tracks for GDC.
So if you have ideas for our advocacy track, audio, business and marketing
design, production and team management, programming, and visual arts, if you
have ideas for talks and you want to share all that knowledge at GDC 2020.
Um, yeah, you should definitely submit. We implore you to.
Yeah, you can find all this information on gdconf.com. That's kind of weird, isn't it?
Is it gdconf.com or gdconf? Yeah, so gdconf.com. Um, and there's all kinds of news just spilling
out of the official Twitter account at official underscore GDC.
You know what else is new?
That's not a rhetorical question.
Your audio cut out for me there.
So I'm not sure what the rhetorical question is.
I don't know what happened.
Um, yeah, there's, uh, there's, there was another new announcement
and it was advisory board members.
So these GDC advisory board members, these are people who help us basically
shape.
the content or the hashtag content of the show, if you will.
And that kind of brings us to our guest, our super secret guest.
This person is a full-sale Hall of Fame inductee.
He worked at MegaTouch.
Producer id Software, might have heard of him.
Epic Games, might have heard of it.
He also currently runs a production consultancy, it's called Shonk Ventures.
That's the first big clue.
Shonk Ventures.
This person is a long time friend of GDC.
He's been a CA, he's been a speaker.
Now he's on the advisory board.
He's also the co-author of books called Gear Up, Advanced Game Development Practices, and
another one called Creative Agility Tools.
I don't know how this person is bending the space-time continuum to do all this stuff.
Not only that, I'm really building this up a lot, so this is going to be huge.
worked on. Credits include Rage, Paragon, Battle Breakers, Doom, Wolfenstein, and about 60 other
games, including a little app called Fortnite. Got credit on that. And so here we go. Let's
welcome Grant Schankweiler. Wow, that was overwhelming. Did we miss anything?
I don't know, I was born at some point.
I mean, that's just...
Chris, thank you for the great introduction.
That was a lot about me.
Yeah, yeah.
No problem.
This required so much internet stalking on Alyssa and I's part.
I mean, we started kind of feeling gross about it.
Yeah, so tell us a little bit about your background.
You are a producer and your consultancy is Shonk Ventures.
And tell me what you do.
Yeah, so I've been I've been making games for a long time.
I started actually making games when Pokemon Red came out.
My buddy and I swapped games back and forth back then.
And and I taught Pikachu Cut, which was apparently the wrong thing to do.
We got in a big fight.
We were.
Punching each other was great.
And I said, you know what?
I think we can make a better Pokemon game.
And so we designed our own game called Pokemon Killer, aptly
enough, submitted the game to Sony, actually sent paper
designs to Sony, and said, this is going to kill Pokemon.
You're going to be bigger than Nintendo.
They actually wrote back and said, we don't want to get
sued, but keep on designing games.
That's cool.
And that was it. From there on out, I've been making games. I started modding games and just
designing and doing goofy little things. And then I went to Wholesale University to learn to be a computer programmer.
And then I
started in the industry at Megatouch Games, as you mentioned, where I was a programmer and then quickly realized all the other programmers were
much better than me, and I was not progressing at the rate that I wanted to be. So I
So I told the creative director I would help him out with design, and next thing I knew
I was a designer, and then I was a lead designer, and then I was kind of running all the game
stuff at that company.
So that was crazy.
If you don't mind me interrupting real quick, we need to pump the brakes a little bit and
go back to Pokémon Killer.
And Sony actually must have looked at the design document if they replied to you and
said we don't want your game.
Yeah, yeah, which is of course crazy to think about.
I don't know if it was just like an intern or someone who opened up this file and was like,
just reply, it's like a kid, you know, make them feel good about their day.
But I really appreciate that and I've had the opportunity to talk to many people who were at Sony back then
and say, you know, I want my document back.
So far no one has found it, which is probably good because one, it's terrible, and two,
my handwriting has not improved and was really bad back then.
It's just got to be framed up in someone's office somewhere, this letter that was sent
in once.
Yeah, the one thing I remember was that I used red ink.
I don't know why I remember that, but I used red ink because...
Killing!
Because of the killing part.
Yeah, it was a very violent game.
Do you think that Ken Kutaragi has that hanging in his family room?
I like to imagine that he does.
I would think that he does.
So you're a producer guy and you've done talks at GDC and PAX and other places.
And your background, when I'm listening to you talk,
obviously you're well-versed in the methodologies of product development and all that.
But...
You talk about the fundamental stuff, like the foundational things. Can you
tell us like the most important parts of being a producer? Yeah, so the most
important thing that I always tell you know when I when I start working with a
junior producer is first off your communication skills, right? You have to
be able to communicate with people at their level and their
language, so I recommend all of my junior producers.
Learn a little bit about coding, learn a little bit about design and art and stuff.
I'm not asking them to become those things, but at least be able to speak the language.
I often tell them to do the thing that I do, which is like,
I'm not a senior artist, can you speak to me like I'm five and explain to me what maps are, or whatever it might be?
Because you want to start to progress to the point where you aren't interrupting meetings because you just understand things.
So communication is the first one.
The second one is just understanding that people are people, and that is ultimately
our job.
Our job is people first.
So focusing on people and making sure that they have what they need.
Another thing I always tell people when they become producers or junior producers is, congratulations,
you're now the lowest of the low.
People think producers are the lowest of the low.
It's not true.
Our job is anything from getting coffee to making big decisions.
And we do that for everybody, even if they're considered more junior than us on the org
chart.
So I tell people, in a lot of ways, you're a servant.
You're a butler.
And you're also a little bit of a camp counselor because people will come to you and complain.
So those are like the core basics.
If people understand that, then I can teach them how to be at least a decent leader based
off that and I can teach them all the processes of game development.
And those are things that you just learn as you make games.
But the core stuff, if you're not a good communicator and you don't understand people at a basic
level, then you're really going to struggle to be a producer.
It seems like humility and empathy are some core parts of being a leader as far as a producer
goes.
Yeah, which is interesting because then you talk me up and that makes me feel really narcissistic
and so I have to bring in the humbleness now, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Hey, great work.
Hey, you still suck.
Yeah, so you did something like a while ago, I talked to you a little bit about it at GDC,
and you left the game industry for a little bit, am I getting that right?
Yeah.
What did you do?
Yeah, so I left Epic and took about a six month sabbatical.
And I wanted to, I won't say I wanted to understand myself or anything like that, but I weirdly
have had a job since I was very young, illegally at eight years old, and then I went to college
and then started making games and I realized I was starting to feel a little bit of burnout
and I was talking to different mentors that I have about burnout and realized that that
was coming.
And so I wanted to figure out if I could be happy doing something other than making games.
And so what I decided to do was just travel around the world and do odd jobs.
And that got to the point where I was, you know, staying with friends and building them a new restroom,
to, you know, working on construction sites in Indiana,
to going to New Zealand and hiking for a few weeks.
And then ultimately I ended up on an island called Lord Howe Island off the coast of Australia
that my friends own and was working on a farm.
for a while. So that was probably the culmination of it. Oh, the friends on the farm, not the
island. That sounds way crazier. So yeah, I worked on a farm and then I came back and
Clint asked me if I wanted to write a book with him and that's when I decided to come
back into the industry.
And you're talking about Clinton Keith?
Yes, Clinton Keith.
Yeah, world-renowned...
Production guru. Yeah, that was quite the shocking call when he was like, hey, you want to help me with this book?
And I was like, I've looked up to you since before I started in the industry. So I talked about a humbling moment
Yeah, that was one of them if not for that moment
Do you think you would have come back eventually or would you still be on a farm on an island somewhere?
Yeah, so interesting thing about that was I was on that farm, but I'd already bought tickets to the next GDC
So I wasn't like, I'd already like volunteered to the SCA and a conference associate and I had bought my flights and hotel rooms and everything.
And I was like, I'm going to come back and I'm going to be this really weird person at GDC who's like, I work on a farm.
But what happened was I started working on this book and then I was at GDC and a friend of mine asked me to
Review some stuff that their company was doing
And then they paid me in an Amazon gift card and I was like wait
People get paid to like give other people advice and they were like he was like, yeah
In fact, we'd like to hire you to give you a tip for you to like review stuff and give us advice
And that's when I started my company was actually at GDC
I think a lot of people are like that, right?
I have some information, and you're obviously an enthusiastic guy sharing all of this stuff
that you've learned over the many years that you've been in game dev now.
People are just kind of like, oh, I can get paid for this?
For my time and all of these 10 years that I've been here, I can actually make a living
out of it?
Yeah.
Yeah, I've been doing it for free for so long that when somebody was like, I'll pay you, I'm like, is that fair?
Yeah, yeah, I don't know. I mean, your hands are calloused and your brain has been, you know,
just through all of this stuff. Hey, so like going off and doing that and kind of getting away
and you know what? Finding yourself, sure. What do you feel like you came away with from all that?
Like, what did you learn?
I learned a few things.
The first one was it allowed me to be creative in ways that I have never been before.
I used to write a lot when I was younger and I wanted to take some time off, so I actually
wrote a couple screenplays that I expect will never be made because I've never done anything
with them.
But I wrote a couple screenplays just to kind of explore creativity in a different way.
I also learned that stress is really...
Fairly easy to defeat when you realize that most things that we're stressed
about are not important in the grand scheme of things.
This is a little philosophical, but when you're hiking in the middle of New
Zealand and you're the only person for like 50 miles around and you're sitting
on top of a mountain, you realize how infinitesimally small you are in the
grand scheme of the cosmos.
And so when you think about that and then you think about like.
Oh man, our game is broken in X way.
You're like, that doesn't really matter.
Uh, and so we're all going to be doing it anyway.
Yeah.
And so you can either go the very nihilistic route or you can go kind of a
positive route, which I do, which is like, Hey, this isn't like as soul crushing as
possible.
Let's just calm down, relax, and we'll get through it.
Um, and, and because of that, I feel like I'm.
Even more kind of chilled out when it comes to the hardcore process of making games.
So that was definitely a big thing that I learned.
As well as just learning a lot about myself and ways that I function well as far as sleeping,
eating, things like that.
Because I wasn't in a tight bubble of have to wake up at this time and do this and that
and that.
So, yeah.
I wasn't expecting the first GDC podcast to go full galaxy plane, but I appreciate it.
Yeah.
Um, so, all right.
We, uh, we talked about philosophical stuff, uh, maybe, which it was just great.
I love it.
And I think it is important, you know, that's the foundational foundational
stuff, uh, working in a, in a job like game development.
Um, so now I'm wondering, uh, why you wear a rugby shirts all the time.
That's let's get the nuts and bolts of production here.
I promise I'll segue into the production stuff.
So what's interesting is this is another GDC story.
So when I first started going to GDC in 2008,
there used to be a charity poker tournament that was open to anyone.
And I wanted to go.
And I was a student, and I was like,
you know, I don't really have any nice clothes.
The only thing I have that has a collar is a rugby jersey.
And so I wore a rugby jersey, and weirdly...
I guess not weirdly, most of the people who were at this poker tournament were people
who had been in the industry for a while, had disposable income, wanted to schmooze
with each other and give to charity.
And so here I am, this young guy in my rugby jersey playing poker with people and beating
them quite soundly because I used to be very good at poker.
And I distinctly remember meeting Kenny Young at the time, another GEC advisory board member.
And him being like, you're American, why are you wearing a rugby jersey?
And I was like, well, I play rugby.
And he was like, oh, that's interesting.
So fast forward to the next day, and I'm walking around GDC,
and Kenny comes over and he's like, hey, you're the rugby jersey guy.
And I was like, what?
And then somebody else came over and was like, hey,
you're the rugby jersey guy.
And that's when I was like, well, I guess I'm the rugby jersey guy.
So.
So that's my brand.
So ever since then, whenever I travel to a new country, I try and get a national rugby jersey or a team rugby jersey from that area.
And that is pretty much my exclusive wear when I'm doing professional things.
I'm even wearing one right now.
Other than maybe wearing a GDCCA shirt, most people expect to see me in a rugby jersey.
Those are the only two shirts that I've seen you.
Yeah, I went to visit friends who I had met through GEC once and I was not wearing a rugby jersey and they walked right past me.
And I was like, hey, I'm over here.
And they're like, oh, what are you wearing?
And I was like, it's just a t-shirt.
Completely unrecognizable.
There's like an Archer episode where he opens his closet,
and it's all these like black and like off-black turtlenecks.
And like that's what I'm imagining.
It's just a closet, wall-to-wall, rugby jersey.
Yeah.
Pretty much.
Kind of like Steve Jobs and the turtleneck machines.
Exactly.
Great little networking pro tip.
Yeah.
So, speaking of rugby, scrum.
I mean, what came first, the rugby jerseys or the product development methodology, interest
in scrum?
That's interesting.
So, I've had rugby jerseys since high school, so that one would have come first.
And then I remember studying scrum for the first time in high school.
In college, and interestingly, there was like this whole video that they showed and it was a rugby player talking about scrum and agile development.
And I was the only person in the room who knew what he was actually talking about.
So I was like, Oh, I played rugby.
And so yeah, then I was like, well, you know, this takes one of my loves, which is.
So, I'm going to try and learn and become a master of this so that I can use it everywhere
and then I have a reason to wear rugby jerseys I guess.
So for our listeners, or maybe even listener, I don't know.
This is a brand new podcast, I don't know.
Can you describe Scrum in rugby
and Scrum in product and game development?
Sure.
So Scrum in rugby is used to restart play.
So just like in basketball when they throw the ball in
or soccer, they throw the ball in.
or if there's a penalty, they kick it.
In scrum, in rugby, there are a certain type of infraction that need to be restarted through a scrum.
I won't explain what all those are, but basically what happens is you have eight players from each team
and they bind together very closely and act as a single engine, a single unit,
and they slam their bodies into each other in the most violent way possible,
and the ball gets inserted into the middle and they kind of push back and forth for the ball.
It's really interesting that they picked that term for agile development for development
practices.
Oh, I thought we were describing agile game development.
Oh, that was the rugby part.
Really close.
And I think it's because ultimately you're taking eight people of very different body
shapes and sizes and turning them into one cohesive unit that can generate power beyond
like really beyond a normal person can imagine.
And so that's kind of the idea of Scrum.
And I'll kind of just describe Agile development,
which Scrum is one of the many terms and types of that.
In Agile development, it's about being iterative
as opposed to waterfall development,
which is like, you know, we want to make a game,
we wrote a design doc, and then the artist did this thing,
and then they handed the design and the art to the programmers,
and the programmers made it, and the game came out.
It's more like we have a set of features.
and we design the basics of those features and the artists maybe do a little bit of their work
and while they're doing that we're prototyping it and we're iterating it in that tight loop of maybe
two to three weeks and in that you're kind of going in circles. I'm making circles with my
hands here. You're going in circles. I can sense it.
You're going in circles where you're like, you know, create, test, re-evaluate, and then
you kind of go through that over and over again.
And what the value of it is, is that you can very quickly move through things and things
can be more flexible.
The negative of it that a lot of people have is if you don't monitor it closely, which
is where Scrum comes in.
Then it just comes to major feature and scope creep where people are like,
we're agile, we can do whatever we want.
And then they throw in a new feature in the middle of a sprint.
Scrum is a set of rules and practices that go around that,
which I won't get into all of them, that help you kind of prioritize and
figure things out in a proper way to make sure that you're not overscoping
within that process.
Give us the one, what's the best Scrum rule?
What's your favorite one?
My favorite rule in practice is actually the daily stand up.
So I like having a time to get everybody together to talk about things.
That's probably the one that I adhere to the most.
Even though everybody does what we call butt scrum.
It's scrum butt, I do this, it's scrum butt, I do that.
But the one that tends to be done by everybody is that one right there where people are.
Getting together once a day and saying what they're working on, where it's at in the process,
and what they're going to work on that day.
Alyssa, do you have anything to say about Buzzkram?
Oh, well, no, actually, it's really interesting.
I knew nothing about rugby scrum or game development scrum prior to that explanation.
And hearing just that brief description of it has helped contextualize some of the things
I know about other studio structures and from talking to other game developers and stuff
like that.
So it's all kind of coming into focus with the understanding of scrum.
Yeah, you're welcome.
And it's fun to say, scrum.
Yeah.
Uh, so when you're working at Shonk Ventures and you're talking to clients
and they're saying, please deliver us from the mistakes that we made.
Um, what, what are the most common production mistakes that
you see with your clients?
Yeah, that's wow.
That's a great question.
Um, so the first.
The first common mistake that I see from people is this over-strict adherence to rules that
they've created in their own brain.
And what I mean by that is we have to be by the letter with Scrum or Agile, and we have
to make sure that we're doing this.
And it tends to be at the detriment to the team.
And if we go back to what I said your core tenets of being a producer are, which is
about communicating and being kind of, you know, just this facilitator and
person who's focused on people, Scrum and Agile tend to cause a lot of problems when
they first come in and people get angry and frustrated.
And so what I say is, you know, I actually talk about it in the book, but we call beachheading
a new practice where you take a small group of people and you have them learn that practice
and then they can kind of change it based on your studio culture and then they are your
champions bringing it out to the rest of the team.
So that's one of the main things that I tend to see is that people are like,
we decided to become agile and they're like,
here's our super strict rule set and they bring it in and everything breaks.
And they're like, ah, and everybody's like heads on fire.
So I'm always like, don't worry, we're going to fix it.
We just got to kind of iterate through with the team.
So the main thing that I usually like help my clients focus on is
making sure that the team understands why changes are being made.
Making sure that the team understand the goals of that and then understand what the
team actually wants out of these changes.
So it's a lot of outsider kind of perspective and bias where I'll talk to the teams and
I'll talk to the producers and the leaders and they may kind of be saying the same thing
to each other but not really hearing it and then I present it and now everybody thinks
that I'm a genius.
So.
I tend to apologize a lot to especially the producers because a lot of times what I've
found is that the producers know the right thing to do.
They're just stuck on one or two things.
And also there's that relationship baggage that might be in there.
Even if they have a lot of trust from their team, there's still a,
ugh, he's been doing X for this long,
or she's been saying it this way for so long now,
they want to change it.
Whereas I can come in and say,
well, this is actually what we need to be doing.
And a lot of times it's exactly what they were saying,
but people are like, oh, yeah, yeah,
that makes a lot of sense.
You worked on Fortnite.
And I'm like, whatever, yeah, thanks.
Yeah.
Just call me the rugby shirt guy.
And that's probably something that also benefits from what you were saying earlier, where you
have some multidiscipline experience, and I imagine some of that language gets lost
when they don't have the verbiage to describe what they want in the terms for the developers
they're speaking to as well.
Yeah.
Definitely, definitely. And it's one of those things where, you know, I always say that, you know, the best team is a team that is a little, everybody's a little bit well-rounded and a little bit of everything.
Obviously, people are experts at things, but I want everybody on my team to be a game designer and a producer as well as whatever else they are, because I don't think a game designer should be holding the hand and,
telling a programmer every single thing that needs to be done in the design.
There should be some creativity in there.
And a designer shouldn't be, you know, not caring about the schedule.
So one of the things that I tend to do with all of my teams that I work with is
try and figure out ways to level up all of the individuals on the team.
So it'd be that spending a little bit of time.
every week or every month with the creative director or lead designer kind of explaining
what the game is in more detail or having the producers kind of teach tools in a more
intuitive way so things aren't super, you know, their JIRA isn't super complicated but
it's very simple for people to understand so that they want to be in there.
moving things along and making it more interactive and fun for them as opposed to having to walk
around every day and be like, did you update your Jira?
Did you update Hansoft?
Which I've been that guy.
That's not a fun experience for anybody.
So that's a big part of what I've been doing.
So you swoop in and obviously you don't stay, you know, you're a temporary person.
How do you leave the lessons with people and how do you kind of give the producers that
you work with and the teams you work with the tools where they will have less disagreements
and they'll be more efficient?
Like, how do you just hand that off?
Yeah, so part of it is there is like a monthly or every other week follow up with the key people that I've worked with.
So be that someone in leadership or producer, kind of a coaching relationship where we're just having these constant conversations.
Jokingly, a big part of why Clinton and I wrote the book was that we wanted an easier way to
leave a client. And an easy way to leave a client is, like,
yeah, in a way, right? In a way, like, you know, if you,
one, if you can't afford one or either of us, you know, you can just buy the book, which is much cheaper.
Or two, you know, we kind of leave and we're like, hey, just a reminder,
here are the six or seven practices that we put in place.
Let's make sure we're on the guidelines of this.
But, you know, just like any leaving of a job, I write up documentation.
You know, I do like, I wouldn't call it an exit interview, but I do kind of a like, hey,
I'm leaving.
Here are the things that we accomplished here, the things that still need to be done.
Here's how you should do those once I'm gone.
You know, you want to leave them wanting a little bit more.
That's how you get repeat clients.
But you want to fix as many, if not all, their problems in one go.
Yeah.
You also run, um, game dev drink up.
Uh, yeah, I, I, I'm a multifaceted person.
Uh, so, so John, Jonathan Hawkins, um, in LA who runs his own studio, he
started the game dev drink up.
Oh man.
I think it was nine years ago, almost nine years ago.
He asked me to...
I kind of took over the Dallas chapter after it had one meeting, and then the guy who was running it left.
So he asked me to run it, and then over time I've just kind of taken on a lot of the responsibilities of setting up the events, helping new chapters start, and things like that.
Which is odd because I don't drink.
And a lot of people say to me, like,
I don't want to go to the Game Dev Drink if I don't drink.
And I was like, I run it and I don't drink.
It's not a requirement,
it's just the name.
And very excitedly,
the first chapter, which is in LA,
is having its 100th
event in August.
So we have been doing it for a long time.
I forget how many events we've done,
but it's close to 600.
And we've had over 15,000 people attend,
and we're in four countries right now.
So, very cool.
That's nuts.
So, yeah, I mean, and that's like what you're all about.
You know, it's a fun thing,
but you're like a community building guy, right?
Yeah, that's, you know,
if we get into my grand philosophy
of what's wrong with the world,
it's that we don't live in community anymore, you know?
If you're in your town, I mean,
I don't know the person who lives across from me
or beneath me in my apartment complex.
You know, I don't know anybody in my kind of area.
We leave the towns we're born in.
We don't necessarily go to a religious ceremony or event anywhere.
So we don't have a lot of community.
So one of the things that I've tried to do my whole career,
starting with my involvement in the IGDA in the early 2000s,
was help build communities in any way.
And so what the Game Dev Drink-Up does differently than the IGDA,
which we encourage all of our members to go to IGDA meetings,
is we're not education and we're not about your career, we're literally just about your community and about helping you network.
And what we found, and this is just anecdotal, I haven't done a full study on this, but what we found is that if a city has a gamedev drink up,
it is much more likely that developers will stay in that city if they're laid off or there's a closure than if there isn't,
because they have a network of people around them that are not just their office.
So that's kind of been our goal all along is provide community so that people don't need to uproot their lives every time
You know, there's a studio closure or or they get laid off
Yeah for people who are like adjacent to cities that host a game dev drink up or another kind of game dev gathering event
What do you have for advice for them to get the most out of those meetup opportunities?
Yeah
So first off if your city doesn't have a game dev drink up you can just reach out to the game dev drink up on
Facebook or Twitter
And we'll talk to you about setting one up.
If you have any other event in your area or you have a game to have a drink of,
what I always tell people is just show up and just be friendly.
Don't show up with a resume in your hand.
Don't show up trying to impress people.
Just show up and ask people about themselves.
I am a little weird, and this is a weird thing to recommend to people when I realize how weird
this is.
I have done targeted networking, especially when I was younger and looking to learn about
the industry, where I would know that certain people would go to certain events at GDC or
the IGDA meetings, and I would go specifically to try and meet that person.
I think as long as you're not doing that in a creepy way, like, yeah, I came here to meet
you.
The way you described it doesn't sound creepy at all, Grant.
Not at all.
Hey, you're the two who stalked me online, okay?
This is true.
But, you know, coming to an event and saying like,
hey, you know, I love your games and I wanted to ask you this piece of advice.
You know, I've had people do that with me and it's less creepy than,
for some reason I get really creeped out when somebody's like,
I follow you on Twitter.
And I'm like, whoa, why? Why would you do that?
Yeah, I know that feeling.
So be very, very purposeful in what you go to the events for, which is to meet people.
And what I always tell people is networking is just a fancy word for making friends.
So just go up to people and ask them, hey, what game are you playing lately?
Or, you know, what are some of your hobbies?
Just have conversations with people.
I feel like it's really easy to look at these networking events, and especially if you're
younger.
I went to a school with a game development major, so there were a bunch of people being
like, oh, you have to go to these conventions, you have to go to these parties, and you have
to meet these people.
And it was this very high stress to-do, to-do, to-do, to-do.
And it seems like kind of not doing that is what you're recommending in a way?
Don't stress about it.
Yeah, don't stress about it.
Don't think of it as a job interview.
Just think about it as a place to meet friends.
Obviously, you want to maintain a level of professionalism.
If you're going to a networking event, I don't recommend you getting drunk.
Right?
But you can go and have a couple drinks, have a good time.
I know, Chris, we have to talk later.
You can have some drinks, you know, have a good time and get to know people.
I jokingly say that the real reason I started Game Dev Drink Up chapters everywhere that I've moved is that I'm an inherently lonely person and I just want to make friends.
So I started a Drink Up chapter and then people come and hang out with me once a month. And I'm like, look at all my friends!
You know what? I meant to bring it up earlier, but I think the first time that you and I met, and I think it might have been the narrative...
So, we're going to be talking about the GDC Summit meetup when GDC Online was happening in Austin still.
Grant and I were at this place called the Ginger Man down here. I ended up moving here.
I think that there's a Facebook picture of us somewhere. I think that you might actually be carrying me.
So Grant, like the first time I met Grant, he like literally swept me off my feet.
So that's just the kind of guy he is.
So there's the header image for this podcast when you get published somewhere.
Yeah, we'll find it.
Dig that one up.
Yeah.
Well, we're gonna wrap up here.
I do want to talk about, I want to talk about Crunch because, hey, we want to end on a
really happy note.
Yeah, but I'd like to talk about that just a little bit because you're a producer and
do you think that, do you find that one of your duties, one of your jobs is to totally
help teams eliminate that?
I think it's about helping teams understand why it exists more than it is to eliminate
it.
I mean, I think that that is often a goal, which is let's eliminate crunch.
What I can help is not just straight eliminate crunch, but help you understand why crunch has existed.
And Keith Fuller, who also is a consultant and has worked in the industry for a long time,
describes crunch in two different ways, which I like to understand as well, which is
there's crunch and then there's overwork. And crunch can be voluntary, right?
Like, you really want to make this game great, and so you want to work.
a few extra hours and put that in.
And I'm usually fine with that as long as it's limited to two weeks.
I don't want somebody being like,
I want to make this game great, and six months later I realize that they've been not seeing their family
a single day during the week for six months.
And then there's overwork, which is when a studio stands up and says,
Hey, we have to all be here for 12 hours a day, six days a week.
And that is...
almost easier to fix than the second one.
Because the second one is just people being passionate
and helping them understand what their limits are,
which is a lot of kind of talking with people
and understanding them, and especially if they're younger,
helping them understand their limits.
But overwork is, you know, the first thing to say is like,
hey, we're not gonna do this,
and then figuring out why you've been doing it.
And usually it's not about deadlines,
it's about misscoping,
You know, figuring out where you can't, like, you know, you get to a point where you're like, I can't cut anything.
Okay, but can we limit things just a little bit?
Can we focus on things differently?
And understanding that as producers, it's our responsibility to make sure our team doesn't have to crunch or overwork ever.
So if we get to a point where we are doing that, then ultimately we fail.
And I know that that can sound a little bit harsh to people who have been in that position, and myself included,
where ultimately it was the decision of people above us to do that with the team,
and we could have delivered the game on time if they had let us cut certain features.
But we have to kind of stand up and be like, no, this is the human cost of what we're doing,
and here's possible solutions and ways to work.
It's not as easy as staffing up.
It's about making hard cuts, hard decisions,
and understanding your team and what they can actually do.
So from your perspective as a consultant
and somebody who's worked at these major studios
and smaller studios in 2019,
has Crunch gotten better?
In my personal life, it's gotten better,
but that's because I'm a consultant.
I think that the stories that I'm hearing about Crunch are a little bit different and
I feel like they are less ubiquitous.
When I was going through my first major Crunch in 2008, 2009, it was everybody.
Everybody was doing it.
We were all trying to hit Christmas deadlines or whatever it might be.
I remember talking to all my friends and being like,
oh, I was at my work until 2 a.m.
and they were like, oh, I was there until 3.
And now I feel like people are getting older
and having families and responsibilities,
so they're willing to kind of push back and be like,
hey, you know, I'll work a 12-hour day,
but I'm not working Saturdays.
and figuring out ways to have work-life balance.
So I think that it's not as common in the industry,
but it is still common.
And it's something that we have to keep kind of fighting against
and figuring out what are the proper solutions
and ways to do this.
I think the big difference between.
2008 and now is there are a lot of studios standing up and saying we don't crunch or we are now focusing on fixing this problem.
Whereas in 2008 it was kind of like yeah crunch is bad and then everybody's like it's not really bad we're going to do it anyways.
Whereas now it's people are coming out and publicly saying these are the steps that we're taking to change.
And I really like a lot of the pressure that has kind of been put on gamers to understand what...
What happens in this and now they're kind of pushing back on their studios and being
that of the games that they love and saying, hey, don't sacrifice your people to make sure
we have new content every two weeks.
Like that's not that's not worth it to us.
So I think it's about educating everybody from the game players themselves to people who are making games and their families
to understand the proper way to have work-life balance.
And ultimately, once you can get to that work-life balance, the team is going to be richer and more passionate and understanding about the project
than they would be if they were working 75-80 hours a week.
That is a great summation.
of what we should do. I love it. I also think it's a great place to bring an end to this segment.
But Grant, where can people find you online? I mean, Alyssa and I already know everywhere to
find you online. If people want to get in contact with you about your consultancy, where can they
find you? Yeah, so the easiest way is just to Google Shock Ventures, which is just S-H-O-N-K
and then Ventures, like Ed Ventures, but you take off ads.
If you Google that or gshonk, G-S-H-O-N-K, you will find all of my social media websites,
emails, and easiest ways to contact me.
Sounds great.
Well, thank you so much for joining us.
Thanks for having me.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Wow, that Grant, huh? We're still trying to get our editing down on this podcast, by the way.
You can tell by all our casual banter that we've had throughout the conversation.
Yeah, wow, that Grant, huh?
What an insightful conversation here at the GDC podcast.
Oh my gosh. Yeah, actually, we're recording this before we even talked to Grant.
No, actually, no, it's after. Alyssa, what are your takeaways there? What's going on in your
brain after this?
He mentioned hiking like way at the beginning and I've had this just camping itch for just
like just going camping and then contextualizing that with like oh it's this whole creative
refresh and kind of figuring out your like de-stressing and figuring out your place in
the world and like throughout the entire conversation there were so many great things mentioned
but I just really want to go hiking.
Yeah, like hardcore hiking, like Appalachian Trail hiking, or go to the park.
I've got family in South Dakota, so I'm just going to flash the Black Hills and go up to
Harney Peak.
Yeah, it's great.
Oh my gosh, Harney Peak?
Harney Peak.
Tell me about Harney Peak.
It's a high mountain with a view.
Yeah?
Okay.
Oh, you have to do it?
Yeah, no, I think it's this old fort is built.
It used to be like a fire watching fort, but now it's just some old cool castle that you
have to walk for three hours up a hill to get.
And it's really refreshing.
So I can relate to that point of the conversation.
So after talking to Grant, basically you're going to take a six month sabbatical from
Gamasutra, do some editing.
I'm just going to go straight AWOL in Slack and I'll be on a mountain somewhere.
I guess we'll have to discuss that later.
Yeah, but it's so good to catch up with somebody like that guy.
That guy, he seems very in touch with how people operate.
Yeah, it's interesting to get the perspective of someone who has been in game development,
isn't in the thick of it now, but is still in the industry in a way, doing especially
the consulting stuff, you have a unique perspective on that.
So to kind of capture that and dig into it a little bit was a super interesting conversation.
Yeah, and that's got to be difficult too.
Just going into, I don't know, basically someone calls 911, you're like…
Everything's on fire and you're like, oh my god.
Yeah, the person is like, we need somebody to fix all this.
It's lightly heroic in a way, like, Kate billowing in the wind as you swoop in to fix
all of their production problems.
Yeah, his rugby shirt just billowing in the wind.
Yeah. Well, I know, I want to just point out that usually when you talk about crunch, it gets like,
this somber mood kind of sweeps over whenever crunch comes up, but that was a really good
summary of issues that lead to it and productively how developers can kind of work through it and
work past it and understand it. And I think that was just a really good context to have too.
Yeah, it is. Because it is something easy, like you get rightfully fired up about it,
and then talking to someone who has to solve those issues on a practical level, and then just,
I don't know, like... He's been there in all the different situations,
different studios, their own projects, projects they've consulted on, so it's,
yeah, really useful information. I'm glad to be a part of that.
Yeah, me too, Alyssa.
So, okay, well, this is where we tell you to subscribe,
smash the subscribe button, or is that more of a...
Is it lightly tap?
Do people click anymore?
You can tap it, mash it.
You can mash the subscribe button
if you're on a touchscreen device on your phone.
And we promise to bring more fascinating guests.
Right now we're trying once a month.
We don't wanna burn ourselves out here.
And I'm kinda lazy.
Yeah, but we may ramp up from that depending on how things are going.
So thanks everybody for listening.
Again, I'm Chris Graft.
I'm Alyssa McAloo.
And mash that subscribe button with your thumb.
And if you love us, rate and review.
See you next time.
Thanks everyone.
Bye.