Today's topics will cover a short introduction and background on who we are, how to source
vehicles, planning and prepping for a vehicle recording session, the actual recording session,
editing and asset creation, and also implementing.
So who are we?
We're an audio outsourcing company based in Stockholm,
Sweden.
We do sound design for film, games, and trailers.
We do complex field recording, like guns, ambulances,
vehicles, and much more.
We produce sound effect libraries that we sell online.
We also have a long experience from music.
Our composer, Mats Lundgren, is highly skilled at
composting and producing adaptive music for games.
And Bernard here on my side is also a very well-established
mix engineer and has done several international number
ones and recorded and mixed the music for the Mamma Mia
movies.
So here's a small selection of titles where our sounds or
music can be heard.
We also recorded for these two films, which we are very proud of.
And right now we're involved in a research project together with Volvo Cars,
where we are looking at self-driving cars and the interaction between the user and the vehicle.
We'll focus on establishing a trust to feel safe in the vehicle and also on preventing motion sickness.
And here's what a day at the office can look like.
Thank you.
OK, hi, I'm Bernard.
I want to tell you a little story about how this vehicle
recording once started.
My background and my work through life has been music
recording and music producing.
But my hobby has been, from the beginning,
cars and car racing.
And from 2001 and onwards, I was driving the Swedish
championships for GT cars.
Actually, in that Porsche you see there.
And one of my fastest competitors had a computer game
company called Simbin.
They were doing simulation games for PC, computer games,
for simulation games for racing cars.
He knew about my profession and asked me if we could record some race cars and try to
do that to deliver assets for his game.
And what we did was we brought my race car and we hired a lot of film recording equipment
and went to a racetrack.
We also prepared the car by taking off the silencers.
to get an open exhaust sound. Swedish racetracks have
very hard sound regulations, but we wanted to have
the straight exhaust sound, so that's what we did.
We put some mics in different spots,
and put the recorders in red.
And I started and drove out on the track.
And I managed to do like four laps
before the track owner came out yelling and told us to stop,
because it was too noisy.
But we got four laps, and it sounded like this.
And I'll see you next time.
Bye.
Yeah, okay.
And then, well, back in the studio, we discussed how to get this organic sound into the games,
because what we had heard earlier was loop-based sounds recorded on dinos, and we felt that
they are really dead in sounding, and often roomy, because the dinos were often in a room,
actually.
And we took, we tried to find out our own method to put the actual driving sound into the game.
And what we did in the beginning was to create loops with basic audio tools,
like we did some evening out the RPM on a...
sound like this. We used software samplers and programmed the pitch wheel to get almost
a straight RPM and try to loop and managed to do really good things. And that was how
it started, actually. And we started to record race cars for this company first.
And after a while, we were contacted by other computer game companies to record other types
of vehicles, a lot of military stuff like tanks, airplanes, and that's the way it was.
And if you look here, this is a bit like what it looked like when we were starting.
And today, it's more or less like this.
You see all the bags.
And we are lots of people coming at the same time.
And we can manage to do, like maybe if we're talking cars,
maybe five to seven cars a day if we are well organized.
OK.
So I will talk a bit about the sourcing of the vehicles.
Where do we find them?
Obviously, internet is a great resource.
You can search for clubs with car owners.
You can also search authorities on license plates
if you walk down the street and hear a car that you like.
Or even search for certain models.
We also approach museums and private collectors
around the world.
And we have a huge network, since Ben had mentioned,
he's been racing, I grew up in a car family as well,
we have a huge network among friends as well,
which keeps growing the more things we do.
It can be challenging sourcing.
Once I tried to find tanks in France at a museum,
and I don't know any French except the bad words.
So I tried to write in English and then I used Google Translate
and I sent them emails and I thought it went pretty well.
I could translate their emails back
and it came to a point where they didn't understand anything
and asked me to call them, and then we ran into issues
and we needed a French-speaking person to help us out.
Another example is with a Messerschmitt 109,
a German plane from the Second World War,
which is very rare.
There's like five of them with the original engine flying.
And I tried to get access for almost two years, I think,
before I got an email from someone who knew someone,
and that opened all the doors for us.
And that recording was later used for Dunkirk as well,
because it was so hard for them to find anything else.
You need to figure out what to record.
It doesn't have to be authentic,
like many of the old World War II stuff
has replaced engines.
And that's the case with the Messerschmitts,
for instance, the 109s.
There's lots of them,
but very few have the right engine.
Also, tanks can have replaced engines and so on.
And then...
we need to look at if you want a stock car or a modified car.
Stock cars often sound very boring.
There's not much tone coming out from the exhaust pipes.
And you need that tone to make assets for games.
So for games, it's often more you're better off with a
modified exhaust system, while for film, it's the other way
around often.
And then you need to understand what the client is looking for, as in this case, if the client wants the Volvo in the lower picture, and you find the Volvo in the upper picture, the client is not going to understand really what you did.
Sourcing is extremely time consuming.
Some clients want video approvals on every car you find.
So you need to find a car first.
You need to make sure it has the right information.
And then you need to make a video with it
where you record the engine running
and some blips and stuff.
And then you need to send that to the client
and either you get an approval or a disapproval.
And if you get a disapproval,
you need to start all over again.
And if you can't find the correct vehicle,
can be old collector items and stuff,
then you need to find a substitute
that's as close as possible.
So you need to do a lot of research on that.
And once you get to actually record, you might want to be
cost and time efficient.
You might need, like Bernard said, we do between five and
eight cars in a day.
So you need to find all these cars.
You need them at the same location at the same time.
So then you need to look at if there's a location nearby
where you can get all the cars, or if you need
transportation to collect the cars and bring
them to the location.
And nowadays, we have the luxury of actually having a
person dedicated to only doing this, which is very, very
helpful.
It saves us a lot of time.
Then we have the planning and the preparation.
Planning is everything, as it says here.
You need paperwork in place.
You need an agreement with the owner to clarify what you
expect to get.
involved.
And more important, also you need an agreement with the
client that covers access fees, track rentals, travel
expenses, equipment, staff, insurances, delivery dates,
and so on.
And very important is to also cover the what if.
We make sure that we can't be held responsible for things
that we can't control, such as cancellations due to weather,
delayed flights, vehicles not starting, and damaging
vehicles, and so on.
As an example, in the film we showed earlier, there was this
huge bomb plane flying by.
And when we went to Canada to record that plane, we were not
sure about the weather.
So we needed to have three days.
Even if we just needed one day to record, we needed the two
extra days in case there would be bad weather.
So it's things like that that you need to
consider all the time.
And recently we also had a client who asked for vehicles
that were driven on snow.
And Sweden is known for snow, I guess.
We didn't think it would be a problem at
this time of the year.
But there were no snow in sight at all.
We looked everywhere.
We followed the forecast all over Sweden,
and there was no snow.
So we got a bit panicked.
And then I saw on Facebook a friend of mine was out skiing
somewhere, cross country.
So I called him and I asked him, where are you?
And he got us the number to the skiing facility.
And we had them open it up for us nighttime, putting on all
the lights so we could record their nighttime and we could
deliver on the date.
But if we wouldn't have had the clause that we can't be
held responsible, then it would have been problematic if
we didn't find any snow.
Another example is with one client, we recorded very, very
old vehicles.
And when we came to one location, the vehicle didn't
start at all.
It did start the day before, so they were kind of puzzled it
didn't start this time.
But in that case, we needed to add in the agreement that for
every
recording session, we would make sure there was a mechanic
at the place as well.
So they would start the vehicle the day before to make
sure it ran.
And when we came to the location, there would be a
mechanic, so in case it didn't start, we at least had the
chance to work with this mechanic to get it started.
Also, with damaging vehicles, we learned the hard way.
We recorded a Lamborghini that broke down.
It's not fun.
It was not our fault.
But that meant we couldn't deliver anything to the
client, and they didn't pay for anything.
So we had to cover all the expenses ourselves.
On the other hand, when it comes to responsibility,
we take full responsibility for everything that we can affect,
making sure that we have equipment that works,
that we have staff that is doing what they should, and so on.
So you need to take responsibilities as well.
Another part of planning and preparations
is finding a location.
We started out driving on public roads, driving cars for 200 miles per hour.
And it's irresponsible and it's dangerous.
You get a less controlled recording session, which gives a less good result.
So don't try it at home.
Today we always try to rent a track, if possible.
So when you know where you will be recording,
you need to look at a map and try to identify disturbances
and problems with the location.
It can be nearby airports, it can be railways, highways,
or other noise disturbances.
But it can also be safety regulations, restrictions,
and limited daylight, depending on where you are.
So you need to identify all these things.
You need to explain the intention for the people at the location, if it's an airport for instance,
and explain in detail what we need to do, that we're attaching equipment on their vehicles,
the driving that is required, staff on the airstrip, we need to be out on the actual airstrip,
you're not allowed to do that everywhere, and maybe you need to do very, very low flybys.
Again, when we recorded that plane in Canada,
it's a huge bomber plane from World War II.
There was only one flying at the time when we did that.
We were at the commercial airport
where they were not allowed to do flyovers
on a low altitude.
So to work around that,
the pilot reported to the tower
that we're coming in to land.
They came in, and when they were where we were,
they reported to the tower back again,
we were aborting the landing,
and then they took off again.
And they repeated that seven times, I think.
So if there is a will, there is a way.
You also need to keep an eye on the weather forecast.
Is it a cancel or is it a go?
Sometimes you don't really know,
and then it's a bit of a gamble.
If you're abroad, language might be an issue.
So it could be a good thing to have the maneuvers you want
to perform translated on the paper or in the predator.
You need a good driver.
We are lucky to have Bernard, who's extremely experienced.
Whenever we can, we let him drive, not planes, though, and
tanks maybe, but cars.
And then you have the unknown and the unwanted.
This first example here that I'm going to play to you is in Swedish, but I think you will get it.
This is a sound dampener.
You did this when I came and drove by here.
When I came down here, it was still heard down there.
On the other side of the forest, it was still there.
I understand.
Now it's done with the noise.
Now I'm taking this with a lens filter.
We've had enough of his shit.
She's obviously not too happy.
And she eventually called the police.
Police came, and they were super excited what we were doing.
They didn't care about the poor lady.
And the other example is from a very frustrated recordist.
Fucking birds.
Fuck you, fucking birds.
Die, you fucking birds.
We were recording old planes and there were obviously birds, different kinds of
different kind of were birds I guess. So here's a simple rule of field recording
there's always birds if you want to record planes and there's always planes
if you want to record birds.
Next part of the planning and preparation is equipment.
You need to charge batteries, of course, and all that.
You need to bring zip ties, gaffer tape, cables, memory cards,
backup drives, sync to machines.
You need to look at the weather. Some zip types, they break if it's too cold.
Some gaffer tape doesn't stick if it's too cold or wet.
And you still need a gaffer tape that's very gentle to the vehicles,
especially if it's like luxury vehicles.
So there's these kinds of things to consider.
You might want to have rental equipment.
If we go abroad and record planes,
we need tons of sandbags and microphone stands and cables.
And it's much better, of course, to rent that on the location
and have it delivered to the airport
than trying to bring that in your luggage.
Another thing is packing your bags,
which might sound ridiculous.
But we have learned the importance of that
as well the hard way.
And we try to bring as much as possible in our carry-ons.
It causes you some issues in the security, but it's well
worth it.
The rest that we can't bring in the carry-ons, we split up in
different bags.
But I would advise you not to put all the recorders in one
bag and all the microphones in another bag.
Because when you go to Japan and you change flight
somewhere, and then you arrive in Japan and one bag is lost,
then you only have recorders or only microphones.
And it will make it very difficult.
Yep.
Bernard will talk a bit more about the equipment.
OK, here's a picture of the basic recorders and the
microphones we have just put out on the table just for you
to see.
And I will show you a list here.
We start with the recorders.
We usually record vehicles at 96 kilohertz, 24 bits.
And occasionally, especially for special sound effects,
we go up to 192 kilohertz, but usually 96 for vehicles.
The onboard recorders we use on the vehicles
are often this first list,
Sonosax R4+, Saxon Fusion,
Zoom F8, Sound Devices 702, and the new MixPre.
And for exterior, we use sound devices 788, 7022T,
SEX, Confucian, and some smaller recorders
like the Sony D100 and M10 and the Olympus LS12.
And, yeah, that's just a list of the equipment.
And then we will look a bit closer on the microphones.
So this is a basic setup we do for recording cars.
The car here is a McLaren 570S, I think.
It has a twin exhaust.
What we use on the exhaust, always as basic, is the DPA 4062.
They can stand 155 dB.
They are taped on this one here, one there and one there.
And then we have two electric voices, RE50,
which are really good to take up a little bit more of the low frequencies.
And you can see it here, one there, and one there.
And also, we have an extra 4062 sitting a bit from the
exhaust to get a bit more of the low frequencies, because
the wavelength has some time to grow from the sound.
Occasionally, we use some extra mics also for low end
and bite, and I will show you some examples a bit later.
If we look here, we have an engine.
This is a Datsun 240 Fairlady, 240Z.
We use DPA 4061s and 4062s, depending on noise level.
Often, the 4062s we put on the intake.
And on the intake, if we can, we try
to open the intake and put the microphone inside
if it's possible.
We use the Shure VP88 for stereo image.
When you're mixing the engine and you want some stereo image,
it's very difficult to get a good stereo image
if you don't have a stereo microphone, which
you can pan a bit out.
We use occasionally, of course, the Sennheiser MKH 8020.
Actually, you can see it here on the picture.
And the Crown PZM.
And actually, we try with different mics all the time to
get the different sounds out of the engine.
Here we have a setup for the interior of the car.
It's a stereo pair, DPA4021s, which you can see here.
With a head-through coil.
suction cup. Yeah, it's here on the on the window stereo pair and we have the Sennheiser
AmbioMic for VR reasons and also that it has a good sound for the interior and occasionally we
also use extra stereo pair of DPA4061s. I think the next one is also this is from a
and Mercedes AMG GTR.
also the ambient mic.
OK.
Let me see where we are.
For the exterior microphones, I had to show you the basic
configuration we use almost always for recording.
This is an airfield north of Stockholm, which we often rent,
an old military airfield which is not used
anymore for airplanes.
So we basically start at, we have the station A,
we have the station B, and we have two turning points.
and also a place for a distant microphone placement.
So if we have a look on the station A,
this is me and a Dodge Challenger.
We use the HoloPhone, which is actually
an eight-channel microphone, but we use four channels for it
and record it in quad, left, right, and left surround,
right surround.
It's this one here.
We also use a very wide stereo pair, in this case Sennheiser MKH 8060.
You can see the right-hand microphone here, and it's a very wide stereo pair actually.
The left one is before this picture, so you couldn't see it.
And also we use a shotgun, handheld, of course,
a Neumann RSM-191.
It's the one laying down here on the ground.
So this is station A. And station B is this one,
handheld Sanken CSS5.
And we have an ORTF set up with Sennheiser MKH-8040
in this package down here.
And for the turning points, we have an RTF set up for the first turning point,
which shops microphones.
And turning point two, in this case, a little simpler recorder.
And also on the distant microphones, we have a simpler recorder.
This is the basic thing we do for car recording.
And of course, it's very different with every vehicle.
So if we go to this picture, this is.
A Spitfire recorded at the Duxford in England, in north of London.
This is for the movie Dunkirk and Richard King, who was the supervising sound editor for the movie,
asked us absolutely to put mics inside the engine compartment.
And that was not something they really liked.
During flight.
During flight, yeah, actually.
So you can see me here trying to put in an Electrovoice RE50
in the compartment.
And we had them to, of course, take off all the hoods
from the plane.
But we managed to do that.
If we go to next picture, we have
this is our colleague, Niklas, recording this cigarette Top Gun
boat.
And he used the same setup as we did on the car.
So this is a DPA 4062 taped on the boat.
And here is actually an RE50 in a plastic cone
to get rid of wind.
I think it did 100 knots or something, that boat.
It's super fast.
Coming over here, we have a recording of a military APC vehicle.
This is the exhaust.
Again, a 4062 here, an ElectroVoice RE50.
And also we use, in this case, we use the DV Moon mic also to get up some extra low frequencies.
Next picture is the tracks on the tank, which in this case has an RE-50 microphone attached.
No cable yet, but...
Here we have a motorcycle.
Motorcycles are very difficult. There is always a lot of wind
issues, and it's difficult to fasten the microphones.
And there's also no place to put a recorder.
So what we do, we use a backpack on the driver.
And you can see here is an ElectroVoice RE50 striped to
the back of the motorcycle.
And this is at station A. So you can see the wide pair and
the hollow foam.
And this is what it looks like in the backpack.
In this case, a Saxon Fusion and a Sony.
No, a Zoom F8, of course.
While recording planes, there's...
Different ways we record them, we record them standing still
on ground with all the RPMs we can drive on ground.
And it's very difficult to know what
microphone will sound good.
So we have microphones everywhere.
As you can see, there are microphones here, there, there, there, there in front, in the back, on the sides, and also very different distances.
And it's impossible to know which of the microphone that sounds good until we are at the studio, actually.
So that's something we learn more and more.
But also, there's so much wind, so it's impossible to find out before what mics are sounding good.
Okay, then we come to this little thing.
This is about the recording schedule.
It's actually a long list of maneuvers that we do
by driving and reversing and going around the turning points
at different speeds.
If you are interested of the actual checklist for this,
we can talk about it a bit later,
but it's a bit too long to take in this.
speech. The thing is, we do everything actually often in three speeds. We call it the granny
driving, the medium driving, and the bank robber driving.
So that's three of the different things.
And we try to get all the maneuvers you can do with the
car actually recorded.
And we also, of course, record fully on the cars, or
vehicles, all vehicles, as much as we can.
And we also record IR sweeps on the interior,
so you can use the acoustics for later
if there is a dialogue inside the car or whatever like that.
OK.
And there, here's a very important rule.
for recording three times, you can forget it anyway.
It's always a problem.
But we have to slate all recorders very good to know
when you come back to the studio.
When you're recording, you always know what you're doing.
But like two days later, you have forgot everything.
So slating all recorders are very important.
Yes, as I told you a bit before, of course, recording vehicles,
different vehicles require different methods, of course.
If we look at planes, we record them standing still on ground
and, as I told you, different RPMs, as much
as we can do on ground.
And then, of course, we record flybys.
On tanks and heavy vehicles, it's, for instance,
very difficult to record ramps because they
have such a short RPM range.
So there we concentrate a bit on steady RPMs
and try to get with as much load as possible, of course.
And also the same with boats.
Here we have some difficult tests that can occur with recordings.
First one, I have wind.
Wind is always a problem when you record vehicles.
So I will show you fast.
Here's a little trick that we use a lot.
This is a McDonald's cup.
And also as you saw on the boat picture before, you use it as a windshield.
Put the microphone inside to get rid of wind.
Highly professional.
Highly professional, yes.
You always have to go to McDonald's first to pick up some.
That was the first you took it, yeah?
And unwanted noise, like nearby traffic,
humans on location.
We have had dogs catching microphones running off.
Heard of sheep coming out on fields
right next to the track, which is, of course, dangerous.
And yeah, stuff like that.
Yes, we have had, of course, a lot of failure on equipment during the years.
And yeah, it's the same picture here.
You can see this is a burnt shore beta M58.
While recording cars and old vehicles, something is always really hot.
And that is a problem.
So cables.
they melt and microphones burn up.
And also in the beginning, we recorded almost everything to
try to record to hard disk.
But that didn't work good on race cars, because it sounded
great, and the recordings worked fine in the pit and
going out in the pit lane.
But then when the G-forces went too high, the
hard disk stopped.
So there was nothing when the car came in.
So nowadays we record everything to these small SD cards.
Yeah.
Okay, it's yours.
This is recording tanks in the UK.
So far we have only rolled the tank out on the field.
And you can already see what the field is starting to look like.
So you can imagine after the bank robber driving what it looks like.
And then you might have this.
So it was obviously someone's feet.
Oops, sorry.
We had been given permission, of course, to go there, but some mistake must have occurred
somehow.
Yeah, they didn't understand that a tank makes some issues.
And, yeah, the next one is yours.
Yeah, the next one is, yeah, bad driving due to drivers not understanding why we are doing
different maneuvers, which of course can be difficult if you're not into sound recording.
And also there can be, as Max mentioned before, communication problems with the driver or the
pilot.
So we try to, for cars and motorcycles and that type of vehicles, we try to drive ourselves.
A few of us are driving different things, but when we come to a plane, of course, I have no problem.
plane education or pilot education,
so then we have to trust the pilot,
but we usually use somebody that we can speak to
as an, what do you call it?
Like a specialist.
Yeah, that can transfer what we want,
so the pilot understands.
And we write these long lists with maneuvers to do.
And about communication problems, I went to Japan to record cars and there was this one car that we could not drive ourselves.
It was a Japanese driver.
He didn't know any English. I didn't know any Japanese.
And it was very difficult to get what we needed.
So the only Japanese word I actually know is moikai, which means one more time.
Okay.
So...
Next.
This is also a rule, back up, back up, back up, which is very
important, of course, so you know that you have something
with you when you come back home.
Let's see, where are we next?
OK, a little bit about editing and asset creation.
Today in the studio, we use mainly Prutools for doing
assets, and we use FMOD and Rev for testing sounds when we
are doing loops, for instance, or ramps.
But Pro Tools is our main tool.
And you can see a list there of plugins.
But we are like four or five people doing assets.
And all of us have our own personal choice to what tools
to work with.
OK.
The first thing we do when we come back to this recording studio is to line up everything in time.
All our recordings are done and we try to sync everything at 100 percent.
And it will look like if we look on the Protus project, you can see here, I will go briefly through.
This is a car recording done here in US actually, a Camaro, I think.
The first two are like a stereo pair on the interior.
Then you have five microphones on the exhaust,
and you have four microphones in the engine compartment.
And then these channels here are the station A,
which is the holophone in quad,
the wide stereo pair,
and the handheld RSM-191.
And this is two stereo tracks from the station B.
And then you have the turning points, two stereo pairs also.
So this is what it looks like when you buy a sound from us.
Maybe it's cleaned up a bit, of course.
But everything is in time all the time.
So it's very easy to, for instance, edit to a picture if
you have an interior thing.
And listen for an acceleration, for instance.
And then you go over to a.
exterior picture when the car is passing by you can just cut between here and
everything is in sync. So yeah and back one I think yes
When creating assets, of course, it's very important
that the customer come with the requirement they have for
their game.
Depending on what engine they are using, and if it's a loop
based system, or ramp based granular playback system, or
maybe a combination of both.
Also, of course, the sound perspective they want in the assets are very important.
And if it's a mono, stereo, surround or surround asset they want.
I have a little bit more here to show you.
Here is what we do often for ramps, for instance.
It's very difficult to record ramps on some vehicles because
you want to load all from the idle and the full load all the
way up to the top of RPM.
And if it's a powerful sports car, it's easier to get the
load on a higher gear.
But in the end, then the car will go very, very fast in the
ends, and that's not good because you get more wind.
And so often you have to stitch the ramps together from
different gear drivings.
So I have a little acceleration here.
This is what you will hear is this.
Combined, here is the engine and the exhaust on the car and it's stitched so it's the end of the ramp is from another take.
It sounds like this. This is the same Camaro as you saw before the picture.
As you could hear, there is a supercharger engine also.
So the winding comes from the engine compartment.
And we have the acceleration.
This is just the basic recording.
OK.
So finally, implementing a few words on that
will be quite quick.
There's a few considerations when you make your assets.
You need to look at what frequencies the vehicles are in
and make room for your vehicles in the rest of the game.
So if many vehicles have quite a broad range of frequencies,
you need a low end to make it feel powerful
and you need some of the mid to make it sound cool and so on.
And it's important that you get this through in the game.
You have to be careful not making sounds too repetitive.
In a film, for instance, if you have a car chase or something,
you can always change the camera.
So you can alternate the sound a bit from inside, outside,
and all that.
But in many driving games, you have the camera
fixed a couple of meters behind the cars for hours.
And that can become quite annoying to listen to
if it's too raw sound or so.
So you need to be careful how you tackle that.
With the music, an example of that is I worked on the Mad Max game, and when there's like vehicle combat in that game, there's can be like 5, 6, 7, V8 engines roaring, so it's already quite messy.
And on top of that you want combat music.
So I specifically asked Mats from Pol, who did the music for
that game, to make music with less bass information in it,
and try to make the music a bit wider so that we could fit
the vehicles in between that.
And we also add a lot of add-ons, of course.
The engine is just, as I see it, a small part of the vehicle.
All the add-ons are super important.
It can be suspension sounds, chassis transmission, turbos,
superchargers, as we're hearing here.
the wheels on the ground, different surfaces and all that.
And I'm gonna show you just very quick in F mode
what that can look like.
Yesterday when trying this we had a bit of an issue
going between the software, so please bear with me
if you get static on the screen here.
Now, it worked fine that way, anyway.
So here we have a few different add-ons.
It's Speedwind here, Rolling Tarmac, Tarmac Skids,
I think it is on this one, Chassis Rattle,
and Suspension Sounds.
All of this is looping sounds, except for the suspension
sounds, which are triggered one shots.
So I'm going to go through these very quick.
We don't have much time left here.
Speedwind, of course, speed driven.
Maybe it doesn't sound much like this, but adding it on the vehicle makes the vehicle
sit in the world immediately in a very nice way.
And then we have tarmac rolling, also speed driven of course.
A bit dirty tarmac is setting, there's some dirt in it.
And together with the speed we get this.
It adds a lot to the sense of speed.
Then we can add skids and spins on this.
Next up we have the chassis rattle. Sounds like this. Also speed driven.
This might be an old vehicle, quite squeaky.
I can add speed with that as well.
Then we have the suspension. It's driven by
pyramid polygonal droppings here.
And this, of course, has to be fed from the physics of the game
to work properly, but it gives a nice package.
So now I'm going to try to go back.
So fingers crossed it's going to work here.
Yep.
So last year, we have some other considerations
with implementing, which is more of a game design issues
that you can get into.
Game directors is one of them.
They make the decisions.
They decide whether the vehicle should be easy to drive,
difficult to drive, if there should be a learning curve.
And they also have a saying about what's good and bad often.
And the decisions they make,
especially whether it's gonna be hard or easy to drive,
that affects physics and vehicle behavior.
And that indirectly affects audio, of course.
So that's something you need to try to sort out
quite early on on a project.
You have level design.
If you have V8 cars, powerful muscle cars, physics driven,
going around in the desert, that would mean you wouldn't
have any grip.
You would be spinning and skidding around most of the
time, but you still need a proper game play and a
drivable car.
So that gives you quite a contradiction to work with.
Another problem with the level design can be, if it's a huge area, nothing that really affects the driving.
So you can go full throttle all the time.
You will eventually either gear out and get a quite annoying sound by just staying on the...
straight RPM for a very long time.
Or you might want to try infinite gears,
and then you will have a vehicle just gearing up,
gearing up, gearing up, gearing up,
and that will sound ridiculous after a while.
On the other hand, if the level design is done
in a different way, you might need to brake sometime,
you need to turn, and all that can make the sound
much more alive.
So it's also something you need to look at.
Game pacing, very important.
If you have an action game where you enter a vehicle and
it should be up at full speed in three seconds and get
through seven gears in that time, it will
sound very weird.
So you're going to need some kind of filter in between to
make it sound OK.
Also, with the physics, the friction on the ground and all that will affect.
So you might have done the coolest skidding sounds with a huge difference between low
skid, high skid and all that.
But if the friction is set up so you just get one value, totally full skid all the time,
then you need to have like a smoother or something in between that as well to make it work properly.
I often say that audio is often the symptom on something else being the cause,
because you get it like a sound bug reported.
Okay, there's something wrong with the audio.
But when you start scratching on the surface,
you realize that this is not actually the audio.
The audio is doing exactly what it's told,
but it's the physics driving the audio that's not set up correctly.
And then we have the mix.
You need to make the audio interesting over time.
One way to do that with vehicles can be to actually highlight when the player does something.
It can be when he turns, he or she, by the way, brakes, accelerates, bumps into something
and then you can bring up the engine or certain parts during the gameplay.
If you just have the engine up front in your face all the time it would be very, very boring
I think.
So other sounds to bring up can also be the rattles and the wheels and all that and also the music of course if you're driving for a long period of time.
Finally, I will show you just a very short example from in-game clips.
It's some footage from Battlefield V. I had the honor to work in-house creating vehicles
along DICE, an amazing audio team for Battlefield V. And there's also some footage from the
older Mad Max that I worked on a long time ago, which I still think holds up pretty well
actually with great work from Avalanche's audio team.
This clip starts out with a V1 rocket coming in the sky,
and that sound comes from a crazy Pulse Jet Snowmobile recording that we did.
They're not the grand moats or what sits on the hood!
Great power for us!
Yep, that's it for us, so QA.
Hey Max, it's Mike from Grand Trees.
How's it going?
Hey, good to see you.
Good to see you too.
What do you guys use for syncing all the field recorders on site?
Do you guys just jam sync things and then sort of split the recorders up or?
We actually do it very, very manually.
First of all, we set the clocks in all the recorders to
be at the same time.
Then when we start recording one vehicle, we stop with the
onboard recorders at the first position, do a hand clap, go
up to the next position, do another hand clap, up to the
next position, hand clap, and to the last
position, and hand clap.
Gotcha.
Thanks.
How you guys doing? Thank you for the talk. It was great.
Um, quick question with, uh, older cars, you have a manual transmission, so when you let off the gas,
the engine naturally decelerates, you get that nice, natural deceleration sound.
But if you're recording more of a modern passenger car, that's not necessarily like a McLaren,
and you have an automatic transmission, when you let off the gas, the engine just goes down to idle.
How do, how would you, in a, like, normal automatic car, get that nice deceleration sound, like, from a higher speed?
On most automatic cars you have the possibility to lock the gears in first and second.
That's what I do all the time.
Okay, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks for the talk, and great.
But my question is, you know, like,
what all these sounds have in common,
like whether you're doing vehicles,
or like firearms, tanks, and all that,
they're all like really, really loud.
So like when you guys are on location,
what's generally like a rule of thumb,
like where you set dBs,
like when you're recording stuff like that,
like minus 20, or like does it depend
on whether you're doing it interior, exterior?
That's a topic of its own, really.
Depends on what vehicle or what the recorders you have
and how the preamps work.
Some preamps work better if you drive them pretty hot.
Some don't have to be that hot.
Depends on if you use limiters or not.
We have been going a bit back and forth on that.
On the new recorders we have, which are the Sonos Access,
there are no limiters.
That solves the question for us easy.
But not too loud of course, that's not good, but I wouldn't do it too low either.
Yeah, because I've recorded access to some firearms too for first-person shooter stuff,
and doing vehicles, but I've noticed that at least the gears that I have,
like Soundgear 702 and the Zooms and such, I had to run them really, really cold,
just so they didn't clip.
Yeah, yeah.
On the other hand, when you do firearms,
you need the transient to clip because you
need to set your levels on the tails, I would say.
Yeah.
And also, there's also, when we record vehicles,
we almost always have the same combination,
this recorder with this mic.
And you get an experience.
You know, this is a quite loud car.
Let's put it on seven, for instance, or whatever.
Yeah.
So you learn, like, a bit.
what the different recorders. It just really depends on the gear that you have. Yeah,
together with the mics. Great. Thank you very much. Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
That was an awesome talk.
So my question specifically about how you schedule your
recordings, do you usually go into a recording session with
all of the possible maneuvers you would want to record,
scheduled pre-hand?
Or do you have just the things you want to record for the
specific needs of the project?
And also, is this different for film versus games, where
films are more scripted versus games where you could have a?
whole array of things that you possibly need the vehicle to do.
We have a very structured driving schedule.
We always try to do that on every vehicle,
no matter what, to future proof.
Many game developers think they only need onboards,
but then they start doing trailers,
promos, and all that kind of things,
and then the exterior stuff comes in quite handy as well often.
So we always try to cover that.
OK, so you'll cover every possible maneuver
that the vehicle can do?
Yes.
Yeah.
Everything we can find.
I think we are out of time here, so we
need to keep taking the questions outside.
But just grab us outside.
We're happy to answer any questions you have.
Thanks for coming.