Deadly Premonition is best described as a sanity-be-damned romp into the mind of one
of Japan's most unrestrained video game creators.
Pure, unadulterated entertainment.
It's a good thing they took a research trip to the Pacific Northwest.
I think they really captured some idiomatic sense of being in America.
If you can explain what's happening in Deadly Premonition, you haven't been paying attention
enough.
It's the product of a sick and twisted individual.
Kind of scary.
Sometimes unintentionally so.
I really like that his raincoat automatically comes on when it's raining.
He's paying $99 for a turkey sandwich.
Oh, the controls.
The controls are pretty bad.
Dreamcast quality graphics.
It may not be the most technically proficient game I've ever played,
but it's the most unforgettable.
It has a lot of technical polish in areas you might not expect, like in rendering sweaty fat man saliva.
There's this girl in Deadly Premonition, this female monster, and she will, like, stick her hand down your throat when she tries to attack you.
I don't know, that's awesome.
Wargames seem to say, you know what? Fuck it.
It's the best open world third person survival horror action adventure game I've ever played.
You can kind of walk around town and like peek in windows and just watch people doing their everyday life activities.
That's really creepy and that's awesome.
This is a game from a very creative visionary director from Japan.
I'm honestly super excited to see what he does next.
He brews his creations from a funky, fishy flavor, and it percolates straight from his heart.
Game design in the coffee.
game design in the coffee. Okay, start. Uh, good evening everyone, my name is Shua Li from Access Games. Uh, I am the director of Deadly Premonition. Uh, I'm honored to able to speak with you today. Uh, and I'd like to express my
gratitude to those who made today possible. Thank you. And
to those who took part in the video, thank you guys too. Uh,
with me here is Tad Horie, uh, from Catalyst Lab. Hi, Tad.
Hi, sorry. Uh, my name is Tadayuki Horie. I'm from
Catalyst Lab. Please call me Tad. That's what everybody calls
me.
I'm an international project manager.
I translated the script for this game.
I also helped out with some of the voice recordings.
Swery asked me to translate this session
and help with some MC work today.
So we're so glad to see so many of you lovely people
here tonight.
We certainly hope you all enjoy the show.
And so I'm reading off my script.
Yeah, so no matter who you are and what
you do to live, drive, and survive,
there's still some things that make us all the same.
We have to put away our video cameras. We have to turn off the cell phones and turn in these little thingies at the end of the show.
Can I speak Japanese?
Okay.
Point 1, how to make a game that you suddenly remember when you're not playing it.
Point 2, how to make the scenario that you've worked hard on play.
Point 3, how to build a scenario that's unique to Openfield.
Point 4, how to prevent the game from being interrupted on the result screen.
Point 5, how to make a charming character.
Point 6, what I'm worried about when recording voice.
Point 7, what is the most important thing?
So today we'll be talking a little bit about what Sori-san has learned through the process of making video games,
specifically about some tips regarding storyline creation and game design.
We'll be going over these seven points that are on the screen.
I will not be reading them all to you the way Sori did for his Japanese audience here.
Let's keep going. お願いします。
あなたのシナリオが死んでるかもしれないポイント1、デッドリーポイントですけども、
遊んでいないときに思い出さないゲームは死んでいる。
We want to talk a little bit on the first point, we want to synchronize the player with
the character on screen.
the players outside of the TV set, the characters inside the TV screen,
what we as game designers want to do is
try to fade that barrier, make that kind of disappear as much as we can.
So gamers who smoke have said this a lot.
When York lights up a cigarette, it
makes the player want to light up a cigarette, too.
There is a cause and effect going on.
Having as many of these scenes in the game
that causes an effect to the player is a good thing.
Go ahead, next.
In addition to cigarettes,
people may also get sleepy, or hungry,
or grow out a beard,
or smell bad,
or have cigarette smoke.
When we add these elements,
And in the same fashion, Deadly Premonition has sleeping, hunger, and shaving, and wanting
to stay clean so that you don't have those flies flying around you.
These things seem totally unnecessary at first glance.
They help with the cause and effect because they act as reminders to the player.
It's not about...
Seeing the character on the screen go to sleep and then thinking that I should do the same. It's more about
Having what goes on the TV screen acting as a reminder to the player
Oh look at what time it is. I better get some sleep or maybe I should get something to eat
I haven't eaten yet these reminders in life
They're interesting to actually go into a part of your special part of your brain that kind of remembers them
And so the next time you actually shave or go to bed or eat something you have that memory
linked with deadly premonitions
In Deadly Premonition, we incorporated these kinds of physiological phenomena
to make the game so that the user can remember how to play the game
when he or she is not playing the game.
I thought that these physiological phenomena were the most effective,
so I incorporated them.
In particular, by incorporating coffee fortune-telling and movie sequences,
I tried to play more experimentally.
After drinking coffee, people who do coffee fortune-telling have a habit of peeking into the coffee.
I think that the movie sequence, where Yorke says,
this movie is recommended, and by talking about it in the game,
people who watch the movie later, or buy the DVD,
or increase the number of people who watch it, had an influence.
Soeri likes to put in daily human needs, physiological deep desires into his games
because they help causing an effect to the player who is sitting, again, outside of the TV screen.
And for that premonition, we took another step forward,
and we put in some what we call playful elements,
like fortune-telling coffee and conversations
about old movies.
People have come to us and said that they've
taken deep looks into their mugs of coffee
for signs from heaven.
And they've also told us that they've
rented one of the movies that Jörg talks about in one
of the driving sessions in the car.
These fun little elements helped us make players actually remember the game, regardless of whether it occurred days or months after they finished the game, simply having a cup of coffee or seeing an old movie would trigger these memories linked to Deadly Premonition.
These things like the movies or little coffee segments, they linger in your mind.
So it helps with the lingering effect of the game after you finish the game.
So the next point here is about being forced to play through a storyline that has tightly
set rails.
Those kind of rails basically make the player feel like he's being forced to do something.
So how do we alleviate that?
People ask a lot of times, how do you make players actually want to play through this
one path storyline?
So here are two commonly known methods that would help, multiple endings and side quests.
They both add some branches inside the story that help with creating some kind of player
sense of freedom.
And Deadly Premonition, we chose a third method.
It was experimental, and we called it the freedom of timing.
Freedom of timing basically means allowing for a change of heart, creating the illusion
of freedom.
It's a game flow.
First, the quest starts.
Then, what's written?
Challenge?
Then, there's a challenge.
After that, there's a judge.
This is the judgment.
It's only whether you succeed or fail.
For example, if you fail,
you get a hint and go back to the start.
If you succeed, the quest ends.
Can I do that?
Yes.
Next, I'd like to talk about how this is different in the case of D.P.
After the quest starts, there is a split at the timing of the challenge.
Here, not only do you proceed with the quest and proceed to the judgment,
but when the player is determined and wants to quit in the middle,
you can quit and return to free play.
We have prepared such a split.
When you play the game, sometimes...
and I often end up in a situation where I have to fail to quit.
But that's not the case.
I want to do something else while I'm quitting,
and that's one of the options.
I made that choice again,
and that's what makes me different from other professionals.
So while moving forward in a quest,
there are times when you want to change your mind as a player
and not follow that quest.
And however, most games, when you do that,
it just equals a failure.
You failed on that quest.
That's the standard game flow.
But for Deadly Premonition, we thought
that should be allowed as a player's decision.
And so we spent some time making an extra branch
so that the player can have that as an option.
This allowed players to feel better
about taking a break from the game,
and this allowance of a change of heart, if you will.
makes the player feel more comfortable, and once they are comfortable, they are more willing to cooperate with the story.
There are times when you just want to do something else in the game, but if that causes a failure, you feel so constricted.
But D.P. wanted to change that.
When the game failed or stopped midway,
the game's operator would say,
Oh, that's great. I thought so too.
So we made it so that the player would agree.
And the player would think that the choice was okay,
and they would feel at ease,
and they would think, I can play freely.
I think that's an important mechanism.
So in the flow of the last slide,
if the player fails to move forward, he fails.
And so he's given a hint, and he has
scolded at the same time.
It was like that in Spy Fiction on the left here,
another game that Suerison made a while back.
Your player's partner, Nicholas, would say something
like, what are you doing?
Mission failed.
However, on the right side, what we did on Deadly Premonition,
we wanted York to go along with the player when
the player changed his mind.
That's exactly what I was thinking, that kind of thinking here.
And when the player hears that kind of friendly response,
it causes the player to feel okay, a little bit more comfortable, more in control,
and hence this sense of freedom.
And there's another trick in DP.
In a story, you don't have to rush the important characters.
What's important is timing.
You have to play at your own timing.
And in Deadly Premonition, we even took another step.
We made an important character say that you have no need to rush.
You can take your time, you can do things at the time that you want to do them.
Modifying the story to confirm that this is okay to change your mind allows for the player's
desires to be fulfilled.
Third, I will give you a recap of the freedom of choice.
First, you can provide a system that allows you to retire anytime.
This will prevent the player from being forced to do so.
Next, you agree 100% with the player's actions.
This will make your actions justified and the player will be honest.
Third, you can follow the player's actions.
So to recap this third point, we allow for a retry at any time, which makes the player
feel like he isn't being forced and has some freedom.
Then we agree with the player's actions 100%, and that causes the player to feel like his
actions were approved, and that always feels good.
Have the story allow for it, too.
That's the third box here.
Just having the story allow for it.
makes the player feel empowered by the game because his desire is actually fulfilled.
And now here's why we do all of this.
It helps to make the player ease into the story.
It helps to get gamers immersed into the world you created.
They have to suspend their disbelief in order to do that.
And you have to make it easy for them.
And once that's done, the gamer will cooperate with the story.
They'll feel more prone to do what you tell them to do.
And that way, they'll proceed along the path that you create.
Next up, point number three.
In general, I had little impression of the characters performing on stage.
Speaking of which, I changed the title of the session.
Is everyone bringing coffee?
So, yes, we need to make a universe and people,
characters in our game that resonate with our audience.
By the way, does everybody have a coffee?
Did everybody bring their coffee?
Oh, good.
Can I have a cup of coffee?
He wants to take a coffee break.
Yeah.
Let's take a break.
Let's move on.
Yes.
Usually, when you write a scenario for a one-way game, you write a synopsis, then a plot,
and then you make a character list, and then you make a scenario.
This is how it works.
Like this.
You write a synopsis, then you make a plot, and then you make a character, and then you go to the script.
and create the details of the characters.
But DP is different from this.
DP first prepares the synopsis.
After that, instead of going to the plot,
we spent the most time creating the map and the characters.
We actually went to the interview, drew the map of the city,
and for the characters that appear there,
we made a code table that took 24 hours.
and then create the plot and the scenario.
This is how we create the story.
Rather than making a single movie,
we create the characters and the story.
It's like making a TV drama or a Japanese manga magazine.
I think it's similar to that.
So normally for a single path storyline,
you do what's on the left.
You'd create a synopsis, create some kind of plot,
list up your characters, and create a storyline.
It's not uncommon that you would start making the map
and figure out all of the details of your characters
backgrounds after all of that other stuff has been done.
But for Deadly Premonition, we did what's on the right here.
We created the synopsis, and then we
went into some more details for the character,
created the map.
and then figured out the details of the map and what the characters would be doing on a 24-hour timetable inside that map.
And then we created the plot and storyline.
I think that, like the story, setting the world and the characters are very important.
The reason is that the player is always in the open world,
and while they are in the Greenvale city, there is no space.
I wanted something to happen while they are there,
so I think it's important that the city is always moving.
So why, you may ask, did we do it this way?
It was because the characters and the universe
are just as important as the storyline.
When we started the development of it,
there weren't many games that we could refer to
that had an open field, free roaming style gameplay.
So we had to figure out a way to do this on our own.
The player, we knew that the player
was gonna be placed in this world,
this town for a long period of time,
and so the stage of the town of Greenvale
was very, very important.
then we figured that, you know, well, who would be living here in this town that we've created?
And once we went through that process, we were able to create a very rich and dense, deep universe.
And in hindsight, since the detailed story was written after the setting and the characters
were made, one might say that it was created more like a TV series rather than like a movie.
This is pretty important, but when you're playing a game, you're usually only concerned about the ending,
but the game that you're more concerned about the ending than the next chapter of the story is over.
Ah, I made coffee.
Hold on, please.
Alcatraz glass?
He went to Alcatraz.
Thank you.
So, let's go to the next page.
In a normal game,
there is a task, a hint, and you have to clear it.
Then, you get a reward, money, and other things.
Then, the result screen appears.
You have to go back to the beginning and repeat the process.
But after the result, you want to quit.
You want to quit, and that's what happens.
So normally, you would take on a challenge, you would receive a hint, and when you finish it, you receive a reward, and you get your results.
And the player's mind is now thinking, something just ended, is this a good place to quit?
So for Deadly Premonition, we did this.
We inserted a glimpse of the next challenge before the result screen.
the player's mind is now thinking, I want to know more of what's coming next.
The results screen actually acts as a tickling tickler.
It basically tickles you to want to know what's going on in the next scene.
This is a cliffhanger.
It's still not in the game, but it's quite important.
I hope more games like this will be added in the future.
It's kind of like a cliffhanger.
As games are going to progress...
people are going to want to make episodic games and these cliffhangers will be very useful.
Next. What number is it?
Number 5.
The game where you can't remember the character's name is over.
It says it's a virtual game.
If you can't remember any of the characters' names, then that game is garbage.
It's a game where you can't remember the characters' names.
The character is very important.
I have three points.
First, let's write a history.
When I write a history, I use a mind map.
For example, the character is an FBI agent,
so I think about how strong his body is.
And not only the character's appearance,
but also his various characteristics, such as hobbies and hobbies.
To put it in detail, his academic background,
his first love,
and his favorite books as a child.
You need to spend a lot of time to make deep characters, and it really helps in Sori-san's
mind to create a resume for each of the characters that you want to create.
So he likes to use mind mapping, as you can see here,
to get at least a fuzzy image of the character.
Then he likes to write down some notes
to generate a resume at the end.
And when we talk about resumes,
it sounds more like it's just work-related stuff,
but it's not just that.
It's also about physical appearance, personality traits,
ways of thinking, habits.
hobbies, the character's first love, what kind of stuff
did that character like when he was a child,
anything that comes to mind, just jot it down.
And then those notes could then be turned into a resume.
And the resume doesn't have to be final at this stage.
It can be messy.
You can still make changes to it while you're still writing out
the full and detailed story.
But getting just the core elements locked down early,
that would be very important.
If you get stuck in the story when you're writing the story just because of the resume,
then you should probably make a change in your resume.
You're a jockey, young surfer.
I am NOT supposed to answer this question.
Why were you thinking you were a jockey?
What was the reason?
All I can say is that I couldn't do it.
When you finish your resume, when you realize you're not quite right,
The player will imitate it, and even after the game is over, it will still have an impact.
This is just a small example, but I'm happy to receive many fan letters from the users.
This partially goes back to the first point where we talked about having something inside the game affect the player outside of the game.
So he thinks it's important that your fans can actually copy the poses and use the phrases and draw the pictures of your characters.
So you want your
characters to have these elements that are copyable and mimic-able.
In Deadly Premonitions, Sueri-san used some very over-exaggerated moves, animations for
his characters as signature poses and gestures.
You don't have to do that.
It can be a lot more natural.
Some things like he just did, like he scratches his head a lot.
Having that kind of mimicable action in your game.
makes the character much more relatable and dearing.
There are some good-natured and child-loving men,
and that's their favorite part.
But there are also some bad parts,
like their true feelings.
For example, York.
York is an otaku,
and he can't read the room.
Emily is a woman who is terrible at cooking,
and has a lot of insecurities.
And Jason is,
you know,
he's not shy around women.
He's very erotic.
So, let's hear. So, they say every rose has its thorn, and just like every old cowboy has watched the TV show Facts of Life.
So, in life, we are in love with someone. We actually are in love with the good side of that person and the bad side of that person.
We're in love with that mixture, that unique blend.
So don't be afraid to add bad sides of your characters
inside your game.
The three characters that we have here,
we have York, the dapper and looking FBI agent,
yet he's an otaku and he's inconsiderate.
We have Emily, very beautiful looking,
but filled with bad personal problems
and is a horrible cook.
The nice guy on the right has a hard time
keeping his pants on.
So having bad sides to your characters
is a good thing.
It takes courage as a game designer to be adding a bad side to your character.
You want to, when you're creating characters, you want your players to love your characters.
So it kind of goes against the grain to be adding a bad side.
But you have to remember that this is true to life.
When you think about your friends and your family, what have you, they all have a bad
side, but you still like them.
So it's also important to have your characters talk in a way that is memorable.
Here's how Suwari-san directed the voice recordings.
Now, Suerisan says he can't really speak English, at least not very well, but he was still,
as a game director, had to...
give directions to voice actors and ask for new takes and give okays in the voice recording studio.
And so, instead of focusing on the actual content of what was being said,
he focused on how the lines were being spoken.
Does it fit the character situation? Does it sound like the vocal range fits the character?
Does the rhythm and up-downs in tone, like musically, how do they work in the scene?
Liverpool Sound and British Universion.
Let's move on.
I also have a similar idea for other characters.
When I make characters,
I need to have this idea to avoid the risk of not being able to speak English.
George is a violent character,
but he has a legendary image.
He's a hard rock artist from the 80s.
Emily is a country girl,
and she's nostalgic.
And so York, as you saw in the earlier slide, sounded like, in his mind, kind of Liverpool
soundish, British invasion soundish.
Other characters we have on screen, George is tough and gruff.
And Emily.
Yeah, George is tough and gruff, destructive and wild, but kind of like the old 80s rock.
hard rock. Emily would be somewhat not really too country style, but she needed to sound
nostalgic and still fresh and offer a sense of like motherly relief to the player's ears.
Of course, Rui-san did not use this on every character, but he was able to feel the emotion in what people are saying and it's the emotion that's really important.
To recap on this slide, what we're trying to say here is that you need to make sure that you have your own set of rules when you go into a voice recording.
Create some kind of ruler of your own to make decisions with and to make a judgment on what is good and what is not good for the voice file.
And so, what's most important are your ideas.
Please use it when you have an idea.
It's a chance to use it.
It's a waste to not use it.
It's not like you can take it later.
It's better to use it when you have an idea.
It's okay if it's useless.
It's okay if no one notices.
It's an idea.
So I think it's better to include it as much as possible.
This map is meaningless.
But I came up with it, so I'm going to include it.
I think that's important.
We did this because this idea came to Suwari-san. There's no rhyme nor reason to do this, but the idea was there and we wanted to do it.
Yeah, there's no rhyme nor reason.
The third one is, the story is important, but we should put more effort into the characters.
The fourth one is, the result of the game is wrong. We should make the game with the result of the game.
The fifth one is, the story is good, but we should put more effort into the dialogue.
The sixth one is, the story is good, but we should put more effort into the dialogue.
Lastly, the ability to use all ideas when they are needed.
These are the seven points I wanted to talk about today.
Now, that's it for the slides.
Those were the seven points.
Kind of recap, you've read all of them in Japanese.
I won't be reading them all to you.
I'd rather use the time for a Q&A. So let's see here.
But he has one more thing.
Hold on, please.
Is there an idea in his coffee?
There's an idea in his coffee.
Please come see his coffee. There's ideas in there.
Did you find something?
Was there a game design in his coffee?
more art.
So hopefully after we overcome this technical difficulty here, we will be able to show you
a video and then we'll get into the Q&A.
I used to make fighting games.
It's a tomba.
This is a difficult game.
This is my first direction work.
It's him!
FBI Special Agent Francis York Marvel
XS Games
Thank you again.
So, AXS Games will continue to be making games that challenge the boundaries of video game
design.
If given the chance, I swear he would like to use the experience he has to make games
that take, original games that take larger leaps than seen before for the worldwide audience.
So let's do a Q&A if there's anybody have any questions.
Looking at the approach that you took with Deadly Premonition, I was kind of wondering about your opinion on another franchise, which on the one hand does seem to do some of the same things, but takes a very, very different approach.
So I'm wondering what you think of Metal Gear Solid.
Speaking of a different franchise,
a similar type of thing,
there's Metal Gear, what do you think of it?
In comparison with Deadly Premonition?
What do you think of it in general?
I love Metal Gear 2.
I loved Metal Gear 2.
Any other questions?
Not over here.
Oh, please.
Can you talk a little bit about why deadly premonition is set in the U.S., and specifically
in the Pacific Northwest?
What is your fascination with that region, and why did you select that?
The reason why I chose the American people is because I haven't really seen a lot of
US combat experience in the Pacific Northwest, so I don't really know much about the experience
there.
I don't know much about the episodic world, cause I haven't actualy experienced that.
One of my relatives used to live in Canada, and so initially we were thinking about using Canada, but
At the time, we were also thinking about, well, where are most of the gamers?
And most of the gamers are in the U.S.
So we thought using somewhere close to Canada but in the U.S. would be good.
Hi.
Hi, how's it going?
I wanted to ask a question about the nether world in Deadly Premonition.
How it is to have a population that's so vulnerable in the entirety of the game?
So Deadly Premonition has a regular reality and then it has another world that York and
eventually other characters pass into.
And I was wondering if you could talk about that and what the goal, I didn't want to say
what the meaning is, but what the design of it is.
So, I'm going to speak in Japanese.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you.
I'd like to ask you about the back story of Deadly Premonition.
There are two worlds, the normal world and the other world.
There is a place where the yolk grows and solves the mystery.
Could you explain about that?
Oh, you mean the special oil?
Yes.
Well, it's a very complicated story.
The world of Retro-Premonition is a human world,
and there are two worlds, the normal world and the other world.
影響し合っている不思議な空間にあるそういうテーマの話で 赤いっていうのは悪いことで森っていうのがいいことをみたいなのがあってその赤いっていうのが
人間の世界にこうちょっとずつ漏れ出してきてて それを防ぐのが森でその漏れ出してきているところっていうのが今あの質問いただいたその不思議な
ナイトメアの世界っていうことになります 森のところがとこよ森がいいところで赤がところ
Okay, so it's a complex question.
There's a human world, there's a red world,
and there's a forest world.
The red world is bad.
It's eating into the human world.
The forest is kind of stopping that from happening.
The red world is probably what you mean by the other side.
Okay?
Is that scratch the itch for that question?
Next question, please.
If there were to be a sequel to Deadly Premonition,
would you continue the story with York or would you have a new character?
I don't think we should talk about it again.
Yes, I get asked that a lot.
York went back to the forest so of course everybody is going to wonder, can we still
use him?
But people want to see more of York.
And that's a dilemma.
We can always pretend like Deadly Premonition 1 never happened, and create a sequel.
Sorry, I guess I meant Zax.
Zax, yeah.
I thought it was Zack.
That's a good point.
I have the impression that three songs were used.
Was that intentional or was it inevitable?
I had a lot of time to make songs, but I always ended up using the songs I liked.
So I used those songs, like Life is Beautiful.
Whistling
Well, we had the resources to make more music, so it would be intentional.
Naturally, I had to choose the songs that I liked, and I liked those three songs.
I just walked up, you're next.
A lot of the craft of game design involves
paring down what you want to do.
If you'd had more resources, either with the game engine or more time, for instance,
what things would be different about Deadly Premonition?
Or more precisely, what were some of the things you wanted to do with it
that maybe you had to cut at some point in the process?
YORK UCHIHARA I wanted York to ride a bicycle.
I wanted York to wear cologne.
Good.
Thank you.
This is Amina.
Yes.
So I think a lot of people would say that the combat was the weakest part of Deadly
Premonition, and as someone who designs, I think we're mostly interested in you as an
interactive storyteller.
And I'm wondering what your thoughts are on conflict resolution without resorting to guns.
I'd be interested in hearing your thoughts on that.
But when you make a game, there are a lot of things like conflicts and things like that.
What do you think about that?
At first, this game didn't have any combat.
It was a game where you just held your breath and ran away from the shadows.
But then I was told that it wouldn't sell in North America, so I added combat.
Yeah.
Originally, this game didn't have any combat.
The player was just to control the character
to run away from shadows.
We were told that that would not sell well in the United States,
so we added some combat.
You're wrong.
It probably was a mistake.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Only five minutes left.
So I was primarily curious, seeing that the graphics,
I would say, are not the emphasis of the game.
And seeing how much effort you put into the storytelling
and the detail of the world, I was basically
curious how much of that came out of your desire
not to distract the player, perhaps, with flashy graphics,
and how much of it was just the constraints
that you were operating under.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
Yes, Deadly Premonition went through maybe about four times where the project may have
been canceled.
That happened over a span of five years.
During one of those, after we reached a certain point, we just were not allowed or we could
not.
work on the graphics anymore and that's kind of what happened.
My question is if there was a sequel to Deadly Premonition,
would it take place, would you think about taking, take place
before or after York's story and where else would it, could it
possibly be located?
Do you want to talk about before DP1 or after DP1?
Or do you want to talk about the same place or a different place?
I haven't thought about that yet.
Sorry.
It's all right.
One more question.
Very simple.
In your opinion, what is the point of narrative in games?
Narrative in games? What is the point of it?
Yeah, why? What's the point of it?
Sorry, the question is why do we have narrative in games?
What's the purpose of narrative in games? Might be a better way of phrasing it.
What is the purpose of narrative in games?
It's difficult, isn't it?
You mean narrative story?
Or...
What? I mean, yeah, I'm just curious about the opinion on that.
Like, as simple as that is, what is the point? What's the purpose?
Please take this as a very light question.
What is narration to you?
I feel like he is definitely progressing the idea of narrative in games,
so I'm curious what he thinks of like...
In the case of narration, it's mostly about explaining the story and giving hints.
That's the only thing that's used in the game.
Not just that, but I think it's a very useful tool for making the game more intimate with the player.
That's all for now.
So we're out of time.
So if you guys don't mind, I think we need to end.
But we're going to hang out here.
And you can ask him questions on Twitter.
But we'll still be here.
So if you want to hang out and ask some questions,
we'll be here.
So that's it all of time we have today.
I'd like to thank everyone who showed up.
And also, that helps with this session.
Thank you Ted, thank you Ryan, David, the GDC staff, Chris and Brandon and Megan and
everyone in this room.
I love you all.