All right, everybody. Good morning and welcome. And before we get started, I just wanted to
ask everybody to please silence your cell phones or any noise making devices. And if
you could please just remember that after this to fill out the electronic speaker evaluation
forms, that would be killer. So thanks for coming down today. We appreciate it. I know
Friday morning is sort of a, it's a tough period for most people. We're really happy
that you guys could make it and we appreciate it.
And just to get things started, I'm Chris O'Neill, and I was a senior level designer
on God of War III, and I work at Santa Monica Studio.
And my name is Bruno Velasquez.
I'm the lead game animator at Sony Santa Monica Studios.
We're really honored to be able to do this presentation with you, our peers.
And I just want to say that even though there's only two of us up here, this was truly a team
effort, and, you know, we're just honored that we were able to represent our studio.
And we also wanted to thank GDC for approving this talk and letting us come up here and
share this with you.
So as the title suggests, this talk is about the Titans, and it deals with level design
in God of War III and creating the spectacle kind of landmark sequences that we had in
that game, which were the Titans, Cronus, and Gaia.
So using Cronus as a specific example, we're going to go through the entire development
process from the beginning to the end and really outline the tools and technology as
well as the philosophy that enabled us to kind of create the sequence in the game.
from the beginning to the end and what our process is, how we achieve this stuff.
But before we do that, I wanted to just talk about a couple of things
and just dispel a couple of rumors or thoughts you might have about us.
Us being from Santa Monica studio, you guys probably think that we're obsessed with violence,
that we hate our fathers, that we hurt small animals,
and that we engage in these lavish mass sex parties.
And I'm here to tell you that actually none of that is true.
The reality is we actually just don't hate our fathers.
So just to kind of give you a little bit of background
on who we are and what we're like.
So this kind of fills you in a little bit.
Yes, thank you for clearing that up, Chris.
Really appreciate it.
So to get things started, we just
want to kick it off by showing off this video that
highlights some of the moments in the Kronos Titan
sequence from God of War III.
For those of you who might have not played the game,
and also for those of you who have played the game,
just kind of serve as a little refresher.
So let's go ahead and get that playing.
So my only regret about that was that I wish it were epic.
So let's talk about kind of a high level on what this experience was and really kind of
nail that down. So it's worth mentioning that this was the biggest undertaking that as a
studio we had ever attempted to develop, not only literally but only for, not only literally
but also from an organizational standpoint. Just the manpower alone, the amount of time,
effort, resources dedicated to this was far and away unrivaled in our studio's history.
We had the nice distinction of being evaluated as the number one IGN boss battle, which was
interesting for us because this was never really intended to be a boss battle per se,
but nonetheless we were really happy that that was embraced in that fashion.
The next thing worth mentioning is this is kind of a million-dollar money shot.
And by that I mean it was just, this is a 25-minute sequence and, you know, the amount
of time, energy and money invested in this in order to deliver on something that's really
about one twentieth of our game is pretty extreme considering.
The other thing worth mentioning is this is a five core team developed kind of process.
And what I mean by that is it consisted of me as the level designer,
consisted as an animator, Jason Hall.
It consisted of a combat designer, Adam Poole.
It consisted of, let's see, Tyler Breon, the character artist,
and Gary Kavanaugh, the technical artist.
And three of us were dedicated to this full time from the beginning to the end.
Also, even though we had five core team members, the total amount of people that were involved
at the end were 35, which is about a third of our studio at the time.
The animations required for this character were approximately 420, which were more than
any other character that we've done except for Kratos himself.
Also, the joint of the counts of joints for the character was like 500.
He was comprised, this mesh was also extremely complex.
He had 160K triangles and about 18 million polygons.
The average time, as Chris mentioned before, was approximately only 25 minutes out of a
10-hour game.
So it was really just a, you know, it was a huge undertaking, but it really was, as
a whole, the amount of playing time wasn't as big as the entirety of the game.
Also the character, this was the biggest character we've ever done.
He was approximately 500 meters tall.
So we've never really done anything with that scale before.
So let's really talk about the kind of inspiration for this and where these ideas come from.
And you know, Albert Einstein said that creativity is knowing how well to hide your sources and,
you know, game development is certainly no different. You know, oftentimes things are
borrowed from other projects. And at the beginning of development of God of War II, the God of
War II director, Cory Barlog, had a vision to create God of War's version of the Shadow
of the Colossus, which is another interesting Sony game that came out several years ago.
And that kind of set the precedent moving into the third one, how you're going to start that.
If you watch the end of God of War II, you know that it ends on the back of the Titan guy on this big cliffhanger moment,
which later gets picked up at the beginning of God of War III.
And so, you know, that kind of taking that idea and figuring out, well, you know...
and sharing with you guys, well, how do we actually achieve those moments?
What is our process for, as a studio, for embracing doing these kind of high-impact games
that, you know, really can be kind of these insane spectacles and ultimately very challenging?
So...
The Santa Monica Studio development philosophy is essentially that we always start our games
with a bang. That's number one. It's that we really want to grab the player from the
very beginning by the throat, almost literally, and say, this is what we're going to be showing
you for the rest of the game. Here's how we're going to start it. You know, there's no cool
up. You know, we don't, there's no cinematics really. You know, there might be a little
one, but it's just right into the gameplay. You know, it's just boom, you're in it. And
if you look at God of War I through III, it's always the case.
And we feel as a studio that we have much more of a chance of doing something exciting
and something that the fans will appreciate if we think huge and really are kind of unrestricted
about what we're going to try to do on a level as far as feasibility and what's achievable.
And we're just going to go balls to the wall and figure out what's possible.
And then we feel that after that we can wrangle it in and we can condense it down from that
rather than starting small with what's manageable and expanding outward, which we don't feel
works very well for us.
The other thing worth mentioning is that we playtest a lot, and I can't emphasize that
enough.
There's no secret that these games are released and they have high review scores, at least
in our experience.
It's because we playtest our game probably 12 times externally during the development
process, which can range from anywhere from two to three years.
And internally, on any given level or boss fight,
we probably playtest it between 40 to 50 times, sometimes more,
per level or boss fight, depending
on what stage of development it's in.
So you can see that there's a lot of eyes on this.
We don't develop things in a vacuum.
And the next thing worth mentioning that ties into that
is that my belief and my experience working
at the studio and learning from this team
is that great games are really made one piece at a time.
If you have an intro that's rated a 9 or a 10, and then you have a puzzle after that
that's a 9 or a 10, and then you have a boss fight that's a 9 or a 10, you have a game
that's a 9 or a 10 all the way through.
That's very obvious, but it was something that became new to me, seeing that in practice
at Santa Monica Studio.
One thing that I'm grateful about our studio is that there's a commitment to quality all
the way from the top.
So management really gives us free reign to be creative and to push ourselves and try
to make the best game possible.
Also, we've had some great directors on the God of War series, Dave Jaffe, Cory Barlog,
Stig Asmussen, and they've been the gatekeepers.
Every decision is made through them.
Everything from marketing pieces, everything to the music, they really, really, really
have a grand vision for the game.
And that actually really helps us to get things done because we don't have to make decisions
necessarily through a committee or through a publisher or anything like that.
You know, although we do provide a lot of feedback as a team to come up with ideas,
but in the end we have that one person that really makes the hard decisions.
Also, our studio is good because we specialize.
Like Chris mentioned before, we have a combat designer that
focuses only on making sure the AI feels good, making sure
that Kratos feels responsive, feels great.
We have level designers that focuses only on levels and the
moment-to-moment events that happen in the levels.
We have people that just focus on the character modeling,
environment modeling.
So it's very very specialized and I think that helps us to to really focus on on the things that are
That we really want to push and really sell and it's a good way of
Approach a scene like like the Titan
Also, we don't like to play it safe. You know we try to
Kind of go for something that we're not really sure if you're gonna be able to pull off
So then by the time that we finish it we hopefully still have something that that was pretty grand
So at the beginning of God of War 3, the God of War 3 director, Stig Asmussen, he set forth
to establish the vision with the team and really to figure out not only where the game
will take place and what are the locations and the grand moments, but also leveraging
the previous moments from God of War 2 and really trying to create those within God of
War 3 and the Titan moments specifically.
So let's just talk quickly about establishing a vision for our games.
What does that mean?
When we set out to create our games, generally the entire studio will spend a month or so
coming up with ideas, submitting ideas to the director regarding locations.
And so our locations can be anything from ideas like, I want to go to the future, I
want to go to Egypt, let's do something in the Stone Age, whatever, it doesn't really
matter.
But if you look at God of War 3, our key locations in that game were
were Olympus, were, let's see, Hades,
and the caverns in the labyrinth
were kind of the key locations.
And so it really gives you kind of the diversity
of not only the visual landscapes
that you're gonna be traveling,
but it just gives you good pacing
and to understand the tone of your game.
The next thing we really focus on is defining what our epic set pieces are.
And that's very important for us.
Because if you look at God of War, throughout the game,
there are many iconic locations that you'll
visit frequently throughout your experience playing
through the game.
And in God of War II, another senior level designer
that works at our studio, Jonathan Hawkins,
he had, using this image, came up with an idea from the movie Cube
to create a sequence in our game, which ended up being the labyrinth.
So that's another idea, as well, is to establish those set pieces.
And then lastly, we really work on establishing,
what are our wow moments?
What are the things that are really gonna anchor
and brand the player in their brain and kind of.
The things that they're going to remember, you know, two years from now, a month from
now, ten years from now, are those things that, you know, really cemented in their mind.
And we think about those three things.
And that's the kind of holistic approach that we take in order to establish what our game
is.
We don't define our game by story.
We don't define our game not by story.
But we generally define our game in terms of what do we want to do, what is the most
compelling thing in terms of locations, set pieces or wow moments.
And the director will distill these ideas down and filter them through him.
And he'll ultimately make the final decisions.
So part of establishing that early vision also is the previous, you know, getting the
art team and the concept art team to start developing some inspirational pieces of the
scenes that we want to go for.
So this particular one here is showing off the chronosequence and Kratos, you know, running
around on his arm, kind of setting the tone, setting the scale, and it's really, really
a good platform for us to jump off and start exploring about how we're going to actually
get this done.
Next thing also is doing a lot of storyboarding, especially in the more complex sequences.
This is just a really cheap way for us to get something down with the director and start
flushing out some ideas of what perhaps the sequence could entail.
So it's very important for us to do this sort of stuff.
The next thing we want to share with you is this video.
This is a pretty cool previous video that we did.
We took God of War II assets.
We actually grabbed the Cyclops and we just scaled them up.
And we start parenting all these environments on them.
And it was just really just an early way for us to start
kind of wrapping our heads around how we were going to do,
what sort of things were going to occur on the Titans.
And at this point, we didn't have any tech.
or anything at all. All we had was old assets.
So we just started putting things together to get things rolling.
What's great about that is that you can really prototype something very cheaply
without having to build any art or tech or anything really other than things you already have.
It's a huge saving grace for us because you can sell that idea immediately to the team and to yourself.
So let's quickly talk about the brainstorming process.
There's a lot of different philosophies, and a lot of
different people in studios have different ways of doing
it. The way we do it at Santa Monica Studio seems to be
effective for us.
So I thought I would just touch on that really quickly.
Generally, when we kick off a brainstorm, the director will
come into a meeting with the design team, and he'll submit
a photo, usually, or a high concept.
And in this case, the photo would have been something
previously that we had shown, which is that high concept
division for Khronos.
And so the team is essentially tasked at that point with
with three criteria that they need to define as a group.
And so one is getting on it.
How do you get on it? What do you do?
Do you fly a plane and do it?
I mean, do you, you know, do you go to a Chuck E. Cheese
and then, like, he picks up the Chuck E. Cheese and swallows it?
Like, whatever. Like, how do you get on it?
What do you do there?
Like, what is the thing that you're doing when you're on the creature?
That's very important as well.
And then lastly, how do you get off?
Do you kill it? Do you drown it?
I mean, is he your buddy?
Like, what happens? Do you guys go to McDonald's?
I mean, I don't know.
So you just kind of have to figure those three things out.
And then the third thing is that the team will break into groups, or individually rather, for 30 minutes, at which point, you know, we'll go read Wikipedia or try to come up with different concepts and jog our brain with ideas and we'll basically write all those down within the criteria framework and we'll bring them back and we'll regroup and we'll put it on the board.
And that's a pretty gnarly process and it takes a lot of time, but it's very valuable because you get.
a lot of ideas and it's a huge smattering of different ideas and then at which point
the director and the leads will take that list and they'll evaluate that privately and
they'll figure out, you know, what are their favorite three within that list and that group
of maybe six to eight people will get together and they'll ask his popularity, which actually
is totally a typo, but I just left it in there because I thought it was kind of funny. And
designer spelling, you know, we're super good at it. And at which point then we'll figure
out and assess the popularity of it and, you know,
it'll probably get distilled down to a few, at which point the director will make the
ultimate decision on which ones he wants to put in the game. So it's a very democratic
process that involves a lot of people, and we find it to be very effective in leveraging
the cohesive kind of team brain rather than the individual brain, which is one way of
doing it, but we find the strength in numbers is very important.
So you know a little bit about our philosophy, a little bit about establishing a vision in
our studio, and a little bit about the inspiration.
Let's talk about the research and development because this is not something that was very
easy for us to do.
We didn't have the technology that was in place in order to pull this off.
There was a lot of new things we needed.
So first and foremost, let's see if this is not cooperating.
So there we go.
Initially, we didn't have the ability to attach a character to a mesh and move the mesh around
and have the character respond.
So Fabrice Odero, one of our senior programmers, basically, who works on our navigational system,
he created a dynamic state transition system that would allow any AI or player character
that while moving, the environment around him would respond dynamically to that.
So that was a huge element in terms of selling the dynamism within that experience.
So when players are playing through it, they really feel like I'm on this creature.
I'm not just like standing on a...
a static object.
So next, this is our gray box man, which was the initial iteration of the Titan as soon
as it loads up.
Basically, it's a, it was just a quick way for us to get something, just start animating
something, start trying to figure out if this guy is going to be walking on two, on all
fours, what is he going to be doing in the environment, how is he going to be attacking
or interacting with Kratos.
But this way it was just something really cheap and dirty that we could do and the nice thing about this is that we were
able to get this guy into the game and
Start actually prototyping and getting craters to attach to him and climb on him in a very very economical way
the next thing is
you know, now that we had this gray box, man, we wanted to iterate and start fleshing out
what the character was going to look like. So this is the cinematic model from God of
War II. So we were able to strip that from the cinematics that were actually high rendered,
that were a separate model than the one that was actually used in the game. And we were
able to just quickly take that and start adapting it and start getting it into our new engine.
So that was a huge, huge savings of time for us.
So
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
you all know this, you know, you make games, you design levels, it's very obvious that
you, usually you're working in a static environment, like yeah, maybe your levels will change or
something a little bit, but generally it's a static medium. And the big challenge for
us was that, you know, we built this on a real creature, this isn't faked, so how do
we do that? That was the initial super challenge for us to achieve was...
actually getting all of our in-game kind of scripting logic and our in-game entity system
that controls our cameras, our level scripting, our sound and everything to actually exist
on the player. There was no way that we could do this without having a system created that
would allow us to attach it to the creature. So Matt Arrington, one of our senior tools
programmers, basically built us a system along with our tech art department that enabled
us to attach specific, any game object that we wanted within Maya.
to specific joints that were defined on the creature.
And so as you can see here, you have, you know,
everything in red is kind of designer entities in scripting,
and everything in green is for the camera team,
and everything in blue is for sound.
And so that as the character moves around like this...
those objects from the T-pose would also match the mesh and the position that he moved in.
So this is a hugely important part in actually selling this experience because if we couldn't
have all of the actual information within the game following the character, there was
no way we could achieve this without it being as cinematic.
And so I'm sure you're wondering, well, okay, that's all well and good when you're in a
T-pose, but unfortunately the game isn't played like this because if it were, it would be
pretty bad.
So what we ended up having to figure out was, well, what happens when the character is moving?
So if the character...
you know, is in an animation, then what do we do?
And the big problem with that was that, you know,
immediately going from this to going to this or anything,
all those game objects that you had at a specific kind
of orientation within Maya would just shoot all across the level
and it became super nightmarish for us to try to build this way.
And so what we ended up having to do was to basically
to create a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a,
a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a,
preview animation system that TechArk created for us, which allowed us to play animations
and to see where those specific game objects would exist within the creature itself.
And this is, I can't even emphasize how annoying this process was in the long run.
It was the only way we could do it, but it just takes forever because for all 400 animations
that you have, you have to check that each specific object that you need is in the exact
right location.
at any point in the animation timeline.
And it just is, you can imagine how much of a nightmare that is.
And this thing, there's no secret this thing took, you know,
several years to develop.
So that kind of gives you an idea of kind of how we achieve that.
And the most important thing is that, you know,
really emphasizing in this video is
that we could not have actually done this sequence
without this technology.
And the next thing that we had to do was to create a new collision system.
And so Vassily Filippov, our lead programmer,
and Jim Thielander, a senior programmer on our team,
essentially created us a system that enabled us to put collision
on a meshed character,
on something that wasn't kind of a primitive geometry.
And as you can see here, we kind of have the arm of Kronos,
and the green is the run, and the red is kind of like a no-slip stuff.
And the important thing about that is that we had gone from a studio that could basically
move around primitive shapes that we called CD halls that could be animated, but they
couldn't be very dynamic or very, or really stray too much and have too many polygons,
to a system that enabled us to animate a mesh in the same way we would animate a creature
and to attach collision to it.
So as you can see here.
Here's Cronos as his actual, like, whatever million,
50 million or whatever polygon, I don't even know,
it's out of control.
But we could never put collision on a creature like that
because the amount of just, you know,
faces on a creature is just, it's too crazy.
So there was no way to do it in that fashion.
So this mesh was actually just a visual component.
There was really no collision attached to him.
What we ended up doing was, in the same way you'd have like armor pieces, we had specific
instance versions of collision by region that we would turn on and off throughout, you know,
the sequence.
We would define it by hand, by stomach, by arm, and it was the only way we could do it
without crippling the power of the PlayStation because if you put collision on a character
that big, it's just not going to run.
So this is the way we were able to achieve it, and it was definitely a new system for
us.
So this video showcases a combination of like the three months of research and development
that we did.
Now we had, you know, an actual model in an environment.
We had Kratos fighting enemies.
He wasn't completely falling off.
He was able to nab on him.
And we had some kind of rough animation blocked in.
Alright, so we've talked about all that stuff, the tools, the technology, the philosophy, etc.
And now how do we sell it? This is an important thing.
From the very beginning, the mandate was, well,
we can't just create this kind of like magnificent, like, idiot robot.
Like, this needs to be legit. This needs to be like an actual creature
that you feel you're having an interaction with.
That emotes, that lives, that breathes, you know.
This can't be, you know, we can't spend two years developing something
and just have it be overseas.
We really need to focus on how we sell this experience.
So the first mandate that Sig gave me specifically,
he was our game director in God of War III,
was this thing needs to be alive.
We have to bring it to life.
If it doesn't feel alive, we're totally screwed.
So how do we achieve that?
How do we bring this thing to life?
And the first thing we really tried to create
was the emotional buildup.
So if you play through this experience, you know, from the beginning,
Cronus is rather, you know, amused with Kratos.
He's kind of holding him on his thumb, laughing at his grandson,
and he's basically like, oh, whatever, you know, you're a flea to me.
I don't care about you.
You know, you blind him.
He gets irritated.
You land on his hand.
You break a sword.
Now he's like, he's kind of pissed off.
And then you proceed forward, rip his fingernail off.
Now he's furious.
He's, you know, he's angry.
He's like, what, you know, what are you doing?
You're like, rip my fingernail off?
I got to kill you now.
And so he goes through this kind of dramatic kind of character arc,
and through that process.
You know, he ultimately is defeated and he goes through these kind of agonized stages
where he's becoming progressively more and more disturbed and defeated.
And so you really wanted to try to achieve that in telling that story for the character.
Next thing was we had to really keep this believable.
You know, yes, it's Greek mythology, yes, it's fantasy, but we came at it from the perspective
of how would a man kill the giant?
And we felt that if we could anchor it in that context, then it would feel more interesting
and more believable for the player in the context of God of War.
So that was very key to us as well.
The next thing is dynamicism, which actually isn't really a word, but it's just kind of
something we throw around at Sony Santa Monica, and it's just really is the dynamism aspect.
Making sure that we have those moments where the character throws his arm out and grunts
are falling off and falling into the abyss, or rocks are falling, and that the character
is moving and you're changing states.
You really had to bring that and we really had to sell that.
So the animation early on, when we pitched this idea,
we knew that it was going to be critical to sell the emotion
and to sell the progression of the battle.
And as well as dealing with an actual moving level,
we hadn't really done that before.
The visual effects were also going to be a critical part, you know, all the sequences
which Kratos interacts with them and begins to slowly kill him or do damage to him, we
knew that the visual effects had to be spot on and had to really complement the animation
as well as the sound effects and the VO.
You know, it was important for us to have this sort of dialogue in place so that he
could kind of have a back and forth with Kratos.
So it wasn't just, you know, some soulless creature that didn't have any feelings or
emotions.
We really want to make sure.
So that's why it was important for us to fit as much dialogue as possible throughout the
sequence.
So here we have Kratos, you know.
Men love him, women want to be him, whatever.
And he's seven feet tall, roughly, on average.
Then we have Hades, who's about 20, 25 feet tall.
Then we have the Colossus, who is, I can't read that,
but he's pretty big.
And this is actually the real reference size
of how this would be in the real world.
You have the Empire State Building now
next to the Colossus.
And then finally you have Cronos,
who comes in at about 1600 feet tall.
And so you can see the actual kind of scale
that we're dealing with here on a character such as this.
So we knew, of course, that the scale was going to be critical to really sell this, to make this really grand.
But in order for us to do that, we also wanted to make him a real character, not just a set of pieces like one arm here and one head there.
We really want to build a whole character.
And this really, really, really was challenging,
but it was actually in the end, it was a big payoff.
We also needed to have moments of relative scale.
You know, that's why we had enemies running on Kronos
and Kratos interacting with other enemies other than him.
We also had to display moments
where we could show Pandora's Temple
that was strapped to Kronos' back.
which got a war probably like I think around 70% of the game took place on the back of
Kronos.
So we wanted to make sure that we included those moments as well as the moments where
you could see Kronos place his hand on the side of the mountain and kind of show a couple
shots of the ground to really, really sell that relative scale.
The camera work was also very critical.
We had to make sure that we had, you know, dynamic up shots, down shots.
And then that's another reason why we wanted to have a real character in an environment
because there was many, many points where we needed to really remind the player that they
were on top of this giant character and the director would say, pull the camera back,
you know, way back.
And if we didn't have the real character, we would have ran into a lot of problems.
So by having this guy really be in an environment really saved us.
Also, we wanted to keep it all real time.
So we really reduced the amount of cut scenes
that we had during the sequence and the amount of cuts.
It was one consistent camera from the very beginning
to the end, with the exception of maybe
when he swallows you and you go down his throat.
That was probably the only time that we really cut.
But other than that, it was sort of like a seamless thing.
We kind of, you know, were inspired by like scenes from movies like the opening of Boogie Nights,
where it's just one constant shot going through one scene, of course, without all the cocaine.
But, you know, we really wanted to sell that.
And of course, like I mentioned before, the animation was critical to sell the scale.
We needed to make sure that this guy felt heavy, that he felt grand and slow.
So it was a special challenge for our animation team to really pull it off.
did a great job in emphasizing kind of the sense of scale and how we achieved that. But
let's talk about the design decisions that were intentionally made from the very beginning.
And the first thing that we made, you know, very clear as a team was that establishing
this was an experience and not a traditional boss fight. You know, God of War has a lot
of great boss fights. You know, if you look at Hades, that was a really cool one. Or if
you look at the Hydra in the beginning, you know, we have traditional boss fights that
are stage-based encounters where, you know, you fight a guy who's roughly your size at
this stage and you do damage and you move to the next stage. And you're engaged in kind
of a natural combat.
and a natural kind of, you know, narrative in fighting.
And in this, we were not emphasizing that.
You really wanted to sell the experience,
not so much a boss fight.
The next thing is, you know, that as designers,
we're always trying, and level designers as well,
we're always trying to show the goal whenever we, you know,
you know, to the player whenever we're creating
our environments.
We always want to, you know, dangle that carrot
in front of their face.
And this is certainly no exception.
And, you know, when we were play testing it,
we would ask people, what do you think the goal is?
And, you know.
overwhelmingly the response was, it's his head, you know, it's his head, you see his
head and that's where I'm supposed to go, which was actually our intention, but we were
surprised people intuitively knew that. And the other thing we really wanted to establish
was that in addition to having the, you know, the large goal, you need to have those intermediate
goals as well. So, if that's moving from, you know, the wrist up to the forearm, you
know, and then, you know, destroying his fingertip and showing those goals all along the way
and, you know, presenting them every few minutes is very important for us.
And in doing that, and in having those kind of intermediate goals and long-term goals,
we really feel it's very important to reward the player for everything that we ask them
to do.
And as you move up, eventually, to his belly and go through this whole sequence where you're
fighting a cyclops on his shoulder, you're rewarded with being able to be swallowed by
him and go down into his stomach and then break out of his stomach.
Every five minutes, the player is experiencing something cool.
And I really call God of War a bro on the couch game,
because I feel that every five minutes,
somebody watching you play is gonna see
something interesting.
Whether it's ripping the eye out of a Cyclops,
or if it's fighting a Titan, or whatever it is,
every five minutes you really try
to give someone a big payoff.
And the next thing, obviously, is comfortable pacing.
Yes, this is a high-impact sequence.
And yes, it's very tense, seemingly.
But we couldn't expect the players
to be stressed out for 25 minutes, constantly dying,
constantly frustrated.
We had to create the sense of danger at all times
with picking and choosing very specifically when
we were going to actually have it be tense and hazardous.
And then lastly, plausibility.
And we just really need to have this whole situation make
sense.
There were no laser beams.
We weren't going to ride a magical unicorn and strangle him
with an invisible lasso.
We couldn't do anything like that.
We had to have it make sense.
Is this justifiable?
Could a man kill a creature of this size?
Okay, so we had our research and development.
We've roughed up, you know, some stuff.
We kind of had the layout of what the events were going
to happen.
We knew what the goals were.
Now it was time to actually start executing it,
executing the sequence.
And of course, Kronos was going to be the star of the show.
So we needed to focus on him, make him really,
really detailed.
And one of the biggest challenges was for...
the modeler Tyler Breon, the character artist that worked on Kronos.
That usually we have character artists focused just on the characters and we have environment
artists just do the environments.
But this was a unique case because we had to tell Tyler, guess what?
You're now promoted to environment artist as well as a character artist.
Because at first we were going to have two different people work on this character, one
for environments, one for character.
separately, but we found out that that just wasn't going to work out because it's like
having two people work on the same thing at the same time. It was really challenging.
So I think it worked out for us to actually have the character artist kind of take over
that responsibility as well.
And the next thing that was super important to touch on is that, you know, generally in
a level design process at our studio, you know, the designers will work on kind of the
levels in isolation from the artists and we'll kind of build things in Maya and essentially
construct our spaces how we want and iterate on them.
Unfortunately, in this case, we didn't have that luxury because we had to create this
in tandem with the actual physical model itself.
And so, you know, when you're on top of the hand as you can, or under the hand rather
when you're, as you can see in this photo, and Kratos is kind of climbing along that
path.
And the thing that was very challenging was that, you know, in that ceiling climb state,
the creature, you know, would move his hand, animate it slightly and then he would fall
and there wasn't enough fidelity actually carved into the mesh.
that enabled us to have kind of clean navigational transitions
through the mesh.
So what ended up happening was, in order
for us to get that cut properly.
It was pretty much a nightmarish process where I had to take screenshots and as you can see
here kind of draw in and say, I need more fidelity here, cut here, cut here, cut here.
And then the character artist, Tyler, would spend, you know, an afternoon doing that and
then he would hand that off to our technical artist who would then re-skin the whole thing.
And that process took about two to three days.
So you can imagine just, you know, just assembling that, just the back and forth in that pipeline
was just super arduous.
But it was the only way that we really could do it at the time.
So it was definitely worth noting but super frustrating.
So we're just going to talk a little bit about sort of the challenges that we're facing in
each department.
And as Chris mentioned, you know, TechGuard had to continuously update this character.
And one of the things that we added to Khronos, after the E3 demo was well received, there
was a sequence there where the centaur got de-gutted by Kratos and, you know, you would
see his entrails come out.
So, the director was really happy with that and he's like, okay, we got to do that in
a much grander scale.
We got to put that in Kronos.
So, we had to kind of transfer this super tech that we had developed from a very small
character into this really gigantic scale and that was really, really complicated.
Also, we had, as I mentioned before, a massive joint count, not that kind of joint.
But, you know, we had 500 joints that we had to deal with.
So we had full facial animation on the character.
We had full fingers, everything that was required
to really bring him to life.
And every time that, as Chris mentioned before,
they had to change the path of where Kratos was going
to be running, they had to re-skin it every time.
Eventually, we developed a system where, you know,
we could transfer the skinning a lot easier.
But early on in the beginning, it was not that way.
It was definitely, definitely challenging.
And for animation, we have never really done something like this.
Usually we animate a character that interacts in the environment, but we never had a character
that was the environment.
So we had to definitely figure out how we're going to pull this off.
Because of that we had to deal with stability issues versus aesthetic issues
And what I mean by that is that of course we want to make this guy feel alive like like he's really there
And not not just some animatronic character, but at the same time we had to keep in mind the gameplay
So we couldn't just have him flail around and move like crazy because you know things could you know credits could fall off things could
Could break
you know, and that wouldn't have worked out.
So we had to constantly balance that with the sign.
All right, does the character feel alive? Yes.
Is he moving? Is he not moving too much?
Just enough so that the gameplay is stable? Yes.
And then we were able to achieve that in the end.
Also, the animation resolution, because the character was so large, the further you got
out to his extremities, like fingertips, the animation would start, like, you know, shaking
and it would just start becoming unstable.
So we had to deal with that and we had to, you know, work with our tech art department
to find solutions for animation compression so that it would be able to work in the end.
So let's give it up for Keyboard Cat real fast.
And we love Keyboard Cat.
And so basically, the level design challenges
that we faced, at least for myself,
were that I went from basically working on maps and designing
levels and then handing them off to art
in a kind of traditional pipeline that's governed.
You hand it off.
you just assume it's going to get done.
We have producers that worry about that.
And yeah, you'll interface with the artist a little bit,
and he'll come ask you questions.
But this is very different.
In this instance, the level designer myself at the time
essentially became the nucleus of this effort insofar
as that my job kind of transitioned
into also half producer.
I was also.
I was the only person who really knew everything that was going on with this creature amongst
a massive team that eventually was comprised of 35 people.
So no one else knows.
So we didn't have a producer on it.
So half of your job is actually doing, the other half is just task management and figuring
out where everything is and who's working on what and when it's going to be ready.
So that was certainly a new challenge.
The next thing was, I literally had to become one with the animator.
We might as well have just had our bodies sutured together.
he was my left hand and I was his right hand because I couldn't work without him and he
was basically moving my level around and without us being able to directly collaborate very
easily it was near impossible to do anything in a reasonable time frame. So we had to actually
end up sitting together just like side by side and essentially like step brothers you
know like we were bunk mates so it just became kind of weird but it was actually super necessary
in the end.
And then also working, like I said earlier,
with the new collision system was terribly daunting.
It had a lot of challenges associated with it
in terms of debugging it and making it work.
And then in reliance on other disciplines,
and like I said before, traditionally,
designers at our studio can kind of work in isolation,
but in this case, it was being very much tied
into the animation team, very much tied
into the tech art team and the character art team.
And I needed these guys in order to achieve
what we were trying to achieve.
I couldn't do it by myself.
And then as far as camera design is concerned, you know,
obviously the moving foundation is a huge concern.
How do you camera a level when it's moving?
So we needed to kind of tackle that and figure that out.
And Mark Simon, our, you know, our lead camera designer
who did a great job on God of War III,
camera-ing this map, sorry, this character level, you know,
I think he nailed that pretty well.
And then also, obviously, selling a ridiculous sense of scale was super challenging for us.
And, you know, not being afraid to pull the camera in to show the detail, but also, like Bruno had said, being able to pull it out.
So those are challenges that we face in new ways of designing.
So we've talked a lot about kind of where we came from, but let's talk about, you know,
what happened when we were actually getting it done.
So, you know, after the initial research and development phase and that prototype you guys
saw earlier, where we were into the development process was Nathan Gary was the level designer
on it at the time who had pioneered the technology and kind of taken it in its very early stage.
And the goal now was to get it into a shell form, which is essentially to take it from
the very beginning all the way to the end with our big kind of spectacle moments mocked
in.
It gives us kind of a rough outline that you can play through.
It doesn't have the connective tissue.
It doesn't really have anything in it other than the kill,
and then all the intro, maybe five nodes
of what you do from the very beginning all the way through.
And it's basically just to get a starting outline,
a starting palette to work from within.
But let's talk quickly about that, because it's very important for our level design kind of process.
We, like I mentioned, we use a process where we define shells for our levels.
And so as you can see here, this is the Hades shell from God of War 3.
And what shells enable us to do is to create a continuous mapping and progression of our worlds.
And this is the Hades world.
uh... and all the levels that are comprised in that world and how do they
physically fit together
uh... not only
obviously physically but also in terms of what is the pacing for each area you
know
we need to have a boss fight here we need to have a loading hallway here
there needs to be a puzzle here
a fight space here and we'll actually go through and meticulously, you know, spreadsheet this
stuff and figure out where are our wow moments, what is the time breakdown of our wow moments,
where are our fights, what are the time breakdown of our fights and create a kind of a spike
chart for the entire game and what is it delivering.
to the player from beginning to end.
And so as you can see, it's very effective for us.
And we can literally run through the whole game, essentially,
in shell form from getting to end and say,
here's a vista, here's a fight, here's an epic wow moment.
Some of it's very TBD, but it gives us a good understanding.
So in addition to that, our design philosophy
at Santa Monica Studios to expound on that,
and this is worth sharing, I hope.
Is that we value experimentation iteration over documentation and we do not document.
Yes, we will write things in like Microsoft Word to pitch and share it will brainstorm in that fashion. We will do things in illustrator. We spend most of our time doing we spend most of our time building. We don't find that tying ourselves to documentation is very helpful and in fact or documents always come last.
You know, we don't write game design documents.
We define mechanics, et cetera, after they've been designed,
after we've iterated on them.
And our level design docs are the same.
In fact, we don't even create those anymore.
We just do video run-throughs.
And we find that we don't marry ourselves to anything.
Because, you know, looking at God of War from the outside
before I started working at Santa Monica Studio,
I thought these guys were like insane mad geniuses.
I was like, well, because I came from a world where you design
maps on paper, and then you have to get it right.
And you have maybe one shot to do it.
And that's not the case.
You know, we have the luxury of being able to.
have the time to let things come together and that's very important.
There's a commitment that, in our studio, that things need time to come together.
You can't make a sequence like Kronos or any of our elaborate puzzles
or Pandora from God of War I in a week, two weeks, a month, even three months.
Oftentimes our boss fights take six months to design.
Our high action moments in our games can take years to build.
And it's just about giving it the time and valuing what's important
and figuring out where to spend it.
Additionally, Tim Moss, essentially our tech director,
and Christa Erickson, our tools director.
are very good about giving us strong tools that allow us to iterate very quickly. You
know, like I said before, we can basically build everything in Maya ourselves and in
fact the entire studio works within Maya. There's no, and artists will use ZBrush but
everyone is actually interfacing and working within Maya directly so it gives us kind of
a unified platform to develop from within. And that allows us to iterate very quickly
and to build things and we don't have to go back and forth with art and have them essentially
build our maps. We build the maps and then they art on top of it.
Also worth noting is that in our studio, designers are really encouraged to think for themselves.
This is, like I said before, it's not a one-person vision studio.
You know, it's not one guy thinking of all the ideas and making them happen and telling
people what to do.
You know, obviously there's, you know, people make decisions, but we all think as a collective
unit and we find that that's very important for us in terms of getting a lot of ideas
and distilling it down to the best ones possible.
And then it's also about getting the right people on the bus.
You know, the interview process at our studio is very painful.
You know, we have a gnarly test that takes forever for people.
We give them a week to do that.
And if we get to pass that stage, you probably have, you know,
they're greeted with eight to ten hours of interviews in a day.
And they go through pretty much every department.
And it's very brutal and it's very agonizing.
But we feel that if we can vet our designers and vet our staff within our studio,
then we know that we have people that can handle it and they can do good work,
that can be entrusted, like I said before, to think for themselves.
And we don't have to manage them.
overmanage them and they can create content and they can
really just build and do what they do best.
The next thing is really knowing your philosophy and sticking to it, whatever it is.
Whether the vision of your game, For God of War, for example, you know, it's an action
adventure game with combat, puzzles, and platforming.
And that's our game.
You know, we don't build things that deviate from that.
We don't, you know, we don't try to build like social networking components within the
game.
We don't build PlayStation Home hubs.
We don't do any of that.
We stick to what we know and we continue with that.
And that works not only on a grand scale for our games, but also on a small scale for what
our levels are.
You know.
So for...
designing the lab with levels, you know, we knew that these are mechanical contraption
rims that are essentially hazards and we don't, you know, we don't do anything unique in there.
We don't have, you know, there's no water in there, it's nothing crazy. And so we stick
to the vision and the, you know, philosophy of whatever that is and we keep that going.
And the last thing, you know, is that we really value the strength in numbers and like I said
before we have a lot of people, we have a lot of people that are really, you know, passionate
about what they do and that they can contribute. And, you know, I've worked in a lot of levels
at Santa Monica Studio and I know that
You know, they've always, always, always worked out better in the long run than what I originally
could have conceived.
And had I built my initial vision of what I thought a map could be in isolation, it
never would have been as good as what it ended up being in the long run.
Once you have other people looking at it, you get the feedback from other designers,
et cetera, et cetera, and the leads come in.
And, you know, you get a lot of insight from different places.
And it's very important for us to be, you know, kind of communicative and reciprocative
as far as sharing ideas and being honest.
I just wanted to quickly touch on the art philosophy using this example.
So this is a shot from the announced trailer for God of War 3.
And this was all a trailer that was developed in-house.
We did everything in the engine.
It was sort of a way for us to kind of test our new engine and see what we could pull off.
So we had this moment in the game on the trailer and it sort of kind of set a goal for us
to push towards for the final game.
And although that moment didn't really occur at the beginning of the game on Gaia, we were
able to get that moment into Kronos.
So it's sort of that goal that we set for ourselves, that we want to make sure that
we delivered on the promise that we had established with that trailer.
Also, you know,
pushing ourselves forward, we just want to make sure that the character of Acronis was
the most detailed that we could do. So Tyler Vriand did a great job on detailing everything
from the veins down to the fingerprints. So definitely our most complex character we have
ever done.
The next slide shows sort of like a progression.
First is the cinematic model from God of War II.
And as you can see, the character didn't change too,
too much, but there was definitely a progression
that you can see here.
A lot of iteration, a lot of fine tuning, a lot of detail,
you know, that added, got added over time,
as well as you can see some height changes.
And it's also worth noting that this is anatomically correct.
And Tyler definitely got into some hot water over this.
This was a point of contention on the project.
He was told not to do this.
He did it anyway.
And it didn't end up making it into the game,
because it would have been weird.
Because as you fall off the creature,
there would have been a lot of crotch shots.
And it just would have been kind of bizarre.
And it is a bit ironic for a guy so big.
He is.
not so big.
And someone, I think at one point, they were talking about sex minigame and all this stuff.
We were just like, no way.
We just couldn't figure out how to make it work.
We didn't know.
If you guys have any ideas, we can talk later.
So at this point in development, we had basically created a shell.
Nathan Geary had spent time working with the team, you know, main viewer, animator, et
cetera.
And, you know,
basically building this for us with Tyler and working from the very beginning to establish
the show. And what we were able to do was put this together, as you can see in this
video, from kind of beginning to end. So this is six months into development on the creature
we were at this point, and three months after the tools and technology had been developed.
And at this stage, you could play through it. It had a lot of the major beats. It wasn't
exactly fun yet, but you could see the kind of the spectacle there. There was no connective
tissue really built, and it was all really kind of mocked.
in and to be determined. There was really no art added, you know, it was very basic.
There was still a ton of work to be done, but at least we had a kind of a nice starting
point. And as you can see here, that's our hotbox sequence and, you know, we kind of
have these like weird college humor names that we attach to all of our sequences in
order to kind of create.
like a nomenclature so we can easily reference them within our team and we feel that's helpful
rather than being like, yeah, it's the thing where he's like holding the hand. People say,
yeah, it's the hot box. Everyone knows the hot box, you know. So, and you go through
that and we basically do that for everything that we have in our game. It's kind of big
and requires, you know, a lot of conversation. So that's pretty cool. I see him getting strangled
right there.
And so where we now so now we have to do it for real.
So Nathan Gary moved on to a different position within Sony and that was
exciting for him and it left a vacuum in order to see who was actually going to
finish this thing off because as you can see it was kind of there in a shell.
The idea was intact.
It kind of made sense.
Um, we actually had to do it now and how are we going to do it?
So I was actually brought in for better or worse.
I was super excited in the beginning and you know, I.
I quickly turned to Dread, went to talk to everyone who worked on it to figure out how
gnarly this was.
And we just got to it, man.
There was really no option, so we just jumped in.
And I started working on it with the team.
And I was initially tasked with a few things.
And one of them was to figure out, well, play through it and figure out what works and what
doesn't work.
And I felt initially that things, a lot of it was working.
And in fact, I think it was quite cool already.
But I felt like we were missing some things.
We were missing the dynamism.
We were missing a lot of kind of those big moments I talked about where the character
transition states, et cetera.
And we really needed to shore it up.
We also needed to really create a fight sequence between the
character and Kratos, and really selling that
experience.
And we feel like we didn't really have that at that
point. So we had to figure out what we were going to cut,
what we were going to keep, and what we were going to
improve upon.
So I just want to share with you a couple of the cut stuff.
So this is a part where Kratos is actually going across
to each one of Kronos's eyes and just ripping it out
and then just having at him.
We kind of figured out that by the time that you reach his face, he was pretty much incapacitated.
Kratos is a brutal character, but he's not necessarily sadistic.
So we felt that, hey, he should just go for the forehead and just finish him off.
But on top of that, we just had too many eye-ripping scenes already in the game.
The next thing is this attack that, you know, we had for Kronos early on. Yes, Kratos is
the size of an ant compared to Kronos, but this attack was just way too literal and it
just didn't work out for the character at all. But I just thought, you know, I wanted
to share this with you guys. And so the first thing we decided to tackle was let's just
nail this from the beginning to end, you know, let's just fill it in from start to finish.
you know we started to start with the right arm and this is kind of the right arm and
maybe
I want to say like the pre-alpha stage and
We were kind of figuring out what we wanted to do here and what worked.
And we spent about three months just working on this one section.
And it was the most challenging for us because this is where we really wanted
to sell the actual, even though this is not like a real boss battle,
but you know, our version of a direct fight between the two of you.
So, you know, we have, you know, we have Cronos screaming at you.
We have you running over to him and like attacking him.
And we had a, we really struggled with this for a while.
You know, we were struggling with the transition state from this point to the belly.
And one day, we were sitting there and kind of out of frustration,
and he said, well, why don't we just rip his fingernail off?
Thinking people were going to be like, oh, that's a bad idea, whatever.
Everyone was like, actually, that's kind of cool.
Let's try that.
And so Jason Hall mocked it up that day, the animator, and we just.
we tried it and it instantly sold itself.
People were like, that's really, that's terrible, actually.
That's weird.
Why would you do that, man?
I'm like, you're ripping people's heads off
and doing all this other stuff,
which is really kind of unrelatable,
but everyone can kind of relate
to having your fingernail ripped off,
and it just is really evocative.
You don't really see that here,
but if you play the game, it's pretty gross.
And the sound and the audio and everything,
it's pretty nasty.
So where did that leave us? That left us at the point where we needed to solidify the progression of the whole experience.
And I liken kind of Cronos to, you know, like a classic car.
You know, if anybody who has had a classic car knows about them.
You know, everything will kind of work when you get it, you know.
And then like a week later, the windows won't roll up and then the sunroof won't close.
And then like, you know, you need like a new oil pan.
And like what happens is that you can never get everything above water.
Everything, something is always submerged. Something is always malfunctioning.
And that was the case with this. It took us about, I would say, you know,
nine months just to get it to a place where we could play through the whole thing from
beginning to end with progression. And that was really our goal, was can we get through
it? And it took forever, you know, it kept crashing or you'd fall off and that was gnarly
and very disconcerting. And then that took us into the next stage, which was the play
testing and kind of iterative process stage of the whole experience. And I liken this
very much to being attacked by a shark while you're riding a helicopter under the Golden
Gate Bridge.
And for all of you who have done it, it's awesome.
Or if you haven't done it, you know, whatever.
Check it out.
But as you can see here, it's wrought with peril.
And it tests a lot of your assumptions.
And it can be very taxing and time consuming and
frustrating, ultimately.
So we went through that process and we figured out that
people were responding well to this.
They were falling and dying a lot.
But they were responding to the grand spectacle of the
whole thing, which we were very happy about.
And that opened it up for us to figure out, well, as game
developers, we're aware oftentimes it's
It's not what you add to an experience, it's what you take away from it in order to create
the better experience and what to subtract.
And that was certainly the case with this sequence.
In some respects...
we had to find things to add to, because we felt like we were still missing things at
those later stages, like the sequence where you saw earlier, where he grabs you off the
belly and holds the hand out, and those dynamic state changes, and we really wanted to sell
those.
So we had to get those in, and there were a lot of eye rolls about that when I suggested
to do that, because, you know, we were already pretty much screwed, and seemingly unable
to pull this off in the time we had, but we felt if we were going to do it at all, we
had to go big.
So now that we trimmed the fat and we had everything working,
we had a progression, that was time to really turn up
the volume and polish this thing out and get it out the door.
So that's when all 35 members.
all hands on deck, everybody jumped on board to start polishing this thing, getting it
together.
So team members like Max Ankar, who's the lead visual effects artist, you know, did
a great job on Khronos.
Kerry Gavina, the technical artist that worked, he can tell you some crazy stories about working
on Khronos.
But, you know, they did it, they pulled together, everybody came together.
So this is a shot of pre-alpha Khronos.
And here's a nice transition to what it actually ends being.
So this is the moment that was most exciting for us.
We're starting to get the visual effects, the sound,
everything's, the new updated animations,
the final character models in place,
and the frame rates becoming more stable.
It was really, really, truly an exciting moment for us
at this stage.
So at this point, it's pretty much alive, and I think that for us and for me, this was a big experience to have it all come together.
This is the hardest thing I ever worked on, and it was a situation where every day it seemed impossible.
Every day, people didn't feel they'd be able to do it in time, or people couldn't see the vision.
And it was very challenging. It was like looking into a dark abyss.
And as game developers, we all know that.
and working in a creative medium with time constraints,
you know, you don't, you can't see the end result necessarily,
but you operate on that daily faith
that if you guys work hard as a team
and you try to be as, work as smart as possible,
you'll be able to pull it off.
And that was, you know, that was, it was very rewarding for us.
And to work on something like this
was really why I got into games.
It was to work on cool things that I was excited about
and passionate about with really talented people.
And to me, it was very satisfying, you know.
professionally, emotionally, personally, in order to work on this and pull it off and
to see it all the way in the end.
And I remember, you know, having to set this up for a year and a half, I went through this
and I played it after we got all the VO in and everything.
And I remember playing through the whole thing and just really being blown away in the end
when, you know, stabbing him in the forehead and he's like pleading with you not to kill
him.
And I actually felt bad, you know, which was weird because if anyone's like the Wizard
of Oz on this, it's me because I set the whole thing up over the last year and a half.
But I actually felt that we had achieved what we set out to achieve, which was delivering
on the believability and the spectacle and selling the experience.
For me it was a kind of like a unique experience to be able to work on this because I kind of had
Sort of like I was able to step back
I wasn't actually doing the day-to-day animation on the character
But I was able to sort of supervise and see it born all the way from that you know
Got over to Cyclops
Previous animation to the gray box man to each iteration and I could really see this character growing and slowly coming to life
So I just you know
I'm very grateful that I had that opportunity to kind of have that perspective on the sequence.
We're wrapping up now, but I'll just jump into an outro clip, and this is kind of how it ends.
And so lastly, I just wanted to give a lot of thanks and
credits to everyone who couldn't be here that worked
on this.
Like I said, it was a massive team effort.
And this is a list of everyone that worked on it directly.
And we just wanted to thank them personally.
And then if you like money watching mansions and cars
like we do, and you like what you see, we're hiring.
So you can check us out at the Career Pavilion if you're
interested.
Check us out.
Come on down and join the team.
That's something we have for future projects
we need help with.
And then.
Lastly, if you want to get in contact with us,
if you have questions about any of the stuff that we've done,
this is our contact information.
And yeah, it was great.
We don't, unfortunately, have time for questions.
I think we ran the full schedule.
But you can meet us outside after the meeting
if you have any questions and you'd
like to talk about it with us.
Please remember to fill out your speaker feedback forms.
And let me make sure I got everything else.
Yeah, that's it.
That's it.
All right, thanks a lot, guys.
Thank you so much for coming, guys.
Thank you very much.