This is GDC Podcast Episode 3.
Remixing the radio host voice a little bit.
I should super...
This is GDC Podcast Episode 3.
Hey everybody, we are back. I am Chris Graft, Editor-in-Chief of Gamasutra. I'm here with my co-host Alyssa McAloon.
Hello, I'm Alyssa. I am the News Editor over at Gamasutra.
You are, you're also the associate publisher.
Yeah, I think you explained that my job is to stare at the website all day.
Yeah, yeah, that is actually, that was the only requirement on the job description,
must be willing to stare at a game industry website for...
The refrigerator in control, you just gotta make sure nothing bad happens.
Oh yeah, oh, I haven't gotten to the refrigerator in control.
Oh, well, spoilers.
Yeah.
There's a refrigerator in control.
It's been spoiled.
You fight a refrigerator and everybody hates it.
Ooh.
Ffff.
Welcome.
Welcome back.
So yeah, this is episode three.
We haven't been canceled yet by the bigwigs
at Game Developers Conference.
we have managed to stagger away through two
and hopefully we can make it through three
without any major issues.
Yeah, I feel like that's the way to jinx it.
So like knock on wood or whatever superstition
you subscribe to right there.
We are doing so good.
It's perfect.
This is going to be the longest lasting podcast ever created.
So, before we get into our next guest, our next guest is huge, by the way.
She's just basically, I mean, she's Forbes 30 under 30.
I never got that. It's too late for me.
You still have.
I've got two years to do something impressive, so we'll see if that...
Yeah, clock's ticking.
Yeah, and, uh, yeah, and she's also, she was, uh, you know, I'm not going to spoil
anything yet, but she was also, uh, the IGF host.
Um, you know, the indie independent games festival host.
And, uh, I'm not going to even tell you the year because, you know,
that's going to give it away, but it was pretty recent.
And, uh, and she's even a, uh, multiple times GDC speaker.
So, um, yeah, but we're not going to quite bring her in yet.
Uh, what have you been up to?
So what have you been playing?
I got my PC back up and running after it was out of commission.
I killed my motherboard somehow.
How'd you do that?
Don't know.
I hope it doesn't happen again, because I got a new one
that I spent a lot of money on.
Yeah, you know you're not supposed to just pour water
on your computer, right?
Yeah, yeah, no, I'm learning that.
I've been using toasters when I set things on top of my computer
from now on, I think.
Yeah, that's good. That's how I do it now too. No one told me that you're not supposed to pour
water directly on electronics. Just a pro gamer tips here at the GDC podcast.
Yeah, yeah. This is for game developers and just if you want random tips on electronic.
No, I was talking to someone on twitter.com the other day and they reminded me that Disco Elysium
comes out. So I stayed up until 11 putting the pile of parts I'd compiled into my computer and
getting everything working just so I could play this game today.
Yeah, wow. And that's made by, I don't know how to pronounce it. It's Z-A-U-M, Zaum.
But there's also like a slash right in the middle.
It's very stylish, just like the game.
Yeah, the game is very stylish. What do you find stylish about Disco Elysium from Zaum?
It's got that good art. So I think we've both only managed to play like 15,
20 minutes of it on our lunch breaks today.
Yeah.
But yeah, it's got really stylish look and art.
The writing is like, it's like being at a cool little poetry night that a friend of
yours invited you to, and just let it have a kind of jazzy feel to it.
And the voice acting's great, and the first 15 minutes of that game, super fun.
Yeah, yeah, it is kind of poetic. It's also got, it's got prose for days.
And yeah, so far I've had a tie speak to me. It like lets you get in your own head
and you know, you have this inner voice that's talking to you and you talk to it and apparently
inanimate objects talk to you as well. And I like the unexpected weirdness of it.
Yeah, no, it's really weird how conversations come out of nowhere, and like, because it's
a RPG depending on how you build your character at the beginning, it's got that kind of Fallout
2-esque where if you just have zero intelligence, you will just try to hit things with a rock
instead of opening doors.
It's got that kind of writing, but on this really, really poetic, and it's just good.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to putting some more time into that.
Yeah.
So big GDC news this week, registration is open.
You can actually go buy some tickets and go now.
Well, not, you can't go now.
I mean, you could plan ahead a little bit, just show up incredibly early.
Punctuality is important, but...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Try not to show up, uh, five months early.
Um, but yeah, it's a, yeah, shooting for March.
So, uh, that stuff is all live on the website now at gdconf.com.
And speaking of other GDC things, which we kind of like to do here on the morning
announcements, we're on YouTube now, right?
Yeah.
The podcast.
Yeah, the podcast.
Well, us also.
But.
So far the first two episodes are live up there and this one will be once it's live probably as
well too. Episode one is talking to Grant Schankweiler about game production and episode
two is talking to Matthew Burns about designing neat and compelling choices. So you should give
them both a listen, they're really insightful. Give them a listen and then give them a thumbs up.
Like, subscribe and the bell icon is YouTube's thing, right? Yeah. I don't YouTube a ton but...
Oh, you're not a professional YouTuber then.
No, no, only the GDC YouTube channel.
Yeah, cool.
You know what else happened as far as GDC stuff?
GDC stuff happened.
We, we, we closed out the IGF submissions.
We ended up getting 550 entries.
So that is off to the judging process.
There's a lot of, that's a lot of games.
Yeah, no, I, I know a few people, I think were IGF judges that were
talking about it and just kind of like cracking their knuckles to sit down
at the keyboard, because that's a lot of games to go through.
Yeah, do you think they crack the knuckles?
I mean, you have to like cinematic effect, right?
You do the little like flex, then you start like hacker man.
That's how I start every work day.
Typing at your keyboard, yeah.
Yeah, and you know, there's like submissions of clothes like I've seen, you know, the talks that I'm I can't talk about any of this
Uh, but there's just going to be a lot of really cool
talks at gdc 2020
Uh, it was not paid to say that specifically
I'm literally part, you know, I I literally get paid
Uh from by the company that runs gdc. So, uh, I guess but but I really believe that yeah gdc 2020 has some
Really cool stuff coming up, and I frankly cannot wait.
And GDC kicks off on March 16th of 2020, right?
Yeah. Yeah.
March 16th to 20th, it's practically here.
Oh my gosh, I don't like that.
Well, I do like that, but like,
the concept of time moving too quickly.
Yeah, yeah. I can't. Yeah. Well, speaking of moving, I think that we should get our next guest on.
Alyssa and I are kind of excited about this one, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. This is kind of... Does indie game dev have royalty?
What kind of system, political system does it use? I would say that if there was some kind of royalty
or monarchy, our next guest would qualify.
No, I'm a plebe.
Oh, there she is.
Don't worry, I'm just a scrub.
OK, our next guest, we're very excited for this scrub.
She is known for making these brilliant and.
intensely personal games. She is currently a game designer at Tacoma
developer Fulbright while also doing these other really great personal
games known for the IGF Nuova Award-winning Sybil, which is a game
about falling in love in an online game. How do you do it? Where you like take
dolls and you try to figure out how they do it sexually.
And also recently released the really great vignette formatted
game called We Met in May. So here we go. Welcome to the
podcast, Nina Freeman.
Thank you. Happy to be here.
So for people who aren't familiar with you,
and they should be, can you talk a little bit
about your background in game development?
Sure.
So yeah, like you said,
right now I'm a game designer at Fulbright.
in Portland, Oregon, and before that I was based in New York City, so that's kind of where I got
my start. My way back background is in English literature. I did, like, a lot of poetry stuff
back when I was in school. And then I got kind of into the New York City game development scene
through some friends who were doing, like, indie game stuff at the time.
um and through them I like got super involved with going to like game jams in New York and
different events like baby castle stuff and whatnot.
Um, and that's kind of how I got started was just going to these things with my
friends and making tiny games with them and participating in local events and
stuff. Um, and yeah, even like a lot of the
early stuff I was working on was still like
personal stuff, not all of it was because you know I'm just doing game jams with
my friends, but I was really into like personal writing
and poetry so I
since that's what I was doing and that's how I learned to write, I sort of instantly brought
that over into my game development life. And during that time, that's when I worked on How
Do You Do It with a bunch of my friends in New York and a bunch of other games. Sybil
sort of came out of that as well, although I ended up working on that pretty heavily when
I was in grad school at NYU and their integrated digital media program.
And then shortly after I got a job at Fulbright and worked on Tacoma as a level designer and
still worked on my own personal projects on the side, again with lots of different friends.
I always work with sort of different teams on each side project.
But yeah, so I've been doing Fulbright stuff and otherwise keeping up with my
smaller games work on the side.
So that's sort of my background.
Great.
Yeah.
So all of you aspiring game developers listening right now,
that's exactly how you get into the game industry.
And that's how you just have to do it.
Follow it beat for beat and guaranteed success.
Solved.
It's always interesting to hear how many people in games...
I'm a former English major.
I graduated with an English for New Media degree.
And I think two other people at Gamasutra are too.
And a bunch of people in games.
So it's always interesting to see how that spirals out
into different careers in game development.
Yeah, for sure.
I mean, what else? I mean, I also have an English degree.
And then I end up doing, I'm doing a podcast now.
So I guess, you know, it's also how you get into podcasts.
So English degrees, game dev, or podcasting.
That's how you do it.
Very multifaceted.
Yeah, so it's interesting also just academia leading into this career.
There are lots of young people, there's always that question, you know, do I need to get a
like a game design degree or game development degree to, does that improve my chances of
becoming a game developer or does it matter?
I think it really depends on the situation.
I mean, school in general is always going to be good, right?
Like, you know, getting an education is good, but
it can be super expensive, so the only reason I was able to
do...
undergrad and then grad school was because of like the immense amount of financial aid I got
because I did not come from a rich family. So I was really lucky in that sense. But I think like
go to school if you can afford it and you're not going to completely be like in debt for the rest
of your life.
And if you can't really afford it, there's a lot of other ways to build up what you would get from school.
I think the best thing you can get out of school for games is a portfolio and a body of work.
And also being a part of a social space where developers are giving each other feedback.
I think those are the two most important things that you can get out of school.
But you can find that just in the real world too.
I had that when I was...
getting into the game scene in New York just because there was so many like community events
that weren't academia related. And I really got my start making games in that environment where
I was like just with friends, people in school, and people not in school at local stuff. So I
think it really depends on your situation, but I wouldn't...
put yourself in debt for school, personally.
Just make stuff, like, ship stuff, put it online, meet people, get feedback, actively
seek that stuff out, and just, like, build a portfolio if you're in school or not.
For some people, school makes that a lot easier, and if you need that, that's totally fine,
but...
Yeah, don't go into too much debt.
No debt.
Yeah.
It's tricky.
It's a tricky thing.
It is.
Yeah.
So, let's talk about your games a little bit.
I had played Sybil in the past, but I hadn't played all the way through it because I just
I don't know, I just get, I have the attention span of a caterpillar or something.
But yeah, so I did actually play through it recently again, and it's, you know, it's completely
brilliant.
Can you kind of, can you explain the background of that game for people who aren't familiar
with it and what you were trying to do with it?
Yeah.
So Sybil sort of...
The beginning of it actually hilariously happened when I was in school.
I was at NYU in grad school, and I was in Bennett Foddy's Prototype Studio class, which
was the class where we made a game a week for a whole semester.
It was like a game jam a week, basically.
Each week had a theme.
One of the weeks, my friend Francesca and I were like, let's have the theme be sex!
We just decided we want it to be, because we make games about that.
So we forced that theme on the class, which was funny.
And...
So out of that theme came the idea for Sybil,
and I made like a little prototype for it,
which was really cool.
And I was into it and wanted to work on it more,
and Bennett encouraged me to work on it more.
And I had a bunch of friends who I'd been jamming with.
So Emmett Butler and Deki Koss,
who had both done How Do You Do It With Me.
Emmett doing a lot of code with me,
and Deki was the musician, sound designer,
and I did design stuff.
So I took the prototype to them and was like,
hey, do you wanna work with me again?
And then Rebecca Dunlap came on.
She's an illustrator in New York, really talented,
and I knew her, so I invited her to work on it too.
So it started out as a small project
that came out of a class.
I decided to do it for my thesis.
It's based on my real experience
playing Final Fantasy XI as a teenager
and falling in love with this guy.
And him and I met up and had sex,
and that was the first time either of us had sex.
And then, yeah, the game is about how he kind of just like bounces after that.
And it's, yeah, it's like, you know, I don't know.
It's hard.
It's a hard game to spoil.
Cause it's more about the details.
I think, um, the mechanics and design of it are kind of inspired by games like
Gone Home, which are games where you experience the story through the
things you find in the space.
Um, it's a combination of that with a lot of sort of voiceover stuff.
So.
That's kind of how that game got started.
What did the what are the prototype for Civil?
Because it's like simulating, you know, it's your desktop, you know, quote unquote.
What did what did that game in its early stages look like?
So the prototype was like a little pixel art 2D
game that.
was basically the same as what ended up being like the game in a game of Sybil.
So if people haven't played it in Sybil, it's like you're playing as this girl
who's playing an online game and you have access to her desktop.
And then you also play the online game she's playing with this guy she likes.
So the prototype was the online game part of that.
And in the prototype, it was all I didn't really have time for voice.
There's like a little voice.
So it was like some voiceover of her talking and then text from him
in the chat like.
you know, the fictional chat in the game.
And there was just like a little conversation of them flirting.
And you would just walk around and like kill enemies.
And his NPC didn't really do anything because I didn't have time in a week
to like make an AI or like even a scripted character.
So, yeah, it was just a really simple expression of that
that online game aspect of
of what Sybil ended up being.
It's so interesting because you feel like you're playing with this person, you know,
and the way that you describe it, you know, it's kind of a simple idea.
It captures a lot of like, if you, I've played, like I've had partners that I've communicated
with normally through just playing online games together, playing Destiny together for
like hours and hours and hours, and like, it captures the thing where the games kind
of becomes background noise to the actual conversations and relationships developing
through that.
Like, that was captured very well in your game.
Thank you.
Yeah, I wanted to... I always, I think MMOs are funny because I think they're like super...
It's easy to forget how simple they are, like if you strip back all the layers of like
different leveling systems, different job classes, different whatever, like in the end a lot of them are just like, you click on stuff to kill it.
So I also kind of wanted to make a parody of how that's really what a lot of those old
MMOs are.
So yeah, I was trying to capture that for sure.
You called it out in the writing too, just like, what are we doing right now?
We're just smashing stuff.
I mean, after I played Final Fantasy 11 from like age 14 to 19, like a lot.
So I, I was fully prepared to like, get down and make fun of it, even
though it's a game I adore, but you know, when you think about a lot of
games like that, it's like a lot of it really is a lot of the interesting
parts of it come out of the social interactions you have.
And the fact that they're really simple games actually makes socializing a lot easier, I think.
And that's an interesting thing about those games, that comes out of the simplicity of the mechanics.
And I was excited about that when working on Sybil, for sure.
Yeah. Alyssa, are you an MMO person?
I've tried to be in field several times.
I played Final Fantasy XI when I was an early teen with no money to afford the monthly subscription
fee and my mom wasn't very receptive to, you want to pay this money every month to play
a video game?
So that one didn't last very long.
Ah, come on, mom.
Yeah, yeah. It's definitely Destiny, though, and how more and more live games are kind of becoming the modern MMO in a way,
where those communities now form around these games that, I don't know, can be played single-player,
but you can just kind of tune them out and play them multiplayer, just go in these loops forever,
without having to commit like 80 hours to beating the primary story of Final Fantasy XIV or something.
It's nice. Video games are good. I don't know how, I don't know why I can't either.
Well, I kind of know why I haven't gotten into. I have a friend who's like, has
been really on and off into World of Warcraft since it first came out. And
every time I try to play with him, like, I'll skip a day playing with him. And the
next thing I know, you know, I play with him and he's like level like a million
on like a flaming awesome horse mount with all this.
It's like, oh yeah, I've played it for 24 hours straight since last. It's like, well now there's
nothing for me to do. I'm just going to be like a little wimpy guy and I just feel like I missed
out. Yeah, I don't know. I think I'm just old too. It's interesting too, speaking of being old,
like being a 39-year-old dad playing Sybil.
And you're kind of, I don't know, it's like you end up, you empathize with it in a different way than you would if I was, you know, a young woman.
We talked about this a little bit ahead of in DMs where you're like, oh, my dad, like instincts are just going crazy.
And I'm like, no, the tone of this, I have talked to these guys online before.
I have had this guy being like, you want to send me a picture?
And I'm like.
it's too real and I didn't like it in that way.
And so to kind of talk about that, the personal nature of your games,
you know, people are making more of them,
like, what is your, what do you feel like is your
process for making a game that is just so
incredibly personal and autobiographical?
I am the type of game designer that really likes sort of a research-driven process, so
for Sybil, for example.
I'm like a notorious archiver of everything in my life, and so I have this flash drive
with everything from all my computers since I was a teenager.
So I was able to go back and read a lot of actual conversations I had back then with
my online friends and with the guy that the game is based on.
like based on. So I had a lot of like you know source material to draw on and then I also like
went on the Wayback Machine and dug up some of my old blogs and stuff from even earlier than
the game just to like give myself
some context to like get in the character's head to like write that voice accurately.
And I even I actually found on YouTube a video of my old Final Fantasy XI Link's shell doing
this like big fight so I could hear that guy's voice again. And so I even found that. So I like
gather when I do a personal game, I gather as much like real stuff as I can,
especially if it's something that happened a long time ago.
Although with something like more new like we met in May, which is about myself and like my current partner Jake,
like the research for that is a little different. It's mostly like conversations between us about like whatever the dates we've been on.
because there's not as much of a digital trail left by that game,
because it's about real physical dates we went on.
We have pictures from them and stuff, so that helps.
But yeah, I try to research in whatever way
is appropriate for the kind of game I'm making.
When you're using yourself as a character, writing something autobiographical about events
you've been through, it would be really easy to just be like, here's my recollection of
that and that's how it is, but things are so much more multifaceted than that.
When you're using your past self as a character, how do you detach from your current self in
order to make that as accurate or true as possible?
It depends on the topic, but for something more serious like Sybil, uh, or like, you know, an emotionally painful memory, I have to, like, give it a lot of time.
So I, like, didn't even consider writing that until...
I think it was like it had been like eight years since I had had that experience.
And then maybe a little, maybe like seven.
And then I'm like, I think I have enough critical distance from it to like look
back and be able to like look at myself
in like third person and like not like it's me
and not have any like emotional investment in it.
Yeah. So the timing depends
on the specific situation or memory I'm drawing on.
But I try to like.
or I make sure I have like the critical distance from it to like look at it for what it was.
And also the source material helps a lot with that because if I have real text to draw on,
I just use that and like I'll edit it so it makes more sense but like a lot of Sybil
is just literally things I said or things that that guy said so.
yeah I have that kind of like I don't even talk about myself in the first person when I make
games like that it's always like I talk about Nina like as if she's someone else so that helps
yeah wow so um so you just uh basically copy paste all the chat logs and then some of them
were actually pretty much copy pasted uh not all of them most of it was pretty edited because like
With something like that, there's like a lot that happens and is said between two people that can kind of like distract from the point of the story or like the emotional tones I'm trying to hit.
So there's a lot of like filtering out of like.
things that were really said but really didn't matter in the end,
um, that I can recognize now that I'm like so far out of it.
Um, whereas when you're in the moment you're like picking on every single
little detail and trying to read into everything, or at least that's
kind of how I was at that age, uh, but now I can take that story and like
distill it into something more straightforward, so I guess that's
like another element of the process.
It's also interesting because you're like now a couple of times removed from the original experience.
Is it weird for you to talk about these personal games that are about a specific period in your life?
About a specific thing?
I'm so used to talking about them that it doesn't really faze me anymore.
Okay.
I don't... I mean, when I'm working on them, I don't...
Like, I don't know, it sounds weird, but I have a very, like...
distant approach. Like, I don't, I'm not, like, emotionally involved in it at all, really. Like,
I'm doing it for the art of it. And that's not true for everything I've made. Like, Sybil is
one example. But, like, I think when I made Freshman Year, which is a story about, like, a
sort of like sexual assault situation I was in, that was like a little more emotional and I
couldn't remove myself from it as easily, but even then I can still like talk about it. I think a lot
of it just comes with experience too, just like getting used to talking about this kind of thing.
Yeah.
Yeah, I was, I was going to ask, but now the question, you know,
doesn't make as much sense, but you know, um, I was going to ask, you know,
was it ever difficult for you to put yourself out there in the way that you
do through your games, but I guess it just depends on the subject matter.
Yeah, it definitely depends on the subject and.
Also, I benefited a lot from my English degree, actually.
Well, because I took a lot of, I did poetry, like, was my focus.
So I was in a lot of, like, poetry writing, like, creative writing classes.
And in those, you know, you're, like, sharing your work face to face with people.
my professor Charles North, he was having us write a lot of personal work.
So at a really pretty young age, I was already talking about pretty personal and sometimes
dark stuff to classmates I wasn't even close with.
And I think that experience made it a lot easier for me to do in the end.
That was like the practice that I got that prepared me to do it on a larger scale.
Was anyone ever like, geez, Nina?
No, I mean, everyone was writing like intense stuff, you know, English majors.
Sure, sure.
Yep, yep, I do.
Flashing back to a very specific day in my poetry class.
Yeah, yeah, you know.
Well, what is it about, you know, relationships and sexuality that lend themselves to game
mechanics?
I mean, I can imagine some answers to this, but, you know.
It can kind of be like a taboo topic, too, like, talking about sexuality and romance
just as they are and the goods and the bads, but also, like, based on real situations,
it's like, oh my gosh.
Well, I mean, again, I think I got used to it in the poetry.
time. I actually remember we, like, had this whole, like, erotic poetry thing that we were doing at
this at school and, like, so that got me even more used to it, but anyway, regardless, I had
the experience coming into it which helped, but more related to, like, game design. I,
my biggest interest as a game designer is games that, like, help you embody a character and
I think player character embodiment is like a very performative thing, so it's almost
like theater, like you're playing as the character, almost like you're on a stage, and that was
kind of the motivation behind the design of Sybil.
for example, where it's like first person, you're supposed to be at her computer as her
doing all these things.
It's like role-playing, but more in a theatrical sense in my mind.
It's like zero-th person.
You're like the person.
It's your desktop.
Yeah.
And a part of that process for me is always like, I think the memories I like to draw
on the best for personal games especially are things that have a very physical element
I think could translate well into game mechanics.
So I like to have the story first and find a game mechanic in the story.
So in Sybil, it's the act of like sitting at the computer looking through your files
and playing the game.
That is like a physical experience.
that's how those mechanics came out of that, or in How Do You Do It, the physicality of, like,
playing with your dolls and moving them around in silly and awkward ways and the physical experience
of that. And I haven't done that kind of design for, like, literally everything I've done,
but it's one of my big interests, and I think...
you know, sex and relationships and sexuality, like, there's lots of sort of stories within that
space that are so physical, so I think there's a lot of territory to be explored there mechanically.
I think one thing I noticed when I did a quick brush up on as many of your games as I could
find this morning, just to make sure it was all fresh, and going through We Met in May
and how each of the different vignettes has their own mechanic that goes with it, but
the mechanics feel very tied to the absurdity or the romance or the intimacy of the situation,
and that just all comes across as the mechanics as the vehicle for narrative versus a game
where it would distract you from the narrative or something like that.
Yeah, for sure. And I've gone both directions, like Kimi is a game I worked on that's more of
like a visual novel style game, which is another genre I really like, so just depends on what
you're going for, but I think it's exciting to like look for the mechanics in the story,
like how can you have the player like step into the character's shoes and like
actually perform as them.
in a physical way.
Yeah.
I played through We Met in May this morning
and it's hilarious.
Thank you.
It's just, um, yeah, I mean, it's already like kind of, uh, you know, on, on game
blogs and game sites, so no spoilers, but you do tweak, uh, Nina's boyfriend's
nipples in it while he's trying to make a, make a meal and it's just so, just so
funny, like how, uh, how evocative it is, like the emotions, like it's, it's so
playful.
Can you talk about incorporating this playfulness and how you zero in on that?
I... so first, we met in May, yeah, Jake and I made it together and we had all these fun
dates and like, one of our first dates was this one that...
where we were at the beach and we discovered we both really like sand
and like rolling around in the sand and stuff, which a lot of people think is weird,
apparently, but I grew up like right next to a beach.
So I'm like, I don't know. It's just like what I always did.
And he did, too. So we like bonded over that.
And then we were like talking about that experience with some friends.
They were making fun of us for liking sand.
And we were like, oh, yeah, like that would make a pretty interesting game.
And then we could like show people that liking sand isn't weird.
Like, the idea came from, like, kind of a playful place for us, um, and like, we...
We...especially as someone like me who I've made a lot of, like, kind of darker games about romance and stuff,
I wanted to really try getting back into, like, the comedic and lighter side of things,
like, what we had done with How Do You Do It back in the day, for example.
Um, that's, like, a much more light-hearted game, uh, even though it tackles something...
kind of serious in a way.
So, yeah, Jake and I were like,
yeah, let's pick, find
some dates we've been on that we thought were really
funny or memorable in some way, and
see what was funny and memorable
about those, and
translate them into a game, and find the game
mechanics in those moments. So we came
into it with romantic comedy as
a goal.
So, we're glad it comes across.
Yeah, it definitely does.
So,
the...
In your games, there's always this, like visually it just fits.
Everything is so cohesive.
Um, what are your, what are your, what are your thoughts on, you know, uh, the
aesthetics of, uh, and how that plays into the storytelling aspect?
Uh, I mean, you can talk about specific games, like, like how, like how do you do
it or, you know, anything.
Yeah, uh, so for all the different games I've worked on, it's usually...
a lot of them have been with, like, many different artists. Like, I haven't
worked with the same artist multiple times, just... just because of, like, these being, like,
side projects and all of us... many of them being done when I was a student and stuff, you know?
It's... I wasn't, like, building a company or, like, anything like that yet, so it's just, like...
which my friends wants to make a game today.
Kind of thing.
But I like, I always would reach out to artists
whose work I really liked.
And I'm not, I try not to be the type of designer
that like micromanages an artist.
I kind of just like, you know, if I am into someone's style,
I'm working with them for that reason.
And we usually relate over that.
So yeah, my collaborative process with artists
is always like, I just like what you do.
do that with me, please.
But out of that comes a lot of really cool stuff, so like,
how do you do it is a good example.
Marina Kitaka did the art for that game, and she...
I actually did work with her a couple times.
She released Anodyne 2 recently with Sean.
They're a pair of game developers that have been working on stuff.
We're like old friends, it's funny.
We all like, I know Marina through Sean, who's a friend from New York.
So anyway, small world of game developers.
Marina's great.
Anodyne too is super good.
She is a super talented artist with a really good eye for design stuff too.
Game design stuff and writing.
So when we were working on that game, I like storyboarded what I had envisioned for How
Do You Do It? and actually, originally, it was more focused on the hands and the dolls in her
hands. But Marina came back to me with a reverse view that included her face, because she was like,
I really want to draw her expressions, because I think that that is super evocative
for this concept. And I was like, great. Yeah, sounds perfect.
I'm so glad that you thought of that,
because that really makes the game what it is.
So yeah, my process with artists has always
been really collaborative in that way for the design, too,
because the visual design of the games matters a lot to me.
Oh, yeah.
It's funny, too, how in your games,
you add a point system that doesn't really like,
it's unclear of how exactly it works.
They all have a logic behind them, but it's not like... it doesn't really matter.
It seems like it's kind of like poking fun at the gamification of things sometimes and yeah.
Yeah, I like, I don't know, I think to me as a game designer it's important to not take...
traditional game mechanic expectations too seriously, because I think it's more interesting
if you try and poke fun at them or use them in a weird way.
So yeah, I do my best to try doing that where it makes sense.
And yeah, I've done that a lot with scores, because I think they're silly.
Yeah, I was pretty proud of my high score on, we met in May when I was putting clothes on,
or when you were putting clothes on, I was putting, yeah, I'd come out and then just,
then Jake just goes ragdoll. So yeah, so this is how it works. Like, apparently Nina and Jake went
on a date where she's trying clothes on at a clothes shop, and then she comes out of the
dressing room. And then depending on how you come out of the dressing room,
which you can choose, you'll just literally blow her boyfriend off of his feet
and his character models, yeah, damage numbers
come up and he just goes ragdoll. Is there like a hidden leaderboard somewhere for whoever's
tweaked the nips the most times?
I would have loved to do that. I mean some of this stuff actually also comes down to
like scope or like time.
Yeah so we there's actually like a ton of other stuff I wanted to do when we met in May but we
just like literally didn't have time for because it's like we're both so busy actually Jake also
started working at Fulbright recently so it's like hilarious how
We both started having really, like, you know, working a day job and making a game on the side is pretty hard.
So the silliness of the scoring also sometimes comes out of like,
well, I don't have too much time to think about this, so what's the funniest thing that comes to mind first?
And yeah, so sometimes the smaller the scope, the sillier your game might end up, it turns out.
Both We Met in May and Game Jam Games both started as Game Jam Games.
Sybil, right?
Oh, yeah.
Sybil was it?
Yeah.
How many Game Jam Games have you put together altogether, and what's the secret sauce for
taking the concept of a jam game and making it its own thing?
Oh gosh, how many jam games have I made?
Like, so many.
I think...
Honestly, almost all of the games I've worked on started at Jams,
just because I like working that way. So probably done like...
14 or 15 game jams at this point.
And God, actually way more than that,
because that prototype studio class was like a whole semester of game jams.
Oh my gosh.
I actually don't even know.
And like most of those aren't released.
Yeah.
Sybil came out of that and also Bum Rush,
which was a game I did for No Quarter a long time ago.
So I would say like game jams are really good because I think people can get.
caught up too much in the details of implementation when working on a game, when sometimes, like,
the best game design can come out of, like, spontaneity and just, like, hacking something
together and, like, taking the, you know, the shortest road to something playable.
So I've always tried to have that approach where I, like, don't worry too much about
the technicalities and just try to make something that people like.
either enjoy or understand the story I'm trying to tell or whatever my goal is. What matters most
to me is that I can put it in front of someone and have them come away with whatever I intend.
And I think game jams are a really good way to be quickly iterative, because iteration,
I think, is one of the most important things to game design. It's like making something,
putting it in front of a player, seeing how they react, and then tailoring the game further.
based on that feedback you get. And doing that over and over and over until your game works.
So basically the game jam is usually like the first iteration of that
and gives me at least a base to work with. Then maybe sometime I refactor it and not always.
But regardless, like building it out after the jam just ends up being like more iteration like
that. It's just maybe not as...
not all in one weekend, spread out in a more reasonable way.
So it's like starting a project in a game jam where you are in a time, a fixed time
window keeps you from lingering too long on making one thing work just right or falling
into those kind of fallacies?
Yeah, yeah, or like trying too many things, because a lot of games fall apart from being
just like too much stuff, too many mechanics or whatever, and I think jams can force you
to be focused.
So that's something that helps me a lot.
And as someone who has always had full-time jobs where I like...
I'm doing other stuff, it also gives me deliberate time to like work on something outside of
work, and sometimes like, you know, as a busy adult or whatever, having that like time where
I'm like explicitly just doing that one thing really helps me get it done.
Yeah.
And I care first and foremost really about finishing things.
I tend to like, even if I'm not happy with the jam game at the end, I'll just release
it anyway, as long as my teammates are okay with it.
Just cause like, I care a lot about like...
Just like putting it out there and being like, it's done.
Don't like leaving things hanging.
So jams are great.
Are you somebody who is constantly like in the back of your mind?
Oh, this could be a game.
I do have a bunch of notes on my phone and in various Google Docs about different game
ideas I come up with while I'm just walking around or whatever.
But actually, it's kind of a bummer.
I used to have more of that when I was living in New York and walking around all the time.
ever since I moved to Portland I'm not it's not it's still a walking city but I find myself like
having less ambient time just traveling um and so I've like had less of that over the years
and have had to like more deliberately like sit down and brainstorm occasionally um I think leisure
time is really important coming up with like good ideas so
But I have to kind of, I'm at a point in my life where I have to schedule that in.
You know?
So...
Yeah.
That's the game.
Schedule and lose your time.
Yeah.
It's all spreadsheet secretly.
Pretty much.
Yeah.
Well, we're kind of winding down here. So before you go, I'm
just, I just wanted to ask to for for people listening and
people familiar with your work or who would like to, you know,
do similar stuff, you know, that's that's personal. You
know, what, what should people who want to make you these kinds
of really intensely personal games keep in mind?
Hmm, I think
Familiarizing oneself with, like, other, you know, personal games that have been done,
like Dysphoria, for example, was really a big inspiration to me when I was getting started.
Looking, playing a lot of other games, and, like, keeping up with that stuff can really help,
and just, like, seeing what's been done.
And...
making sure to not only do that but also look to other mediums, because, you know, like, poetry,
for example, has a long history of personal writing. And you could say the same about film
or painting or anything else that has that kind of history. Like, people do personal work all the
time. And I think it's important to engage with that work, just to, like, give yourself ideas
and find inspiration. And when you do have those ideas, write them down and
try to act on them, try to make something really small and finish it, and actually release it and
show it to people. I think that those two things, the act of engaging with other mediums and also
looking at other games and making something small and finishing it and releasing it,
are two of the most important things, at least in my experience.
And of course, get an English degree like we all do.
I mean, I'm glad I got it, but I'm always like, I don't know.
It's interesting.
I like a lot of my friends, like, don't have any college degree.
And like, I think you can do games with or without, it really doesn't matter.
All that matters is that you make stuff.
Um, and don't let anyone like look down on you if you don't have a degree or if
you don't have a degree from an Ivy league or whatever, like.
What matters in the end is your work and your creative output and that stuff.
So that's my belief, especially having been doing games for a while now.
I never ask about people's academic history.
I just look at what they've made and play their games, and that's what I react to.
Yeah. Well, there you have it. Well, thanks so much for taking time out of your day and, uh,
best of luck with, um, I'm sure you have multiple projects in the works and we'll
keep an eye out for them. So thank you so much. Thank you.
All right, we're back and uh, yeah, that's Nina's super interesting, right? Even though she considers herself a plebe scrub
Not indie royalty a high-ranking plebs. Please scrub. Yeah. No, I think that's to aspire to yeah, she she's absolutely royalty
Yeah, what what did you what did you think about that?
What were some of the things you you uh that are just like just your mind is still reeling over right now
I just, I like games that, like, the narrative just, like, knocks you off their feet, and,
like, all of Nina's games seem to, like, accomplish that, where it feels like real people and
real stories, and, like, I guess that's because they are based on real people and real stories,
but, like, even when you do that, it's incredibly easy to...
lean into, I don't know, the idea of somebody or the idea of a situation and not have it
feel authentic.
But like, all of hers do have that authentic feel to them.
Maybe because she's able to kind of look back and detach a little bit and go through her
archives of teenage poetry and everything like that.
That's the secret to writing good characters, maybe, is teenage poetry.
Yeah, it's, uh, it's like total honesty and then turning it into a story that
other people can experience and, uh, her ability to compartmentalize things,
you know, even what, what's a, what kind of surprised me and maybe it shouldn't
have, uh, for Sybil that she basically went back and internet stocked herself.
So that she could remember this experience from several years ago.
The phrase, uh, way back machine to find forum posts, like sent a shiver through my spine.
Yeah. Like, oh my. Like I, yeah, seriously, as you know, people who work on the internet,
uh, there's just this crap that we've made or written just in all kinds of places, probably
archived in certain places. And just to think that, you know, actively going out and trying to find that.
I think the current, I guess my generation, right where I'm at, I think Nina and I are
about the same age, somewhere in there, where I feel like exposure to the internet started
in about the teenage years when all those hormones and drama was running high.
So that kind of weird artifact of your entire teenage, frozen in time, for you to look back
on for inspiration later.
I've mentioned this before, but I have a...
my childhood computer because my dad works in IT so I got like a hand-me-down computer that I had
in my bedroom as a teen and like there's still all these MSN chat logs on there just all these
embarrassing conversations I had with my my anime group friends and like all of that but like
Especially going into the next generation who's always online having all of this potential
research material to turn around and maybe their personal games will blow us out of the
water someday.
It's just mind-blowing.
I think that all of our listeners should know that the next GDC podcast is just going to
be Alyssa reading out all of her MSN chat logs about anime.
It'll be me talking about all the fanfiction I wrote with friends that I will never give
usernames for under penalty of death. Yeah, yeah, it's gonna be, uh, we're gonna take
Nina's advice and be, we're just gonna really, you know, get personal here. We're going to
talk about all of those things.
I don't even know where to go from there.
I'm just dwelling on all the embarrassing Inuyasha fanfiction I made in The Sims 1 back
in the day.
I'm like, ugh.
No, I think that it would be good, actually.
Yeah.
Good video game.
Back to Nita's games.
Yeah.
Like, We Met in May is just like, and stuff like Sybil and How Do You Do It.
They're, they drill down so deep into a certain emotion that, uh, yeah, it's just, it's just
pure, pure focus and pure honesty and pure authenticity.
And I just, uh, I really admire that.
You just don't see that so often.
It's really interesting to hear how those two games in particular evolved from jam games,
because it was a memory and a concept that started as a small thing and then once the
weekend session was done was able to expand and evolve.
And I feel like it's the reason I asked about how many game jams she'd done to date, is
because you can do a million, you can have a million ideas and try a million prototypes
and stuff like that, and they're not always going to work out.
But then the ones that stick and the ones that you focus on and that you land on can
evolve into these really evocative and cool things like a lot of her games have.
Yeah, and the autobiographical nature of these, it just kind of, it, you know, it blows my mind,
because I was talking to you earlier for prep on this, just for me, I just bury all of my
autobiographical things are all of the viewpoints that I might have or feelings I might have in
like robot metaphors.
I'm also a coward who hides behind metaphors, so I feel that.
Yeah, so and then with her, it's kind of like, well, when I was a kid, I used to jam plastic
dolls together to try to figure out how sex worked.
Which is relatable, because like...
I also had that memory as a kid with like Barbies in the basement like being like, oh, this is what I saw on the
The tv show and then I would also have them like ride dinosaurs. So like it was all this exploration of possibilities of life
I don't know where I was going with that. No, I mean, but but you're right though. Um the things that we
as human beings, um, you know, we're
Kind of ashamed to talk about or too shy to talk about it. Um
that's what's good, I think, about Nina's games, like how we met in May, like talking about like
the awkward, cute, fun absurdity of a new relationship, things like that. Because
everything, like we're not as individual people as unique as we think we are. We all have these
experiences that are, that each of us can relate to.
Yeah, even if it's not something that people are prone to talking about, using it, like
creating a game on that concept is, makes it easier to discuss that, like, in the lighthearted
way with, uh, what's the, how do you do it?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, in a lighthearted way with that one, but then I also played her freshman year
game, which is the game she was talking about, about sexual assault, where your character
goes out.
to a club trying to meet up with a friend, the friend's not replying to her text messages,
and then the bouncer starts hitting on her and the situation spirals, but like,
even that one was like evocative of like, real experiences that can be tough to talk about,
but using a game to kind of like, share that and be like, no other people go through that,
it's just, it's really...
I don't know, it's interesting.
And it's kind of like freeing in a way
to just see these experiences play out on this mass stage
that everyone can discuss.
Yeah.
And it helps people.
It helps people feel less alone.
That's a good thing.
She's doing the Lord's work, that Nina.
Okay, well, um, I think that, I think that's it.
Yeah.
Uh, yeah.
For, for number three.
Um, yeah, we're still pretty new at this.
Uh, I think,
Oh, I feel that we should have asked Nina to plug her games, uh, where you can find
them.
Yeah.
Oh, we should do that.
We should do that.
You can, um, uh, Nina says so.
Nina says dot so would be the website.
You can find her independent work and she's also working at Tacoma developer Fulbright
currently.
So yeah, she has so many games and so many of them, you know, you can, uh, you can, you
can download for, uh, you know, for free or like a small, a small donation to or a large
donation.
Yeah.
Listeners give Nina a large donation.
Thanks everybody for listening.
I'm Chris Graft.
I'm Alyssa McAloon.
And don't forget to subscribe and to rate our review.
If you love us, give us a give us them five stars.
That helps a lot and say something nice about us.
So thanks, everyone.
And we will see you next time.
Bye.
you