Hello, I am Katherine Himes, a game designer and computational linguist.
Also, I am allergic to summer, so fingers crossed I don't sneeze.
I'm here to talk about the potential for games as a form of community-driven care,
specifically exploring the topic through a collaboration and co-design project in making
games both with and for people with aphasia, which is an impairment of language.
This talk is being given amidst the pandemic and right now it feels inevitable to be asking
ourselves how we might use our energy and skills, whatever they are, at GDC specifically as game
designers to contribute to important human-centered questions. The hope is that this talk is helpful
in showing one way to apply game design through a deep community collaboration in service of the
public good.
There is a well-established movement for games that are designed with a goal that is different
than entertainment. Sometimes these are called serious games or games with a purpose, and that
isn't to trivialize fun or self-expression in games, in fact pretty critical for most any game
to be interesting. Rather, these games are designed to accomplish something specific outside of fun.
In the domain of therapy, one motivating question may be how might the context of play
positively affect patients or facilitate community support or
help people to make a change in their personal health or behavior?
There is a wide world of game development looking to design games for applications in health,
for care, for rehab, and the idea of playful medicine or playful therapy is here and happening
right now. A couple of examples for you. Last June, the FDA approved the first ever digital
therapeutic video game that was clinically shown to improve attention span in kids with ADHD.
Stroke patients can be prescribed game-based therapy to recover movement and motor function
at home. This is really hard to do. These games have to clear all of the hurdles of proving medical
efficacy while still being fun, but they open up a world of experience-based therapy through games.
This talk will focus on the project Aphasia Games for Health,
which was a collaboration over the last year where Aphasia community members,
medical professionals, and game designers came together to make games that explore the potential
for play as a community-driven form of care. And by that I mean playable at home,
in support groups, out in the wide world without the need for a specialist to run it.
Here I'll focus on the co-design process itself. It's going to be a fly overview of what it is to
work across different backgrounds, expertise, and communication needs to produce games.
I am a game designer and linguist by trade and only one member of this team,
but you'll get to see more of our co-design group later on.
First, some brief background.
Aphasia is a language disorder caused by stroke or other brain injury that affects a person's ability to communicate.
This is an impairment of language.
There's no one single experience of aphasia.
Someone with aphasia may have difficulty in speaking, understanding, reading, or writing.
But living with aphasia can have a big impact on many parts of social and professional life,
which just gets in the way of expressing oneself and connecting with others.
Across the US, there are over 2 million people living with chronic aphasia.
People with aphasia often report that they don't have enough healthcare access for meaningful treatment.
And when they do receive language rehab, it is typically limited in scope.
So think 10 hours of speech-language services in the first year after a stroke.
And then a really high drop-off beyond that.
But rehab helps.
There is strong evidence that speech and language therapy can improve communication
well into the later phases of recovery.
So given all this, there's growing interest in the aphasia community
to find new ways to receive community-driven therapy
that's done at home, without a clinician, for long-term language recovery.
Why consider games for this? Reasonable question. Games designed for aphasia rehabilitation have
some exciting potential here. First, we have prior evidence that games can be built to include
therapeutic rehabilitation principles, but also be played and run at home by non-professionals.
They can be made to be flexible to the needs of different players, flexible in format,
made available in person or online, which is important for many folks who live outside of major cities or with limited transportation options.
Compared to other treatments, games can be scoped to be significantly cheaper, with a single purchase allowing for long-term play.
Also, games can be social while doing all of this, and by being fun,
They can be built to help people connect and keep engagement up.
So taken all together, this is a compelling case to explore aphasia games for health.
Will Evans, a professor and speech-language pathologist out of the University of Pittsburgh,
spearheaded the effort to assemble a co-design group to make card-based games
playable in person and online.
that can incorporate mechanics that are helpful for aphasia treatment.
Now, many folks in the aphasia community are already playing all sorts of games.
Sometimes they're used in modified forms as exercises in aphasia support groups.
The question here was to ask, can we add to this by designing games intentionally
from the ground up that meet some of the needs of the aphasia community?
To make games like this, we wanted to bring together different kinds of expertise.
In particular, insight about the lived experience of aphasia that can come from aphasia community
members.
We needed a way to evaluate the therapeutic foundation of a game as it's being developed
and iterated on with knowledge from speech-language pathologists.
And we also wanted to build scalable, playful systems around all of these ideas that can be woven into a game, as contributed by professional game designers.
So, together, we formed a single co-design team that collaborated to produce new games for health for the aphasia community.
And these partnerships included aphasia community members from ARC,
that's aphasia recovery connection, which is a nationwide support group of 9000 plus people.
Speech language pathologists from the language rehab and cognition group at the University of
Pittsburgh and independent game designers from both industry and academia. Each game featured
a lead designer and then was made in partnership with the whole team.
So before starting out, we needed to draft a set of design principles that would ground what we make.
Simply outlining what an aphasia game for health would aim to do is a challenge in and of itself.
Based on deep dives into research, literature and interviews with members of Aphasia Recovery Connection,
here are some elements that we wanted each of the games to incorporate.
First, we wanted games to have a therapeutic foundation
by using one or more of these behavioral rehab activities
that are backed by evidence to treat aphasia.
They should have a way to adjust difficulty.
That means that people with really different profiles
of aphasia can play the game,
and also that a single individual can keep on playing
as their own experience changes over time.
We wanted each game to allow for performance feedback during play,
which is a real standard component of therapy that you can mechanize
or support through the structure of a game.
We'd like these games to be playable and replayable
so that they can be a part of long-term therapy.
And, of course, these games needed to be accessible.
They have to target the common scenarios around social access and community constraints.
How many people are playing? Who are you playing with?
As examples.
All of this together, it's a tall order, and it's important not to overpromise what any one game can do.
But knowing what to strive for is a first step.
There are many more steps to actually show that a game is therapeutic or that it's broadly accessible,
especially across the community with really different needs and experiences.
So in the next few slides, I'll put a spotlight
on some of the ways that we structured co-design
to both be accessible and functional
across really different kinds of expertise.
So for a creative collaboration,
bringing all of this different experience together,
it has the potential to be utter chaos.
We needed to spend serious time and energy upfront
figuring out how we were going to work together.
Though this collaboration has lasted more than a year, the heart of design happened over a summer.
So over the course of three months, we held a series of workshops and interview sessions
that involved our whole group of co-designers. Workshops were done remotely over video conference
and were used to do brainstorming, game design, pitching, structured playtesting, feedback,
and of course just general hangouts.
Each workshop followed a similar format.
An overview of a game idea in progress was presented,
the basic explanation of the rules,
then game designers would model an example turn of gameplay,
and then community members with aphasia would be invited to playtest and comments, give suggestions.
After playtesting, aphasia community members would share their immediate thoughts, feedback
on whether or not the game was fun, what was simple, what was challenging, and then together
with feedback from our speech-language pathologist, the designer would iterate and present a revision
at the next workshop.
This was done through three cycles of design idea, workshop presentation, and revision
until finally a playtested prototype was made.
During co-design, one of the first things we had to think about was how to make this accessible for our team members with aphasia.
We employed a whole range of adaptive techniques to help with communication in our workshops.
Many of these come from standard FAIR that online aphasia support groups are already using today.
We were, one, doing video conferencing, and that forced by the pandemic, but that ended up being
helpful. We used different modes of communication at the same time to help with participation.
Slowed speech and writing together were especially effective. Someone would type keywords from
speech into a chat window to help cue a conversation so everyone could follow along.
People could share pictures and visual aids to make explanations clearer,
even at the earliest stages of game design.
And timing for meetings was needed in order to not cause mental fatigue.
Afterwards, recordings were shared with everyone to allow people to review a
particular workshop if they wanted.
And along the way, we had regular active conversation with our team members,
with Atheja, to ask what else they may need.
Cross-training was another one.
We recruited game designers who had really strong design work
and an interest in this language-related play.
Some of these designers had experience with aphasia
through their family,
but we knew that there was a lot more to know,
even while working within a co-design group.
So prior to starting any kind of active development,
game designers followed a month-long preparation program
of sorts, done part-time.
They were given lectures on aphasia from the rest of the core team.
They attended separate online conversation groups led by the aphasia recovery connection,
typically involving around 20 people with a wide range of aphasia profiles.
The idea here was that this allows for exposure to a larger range of people who might benefit
from the designs we would later make.
And then before starting with the core team, designers were then asked to attend an aphasia group where people with aphasia play existing games together like bingo or trivia, some of which are regularly led by some of our team members.
So here's one tangible example of how we tried to make the creative development across expertise actually work.
Game designers were given a design brief with details on project goals, but also existing
therapeutic activities that might be mechanized in future design choices. We wanted games to
feature one or more evidence-backed behavioral rehab activities.
The majority of activities are all around providing context that allow people to practice speaking, processing, or combining elements of language together.
This wasn't an exhaustive list by any means, but it was some important tools as considered by our speech-language pathologists.
So after that brief window into co-design, I'll give you a high-level peek into the game prototypes that we made
and point out at least one way that they followed our game design principles.
First up, The Minister's Cat, led by game designer Meg Baker.
This is an evolution of a 19th century perler game. It's a memory letter game for two to six players.
where players will tell small stories about a minister's cat featuring a word that matches a pre-assigned letter.
So it's meant to be a storytelling game using repeated phrases along with nouns provided by the player.
Every sentence is prompted by this deck of themed cards that come with a base sentence.
So think the minister's cat eats, the minister's cat wears, then players take turns creating
sentences in rounds and flesh out the story of their cats. It was a big cat fever of the summer,
as you can tell.
For this game, I'll point out an example mechanic that's based on behavioral rehab principles.
So one standard rehab technique is to modify the difficulty for a task by cueing.
That means offering clues, perhaps around meaning, the type of bird, or...
Sound starts with a P, something like this.
And this led to a mechanic in this game where players are asked to recall words with cueing
that are based on sounds constrained by some topic.
For example, you know it has to do with food and then start to B.
Audition is a memory and improv game led by game designer Cleo Yunsu-Davis.
Players take on the role of an actor who is auditioning for a movie and the acting coaches
who are trying to help them, but the problem is that neither the actor nor the coaches
have memorized the script.
So the actor has to do their best to improvise a monologue that includes the key words from the script,
while these coaches are helping them by prompting those words.
Another example of our design principles in action is that this game incorporates a mechanic based on adaptive levels of difficulty.
In particular, it mechanizes different player roles of both actor and coach.
that allow for different kinds of challenge around what kind of pressure you want to be under
and how you're prompted to say things on the spot.
Do you see what I see? Led by game designer Tim Hutchings.
It is a video chat game that combines storytelling,
20 questions, and environment interaction at a distance.
Great for play over Zoom. Players will join this video chat from a room in their home.
And then one player is the chooser and selects an item in the background of another player's video chat window.
The other players will ask simple yes-no questions in order to try and guess what's been selected.
And the person whose object was chosen then tells everyone something special about it.
It really gives a nice alibi to share something personal with the other players.
Variations also layer on this game in terms of new rules to increase the difficulty.
Like you might have an off-limits danger item.
An example mechanic based on the design goals of long-term engagement is that
every time you play it's different based on the background content,
which players can modify or replace with even virtual backgrounds.
So next up, I want to actually show you a clip of this game being played by a subset of our co-design team.
This includes Trish, Dee, and Jill, some of our team members with aphasia.
Carol, who is the co-founder of Aphasia Recovery Connection, and Will, our speech-language pathologist.
Great.
All right, who wants to be the chooser?
I will.
Awesome, Trish is the chooser. Remember, now we are guessers and we can ask yes or no questions
like is it green or is it round, but we can't ask whose background is it behind.
Let's get started.
Is it on a table?
No.
Is it a square?
Yes.
Is it on a wall? Yes.
Is it a mirror? Yay!
And now, since Jill guessed and it's behind Jill,
Jill can tell us the story of the mirror.
Well, I like mirrors
because my grandson is 17 months old
and he loves to look at himself.
Of course.
Good, good.
Good job, team.
Awesome. Let's play another round. Okay, who wants to be the chooser? D.
All right, D's the chooser.
I know what I'm looking. I have chosen my thing.
So we can start asking questions.
Okay, is it...
Um big? No.
Is it a squam? No.
Is it bigger than a chair? No.
Can you drink out of it? No.
Hmm.
Really?
Is it white?
Uh, I think so.
Is it round? No.
Is it on a table?
Uh
No
Is it on a wall? No. Oh, maybe
Is it more than one color? No
Is it...
Wait a minute.
Counter.
Counter?
Yes.
Is it my iPad or the...
iPad.
iPad?
Yes.
Yay!
Yes. I didn't know if it was white or gray. I couldn't see it. It was white or gray. So yeah.
That was okay. The way you said it, we knew that it was close to white.
I was the apple.
And this, um, the, my colleagues, this is me.
What?
Wait, wait, wait.
I have to make it bigger.
Wow.
Which one are you of the six?
Yeah.
Oh, oh, wow.
Oh, so is it like a picture frame?
Yeah.
Oh, that's awesome!
Very cool!
Wow!
I love the personal stories that people can share in that game.
And so hopefully that gives you a taste of some of our game prototypes.
Here I will share a brief reflection on co-design.
First off, for collaborative co-design, there is a real lift with cross-training for everyone.
Some of this we anticipated ahead of time, for example, for our game designers getting
more formal background on aphasia, and others we had to incorporate along the way.
We found that both our speech-language pathologists and team members with aphasia could benefit
from more background on the game design process itself.
What to expect, how to give clear, actionable feedback, and all of that.
We ended up holding a separate, accessible training session for all non-professional game designers, which helped with future workshops.
Another takeaway.
was around the impact of small decisions from a design perspective having big implications for
the ultimate therapeutic status of a particular game. We had a speech-language pathologist who
could help actively guide in making therapeutically motivated choices,
but we found we really needed even more detailed back and forth.
For example, in the audition game, where a player improvises lines based on card prompts,
the choice of what counts as a line has real stakes for who can play in the actor role,
and the choice also changes what skills and abilities are being targeted for improvement.
And lastly, we learned some things about game design-specific adaptations to make the process more accessible.
We already talked about the general adaptations we used to support our team members with aphasia.
We also found that there were specific activities in game design that needed their own attention
to make sure everyone could fully participate. A lot of this was around playtesting games at
various stages of development. Two most useful techniques were the liberal use of visual aids
and example turn demonstrations.
even for ideas that were in really early stages or in flux.
So some of the suggestions that we got
from our team members with aphasia
also directly shaped the rule explanations
that we drafted for our prototypes.
Results from this effort.
We have three free publicly available game prototypes
that you can check out
along with illustrated game instructions.
We have a website with more details on where people can sign up for playtesting or to follow along.
We also have some great game recommendations offered as videos by our team members with Aphasia, based on what they like to play.
And some of them have also started designing their own games outside of this collaboration.
Lastly, you can also find some training materials and more background info.
We're proud of this work, but it's a start.
We plan to do more playtesting with aphasia support groups to iterate on these games.
These games are based on therapeutic ideas.
Actually proving therapeutic effectiveness is a much higher bar, and they need to be evaluated
through rigorous clinical trials research in order to meet it. We're looking into funding sources to
print and distribute these games beyond the free downloads that are available today, and we're
thinking of ways to help out gaming communities that exist already in aphasia support groups.
Takeaways for you.
This is a brief window into one project around Games for Health that was made through collaborative co-design.
So more generally, there is a growing interest and real momentum in many areas that are looking to game design as a potential form of community-driven care.
And with the right collaboration, you as a game designer can use your skills to contribute.
If you'd like to learn more about this particular project, check out aphasiagamesforhealth.com.
Big shout out to the many people involved along the way.
Thanks and see you later.