Hi guys. You all look very tired. My name is Doro Apeyotese and I'm the VP of product
verification and former VP of strategic initiatives at Paradox Interactive and we are hiring.
Sound a bit more excited. Come on. Second of all, I just wanted to kind of remind everyone
the thing with the cell phones, turn them off and this stuff. But also maybe turn them
back on again towards the end and give me a really good rating when the e‑mail comes
through so I can come again.
Finally, this is a surprisingly good turnout considering the topic. I realize it's not
the most accessible and maybe applicable for everyone. Just as a bit of housekeeping and
expectation management, who came just because we advertised that there would be jokes? Anyone
come for the jokes? One person came for the jokes. Two people. Okay. There aren't any.
No, I mean, look, I went through the presentation and I realized they weren't very good. To be
fair, I did keep one. So look forward to me telling my joke. Start off, let's talk a bit of
background. So what was the strategic initiatives division, team, department, whatever, did we
really put a bunch of people in a room and have them brainstorm?
Of course not. It wasn't just that. So the Paradox SI division, like so many other things
that are cool about Paradox, it was largely the brainchild of the CEO, most people who
know anybody at Paradox know him. And well, basically Paradox has enjoyed a fair bit of
success and growth in recent years. I mean, right now maybe more so than ever. We're doing
really well.
And Frederick wanted to make sure that the qualities that made the company successful thus
far, like company-wide collaboration, grassroots innovation, and a friendly, familiar
culture, would not be lost just because the organization and number of staff changed. And
not to mention the company going public, which he knew about at the time, but he didn't
tell me about. Which is pretty impressive, because we were pretty deep into his good
wine when we were discussing this at his house. And nonetheless, he wouldn't spill the
beans about the IPO. So good job, Frederick.
This is a challenge all this time. I think most people who've had the pleasure and the horror of going from a small company to a medium-sized company to maybe a large company has been through this to some degree.
Something changes along the way. A lot of stuff for the good and some stuff for the not so good. And often, you know, innovation is one of the first things to go.
The reasons can be visualized.
For instance, if your company starts looking like this
and you've got maybe 20 people divided between production
and maybe marketing or something,
and then you start adding silos and levels of hierarchy,
then all of a sudden a lot of the natural flowing
conversation that would otherwise happen
is just not really going on anymore.
And the idea with the strategic initiatives division
was to basically exist outside of this thing.
By the way, this is not an accurate representation
of what Paradox looked like at the time.
That would be insane.
But just mental model. But to kind of be able to interact with the company at all these
different levels and to produce cool new strategies that had been basically vetted by everyone
who needed to look at them before they got articulated. So that was a cool idea.
Now, what was the workflow that we hoped would happen more or less automatically? A simple
way of visualizing it was something like this. So we wanted a paradox employee, sometimes
someone within the SI division or elsewhere, but ideally someone from the grassroots that
would otherwise not really know how to go about getting their ideas through, would have
an idea.
And then flesh out a bit of a concept. And then, you know, get some advice maybe ideally
from someone within SI. And if they could execute it on their own, they would be asked
to do so. Because we're very much that kind of company. We want people to execute on their
own stuff because the results are always a lot better and, you know, the drill. But if
they couldn't execute it and we still thought that it was a really good idea, it would be
a shame for it to kind of die there and then. So we wanted them to be able to hand it over
to the SI.
division. And the kind of challenges that would require SI to adopt someone else's idea, we
predicted would be stuff like bandwidth and priorities. So where does this new task fit
along all the other stuff you're having me do if someone's already pulling 45, 50-hour weeks,
which apparently happens in the games industry? Someone coming along and saying, hey, we've
got this new cool thing that we want you to look at. You should be happy not to get yelled at.
Ownership, so which department takes the lead on this and why?
Cross functional dependencies, so what do we need and what can we expect from other
departments or functions?
Unclear feasibility, should this even move beyond the idea stage?
And these challenges can all be solved, yes, but it's kind of expensive and time consuming
and stressful. And perhaps prohibitively so, especially for large initiatives. And also
we didn't want to have this filter where the only people who ever got any ideas through
at Paradox were the ones who knew how to navigate these things. Right? Because those are not
necessarily the people who have the best product ideas or services or what have you. They're
just very good at navigating the maze of getting stuff done. These are kind of different skill
sets. Right?
Once something did end up with SI, and just a reminder that could happen from everywhere in the
organization and some stuff actually started within SI, the execution workflow would be
something like this. Number one, produce a strategy that takes all of the previously
mentioned challenges into account. So feasibility, bandwidth, cross department
involvement and so on. Present this strategy to relevant stakeholders, making revisions
as necessary.
Number three, get sign-off from relevant stakeholders.
Number four, hand the project over,
which is perhaps the most important thing.
So the one thing we did not want to have happen with SI
is that we end up actually both implementing
and then maintaining things.
So whether we're talking product, services,
anything like that, the last thing we wanted
is to become yet another production business unit
within the org that just balloons
and keeps throwing people at problems.
And before you know it, you...
You're basically part of the line organization and you're not really doing any innovation
work anymore.
But of course we should be around to provide assistance as the initiative gets executed.
So one way of looking at it was that we were using, or sorry, doing a sort of pre-production
on new business ventures and improvement ideas.
And this would require a fair bit of width in our own competencies.
If someone from marketing needed to use the SI workflow or someone from biz dev or someone
from product dev or someone from any department, we needed to be able to meet them halfway.
My background is primarily in product development, game design, game development.
I got help later from a colleague named David who just added so much.
He worked in sales and stuff like that.
So we actually had a pretty good width to our services.
I wanted to look at a few of the initiatives because this is all very abstract so far.
So what were some of the things that we kind of articulated at least through SI.
Just a quick caveat, though. The stuff that I'm going to be showing here is stuff that we
worked on within SI, but the fact that we worked on it within SI doesn't mean that it ever
actually went further than SI. So the last thing I want is a bunch of click bait headlines. I
don't even know if there's media in here. But no headlines saying Paradox will do this thing
very, very soon because you'll look stupid when we don't. So, I'm going to be showing you
Just to look at a few of the initiatives, starting in Q3 2015 and all the way through to Q2
2016 we did a lot of stuff. You see two colors, one being purple for myself and one being
green for my colleague David. We are going to be looking at a few of these in a bit more
detail over the next few slides. And the ones that I've picked out are the ones that fit
into very specific categories because
Well, basically there were three categories where all of these initiatives ended up. And we'll
talk about what those categories are as well. So we're going to focus on three specific
initiatives and starting with the creative workshop. So the question, because most of our
initiatives tried to kind of answer a question or some sort of problem statement, the
question was how can we do a better job of identifying cool ideas from within the
organization and is there any way we can simplify the pitching of everything, in-house
pitching, internal pitching.
Games as well as other products, services and improvements.
And we thought that this would be the first step in accomplishing the intended innovation
workflow. So this is kind of a natural first initiative. If you're going to have an innovation
division where stuff from the grassroots makes it into the innovation department and then
gets executed on, there needs to be some way of making this happen. We had a few ideas
that we were bouncing around and we kind of decided against sitting by the coffee machine
and water cooler and listening really, really hard. We didn't think that one would scale.
So we needed something else.
So what we did was we produced something that we called a creative workshop. It wasn't really
that fancy. What it was is kind of like a digital idea box. Most of you have seen something like
this before. This is a Kanban board that we've made in JIRA. Where we have tickets. The cool
thing about tickets is you can put comments in there so they become kind of like a little forum.
And you have the different columns with the different stages of the process. So you have
when something is new, it's new.
obviously. And then you have feedback requested, feedback provided and then some sort of end
state, right? And I guess one thing that's also very cool is that we have the horizontal
swim lanes. So every category gets its own horizontal swim lane. So it could be stuff
like product dev, marketing, all these other things that we've gone through. General business
stuff, office stuff. We even put office supplier requests through this.
And each and every one of these swim lanes actually had a curator from the specific subject
matter area. So you could actually get feedback as well as sometime a yes or no answer from
someone who actually was in the know. So we thought that was very cool. And the results were
kind of mixed. And we'll get back to exactly why. I mean, the actual product as such, if you
can call it that, it worked as intended. But we didn't really get
Quite as much traffic there as we would have hoped. We'll get back to why a bit later. Next
up we looked at something that had to do with crowd funding. So we were just going fully blue
sky, could we do crowd funding at Paradox in some way that doesn't feel anti-consumer and we
really love our fans. So the question was, yeah, as I say, consistent with our values and
image, respectful to our fans and has synergies with the many other ideas that we have
floating around. Some of which I really can't talk about because those might actually
happen.
And the initiative was something that we called Paradoxocracy.
I mean, I called it Paradoxocracy. Everyone else thought that sounded stupid.
So basically, both featured traditional crowdfunding, because there were multiple tiers to it.
We had the glorified pre-order thingy where you pay us money, we give you a t-shirt, and eventually maybe the game, if you're nice.
As well as experimental ideas like backers voting for game features.
So the idea was that depending on how much money you spent on a crowdfunding campaign, we
could give you tokens and you could vote for certain little things that we could do A or B or
C with and we would have a voting thing happen. Very experimental.
Don't think it should be too controversial. Some people immediately thought what are the
fans going to say. I think it would have gone over well here in America. I understand that the
Supreme Court has said that money is the same as speech. So there you go.
Central to the whole strategy was our having a virtual currency
though and we don't really have a relevant virtual currency that
could be used in this way so the results were basically that we
did not execute this. We didn't actually make this. We may yet
in the future though. We may call something else
paradoxically because I think it's really clever.
Next up we did something called an internal culture audit.
So with some of the initiatives that I had worked on,
I experienced some pushback that I identified as cultural
and I kind of took a step back and asked some questions.
First of all, how does our actual culture map
to our desired and stated culture?
What means could we use to get closer to our goals?
And the outcome was very good in that we did an in-house culture audit. Well, I say we, I did an
in-house culture audit producing a mammoth 132 slide PowerPoint presentation. And we looked at
stuff like what an organizational culture actually is, what factors shape organizational
cultures in general, case studies from inside and outside the games industry. And we also made
an inventory of the paradox culture. And the results were good. So...
Off the back of this, we actually started a pretty far-reaching and still rolling process
of not just doing an inventory but actually doing a bit of a revision and a rearticulation
of the internal paradox culture with a lot of really good activities that I think are
going to really help us gel as a team.
And this stuff can kind of be tracked back to the work we did on the internal culture
audit and strategic initiatives.
So yay me.
Now, rates of success.
Well, overall, you remember that very first slide with a bunch of different things on there?
That was not an exhaustive list. We did a lot more stuff. If you look at it statistically, we
have these three categories. We have good, we have mixed results and we have the stuff that was
not executed.
30% or so good, 30% or so mixed and 40% or so not executed.
And if you've worked at all with innovation
and initiatives like these at a company level,
these are not bad numbers.
These are pretty good.
But obviously I think we want to have them even better.
And we have this category called mixed.
Some of the mixed results are more towards the good
and some towards the not so good.
So I want to hop into some learnings and tips because there are a lot of things that we
would have done a better job of if we would have known at the beginning of the whole SI
thing what we know now.
Tip number one, take nothing at face value. Simply accepting a premise will lead to false
starts. So the people who describe a problem for you to solve are going to have various
challenges themselves. They might be constrained by their vantage points. They will engage
in wishful thinking. They may confuse facts and timelines and maybe be wrong in some other
way.
Like, let's take the creative workshop thing, for instance.
Go back to that one.
The assumption from everyone up front
was that people were simply dying within Paradox
to communicate their cool ideas somewhere.
But the behavior, once the system had been implemented,
didn't really reflect that.
I mean, there were some people
who were really super enthusiastic.
What didn't happen was this big, massive blowout
of really cool, actionable ideas
that we could just make billions off of.
So if you get such an unexpected result, that's sometimes a blessing. You should ask yourself,
what do I believe about my own company that simply isn't so, and try to kind of dig into that a little bit.
So when you're given a mission, like for example, provide people with tools to innovate, can
we find ways to make people live our culture more, head up our new innovation department
and incubate awesome stuff, do everyone a favor and push back on the premise just a
little bit.
Figure out what the background is, what is assumed and or taken for granted so that you
don't end up exhausting yourself working the wrong angles and solving non‑problems.
Next up, stress test your mandate. So some change will always come at the expense, real or
perceived, of some people. It follows that some people will have a vested interest in your
failing. Most important thing is not to figure out who these people are and target them but
rather to figure out what to do in general if and when this happens. Different people may work
against you or at least not help you at different times for different reasons and you should
probably know what to do if and when that happens.
I would suggest to apply good game dev prototyping practices.
Identify your deal breakers, try to provoke those deal breakers to happen as early as
you can, and at the very least have the uncomfortable hypothetical discussions with your sponsors,
managers, what have you.
Who has the right to say no to me at what point and for what reasons?
Who can I escalate to if I feel that somebody is being uncooperative?
Once a decision has been made, whose responsibility is it to enforce?
And of course hypothetical discussions aren't as good as the real thing. So when, not if,
when your progress grinds to a halt, make whatever is blocking you the number one priority.
Because if something or someone is blocking you, you may have a hurdle there that is going
to happen again and again and again unless you solve it right then and there, especially
if it's something that someone is doing. If they get away with it once, now they have
a tool that they can use repeatedly. So whenever something needs escalating, just do it. However
impopular that makes you within your first six months of working at a place.
Next up, this is a bit of a trick of mine. I like to itemize and map out the relevant forces.
I like to think that I'm a reasonably empathic person and I like to apply that in a somewhat sociopathic way.
I just kind of like to reduce certain things down to kind of things and assign strength values to them.
I guess that's a bit of a...
game design occupational hazard, thinking that way. But I suggest developing an understanding
of the forces working for or against you, including the individuals, so the role, formal
authority, informal influence and so on. Culture, so relevant aspects of course, like is the
culture conservative, is it consensus minded, whatever. The company structure in the formal
sense.
The makeup of the executive team, et cetera. Processes, so what do and what don't we already
know how to do with consistent results. Strategy, so where does the company see itself in the
medium and long term and where does innovation fit into that. Like how important is innovation
or innovation processes to the goals of the company. And then I suggest assigning a strength
value to these factors and prioritizing them accordingly. For example.
Stronger forces at the bottom, weaker ones at the top. You've got your tier 1 forces like you
have a snowflake culture or something, a very strong focus on profitability. These don't
need to be tied to individuals. Sometimes they just exist in the walls. CEOs of authority
and influence, ambitious growth targets, a strong but reactive board that's not going to
step in unless a lot of money is lost. You may have an enthusiastic executive team and a
complete lack of innovation or change management processes. These will obviously
change over time. That's kind of the point. That's why you're there. But it's really good
to kind of have these organized in this way because sometimes you can basically take a
high level idea or whatever you were going to do and just do a little pretest against
this and just kind of figure out where the minefields are going to be. I'm going to be
working on this one thing where I don't know when it will be profitable. Well, you're in
conflict with a tier 1 force. You may want to be careful with that one.
Next up, obviously account for scale.
So for the initiatives that I've outlined,
which factor do you think was the biggest predictor
of success?
The short answer is the size of the initiative.
So every time an initiative scales up to involve more
people, departments, resources,
your challenges automatically multiply.
There are simply more things that can fail
because complexity goes up.
This is not news to us.
This is the one thing that we had hoped to solve
that we didn't really manage to.
It was just as hard, like it scaled as much for us as it did for anyone else as we started,
you know, requiring more stuff and there were more dependencies.
I don't have any silver bullet for this one.
I think this may go down in history as just like the brute force problem.
You just have to work your way through it.
I mean, we still had an easier time in absolute terms than an average employee would have,
but that was mostly because we had the time and resources.
It was time consuming and resource consuming to solve some of these issues.
Final thoughts. So was strategic initiatives as a thing a good idea? Yes. Yes. I may have
sounded kind of critical up until this point but yes, absolutely. The thing is
Even if not every initiative that we executed on yielded the results that we hoped for,
the fact remains that without the SI divisions, the things that we actually managed to deliver
on would not have happened. At least not the way Paradox was configured at that time.
And since we've not really tried any other configuration just yet, I have to say that
overall I'm really happy that we did it this way. That's not to say there's not a better
way to do it. Also, right now we're in the process of kind of doing a
A bit of a retake on some of this stuff.
So we're kind of reorganizing the whole innovation pipeline a little bit.
And one of the things that's happened is we actually have an external vendor.
I think I'm allowed to say this.
They're kind of helping us a little bit with looking at these things, you know, with innovation
and stuff.
And one of the first things that they suggested was, hey, have you ever thought of a ticketing
system?
Yes, we actually have a ticketing system. That's not the challenge. The challenge is getting
people to use it at the rate that we want. But theirs is better, mind you. They actually
have apps and stuff like that. Obviously I wasn't about to start building it to that
extent. But conceptually the idea was a good one. So some things were good in theory, but
we just couldn't execute at the level where we should have. Nonetheless, doesn't mean
that SI was a bad idea.
I will say, though, that both the things that went well and the things that didn't go so
well were probably because paradox is paradox. And ultimately this whole thing may not be
for you. Because your culture is your culture. Your organization is what it is. I'm sure
very different if you're EA or if you're Valve. But at least think about it. I think there
are ways of working with this that can kind of be made to work if you really care.
Try. And if you're doing it honestly. So if you don't want to take the plunge with both feet,
for instance, you might consider a more flexible solution. So maybe employees with cool ideas
could be given like a temporary seat in SI, sort of like a mission to evaluate something further.
Maybe during downtime between projects, I've heard that there are certain studios where
people basically get benched waiting for new projects to come around. Not naming them, but,
some of them might be in Montreal.
And once their idea is properly fleshed out and approved, they can then help to execute.
Right? So it could look like this. And this is my awesome diagrams again. But an employee
might have an idea, go before some sort of approval committee, yes? And then get taken
So we're going to take that away from that flow and put it into the SI division where they can
flesh out a concept together with other clever people and then maybe after that be put into
the team that handles the execution of that same thing. So thus being part of the whole flow
and actually managing to midwife their own idea or whatever you call it. So, you know,
As it so happens, both me and David are actually in new roles.
So I was VP of strategic initiatives and one of the strategic initiatives that I suggested
was really well received. So much so that they said we can't imagine anyone else doing it.
So they just kind of plucked me right out of there. And same thing with David,
because he worked on some stuff with our friends at Tencent and that went over really well.
plugged him out too. So I guess that's a good place to wrap up. So the two people who were in
charge of innovation managed to innovate themselves right out of the innovation team. And
I suppose you could call that a paradox. I'll take groans. It's okay.
Thank you!
Any questions?
Oh, thank you. I don't know this man. I have not paid him to do this.
Where was the joke? How big was your team? Was it a few people? Was it tens of people? Did it
scale up and down as you did different things or was it like a fixed number of people?
So the question was how big the team was and did we scale it up and down with the size of the initiative and the thing that was being worked on.
So the only permanents were myself and my colleague David, at least in the way the SI division used to look.
In the newer permutation we actually have more people but the roles are a little bit different.
What we would do then when something would scale up is that we would use like outsourcers
and stuff. So one of the things that actually happened off the back of something that my
colleague David did was this whole thing with the choose your own adventure electronic book
things that we've been releasing a little bit. I don't know how many of you have caught
that. That actually came out of SI. And the first iteration was actually done exclusively
with outsource vendors. So. Yes?
Thanks for the talk. I'm wondering, so you mentioned in the workflow that some of the ideas submitted by the employees will just go directly to them if it's executable just in the team. So do you have any examples of game features that you guys looked at and eventually went back to the games team? Like how much influence do you have on game feature, strategy about game features? You think this is very important, you should add in it versus just cross-company initiatives?
Yeah, so the question is how much influence did the SI division but more importantly the
workflow itself have on game team features and so on. Actually quite little because they
have their own process for that kind of stuff. But what we did have is we had some ideas
that had to do with corollary things that were not really part of the current scope
of the game project. So there was one gentleman that had a really cool idea, like one thing
that's pretty big.
Our strategy games are the so-called after action reports where people write down their game sessions and stuff like that.
And he had a really cool idea about having a system that would at least partially maybe automate that.
So that we got more of them. It was a really cool thing. And then he quit.
We'll pick that up someday, I'm sure. But those kinds of things. This was also a place to get
feedback but also to some degree it was a way to get attention of the people who can sign the
checks and say, well, this sounds good enough that we can actually give you the hours that you
need to put on this and not have it be something that you're supposed to do in your own time
because that's just not how it works. Thank you.
I have a question about the strategy initiative. So actually I think it's hard to value how much
money you can make through your department. So why the paradox can establish this permanent
department within your company and make sure that thing is worth running?
So the question is, it's very difficult to assess how much money and what kind of return
on investment that we can get from doing something like this. We did it because we're Paradox
and this is the kind of stuff that we do. If it's small enough scale, Frederick will
basically go, let's try this and we will try it. But of course part of the ‑‑
hope was that the work that we did would kind of validate itself eventually, if that makes
sense. So we would not have run it indefinitely. We were keeping track of the amount of
billable hours and if nothing actionable would have come out of SI, it would have died,
guaranteed. What happened now, though, is that we did a lot of stuff that actually went
somewhere, which is a very good thing.
And I don't know if there is any way of knowing where the threshold should be ahead of time for
profitability, but I'm pretty sure that in this case we did reach it because I still have a job.
Does that answer the question?
Yeah, I think so.
Thank you.
Is there time for another question?
For me it's fine, yes.
So what were some of the strategies that you used to get stakeholder influence when it came to creating the Strategic Initiatives Program?
So the question is what kind of strategies we use to get stakeholder influence and buy
in from the stakeholders.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, there you go.
So that is work that was actually done by the CEO, Frederick, before I even hit the
ground, before I was even in the office.
So I showed up and this had already been kind of advertised within Paradox and he kind of
handled that more or less himself.
But there was an element of maintenance.
So it was kind of, you know, like I said to the gentleman just now, we were expected to
continuously kind of validate and justify our own existence to some degree.
And with some people I think the tolerance and patience was a bit, should we say,
different. Some people were a little bit harsher on us, I guess. But I think eventually, as I say,
there is a more modern permutation. We're still doing it to some extent, even without me in the
team. So I think overall we managed to do it. As for specific techniques that I would use,
I guess that overall I'm a big fan of just ‑‑
Catering to people's wallets.
Like find some angle where you're solving other people's problems.
Or at least pretending you're solving their problems.
And that should probably get you funded at least until you've proven that you're not
actually solving any problems.
Gotcha.
Thanks.
I think that's about it.
Thank you so much for coming everyone.