Thank you for coming to my talk.
I appreciate it.
It's a really nice day, and there's a happy hour going on the Expo, although I should
probably not tell you that, I guess.
But thanks for coming.
So my name is Oliver Franzke, and I'm the lead programmer of Broken Age.
And so today, this talk is a little bit...
of a weird talk for me personally,
because as a programmer,
you know, I like to talk about technical things.
And in fact, the last couple of GDCs,
I talked about various issues
or challenges that we were facing when making Broken Age
and how we approach those.
But today I'm going to talk about something completely on technical but attack a topic that I think it's really important and that in many ways is you know underserved and it's a bit of a mystery around it, but it's such an important topic that can really you know make a break a game of any size and that is the topic of leadership.
And specifically I want to talk about kind of this point in your career.
when you're promoted into a role with leadership responsibilities or
in other ways, maybe in college or whatever, you get, you know, all of a sudden
have responsibility for a group of people, not just yourself anymore.
Because this is, you know, very different or like a very interesting time
when a lot of things kind of change in your kind of day-to-day job,
but that isn't talked about all that often, but it's, you know, such an important
topic that...
I want to share a little bit of my experience
and what I've learned over the years.
And before I'm going to start talking
about very specific things, I would
like to get you guys' help.
Just three really short questions.
After that, I promise you can sit back and relax.
You don't need to do anything else.
I realize this is the last session, so it's been a long
day.
First of all, I would be really curious who here in the audience had at any point in your
career any kind of like leadership experience.
Please raise your hand if that's the case.
Wow, awesome.
Wow, that's a lot of people.
Now to narrow down this question a little bit more, I would be curious who is kind of
new to this role right now.
So if you've been promoted in the last year perhaps, please raise your hand.
I am OK, awesome.
And then the last question is so for all of you
who just raised their hand in the first question.
So you have any kind of your experience in the past.
I would be curious who received any kind of preparation
for this role.
Did your company sent you to a course,
gave you some books, or like in any way
prepared you for this role.
So please raise your hand if that's the case.
Oh, well.
OK.
That's actually good. That's more than what I've seen in the past.
And so what I just saw is like, there were a lot of people,
you know, maybe even like half or 60% of the room,
you know, were responsible for other people at some point.
But when it came to the question of like, you know,
where you actually prepared for this role,
not all that many hands.
went up and that is in many ways off the talking to many leads that seems to be
pretty standard practice in the games industry and I find it really baffling
because in a way as a lead to get kind of you know pushed into this role and
you kind of left you know to your own device to figure out how you supposed to
now you know change the day-to-day job and kind of you know how you supposed to
deal with this and considering how important as well as I'm always kind of
baffled by that.
Now the first thing really to realize when it comes to leadership is that as a team lead,
you know, leadership requires a whole different additional set of skills that you have to learn.
And these are skills that, you know, you kind of add it to your list of skills that you had previously as an individual contributor.
So if you've been...
you know programmer and out as the design on you obviously you know have
been doing really good work at your at your company and you know somebody
in trust you now to bring that good work to and you know be responsible for
entire group of people. But this additional set of skills and nobody ever
tells you about.
That is really important and that's kind of what I want to talk about today.
And it might help you to know that most leads really struggle with this adjustment.
This is not an easy thing to do and it's not something that just kind of happens naturally.
And most people I talk to really said, you know, it took me a long time to kind of learn
this skill and that skill and to really kind of get used to.
get used to this, but I really thought for the longest time
myself that you really have to be born to be a good team lead,
like you know, you can't learn this,
but I don't think that's true.
I think this is just really a set of skills,
and you can learn this, and you can become an effective lead.
And if you're in this position, you
should really consider spending some extra cycles
to learn about this.
Now, before I'm going to start.
talking about a very specific things and responsibilities and techniques and so
on. I want to very briefly sure share with you my own kind of leadership
story and the reason why I'm doing that is because in my mind leadership is a
very personal skill since it is a soft soft skill and everyone kind of
approaches that in a different way and you know certainly for me every
supervisor ever had was very different and you know approached this role in a
very unique way.
So I want to give you a little bit of context for you know
what I'm going to talk about later on.
So my personal leadership story in the games industry
began when just shortly after I joined Double Fine Productions
here in San Francisco.
At the time, we were making a 360 connect game
in collaboration with Sesame Street called Once Upon a
Monster.
And the project lead for this project asked me, hey,
do you want to delete engine program on this game?
And I was really excited.
You know, this was an awesome, an awesome moment
for the longest time.
And my kind of career objectives,
I had the sentence like, hey, you know,
I want to be a lead programmer.
Or like, you want to be responsible for a group
of programmers.
So I said, yes, awesome.
I want to do this.
Fantastic.
And I accepted the job.
You know, came to the office on Monday.
The following Monday, sat down in front of my computer.
And I didn't really know how my day-to-day job was
kind of supposed to change.
And in fact, while I was going through my old photos the other day, I found a picture of myself from just about that time.
look at guys all excited. You know that now is
responsible people or dogs, I guess, but he has no
clue and must be the old to because I
just now realize that this video cell phone in a
picture, you know, it's a old school dog, I guess
but joke aside, you know, I really I think I
feel he felt lost in the beginning and I think
my reaction to this which you know I hope
this is normal human reaction is that in times of
uncertainty, you just kind of continue doing what you know
right, you just kind of continue doing that and.
So I kept my head down I did a lot of programming and I think
you know we shipped this game of you know, I'm pretty proud of
it.
After the budget was over and I had some time to kind of think
about about my role as the lead on the specific project I
realized that I really didn't do anything in this regard in this
kind of leadership aspect and if I ever want to accept the role
again and just forgot I really should spend some more time
learning about learning about this and to be more effective.
And the first thing I did after kind of coming to this conclusion
is to think about supervisors I had in the past.
And I noticed, you know, obviously there were some of my bosses I really liked,
and I thought they were doing a fantastic job leading a group of programmers.
But then there also were a few people I didn't really like,
and I thought, you know, they really should not be in charge of a group of people.
Now, I wanted to break this down a little bit more.
And so I started to write down some of the similarities
in these groups.
And what I noticed is that for the supervisor I really liked,
generally, team morale was really high.
People were motivated to work on the tasks
that they were assigned to them.
Generally it the direction that he was going and the entire
project was going was clear and even if there were changes.
They were communicated well ahead of time and in in in the
good way and for me personally and probably most importantly
as an individual contributor I was felt that my work mattered
and that it was valued and important to my supervisor and
because of that you know it fell I felt motivated to give
this extra bit of like creativity and energy to make
this project awesome.
Now, on the other hand, in times where I didn't really like my supervisor too much, I realized
generally team morale was pretty low.
There was a lot of complaining going on, gossiping, like company politics happening, direction
wasn't clear, and even if, you know, there was some kind of goal that would change frequently,
so you know, there was not a very predictable working environment.
Maybe some of you kind of recognize some of these symptoms.
Most importantly for myself, though, I felt that my own work didn't really matter.
I didn't really feel that my supervisor thought that what I was doing at the time was really important and mattered anyway.
So, you know, why should I be excited about it and spend an extra amount of energy on it?
So usually I just wanted to get this project over with to move on to something else.
Now obviously, you know, we want to figure out how to be like this guy, right?
Like, how can you be this person who hopefully, you know, motivates the team and makes sure
that everybody, you know, feels empowered.
So this is what I want to talk about today.
So if you're new to this role of leadership,
hopefully I can give you a few things
that will help yourself to,
because practically it's how to kind of get used to this role.
You know, if you've been,
if you're like a senior manager and you've been in charge,
or you are in charge of other people who are leading people.
Maybe this will help you to re-familiarize yourself with the situation that, you know, this is not a natural thing to do.
This is not easy for most people and, you know, maybe there's something you can do to help other leads in your company.
But why is leadership kind of even important in the games industry?
And that's not a bad question.
It's actually a pretty good question, because
if you're working for a standard games company, chances are
your hierarchy in terms of like organizational structure is not very deep.
You probably have like a department lead,
and then chances are it's already like project leaders, like the CEO.
Now this combined with the fact that you're surrounded by people
who are probably a very similar interest in you,
and in many ways are probably going
to have a similar age than you, leads
to this kind of environment where
it feels like kind of like in college,
you're just making a game with a bunch of buddies.
And this is great.
I don't want to put this in any kind of negative light
because this fun, creative environment is really
why I personally stayed in the industry for such a long time.
On the other hand, I think these days while projects are getting bigger and you know,
cost more money, it is important to realize that, you know, it is an industry and you
know, now that we, you know, projects have become so big, there are different divisions
and different departments and then subgroups in there, it's become infeasible, became infeasible
for everyone in the company to know everyone else and to effectively communicate with everyone
else to make this project a success.
And this is why where your role as a lead
is just incredibly crucial because this kind
of interdisciplinary cooperation and coordination
is what will make or break potentially the game.
So I guess what I want to say is if your title, your job title
includes the word lead, I encourage you to just really
take the serious because your contributions are really,
really important.
And sometimes it can feel like.
you know, only your kind of programming or art or design tasks really matter,
but that's not true.
The leadership aspect is really, really important.
Now, what are some of these responsibilities
that I talked about earlier?
Now, I think personally, first and foremost,
as a lead, you should really work very hard
on establishing an environment of trust.
And this is important because now that you've been kind of you've been promoted into this role and you kind of left this group of peers, you actually have to work hard on to make sure that you know you can communicate professionally and that you're approachable and that you're trustworthy.
Because you know people might come to you with sensitive information and in
how can someone you know talk to you about something that's going wrong if
you're known as someone who gossips that's not a good environment to be in
or you know if if someone on your team notices some kind of issue that will
potentially put the next sprint at risk of you know have even further reaching
implications if you known as someone who generally is not really approachable.
or generally doesn't take bad news well
chances are you're not going to hear about it
because the person is either going to step around you
talk to somebody else
or maybe not even say anything at all
and then just wait for the train wreck to happen
that is not a good thing, you don't want to be there
but getting to this environment where
you can trust your team and the team can trust you
is not automatic, you need to work on this
and this is something that's important
and I'm going to talk more about it later on
how to get there
Now, of course, also, now that you're responsible for an entire group of people and their work,
that means you're not just responsible for your own kind of tasks anymore.
And that means you should also work on kind of setting a direction for your team.
And ideally this should...
end up in a kind of near term a long term kind of plan.
So near term maybe like you know months or 2 down the road. Long
term plan perhaps you know 6 months on the road or and of
the project.
And this should.
ideally end up in kind of a vacant size mission statement,
you know, let's assume for second year
responsible for a group of that tools for them is
you could imagine you know a good business statement would be
as a tool steam we want to make sure that every content update
that gets made by a con equator is reflected in the game
engine within 10 seconds.
This is great. Everybody can understand this. It's very clear. It's short.
And it's challenging. It should be challenging.
So this is great.
Now, this is not just a thought experiment for yourself.
It's not just so you can write it down on a piece of paper.
You know ideally you know you make sure to communicate this to you to your team
as well because day-to-day decision-making process you can be
influenced by where you want to be in in a year. You know as a programmer you may
notice if you start writing a very complicated system that will be in you
know games
for the next 5, 10 years.
It will make a huge difference to your decision-making process
if you know that some feature or some constraints
will be important later on.
And then lastly, I think the most important responsibility
really is to support your team.
And I think I got this totally wrong in the beginning
because when I thought about like leadership,
I always thought about this kind of traditional image
like of a pyramid, you have to kind of delete on top
and then kind of, you know, more and more people on the knees
and work distribution kind of triples down
and stuff gets done.
And this works well if you're in an environment
where you have, you know, where authoritative leadership style
is important like the army,
but I don't think this works very well
in the games industry in this kind of creative environment.
In a way, you're there to make sure that your team can be successful to achieve the goals that you set.
So it's almost like a flip pyramid, where you're there to kind of hold up your team to make sure
that they can get there, that they have everything they need.
And this can be as simple as making sure that they have software and hardware they need,
or to talk with someone on your team about a certain task and how to approach it,
or if somebody struggles with work performance, that's also your responsibility to help this person.
Now, some of you may ask yourself this question now,
but what about my actual job?
And this is the question I heard a lot
when I started to talk to other leads about this.
Like, after I realized I should learn about it
and I started to write down a little bit of some
of my experiences, I kind of talked to a lot of other people
to kind of get their view.
And what I heard very often was a story like,
you know, I really like being a lead.
I like to be involved in some of the kind of more project-wide
decision-making process.
But with all of these meetings and talking to people
and all of that stuff, writing reviews,
I really don't know when I'm supposed to do my actual job.
And this is, I think, probably the biggest misconception
when it comes to leadership.
Because as a team lead, leadership is your actual job.
Now, this is really important to me.
So if there's only one thing you take away from this talk,
I really hope it's this.
As a team lead, leadership is your actual job.
All of these meetings, writing reviews, talking to people,
helping people, supporting people, all of that stuff,
that is what you're supposed to do first and foremost.
Now, of course, this means that you will have less time
to work on programming tasks, art tasks, or design tasks.
So depending on the size of the company and your team,
you can expect to spend between 20% and maybe even up
to 50% of your time on kind of leadership and management
tasks.
So, you know, make sure to take this into account
and don't overcommit yourself.
Because if you take on too much work yourself,
chances are you're going to be working a lot,
you're going to do over hours,
and you might not be as approachable
as you should be.
And that's, again, not a good place to be.
But how can we, you know, what specific techniques can you do
and what kind of skills are important?
Well, just like with many things in life,
unfortunately there's no real single secret
to good leadership.
And as I found out myself, if you go to Google
and type in like, oh, you know,
how can I learn about leadership?
You'll find a lot of things like,
10 minute videos that will promise that you know after you watch this you will be the
perfectly or this 20 step program you can read on I don't know ww leadership dot com
this is part of it, but I can guarantee you that this will not be like the single thing
you have to read.
In fact, if there's only if there's a singular kind of formula that I.
Except in this regard, it's really this quote from Mike Acton.
I really like this.
If you absolutely must have a formula for your leadership work,
here's mine.
Figure out what doesn't work and do less of that.
And figure out what works well and do more of that.
It's so simple, but yet it is important
because it also shows that you're never really done becoming a lead.
You know, just like as a programmer.
You're never really done acquiring a maximum kind of skill level in this regard.
So it's important to realize that every once in a while you have to take a step back and
kind of think about what you're doing and adjust your strategies.
But what specific things can you do, now that you've been promoted?
Let's get to the meat of things.
Personally, I think one of the most important things you can do,
especially if you're just really, really new to this world,
is to find a mentor.
And the mentor in this regard is someone that you personally really respect
for his or her leadership abilities.
Ideally, there would be someone in your own organization
just to make communication much easier
and kind of have a faster turnaround time, so to speak,
when talking about specific topics.
It doesn't need to be your direct supervisor, though.
So if you're a programming lead, if you
see someone in the art department
doing a fantastic job.
you know, communicating and like leading this team and everybody's motivated and
doing fantastic work.
I encourage you to go to this person and ask, like, hey, is it okay to come by every
once in a while,
you know, talk about some of the challenges I'm facing, adjusting to this role and
kind of the progress I'm making.
Because this kind of practical advice that, you know, has been
gathered over years and years of working in this specific role is
really invaluable.
And it will allow you to, you know, talk about specific situations you ran into
and how you handled these and whether or not that was
a good thing to do.
But even if you feel like there's no one in your own organization that you can talk to
directly for whatever reason they may be.
I encourage you to reach out to somebody else in the games industry to ask questions if
you have them.
For example, the Australian artist Zach Duff did this when he was first promoted into an
art leadership role.
When he wrote, you know, a mail to John Romero to ask questions about this topic.
And as it seems, I have not seen his email, but as it seems, he felt that was pretty helpful.
And this definitely also reflects my own experience, you know, after I kind of came to the conclusion
that I should probably do a bit more in this regard.
I started writing emails to people I respect very much.
for the book in this field and I asked very specific questions
and I found that people are pretty generous with their time
and really helpful and really want to help because, you know,
these people have gone through this kind of struggle at some point,
so, you know, they're well aware of this problem set.
Now, it shouldn't come as a big surprise that communication
plays some role in all of this.
In fact, you know, effective communication is probably the key skill
that you will have to work on.
Now that now that you lead and if you can't communicate you
can't really need just make sense.
Now it's important to realize that this may take more time
than you think and you know as a programmer I certainly
went to this myself you know as a program I guess we're
a program so generally gets known that you know maybe
then all this understandable to the art department design
department and I'm sure that's the you know certain truth
that and for me I had to learn that it's really important
to make sure that you know I change.
The way a communicate depending on who I talk to if I want to talk about even the same system or tool or whatever is to someone on the art department. I have to use different vocabulary and talk of you know different. About different details than if I would talk to someone on the programming team. This is really important. So just you know make sure to to do this and one thing I want to mention at this point. As a newly it's I think.
important to realize that it's OK not to know everything.
Sometimes I feel like there can be this pressure that you kind
of have to know everything and you
have to be able to do everything all of a sudden
because someone in your work kind of entrusted you
with this position.
So I know this pressure, but it's OK not to know everything.
It's OK to say, you know what?
I don't actually know this right now, but let me find out,
and then I'm going to come back and talk to you later on.
Now other things that are really important.
But he's you know be proactive if you notice something that's
not going well don't wait for somebody else to to solve this
problem, you know you in a position where you know you
take on this extra responsibility to so make sure
you know you actually fulfill this role so if you see someone
in your team being rude to somebody else don't wait for
somebody to come to you like this is something that you know
you should should deal with on your own terms or by
Now, also, especially when it comes to communicate, I think, to your supervisors, you know, do make sure to be transparent.
As a new lead, I think it can be sometimes, for some new leads, it can be hard when things don't go well and, you know, maybe...
There's a problem and maybe you feel like you know, maybe I shouldn't tell anyone I can probably fix this and nobody will ever know
Don't do this
You know if something is going wrong
Go to the people that will be affected by that tell them about this and then you find a solution
You know things will go wrong. This is the games industry and I think it's probably applies to all the other industries
It's just the way the way it goes
Also be clear and I kind of covered us a little bit already, you know, people can't read your mind.
So make sure to break down whatever you want to say in as simply as you can or as clearly as you can rather.
And you know, if you feel like maybe somebody is not quite on the same page, you know, ask probing question, you know, does this make sense?
You know, is there any way I can break us down?
Should I like draw a diagram?
Whatever it may be, you know, be really work on this.
And this is, you know, takes takes some time.
Now, one thing I think I completely underestimated
before being in this role is I think
it's the importance of listening.
In my mind, when I thought about leadership,
I always thought about someone standing on a podium
giving an inspiring speech and everybody runs off
and does some amazing work.
But that's in reality not how it works.
And what's actually way more important is that
for you to find out what's happening and gather information and to listen and to really kind
of understand who these people are and what their problems are.
There's a saying as a human, you have two ears and one mouth, you should use them in
that ratio.
And I certainly think that this applies to leadership.
Now one thing you can do as a specific technique that could, would help you with improving
your listening skills is to ask more open-ended questions.
And open-ended questions are questions that can't be easily answered with yes or no.
And in fact, these are kind of questions where you want to invite your communication partner
to elaborate a little bit more about the topic, and so you can find out about the kind of
what and why.
And these things are really important to get this excellent information.
Now I was for a while thinking about whether I should make this an interactive part of this presentation, but I decided against it.
But as an example, let's assume for a second your project lead decides that, you know, all the vehicles in your game should be drivable by the player.
Now, maybe you have to delegate this work.
So you could bring this up to someone
on your team asking an open-ended question,
like this.
Hey, James, what do you think about this feature?
And how long do you think this will take to implement?
Now, compare this to the closed form
where you would say something like this.
Hey, James, we decided to add this feature.
Can you get it done this sprint?
Now, this may seem kind of like a very similar question
at first glance, but it's actually a huge difference.
Because in the closed form, really what you're doing,
you're dumping some work on someone else's plate.
You're not really interested about any kind
of potential side effects or stuff
that you may not be aware of.
And you're certainly not interested in this person's
input on this feature.
And how is this person supposed to feel like this is something
to be excited about?
So you're not going to get much buy-in.
On the other hand.
you know asking this is an open question you what you really doing inviting you
know writing a teammate to kind of work on this feature on this problem.
Together with you and because of that you know you're going to first of all
find out about potential side effects problems that you may not be aware of or
maybe it's not a good idea because of that or this.
And generally it shows that you trust this person and that you value this person's input.
And you know, that's going to lead to a very different place.
This person hopefully is going to have some buy-in in this feature by the end of it.
And you know, it's just an important thing.
And you know, it takes a little bit of time to get used to kind of restructuring the way you ask questions.
But it's really helpful.
So I can only...
I suggest you do this.
Now, another listening technique that's really helpful,
especially when kind of dealing with kind
of difficult conversations.
So, you know, something is not going well,
there's a problem, maybe people blame each other
for the problem, emotions are running high.
This is an ideal situation to use a technique
that's called active listening.
An act of listening, the idea is to essentially minimize
the chance of miscommunication.
And you do this by restating or paraphrasing
what your communication partner says back to him
using your own words.
Now obviously, you want to first think
about what the person said and then paraphrase that.
So the idea here is that you essentially
make sure that the other person can hear what you think he
or she said, so that if there is any miscommunication,
that it can be resolved right away.
I certainly had my fair share of conversations, both at work
and with my wife, where we're talking,
and I just feel like, why does this person not get it?
It's so clear.
Only to find out eventually that actually we're
actually talking about different aspects, perhaps
of the same topic.
This will help you with this.
It's a very, very helpful technique.
And it will also become very, very handy
in one of the most important things you can do as a lead.
And this is one-on-one meetings.
Now as the name suggests, the idea here is to meet with everyone on your team on a kind of regular basis to kind of a face to face conversation.
And this is important because now that you're responsible for the workload of a group of people, you really have to know the people on your team because how else are you going to be able to lead these people, right?
You have to know what...
what they're good at, what they're not good at, what they enjoy working on, what they don't enjoy working on.
And the only way of finding out is by asking them about these kind of topics.
And this also will really help you to kind of establish,
well, hopefully, to establish this kind of environment of mutual trust.
Hopefully you're going to get to a situation where your team will realize,
yes, I can talk to my lead about these kind of topics and potentially
also about something that's going wrong and nothing bad will happen.
So this is a great thing to do.
Now, one thing I kind of found out myself is,
you know, definitely made this mistake myself,
is ideally don't skip these meetings.
You know, towards the end of a project,
things can get stressful.
So it's easy to say, well, you know,
let's just not do it right now.
It's OK, I think, to have a short meeting.
But ideally, you would keep this going.
And this is something.
yeah, that I learned myself.
Also pick a location where you can potentially
discuss sensitive topics.
So a meeting room in your office is a great place, of course.
You can also go to a nearby coffee shop if you want.
As long as both of you can feel comfortable,
don't need to be worried about somebody else just dropping in
and potentially overhearing a part of the conversation
that they shouldn't hear.
Now one thing that's kind of, I think, often misunderstood, I feel, is that what you should talk about in these meetings.
And it's important that this is not a status update.
So ideally, the core of this conversation should not be about what the task load is and we know when it will be done.
This can be a starter, but you should...
concentrate on trying to figure out you know career goals can a problem set
happening and other things so off try asking questions like you know to enjoy
what you're working on is there something else you want to would prefer
to work on is this something you want to learn where do you want to be in 5
years.
you know, if there's something if there's one thing you could
change on the project right now, what would that be.
Now, of course, don't ask all of these questions
and the first meeting you meet with when
you meet with your teammate.
All you're going to find out is how patient
your teammate is at this point.
So don't do that.
But it's just to give you some kind of idea of hopefully
what you should talk about and try to find out.
And what's really important is to.
make sure to really listen when you go to these meetings.
Don't have these meetings in front of a computer
where you can see email notifications popping up
every minute.
Or if you have to bring your mobile phone along,
make sure to silence it.
Because the important part is to make sure
that you concentrate on this conversation
and that your teammate can feel valued and important.
And that's how it should be.
Because nothing is worse than having
a half-assed conversation where you're just
responding with, uh-huh, yeah, uh-huh, OK.
That really shows disrespect, so don't do this.
And lastly, if there's something like an actual actionable item that comes out of this, like...
We should send you the course, or we should send you to GDC.
Make sure to write this down so you don't forget about it,
and send it to the person you talk to,
so you both kind of have this as a baseline in written down
form.
And it will also help you to kind of later on look at,
OK, what did we talk about in the past?
What kind of specific actionable things that should happen?
Now, one thing that's, I think, really hard,
especially if you're new to this role, is how to.
how to deal with expectations and that it's important to set
expectations because as a newly, you know it can be you can feel
like you know who are you or like you know who am I to to
to tell these people to do their job. Yeah, I'm not.
You know, I'm so new in this role, but this is not really
what it's about it's not about telling people how to do their
job it's about.
letting people know what is important to you and what would frustrate you if not done well.
Because what is really bad would be a situation where you get back some kind of task from someone
and you look at it and then you say like yeah, you know, this is good, but can you change it
according to these rules I never told you? That's very frustrating. So ideally don't do that.
And of course, you know, try not to go in and change things yourself.
That will really make you appear like a micromanager
and chances are people don't want to, you know, why should they invest their time
if you're just going to go in and change it anyway.
So this is really important if you want to reduce your frustration.
So as a programmer, it's a specific example.
If coding standards are really important to you,
you make sure to let your team know that this is the case.
Because nothing is worse than having some kind of unspoken
rules that nobody really knows about.
OK, so one thing that's also, I think, really, really hard
for a lot of new leads is how to delegate
and to kind of get used to this idea of delegation.
And I personally found that one way of actually doing this,
getting used to this kind of in a good way,
is an easy way, is by having sprint planning meetings.
And the idea here is to get everyone
in the team into a room.
And you first talk about what you did in the previous sprint,
and kind of what got done, what didn't get done,
why it didn't get done.
And then you talk about what needs to get done for the next sprint.
And at this point you can invite people on your team to just grab the tasks they would prefer to work on.
And hopefully this is going to lead to a situation where people on your team are actually pretty happy with the majority of their tasks.
Now, of course there will be stuff that nobody wants to do.
You know, whatever this may be.
Writing yet another safe system, UI, I don't know, whatever it is.
So you still have to deal with that.
You could take that task on yourself.
That's totally OK if you want to be a nice boss
and you want to make sure that everyone in your team
only has the task they want.
But of course, do remember, don't overcommit yourself.
Don't say, yeah, yeah, I will do all these things
if you're just going to be stressed out afterwards.
So also at this point.
This is a good place to talk about kind of some of the potential implications that come with these
with these tasks, you know, how will that work with multiplayer,
will that bloat it, you know, the texture limit, texture memory limit,
stuff like that, just kind of ask probing questions and you know, hopefully your experience
as an individual contributor will guide you here to kind of ask the relevant questions.
Now one thing that I kind of had to learn.
over the, you know, while adjusting to this, it's kind of,
that delegation really goes further, further than this.
It's also, it's not just about work distribution,
it's also about making sure to keep your team involved
in the kind of day-to-day kind of decision-making process.
Because it's important to remember that the people on your team are really the domain experts.
These are the people who are down in the trenches doing the actual work.
They know all the details about whatever it is that, you know, your group does.
And even you may not know all those details.
So if it comes to kind of questions about these parts,
do make sure to keep them...
to keep them involved in this as well and I certainly you know
found this out the hard way and you know you can certainly
if you know start kind of over stepping over people and like not thinking
about this
you can certainly lead to like hurt feelings and people
feeling like you know you don't trust them with with answering questions or
something like that.
Now, lastly, delegation is also a great, great tool
for skill development.
Because most people don't really enjoy
working on repetitive tasks.
I don't know about you, but I certainly
am most happy at work if I'm doing something that's
challenging me, and I feel like at the end of the day,
I learned something new.
And that's true for most people.
Now, of course, one-on-one meetings
are a great way to find out how somebody
feels about doing the same thing again, over and over again,
or maybe wanting to be challenged.
at which point or how much this person wants to be challenged.
So let's assume for a kind of a made up but specific example,
let's say you're leading an art team.
And for the next sprint, you have to model an orc.
Now, you could give this task to one of your senior artists
who has modeled several orcs for the last couple of projects.
And you know this person will get this done
in a pretty short amount of time and to the quality level
that you expect.
Now, but maybe you recently hired a junior artist who
has expressed his interest in character modeling
in one of the one-on-one meetings.
Now, if time permits, you may actually
want to consider giving this task to the junior artist,
even though it will take this person probably longer
to get it done and it will take a couple of iterations
to get to the quality level that you want to.
But it will help this person to develop these skills.
And that will become helpful.
Probably it will help yourself, because later on your team
can take on more challenges.
And it will also help this person,
because as you learned, he or she is very excited about it.
So hopefully this person will be very motivated about it.
And if you want to get extra points as a lead,
try pairing up the senior artists and the junior artists
so they can share experiences.
That will also help a lot.
Now, of course, now that the work distribution aspect is done,
your job as a lead is not over.
As a lead, you're really representing your team,
which means you have to know what's up
and what the progress is of everyone in your team,
not just your own workload.
And I think this is a point where sometimes this kind
of my actual job syndrome can kick in.
You feel like, I distributed work.
Great, everybody knows what to do for the next two weeks.
I'm just going to like be heads down and write some code or draw some textures or you know balance
some some specialties for units.
Make sure to take some time to stay up to date what's going on in your team and the
different ways of doing that I know people who really like reading checking comments
and purpose for example to kind of stay up to date what's happening there if you have
a producer that's walking around in your team was kind of.
checking in anyway, you know, have a coffee with the producer and figure out what's going on this way.
Or, of course, just walk around yourself and talk to people.
And this comes as the added benefit that you hopefully hear about potential problems
way before they become an actual issue
and so that you can do something, you know, at the earliest possible time.
Okay.
So now I want to talk about a topic that's probably
the hardest lesson for most new leads,
at least that's came out of the conversation
that I had with other leads.
And that is the importance of providing feedback
and how to provide feedback.
And I want to talk about both the negative side of things
as well as the positive side of things.
Let's start with criticism.
As a lead, it's important that you take this part of your role
also seriously, because you're responsible for what's
going on your team.
And if something is not going well, you have to deal with this.
You can't just push this out.
because in my experience problems never go away,
they just become worse.
So, you know, deal with it.
And this won't be a fun conversation, of course,
you know, and it's probably not gonna be the best day at work,
but that's okay.
It's just you have to get used to this.
Let's assume for a second again as a kind of a made up example
is that someone on your team keeps breaking the build.
And that's beside the fact that you explained
that this will disrupt the entire team or project.
And you even explained, OK, the way to avoid this,
make sure to test all your changes locally
and then check it in.
But it didn't help.
You did all that.
It's still happening.
Now, you have to deal with this.
Don't wait for somebody else from another team
to come and say, hey, what's going on with this person?
Now one thing you shouldn't do is to walk into this person's work area and start, you know,
criticizing the person right there. Because if you criticize people in the open, in public,
all that will happen is that this person will end up in a defensive position, right?
Because what they're probably mostly concerned about at this point is not to lose respect in
front of his or her work colleagues.
So instead get a meeting room and have a discussion there.
And at this point, you do make sure
you approach this conversation with empathy.
There may be things going on in this person's life
that you're not aware of, whatever this may be.
So don't storm in there and wave your finger and say,
if you don't stop this in the next week,
I will make sure that you get fired.
That's not a good way to approach that.
If you have a
If you have a kid and maybe you're here from school,
your kid is not handing in the homework on time,
you're hopefully not going to storm in your kid's room
and say, you know what?
If you don't start handing in your homework,
I'm going to fire you from this family.
Instead, I hope what you would do is say,
you know I heard about this issue with the homework.
What's going on?
Is there any way I can help you with this?
And ideally, you want to approach this situation
exactly the same way.
As a team lead, as I said earlier,
one of your responsibilities is to support your team.
And that means sometimes to make sure
to help people who struggle with whatever
it may be at this point.
Now, you know, do make sure to find out what's going on,
you know, if your teammate trusts you with that information.
And then work on a plan together, like figure out,
you know, these are specific things we can do
to not be in a situation anymore.
Then write this down and, you know, send it,
send it as a form, in form of an email
to this person you talked to.
And then, of course, going forward, you know,
do make sure to check in and see how it's going and, you know,
ask, well, first of all, you hopefully should see
whether the situation is improving.
but also you know to inquire like hey this this plan working for you
says something we should change.
So this is kind of an important aspect now
on the other end of the spectrum is also praise and I think sometimes as a.
Here we go.
It's praise.
And I think sometimes as a new lead,
it's very easy and kind of natural
to concentrate on the things that you like to change.
And you like to tell people, hey, don't do it like this.
Don't do it like that.
And it's way too often and very common
that leads will kind of forget to tell people.
that they're doing well and to praise them, but it's important to tell your teammates
that, you know, if they're doing a good job, that they are doing a good job, because most
people really want to know how they're doing and hopefully that they're doing well.
And so just a few little words like, hey, well done,
or the way you kind of solve this problem,
I really like this, go already a long way.
And unlike with criticism, it's totally OK,
and I would say, in fact, encouraged
to praise people in public.
Because you share kind of this success with a wider audience.
And hopefully this will kind of boost team morale.
So if you have a meeting at work where
you're representing.
your team, maybe to an entire project, make sure to kind of, you know, mention that,
hey, you know, these cool things happened, and this is the person who was responsible
for that.
You know, hope, you know, this will make feel, make people feel important, and that's really
an important thing.
After hearing all of these things, you may think like, man, this leadership thing is
pretty hard.
Maybe there were a few things I didn't really think about before.
And that's true, you know, adjusting to this role is pretty tough and takes a while.
It's not an easy thing to do.
But it is impossible.
It is not impossible.
It is possible.
That would be the weirdest message ever.
Guys, sorry.
Thanks for spending an hour with me,
but it's actually not happening.
No.
It is definitely possible.
And you can work on these skills.
You can adjust to this role even if it right now it seems like you know how many start getting used to this and you know, maybe I already been a lead for half a year and that anything doesn't matter you know start doing some of the same set up one on one meetings put in your calendar and whatever it may be.
I really like this quote from Brian Sharpe's talk
here at GDC in 2012, when he said
that when it comes to leadership,
there's this misconception that comprehension equals mastery,
when it's clearly not the case.
Just because you read all the books
or seen all the presentations about leadership, by the way,
thanks for coming to this presentation,
doesn't necessarily mean that you're automatically
going to be the most awesome lead the next day at work
and will be able to apply all these things.
In a German language, you have the saying that no master ever
fell from the sky, meaning that nobody ever gets all the skills
that he or she needs overnight.
And it takes time to learn these things and dedication.
And you know another thing that's Brian said in this talk is that
practice is really the opposite of hoping. So rather than saying,
oh man, I hope I will be like one of those awesome bosses I had in the past.
The only way to get there is by actually, you know, working on this and
kind of taking a step back, thinking about does this work, you know,
should I change some of my strategies.
And really this is just the beginning if you're new to this role this is a
fantastic time in your career it's very exciting you know some obviously people
at your work think that you know you're ready for this and that you have what it
takes to fulfill this role.
But it will take time to kind of learn this
and to kind of flex your leadership muscles.
But being a teammate is a great place to be.
And it still baffles me to kind of think
about at the end of the week how much work gets done.
It is just such an amazing feeling.
And really, all I talked about today
is really just kind of the fundamentals of this.
It's the most basic things I think you should know about.
And I hope this will help you to hit the ground running.
And, you know, it will hopefully make it easier for you than it was for me, perhaps, and some
of the other leads I talked to.
And unfortunately, before I make any more weird things and say weird stuff, this is
all I have time to talk about.
So thank you very much for your attention, and I'm happy to answer questions.
Thank you.
Hello.
Hey.
Can you hear me?
Yeah.
Can you share your thoughts on the role of the leader
when things go wrong?
Who should have the blame,
especially going up to management and whatnot?
So can you repeat the first part of this question?
What are your thoughts when things go wrong?
What is the leader's role?
Well, I think first and foremost,
I think blaming people is the complete.
Oh, I should repeat the question.
What is the role the leader has when things go wrong?
I think first and foremost, blaming people on your team,
I don't think it's the right approach.
In fact, very often what you'll read
is something like, as a good leader,
really what you should do is accept all the blame yourself,
and then share all the praise, and give that out.
And I think my personal opinion is that.
try not to make this an emotional thing like if there's a problem, you know try
to be as rational as possible like look you know these things happen you know
whatever reason this this may be let's try to figure out what what can be done
and then you know do everything you can to to kind of solve this problem but I
would definitely say like don't go around and you know go to a bus and
saying you know
It all went wrong because James did it wrong.
I could have told you.
And even if that's the case, even if James did something
wrong, I hope there are no Jameses here.
Even if that's the case, then it's still your responsibility,
right?
Because what did you do during the day?
Like, how did it get to this point
that you didn't notice that this happened?
So I like this book. I actually have it in my resource section.
Let's see if I can get there.
It's called Difficult Conversations.
How to Discuss Matters That Matter Most.
And in this book, the authors discuss
kind of how to approach these kind of situations from a different angle
and to essentially kind of change the way you look at this.
from kind of a blaming point of view to more like a contribution like how what
was my role in this like how did it get to this point and you will find
hopefully at this will actually was off the problem in a much better way than
otherwise.
Hi, I'm Natalie. I wanted to ask about, well often when you're a team leader, then you have a situation where you have people working under you who are much more experienced, much more like objectively have more knowledge. And I've been there, so I'm kind of wondering if you've had any difficult situations around that, decision making that has been hard, and if you can share a story about that.
Right, right.
So the question is, what do you do
if you're responsible for people who actually have more work
experience in this field than yourself?
Is that correct?
Yeah, so actually, this is kind of how I started out.
So when I talked about in the beginning,
that was my situation where.
You're kind of really in the spot where you feel like,
man, how can I, you know,
who am I to tell this person who has way more work experience
than me that how to do things.
I think it's important and, you know, this is really hard.
I think what you should do is like...
You know have a one-on-one meeting and actually be pretty candid and say like you know look I
realize that you you know you have way more work experience in this in this
field than myself and I'm really new to this role.
So you know if there's actually anything I can learn from you that would be great to just kind of get to this
point where it's hopefully not as awkward anymore and that you kind of feel like you can trust each other
and if this person.
it's been around for a long time and perhaps been in the same situation,
then, you know, chances are that this person will actually understand what you're talking about.
So, try not to, I guess, try not to like, you know, brush it on the carpet,
but actually bring it up and like talk about this very specifically.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi.
First of all, thanks for the talk.
That was really amazing.
Thank you.
And so my question is more, so I'm a game designer.
And at work, we end up being product owners, right?
So we're tasked with leading multidisciplinary teams
that are more feature-focused.
So I was wondering if you have any insight or best practices
or experience that you can share regarding
leading multidisciplinary teams.
Right, so the question is what to do if you're not just responsible for like a small or like
a group of programmers or artists, but like actually for an entire umbrella of people.
To be quite honest with you, my own experience has mostly been focused on leading programmers.
But I think...
especially the situation. I think what I would do in a situation is to make sure to talk
all of the kind of the people on in this team to kind of get their opinion on things so
you know if the senior designers saw the so whatever to make sure to get us to list solicit
a feedback, especially about topics that you're not sure about yourself and that you actually
have any specific example experience was just like this the other answer, you know, you
know bring this up in the open say like you I.
And I know that I, you know, I'm a programmer, you know,
now I'm in charge of artists as well.
This is something I'm not really,
I don't have any experience in.
But I, you know, I will try to do my best.
And, you know, I do want to learn from you guys.
I do want to learn how you approach the situation.
So, I don't know, I don't think I can give you
more like specific practical advice,
unfortunately, in this regard.
Okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
Hello. My question was sort of making the transition from peer to lead with when you're sort of faced with a group that still feels you as the peer, sort of what it's a rocky transition.
And you have the group that's refusing the one-on-ones,
refusing to participate in the things you're
sort of instituting, and how you sort of repair
the relationship, or even in an upcoming project,
just making sure things are smooth going forward.
So the question is, when you adjusted this role,
and people that you now support.
Your teammates that you're supposedly responsible for don't recognize you as the leader, essentially, right?
Or see you as a peer, right?
Yeah, continue to see you as a peer.
Yeah.
Well, I think this is actually really hard situation.
I talked to some people who really had problems with that,
because also, you know, like friendships
were really put under stress.
Because now you're kind of a different angle,
and maybe you have to make decisions that somebody else
might not feel are the right way of doing things.
So it's hard, and I think.
I feel like really weird giving the same answer 3 times,
but I think it's really important for these things
that usually go unspoken.
You know, that kind of stuff that you're like,
this is so awkward, but I don't really know what to know.
I think it's important to, OK, 5 more minutes.
OK, awesome.
Thank you.
It's important to bring this up and say.
have a you know have a one-on-one meeting or you know whatever catch them on the way to the coffee shop
it's like you know you know I noticed that you don't want to do the one-on-ones or the way you communicate with me
maybe it's not in the same way or how you should communicate with the lead and I realize you know we used to be peers
and this is really hard and I'm adjusting to this but I would really appreciate if you know you could you could help me with this and like just
make sure that this person understands that which position you are in and you know sometimes
even for the people that you're responsible for that's also kind of a weird thing to adjust to.
So maybe I should just give the generalized answer is make sure for everything that's unspoken you
know do make sure to bring this up and that's hard I mean this is not an easy thing to do and
it's very uncomfortable very often but I think you will feel much better about it afterwards and
I think honestly that's the best thing you can do in the situation.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
Hi.
Fantastic presentation. Thank you for that. So when a lot of us that are in a lead position are
likely experts or past, you know, have had a lot of experience in our field doing a particular
job that we might now be responsible for other people doing. So when we are bringing someone
in that position, we'll want to train them, show them the tools and the things they need to
know. But there's a point at which I think we each have our personal processes, right, and
how we do it and what worked really well for us.
And I think there can be a point where, I guess the question is, is there a point at which we can be too, we can try and push our own processes on someone else too much?
And then also, how do I identify that point where, what do our employees need to know to do what they need to do?
Because my curiosity now is like whether to take an approach of, alright, here's what you're responsible for.
go for it, you know, and kind of let them figure it out.
Right, right.
So the question is, like once you're
kind of writing up the hierarchy,
you get to a point where your own kind of process
is so used to this that you perhaps
don't realize that there are other better
ways of doing things.
And like, when do you get to this point,
and how do you realize that, and how do you perhaps
deal with this?
Is this about, right, like a summary?
Yeah, yeah.
I want to know when to not have to tell someone
how exactly I might do it.
Yeah.
And, well, I think this will definitely happen.
And it kind of depends, I think, sometimes on your team size also.
Ideally, if you have, let's say.
let's say you're leading some kind of tools team and at some point you were to
for himself and but now you have people and you I think it's ideally would keep
the people actually working with on a day-to-day basis involved as well so if
you have someone in your team. It's like a senior programmer make sure to bring
him along and like also solicit is a question like so you know the way we
doing around right now this is make sense or for me my own experience with
this perhaps the closest to that is.
Sometimes, at least in my own experience,
when tools specifically don't work very well,
but artists are sometimes too shy to bring this up,
it can be hard to get to know this point.
And sometimes it just takes.
you to go around and kind of realize and I was like, wait, what's going on and then
like talk about the specific situation like, you know, I notice you doing it this way,
why are you doing this way, what is, you know, is there something that's broken with this
process and I'm just trying to be sensitive. I think as soon as you start actually being
kind of sensitive to this topic and kind of.
take a step back like want to think about it. I think it will already change a
perspective on it. And then you know as I said generally like make sure to kind of
keep people in a team involved like people actually working the specific
aspects you know make sure to ask their opinion as well and even you know even
if it's if you make a decision otherwise they don't it's it's good to have this
information anyway.
About now? Yeah, I appreciate it. Thank you.
Hi. So I recently started taking up some leadership responsibilities on my job, really recently.
So one of the things that I struggle with, that I find really hard, is when I'm put on the spot to
make a call, the decision making, because I can't help having in the back of my mind this, what if
you make the wrong choice and one of your superiors calls that out and say, oh actually we don't do
that, that way we're going to do the opposite.
So this kind of anxiety or this kind of, you know, when I have to make a call
I guess it's just feel fear of failure or you know, it's post syndrome or something like that
Do you have any advice for this kind of situation?
So the question is that, you know, while
decision-making process happening, you're kind of handing off some of these kind of
decision-making parts to your peers, but you kind of want to, you feel like, oh, you know,
maybe this person will make the wrong choice.
Is that about kind of like how do you deal with this?
Yeah, kind of also from the point of view of...
still feeling I guess it's the opposite of the previous question where I still feel kind of appear
myself so I feel like I want someone else to verify that what I'm doing is cool.
Okay, right. Okay, so first of all this will be the let's do this and make this the last
question like with the microphone and if people still want to talk to me I will be around.
Yes, this is a really hard thing.
I think especially as a programmer,
this takes a while because it's kind of hard to kind of take
your hands off the keyboard and say, OK, let's you guys do it.
I don't, you know, I trust you.
It's not, I mean, the thing is, I think just the problem
of feeling like maybe somebody will make the wrong choice.
You can get around this by making sure
to talk to the people who actually work on this
pretty frequently.
And kind of like, don't do it in a way where you say,
don't do it like this, don't do it like that.
But kind of just asking, like, hey, what are you doing?
What's your approach?
And then try to take the statements
or the recommendations that you have
and try to put them into questions.
So you would say, oh, well, OK, that's interesting.
But have you thought about this?
Try to guide them in a way.
And if you do this right, it takes a bit, I think,
to get used to.
But if you do this right, you will actually
make people feel like they arrived at this conclusion
completely on their own terms, which is great.
This is where you want to be.
The people feel really empowered.
But you can also feel really proud,
because you helped them to get there.
So I think trying to just communicate
you know, try to find out what's going on.
And then if something is happening,
first try to be nice and ask questions.
And if something is really obviously
going the wrong direction, then you may have to say,
like, oh, you know what?
I don't think we should do like that.
We should do like this because of this and that and this.
So try to obviously use your experience
that you have in this field.
OK, thanks.
Yep.
That doesn't sound dissatisfied.
Maybe we should talk afterwards or something.