Okay, so thanks for coming to the session,
throwing out the dopamine shots,
rewards without the neurotrash.
Just to get started, we've got the housekeeping
stuff, please turn off your cell phones
or put them on silent and please do
the evaluation afterwards, it'd be
really cool.
Okay, so my name's
Ben, I'm a UX researcher
at Epic Games, I have a PhD
in psychology, I've worked in neuroscience departments
and human effectiveness departments
and I'm a kiwi, that's the nationality
not the fruit or the bird.
You can reach me at that email address or on Twitter or I like playing games so please feel free to add me on any of these services. I kind of hop around between them.
Okay, so that out of the way, who's ever said or heard someone say that a game mechanic gives a player a shot of dopamine? Hands up. Okay, a lot of people.
So what does this mean? I want to talk about that very quickly.
Dopamine is a compound.
It's found in various parts of the body.
It's a precursor to adrenaline, for example,
so anywhere that adrenaline is produced, there's dopamine.
But most people, when they're saying a shot of dopamine,
are talking about its use as a neurotransmitter in the brain,
where you will find it.
And I think what a lot of people talk about when they're saying gives you a shot of dopamine,
they're talking about pleasure, a good feeling is what's occurring right now.
And based on the science, this is an idea that's about 30 years or so old.
And it was based on an idea that, of course, if animals are going to work for a reward,
it must feel good, because none of us work for things that feel bad, right?
And that was kind of the idea when it came around.
And certainly if we look at dopamine and its impact on animals,
if you genetically engineer mice to not produce dopamine,
you get a different type of behavior.
So the mouse that's running around, that's normal mousy behavior.
The one that's just sitting there and letting the other one walk all over top of it
is dopamine deficient, not producing any dopamine.
And certainly these mice, they lack motivation
and they will eventually die unless you make sure that they eat enough.
So it certainly does something.
The idea that it's responsible for pleasure and for liking rewards has fallen away within
the scientific community.
And there's various reasons for that.
One is that with animals, they still show that they get pleasure that they like things.
If you give mice a choice between water or sugar water that don't produce dopamine, they'll
choose the sugary water, suggesting that they still get pleasure from things.
If you're not convinced by animal research and want people that can actually talk to
you and talk about the pleasure they're getting.
You can look at Alzheimer's patients.
Alzheimer's is defined by a drop of dopamine.
But these people still report pleasure.
They still report liking things.
That's my father, by the way.
He doesn't have Alzheimer's,
but he looks like he's having fun.
So the idea that dopamine has to do with getting pleasure
or a reward system and all this kind of stuff
has kind of fallen away,
and it fell away quite a while ago.
It's just the popular way that it's talked about has not.
And even the people that originally put forward the idea of dopamine being pleasure have said,
okay, it's not.
And what followed after that was some thinking that it's to do with learning.
And this was based on the idea that in the brain, just before a reward is delivered,
there's an increase in dopamine.
So you're anticipating something happening.
Now, this is interesting, but there's some problems in that dopamine deficient mice have
been able to learn where rewards are in a maze.
Rats that don't produce dopamine have been able to be operatively conditioned to learn
new things.
So maybe it's got something to do with learning, but it obviously doesn't look like it's necessary.
So where most people talk about dopamine in the literature nowadays is around wanting.
or needing or compulsion.
The idea is that dopamine has something to do with
a real magnetic draw or need for something.
Often what's talked about is junkies,
particularly for drugs like meth,
once they take a lot of it, they stop getting pleasure from the drug,
but they feel very compelled to still get the drug,
even though it's an unpleasant experience.
And certainly this is reflected in change in the dopamine system.
So if you're saying your game gives people a shot of dopamine, you're not necessarily saying it's fun or anything worthwhile to them,
just that it's compelling them to play it, which may not be a nice thing to say.
And even if that was the case, it's really not that simple.
If our brains were simple enough for us to understand we would be so simple.
that we couldn't.
This is a nice quote.
It doesn't necessarily mean don't study the brain, of course.
Like, that's silly.
It's more like it's not that simple,
and we need to be careful of simple explanations,
like a shot of dopamine.
These simple explanations are very appealing to a lot of people and there's been a rise
in neuro things in the recent years.
Neuro training, neuro food, neuro exercise, all these things are real things and there's
a lot more of them.
You can pay money and have people do these things.
And the reaction in the neuroscience community as a large has been to declare these neuro
trash.
To say, the brain is more complicated than this and all this stuff is preying on cognitive
biases and preying on people with money.
And I want to ask us here at GDC is why do we care about this?
Why do I hear people talking about neuroscience here?
Well, first of all, science.
Science is cool.
I like science.
I have a PhD.
I think data's really cool.
I think science is amazing.
And I think, look, you can put a piece of broccoli in an
fMRI machine, and it looks fucking awesome.
So it's cool.
Science is cool.
But if we look at a statement like this,
rewards delivered on a variable schedule strongly motivated players
due to activating a complex web of neurons
resulting in various neurotransmitters being released.
Okay.
But this is what we care about, right?
If we're making games, we care that what we can do,
rewards delivered on a variable schedule,
and what the behavioral outcome is, strongly motivated players.
So I really want to say, let's throw away the dopamine shots.
Let's not really care about neuroscience.
Not because it's not important, but because what neuroscience is doing
is it's explaining already known principles.
Neuroscientists want to know the physiology behind these principles
that already exist.
They're often not finding new things other than the physiological pathways,
which are interesting,
but from a practical standpoint, it's not that useful.
So let's get rid of those.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
If you do want to hear me talk about ways you can measure physiology and stuff like
that, look at my Twitter handle, I gave a talk about it a couple of years ago at another
GDC.
But I'm not going to talk about biometrics anymore, I'm going to talk about rewards and
motivation and what we already know.
So I'm going to start off.
by talking about intrinsic and extrinsic motivation.
And this is not because I feel that these theories require
particularly important attention paid to them,
rather that I know that they're very popular in games right now.
Who's heard of intrinsic motivation and extrinsic motivation?
Okay, nearly everybody.
Right, so this idea is a popular theory in games at the moment,
and it's the idea that intrinsic motivation is personal gratification,
intrinsic motivation is to get something from the environment.
Now this is just one model, one theory, and to give you an idea, this was my wall during my PhD.
My PhD was on just one area of human behavior which was driving behavior,
and this was a snapshot in time of every single model or theory I could
find that had been made to explain driver behavior.
And there was ones I didn't have up on this wall.
There was a lot of them.
And there are a lot of them.
And that doesn't mean that they're all worthless or we shouldn't think about them.
But as applied psychologists, which is myself, and working in an applied area like game design,
what we can do, and the advantage of this, is we can look at all these models
and we can find the commonalities between them.
Because if lots of models are agreeing on certain things,
then that's important.
So here's where the models currently agree and it's what I'm going to go over.
You don't need to read it all right now, I'm just letting you know I'm going to step through
these as we go.
And these may sound like the things that fit your model of choice that you may think about
and that's because these models are often explaining the same thing.
like the brain not being so simple, human behavior is not so simple. So try to not be dogmatic about what you're talking about.
So the first is feedback is important. And I want to start with this because feedback is vitally important for rewards.
If you take nothing away from this talk, please have it be that.
If players don't know they got a reward, they can't get it again.
If players don't know why they got a reward, they can't do it again.
And if players don't know the value of a reward,
then they may not care about it.
You can give them all the stuff in the world,
and they're like, eh.
So,
rewards are feedback, fundamentally,
and a lot of feedback can be reward.
And usability and clarity of feedback
is a core component of what we do in user experience work,
which is why I'm here at a UX summit talking about it,
because UX is fundamentally about reward in a lot of ways.
You're a wonderful audience, by the way.
I really mean it.
Paying attention, especially you.
All right.
So if we're going to go back to kind of basics,
we can talk about some learning principles.
We can talk about classical conditioning,
which is linking old responses to new or responding for a reward.
So as an example of this,
seeing this image is probably quite rewarding for a lot of people
because of the activity that's often associated with it.
Hearing the sound, also probably quite rewarding.
And that's because they're often linked together.
And let's stop that.
They're linked together and linked together in a performative way when playing the game
and it gives you progress. So they've been associated, they've become a reward.
Maybe a more practical example of this is in a lot of games
currencies that are used are gold and gems and...
dollar amounts and things like that. And that's because we already have an association with these
as having value. And by using them in a game you don't have to re-establish the value of the reward.
You can use a completely made up space thing as your currency, but you're going to have to
teach players the value of it. By using an established one it lets players immediately
know this is something valuable. And that's why it's so commonly done.
Another example of classical conditioning is if you look at the idle games,
often you get those going and then they kind of run by themselves.
And because we're so used to association, numbers going up,
and feedback like this with progress,
it feels like we're doing something even though that we're not really.
We're just watching a gameplay itself.
So another learning principle we can talk about is operant conditioning.
It's rather than responding to a reward, it's responding for a reward.
You're doing something to get a reward.
So when we talk about operating conditioning, we can go through schedules.
I don't want to spend too much time on this, but it is important.
Fixed ratio is when you have to do a certain number of responses to get the reward.
So turns in a unit, until a unit or building is ready in a turn-based game would be a classic example of this.
You just have to wait and hit that next turn button.
Or clicks in a clicker that doesn't have a critical hit system or anything like that.
You have to click a certain amount of time, then you get enough gold,
and then you can buy your reward and then click some more.
And the reason these are important is if you look at these graphs, you've got the number
of responses up this side and then the time across there, and these are the responses
over time with each tick being a reward.
And what you typically see with a fixed ratio, and this is just one single fixed ratio,
running at a certain length, so maybe you have to press 20 times and then something happens each time,
is that what happens is you get pretty fast responding, then they get the reward and they
stop for a little bit and then they go up. And it's because once you've got the reward you've
got that whole process ahead of you again before you can get to the next one. So it's kind of like a rest.
And the way that these turn-based games work to stop that rest is you always have multiple things going at once, right?
So your building's done, but you've got three other buildings on the way, so you just take one more turn, you get a lot of things going.
Fixed interval, appointment gaming type stuff.
This is an example from Paragon of our jungle minions spawning at set times,
so the players know, be there at this time, kill the minions, get the reward.
The response that this kind of interval of reward produces is like this.
You show up at a set time, respond, and then you go away until that set time.
It's used a lot in mobile games for timers and daily login bonuses,
which is effectively trying to pace out people using the game
and have them coming back at certain times.
Variable ratio is probably the most famous of these.
It's used a lot in gambling.
It leads to reward chasing behavior.
And it is where there's a variable number of responses
until the reward shows up.
So it's not 10.
It might be 10 to 50, something within that range.
And loot drops, like the loot crate system in Paragon,
are example of this.
And critical hits are an example of this,
where you hit a certain amount of times and will do damage.
And the response rate that that tends to get
is high and relatively steady.
The reason it's steady is because it's unsure
when the next critical hits, they will come along.
You want to keep on trying to maximize those critical hits.
There's no like, I've already got it,
and I know I have to work harder
until the next one comes at a certain set point.
The last is variable interval, or event-seeking behavior.
An example of this I found is from Destiny
with their public events.
happen at certain times but around that certain time and may not happen every time.
And it generally encourages people to move into an area and hang around because they don't know
exactly when it's going to happen. And this kind of random world event is a little bit more if you
want to drive people to a zone and then have them wait around for things. It gets a pretty good rate
of responding because you're not sure when when the event's going to occur and people will stick around.
Now of course this is just a diagram I've copied off data from textbooks.
And in a real game, in a lot of cases, you'll be mixing all these schedules together.
They'll be running over top of each other.
But it's kind of interesting to pull them out one by one like this
and look at their kind of fundamental characteristics.
So moving on from those.
We want to talk about reward timing and uncertainty.
Ideally, rewards should come immediately for success mechanisms,
progress mechanisms, and choice mechanisms.
If I make a choice, if I'm succeeding or I'm progressing in your game,
I should know about it straight away, and I should be rewarded straight away.
Now this doesn't necessarily mean we can't have long-term rewards that we're aiming for,
but people are generally not great at long-term rewards.
There's the famous marshmallow test where you give a kid a marshmallow
and say if you wait, I'll come back in a few minutes, you can have two marshmallows,
and you leave the room and the kid just shoves the marshmallow in their face.
And as adults we like to go, ha, children, but actually we're all pretty bad at that.
So if you want people to work to a long-term goal, they need to know there's a long-term
goal and you give short little feedback bursts on the way there.
Progression bars or experience bars are a classic example of this.
They're little bursts of feedback, little bursts of reward to let you know you're making
progress towards a big thing.
Now, I've been talking a lot about, I've just talked about things being immediate rewards.
Of course you can also have unexpected rewards.
And unexpected rewards can be very strongly motivating.
So an example of that would be in a game like Portal 2, you unexpectedly work out a way
to solve the solution.
It feels very satisfying, it's not something you necessarily saw coming, and it can feel
good, right?
Surprise puppy.
But the problem with unexpected rewards is if I, in six slides time, showed this puppy again,
it probably would have less impact.
And if I kept doing it, it would have even less impact.
And even if I mixed up different puppies, you might start to expect the unexpected.
So, unexpected rewards can be really valuable, but they're hard to pull off, and they're hard to pull off repeatedly.
The next thing I want to talk about with feedback is game feel, the way it feels to play your game.
And I want to argue to go back to this idea of intrinsic motivation,
that this is the ultimate in intrinsic motivation.
A lot of companies when they talk about intrinsic motivation will talk about a lot of goal structures
and adding a bunch of stuff on top of the game.
And that can work.
But if you look at the games that are commonly cited, games like Destiny as having great
intrinsic motivation, they're games that just feel satisfying to play.
That the action of just moving a controller or a mouse feels impactful and immersive.
So there's an example of this from Gears of War and it's the active reload mechanic, where
it takes the simple action of just pressing a button.
to reload and makes it into a mini game.
You've got a nice little bit of feedback there, a chance to succeed more or to fail.
Of course, rhythm games like Thumper
heavily rely on having a good game feel in order to succeed because all you're
doing in these games is pressing left, right, up, down
and buttons and rhythm.
It's not that complicated a thing to be doing, really, but by using the rhythmic design and the sounds and the ramping up the difficulty, they can create a very compelling game feel.
It feels satisfying, it feels like it builds, it feels like you're doing an important thing.
I already mentioned Destiny, but Destiny, the developers at Bungie, worked very hard
on making the animations and everything like that feel just really satisfying to reach
out and every action in the game makes it feel like it has impact, even though, say
this melee attack, all you're really doing is pressing a bumper on a controller, but
it feels like you're really reaching out there and hitting your enemies.
And even a simple screen shake, even though it may not be to everyone's taste,
makes this space marine in Space Marine feel like he has weight,
even though all that's happening is pushing forward on a stick.
Feels like he's physically in the world.
This is something we've done in Paragon with several of our heroes,
and I want to just give a brief example of that.
Okay, of course it's exaggerated for the trailer, but Steel's this big android and you can feel
the weight to his moves, the weight to simply moving with him and simply pressing the button
makes it feel satisfying to play even outside of the other structures of the game.
It's six slides by the way.
Alright, moving on. The next thing is progression.
Progression towards clear goals. This is kind of pretty easy stuff.
Progression towards clear goals, whether those are internally set
or externally set by the game, is rewarding and, of course, relies on feedback.
I already mentioned having to give progression feedback for long-term goals.
And typical examples of this would be, this is from Paragon, we have a bunch of things,
weekly quests, your progression in game as you level up and get new abilities in Almoba,
daily victory chests, living up your account progress, all of this is progression and to
show to players that things are happening and that their actions are being rewarded.
Progression is also commonly used in tutorials, or at least tutorials that do
things well.
This is the tutorial from Unreal Tournament.
It's clearly telling the player what to do, to jump.
It's showing a modeling character doing that action,
and the player cannot progress out of that room without doing the action.
They can't leave without jumping over that barrier.
And once they do, they have immediate feedback that it was successful because
they're out of the area.
The interesting thing about the UT tutorial, which I think is a nice element to it, is
it has optional skill tokens in it.
Optional skill tokens are, as the game teaches you, there'll be skill tokens hidden around
the tutorial that kind of build on what you've already learnt.
So if you've learnt jumping and wall running, maybe in the next room, off in the corner
it's not required for you to do, there's a token spinning up there that requires you
to jump and wall run to get it.
You don't have to do it, but it's a way for you to put together what you've previously learned and show your progression.
So this will be an example. This is probably the hardest one in the tutorial. It's pretty difficult to get.
You can't jump over there, so you need to scoop around,
like slide up a wall, jump around and then slide out to get it.
It's pretty difficult, but it's a nice way to show players progress that doesn't also make them feel forced.
Progression can also be shown by a social comparison.
This is the post game screen that was added to Dota 2
a while ago, where it shows, after the game is over,
the progression of each player during the match.
And it lets the players look and rank themselves
within this information and know how well they did
at certain times over the match and hopefully learn from this
or be rewarded by it.
Now, comparison, especially to other players, can open the path to abuse.
So often making it only available after a game,
where players cannot interact with each other is a good idea.
Hiding MMR is a good idea, so people don't attack each other for,
you're on my team and you've got 200 less MMR than me,
so I'm instantly going to think that you're worse off at playing the game,
because your matchmaking rank's lower.
And making stat tracking websites opt-in.
So if you want to see how good I am at Dota
by looking on a stat tracking website,
you can't, because I haven't opted in.
And what's actually been happening recently that's interesting in games is
the idea of comparison within yourself.
So in
Overwatch, for example, at the end of the match, they don't compare you against the
other players, they compare you against your own progression over the game.
So even if you've lost the game, maybe you've got better at something, maybe that
was your best ever game at healing.
or your third best ever game at healing or whatever it might be.
It's some kind of reward that lets you know that you're progressing yourself
but is not potentially a negative comparison against other people.
And Dota's similarly got this thing that shows you your average for the hero over certain metrics.
Okay, so that's feedback. A lot of this other stuff is also feedback
but I'll talk about it in a different way.
Control and choice is important.
So what we're talking about here is feeling in control.
We like to feel like we have choice and control and generally speaking we just like feeling limited,
controlled or out of control.
And there is a slight difference between feeling controlled and feeling out of control.
I hope that you can get, even though they're kind of the same thing.
There's an exception to this, and that's unless we choose to be controlled and limited.
If we choose to cut off paths for ourselves that are presented to us,
making interesting, meaningful choices within the game,
then that can make us feel in control as well.
So the statement like, people don't like feel controlled,
doesn't necessarily mean they don't like feeling limited.
They just like feeling like they have choice in those limitations.
So this is often talked about around story.
And there's different approaches that can be taken here.
You can go crazy like The Witcher 2,
where a whole act of content can be skipped based on a decision by a player.
They completely miss a massive chunk of hours and hours of content
based on a choice.
It makes choices feel very meaningful in the game.
You can also look at performative stories,
where there isn't actually much formal story,
and there's not much choice in a game like Journey,
except for the way that you play out the game
and the way that the story is created around your character.
And then you can look at maybe more traditional structures
of story games, like the original Walking Dead.
where they very successfully created a feeling of choice that was
praised for its feeling of choice.
Even though if you go back and play through the game and make different
decisions you'll find out that actually the choice
doesn't strongly matter to how the game plays out.
There'll be different people that fill in at different times for people you let die
or whatever might happen.
but because it felt like you were making a decision at the time, it feels important.
And this can be contrasted against Mass Effect 3, which came out the same year, and used
a similar structure, but because players had expectations built up over two games beforehand,
and maybe they were more likely to play through more often, players would know, oh, it doesn't
really matter, this character shows up here anyway, and some players were disappointed
by that.
Now, that's not to say that this was fundamentally wrong, it's just I'm trying to make a point
about player expectation about control and how it can be good, but it can also backfire.
It also interacts with activities in progression.
So what I'm talking about here is examples like side activities in open world games.
If the side activities feel forced upon a player, or they feel like they have to do them in order to progress,
or they're being bugged to do a side activity, they may resist doing it. It may feel like control.
Escort quests can also be very controlling, because they're essentially taking away success from the player
and putting it in the hands of the NPC they have to look after, that can get in trouble or die or break stealth.
Modern escort quest type games like Last of Us solve this by making the person you're
escorting not do these behaviors, so they can't break your cover or they can't die.
This of course is a trade-off for immersion, but it's a worthwhile one for the player not
feeling controlled and frustrated.
And then the other one is of course grind.
If players don't feel like the activities they're doing in a game have meaning, are
showing progression, and are meaningful to them.
then they're more likely to view having to make a lot of daggers to level up in Skyrim
as a grinding activity.
And in fact, this idea about control being so important has come up in the recent literature
as a suggestion to replace intrinsic versus extrinsic and to talk about instead autonomous
or controlled behavior.
And internally motivated behavior, if you feel obligated to yourself, can feel controlling
and be demotivating.
Just like external behavior can feel autonomous if there's a lot of choices set up for you.
So this idea of control seems to be a core point where a lot of theories are agreeing.
And I've been saying it's perception of control that matters, and that is the important point.
You can give players an illusion of control and get just as much...
Impact is real control.
So games like P.E.G.O. where you fire into a random zone, but because you pick where
you fire and you have a special skill, can feel like you're more skilled than the game
is actually working on.
And of course match three games can be masters of this.
You have no control over what's about to fall on the screen at all as a player, but because
of the way that the feedback is presented to you, it feels like you made a really weighty
important decision, even though you just like matched one line.
The last, well, one of the last things about control is this interesting idea of counter-control
that came out of behaviorism, it's been around for a while.
And it's typically the idea that when people feel controlled, we often counter to this.
And this is often talked about in a negative way.
If people feel controlled in your game, they feel like it's grindy, they'll stop playing it.
That's how they break the control of your game.
They're like, no, stop, I'm out.
However, it can actually be used as a game mechanic because it feels very rewarding to break control.
So a classic example of this would be the Stanley Parable,
which is a game all about a narrator trying to control you and your attempts to break that control.
And it feels very satisfying to do so, even though you ultimately fail.
So the last thing...
is control and tutorials.
Now, when a lot of people hear this stuff about control
and feeling controlled is negative,
they'll say, okay, we're not gonna put tutorials in
or we're gonna do tutorials
that have no controlling elements and no guidance in them
because it's better for people to learn things.
Now, that can work out, but the problem is
it's feeling in control and not feeling out of control.
Really, big ways to feel out of control is to feel confused and unclear and not know
what the hell is going on.
And so having a little bit of handholding, a little bit of guidance in tutorials,
if it lets your players get to the point where they can feel in control,
like you're telling them what to do and then suddenly they have control
and they can show that control, it can be worth it.
So this idea of control doesn't necessarily mean don't make tutorials.
And of course, that's one of the nice things about the optional skill tokens
in Unreal Tournament, is that there are optional things players can do
to show that they've mastered the mechanics that you're teaching them.
Okay, last thing in control is non-contingent rewards.
These might be known as participation awards.
Who thinks participation awards are a dumb idea?
Not as many people as usual.
Participation awards kind of came out of SDT and the intrinsic model theory.
and there's a reason for that and it's that participation awards which are
awards you get for just showing up are less likely to be seen as controlling
which we've said is not good and more likely to be unexpected right because
you don't have to do anything to get them they're not based on your
performance of course because they're not based on your performance they're
not really giving you feedback on anything however there are multiple
occasions that they're used in video games so probably the one that the
people have the most negative association with its rubber banding
This was where mechanics in the game like in Mario Kart will help losers equalize with winners.
And it's good for casual games because nobody wants to just be beaten over and over again
if they're supposed to be just having fun with their kids or family.
Another example from more hardcore games is gold drips in MOBAs.
As long as you're playing a game of a MOBA, there's just some constant resource coming
to you, no matter how well you're doing, that might let you buy that one item you needed
to win the team fight and come back in a situation you were otherwise losing.
A similar example in Titanfall 2 is the Titan drop.
progression which like a gold drop in a MOBA was just constantly coming in in Titanfall 2.
So even if you're getting beaten and not performing very well,
you probably still got to use your Titan and experience that part of the game
and get that reward during a match.
So that's what these non-contingent rewards can be quite useful for is this kind of balance
and making sure people experience more of your game.
You're a really wonderful audience by the way.
Okay, so I'm not going to do a bunch of slides about this one, in fact this is the ODee slide,
but not getting a reward you expect can make a reward a penalty.
So this is the idea that if you build something up as really big and important,
like players go around and they pick up every single consumable and collectible in your entire game
and they get nothing for it,
this can feel like a bad thing if they were expecting something to come out at the end.
The next is that task inherent rewards motivate more than task relevant.
Or to put that more simply and basically,
rewards that are meaningful to a player are more motivating.
A classic example of this would be the agility orbs from the Xbox game Crackdown.
These orbs, you had to show agility in order to get them.
You had to climb up buildings, jump, and generally show that...
you had agility and power in your character, but by collecting them
you also increased your agility. So they had meaning in two ways to players.
You showed competence in this to get them and then you're awarded by
being able to do more of this, you got the progression of being able to do that.
And one way you can do this in games is to personalize if you can, if you have
data on what people are already doing in your game you can reward them in ways
that you know
will be rewarding to them because it's the type of thing they're already
interested in.
but you don't have to go that far. All you really have to do is show value.
And when I was working as a consultant, this was often a problem we would see
in mobile games that would come to us, is in the tutorials
they would throw all their awards at the players. They would say,
here's premium currency, here's this, skip this timer, all these things.
And it was like, here's all the things, but we're not telling you why or what
the meaning or what the value is. We're going to get you to skip a 30-second
tutorial.
Like, why is that important to somebody?
And it doesn't, it hurts people's learning
and it hurts the evaluation of the reward
if the reward is not meaningful.
Okay, interacting with others positively is motivating.
And when I say positively, it's positive
for at least one person in the equation.
So if I beat someone at a game,
it may not be positive for them, but it's positive for me.
So, when you're interacting with others,
you can do performance comparison.
you can compare your performance against other people.
And this is potentially rewarding if it's in our favor.
It's also potentially motivating if it shows progress
or changes expectations positively.
So even if it's not in our favor, but it shows we made progress
or it changes our expectations,
like we did better than we thought we would, that can be good.
But of course, it can be demotivating if it's against us
or if it changes our expectations negatively.
And I'm going to give you an example of this.
It's not necessarily a reward example.
But in Dota, they have these conduct summaries.
They'll show you about your behavior in terms of how you've been reported by other players.
This is a report of a negative player.
They've got six reports and they're being told that 94% of the population, their report
rate is higher than 94% of the population.
So the idea is you're supposed to go, oh no, I must be a really bad person and it's not
normal to do this and I'm supposed to change my behavior.
Now this is a conduct summary of a nice person, it's me, who's got less than three reports
when this popped up.
And they're being told that only 77% of players have three reports.
Well, 77% of players have less than three reports.
But you might view that as, okay, that's good.
But it could also be telling you that over 20% of people
have more than three reports.
Maybe I don't need to be so nice.
And certainly in research where they've shown people
in neighborhoods energy use, where you get to see,
hey, your neighbor's using more energy than you are,
but congratulations, you don't use much energy.
The people that are being told they don't use much
start using more, because they're like,
well, everyone else is doing it.
So you gotta be careful when presenting this information.
Now competition is a social interaction that comes naturally to game designers, I think.
Quite often we think about it nearly straight away.
And it's a strongly motivating force, especially if you think you can win.
And it does have a potentially slight demotivational effect immediately after winning.
And that's often because competitions are often in a fixed ratio or fixed interval.
They only run at set times or only for a set period.
And so after you've won, often people kind of take a breath and then start competing again.
It's just something to be aware of to keep people motivated between events of winning.
Of course, the downside of competition is it can demotivate those who think they can't win
or know they can't win.
So in a mobile game, if you load in and it tells you you're 31st thousandth in the world
at this game when you first started playing it, that might be really demotivating to you.
Unless of course you make a lot of progression quickly.
So one way to get around that is to put people in local leagues where they can actually see
progression.
It's also, I'm being hard on competition here maybe, and it's because I think as game developers
we often don't think about the losers in our games and how we can make losing a pleasant
experience.
An experience that we can let people learn from and come back from and feel like they
can stay engaged with our game and don't just go, well this is over, I'm going to stop playing.
Cooperation, on the other hand, compared to competition, is a very powerfully motivating
factor for a lot of people.
And that's because it allows everyone to contribute to it.
Nearly every top game you can think of nowadays has some kind of cooperation element in it.
Cooperation, according to psychological research, motivates people a lot more than competition,
which has been shown to...
Competition has been shown to do things like suppress creativity, cause conflict, all these
kind of things.
And it does allow for cooperative competition where guilds can compete against each other.
And this gets you kind of the best of both worlds.
You've got the competition stuff but you've also got the cooperation between people.
It allows for repossessity, which I can never say, but it's basically the idea that people
feel like, oh, someone's being nice to me, so I'll be nice to them.
A monetization example of this is in Game of War, Fire Age, which is anyone in your
guild spends in the game, it benefits everyone in the guild.
So this is a monetization application of it, in that by spending within this game, it benefits
everybody.
and that's one of the things I want to talk about here with that's kind of the idea of
positive externalities which is a economics term that is by spending in an economy I don't
just benefit myself I benefit everyone else around me and this can be a very powerful
motivating force because while it's not a selfish competitive force it says
By me contributing to this game, I'm part of something bigger.
I'm helping other people. I'm helping friends.
And also, if I've already spent as much as I want to help myself,
I can continue to spend to help other people and feel like a good person.
There's an example of this in Paragon.
And this is our master challenge system,
where by buying into these master challenges,
you get an experience boost that goes up the more you play.
And the more people that have these experience boosts
on your side when you're playing,
the faster everyone's experience goes outside of the game.
So the idea is by purchasing this,
you're not just helping yourself, you're helping others.
All right, so last one on this big, long list.
And that's that rewards can, in certain situations, be demotivating.
I've already tried to call this out where it comes up,
in terms of if they're felt to be too controlling
or they're against expectations, things like that.
Now, before I finish up,
I do want to just briefly talk about some cognitive biases,
and only a couple of them that I feel can be important
when it comes to reward.
One of them is the representativeness heuristic.
And this is the idea that the more time, cost, effort you put into an activity,
there's a basic expectation that you get more reward for it.
So imagine you're a relatively tough fighter in an RPG game,
and you encounter an unconscious goblin,
and you knock it out and kill it.
You probably don't expect to get much reward from that.
You haven't put much effort in, you haven't done very much.
But if you fight something like this, you probably expect to get a lot more from beating it.
And this is somewhat common sense, but it can be a problem for games that have a lot of randomness or procedural generation in them.
I've played quite a few roguelikes where I'll go through a room that was really, really difficult
because of the configuration of monsters in there or the way that it was laid out,
and then the room on the other side is just an empty hallway with nothing in it.
And that feels against expectations, against this heuristic, that if I've put effort in,
I expect that effort to be rewarded.
So this can be taken into account with the reward systems also being tied to the randomization
or the proceduralization that comes out at the end.
If it's over a certain amount of difficulty, then there should be more reward for doing it.
This can also apply to monetization.
If people spend more in your game,
they of course expect to get more from it.
So you need to make sure your economy is balanced
to support the people who spend more in your game,
or at least they feel like they're getting more value.
And in fact, some games...
So it's important to go back to this idea of feedback
and making sure that everything's very clear
and the value of buying things is very clear
and the value of the things you can purchase with money
is really clear.
even before you make the purchase.
But some games will also, once you make a certain level of purchase,
they'll, without telling you, modify the odds
of certain good things happening for a little while afterwards.
So the game suddenly is more in your favor after you've spent
perhaps a dark pattern.
Another thing with this is after a string of bad luck,
we expect the payout.
This is what keeps people gambling.
But it can be something that we can use in games
to reinforce this expectation and make people feel
like your game is fairer and more in line
with what they want.
So an example of this from Destiny would be the Vanguard bonus.
In Destiny when you run strikes you get loot, random loot based on how you play through
the strike, it just pops up.
And the more strikes you run in a row, the higher your Vanguard bonus gets, which increases
your chance to get better stuff, which meets this expectation of the more effort I put
in, the more I get out.
Another example of this is non-replacing randomness and variable loot rewards like a loot crate.
Once you've got something out once, it's out, and that increases the odds of you getting things that you actually want out of it.
And that feels better to players. It's more in line with what they expect for their increased effort and increased spend.
You also need to make sure you set expectations.
This is another Destiny example.
When Destiny launched, they had the Engram system.
The Engram system shows you...
is kind of random loot you pick up in the world.
And when it launched, the color of the engram was the highest possible reward you could get out of the engram.
Which set the expectation, if I see this, it's got to be an exotic, which is really cool.
But you could hand it in to the Cryptarch, and you'd get a common item out of it.
And people didn't like that very much because it was against what they felt was being represented to them.
So in my understanding what Bungie did is they didn't change the drop tables,
they didn't change the loot or the underlying math of this.
All they did is color the engrams at the lowest possible thing you can get out.
So now you saw a blue ingram, you knew you were going to get at least a blue item out of it,
but maybe you got a surprise and got an exotic.
So it's important to be aware of what expectations you're setting up for your players with the reward systems.
The final bias I want to talk about is the idea of loss aversion.
This is simply state that players will often work harder to keep something they have
than to get something they could gain.
So maybe a complicated example of this could be...
If you're designing a MOBA and you want people to attack towers,
you want to encourage them to stop playing defensive and get out there and attack,
one thing you could consider doing is lowering the hit points of enemy towers,
making them easier to take down and attack.
You can achieve your attack more easily.
And that might work.
Or, what might happen is people might work that out and they might start playing even
more defensive because people view that tower as something that they own and they control.
And even though now it's easier to go out and gain, it's also easier to lose and people
will often work harder to keep something they have.
Other examples from games will be continuous login bonuses where if you don't login every
day you lose progression.
Of course...
That can be a very negative thing if you actually hit that not logging in on the day.
So sometimes you can buy that progression back or sometimes games don't use a continuous login bonus.
You just get an increasing bonus every time you open it rather than it being continuous.
Consumables and durability. People often hoard things like potions and consumables.
Because of this reason we don't like spending something that's going to go away.
So you need to make sure that the base rate and the drop rate of these things
is good enough that maybe...
people will use it or you really demonstrate the value of doing so.
And paying to continue is a classic example of this,
you're paying to keep the progression that you have.
Alright, so I just want to summarize the points I've gone over today.
It's not everything about reward, but it's what I feel
there's a lot of agreement in the literature.
First of all, what I talked about with dopamine at the start,
I really hope that you can be skeptical of any simple expectations, whether they be neuro
or not.
Shots of dopamine are not needed.
There's practical answers out there if you look for them already.
They don't have to be the newest and hottest things.
There's a whole load of research, and there's more that you can find.
To go over what I've gone over today, reward is feedback.
Please do provide feedback on rewards as close to the behaviors
you want to reward as possible.
For long-term rewards, this can be progression towards them.
Mix certain guaranteed rewards with rewards that feel more random
and unexpected to get different types of behaviors,
to get different kinds of response rates.
Control and value. Help players feel in control.
This does not mean not guiding them or teaching them,
but help them be able to access your game
and get at the rewards and not feel controlled by those rewards.
And show the value of the rewards and behavior,
which can often be a good way to reduce control.
When we talk about social rewards,
comparison, competition and cooperation can motivate,
but they do come with risks.
Really, try and think about the players in your games that are losing out on your competitions,
or not coming in first place, or consistently not showing any performance increases.
By giving these players some way to stay motivated, some way to still feel in control, to feel
like they can progress, you can keep them in your game and keep them retained.
Social pressure and cooperation to do things like give gifts to other players or work together,
it can be good.
If it's presented wrong, it can also feel like control,
which may cause people to abandon it.
And you should set and meet player expectations.
Try and understand what these expectations that you're setting up
may be unintentionally,
and at least meet them, if not exceed them.
And preventing loss can motivate more than working for gain.
Okay, thank you very much, and any questions?
If you have questions, please come up to the mic.
And you can contact me at these addresses down here.
Hi, thanks so much for the talk.
So in a lot of, especially casual and mobile games,
there seems to be an order of how these things are unrolled.
Like early on, there's more simple rewards
and like a variable schedule.
And then only later do you get things like social rewards.
Is there actually like a hierarchy,
or is that just kind of convention?
Do you think these kind of roll into each other?
I think there's a hierarchy in terms of the cost to the developers in some ways.
You don't want people getting into social too early in some cases because that might
be more load for you.
You want to make sure that they're engaged with your game first and a good way to that
is to show the value and roll out these more simple rewards early on and show them.
kind of the fundamental nature of your game and why they might
want to have this value of working with others, right?
Rather than just forcing working with others on them before they understand
what the potential of doing that is.
I think that could be what some developers are thinking.
There's not really a formal hierarchy to it, but I think it could be around this,
you know, get people into the game, show them the value and make sure that they
Engage with these later systems that might be a bit more
Ask a bit more more of them in terms of how much they time they're giving up or how much if it they have to
put in
Thank you, that was very interesting talk, thank you so many of the free-to-play games rely on
Boosters and power-ups to win levels
I wonder if you have any insights on when using these boosters and power-ups you have less or more reward mm-hmm
so I think
One interesting trend I've seen in free-to-play mobile games that use boosters and rewards,
which are consumables, which people can be kind of averse to using,
is to, instead of having them as things you collect and then they go away,
they have them, the last one of them goes on a timer.
So it's not gone, you've used it, but it's going to come back in a certain amount of time.
And by having it on a timer, which means it's not a permanent loss,
that can help people be more motivated to try them out, see the value of them
and keep using them a little bit more than perhaps they would.
But I've also, I've experienced doing UX tests on mobile games that people don't
like consumables very much and this is one way to overcome it.
Hi, as somebody else who plays Dota 2, I love Dota.
But for people my age, it's kind of this learning curve is so steep.
So like I was wondering, there aren't, the rewards for Dota are consistent.
So do you think for
like new players if they offered, I don't know, more rewards or like different rewards,
do you think that would help bring more players to Dota 2?
So I think the thing with Dota and other MOBAs is the thing about, while they have this really
complicated learning curve to become good at them.
They're actually not that complicated to throw yourself into and compared to an RTS where
you had to control a lot of units and all this economy, all you're doing is controlling
this one unit and clicking on things and you can kind of do that pretty fast and each game
of a MOBA is this nice progression loop where it's an even playing ground and you're cooperating
with a bunch of people in a competition so it has a lot of these other elements and I
think those are what's the really rewarding things about MOBAs and have made them so...
popular, even without the need for a bunch of external rewards or
extra things on top of it.
You had a question. If you have a collectible game
where people are opening booster packs to get rewarded a lot of times,
I've noticed that sometimes opening the 50th booster pack, it's not quite
as fun as the first one. So a question for you would be, do you have any strategies
or recommendations for exploring rewarding players, whether in booster
packs or related to booster packs?
that can continue to be motivating even during deep monetization?
Right. So I would say the way to address that is to maybe talk to players
and work out why it's maybe not so motivating.
And it could be just there's no value in it anymore.
Like I've got all the things I need or I've realized that the things I actually want
have so little value or so little chance of coming out that it's not worth me trying.
And if those cases you maybe you can play with the underlying rates
once people open a certain amount then you make certain things more likely.
there's adding new content.
But ways to demonstrate that value to the players
is important to keep them engaged, I feel.
Awesome, thank you.
Hi. So using Overwatch as a case example,
when it was in beta,
one of the complaints I heard from people I was playing with
was that there was no metagame progression,
which is something they did add when the game launched.
Do you think that's something that is necessary
to keep people interested, or is that an easy way out?
I don't know.
Certainly progression is important and if people were feeling
like there was no metagame progression and that's the feedback
that was coming in and that's what they're getting,
then I would understand doing it.
It's not something you necessarily need
if your core game is compelling enough, but it can certainly add on.
But I'm not familiar enough with that case, unfortunately.
Hi, yeah, when you talk about setting up player expectations
and making sure that you're meeting them,
what do you think is the right balance between having
a cadence that's so expected that your player sort of maybe
like?
save all their money to only purchase on sale days.
And now they're so trained that you can't really break them of it.
So what do you think is the right balance of having those expectations, but
still wanting them to have that intuitiveness about purchasing and using?
And if you see them coming down this path that you don't really want them to be on
where they're so trained,
how do you break that without making them feel cheated?
Right.
So that's going to be different on a case-by-case basis.
But generally speaking, you can try and cut off that
by mixing different kind of schedules so it's not always...
Like, what's important is that players' expectations are met
and they feel like there are certain rewards coming,
but you can still use randomness or still use variable schedules
so they don't know exactly when it comes,
so it's not completely predictable.
It's just be aware that if you have built an expectation and don't deliver on it, that can be a problem.
But certainly what you're saying where because players have built such a strong habit,
maybe all the fun's gone out of it can certainly be a problem,
and I would say just mix it up to get around that.
Do you know any examples of games that you see that's done this successfully?
In some of our games we have a daily log in reward and we might have changed that to be like a collect wheel.
So the expected value is lower but maybe we think they won't notice that or something.
But then the players who are the core players, they do notice based on the feel.
Do you have any stories of...
So I think that's an interesting trade-off because it's hard when you're designing a game
because you're designing for most players who will be satisfiers.
They don't really understand the core base levels of all the probabilities.
They don't really care. They just want to play a game.
And that kind of thing will work for them, but your really hardcore players are optimizers.
They look up the tables and they work out the odds and everything like that.
And certainly the idea of adding a random reward as a daily is on a base level kind of a good one
because it's moving to this more variable schedule.
But I don't know off the top of my head an example of a game that's got over that.
I would just say,
you need to think about when you are designing your rewards,
that somebody's gonna work out the base rates for it,
and how upset are you gonna be when they do that.
Do you feel it will demotivate them if they know the base rates?
And if the answer to that is yes,
then maybe you need to reconsider your base rates.
Or you need to say,
they're gonna be such a small amount of the population,
we don't care if they get demotivated.
It will be a trade off there.
OK.
All right.
Thanks.
Hi.
Do you have any particular framework
you kind of use when you're designing rewards?
Or do you kind of just, because you're a PhD,
you know everything?
Like, what are you used to help you when you're coming up with?
I mean.
Basically the list I had is where I feel like the research comes together.
It's like try and think about all these things when you're designing your reward system
and think about how you're hitting the different parts of them
and is there a good clarity and all that kind of thing.
Fair enough. Thank you.
So you gave some cool examples and some counter examples.
I'm wondering in your opinion what's the biggest sin?
Like where has the dopamine naive theory or naive...
like incorrect model being misapplied widely in gaming.
Like if you could wave your wand and fix.
For me personally, and I don't know if this is the biggest problem, I think it's that
point of,
okay thank you, of a lot of game developers don't think of losers.
And if your competition is
fair, usually that means people losing fifty percent of the time in your game.
And there's often, we like to think about winners because we like to think of ourselves as winners
and winning is already rewarding in itself but we also like to throw a bunch of rewards and
celebrations and everything on top of it and often our losing screens are kind of like heart you lost
and then that's it and we don't allow for our players to still feel engaged with our games
at that point so I think that that is something at least on my personal level I think that could
be improved. Thank you.
All right, I think that's it.
Thank you very much.