In the arms of the angel,
Far away from here,
From this dark, cold hotel room,
And the endlessness that you fear,
You are pulled from the wreckage.
of your silent reverie.
Here in the arms of the angel,
may you find
some comfort.
Hi, I'm Sarah McLachlan. Will you be an angel for a helpless artist?
Every day, innocent artists are abused, beaten, and neglected.
And they're crying out for help.
Please join us at the Technical Artist Boot Camp at GDC 2017.
For just a pass to GDC.
Only 60 cents a day, you'll help rescue artists from their abusers and provide support with
VR projects, procedural content generation, simulations, advanced shader techniques, and
tech art and academia and love.