Hi, I'm John Manning, and at the Independent Game Summit at GDC 2017, I'm going to be talking
about how we made the development process for Night in the Woods better through open
sourcing part of the game's code.
Almost every game in development makes use of some kind of open source code.
It's freely available, and it solves a problem.
However, while many projects are consumers of code, it's rarer to see a game release
code.
The best reason for releasing is that, when done right, you can leverage the skills of
volunteers who contribute back, and make your production easier.
In this talk, we'll discuss how Night in the Woods open-sourced Yarn, its dialogue engine,
and how randoms on the internet took it, improved it way beyond the original feature set, and
made more things possible for both the original development team and for many new projects.
We'll also discuss how to choose what parts of your code to release, how to release code
in a way that encourages others to contribute, how to manage an open-source project to get
the most out of community contributions, and how to minimize the overhead that's involved.
I look forward to seeing you there.