First of all, thanks a lot for coming along to my talk.
Thanks once again to Lee Petty for the opportunity
to come here and speak at GDC,
talk about some stuff that I've learned.
Don't forget to fill out the questionnaire at the end
and remember to silence your phones.
Okay, so just over two years ago, I got into photography
and that journey has been something that,
it's been like one of the biggest learning experiences
for me.
one to help me kind of grow as an artist,
one to help me get out of my comfort zone.
And in that process, I learned about art,
about art direction, the technical side,
and also things like marketing.
And I really became curious how far I could push that.
And that's kind of what I'm gonna talk about today.
When I think back to when I was a kid,
I was 10 years old, and I really wanted to be a game designer.
and my favorite game was Commandos Behind Enemy Lines
and I wanted to work for Eidos,
I would have killed someone for a job there.
I wanted to live on the moon
and I think I had like at least have a futuristic sports car
which is pretty ambitious.
But by 18, like that dream was just gone and dead
and I really didn't know what I wanted to do.
So I had this kind of high school report
that basically said I was struggling in class
and like I was just super quiet.
And so I took a year after high school
because I really didn't know what I wanted to do.
I felt kind of lost,
and it turned to video games as a way to escape.
And so I played like so much World of Warcraft,
and it really helped build my confidence in a weird way.
It taught me about communication, teamwork, and leadership.
And I would lead, my words,
I would lead raids of like 40 people
and sitting in my bedroom when in reality
I couldn't even talk to someone face to face.
So slowly over that year that I took out,
it helped me build my confidence.
And since then, and even now,
these are the three things that have helped me
get out of my comfort zone.
The first is learning something new.
The second is putting myself out there.
And the third point is surrounding myself with talent.
And these are the things that helped me
land my job at Ubisoft.
And when I joined, I was the youngest director, age 25.
And what I focus on in my day job is visual identity.
So my job is to kind of interpret what game is
and translate that into visuals
so that they're unique, memorable, identifiable.
So essentially branding the games,
creating the logos, motion graphics,
anything that relates to the style.
And so I knew that at the time,
like throughout my career in the kind of year by year,
I've just slowly been trying to push myself
out of my comfort zone.
This is my third GDC talk.
And to do that, I knew I had to like
put myself in the deep end.
And when we learn something new,
it's incredibly daunting.
We don't know anything when we start.
And it's, sorry one sec,
artistically, creatively, we try and think of things
that can help push us forward.
So for me, that one thing that I'll talk about today
is my photography.
So believe it or not, these are actually the first photographs I ever shared online.
It was kind of funny because it's the thing I love about photography.
We take pictures of stuff we care about. I just happen to love dogs.
And when I started taking pictures on my iPhone and when I started to travel,
I moved from Scotland, then to England, and then to Canada.
I would start to travel a lot and I never really left my hometown.
So I started to just take pictures on my iPhone.
Never really shared them and I kept a private Instagram where I think
I had like 10 people, I think one of them's here.
So a very small audience and that's because I just felt this fear,
these anxieties of like, well you know,
they're not like great photos, they're not anything special.
And, but I was like, spending my life
and enjoying it. And so everywhere I'd go,
the biggest learning experience was understanding.
how the architecture, just how the cities in general
had like different moods and different vibes.
So I'd go to places like LA for E3, do press stuff.
And yeah, just a huge, important learning experience.
And as I got more and more into learning stuff,
all of my shots on my iPhone,
I would just take my iPhone everywhere
and every day I would just start taking pictures.
And the more and more I learned,
the more and more I wanted to get better at it.
So I started to think about composition, symmetry,
just trying to find nice visual shapes in architecture
or things that I'd seen.
And I just got really addicted to it.
But at some point I hit a plateau,
because I'm an iPhone and I can only ever take a picture
of what's in front of me.
And I wanted to push that further,
so I ended up leveling up.
And so after I finished up a game at work,
I saved up for a little vacation to Tokyo.
And I bought myself a DSLR because I found myself
getting more serious about what I wanted to learn
and maybe the artistic stuff
that I could learn along the way.
That's where I was like, you know,
how far can I really push this?
And in the end, like I learned so much
about just art direction in general.
One of the first learnings I thought was,
when I think back to when I was a kid,
I just, I would freeze up when people were behind me
when I was drawing.
When I was at university,
I would just like minimize all of my windows
because I was ashamed of the art that I was creating.
And it was really photography that pulled me out of that.
So the question I would ask is,
we spend so much time on our art,
whether it's a game or maybe it's your music,
any of this stuff, and how much time do we actually spend
making sure that people see it?
Because to me, at the end of the day,
it's about creating art that connects with people,
and we get to share our vision and the stuff we care about.
And it wasn't really until I captured this one image that I...
my mentality changed, because every picture
that I'd taken before was merely just like
documenting places I'd seen, stuff I'd ate,
dogs that I saw, and I put this on my personal Facebook
account, and I had like, I don't know how many friends,
a hundred friends, five of them were like,
hey, that's a pretty cool shot,
you should take more pictures, and it really helped me
like, break out of that comfort zone.
And so from there it was like, it's a real turning point.
So there's this taxi driver in Shinjuku in Tokyo,
just happened to take the picture,
the composition's there,
the guy's face just happens to be lit correctly,
and I was like, you know what,
I'm gonna go out every day after that, every night,
and try and find these moments.
And so each day I had left of my vacation,
I just went out and I took different pictures
and I would post them on my Facebook.
And at some point I started to think like,
oh, okay, maybe I can...
branch out a little bit, go a bit further
out of my comfort zone.
All the while, like, realizing that I was taking pictures
of stuff like signage, typography,
the stuff that I was used to dealing with
on a day-to-day basis.
And then, this image stood out in particular,
and I sent it off to Smithsonian's Photo Competition,
and it became a finalist, 2016.
And so two years on, when I look back at this image,
all I can see are the flaws.
So it's that idea of progress.
You know, I go from just taking regular pictures
to suddenly, like, ah, photography's really something
that's driving me.
The funny thing is, I shot this picture in auto
because I didn't know how to use my camera,
even though it was a pretty good DSLR.
And I shot the image in JPEG instead of RAW
because I really didn't know my camera.
I literally got it the week before.
The man's out of focus, there's blurring in the image,
the composition's slightly off.
And it was actually, my first GDC talk was March,
so like 2016, and I just came back,
I did my first talk, and I felt kind of like,
I don't know, like a little bit of a buzz,
and so I was like, you know what,
I'm gonna put my work out there,
because I spoke to people randomly.
At this point, no one had seen my stuff,
and so I sent it off to Kotaku,
just because people encouraged me to do that.
And one of the biggest learnings I think about
in my day job, actually, what I focus on
is really marketing art, or like something
that's gonna summarize what a game is
so people remember it and it's identifiable.
One of the key points I would give off to someone
would be to create a press release.
As artists, developers, whatnot,
we already have this body of work
that we're just kind of sitting on,
and I go into that mentality of just like,
why not just put it out there?
So gather like five or 10 images of the stuff you have,
write a little bio about yourself,
and a little description about what the work is,
and include your links.
Best case scenario, someone is gonna share that,
and it's gonna go further than your own network.
Worst case scenario, nobody replies,
but you already have that work,
so you just send off the email and see where it goes.
And then it went online, and over that period of the year,
went up on all these websites.
Which is crazy because it was just a vacation picture that I took that kind of inspired me to keep taking more and more.
And so at this point, I did my vacation, whatever, went back to my day job and I wanted to get better at photography.
So I started taking photos every day, slowly and surely, learning more about how to operate the camera, learning more about the technical side.
If I was at work, I'd go out on my lunch break
and just go with other people who were photographers.
They would teach me all of the different ins and outs
of how the camera functioned.
On my weekends, I would go out at night
and just practice, practice, practice.
Even when it comes to events like this,
I'll message people and say,
hey, does anyone wanna go take pictures?
So I set myself little mini tasks to make it manageable.
Maybe it was how to capture movement, how to freeze time,
how to get closer to subjects,
because as someone who's kind of awkward,
I just never did it.
And to do that, I knew I needed to level up my gear,
so I reached out to Canon, and they were able to loan me
a bunch of different stuff.
So I thought about the areas I was lacking,
and just so that I could become more comfortable
with those kind of things.
And I keep training my eye, like simple shapes,
symmetry, that kind of thing.
And at some point I realized I had all of this knowledge
that I already had within my comfort zone,
which was directing style guides,
being able to do different styles
for different games or products,
and I wanted to apply that to my photography.
So I looked back at the things I was inspired by,
whether it was Akira, Ghost in the Shell,
Blade Runner, Enter the Void,
and at the time I'd never really seen photography
pushed to that kind of level,
because it was the point where I saw my photography
less like documenting stuff and more like art.
So leaning on my skills in graphic design style guides,
I thought about the use of color, composition, content,
in a way to make it consistent, to be distinctive,
and so that people would remember it.
And so I'd have more and more pictures where,
I was thinking about silhouettes, composition.
The thing about photography is talking about patience,
like waiting for the right shot.
Randomly these two people happen to go by,
and they're like 50-50 split right down the middle,
the guy and the girl, the umbrellas,
and I was like, there was this kind of stuff
that was just driving me.
Other times I'd get a bit more creative
because I was learning about the technical side
and I would get flashes with gels
and I would just place them in the streets
and kind of wait at the end and take the shot.
Almost like setting up my own little fashion shoot
on the street, which I never really,
I don't think people do that.
So other times I'll just capture moments
thinking about my composition,
nice clean lines and whatnot.
And so these are just images and images.
So then, at some point I started just tagging
different musicians or directors,
songs I was inspired by, and through that,
I was able to kind of, I don't know,
share my work and have people who like the stuff
I was into also get behind it.
Things like, if you think about art direction,
we think about choosing the right silhouette,
even if it was doing logos or it was doing concept art,
I was able to kind of look through all my thumbnails
and figure out what was it about the image
would work.
And I posted the image on the right,
and I actually took about 2,000 different images
on the first half to get to this one image.
And I cropped out the stuff that was maybe
not in the same fantasy of like cyberpunk
or these kind of saturated visuals,
and I darkened down the silhouette
because I studied a lot of Roger Dean,
not Roger Dean, Roger Dean's sci-fi,
Blade Runner stuff.
And I was able to turn a camera around and readjust myself,
reposition myself, whilst learning
all of these new skills.
And then at some point, I started to just play with color,
play with mood, realizing that I was capturing some moments that
were kind of isolated and whatnot.
I'd bring in the audio to link the people,
and then I would also just think about what
it was I wanted to communicate, using color to do that.
And this is all the stuff that I was doing in my day job.
So again, I was randomly in Tokyo
and I saw this place just outside of Tokyo,
which was, it just looked like Midgar from Final Fantasy VII,
and I posted on Twitter, and then a bunch
of Final Fantasy fans and stuff looked at it.
And so all the while remembering
that I never really put my stuff out there,
and suddenly I have this confidence,
slowly by slowly, to kind of level it up.
And this was one of the more recent pictures I posted.
And actually at the time, I looked at classic Blade Runner.
I was trying to deconstruct what they did
with their color palette.
And there was one shot in particular
that I kind of wanted to match the feel of.
And so going from like,
I want to learn a new skill to,
here's putting my stuff out there, bringing me out,
being able to share my work.
One of the things I realized that held me back was,
all of the stuff I wanted to learn.
And being able to get to that stage,
I knew that the only way to do it
was to surround myself with people who knew it best.
And so, again, I just wanted to see
how far I could take that.
And I started reaching out to different people
because really what I wanted to learn about was portraiture.
When you do street photography, it's quite like a,
you know, it's like just me by myself,
often at night or whatnot, going around by myself.
And the thing I always struggled with was confidence,
like face-to-face communication,
especially the anxiety that I would feel
of just meeting somebody new for the first time.
And so I sent off all these different emails
ahead of the next trips that I'd planned,
whether it was LA or San Francisco or Vegas, Tokyo.
And I had a lot of people reply.
And so yeah, I was able to learn from these people
because they'd been in situations
where they were already used to posing
and I never had to worry about that.
I could see how makeup artists worked.
I could see how they held themselves for different shoots.
all whilst knowing that I'd never really done that.
These are actually, I never shot pictures of people at all
before, maybe my nephew at his birthday.
But suddenly I just had this confidence
and I accepted the nervousness of like, you know what,
I have nothing to lose,
so I would just reach out to different people.
On the bottom right, you see my message.
I go like, love your work.
If you're ever in Montreal, let me know.
Here's my link.
Nothing more than that.
Put it out there, and I think it was that mentality
of like, you know, today, tomorrow.
Nothing in my life's really gonna change,
so I might as well take that step,
almost like tennis, and just serve it.
And so what was cool is I got to meet these people,
and they were really inspiring to me
because these are people that all actually
had some kind of link to video games.
This is a DJ called Danger.
He's actually inspired by one of the things,
the Black Mage in Final Fantasy.
So he has a mask.
French DJ.
And he actually did the soundtrack for Fury,
which is a little indie game.
Great.
The other thing is he's a graphic designer,
so he designs all of his stage graphics.
He designs his logo, all his branding,
handles it all himself.
So I was like meeting these people,
although I had this camera,
it became this kind of device or way
that I was able to just meet people
and hear about their stories.
At some point, one of the biggest J-pop bands reached out.
I noticed they followed me, so then I just sent a message.
And at some point they were like,
hey, you're in LA, why don't we, you take my picture?
I was like, cool.
And this is actually the first shot of people I ever did.
And it's, there's nothing special, but it's, I don't know.
It was that idea that I randomly was in Japan,
like in LA, sorry, and people I'd never met
had to take this picture.
Another person I ended up reaching out to was Ryuhei Kitamura,
and I knew his work from film.
He made the movie Versus, Midnight Meat Train, things like that,
one of the first Japanese films I'd ever seen.
What I didn't know is he actually directed all the cut scenes in Metal Gear Solid.
So from there, I had this skill, I realized I got to know him,
and he mentored me, I think he just kind of helped me out a lot.
And it was actually because of him I got to take pictures of someone else that I'll show later.
There's also a Shima Shirai, she was a climber.
And so I think it's more a point of get is like the fact
that I'm here, I'm at my phone, and I was like,
there must be some opportunities that I can seek and hunt
down just so I can learn more and learn faster,
learn efficiently.
On the right is actually Jessica Vann, who's an actress.
She was actually Hannah in Battlefield 4.
So it was a surreal thing of like, you know,
I'm making all this stuff that I care about.
I'm channeling video games and whatnot.
and meeting people along the way.
At some point, I get the comic artists of,
it's like Spider-Gwen,
and you can see the similarities anyway.
But at some point, I knew I was in LA,
so I reached out to one of the biggest
Spider-Gwen cosplayers,
and it happened to be Hendo,
who has a huge following online.
She actually used to work at Square Enix, I think.
And so when I was meeting these people, I had this kind of these anxieties,
because I get really anxious when I meet somebody
and I didn't know what I would be able to talk about,
how I'd be able to direct them,
how I'd be able to meet the shot that I had in my head
and finding locations, being prepared for it.
Two more points.
Yeah, so as I continue,
just taking pictures of different people,
it was something that,
basically I picked up photography, plateaued,
then I was like, I need to learn something more,
I started to learn the technical side,
start to learn about lighting, consistency and whatnot.
And it was this that kind of led me to
a fashion shoot randomly.
And so I was in Japan at the time,
just on vacation actually,
and I was directing five models.
in the middle of Tokyo and I had seven days to turn it around.
So as someone who kind of works in AAA,
I used to do indie stuff in the past,
but I wasn't used to that quick turnaround.
So it was entirely out of my comfort zone.
Each model was from a different place.
yeah, I had like a brief and had to match it.
And it was a weird thing as a game artist because
I spend so much time just, you know, at my computer or whatnot.
I actually don't go outside that much.
And so this was helping me to kind of just get out there,
put my stuff out there.
And it was a weird thing actually seeing my stuff physically,
which sounds kind of weird to some people.
Whoops.
So yeah.
I guess the craziest thing was like Nigo who's,
he works for Uniqlo and did Bape and stuff like that.
So when I think about, you know,
I was trying to build this talk and originally they said,
why don't you do a talk about your journey in photography?
I was actually trying to think of the stuff
that has really honestly helped me in my journey
and to try and get to where I wanted to go.
So the points that I made were,
first one, like learn something new.
I think.
one of the most important things is to keep learning different skills that can help
impact the stuff that you do so that you can grow as an artist. Number two, put yourself out there.
I think as artists we think about the things that we're scared of. We're scared of if people won't
like stuff, if they won't look at it, if you're honestly just wasting your time, if you won't make
money, all of this stuff. I learned to just forget about all of that, put myself out there in a way
that I was comfortable with, which actually meant not actually speaking to people.
just reaching out.
And I knew that the last point is,
the only way to progress was to actually
be around people who were doing that stuff well.
So I have like one last example.
This to me was like a surreal moment
because at this point I'd been putting my stuff out there
and suddenly I lift up my viewfinder
and it's Hideo Kojima on the other side
and I was just like.
mentally I was like shaking my cameras and stuff,
because I was just like,
I'm not going to get a good shot of this.
Like, it's just not going to happen.
But then I realized that everything, you know,
I'd practiced enough and I was comfortable enough
with the camera, any anxieties I had,
it basically took like 2000 pictures of just like,
I better get something good.
And I knew I wanted to shoot.
So the panic was like lesser than what I thought it was.
And at some point I'm stood in front of him,
it's just him and his office,
and I'm just like, I have no idea what I'm doing.
Like my background is mostly aesthetic pictures,
and I was just like snapping away.
So after a few days of like hanging out,
I was hanging out and I was like,
I need to show him something
because I don't want to make him wait too long
because I don't know.
And I, you can tell actually the anxiety
because I sent a picture of my,
from my phone instead of the high res picture.
Because I was like, I'd rather he doesn't see
what the colors look like and all of this stuff.
I sent him a DM on Twitter and I sent it to Hideo Kojima.
So it was like sneak peek and he's like master of the sneak peeks and stuff.
So I was like, this is probably the most stupid thing I've ever done.
And to make it worse, I see the little blue tick and I'm like,
he's like left me on red.
And it's it only been like six minutes,
but it was like the most stressful six minutes of my life.
And it was funny because as an art director, you know,
being working like five years, nothing.
You're always going to feel these anxieties.
And at some point, they feel less worse
once you kind of get out of your comfort zone.
And he sent me the little thumbs up emoji.
And I was like, phew.
Because I was like, he's not gonna reply.
He's not gonna happen.
Probably just gonna, probably forgot I even existed.
And what was funny is like, you know,
I was inspired by the stuff growing up.
I'm sure a lot of us played Metal Gear Solid.
Some of us might know Snatcher.
It's a Cyberpunk game.
I think it was the first game he ever worked on.
And this was the image.
And I took a bunch of other images.
And so yeah, the point I was making is just,
it's a weird one where I learned a skill,
but I was able to lean on the stuff
that I was comfortable with,
whilst also just being completely out of my element.
And I have one video,
which I felt summarized my feeling.
It's not gonna play the audio.
Great.
into the water than you feel you're capable of being in.
Go a little bit out of your depth.
And when you don't feel that your feet are quite touching the bottom,
you're just about in the right place to do something exciting.
So a cough, yeah, because basically, like,
if you feel safe in the area you're working in,
you need to go a little bit out of your comfort zone,
a little bit out of your depth,
because that's where you're going to make the most interesting stuff.
So sometimes as artists we need to go out of our comfort zone,
pick up a new skill, try a different style,
do a lot of work to kind of slowly chip away at that,
go on a stage, speak at GDC,
things that help us move forward
either a day, a month, a year,
but ultimately things that pushes out our comfort zone.
That's all.
Thank you.
I don't know how I'm doing for time.
I can take questions.
Five minutes.
Feel free to go up to the mic.
Tell me where you're from, what you do.
Hi there.
My name is Brantley McCord.
I'm an instructor over in Indiana at Purdue University
co-instructing while I'm a grad student.
And so where we're at, we mostly try to develop tech
artists, and we're kind of in an awkward position because
we're mainly an engineering school.
So not the best artists, but also not the best programmers
yet, and we're working on that.
But a lot of my students seem to have a reluctance to make
a portfolio because they feel like they need to get their
foot in the door.
good enough for the portfolio to show it first.
Do you think that holds them back
or do you think there is a threshold
that they should get their artwork to first
before they start showing it?
So that's a good question.
I guess the question is like,
yeah, what point do you feel comfortable
with your portfolio enough to share it
and maybe the process it took to make it?
For me, I think it was after university
and again after I realized I wanted to move up.
I dedicated a lot of my time to working on my portfolio
and I think
When you're starting out, one of the most important things is being able to realise what the quality bar is.
Me personally, I would go on LinkedIn, I would find all of the artists that were in the area I wanted to work in,
and I would actually just reach out to them.
And I would say, hey, my name's Liam, I'm just starting out, would I be able to ask you some questions?
And I'd just leave it. I always end with a question in email, I'll keep it brief.
They would reply and they'd give me all of this feedback.
So I think the most important thing is really knowing
where your work is in relation to where it needs to be
so that you can really clearly identify
the parts that you need to grow.
That's what helped me personally.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Good for time.
Okay, thank you so much.
I think there's a room after, but cheers, appreciate it.