What is our job as games educators today?
A common answer to this question is to generate hireability.
It seems like the value of game education
hinges on our ability to integrate
prospective game developers into an existing labor market.
This labor market appears in our institutional meta-narratives
and is often connected to an unchallenged set of best practices.
Scrumming, pitching, jamming, failing early, specializing, polishing portfolios.
In short, we prepare students for a life in which they live for video games
in order to make a living, in which they become hireable.
But lately we start hearing different stories.
Games, as profitable as they are,
are becoming an increasingly unstable industry,
and one that burns out highly talented creatives
at a mind-boggling rate.
Devs in so-called employment relationships
live in the constant fear of being laid off
after the next project if they don't collapse
from burnout before that.
It really starts early.
As a highly productive student in one of my recent classes proudly wrote into their course
resume, to finish my game I had to break up with my significant other.
The student felt they had to ditch a loved one for a BA student video game.
This was happening in a design school, mind you, whose leading faculty pushed really hard
for the artistic and political valency of video games in their curriculum,
an idealism crushed under the tangible dicta of our ability.
Couched in the provisional safety of my own precarious academic niche,
I watch the most talented students buy into and burn out inside this paradigm.
It's a well-documented ritual starting with generous investments into the promise of a
well-paying job.
I see students take out horrendous loans and work multiple jobs to pursue the dream of
becoming a video game rock star.
Due to their passion and hard work,
they land an internship or a junior position,
but most of the time not in the core field of interest.
Example, oh, you're a woman,
you should be our community manager.
A new report by the Higher Education Video Games Alliance,
short HEFCA, suggests that while game dev alumni
have no problem finding a job after university,
their job satisfaction steadily decreases over the years.
This tends to be gendered as well.
Women and LGBT plus folks are more likely to drop out
more quickly.
The reason?
Rampant misogyny and other forms of discrimination,
such as toxic assumptions about unpaid labor,
extra advocacy work, combined with a loss of purpose.
From the perspective of institutional performance ratings,
we're sort of fine with that.
The students were hireable after all.
The problem is that the idea of hireability is based on a 1950s cliché of a secure labour market.
I remember when my nan, who held a lifetime employment under the conditions of a soaring 1950s Austrian economy,
used to ask me,
have you found a position yet?
Or, in an attempt to encourage me a bit more,
you will certainly find a position you like.
What she meant, of course, in either of these cases was lifetime employment
inside a secure and thriving company designed to sustain my mental and physical well-being.
Stable salary, paid vacation and a nice Christmas bonus.
Hireability.
We need to face the facts and start asking other questions,
harder questions,
questions which don't originate in quantification,
such as,
how will students have a stable life
in an industry which doesn't seem to offer one?
How do we ensure our students will thrive
while doing game design for a living?
While game education certainly cannot solve
the problems of neoliberalism in the current gig economy,
It can take this question to heart and formulate strategies
which are more versatile and sustainable in addressing our students' futures.
I think of this challenge in terms of a question
which I ask my students in my mind.
Did my course equip you to define your space in video games culture?
Did you learn skills which actually allowed you to express what you want to express?
Do these skills bring opportunities which enable you to build a sustainable life?
But that's the future.
Back to the now.
In the now we face the serious challenge of how we might go about teaching such skills.
The answer I present in this talk is experimental and rudimentary.
For now, let's call it teaching games that care, or rather the making thereof.
But here's a disclaimer. My idea of games that care is not intended to claim that it can save a structurally broken economy.
It intends to teach students to find new contexts and consumer groups
and be less dependent on existing markets and industry logics.
It is supposed to inspire deep connections to the real world
by encouraging students to work on what they genuinely care about.
I started being interested in this approach.
while writing on my thesis on games and bereavement,
which is now available as a book.
In games and bereavement, I was interested in developing
meaningful ways to represent attachment,
loss, and grief experiences in video games.
This interest was born from the conflict that,
in 2011, when I started this project,
these subjects seemed fundamental to human experience
and absent in games.
The stakes were personal.
When my baby Nico died in 2004,
I found one way of coping with this
by rebuilding my experience in The Sims 2.
I was able to design two young adults
to the liking of my partner and me.
A baby was born through the sanitary animation,
which did nothing to simulate the hard work
that is birth for you.
And at the point at which Nico was supposed to die,
The Sims 2 resisted.
It did not let me represent my experience.
This game about life literally did not support mine.
By disabling the death of babies,
the game symbolically erased the experience
of thousands of other ex-parents like me,
expressing the unspeakableness of our fate
through its mechanics.
Finding mechanics which care, then, seemed crucial to me.
And it seemed like a good idea to do so
by collaborating with students and other bereaved mothers.
Parts of this project were presented at GDC17,
but today it's the first time that I talk
about the didactic side.
Before I continue, I want to note
that teaching grief-based game design
may appear like it's on the extreme end of what
a game design subject can be.
This is because it's such a stigmatized topic.
To many of us, grief is as ordinary and essential as drinking water,
and that's why I chose to work with it.
But I want to encourage you to think of how these teaching methods
I present in this talk might relate to what you find ordinary and essential,
and how you might introduce that into your curriculum.
I also want to note that the methods I used don't come out of the blue, but they have
histories in the plural.
One of these histories is the long-standing tradition of participatory design and a small
recent mapping to game development.
Participatory design, especially in the Scandinavian area,
emerged as a politically motivated methodology,
driven by unions and workers to include end users
in the design process of their future working environments.
In the game development context, the importance of the user
has been emphasized as well, especially
in player-centric design.
One example you see here is Tracy Fullerton's game design
workshop, a classic, which now celebrates its fourth edition.
Congratulations.
In the development process.
It is essential to many studios out there to conduct playtesting in later stages of game development to give feedback on a fully formed concept.
However, participatory game design goes a step further.
It insists on the inclusion of users and experience experts early on in the process.
This can have two advantages.
First, it grounds technology in the world of real players, real people, and their needs.
And secondly, it lets these needs inspire new technologies and new contexts of use.
Participatory game design has been used in various settings around the world,
but there's two examples that have had a particular impact on my work.
These are the Deep Games Lab at Chicago's DePaul University
and the Denmark-based Game Girl Workshop.
The Deep Games Lab teaches design processes
which are built on experiential resonance
between maker and design.
Students are taught how to work with the symbolic language
of people who have gone through difficult yet
common experiences like eating disorders,
depression, or domestic violence.
The explicit goal is to use game design as a way
to foster a deeper understanding of these experiences
rather than designing for quote unquote measurable purpose.
The Game Girl Workshop is one of the earliest Europe-based feminist game-focused initiatives
using a semi-professional all-female setup to guide girls and teenagers through a development
workshop from scratch to finish.
A core pedagogic principle is to increase the girls' self-efficacy in a world basically
designed against them.
It is to encourage their voices, opinions, priorities through game making.
And it does not expect these priorities to align or compete with common game development paradigms.
Game development instead should make space for what is.
By learning from these efforts, my work is part of a wider community spirit,
which desperately needs game development to change.
from rationalized, optimized information processing
to practices of care.
This long but necessary introduction takes me
to the agenda for the rest of this talk.
My ambition is to give you a vertical slice
of some of the detective decisions
that went into the teaching of Jokoi,
which you see here, a game about grief.
I will not go much into detail with the design elements of Jokhoi,
the game that was produced during this course.
Those of you who are interested in it can check it out in my previous GDC talk
or find the game on itch.io, in this site.
Instead I will talk about my teaching methodology
as a case of how care as a development skill
might be introduced into our teaching curricula.
I will start by talking about the context of how the participatory game design was set up and who participated.
Secondly, I'll talk about how to prepare the class, or how I prepared the class,
and how the dialogue between students and participants unfolded and impacted ideation.
Then I moved towards usability testing and the question how to evaluate a game made with and for Grievers.
And each of these steps involved interesting risks and challenges I will reflect on along the way and in a brief final question.
Why care?
About the context of this class.
Our participants were four white women in their 30s who responded to a call
channelled through the Austrian self-help group Regenbogen, which is German for rainbow.
My student team was composed of white, predominantly male, BA game engineering students in their early 20s
who took the course as an elective at the Aalborg University Copenhagen.
The course stretched over a period of three months,
during which the students developed the game Chocoy that I mentioned before.
When it came to the women, their motivations to join this project were political and personal.
On a political level, they shared the hope to create awareness of pregnancy loss
as an ordinary experience worthy of destigmatization.
They had no particular interest in video games,
but they were enthusiastic about the outlook of being included.
On a personal level, the women shared a hope to remember
and celebrate their experience of motherhood, even beyond death.
They expressed this in the way they gave their fetuses names
and spoke of them as children.
For them, keeping in touch with the inner images of their late children was important.
The students took the course mainly to complete their BA course credits and to create an innovative
game with a deep message.
In short, the motivations differed.
My teaching challenge would be to find a way of facilitating a conversation between these groups.
An additional challenge was that the two groups were located in different countries and spoke different languages,
which required cross-cultural mediation techniques.
I found one such technique in an approach called Muse-based Game Design by Rila Khaled.
Rila suggests that dividing the roles in a design team between those who inspire the
muses and those who create can be helpful to structure a participatory design process.
In Rila's words,
Muse-based game design is an experimental, empathic design approach
foregrounding a dialogic artist-muse relationship between a game designer and a player.
Following a user research stage focused on learning about the player,
the designer forms idiosyncratic design constraints inspired by and relating to the player,
which are then used to inspire ideation.
In RILA's original pedagogic setting,
students are the ones conducting this research stage.
But in our intercultural setting,
it was more useful to gather Muse's data beforehand
and provide it in a semi-processed shape
at the beginning of the class.
The data handed to the students included images
and transcribed conversations of a Muse workshop
I carried out prior to the course.
Needless to say, this required a bit of preparation.
So prior to the course, I ran the Muse workshop,
in which the women explored a single question.
What did their relationships to their babies feel like?
They explored this question through an imagination
exercise.
What if they could visit their baby on a planet?
These are the planets.
In response to this question,
the muses created metaphorical images
and eventually mock-ups of their relationships,
informative of their current grief situation.
In other words, they started a process of symbolic modeling,
constructing haptic worlds in which my students engaged
over the course of the semester.
When I went about constructing teaching materials,
I noticed in great horror the risk I had set myself up for with this method.
I could translate and transcribe what had been said and done in the workshop, but would
I be able to honor all the small gestures creating effective bonds between the muses
and myself?
All the small talk, laughs, nods, coffee breaks, and the collective sweating in a hot room
during early July, these were things which contributed to the way the mock-ups were designed.
Would these be lost in translation?
Ironically, the act of writing about experience
erased some of it.
On the other hand, this created some speculative room
for students' engagement with these models.
What mechanics, aesthetics, and dynamics did the mock-ups invoke?
What speculations did they inspire?
And how did the students connect to these worlds?
These were important questions during ideation.
One symbol that drew the students' particular attention
early on was a mock-up we called the cave.
The cave was built by a woman who
defined her setting in an excruciating amount of detail.
The cave was composed of two layers, an inner cave and an outer cave, surrounded by an island.
Inside the cave lived the baby, which had to be nourished by an army of playable characters,
all of them family members and friends.
And the goal of the cave was to make the family live in a spaceship.
But first they needed to collaborate to make the baby grow enough to be left behind safely.
First, there was some collective enthusiasm among the students.
This was clearly a model with mechanics, goals, a setting in place.
If the team succeeded to translate it into a game,
wasn't that a rock-solid way to express authentic grief experience?
The students created a prototype and added features,
multiple playable characters, multi-layer level design,
customizable audio and lighting, lock and key puzzles,
shape-shifting, feeding and holding mechanics,
an atmosphere which conveyed being in an eternal space.
Oh, and what if you could build the spaceship?
The feature list grew and grew and grew,
and so did the doubts as to whether this could possibly
be achieved within the constraint of a three-month project.
At the same time, leaving out the slightest detail from the mock-up,
wouldn't that necessarily mean misrepresenting the women?
This was a good moment to step back a bit and remember the laws and limitations of representation.
According to British media scholar Stuart Hall, representation does not reflect reality, it constructs it.
It is not outside the event, not after the event, but within the event itself. It is constitutive of it.
This means it is virtually impossible to represent truth, not even through engineering.
For my students, this meant learning to embrace their own interpretations of the planet mock-ups.
What did they see and feel and understand about these mock-ups?
What constructed their genuine truth about it?
This insistence on embracing what personally speaks to you
is something I learned from Doris Rusch's work on symbolic game design
in her insightful book, Making Deep Games.
Doris recommends to rely on the developer's personal symbols and associations when creating games about emotional subjects.
I would add that this is especially important in participatory settings.
Rather than overwriting the statement of your partner by trying to represent them truly,
use your own different words to create a genuine response.
Use your broken words.
Remember, being vulnerable is a game development skill.
When taking their own perspective seriously,
the students started identifying symbols in the mockups
that interested them more than others.
They also started seeing blind spots in the women's conversations,
which were essential for understanding their grief.
For instance, the women had taken a perspective of survivorship
rather than grief.
Death was more of an unspoken circumstance,
framing the wish to stay connected to their babies.
To honor this reality, the students decided to model loss
in Jocko's control scheme.
In the game, the player first builds up a connection
between a mother sheep and her lamb
through a shared control, that is the left mouse button.
After the lamb is lost in an earthquake,
the button which used to facilitate childcare
is no longer available.
This is supposed to make players feel a sense of loss
on the physical, on the haptic level of gameplay rituals.
One of the most daunting questions was how to teach suitable methods for evaluating Chalkoi.
I decided to let the students figure it out by themselves first, which led to some exciting frustrations.
For the first iteration of the game, the students decided to conduct usability tests with fellow university colleagues using quantitative questionnaires.
Their main concern was functionality, which they interestingly divided into two parts.
First, did the players know what to do? And secondly, did the players know what to feel?
While the first part returned clear results, the second part,
did the players feel the right thing, produced very messy data.
The playtesters seemed incapable of identifying their emotions by choosing the correct options
in the questionnaire.
This uncertainty confused and frustrated our students.
It took some work to unpack the root of their frustration.
As it turned out, the questionnaire had built on a common myth in effective engineering.
the idea that developers can engineer user emotions by making correct design choices.
In this paradigm, an information unit is triggered in a user when they interact with technology.
This myth is summarized in the brilliant research of Kirsten Boehner and colleagues who write,
in effective computing, affect is often taken to be another kind of information.
Discrete units or states internal to an individual that can be transmitted in a loss-free manner
from people to computational systems and back.
Of course, this is a myth which suits engineers because it translates complex emotion into
quantifiable information units.
But scientifically speaking, there is not much evidence that that's how emotion works.
Instead, what the researchers suggest is that emotion is more like a web of messy interactions
rather than information units.
For my students...
What kind of UX methods were out there to measure emotion as interaction?
Spoilers, very few.
We ended up with a method called cultural probes.
This method was first used in the context of urban design by Bill Gaver and colleagues.
And cultural probes, for those who don't know them, are small activity packs given to users
with the hope for inspirational feedback.
The package is handed over in a little ritual and after that the user engages with the contents
as long as they want and returns them at their own pace.
In most cases, probes are used as a way to establish a connection with unknown research participants.
But in our case, it served as a tool for reconnecting and testing the second iteration of the game with our muses.
The package contained postcards, the game prototype, and a personalized scrapbook.
These materials were supposed to invite the muses
to think about the workshop, the game prototype,
and their mother-child relationship
in their current situation.
On the day the probes were launched,
the disadvantages of this loose method
became relatively clear.
Two of the four muses had to cancel the ritual
and then had technical issues with the game.
Since other probe contents depended on playing the game,
they had to be returned blank.
However, the probes which were returned were of great value for the polishing stage of chocoy.
By now, the students had learned that the muses were supposed to inspire rather than dictate the process,
and the probes offered additional support in crafting an appropriate atmosphere and feel of chocoy.
Overall, what the students had learned from exploring quantitative versus speculative UX methods
was the value of associative ephemeral feedback, which was less quantifiable, but more rich.
So, why care?
The processes, tools, and learnings I've discussed in this talk are in many ways a lesson of care through engineering.
Guiding my students through a development dialogue with Grievers
was a way of confronting some basic myths in video game engineering
and updating them to respect the real world and each other.
It is important that one source of respect
is the respect for one's own vision.
Games that care do not simply care about players
or in-game representations.
They care about those who make them.
They commit to decisions which resonate with and validate creators.
Games that care cannot promise my students to find a stable life inside a troubled economy.
It cannot prevent them from breaking up over a video game course.
It can inspire the choice to develop games they care about.
And this may lay the foundation for a more full, potentially interesting work life.
Months after the end of the project,
one of the participants asked me to present the game
at a self-help group networking event in Vienna.
Strolling through the room,
I noticed a heavy photo album displayed
near the entrance of the group's office.
When casually flipping through the pages,
I stumbled over a section called Our Morning Game,
which contained two photographs from the project.
The images were carefully arranged and glued on this thick, dark blue paper.
And one of them showed a still from the game,
the other one displayed two of the muses looking over my shoulder
as we were playing the game.
I cannot remember having this photo taken.
This photo album reminded me of the real purpose of this course.
By including a group of muses into a BA game development course,
we had incidentally created a memorial technology for them,
which they were both keen on showing off to others
and saving as a cherished memory.
By going through the process of careful engineering,
the students had helped found this entirely new user context
of grief-based development
and contributed to a meaningful dialogue around a stigmatized subject.
My job as a games educator then was to walk with them a bit of the way
and watch them grow into complex, reflective makers of things.
I would like to thank Ida Toft and Simon Nilsson for helping me develop this talk,
and thank you for listening.