Hey, everybody.
This is the first
Game Developers Conference podcast live.
I am Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra, and I'm here with Alyssa.
Hi, I'm Alyssa.
I'm the news editor and associate publisher at Gamasutra, and I'm really weirded out by doing this on video.
It's really weird.
Yeah, yeah, it is. It is weird. We don't usually like we see each other, you know, just like
in meetings and stuff like that. But now I'm it's it's like I'm actually talking to you.
And the art of like face to face conversations is it's rusty for me.
Let's just talk each other through it. Yeah. So so this is actually episode 12 of the podcast.
So that means that's like.
It's like one and we do one a month.
It's like one year.
For a year.
Like this is one year of one year of podcasting.
So let's just let's just do the hey, how's your show going?
It's going great.
I've been very busy.
It's amazing that an online event can kind of capture that same kind of like I'm constantly
behind feeling as the regular GDC does for me.
I'm bad at scheduling, so it's on me, but like it's about the same kind of like heart
rate throughout.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The thing too, though, is that if you're running late for something, it's not like, oh, I'm
in Moscone West and I need to be in South.
You don't have to power log up an escalator.
Yeah, yeah, and then show up at like the session completely like sweaty and stuff.
So although I'm getting a little sweaty from this, you know, but it's the anxiety of podcasting
live podcasting.
We can't edit this.
I don't know.
Right, right.
Yeah, this is edit.
This is edit free.
So if you ever listen to GDC podcast on.
iTunes, Spotify, and YouTube when we feel like it.
Google Play. You can go check us out there. But yeah, you'll find out just how much editing
goes into this. No, we always 100% flawlessly execute our sentences.
Oh yeah, yeah. Sorry. It's always first take. So I'm also noticing this, that there are people
in chat, which I didn't even consider.
that in the Swapcard app.
Hello, everyone.
This is totally a recording.
No, it's not really.
This is actually live.
So hello, everybody in chat.
This is totally new for us.
Thanks for coming on here.
Yeah, I'll try not to look at that too much.
So we actually have an amazing guest here.
Do you think that we should?
We have no GDC announcements to do because GDC is a bomb.
So we can get right to the meat.
No, there's no morning announcements this time.
So we can just, it's like, yeah, we got you here.
The content marketing worked.
Let the content reign.
Let's introduce a guest.
The marketing is done.
And now the content reigns.
OK.
Now here we are.
We do have a guest.
And we're excited.
So I'm going to.
To introduce here.
So you're ready.
No, let's do it live.
OK, our next guest is lead games user researcher at the Able Gamers Charity.
He has a bachelor's in psychology.
I don't have that.
Was a research assistant in the Lever Center for Schizophrenia
at the New York State Psychiatric Institute for six years.
That's a mouthful.
And it sounds prestigious.
He's an advocate for accessibility in the game industry,
and he's led talks, workshops, and consultations
with tech companies that you might have heard of.
Google, Oculus, Avalanche, Activision,
and there's also Microsoft, where he worked.
He did some consulting on the Xbox Adaptive Controller,
which is a super cool thing.
So let's go ahead and bring him on right about.
Now and unmuted, let's welcome Greg Haynes.
That was an intro and a half.
Like, I don't even know what to say after that.
I should just like leave right now.
Thank you so much for that intro. That was great.
Thank you so much for joining us.
That's what we like to do.
All the fanfare right away.
Poppers in the background.
Yeah, yeah. And then just bring the person on and just make them super,
deeper humble. Yes.
Yes. All right.
It goes expanding as we speak.
I know you seem very cocky.
Did we miss any notable achievements?
Anything else you want to kind of brag about a little bit?
I mean, I think you got it outside of my Social Security number.
I think you got my entire history.
Oh yeah, what is that then?
The closing comments, yeah.
All right, so, like, accessibility, that's a topic in games now.
It's a very important one.
You personally, what prompted your interest in game accessibility?
Why are you such a big advocate for that?
Um, that's a really, that's a really interesting question.
Um, I mean, for starters, uh, just coming out of the, uh, the, the
farmer research realm, I really wanted to combine my love for gaming and my
love for psychology and, and helping people essentially find wellbeing
through, um, gaming experiences.
Uh, and, uh, I happened to meet, uh, the, uh, the founder and executive
director, uh, Mark Barlet.
And our director of community, Craig Kaufman,
had a convention a few years ago, and we just hit it off.
And when they were talking to me about game accessibility,
I was like, this is it.
This is the way that I can combine those two loves.
At the end of the day, knowing how important games are to me
and seeing the impact that gaming has made on my life
and the connections I've been able to make,
whether it was content creation or making lifelong friends,
I felt that if there's a community out there that's
unable to experience that for whatever reason,
and I can change that somehow, then it
was my duty and my calling, if you will, to indulge that.
I didn't get into it in your intro, but how long have you been with AbleGamers now?
I've been with AbleGamers since the beginning of 2018.
Since the beginning of 2018. So, two years?
You've done a lot in only a couple years.
I mean, you have to factor in pandemic time too, so it's been roughly 15 years.
Yeah, I'm running up on my pension right now. It's looking good.
Looking good for your board.
Well done.
Before we get more into it, you know, there is a lot of talk about accessibility in games,
but it's kind of a word that's thrown around a lot and maybe not everybody quite understands
what it means. So as an expert in this field, what does accessibility mean to you? How do you define
Oh, you know, I think accessibility that you're right, because there's definitely you definitely see accessibility using the context of like, is this game something that the consumer will enjoy?
But in terms of game accessibility, and essentially opening up the the gaming sphere for people with disabilities, we're talking about being able to remove barriers to play.
For anyone, right? It's not even just people with disabilities, anyone who might have a barrier to play.
And it goes from being able to boot up a game
and being able to just interact with the game.
And we'll talk more about that later.
And also being able to encounter the challenges
that you encounter in a game and being
able to surpass those challenges to make progress,
to ultimately have a fulfilling experience, an experience
that you want to have.
So I guess in short, game accessibility
is really being able to break down the barriers to play
as you engage with these game worlds
that creators are creating.
I feel like I'm stealing this phrasing from somewhere I read recently, but there's like
the idea that game design is like creating barriers for people.
This might have been like something I read in your bio and then just like repurposing
it.
But like, so how do you kind of coach people through or work with like devs who are think
accessibility might be at odds with like creating challenge or something along the way?
Yeah, that's a huge, huge issue.
Because what you're talking about there is like the perception of game difficulty.
Right. Yeah.
You know, we've seen that debate play out time and time again
just in the past few years of like, what makes this game like?
I want to make this game hard.
Like, is it does that mean it's not accessible?
And there's there's sort of a misconception, I think, within the community
that anybody asking for accessible features wants their game to be easy.
And I think that's sort of a disservice to the experience that anybody who plays the game wants to have.
And that's that we all, including people with disabilities, including what I've seen in the research that we've done with AbleGamers,
the disabled community does want...
challenge in their games. They don't want their games to be easy per se, but challenge is relative,
right? Like what's hard for me might not be hard for you, right? So at the end of the day, it's
being able to tune the challenges that they encounter in games in order to be able to
surpass those barriers and again to make progress.
So when it comes to game difficulty, you know, simply, you know, talking about easy mode or, you know, having a mode that's, you know, explorer mode or whatever it may be, it's not the entirety of the conversation.
It could be part of it.
But I think game difficulty and challenge really,
really amounts to having the options
to tune challenge to the way you need it to be.
So that you're getting the right amount of,
I guess, resistance to your progress,
but not so that it's just this thing
that you're not able to enjoy.
Because what's unique to games versus like,
let's say like web accessibility, right?
Like web accessibility, you don't want interaction
with the website to be hard, right?
When you jump on amazon.com, you don't wanna be,
you know, and you put like, I don't know, like,
Anything in your cart. I'm going to say Capri Suns because I was just talking about that today.
Yeah.
Capri Suns. Let's get out of my cart.
I don't want to challenge when I order some Capri Suns.
I don't want like an Amazon, you know, a Gremlin to pop out.
Well, then maybe you're not a true gamer.
We laugh about it, but that's kind of the argument that's out there, right?
Which is, you know, you're not a gamer if you don't want some sort of challenge.
And at the end of the day, it's relative.
Some people want different things.
And what we're talking about when we talk about, like, game accessibility
in the context of challenges, being able to create the environment,
the challenge environment that you want to create.
And that doesn't mean that.
The current means of game difficulty don't exist, right?
Like, you can still have your hardest hardcore modes,
but how I play doesn't affect how the next person plays
and how the person after that plays.
So in terms of coaching, you know,
through coaching developers in terms of the conversation
around difficulty, it's really about presenting options
for people.
You know, it's, we kind of have this concept in the community
where, you know, people want to marshal over the way
other people play.
And it's like...
You know, are you in my house playing the game?
Like, what how do you what does it matter to you how playing the game now?
Again, when you're talking about things like multiplayer, right,
like that's where something where, you know, you might think, well,
what if it's easy for this person and I'm playing on the hardest mode or whatever?
And I'm like, well, there's there's optional matchmaking.
There's things where and we call that house rules in the able gamers community.
You know, where you can tune the rules for online engagements
that you're playing with other people who want to play the same way that you want to play.
So there's definitely a multitude of answers for something like that.
But I think I think game difficulty is a contentious
conversation to have.
And yeah, you know, it's one of those things where it's
like let people game the way they want to game.
Do you think it's fair to put it like this,
like it's about giving access to a wide range of people
with different abilities, giving them access to the challenges
that the game designers intended?
Question mark?
I mean, it's not, I don't think, again, you know, I don't think game developers need to
change their vision per se, right?
What?
Yeah, that's, yeah, that's what I mean.
That's exactly what you're saying, right?
Like you can keep the same world that you want to create, just allow people to tune
the elements of it that they want.
Because ultimately, if you know, we look at the current landscape of game difficulty,
right?
Let's say you have your standard easy, medium, hard, right?
If I want to play it on hard mode, I'm going to play it on hard mode.
If you're going to play on easy mode, you're going to play on easy mode.
And the interesting thing about it is,
I always kind of talk to people about this, which is,
as a gaming community, as a community,
we accept whatever definitions a developer has determined
for easy, medium, hard.
We accept it outright.
We just choose one of those and we just go with it.
And we don't really question what that is.
Because easy in one game isn't necessarily easy in another game.
You know, there are different factors at play.
And what we're asking you is really to have the ability to edit those things.
Like you see like sliders in games like The Last of Us Part II
had difficulty sliders or challenge sliders.
Tomb Raider is another franchise that lately has been doing those difficulty sliders
that allow people to tune what aspects of the game
they want to be more difficult or less challenging.
And ultimately, like it again, if you want to default to easy.
Medium hard, which those modes also which those games also have.
They also have those default modes that are developer sort of determined.
You could jump into that and you can play those modes if you want.
But if you want.
the other way of going about it, then you can do that too.
And as a community, like we all like we always see talks about options.
Like we all want options, consumer options.
Like it is consumer friendly.
And frankly, it's good usability to give a user options
in terms of how they want to engage with the content you're presenting.
No one's going to be hurt by having more options and more ways to choose how they want their experience to be.
Except the so-called marshals that I mentioned earlier.
People that are trying to govern how I want to interact with the game.
This is kind of like what you guys have done with the accessible that games.
Is there a fancier name for that?
Probably that I'm getting wrong.
No, that's that's the name of the site.
It's a really cool portal.
I covered it when you guys launched it at first.
And there's just like so much like free accessible information
about accessibility there and how does can like roll that into their games.
How involved were you in the creation of that?
Is it like your baby or?
Uh, is it my baby?
Um, wow. Now we're getting into legality and child support questions.
Uh, I mean, it is, you know, it is our team's baby.
Did I have a role in it?
Yes, I had a very big part in Accessible.games, including the Accessible Player Experience
Design Tool that we created. It's based on user research, based on this program. Research from
this program we have called Player Panels, which is an assemblage of people with disabilities,
players with disabilities, who have provided feedback about
The way they want to play your games and we turn those into to design patterns that speak a lot about what I'm speaking about right now and where it operates on an access level, which is getting people around what's called the the player feedback loop. So basically, access barriers stop people from interacting with the game and taking out information from the game.
And.
Access solutions would help you navigate those barriers.
And then on the second level, challenge,
which is essentially what I mentioned earlier,
helping people progress through the game,
helping people not just encounter some of the challenges
they might have in combat or progression,
but also emotional challenges, right?
Like sometimes there might be content
that you can't engage with.
A great example of that is you see gore settings in games.
You see games that sometimes allow you
to turn off mature language.
So anything on that level operates in the challenge sphere and anything that.
allows people to get through that cycle, get through that player feedback loop,
and subsequently progress through the game is what we would call an accessible player experience.
So all of that is on accessible.games, including anyone who might have a disability who plays
games who wants to be part of the Player Funnels program. Currently we have registration halted
due to COVID-19, but we usually have a portal there for people to be able to register and sign
up for that program, which is currently sitting at about 600 players.
And right now, thank you.
And right now in the works, we have a research portal
that we're trying to set up that'll
show some of the research studies
that we've already come out with.
Just have it housed there in one spot
so that any developer can come and check out
some of the work we've done.
I do want to go over here and look at chat real quick,
because some people are using the question function.
And yeah, let's ask this one.
from Misha Samaridan.
And sorry if I pronounced that incorrectly.
How much do you advocate for accessibility
with people with autism and Asperger's?
Is there funding opportunities
for those wanting to create experiences for this audience?
Do you have any insight on that, Greg?
So just so I'm clear,
funding opportunities for anyone wanting to do development
for neurodiverse folks.
And what was the other part?
What was the first part of the question?
How much do you advocate for accessibility for those types of situations?
Sure. So, I mean, you know, at the end of the day, you know, we kind of have to get to a point where we're respecting and acknowledging both the physical side of disabilities and also the cognitive and mental side of disabilities as well.
So I very much, we very much advocate for not just addressing some of the physical barriers that people might have to play, but also some of the cognitive barriers, some of the mental health barriers that folks have to play.
You know, we were speaking about challenge.
A lot of the sort of interactional barriers that get in the way of progress usually happen
for a lot of folks who, you know, have mental health difficulties or are neurodiverse.
People with physical disabilities experience that as well, but that is something that certainly
operates for folks who have, you know, those mental difficulties as well as access issues,
too.
Sometimes, you know, you're looking at a game, you're just like, there's too much information
here.
You know, I might have a learning disability and I might need to turn off some of the information because it's coming at me too much. It's too much coming at me at once.
So I think, very much so we should, we should keep in mind that it's not just about people who have physical disabilities.
It's also about folks who, you know, maybe have a disability that you can't physically, you know, see or comprehend without talking to them.
In terms of funding opportunities, that's a really great question. I don't personally know if there are any funding opportunities, like grants, I assume the person is talking about.
I don't think there, I don't know if there are any funding opportunities in that respect. That's not really my area of expertise.
But, you know, I can say that, you know, there's a sizable population of people with mental health difficulties that could benefit from games.
being more inclusive in that respect.
And that's even a population that's
represented in our Play Panels program,
because it's important for us to cover
the full landscape of disability, which
is very much inclusive of people who
have neurodiverse diagnoses and mental health conditions.
Now, if I'm a small game developer,
I don't have a lot of time and resources.
But.
And I'm just like, you know what, accessibility just isn't a priority for me.
Do you have, you know, an argument, you know, that that counters that?
Yeah, I mean, that's one of those tough ones where you hear you kind of rage inside
because it's like.
There's always time, you know what I mean?
I mean, but I understand where they're coming from.
And to that I'll say, that's part of the work that,
as an organization, we're trying to do.
Where we're trying to inform the community
about ways that they can move accessibility
to the earlier stages of development.
The Accessible Player Experience design patterns
that I mentioned earlier, they're available for free
on accessible.game.com.
It's something that you can view freely.
And what it does is it presents accessibility problems
that people might encounter in a problem solution format.
So let's say, for example, we have a design pattern called second channel, right?
So one of the problems or the problem for second channel is people can't take
in the information you're trying to relay to them
through the particular modality that you've chosen, right?
So that's a lot of words.
And when you hear that, you're like, what is this dude talking about?
But a great example might be like the information in the cutscene, right?
Let's say like, you know, voiceovers in a cutscene, right?
So that's one modality.
You're presenting a cutscene visually.
And you're presenting the audio in that cutscene through, you know, one means, audio channel.
So a way to articulate a cutscene, or at least the dialogue coming from a cutscene,
another modality or channel would be to have subtitling.
That way, there's now a visual modality in addition to that audio modality.
You know, when we're talking about visual, sometimes we'll see some game trailers.
Like Everwild, I think, had a game trailer where it was completely in audio descriptions.
So, like, the trailer was presented visually, but the whole thing was audio described.
So, someone who has a visual disability could perceive the entire thing,
you know, from that perspective.
So, what those design patterns do is they identify a problem like that,
and they present a solution, which is present.
information through additional modalities. So by tuning a developer's thought processes that way, it helps them think about game mechanics that they might want to implement their game early on. And some of the barriers or problems that people with disabilities might encounter. So the idea there is you're able to think about
disability, while without thinking about specific diagnoses, right, you're able to come out a few levels and think, okay, how might someone who has a visual disability deal with this feature that I'm including this game? How might somebody within auditory disability
encounter this feature that I have in the game? How about a physical disability, and so on and so forth. Um,
So that was really important to us to be able to create this resource because currently a lot of the industry's guideline focus and guidelines aren't they're not a bad thing.
They're really useful for checking once you've created a game right.
Like it's really helpful to be like OK I've got this feature check checkmark.
It's great.
But.
The difficulty with guidelines is they don't really tell you how to do it or how to do it well, right?
They don't tell you how you're supposed to implement a feature, just tells you that you should have it.
There are best practices that are, you know, guidelines can be inclusive of, but ultimately.
They get so robust, right?
Like, you know, current guidelines right now, like they say that,
you know, we're talking about dozens and dozens of options
that you have to make sure are in your game
without telling you how to input that.
It becomes more of like a checklist than like design decisions at that point
is what it sounds like.
Right, exactly. So with with APX and the way that we're trying to shift design thinking is we're trying to think of the person first versus the versus the technology we're trying to put the human being first. Um, and essentially with with APX, you're thinking about problems or barriers that people might encounter. And
In the process of developing your game,
thinking about solutions that help you ideate,
but don't tell you how to design your game.
It tells you what barriers people might encounter
and allows developers to think reflexively, right?
And ultimately, what it does is it encourages
generative design.
So in terms of smaller developers,
that's sort of one aspect of it.
The other aspect of it is the financial aspect of it.
People with disabilities in the United States
have about $21 billion in discretionary income.
Right? That's like after they've paid their bills,
and they're like, yo, this is party time money.
What do I have?
What can I spend it on?
It's $21 billion.
And to put that into perspective,
that's more than the Black community
and Hispanic communities combined.
Black community has about $3 billion.
The Hispanic community has about $16 billion
in discretionary income.
So there's a financial factor to that as well.
And with 46 million potential players
with disabilities in the United States,
you're talking about a huge player base
that you can tap into as a smaller developer.
And there are other examples of independent developers,
including accessibility in their games.
You know, you've got Celeste,
Infernium, Way of the Passive Fist,
Hypnospace Outlaw, HyperDot.
There's like a bevy of games there now including that.
And ultimately, the industry is changing.
The industry is changing.
And if you're not able to adapt,
people aren't going to be able to play your game.
And ultimately, you know, that's sort of the decision you have to make.
And it's tough to think about it this way,
but not every single game is always going to be accessible.
But we have to start somewhere.
We have to start thinking about things like subtitling.
We have to start thinking about things like remapping,
because as with all technologies, we have to start somewhere.
We have to start somewhere.
And there are too many people being left out to not even think
about starting somewhere so that we can ultimately progress
the industry to the place we need it to be.
I know with The Last of Us Part 2 had like that amazing array of just accessibility options focused at so many different areas of need.
And they talked about how it started with the Uncharted game that I don't remember the number of prior to that.
And they're like, oh, these are foundations we set up by building accessibility options into this game.
And then we were able to iterate on them and just build their feedback.
And just from already having those foundations lay, I just accelerate this into this really cool thing.
So just getting out there and doing even the basic so you can kind of learn and iterate
and do more later on seems to be beneficial.
Yeah, and you know, to that point, I mean, you know, we talked about the player panels program, which a developer is free to submit a project to player panels. If you need feedback from players with disabilities. Again, we have 600 players, you can submit a project to let them let us know what type of feedback you want to you want to get from your game. Only thing we ask is that those players are compensated for their time.
We have to set a minimum rate
for the amount that players are paid.
We don't take anything from that.
It's completely you paying the players
that are involved in it.
And that minimum rate is,
at minimum it's $10 for 20 minutes of work
or $25 for an hour of work.
It's good that you guys pay people for stuff like that, because there's a lot, yeah.
I mean, it's not even us paying them, it's the developer that can.
But you know, when it comes down to it, right, like, let's say you create a survey or a gameplay
play session that's an hour long, and you're like, all right, you're like, I want to get
10 people with disabilities to give me feedback on their gameplay experience, right?
$25 times 10 people is $250. You're talking about $250 for accessibility feedback.
At minimum, right?
Yeah.
Like, at the end of the day, and again, going back to the numbers I sent you before, you're
talking about tapping into $21 billion of discretionary income.
So like, you can make a small investment now to make your game more accessible.
Yeah.
And ultimately you'll iterate and become better at that going forward.
Right?
So, and again, the space is changing.
Also, people our age, right?
Like I don't know about you, but like I'm 30 years old.
I want a game until like.
Until like, the angels start singing for me.
Like, I'm, hopefully angels.
You know, hopefully that was a pitchfork.
But, you know, I'm trying to play for the rest of my life.
But we all know that as time progresses,
you have age-related disabilities, right?
And even things that we don't often think about as disabilities, right?
Your sight might go, right?
Maybe your reflexes aren't as good, right?
We're a huge gaming generation.
When we're older, the industry,
we want the industry to be able to cater to us.
I mean, I don't want to be Zoomers that take over the gaming space
and I'm like, hey, what about me?
Like I'm a millennial. I'm trying to game too.
Games are all I got. I'm broken.
I got debt. I need games.
You know, so like it's important for us to think about accessibility
in that respect because the industry is changing.
Yeah. And I'm 40.
So I've got like a decade on you.
I'm going to be hitting those.
I'm going to be needing some of that stuff.
I'll tell you right now, you shocked the hell out of me when you told me you were 40 just now.
Like I hit it well, like I internalized it.
Oh, you know what I did? I found out the video option in Zoom.
I can touch up.
Yeah, I'm actually just... The gray hair just goes away.
The hair appears.
Man, I need whatever lotion you got, whatever you're using, man.
Let me get some of that. It's called half Filipino, I think.
But I'm going to go to chat real quick for Becky Grady getting
a decent amount of likes on this question.
So earlier you said no one's getting no one's going to be hurt by more options.
And Becky points out in UX, though, there is often a balance
of not making it too complicated or some maximum
where it could become too overwhelming to customize at all.
How do you make sure you're providing the needed options
without going so far that it's too hard to navigate?
That is a well thought out question.
Yeah, that's a wonderful question.
And ultimately, it comes down to player testing.
You know, you want to bring in players that you can source this information with
and obtain data.
As a UX researcher, as a UX designer, you know that feedback is going to be the way that
you obtain this information.
And when it comes down to the menus and options that people are navigating on,
you're right, like that can become overly complex very easily.
I know, for example, sometimes you'll jump into an MMO
and the amount of menus you're presented with is like,
fam, I feel like I'm doing my taxes right now.
I don't know what's going on.
There's a lot of terms and numbers here.
So the way to really navigate that
is player testing and user testing.
Ultimately, I can't tell you what the right menu settings are,
but I sure can tell you that if you source about five to ten people
and you ask them questions about their experience navigating the menu,
Chances are you'll see certain issues rise to the top.
You'll probably see the same five issues rise to the top in terms of how people are navigating things.
And ultimately, when you source those questions, when you do that research, which also takes time and also takes resources, not trying to downplay that.
But when you do that, when you take that time,
you do that research, that's something that's
going to rise to the top.
And ultimately, player testing and user testing,
that has to become a bigger part of the industry right now.
It's simply necessary, because you're putting out a product
and you don't know how people are going to feel about it
if you're not testing it.
Yeah.
Just to kind of segue this into this question
from Gabe Pofcher, which probably
As related to what you just said, they asked,
what do you recommend for projects that may not have even $250
for accessibility feedback?
Is that just going to having people do you a favor
and playtest your product, your game, or something?
Yeah, I mean, what I'll say is, you know, first there are resources like accessible.games to check out.
The other thing I'll say is there's plenty of news articles and things about
games that have good accessibility features that you can check out.
Can I Play This is a great website that talks about, you know, game accessibility in various
games. And you can use those games to help inform how you're going to design your game.
I'm not trying to make it seem like this is an easy thing to do.
But when I talk about there being $21 billion in discretionary income with people with disabilities,
there being 46 million people with disabilities in the U.S. with the World Health Organization
estimating that there are 2 billion people on the planet that identify as having disabilities.
So that's not even counting people who don't identify as having disability.
You're talking about a huge population that is going to want access to these experiences,
especially as we, you know, we move to almost 3 billion players on the planet that play games.
There's, you're bound to be overlapped with people who have disabilities as well.
So, you know, really and truly what it is, is it's a value proposition.
And when it comes to not having the resources
to do something like that, I totally understand that.
But doing things like betas also help to get feedback as well,
because you can see how people are interacting with your game.
But ultimately, time and research.
In the same way that you've studied
to learn how to design a game, accessibility
is something that is here to stay.
It's happening.
And unfortunately,
There are folks that have not realized that and are lagging behind.
But we have things like the CVAA, the 21st Century Communications and Video Accessibility Act.
It's a mouthful.
That legally says that certain people need to have access to these experiences.
And other countries around the world are also starting to adapt things like that too.
So it's...
The landscape is changing from a legality perspective, it has changed from a financial perspective, and the numbers of people that you can potentially have access to has increased as well and continues to increase.
So, you know, the world is changing, the landscape is changing.
Hopefully, we'll be able to do what we can as an organization,
and I mean AbleGamers, to alleviate that.
And that's part of the research that we're doing
to try and put out there, too, to change that landscape,
because we know it's hard, and we know it's difficult.
So what we need to do now is ...
Well, we're going to ... Okay, how are we going to do this?
We're going to switch over to basically a word
from our sponsor, a pre-recorded interview that we did.
And, uh, but when that's done, uh, Greg is going to come back with us.
And there's going to be two more Gamasutra editors.
It's really engaging banter about current gaming.
Yeah, yeah, no, but we can we can keep on talking to Greg too after that.
So if we could roll that beautiful beam footage, is that now it's like the.
Yeah, so we're going to go ahead and switch over to that right now and we'll be back in about.
Up next, we'd like to welcome one of our sponsors, Burak Wardel, CEO and co-founder of Istanbul-based
hyper-casual mobile game publisher Rolik, purveyor of chart-topping games including
GoNuts 3D and Tanglemaster 3D. And before Rolik, Burak was at mobile advertising company AdColony
as head of growth and client solutions in charge of the EMEA and Latin America territories.
Hey Burak, how's it going? All good, all good, Chris. Good.
Thanks for joining us. Appreciate it.
So for those who aren't familiar,
can you tell us a little bit about Ralliq
and what you do there?
Actually, Relic is a hyper-casual developer and publisher based in Istanbul.
So we are working with third-party development partner studios to develop hyper-casual games,
and also we have an internal studio that we produce our own hyper-casual games.
And we are in Istanbul and we are controlling an ecosystem of almost a thousand developers and
designers. Oh wow. And what do you do there personally?
I'm the CEO, so I'm managing the databases, I'm managing business, publishing, and product
teams of the company.
And can you tell us about some of the more successful games that Relic has published?
Yeah, actually until August we published 30 games in total and I think almost 20 of
them became the most downloaded game in the United States and actually in Q2 in the period
of April, May and June.
Rolig developed the most downloaded top two games of the United States,
App Store, GoNuts 3D, and Tangle Monster 3D.
So I think those are the latest big ones, so I can tell those as an answer.
Yeah, great. And I feel like this genre is kind of off of a lot of people in the game industry's
radar, so can you define what you think a hyper-casual game is?
Yeah, actually in the industry there are a lot of talks about genres and they're
creating new genres like super casual, hybrid casual, ultra casual. We mainly don't believe
those a lot. So we believe that there are certain rules of game design that you can apply to the
mobile game you have at that moment.
But of course, hypercasual is a big and popular genre.
So I can define a hypercasual game as a simple mechanic giving a huge fun for the society.
And also the main point of a hypercasual game is it should be played by everyone without any
gender, age or anything. It should be a mass appealing game and a successful one.
Yeah, can you can you describe the gameplay of like go nuts, for example, so that they're kind of like very tactile seeming right?
Yeah, actually, actually, the fun moment of that is I'm tying the knots, right? So
There are tight knots and you are trying to untie them with the simple sort mechanic you use.
It's the same with the Tangle Master.
So in the Tangle Master, you also try to break the ropes and try to have a clean level end.
So it's a very simple fun but it's very satisfying when you achieve the win in the level. So it's a
very simplistic mechanic and a simplistic game design but gives a huge satisfaction and fun to
the user. So that's actually what a successful hyper casual game is. Yeah it's almost like
therapeutic.
Now, Relic has seemed to gain a lot of traction pretty quickly as, you know, Relic is still a young company.
So what do you attribute the fast growth to?
Actually, we are an 18-month-old company, so we are very young in terms of the history of Rolex.
But I think the biggest value over there is in hyper-casual, many of the publishers
are acting like performance marketing companies, and many of the developers are acting like
outsourced development. But in Rolex community, we have a huge gaming culture. So I think the
value of success...
And without measuring the timeline of the company, I think the biggest value there is having the proper game component product culture in whatever you do in your business.
So if it's hyper-casual, if it's casual, it's the same for every game production.
The reason Rolex succeeded this fast is the hirings and the culture of the team in terms of gaming,
not like performance marketing or outsource development.
We have a big gaming culture and every day in Rolex office,
the only topic is the games our team is playing or we are producing actually.
And you work very closely with the developers, right?
So when you are collaborating on games with them, what are some of the design principles that you adhere to when you're guiding your development partners?
Yeah, actually, we are partnering our developers from brainstorming level of the idea to the scaling part. So there's a huge story over there.
We are fast, so we are preparing a game to its launch in mostly in one month maximum,
but in the meantime we are covering a lot of details about the game together.
Like in the first prototype we always try to coach them in terms of how many levels do they need
to test the game properly, what should be the exact mechanic of the game,
or what should the progression look like.
and when we are producing the game.
After games show a potential in the metrics we test,
then comes the updates.
Updates are like bigger schedules for the game
that we are giving the feedbacks to the studio
in terms of every detail of the mechanic,
every detail of every level we produce.
So we are trying to be as clear and as...
Transparent as we can in terms of the idea they are producing.
And also, but the thing we don't coach or don't tell them is the execution quality and the development they do.
So that should be coming from the studio as a know-how and as a...
experience, but the rest of the game, the design parts, like level design, like progression, like
characters, and like the general color palettes of the game, are all coached by Rolick to its
studio partners during the production period. And Rolick also is involved in something
interesting called the Rolick Hub. Can you talk about that a little bit?
Yeah, actually, so we know the physical value when we're producing games together with our
partners, especially in hyper-casual, because these games don't have detailed game design
documents, they don't have a big background. On that moment, you think of an idea, and if
your studio partner is a quality partner,
they will be probably able to develop that mechanic in like three hours, right?
So when you have those partners in your office working every day with you,
then you are able to try more mechanics, new designs, etc.
So something comes up to your mind, you talk on that moment,
and you develop and play it right away and check the feeling of the game.
So Rolling Hubs is the idea of getting product,
like keeping that in the soul.
during production, but also doing a very successful business together with our partners.
We are providing them shared offices in our Istanbul HQ and in Ankara, the capital of Turkey,
and soon in Izmir, the third biggest city, and we are producing together with our studios on
daily basis. And this Woodshop, it was a huge release from our Game Hub, and also the latest
release, Fast Driver, which is the first first-person driving game of Hypercasual History,
was also a game from our Game Hub.
Very cool. And just to wrap things up for game developers who are looking to get into this
hyper-casual mobile space, do you have any advice that you could give them?
Yeah, actually I think first advice is always courage. So don't be afraid, but don't confuse
of producing prototypes with releasing successful games. So in hyper-casual,
Producing prototypes looks relatively easy compared to
really releasing a huge hyper-casual title. So
every day you need to do better execution, better ideas, and you need to
continue testing. And in terms of your partners, choose
your partners very well. If you're a developer, please choose a
proper game artist or a game designer as a partner, or vice versa. If you're a
successful game artist, find a good developer partner that you
can pair with.
You don't need like 10 people to produce a proper hypercasual game. Three, four people will be
enough. And I think choosing the right partners is the key over there to make a sustainable and
future-proof ecosystem in hypercasual industry. That's great. Well, Burak, thanks so much for
joining us and best of luck. And thank you very much, Chris. It was a pleasure. Thank you.
And we're back. Found two more people somewhere.
So, we're going to start off with a quick introduction.
We decided that Greg was too lonely.
He needed to be confronted by a toll road.
We don't have repeat guests.
We've got the normal hoodlums from Gamasutra.
Bryant Francis.
Hey, Bryant.
I'm not a hoodlum.
I'm a highwayman.
You're all good.
That's something I should've announced.
Correctly.
You nailed it.
And here I am in standard hoodlum attire.
Let's go.
Yeah, let's do it.
I want to keep on talking to Greg
because whatever about you guys.
All right, see you later.
No, but Greg, first of all,
thanks for sticking around for the bean footage.
A pleasure.
And then, but you announced something
very developer centric,
which I think would be appropriate for here.
Your D-pad.
That's what you call it.
Yes.
So the D-Pad initiative actually launched today,
stands for Developers Promoting Accessibility and Diversity in the Space.
And really what D-Pad is about,
it's about giving people free access to the AbleGamers practitioner course.
So that's a course that we developed to fund our mission
and also to teach developers about accessibility.
Normally the course's price is $2,000 for a seat.
It's a two-day course, extensive course,
that goes into how to use the free tool
that we present on accessible.games,
how to win the sort of arguments around accessibility
in your respective companies,
how to establish a culture and community of accessibility.
in your companies and ultimately to just coalesce around more accessible design thinking,
generative accessible design thinking. So D-Pad is something that sort of emerged
out of our need to do something in a community to bring improved inclusion in the space.
Um, you know, this year in particular, um, we've seen so much happen from a diversity perspective that really reflects how far we need to go, um, how far we've come but also how much further we need to go in order to have an inclusive safe, safe
space not just in the gaming community. But, you know, in the larger, you know, environment as a whole, and on our planet in our country in our planet.
Um,
You know, from the notion that Black lives matter, from the truth that Black lives matter, not even the notion, the truth that Black lives do matter.
The fact that there are trans folk, trans folks experiencing extreme violence and losing their lives because of their chosen identity, the things that we've seen women
I have to endure in the gaming industry from a discrimination and from a just inappropriate behavior standpoint, we realized that the, the only way to really to really change the industry is to start changing it on the, on the developer
side of things to start changing those environments and.
Ultimately, create cultures there that are inclusive,
and hopefully make games that are inclusive and representative
of the people that are playing these games.
People of color, people with disabilities, women,
people that are members of the LGBTQIA community.
So with D-Pad, we wanted to create an initiative where we can
essentially have developers who are interested in taking that course
and learning about accessibility, developers from diverse backgrounds,
such as the one that I just mentioned,
Apply to this course, apply to this program to be able to join up and get a free session of the course.
So if you head over to ablegamers.org slash dpad, you'll find the application there.
You can submit application super short.
We want to keep it concise because I realize people, people about to spend two days with us potentially doing this course.
So we don't want to have you spend too long on the application.
And yeah, just, just apply and join up. You have nothing to lose. If you're if you're from, you know, a marginalized group, you know, apply, we definitely want to see you and we definitely want to hear from you. And, you know, from, from my experience, you know, as a black man in this environment, I realized that there, there's so much, there's so much inequality, and hatred towards groups that don't deserve it. These are things that
We can't change and even if we could we wouldn't. It's who we are. And I say we when I, you know,
I speak about, you know, my blackness, you know, and obviously I don't want to speak for other
groups that I don't necessarily identify as but I know that we all are the way we want we are.
And we, we embrace that. And
It's the way it is, and we need to make sure that the community opens those doors for those
people to feel welcome.
This community is an amazing community, but it has an ugly side.
The gaming community has an ugly side to it, and we got to stomp that out.
Like, enough is enough already.
So we got to get rid of that.
And I hope that DPAD can start making that progress
towards alleviating some of the biases that are in the game
development space, and sort of improving the numbers
so that there's less of the sameness
that we currently see in the gaming environment,
so that other voices can be elevated
and other experiences can be shared and told.
Is there even anything else to be said?
We've got like eight minutes left and like that is straight up mic drop and that's beautiful.
And you know, it goes, you know, just the fact that, you know, the idea, the concept of accessibility
goes, you know, beyond just a lot of people think, oh, you know, helping disabled people
play games, which that's part of it, but there's, it's, it's a woven into.
All the things that you're talking about.
Yeah, and we want developers who have disabilities to apply this program too.
Because that's another stigma in the space right now, which is,
oh, we don't know how to hire people with disabilities.
And I'm like...
Like, there are plenty of people that are out there that have disabilities that want to be developers or want to work on the gaming side of things.
You know, we've seen Cherry Thompson get hired at Ubisoft, which is an amazing hire.
Hi, Cherry, if you're listening.
She's in chat, yeah.
Oh, what up, Cherry?
You know, so Cherry, you know, is an example of bringing folks who have disabilities who are vocal about the disabilities,
who are expressive about their disabilities and the experiences that the game industry needs to start, like, changing their minds towards, you know, hiring people that have these experiences.
It's an important part of making sure that this community can grow.
Um, and you know, and I'll be honest with you too, like it benefits these companies
are trying to make money to, to, to, to have other people in the community.
You know what I mean?
Like it's, it's not an altruistic thing.
I know to include other people, you know, in order to, to grow your, your business.
So like, it doesn't hurt anybody, but bigots, honestly, so
your perspectives make better games.
I mean, I couldn't have said it better, you know, and I hope to see that, I hope to see
D-pad, you know, be the, be the starter for that in terms of what we could do on our end.
You know, we're not, we're not Nike, you know, we can't give out a hundred million dollars
towards a specific movement because ultimately anybody who decides to support our organization,
you know, they've chosen us to be custodians of the money that they've given us.
And we feel as custodians, a great way to support our mission is to train developers from diverse backgrounds in accessibility to ultimately help the community that we set out to by starting AbleGamers and also to grow the space in terms of a diverse, inclusive perspective.
Hey, real quick, just sliding in with a tiny, tiny correction.
We referred to Cherry in the third person a couple of seconds ago.
Cherry is one of our great GDC speakers, and they use they, them pronouns.
Yes. So just quickly.
Oh, yes. Thank you.
Just to clarify that and make sure, you know, this live episode
doesn't contain any bad feelings after this is done.
So absolutely. Thank you.
If I did do that.
I appreciate.
Thank you, Triskel, for asterisking that in chat.
Yeah, and on the topic of hurting bigots, I saw a great, I saw a great talk today at GDC Summer.
That is a different tack in a different sphere, but I think is sort of similar in some key points.
Brenda Romero gave a talk this morning, I don't know if anybody caught it,
on hidden histories of women in computing. And a key point of that talk, which is going to be
available on the platform for everyone to watch on demand if you missed it, is that
Women are not fairly represented in leadership roles and in creative roles, both in tech and in games.
And one of her key arguments was that, you know, having a mostly male-dominated industry,
a mostly white male-dominated industry, creates a lot of situations where women are physically
uncomfortable, whether it's cold offices or, you know, badly designed games or whatever.
And so she basically made a big call for gender parity, making a good case of like,
basically, the more diverse teams you have, the better games they're going to make.
because they're going to bring their own perspectives
and their own experiences to the work.
And it seems like we're seeing a lot of calls
for that across the industry, and it's great.
Let's just keep doing it. Let's just keep, never stop.
Yeah, we got to keep that same heat that we had,
you know, when we saw everything happen with George Floyd,
when we saw him, we saw the brutality
that was shown towards a human being,
and we all started recognizing that.
When we see all the people in the industry
being outed for their behavior towards women,
like, that heat that we have right now
about trying to improve that.
Like, if this hasn't changed a year from now, we got to have that same fire.
Because every time we let up, every time we let up in terms of, you know,
appealing for more equality and diversity, we take five steps back.
And enough is enough. I'm tired. I know I'm tired.
And I know that I'm not the only one who feels that way.
But at the end of the day, there's a generation that's coming after us that needs to see a better
world. And the generation that exists right now, we deserve a better world. So we got to keep
pushing in that respect. Absolutely. Did you guys see any fun talks about herding bigots?
Yeah, yeah. It was very specific. If you want to read about that talk,
you can find a write-up by Alex on gamasutra.com.
Nice one.
We do work for GammaCitra.com, don't we?
A website with a name.
Yeah.
We didn't really talk too much.
We have a little bit of time left, like four minutes.
I'm wondering, like, working with, like, I mentioned right at the beginning
that you work with these big companies, some of them large publishers.
Yeah.
We work with a lot of big companies, some of them large publishers.
What do you get from those?
Like when when you're consulting with them, are you kind of like surprised
at the culture or are you,
you know, are they usually receptive?
How does that usually go for you?
I think I think it certainly varies.
I think. If I have to be honest, I think I think companies,
it's not that they're receptive, it's that they're somewhat apprehensive.
And, you know, like, for example, personally, I don't identify as having a disability.
And I like to make that clear when I talk about the community, because I always say, like,
you know, I speak about their needs and the community as opposed to me.
So I'm not I don't necessarily identify as being part of that community.
But even myself, it took me a long time to get comfortable with asking questions.
That ultimately serve the knowledge that I'll need to have in order to benefit the community I want to help.
And I think at least with the companies I've worked with, I can't speak for every company out there, but at least the companies I've had the pleasure of working with, it's more so that it's...
It's a lack of knowledge, you know, that really makes creates sort of apprehension.
And to that we try to offer a safe space where you can ask questions about the community
to further inform yourself because ultimately, like asking questions with respect, obviously
we know we're not talking about like, you know.
being, you know, rude or bigoted in how you address the community.
But, you know, asking questions about the experiences that we try to share with these
companies in order to improve their approaches to accessibility.
In terms of...
I'm sorry.
You know, common questions we might get.
We got a lot of questions about like, you know,
what should I do first from an accessibility standpoint?
And like, that's a tough question to answer.
I can say from the players that we've polled,
from the players that we've talked to in player panels,
that a lot of the people ask for things like key remapping.
A lot of people ask for, you know, proper subtitling.
That includes increasing text size,
that means, or decreasing text size if you need to,
or turning it off completely.
Having backgrounds for those subtitles, being able to change the color of both the text and the background to match what you want from a contrasting standpoint, including the speaker name as well if there's multiple speakers speaking in a game.
We see a lot about recoloring, so colorblind options, being able to turn off sort of the background noise that might be coming from the game or flashes might be coming from a game.
Um...
We also see a lot about timed actions.
So things that require you to have quick reflexes,
QTEs being a big one, quick time events.
So it kind of varies.
And ultimately, I'd say start somewhere
and continue to iterate from that respect.
But we get a lot of questions.
It's hard to think of them right now.
We definitely get a lot of questions in that regard.
Oh, and you know, we've got like 17 seconds left.
I'm watching the timer go down.
Perfect.
Yeah, but, you know, people can probably go to what resources,
what website, you know, ablegamers.org.
All right, let's make this quick.
ablegamers.org, accessible.games.
Follow us on Twitter at AbleGamers.
You can follow myself on Twitter at Greg,
Jay, Hazy, Jayson, Jaguar.
And go to ablegamers.org slash dpad if you're a developer
and you come from a marginalized background
and you want to learn about accessibility.
Amazing. And that is a great place to stop.
And thank you so much, Greg.
Thanks to the crew.
And thank you, seriously, everybody in chat.
You're like, you're so wonderful.
So thanks for joining us for this special episode.
And we're going to be doing these live ones again tomorrow
and the next day after that, whichever day that is.
Thanks everyone.
Good to be here.
Bye.