Hi, my name is John Sulwitz, and in my day job, I work as a Principal Technical Director
at Electronic Arts.
But some time ago, I had the privilege to be the lead gameplay programmer on the original
arcade version of Paperboy.
I am pleased to let you know that I will be presenting the classic game Postmortem on
Paperboy at this year's Game Developers Conference.
In my talk, I will try to explain how a rather unique game about the life and times of a paper
delivery kid got done at all. I was part of a very creative video game team and I am happy to say
that I was able to interview each of my fellow members to prepare for this presentation, so
I will be sharing their thoughts and memories with you as well.
My plan is to tell you the story of where the idea came from, how we got Atari to let us build it, and some of the key moments of development.
I will be even showing you how the handlebar controller was created.
And in the spirit of a true retrospective, I will share with you not only our successes, but some of the things that did not go so well too.
You know, Paperboy was made about 35 years ago, and what some of us think of was the golden age of arcade video games, but I think its story is still fresh and relevant.
I hope you join me for my talk, Classic Game Postmortem Paperboy.
See you there.