Hello, I'm JJ, producer of UNO.
Today, I'm going to introduce the UX work of UNO
with our UX design leader, Sissy.
Before I start, I want to ask you a question.
Have you heard of UNO?
I believe most of you have played the UNO cards.
UNO board game was invented in 1971,
then has been enjoying its 40-year-long popularity.
And we just launched our UNO mobile game in 2019.
The mobile game is a new platform for UNO.
It allows us to play UNO at any time even without carrying a deck of cards.
After UNO mobile game launched in 150 countries,
we found 93% of UNO mobile game players have played other versions of UNO.
Obviously, most of the players are actually fans of classic UNO and very familiar with UNO.
This number really shocked us, but it also proved that we were using the right design approach in the development process.
So, what have we done to give players the classic and unique UNO?
And finally, make it available to players to play UNO all over the world.
We encountered some problems but finally found the corresponding solutions.
Next, Cici will talk about their UX strategies to adapt the classic UNO to mobile.
Hello, I'm Cici. Let's talk about our design journey from a few keywords.
First, cars.
Initially, we arranged the cards in a tiled way, but it's a rigid design that makes you feel like you are playing with a robot.
Of course, this version of the design is very simple, quickly implemented, and the cost is very low.
Once the core gameplay has been verified,
We began to modify the way how cards present.
We need to study how players hold cards when playing Uno board games.
To tackle this problem, we organized a group of players to play Uno, and designers came
to observe them.
Then we took a photo like this.
Then the players hold cards.
Because of the palm structure and posture, the card will show a certain arc,
and in order to prevent opponents from picking, they will turn their hands sideways.
But cards in our game are laid directly on the table.
In real life, it's impossible to have such a situation,
because from this perspective we can't see the front of the card.
We tried to use law of closure to design the layout of cards.
When we find ourselves looking at 3D cards, it's natural to think of a hand holding them,
because it can remind us of playing Uno with our friends.
So we made an important decision, designing the cards in 3D on a table as if someone were holding them.
This took us a lot of development costs, but it's worth it, and the final effect is very nice.
After we solved the problem of holding cards, we started to look at the user interactions in different modes.
This is 2v2 mode and I can see my teammates' cards.
But when my teammate has a lot of cards, how can I see them clearly?
Tap to enlarge your teammate's card directly, or slow down and using the previous design approach.
Continue to study the behavior of Uno board game players when they are playing cards.
This is a picture of a player holding a hand of cards.
When playing Uno board game, people are used to deciding which color to play first, then
holding a visually-focused card close to themselves and picking it out individually.
We learned from Uno board game and designed our mobile game card viewing experience.
Just tap on the cards of your teammate, and the touched cards will be held by an invisible hand.
We let the four surrounding cards be lifted at the same time for comparison purpose.
After solving the card problem, make the core gameplay smooth becomes the next problem to be solved.
Uno's Corning Uno is the most exciting part of playing Uno. However,
It's not feasible for a mobile device to call in Uno directly.
We can't recognize it perfectly by voice on the mobile phone platform.
And when players play mobile phones, it's not suitable to short all the time,
which is easier to scare others.
Because the players are not face to face, they are facing a phone.
For the design of calling Uno.
We designed the Uno button on the right.
Players tap of the button is calling Uno.
But we also considered players' habits,
especially when playing Uno mobile game offline with friends.
They may alert out Uno.
So we designed an extra voice recognition function Voice Uno.
Once opened, players can call Uno just like they do in Uno board game.
And kids can easily use this trick to call Uno.
But that's just an additional option.
You can turn it on and off.
Next, Rules.
This case is about rules.
Classical Uno is flexible and we can create new rules.
However, there are different rules in different countries.
In mobile device, it's impossible if we try to put 100 plus rules of game mode for all players to choose.
Therefore, designers need to figure out what is really good design to solve this problem.
In the beginning, game designers planned to apply such optional rule functions.
Where players can choose the roles they like.
This is a good idea, but not a good UI design.
All the optional roles are listed above.
There are too many options and no space on a mobile screen to put more.
And when players start a new game with different group of players,
they will have to adjust the role options.
Hicks' law describes that with more options, the time for players to make decisions will increase.
For mobile games, our original design might have directly led to the loss of players.
We changed the way of thinking and tried to figure out whether we can use the design to solve the needs of all players for different roles.
And it turns out that we redefined different roles into different game modes, which makes
changing game modes much easier than adjusting different role options.
We just provide roles and players are the real game designers because they can edit
their own game modes.
Meanwhile.
Editing roles and game modes by dragging cards are much easier for players to understand.
After such design improvements, there are fewer options and players can spend less time on selection.
Now players can make 488 different game modes with this.
We are planning to put more and more game roles into our game for better understanding.
The most important takeaway here is that we study players' habits of playing UNO card games,
and then turn them into designs suitable for mobile devices.
We do creative designs based on mobile device features,
but not just simply restore the classic UNO.
If you want to put a classic game on another platform and make it more popular, try to
think about how players experienced it on previous platforms and what the core experience
is.
Then keep the core experience and make your own innovations, so you may be able to figure
out where is your direction of design.
Thank you.
If you want to play Woono,
Any time, any will.
Download it.