Hi everyone, welcome to the Gamasutra Twitch channel.
My name is Bryant Francis.
I am the invisible ghost inside your head.
Once again, invisible.
Last time we were here together, I was not.
You saw me and you saw Liam, the lovely cat who is sometimes going to yell on the stream
today.
But we are here on the GDC Twitch channel doing what we usually do, which is talking
to game developers about the cool games that they are working on.
Today we are playing the Blackout Club.
The Blackout Club comes from the folks at Question who previously released the Magic Circle.
And in the lower left hand corner of the screen, I'll give Jordan a little more face time down there.
Jordan, we have... yeah, just pulling Jordan over.
Yeah, well then Mike loses out.
Oh no, I have to pick.
Sorry Jordan.
It's good, it's a Bioshock style Harvest Save situation.
Ah, it's Harvest Save, it's Bioshock.
I guess we'll talk about Bioshock today since you all worked on it.
Anyway, this is Jordan and Michael.
Jordan has the red background behind him.
Say hi Jordan.
Hello.
And that's Michael, he's got the nice headset on.
And they will be taking your questions today.
Basically, The Blackout Club is a four-person horror co-op game, which you are seeing.
We are playing the demo level.
Feral disclosure, this is pre-recorded footage, so you can't yell at me if I'm messing up.
You can only just reflect on the errors I have made.
So we're going to go through the demo level, and then before we're out today,
we will get to see a couple full missions of the game,
because I was able to find some very nice people to play with last night
who were very helpful and very kind. You got a nice community.
Oh, that's very good to hear.
We're very proud of our discord community, especially right now.
Yeah, I admit it wasn't through.
I just found them in the lobbies.
Anyway, I guess to be honest, it's probably mostly the same people
to get.
I guess I'm looking at this high five machine first.
Well, as I awkwardly high five the robot, Jordan and Michael,
would you mind explaining the origins of the Blackout Club
and why you went from making a game like the Magic Circle
to making a four person horror co-op game?
I think we should make Patches explain this.
I would love to hear your take on why that probably was.
For the record, Michael is Patches, although I still don't know.
Oh, we lost Patches' camera.
Never mind. I'll do that then.
Yeah. So following the Magic Circle, which is an extremely meta game
about game development, we had sort of our fill of two things.
One, games that say exactly what they mean.
It was fun, but we've done that for a very long time
through several Bioshocks and then the Magic Circle.
And then secondarily, the sort of length problem,
major criticism of the Magic Circle
from most people who bought it was,
this game is too short, right?
I paid for this much,
I want a game that goes on for much longer.
Okay, the world is changing, Steam is changing.
We need something that we personally believe in,
which is the sort of cooperative horror thing,
but that dovetails better
with the way people play games on Steam.
We're just getting involved with them
and sticking with them over a longer period.
Yeah. And so I pitched around a couple of different things and the one that stuck was this notion of a suburban horror game where the friendship between these sort of the set of kids was going to be at center stage and that you would be scared but with friends.
And we were three people at the time we've doubled in size since we brought on Michael Patches Kelly here, who is now back.
and several others, and we began to sort of bolt it together.
We're now in early access, as you know,
and finally starting to get real feedback from people
on how it feels to play and improving it every day.
Right on. Patches, before you quickly dropped out there,
Jordan said he wants to hear your version
of your origin story for Blackout Club.
So I want to hear it, too. What's your take?
Yeah, sorry about that.
My internet is wonderful quality.
So, let me think about the actual origin of it.
When I started working at Question, Jordan had told me that they were working on,
you know, we were trying to find a way to do a new horror game that was going to solve
our publishing problem as just a small game dev. You probably did answer. So I kind of caught the
tail end of Jordan's answer, so apologies if I overlap. But...
You know, you're a small game dev, you're trying to make a game that plays to our strengths, right?
Like we worked on AAA games, Stephen and Jordan worked on Bioshock, you know, Kane came from Dishonored.
So the sort of first-person immersive sim genre is something we really like.
Obviously, I like working on those games and playing them as well.
So we were gonna do that, except for the idea was Jordan wanted to return to horror,
because that's sort of his strength.
for
the game.
This actually gets pretty scary. We've had people, you know,
writing us on Steam community and on forums basically saying, you know, this I couldn't get through the intro and what looks like just walking
around a house at night
can still be can still be scary in the right hands and so
You know, I felt pretty confident joining question that Jordan had the right hands to make more scary experiences and I wanted to help him with that
so
That was kind of the origin of what became the Blackout Club.
Originally we had, to solve the publishing problem of typically what happens is you're
a small game developer, you make a game, it's, you know, you can only make so many hours
of single player content before you run out of money and time, and then what tends to
happen is people play it, and then they're done, and that's the end of your sort of community,
that's the end of sort of, you know, attention on the game, as well as...
You know, a lot of people will just put it on Twitch and then they'll just watch somebody play through it.
And it's not that we don't want people to enjoy the content, but it's harder to get the sale.
You know, being honest, it's hard to make a living.
And so, you know, multiplayer was something we knew could bring people back in.
But there's a real problem with horror and multiplayer that probably anybody asked or who plays games like this could tell you, which is.
You know, the more friends you add to the scenario, the less scary and usually more absurd it becomes.
Yeah.
Um, so what worked for us when we were developing the Blackout Club was
we can lean into that because they're teenagers.
Um, typically what happens, like, I'm a coward, I'm a scaredy cat.
I don't like playing horror games, uh, by myself alone in the dark.
And, uh, I do it because it's the best experience, but I always, you know, scare myself.
Um, and so I typically like going back to like Resident Evil games and stuff like that back in the day.
I tend to play like over the weekend with a friend on the couch and we'd trade the controller or something.
So that playing a scary game with your friends experience is something we thought like,
okay, here's something we can lean into. It's a little bit of a better...
I'm maybe, I'm telling you too much sales information, but this is, you know, the GDC gama sutra.
So I feel like you want to hear this.
We do, we do.
So yeah, we were like, how do we...
How do we make this something that you can actually, uh, you know, it's a bigger audience, right?
It's a, there's the horror audience, but then there's the friends of the horror audience that you're bringing in.
And it's like, well, we'll, you know, I like watching my friend play a scary game, but usually I'm too much of a coward myself.
But if we're both playing and we're having some fun in the way that you would with like Left 4 Dead or Vermintide or any other sort of like co-op game, um.
Then I've got something to do and you're here with me and so we're brave together.
Um, and...
Really quick, this tree, this tree scared me so much that we just saw a couple minutes
ago.
Yeah, that one.
Yeah, tell me more.
I'm sorry, Michael, do you have anything else you want to add?
Well, that's, so anyways, long story short, that's kind of how we got there was the idea,
like how do we do a multiplayer co-op horror game, and being teenagers in this scenario,
we knew that there's a lot of potential for great horror, because, you know, the genre
tells us that, but, um, Teams vs. Monsters is full of lots of great stuff we love and
wanted to pay tribute to, and we can talk about that later, but, um...
Yeah, anyway, so that was the origin of, from a gameplay standpoint, we were trying to find,
like, let's take that horror experience, but let's find a way to get your friends involved.
And then looking around at other popular multiplayer cooperative games,
if we do it as cooperative, we're in this together against the scary thing,
we felt like that was a good, you know, a good game, a good premise. And we think it'd be
something people would want to play, but also you can't spoil it as much if people are streaming it.
because the magic is your experience with your friends, right?
That's what's fun about it.
And I guess on the streaming end, there's also the argument that like,
if people aren't playing, they're watching other people play.
It's like watching a horror movie.
It's like watching people be trapped in a horror movie making dumb decisions,
which is what you will see plenty of times in the stream.
Because you get to watch me making terrible decisions in a horror movie.
If I can ask both of you about what happened after that first decision, sort of that cognizance that you wanted to make a horror game and you also wanted to make a game that could retain a community.
What was the first architectural and design thing you had to do to take that very loose, I'm sure very like...
It's not exactly, I mean you could say it's Left 4 Dead, but with kids and then build that out.
But I'm sure it wasn't quite like that when you were building it.
How did you go from sort of those fundamental roots of game business and game design to making what we're looking at right now?
It was a combination. The first task was to switch from Unity to Unreal.
Unreal has a built-in multiplayer architecture which was a lot more robust and got us up and running much more swiftly.
Originally the game pitch was that you would be underground the entire time,
trapped alone in the maze beneath the streets. Spoiler alert, there's a maze beneath the streets.
We'll see.
And you would band together with people but in a sort of more Journey-esque.
a format where your sessions would merge and then part kind of seamlessly.
It was interesting, but we transitioned pretty early on to a session-based model
where you're able to actually experience the kids' neighborhood in suburbia,
and then we weren't bound by the rules of a persistent world
like we would be in something like Bioshock.
Yeah.
And so changing towards that made us more Left 4 Dead-like.
Honestly, to some extent, those earmarks that people learn to look for, like,
I like games like this.
We needed a few of them.
And we were willing to say, like, OK, yeah, let's let's let's be as familiar
as possible from the surface and then surprise them once they're in.
And so we developed a sort of.
World Bible, it was by now very far out of date.
We developed a series of mission pitches,
also super long in the tooth now and not highly relevant,
but they got us off the ground and we began to hire.
And so we brought on Patches,
Jason Mojica from the Payday 2 team,
Jeff Lake from Dishonored and Prey,
and David Pittman who had done Eldritch
and worked with us on Bioshock 2.
And we're also working with Patrick Waltrip,
who did audio for multiple Bioshocks, and many others.
And in any case, we're now actually seven.
But long story short, it became a process
of trying to make sure the vision made sense
each time a new person came on.
The hiring sort of forced us to reframe
what the hell the thing was,
as each time somebody new would come in and say like,
okay, well, what is it you want me to do?
And it has been a fast growth process.
It has been challenging.
We've also had help.
We can't really talk about from where,
but suffice it to say,
there are people who believed in us
and helped make the Blackout Club happen.
And honestly, it wouldn't have without them.
And so it was a combination of working with them from afar
and also building our own team
that has, I think, been our primary challenge.
The actual game,
You know, there are a lot of creative challenges, but suburban horror,
the sort of teens versus the truth monster genre is something that everybody's
got their favorite from pop culture in their head.
We felt like it was something that people would be able to drop into easily so we
can be as weird as we want, but you can always fall back on, well,
I basically know what I'm doing. That was a long answer to your question.
No, that's a good answer. Michael, do you want to add anything?
Yeah, you're going to have to repeat the question though, at this point.
I followed Jordan's ride, but I didn't know, I forgot where we started.
You don't know what train station we started at.
What was your experience moving this game from idea to execution?
So when I first came on the project...
We, you know, so I came from a production background.
I was an EP on the BioGames, uh, and Top Spin and a bunch of other games at 2K.
It was my old life.
And then I did mobile games for a while.
And so when I came, before I joined Question, and so when I came on, you know, my first
instinct is, okay, we need a roadmap, we need a plan, we need a skeleton.
You know, how, what's, how are we going to allocate our money and time and budget and
all that stuff?
So, um.
That was the first thing we did and we, I, you know, this was also an opportunity to sort of test, you know, when you're an AP coming out in production land, you know, you are not making any decisions, you're just enforcing other people's decisions.
So I had tried early on to try and say like, well, I've always wanted to and believe very strongly that like a small, playable prototype is the best money we could spend, you know, do not, don't worry about it being pretty, just make it fun.
and we called it Ugly But Fun.
And this isn't just my idea.
The team is very...
I would say, Jordan can correct me if I'm wrong,
but I'd say a very flat structure.
Everybody really does have a say.
We're small enough that it's just not worth it
to try to impose much of a hierarchy other than
obviously I'm not going to do the art
that Steven is good at that.
I'm not writing C++.
In general, we sort of hashed out, okay, what would be like a core experience?
What are the things we know we have to have?
And so, and it takes a while to get up and running.
I mean, you know, we switched over to Unreal.
We weren't in Unity anymore.
All of the code had to be more or less started over from scratch.
Um, and so, you know, it's like, okay, let's make sure, and locomotion takes a
long time, you know, even in Unreal, just to get it exactly the way you want.
We knew we wanted to do, you know.
This kind of combat where you're getting up close with people.
We knew we wanted to have a closed eyes mechanic for the shape.
I think that was a pretty early concept in this game's development
and still stays pretty core to the identity of the game.
You know, an enemy that you can only see with your eyes requires,
you know, some engine modifications.
It's not just, you know, those tricks.
And so we kind of did that.
And then lastly, the recording mechanic, I think was another big one.
We worked on it pretty early, which was, you know, you're going to have this phone in your
hand.
That phone actually shows you, you know, a screen capture of what you're looking at.
You can see it there at the bottom on the left, the record screen capture.
And then we had gone through and then iterate, you know, like figure out what's fun about
this.
So, because the idea is, you know, one thing, but actually making it fun is game development.
So, uh.
That was kind of our first six months, I'd say.
Maybe a little longer was really just prototyping,
prototyping, prototyping.
We had a little map, Jordan Grey boxed.
You know, we did a bunch of art tests
and then it was, okay, let's, you know, get, you know,
we coming from Unity the last couple years, you know,
the question team had to sort of change the mentality
to get back over to Unreal
because it's just a different way of working.
Just kind of all the nuts and bolts stuff
that you do starting a project was my first six months or so
on the project.
And then, yeah, once we felt pretty good
about the prototype, you know,
we changed a lot of things in the core design
because we were like, oh, this is more fun.
That other thing didn't work.
What are you talking about?
It was perfect. It was perfect.
From the word go.
Yeah. We've never changed our minds.
And so we changed our minds a lot.
We worked on a bunch of different.
but the reason you don't put a lot of high-quality art in yet
and really dive in on even sound design and things
first was because you want to be sure that the game is a game that you want to play
for a long period of time and so we had some other ideas that we wanted to add later
you know the procedural mission stuff didn't come on immediately we had to sort of determine
what makes a mission you know what does it mean
It's just dumb stuff like what is an objective?
OK, it's like, you know, like you have to kind of deconstruct games
and put it all together.
So we did that.
We felt pretty good about the prototype.
And then, you know, you you flesh out, OK, what is the minimum viable product?
What's an MVP?
People call that like a vertical slice or a horizontal slice or some slice.
What are the features we know we want to have?
And then what is the stuff that, you know, adding on top of it will make it better?
and you sort of prioritize your work from there.
Like, what is the stuff you know you can't not deliver?
I just realized that orb in the middle
freaked me out a lot more this time
watching my own footage than it did the first time I saw it.
Anyway, so that's, yeah, that was how we got started.
Right on.
MPKNT in chat would like to clarify,
AP stands for Associate Producer, right?
That's correct, yeah. Cool.
It could be assistant producer places too, you know, it's not the main producer.
Yeah.
How does the testing, they would also like to know, how does the testing and
iteration process go for a game like this compared to the single player games
you all are more familiar with?
It's a lot harder.
You know, we are a small team getting four player multiplayer means,
you know, more than 50% of the team needs to be testing at that moment,
which, you know, normally you don't.
Normally it's, you know, you everybody has their own.
Like at a large AAA scenario, you'd have a dedicated on-site QA team, you'd have an off-site QA team, you'd have them embedded with a designer or an engineer working together with a clear test plan.
We're our own QA for a lot of it. We do have an outsource contractor we use, you know, especially to help just kind of nuts and bolts functional QA or format QA, are terms you've probably heard of, but it's just the, you know, can I clip through the wall? What happens if I jump off the ledge?
You know, just normal.
testing. Does this feature do what it says on the 10?
So our test process in general is, you know,
kind of evolved over time, but in general we all play the game as much as
we can all the time. You test a lot in editor before you
check in work, and we have to sort of rely on the
fact that everybody's pretty experienced, you know, this isn't
anybody's first game. So we, you know, we do test
But I will say, you know, being small, it means that we can't test as much as we need to, to ship the game.
And so we've also done, you know, a lot of internal friends and family testing.
And then we did a beta test for pretty much from July through the end of October this year.
And then, you know, in October when we came out.
That's where our Discord community was built,
through a series of closed betas that patches ran very well.
And they were just instrumental.
It's a lot of people you might have met online are probably coming from that original community,
which has been wonderful.
The fact that people would have played our game, at this point, dozens and dozens of
hours well before it's done is awesome.
And that's turned into a lot of our early access community as well to help on-ramp people.
But you know for your listeners tutorials are one of the last things you add in a game
It's the same it goes back to that ugly but fun prototype mentality
You know like don't spend a lot of effort on something you're gonna throw away and rework
Because you know things change, so the last thing you want to put in is here's how it works
So as a result our early access is out and it's not everything is tutorial eyes
Do you know this prologue mission you're watching does it?
really good job I would say, but it's not perfect, it doesn't have everything it needs, and
you know, certainly there are a lot of concepts in this game that are,
you know, we started with the idea of like a first player, you know, stealth immersive sim type game,
but once you add cooperative, once you add a mission-based structure with sessions, once you
add multiplayer, plus a lot of other weird ideas we have in this game that kind of make it unique,
you know, there's just a lot to teach.
So it's been nice having a community that did play through the beta test because they
can kind of help on-ramp new players that we don't necessarily have the bandwidth to
do.
You get to watch some of my struggles right here with the art of not being heard.
Jordan while I'm struggling with the dark forces in this, I'm going to ask a question
for you.
What was your thought process for making this horror cult thing that's going on?
And kind of there's also the sense that the parents are in on it.
There's sort of some implication that happens here at the end of the stream that like...
It's almost like the entire town is engaged in this weird, mysterious stuff you're seeing.
How did that influence making things creepy and scary for players at a granular design level?
Oh, let's see. That's a multifaceted one.
I guess I was really interested in building a...
A kind of horror that worked on at least two levels.
A kind of primal level.
I think when you're an adolescent, in particular, your mind is being broken
and reforging itself in real time.
And so you are constantly questioning your reality because it's important for
your previous model of reality to blow up in order for you to sort of slowly grow
up, right?
Yeah.
So things like.
What if my family is out to get me?
What if my dad is actually evil?
Like that kind of stuff floats through the average kid's brain
as they grow older.
And so it seemed like a sort of ripe age
to talk about learning that in fact,
you are at the heart of a grand lie of some kind, right?
And that your own family could turn against you.
I feel like everybody can understand that
on a visceral level, whether or not they understand
any of what-
The team mocked me by calling the deep lore.
And on the other end of that spectrum,
I wanted to build a kind of mythology
that didn't resemble anything else.
That when you got into the maze under Red Acre,
Virginia here in the national radio quiet zone,
where there's no kind of internet signal,
no cellular access,
you would see something that could plausibly exist
in the modern world,
but made you think of some timeless era.
uh, that you were suddenly dipping, uh, your, uh, your toe into without understanding it.
Um, and so, you know, people float around words, words like cult, but I hope that as they play,
they, they become kind of versed in something even stranger than that.
Um, and, uh, I don't want to go deep into spoilers, but, uh, I, the game states very
little of what it means relative to something like the magic circle or Bioshock because we want
that part of your brain to constantly be grappling with that, that.
fuzzy, unknown edge outside at the edge of consciousness.
And it should feel like a nightmare,
but a nightmare that operates by a strong inner logic.
And we hope that our players slowly puzzle that out.
Right on. I think kind of building on that is, um, what was it's the teenager element is interesting to me because the teens are very not good at what most video game characters are good at. Like, they're not good at fighting. They have they can grab and pin which Dr. Thawse in chat says they're a big fan of that mechanic. But they can't, they can't, you know, shoot monsters. This isn't Left 4 Dead shooting zombies. They're, they're sort of they're, they're really good at grappling hooks, which is probably something I wasn't good at when I was a teen.
But how did you design individual interactions that you think fit the theme?
That were both thematic and good gameplay, and also wouldn't make Pat just over here look at you in horror when you pitched it to him.
Oh, that's another good question with many answers, and I will try to keep them concise.
We had a few creative pillars of the game, and I won't go into all of them, but one of them was that movement was a reward.
intrinsically sort of kind of viscerally satisfying.
And Kane Shin, our sort of technology lead
who joined us late on the Magic Circle
and then sort of saved us, frankly, is big into that.
He plays lots of games where movement matters.
And so he kind of made it his personal baby.
And I think that he's executed on it beautifully.
These kids are way better at parkour than I will ever be.
And so with that.
established we knew that we could say, okay, well that means that combat is not going to be a thing.
Grappling will be a panicky and a pyrrhic victory at best. If you get away from somebody, it's going
to hurt unless you use an escape item, in which case that still has a cost. And so we wanted to
focus on the idea that horror is at its best when...
vulnerability is maintained.
And so we spoke to an age that seemed reasonably vulnerable
and that allowed us to unask questions about
why don't I just fight back?
Why don't I just use martial arts and defeat all of these adults
one by one like you would in thousands of other games?
And so...
It was hard to say no to ourselves for a long time.
We have made many games where combat was a main feature,
but we felt like between the sort of guerrilla tactics,
the kind of clever, outwit your enemies tactics
that began to develop through the other systems
the player has access to, and that movement,
we could sell to the player the idea
that you can either be very stealthy in this game,
because we've built those before,
or you can be loud as long as you keep moving.
And in no case are you gonna stand in place
and defeat all of your enemies.
You have to move on, get your mission done,
take some footage of something forbidden, and then flee.
Speaking to that heart of horror in your hometown.
And all of those, to be perfectly honest,
are willing to handshake with the fact
that we have strong constraints at a team our size.
It is best for us to control our scope
through.
I didn't keep that short but you get the idea.
No, I mean, short answers are not a, uh, as someone who asks long questions,
I probably earn long answers.
If you hear some...
that is not the blackout club that is Liam
returning to us and making his presence known
he's glaring at me right now because I won't pay attention to him
he's on the other side of the room yelling at me
um, uh, Liam's a cat
I want to add animals to the game
but that is another thing that we had to say no to ourselves about for a while
aww
yeah
I hope cosmetic pets would be good
yeah, right?
as long as it doesn't need like a skeletal mesh with rigging and AI
yeah, as long as it doesn't need to appear alive
if it's a prop
Yeah, no problem.
Just a cat that...it's like a cat model that follows you around.
Yeah.
Well, let's not get crazy with the following around.
It's pathfinding.
It's a ghost cat.
It clips through everything.
He'll G-Man along.
My reaction to your joke proposal for just adding a cat is basically my reaction to everything
anybody proposes all the time on this game.
Which is usually like, nope, we're a small team.
Nope, we're a small team.
It's a good instinct that has gotten us still plenty of features.
I will let Liam know that his request for a playable cat has been denied.
Back to serious questions, just a quick reminder for folks in chat, you can ask your own questions of our guests so that you can learn more about the making of the Blackout Club.
Let's talk about Early Access.
What's cool is in a minute here we're going to get to see the multiplayer stuff after I'm done with this bit.
How is it going for you all?
Early Access is complicated because...
It's pitched as, you know, a chance to test your game before you can make it.
In reality, for some devs, it is their first and only launch.
And then if they play it right, they'll get a second launch when they go.
What has been your, sort of, your guiding light through Steam's dark waters, I suppose?
That metaphor was darker than I intended it to be, but that's the game we're playing, isn't it?
I can take this one.
So, you know, I did not do the early...
Like, the Magic Circle did come out on Early Access.
I was not on that project, but that was largely, like, a...
You know, used for, hey, the game really is coming out in just an extra week or two.
And I think that was a really good strategy that they did.
But this time, you know, it kind of feeds into my earlier point of...
The reply about QA.
You know, we need...
We need people playing the game.
to know a lot of things, you know?
Like how is the economy working?
You know, if you've got a weird computer
we haven't tested compatibility on yet, you know,
we can afford only so much, you know,
PC compatibility lab testing time,
where somebody with, you know, 20 different rigs
tries your game and, you know,
gives you frame cap and things like that, you know.
There's so much that we just,
being a multiplayer game,
can't test all of it.
And so we knew we had to do a long early access period.
Well, we did a long beta test, right?
Like, we did beta test.
We told people we were announcing this game
at the end of February that it would be out in 2019.
But by summer of 2018, you could already
play it in a beta test if you were on a newsletter.
And then we slowly let in more rounds of people
after that from both the newsletter sign-up and then
Eventually our discord community. Yeah
And you know we had plenty of takers which was you know
We're very fortunate that the idea was strong enough that a lot of people
You know had were hyped enough to want to help test and beta test because I mean a beta is not a finished game
and you know some people
It's difficult, right because a game like fortnight is on season four of early access
Yeah
You know, it kind of becomes meaningless for larger games that will never leave early access,
because why would they? Because they don't need to.
And a lot of other games that we really enjoy, I mean I'm not trashing that approach, but
we knew that we'd, at the end of the day, still want to hit the date that we set out to do.
We still want to come out in 2019. We want to come out, you know, ideally early in 2019.
Early access is our best chance of pulling that off, and it's because we need that QA
attention, we need a community to sort of vet a lot of design ideas we're trying that
are certainly novel.
And how the community sort of reacts to a lot of surprises we have in store for them
I think is going to inform how ready the game is for full launch, if that makes sense.
But mainly it's just, you know...
It's the best way to actually do what Early Access was meant to do, which is,
hey, if you're excited about this game and you want to help its development and feedback on its development,
Early Access is wonderful.
You know, my hope is that this will be a positive experience for us.
You know, the first couple weeks have been pretty good.
We've got another update hopefully coming out at the end of this week,
before the holiday, the Thanksgiving holiday,
for people to enjoy while we're out.
We did a week one update, you know, it's certainly a lot of
Prioritization of bugs came has already come out of the early access from people who weren't in our beta
But just picked up the game for the first time aren't you know?
Dozens of missions in and their first time user experience is very different than the beta testers were
So, you know, I think the pickup and play nature of our game between you know
Day one and week one was pretty significant just in that first update
and I think it's going to be pretty noticeable again with this week's update.
We're trying to react pretty quick to that stuff.
And the hope is, right, that people feel like we're not ditching them.
Because there is that fear on early access.
You come out, you hit early access, you say,
here's an incomplete game, we'll totally get to finishing it, and then you don't.
We certainly intend to finish it.
So, that's the...
That's...
Our hope is that early access are...
You know.
long-term conversation with the community is not that long-term because there is a,
there is an actual, you know, you can see us trending towards full launch and then we hit full launch.
Right on. We're about to hit the multiplayer part, so Jordan, I'll have some questions for you based on my experience here.
First, you can watch my character creation.
Quick shoutout, I was actually pretty impressed with this creator because it was a very simple tool that let me be pretty...
Like, I could see how different people could express themselves in different ways in this thing in pretty important ways.
Like, it's pretty easy to make a character who is gender non-conforming or of different ethnicities pretty easily.
Yeah, we're trying to sort of let you define what you want to look like with your eyes rather than with sort of labels.
Yeah, although as I tested this for a minute, the dark skin looked really dark.
Yeah, it looks like your gamma is also pretty different. I think we need to be a little more aggressive with our gamma tuning.
Anyway, we are just looking...
Looking in chat, just some quick shoutouts to Snaps the Bunny, Veloxization, and Kane Asylum.
Thank you all for joining us. Remember, you can ask some questions of our guests, Michael and
Jordan. I assume some of you are actual developers on this game, so I'm sure you can just yell at
them in your own time at whatever questions you have. Sorry, I cannot make this a team meeting
as much as I would like to. It's just eavesdrop on team meetings for this game.
Moving on.
Snaps and Velocization are two of our kind of star Discord people.
Nice.
Welcome.
Jordan, I'm going to have some questions about horror design for you in a moment, but I just
want to follow up with Mike on one question related to...
So it's really, I think a lot of devs are sort of...
User acquisition is one of the giant biggest questions that everyone is talking about.
So how did you get folks...
How did you...
What was your method for getting people to sign up for the beta and then early access?
We are hashtag blessed in that we have some name recognition.
The question is, it's not our first game.
We already had a newsletter for the Magic Circle.
The company already had followers on social media.
I can imagine it is that much harder if you can't say,
hey, former Bioshock developers do X.
Clearly all of our old colleagues are doing the same trick.
I wish them the best. I think it's the right move to make.
Shout out to the molasses flood.
Yeah, absolutely.
And yeah, I just read a good what I think on their game.
Anyway, so it's a user acquisition right now.
When we started was we have a newsletter, we have a social media account.
Some people follow those things, you know, personal accounts also bring in followers.
We were lucky in that, you know, again, the credentials of the studio brought people around.
We have a PR agency we work with.
who did outreach as well to press.
So the usual stuff, right?
If you've worked on indie games or if you've worked on AAA games,
the technique is still more or less the same, right?
A PR agency or you is going to reach out to every outlet you can find
and every possible, you know, journalist who might be interested in this.
You know, try not to waste their time.
You have a press kit.
You say here are screenshots and images and basic information about the game.
Here's how you can reach us if you have more questions.
Let the world know that we have an announced trailer.
And the announced trailer we worked on for probably almost a month,
in between normal work, but there was definitely at least a good work of
really this is an important part of getting people to pay attention to us
to get that trailer done.
Even Patrick who does our audio.
and also did some audio on Molasses Flood.
Did a very cool treatment, I think, if you listen to that teaser trailer announcement that we did.
It stands out, not just because of the great art and animation that Steven did,
but also Patrick's work on audio, I think, kind of brings people in.
So we had a good trailer.
We had some name recognition, and that got us, you know,
a 5 digit number of newsletter signups.
That was enough, certainly, to populate a beta test and then some.
So we had that.
We got on Steam as quick as possible so people could wish list us.
And then that gives you like a nice, you know, just speaking
from a production standpoint, you get like a nice snowball effect
of just over time, more people tell people, you know, they tell two friends.
And so you get like a trickle of wish lists coming in
and then just any news announcement.
So, you know, we went to PAX.
To try and get some news and coverage
But also the bit I think the bigger benefit for us with Pax
You don't get quite as much news coverage as maybe I thought we would have gotten
But you do get a lot of hands-on time with real players
And that was a big deal
We got to hear him scream
And they can ask the questions that we don't think of to ask ourselves so, you know, it's a gauntlet it's way too long and
It's like four and a half full days of just like non-stop,
Hey, have you heard of the Blackout Club?
But you do get a lot of people who have now heard of the Blackout Club and want to ask you about it.
And some of them, you know, we had people coming back four days just to play the same demo again.
That's really validating and goes a long way just to team morale,
but also helping us hone the pitch and also,
you know, people who then got beta keys and joined our beta test
and got a t-shirt and hopefully are wearing it around.
You know, just kind of stuff like that that helps us find a little bit of real world validation
and also gets the word out and, you know, you can say that you were at these shows
and you can point to footage from the event.
You know, we met nice influencers like Jesse Cox who came by
and said nice things and talked about us, you know.
So we met a lot of, we made a lot of good contacts.
In terms of user acquisition.
At the moment, you know, early access we did basically the same thing we do for announcement, right?
We had a new trailer, we had a new press release, that kind of stuff.
I also think that the beta test during that time, you know, key giveaways was a way to get people interested.
And, you know, because people are spreading the word and inviting their friends who may also not have paid attention to us yet.
And it reminded people that we are a game that even though we're not coming out till next year.
There's already something you can play now.
So even though we weren't in early access yet,
people could at least anticipate that we were a real product
and not vaporware, which, you know,
I've worked on that in the past too.
And it's, at some point you need to finish the game.
So we're doing a very nice show of proof
that no, really there's a game and you can play it.
And so, but with early access right now,
I mean, our user acquisition strategy is pretty light.
If I'm honest, we want people playing the game during early access, but we do want early access players.
And the distinction meaning, in this case, you know, just a step above a beta tester.
We really do want people who expect a broken game that's totally not, you know, not done with content
and will be iterated on based on feedback from the community.
And most players are not that.
So we will be ramping up user acquisition later.
when we get closer to full launch to do like the normal,
you know, launch rollout.
And we're pretty critical with ourselves about that issue.
Like we QA pretty aggressively internally
and we don't want to release something that is unplayable
or that won't let you get XP and level up your character
or anything like that, like broken in the sense of
there are imbalanced things you can pull off
or you can make an AI look silly, that kind of stuff.
But we try very hard to make sure that.
At the very least, if you buy the game and play it right now,
you're going to have an interesting experience
and an experience that has a loop that completes,
but that you're going to,
we welcome your feedback on how to make it better.
And we have reacted to that already with our first update
and our upcoming one as well.
Yeah, but pretty much the early access feedback
has like really changed the priority
of how fast we were going to roll out stuff.
Cause it was like, oh wow,
this is an issue that people care about immediately.
I'm going to switch over because we are halfway through my successful run.
Oh yeah, this is the great part.
I saw the shape and then ran!
Yeah, that was, you were asking about, you know, designing for horror in multiplayer.
One of the biggest things that we sort of said early on is that there would be almost
no scripted jump scares.
That if there were jump scares, they would be entirely emergent out of systems interacting.
And so the close eyes mechanics where you can see that you're closing your in-game eyes
there for people who haven't played the game before and revealing this boogeyman figure.
The intent was that you would have a jump scare
just simply out of what you didn't know, right?
And where you physically were positioned
and you have to close off this major channel of information
which is the world around you to see this one thing
which is this invisible figure.
And we've had a lot of people would yelp like crazy
in a way that seems like another scripted game
but in this case, there's no two nights
that go exactly alike.
Yeah.
And all of that is, well, a lot of that,
not necessarily the shapes,
effect specifically, but that notion of dynamism is down to David Pittman working on the procedural
mission system. We're trying very hard to make it feel like a deck of cards where we shuffle
and you play a game with a blackout club and you have dealt an interesting hand and the next night
you'll be dealt a different one. And so if Patches, for example, or Jason implements a new mission,
That's like a new card that we shuffle into the deck and it will just sort of seamlessly make the experience more varied as we keep updating it.
Sorry, I'm sure you had a different question, but...
Well, I'm glad, honestly, I'm glad you chimed in on that just because that was important to call out.
Um, uh, yeah, the, um, my follow-up question would be, um, uh, what is, what makes a good mission?
It felt like to me, you're about to see me embark on a second mission and it'll go horribly wrong.
Like, we were exploring a similar space, if not the same space, but we were trying to get to a different location.
What's sort of the underlying psychology behind like making a good procedural mission in this game?
Oh well, that's something that we are certainly learning in real time. Jason coming on the team
has been just miraculous in that front, both in terms of just kind of altering the layout to allow
for more multiplayer style movement among players and more inroads to the same space, right, where
If a mission suddenly calls for you to enter from the absolute opposite end of the map,
that same space now serves all of those masters.
And his advice coming off of Payday 2, I think has helped a lot.
The biggest thing that we're noticing is that there is a very fine line between designing
a mission that...
is simple enough to be instantly parsed by a player who's dropped into a session,
they've never played the tutorial, they were invited to play on Steam by a friend,
and so they just need to follow the crosshair and do the thing that the game says.
And the other end of the spectrum, which is these very advanced players who want a range of
expression, who don't want to be told exactly what to do, who want to want to poke around in
dark corners and get lost for a while.
And we have a certain bandwidth between those extremes
in the blackout club right now,
and constantly kind of trying to find the right balance.
We're even playing with ideas for ways
to handle advanced difficulties,
sort of organically within the experience.
Whether we pull that off, TBD.
But the biggest thing has been clear entry
and exit conditions.
that can easily hand off to one another.
So the way it works right now is there's a category, like steal.
And so the kids are there to steal something.
And the description of the mission says,
okay, we're gonna take something back from the bad guys.
But then the specific thing that you're asked to steal
can be radically different.
In this case it's evidence bags.
But when you finish the evidence bags mission,
it might swap to a radically different card in the deck,
to extend the metaphor.
where suddenly you're asked to steal this bizarre
sort of wooden head that sings every time you move.
So it's kind of like T-Rex vision in Jurassic Park
or something, like every time you move, there's a problem.
And so one player has to sort of be that person
who does a burst of movement,
stands still while the other person runs around
and runs scout for them.
It's like, okay, let's go this way.
There's a lucid, which was one of our bad guys.
This direction, so follow me
because I can move without making noise.
And so.
Coming back to the point of procedural, that objective would just link up under the broader
category of steel, and so it sort of feels generally like you're doing something that
has a narrative frame around it, but that there's a certain amount of dynamism as to
which objectives you're asked to do that night. And then the kids are told to go home, and that
objective is always the same, and exfiltration can often be one of the hardest parts. So it is,
at the moment,
You tend to be asked to do two things a night.
That may extend to three to four kind of shorter things
that you might be asked to do in a row,
all part of the same category.
And we're actually adding new categories
in the upcoming update as well.
And the hope is that you get to know the Blackout Club
and the kinds of things they might do
through the broader kind of buckets
that those categories represent.
But then inside the bucket are, you know, different sort of collections of fun,
valuables, and each night you come home with a different one.
And right now, our biggest burden is content. We want a lot more mission types, a lot more
scenarios and little enemy behaviors, things like that. And we will slowly let them creep
into the build and hopefully take early access players by surprise.
Um, Dr. Thaw says Shape Boy is going to be here before we're even in the maze.
Rip.
Uh, yeah, this one doesn't go so well.
Um, God, this moment, when that, when that, when this jerk run, jump through
that window, I was very unpleased.
Um, uh, I, I haven't, the going through windows stuff was a lot, it was a lot of
work, uh, you know, props to Kane, who is I think in that chat right now, uh, for
the windows and a lot, just our general mantle movement set.
Overall, I think, in a long way.
But during all that time, there's a way for your friends to get you back in the game by tagging you and pulling you back to life.
You can see us try that later. It's gonna go badly. This run goes badly.
What was the mindset behind that? And even though horror is supposed to be about the threat of death,
why was it so essential for you to give players a lot of ways to get back in control before dying?
It's a combination.
Because once you have fully failed, there's a certain loss of your time investment.
You know, you have to restart and because you might have been asked to do several procedural
objectives in a row, we wanted to make sure that it wasn't too frustrating.
And so...
That notion of partial failure is a lesson I learned all the way as far back as the Thief series when I was working with Randy Smith and co.
I don't know if you've met him.
Oh yeah.
We've, we've interviewed Randy, I think on the stream before.
I imagined you might see, I just guessed that because of GDC, et cetera.
But, um, uh, you know, he talked a lot about the role of partial failure in games that even claim to support stealth.
Right.
And even though ours is not, uh, stealth only, um, that idea of, okay.
The game is really fun and really scary when I'm almost screwed,
but not entirely screwed. Can I pull it back up before the mountain?
Can I recover this situation?
And so there's a lot of otherwise you get poor stealth, right? Where, um,
it's insta fail. Uh, like a lot of,
a lot of action games that try to have the single stealth mission where you're,
you just kind of feel like you've been slapped on the wrist by the hand of God.
And, um,
and
it
Each individual kid is caught too many times, then they are deemed to be too large of a risk, and then it's curtains.
Um, and so I don't know if that happens here.
Which is what is happening here.
That's me, right there, we're watching me.
And now we're watching my friends who are, my new friends who are trying to get us out.
Right, and there's a, you know, just from a gameplay standpoint, you know, if you think about, like I worked on the Borderlands, uh, the first Borderlands,
and like, the rescue mechanic, that last ditch mechanic, you know,
They added a lot to the game when they finally put it in.
Probably the hundreds of hours I spent testing led to an innate assumption about cooperative
If you can't save your friend, you know, it's what they did in Gears of War as well, right?
Like saving your friend is just a big part of the experience.
And reviving in general is a good part of like, we're in this together,
we're going to get this sorted.
And so a lot of really interesting things came about when we said, okay, your friend isn't dead.
Your friend is a sleepwalker.
Your friend has now become a dynamic challenge.
Yeah.
The game changes, like the whole experience flips.
And suddenly, you know.
It's not over, and it's also now become a little bit more interesting.
Yeah, and on that note...
You have a chance to be a hero.
Exactly, exactly. On that note,
that this genre that we're sort of trying to build the first major game version of,
the bond between the kids and the sort of vicarious experience of kind of wanting to be one of those kids
and having friendships that strong is a big part of the thrill.
It's not just the horror, it's not just the notion of them sort of...
using curse words for the first time at each other.
It's that notion that they're friends to the end,
that they would die for one another.
And that is in the deep DNA of this game.
We really wanted you to feel like
You were part of a group that your friendship is all you have.
And one of the things that's kind of funny about the Blackout Club is that we don't strictly
enforce it. You can absolutely not just fail an objective, but as long as you've succeeded
at one objective, you get some experience. Failure sort of teaches the club. But then
on top of that, there's a bonus for leaving with everybody, everybody not sleepwalking,
everybody intact.
And it's, but you can, you can go through hundreds of missions and level up your character without doing that.
You can abandon your friends and it can be fine, but nobody does.
We've watched so many people play this game on Twitch and so forth, and they always want to go back for each other,
even when they're playing with randos, which we find deeply heartwarming.
And it feels like the themes are working.
Nice, well as we're about to see my run here is about to wrap up.
My recorded footage is about to shut off for the day.
But yeah, Jordan and Mike, I guess Patches, can I call you Patches?
Am I in the Patches club?
Yeah, Jordan and Patches, thank you so much for joining us today.
This was a really cool chat and I'm really excited to see where
development on the Blackout Club goes going forward.
It's our pleasure. Thanks for having us.
For the folks at home, if you are watching, if you are interested in more streams, we
would love it if you hit the follow button because we're going to be talking to a lot
of other great devs for the rest of the year, into 2019, and as we get ready for GDC 2019.
Brief disclosure, this will be going up on Gamma Sutra later today. Gamma Sutra and GDC
are owned by the same parent organization, which is now Informa.
If you are interested in going to GDC, I would like to recommend you scroll down and click the register button.
Right now is the best time to register because these are the lowest prices, blah blah blah.
My bosses are not going to like hearing me say blah blah blah about our darn show.
But yeah, anyway, this is what we're all about.
Talk to game developers, learn more about the art of game development, share that information with the other game developers.
Liz is a noob, you just got here. Don't worry, we're going to archive this and put it on Gamasutra.
The VOD will go up on the Twitch channel.
We're going to make sure you can watch it and, you know, see what you missed out on.
With that, if they have any questions, where should they ask you guys?
I assume the Discord channel is a good place to go.
Yeah, it's easy. Just go to discord.gg.
Slash the blackout Club all one word. We also yeah are on Twitter at the blackout Club
I'm at at null speak
We tend we tend to engage with Twitter quite a bit just because we get questions there that don't make it to discord
But if you if you just find the blackout Club on steam
We try to be on that on the discussions community hub as well
Although I'm not as good at that as the discord right on with that. Have a good day everyone. Bye. Thanks for having us