Hello, my name is Joshua Cook.
I'm an art director at Ubisoft Toronto.
Thank you for coming out to my talk,
The Color of Enlightenment,
Defining Shangri-La within Far Cry 4.
Back in 2013, our team at Ubisoft Toronto
was approached by Ubisoft Montreal
to collaborate on its upcoming Far Cry 4 project.
Our mission was to bring the mythical world
of Shangri-La to life in a way that felt unique
and memorable.
yet consistent with the world of Far Cry.
This presentation is a glimpse into our development
of this world within a world,
and we'll focus on how our team defined Shangri-La
by creating a strict set of visual rules
focused primarily on color to guide us through production.
Before we get into that,
let me tell you a little bit about myself.
I've been working at Ubisoft nearly 10 years now,
splitting my time equally between five years
in the Montreal studio.
and five in Toronto. I started out as a 3D artist back on Rainbow Six Vegas
I've worked on a bunch of really great titles including Assassin's Creed
Far Cry 2, Splinter Cell Conviction
and Blacklist. My most recent project was Far Cry 4
where I was the art director for the Shangri-La content. For those of you not
familiar
with Shangri-Las, I'd like to show you a quick video so you know what I'm talking about here.
In these uncertain times, look to our past for guidance.
Transcend the depths of your own mind into the spiritual world of Shangri-La.
You will fight alongside a mythical tiger and confront the evil forces that once threatened this legendary realm.
In this world, the rules of reality don't apply, but the consequences are very real.
What you do with this world is entirely up to you.
Far Cry 4
So that is Shangri-La. At least that's the version that we shipped with.
As you can see, our world is very strange and surreal.
And it's probably not at all what you would think about when you think about Far Cry.
When you think about Far Cry, you probably picture something more like this.
So that's what I want to talk about today, how we created our world within this one.
I'd like to share a little story with you.
After our first big press event in Montreal, where we finally unveiled Shangri-La for the first time,
we were traveling back to the airport in a cab with our creative director, Max Bilan.
And we were discussing how the interviews went, and of course I asked him,
did you get any good questions about the art?
And he said, yeah.
They asked me how we came up with the look for our world,
and I told them...
It was easy. We just took a screenshot of the main game into Photoshop and pressed Ctrl-I to invert and voila.
And I'm just like, you ass.
Max likes to give me a hard time, so I'm pretty sure he never actually told them that, but it was foreign press, so for all I know there could be an article out there in German or something quoting that.
The point is, he said it to me because he knew it would drive me crazy.
because he knew how much thought we actually put into it
and how much we struggled to get to where we were at that time.
That little joke was something that stuck with me
and it was really the first thing that came to my mind
when I was approached about doing a talk.
I wanted to set the record straight
and talk about how we actually defined our look
and more specifically how we used color to do it.
And for anyone wondering what happens when you do invert this in Photoshop,
there you go.
Not so hot.
and clearly not how we define the look of our world.
When I was first tasked with creating Shangri-La,
I traveled to the Montreal studio to sync up with the art director for Far Cry 4,
Jean-Alexis Doyon.
He's a very talented guy and he was also the art director for Far Cry 3 as well.
One of the main things he imparted on me for the overall look of the game was
Far Cry owns the colors.
This is a pillar of the art direction and of the franchise.
We don't want to make a game that's another brown-gray shooter.
We want to embrace the color.
That philosophy, along with some of the initial inspiration pieces
and reference images provided by the team in Montreal,
would lay the foundations for the world we would create.
The most compelling references for us came from the holy festival of Nepal,
the festival of colors.
It's an ancient Hindu religious festival where participants color each other
with dry powder and water.
And you can see the imagery is very powerful and compelling.
The world is completely blanketed and transformed by the colors.
This really inspired us to explore a wide variety of looks
for the world of Shangri-La.
Initially, Shangri-La was a very different place.
The main idea was we would create a miniature open world set
in the main character's mind, a strange dreamscape that
would be broken up and interspersed
with different visions and stories.
We wanted to explore using different color schemes
to separate these different aspects of the world
from each other, dividing it up between dream,
nightmare, and memory, each with their own unique look,
feel, and content.
So the amazing concept artists in both Montreal and Toronto
explored tons of different looks and created a bunch
of really inspiring concept pieces for us
for both the environments and the characters.
Due to our tight production timeline,
we simultaneously went directly into production
of actual game content.
Fleshing out the world of Shangri-La
while exploring the visual identity was very tricky
and it's something I hope we will avoid next time.
This was a period of a lot of back and forth
between us and the core team in Montreal.
You get a sense of the kind of changes
we were going through from the concepts
which were just barely ahead of production.
One day the section of the map would have one look,
the next it could completely change.
and change and change.
Not just visually, but with the gameplay experience as well.
The problem really came down to everyone's idea
of a dream world is different.
And because we were exploring the ideas
and experimenting with finding our identity
at the same time as production,
we ended up creating a lot of extra work for ourselves,
as well as creating conflict and uncertainty
amongst the team and between the two studios.
The turning point for us
came at a key time in development when we decided to refocus our efforts on creating
a tighter, more simplified experience.
We went from a wide open world telling multiple stories simultaneously to a more refined sequential
journey that would focus entirely on one ancient legend.
The player would relive a mythical tale of a warrior's discovery of paradise and his
encounters with the demonic invading forces.
On the art side, we embraced this opportunity to refocus the direction.
At the time, I was collaborating with an assistant art director in Montreal by the name of Marco
Bosheman.
Marco is an experienced art director with a strong background in teaching, and he was
really critical in helping us to focus on creating a set of rules based on what was
most important.
Rules that could easily be communicated and we could all agree upon to guide us forward
to the end of production.
We decided to simplify what Shangri-La was to a paradise world hidden deep in the Himalayan
mountains.
We focused on the concept of what paradise would be to the people living in Karat, a
contemplative world, simple and inviting like a warm, glowing fireplace.
To help achieve a sense of balance and simplicity, we reduced from the more modern, multicolored
world of Karat to a more ancient, natural world.
with a simple dual tone color scheme
made up primarily of red and gold.
For our enemies, we wanted to maintain the same look
and associations from Karat
by maintaining the blue color scheme.
With the focus clarified, our studios agreed
on a concise set of rules for color usage
that were then incorporated into a new design bible
that was created to define the look
and game experience of our world.
It was much more rigid than a style guide
and I found these rules to be a very effective way to simplify the decision making process
and streamline our production.
I would like to share with you the ones we defined for color usage, which I feel were
most critical and valuable to us in production.
Gold.
Gold was our foundation.
We chose it to bring a sense of warmth and richness and overall dream-like quality to
the world.
We decided to use it for the sky, the terrain, and rocks, all architecture, statues, and lighting.
This led to a couple key production decisions, including locking our time of day.
This greatly reduced the workload of our lighting artists and enabled us to tailor the environments in a way that would not have been possible otherwise.
Soft golden lighting also gave the world a very warm and welcoming feel to it.
also maintaining a single color scheme throughout the world,
and now enabled us to simplify our architectural look
to a more sculptural, carved from the rock feel
that helped round our world
and give it a very ancient feeling,
a sense that everything really belonged here.
Red.
Red is the other half of the overall dual-tone look
we established for our world.
The red is what brings the distinct look to Shangri-La.
and makes the world feel very strange and surreal.
It also helps create a complimentary experience to the main campaign.
We knew the question of why red was going to come up a lot,
and we wanted to have a good answer for it besides,
you know, it looks amazing.
So our writer, Naveed Kavari, he created this great legend
of how the goddess who created Shangri-La
pricked her finger in a moment of frustration
and her blood spilled out and it transformed the world.
I got a lot of mileage out of that one during our press tours,
and it really felt good to have a satisfying answer
and reasoning behind the logic of our world.
We chose to use the red for all the vegetation,
the water, and of course the blood of the slaughtered animals.
A big effect this choice had on production was
that by simplifying the look for our vegetation,
we required much less variety than we had already planned.
Orange.
Orange is our color of interaction.
We chose to use it because it offers just enough pop in the environment to stand out
without being too obvious or breaking the overall look.
We used orange on our climbing ledges, our explosive pots, yes, even ancient paradise
world needs things that blow up, and also the handle of the prayer wheels, which act
as interactive switches that enable player progress throughout our world.
During the playtest, before we added it to the handles,
I observed many players circling around the wheels,
trying to figure them out,
and ignoring the giant handles sticking out the side.
But as soon as we introduced the orange powder,
I was amazed at the difference
this little splash of color made.
We saw an immediate improvement
in the understanding of the players.
White.
White is great for creating a sense of purity and sacredness.
so it was a natural choice to use it to define our sacred elements.
The white acts as an accent color throughout the world
to highlight these sacred elements and create visual interest.
The white is used for the prayer flags,
the prayer candles,
all the animals, and the protector,
the white tiger companion who fights along your side.
The decision to go with all white animals was not just an artistic choice,
but it also tied into the game design as well.
Originally, we had planned to have predator animals in the world,
but as we embraced the idea that the player was meant to be a protector of this world,
running around and slaughtering animals just didn't feel right.
It was supposed to be something only the demons would do.
So we removed the predator animals and made all our creatures passive and white
to give them a sense of innocence and purity.
This choice drastically reduced the overall workload of the character,
design, and programming teams.
The white fur also really enhanced the contrast of the blood and brutality of the slaughtered
animals found throughout our world.
Blue.
Blue is the color of evil in Shangri-La.
We needed to use a color that would really stand out and feel very foreign in a world
of red and gold.
The decision to use blue on our enemies originated from the enemies of the main game.
who were themselves inspired by the Nepalese police force.
We really wanted to play off the players' established associations
from the world of Karate of blue equals enemies.
And because it is so out of place in the world we created,
the blue really helped to make the enemies stand out
and feel that they do not belong in this place.
In the last missions of Shangri-La,
as the player draws closer to the final confrontation,
We chose to coat the whole world in a blue light to really emphasize the enemy's presence and effect on the world.
Note that even though we tinted the world blue, we still managed to preserve the reds in the vegetation through color correction.
This ensured that we would maintain the signature Shangri-La look that we were trying to create.
Another color-related aspect I'd like to touch on quickly, as I feel it's pretty important,
is our use of color transitions.
We chose to use the color transitions boldly and abruptly
to accentuate a couple key events.
The first one is the opening visit
of your first time in Shangri-La.
I actually had to fight really hard
to make this one happen
as a lot of people felt it was unnecessary.
But for me, sometimes you gotta fight for things.
Because we wouldn't know what the player was doing
or where they were coming from when they entered the world,
I felt it was critical that we create an opening sequence that would really accentuate the transition.
This was really inspired for me by the movie The Wizard of Oz.
The world of Oz is even more vibrant and shocking when you first encounter it
because of its contrast with the black and white intro,
and I wanted to craft a similar experience.
So instead of dropping the player directly into our world,
we send them back just a little bit further in the story.
to the moment just before Kalanag leaves the snowy mountaintops
and enters our world through an underwater passage.
This allowed us complete control and it really enhanced our introduction.
This transition from an almost colorless world
into a vibrant shores of Shangri-La is very powerful
and in the end it was totally worth it.
The other key transition is at the very end of Shangri-La
as the player defeats the giant Rakshasa.
and the presence of evil is visibly lifted from the world
and it is restored back to its full vibrant glory.
This wrapped up the experience nicely
and really helped to emphasize that the player's actions
had actually affected the world.
With our choices established
and the color rules firmly in place
to maintain a consistent look throughout our world,
the artists were then freed to create beautiful
and compelling spaces without the worries
of uncertainty or change.
We were also able to be very confident that we'd be delivering content to the core team
that would not contain any unwanted surprises or conflict with the overall vision for the
world.
One more video.
Where we were, kinda think, bet you pause, all alone
Port winners, I burn autumn
Guts niggas so Kirk-mama
Ill-bombed, got a crush on her
I gotta wait in line for that
Ain't nobody got time for that
Ain't nobody got a rhyme for that
Too true like it's too changed
Blue blood, lucky both gangs
When we were, kinda thick
Bet you'd fall, all alone
When that video came out, I was super proud.
To me, this was all the confirmation that I needed
that we had achieved all our goals.
We created a world that fit perfectly
with the world of Karat
and enhanced the overall Far Cry experience.
If there's one thing I'd like you to take away from this,
besides the fact that Ubisoft has amazing artists,
it's that color is a very powerful tool.
Not just for making things look great and interesting,
but also for helping to define your worlds.
This approach won't necessarily work for everything, but for us, defining a distinct set of rules for color usage,
our team simplified the production process, reduced arguments, and made all our choices easier.
All while creating a unique and memorable experience that defines Shangri-La within Far Cry 4.
Thank you.
If you have any questions or you'd like to chat about anything, please come see me in
the wrap-up room or find me this afternoon at 12.30 in the Ubisoft Lounge, West Hall,
third floor.
Thank you again.