My name is Lucas Leminski, and I'm a senior concept artist
for ZeniMax Online Studios.
Hold on one second.
I jumped the gun on myself here.
Okay, here we go.
Okay.
Yeah, I'm a senior concept artist for ZeniMax Online Studios
where my main responsibility is producing
key art illustrations for The Elder Scrolls Online.
And just to give you a bit of background on myself before we get started, I originally
went to college for illustration at Syracuse University in upstate New York.
A lot of Syracuse fans next door.
And although Syracuse is a great school, their traditional media curriculum didn't really
prepare me for a career as a concept artist, which had always been my primary career goal.
So after Syracuse, I decided to go to grad school
at the Savannah College of Art and Design,
where I focused more specifically on 3D art for games.
And shortly after graduating from SCAD,
I was hired at Turbine in Boston,
where I worked on The Lord of the Rings Online
and a short-lived DC Comics MOBA called Infinite Crisis.
And then in 2015, I moved to Baltimore
to work for ZeniMax Online Studios,
where I've been painting the key art illustrations
for The Elder Scrolls Online ever since.
And...
I imagine a lot of you are familiar with the game, but in case you're not, I'm just going
to give a bit of background on the Elder Scrolls Online, or ESO for short.
Our game is an MMO set in the Elder Scrolls universe, taking place about a thousand years
before the events of Skyrim.
But unlike preceding Elder Scrolls titles, ESO is not developed by Bethesda, but by one
of its sister companies, ZeniMax Online Studios, or as we call it on the dev team, ZOS.
The game launched on PC in 2014
and on Xbox and PlayStation in 2015.
It currently has around a million monthly active players
and we continue to support that player population
with a regular release cadence
of four major content updates per year.
And as part of the marketing campaign for each update,
Zost tasks me with producing a highly detailed,
hand-painted digital illustration in-house.
And of course, that's what we're here to talk about.
So my goal for today is to give you a peek
behind the curtain at ZAS,
showing the process I use to create these illustrations
and the various competing influences other than me
that ultimately shape the outcome of the final artwork.
So more specifically, first I'm gonna try to clarify
exactly what I mean when I refer to key art for ESO,
plus how it's used to support the game
and the main parameters we use to evaluate
the success of completed marketing illustrations.
From there, I'm going to show some examples
of how I try to balance
the sometimes contradictory demands of the various parties
that have a stake in the key art.
And once we understand how they serve to limit my options
when designing compositions,
I'm going to dig really deep into the details
of some of the strategies that I use
for visually crafting narrative
within single image illustrations.
And then finally, I'll try to show
how I put all those ideas into practice
by walking through the full production process
for one of my completed illustrations.
It's an ambitious itinerary,
and we're already on the clock, so let's get started.
Key art is a term that can mean a lot of different things
in different contexts, so rather than get stuck
in the weeds on terminology, I wanted to find key art
solely according to the way we use the term on ESO.
When we talk about key art at Zoss,
we're specifically referring to the illustrations
that we use to market new content releases
for the Elder Scrolls Online.
They're single images intended to be
the primary visual representation
of the content release they each accompany.
So basically, you can think of key art
as the rough equivalent of box art, but for a digital game.
The key art is featured on the ESO website and gets used in ad banners across the internet.
And they're also released as desktop backgrounds and promotional posters at conventions and
other fan events.
And just to be clear, I should mention that the marketing campaign for ESO's big annual expansion in the second quarter of each year
also includes a cinematic trailer, a logo refresh, and a CG key art banner, which are all built using CG 3D assets.
All that stuff is outsourced to creative agencies, which means I'm not involved in their production.
So for the purposes of this presentation, I'm not going to be including any of these within our definition of key art,
and we're just going to be pretending that these things don't even exist.
Okay, so this is what the key art production process looks like at the broadest level.
We start with two to three weeks of planning and development, where I research the story
and iterate on several rounds of comps, short for compositional sketches, before getting
the green light to go ahead with a particular composition.
I then move on to the main production phase in earnest, which usually takes about six
weeks.
So the whole process takes about eight weeks in total, which is a really long time to spend
working on a single illustration, and nobody knows that more than I do.
However, my art director prefers that I focus on realism
and detail rather than speed, and he likes me
to take a constructive approach to figure production.
And because of the variety of potential use cases
for the key art, I also paint it at a very high resolution
which allows for smaller areas to be repurposed
for different uses in the future.
And all of these things contribute
to a longer production time frame.
And since Zoss invests so much into these images,
and they feature so prominently in the way the game is presented to the public,
the key art sits at the intersection of various competing interests,
and the stakeholders for those interests each get varying degrees of input into its development.
So traditionally, it's more typical for a studio to outsource the production of marketing assets like key art to a freelance illustrator.
or a creative agency, and the discrete nature
of that vendor-client relationship forces
all revision requests through a single point of contact,
usually represented by a marketing art director
who is typically not the same person that's in charge
of the in-house game dev art team.
But because I produce the key art in-house
as a member of the development team,
our art director at Zoss is able to exert
a much more direct influence
over the final look of the key art,
which tends to result in the illustrations.
more effectively intimating that same character and tone
that's shared by the rest of our game's content.
But it also means that I'm more directly confronted
by the needs of different stakeholders
than I would be under the traditional freelance model.
So let's diagram those stakeholders
and my relationship to them.
As the illustrator, I sit in the center of this diagram
and the ESO art director represents my primary source
of critique and feedback.
But he's only one of several members of management
that get a say in which of my comps
is approved for production.
I call this group the executive team, and it includes Zas's studio director, the general
manager, and finally the Elder Scrolls brand manager who works at Bethesda and represents
their marketing department.
Each member of the executive team has de facto veto power over any of my compositions.
My art director insulates me from direct communication with the other executives as much as possible
so that he represents the single source of directorial feedback for me.
Now, in one sense, this is really helpful
because I'm not faced with the challenge
of reconciling contradictory requests
after submitting each round of sketches,
but on the other hand, when my art director
has to relay feedback on behalf of the other executives,
it can sometimes be tough to determine the essence
of the original critique that I really need to respond to.
It also makes it impossible for me
to advocate for my own concerns directly,
so I have to rely solely on my art director's impulse
to push back against decisions that I might not agree with.
I also get content-related input from the ESO Loremaster,
and yes, that is his actual job title.
And he ensures that nothing I'm including
in the illustration contradicts rules previously established
in other parts of the Elder Scrolls universe.
So while the left side of this diagram
is full of stakeholders telling me
what the key art needs to look like,
the right side will represent downstream dependencies
for the key art.
And none of the stakeholders on this side
have directorial oversight of my work,
but they do each need me to hit particular benchmarks.
to facilitate their own uses for the artwork.
So the creative services team needs the key art
to conform to specific technical parameters
so that they can process it for various use cases
before handing it off to the web team,
which publishes it on the ESO website,
along with promotional copy written by ESO
community managers who use the key art
to help frame the focus of their content
while also sharing the key art in social media posts.
Meanwhile, my producer manages and enforces my deadline.
in concert with the lead concept artist
who really functions as my manager
and helps to facilitate my interactions
with the other teams.
So with all of these parties involved,
my task in creating key art sadly isn't as simple
as just painting a pretty picture.
In fact, in addition to the technical specs
required by the key art's eventual use,
the content of what I paint is more broadly guided
by a series of persistent marketing goals.
And we use these as parameters to gauge the success
of proposed sketches, and they greatly influence
how and why I arrive at my final compositions.
So, here they are.
First off, the primary purpose of the key art
is to generate player excitement for new content updates.
And of course, we want to attract players
that would be interested in playing the type of game
we're actually made, so it's important that the key art
help establish expectations for the specific
gameplay experience we're offering.
ESO is not a horror game or a comedy,
it's a social dungeon questing RPG,
and the key art needs to convey a tone of adventure
and meaningful character interaction
that's representative of what players will experience
when they log in.
And of course, the key art needs to highlight
the new features and setting of the content update
that it accompanies.
This seems obvious,
but it does have more detailed implications,
like decisions to clothe the characters
in newly created armor and outfits
to reflect the gear that players will be able to collect
in the accompanying update.
ESO is also extremely story driven,
and the key art needs to reflect that
by being focused on narrative as well.
Now this is a major point of emphasis for my art director.
He's always pushing me to inject as much narrative
as possible into the key art,
and as we'll see, that heavily influences
the content of the compositions that I develop.
And then finally, another important requirement
is that our key art feature
emotionally resonant player characters.
Emphasis on the player character part.
Bethesda's marketing department insists
that the key art for ESO include figures
that the player can imagine themselves inhabiting
based on the type of experiences
offered to them by the gameplay.
That means that I can't just depict
off-screen story moments occurring between NPCs.
A figure representing the player
must always be involved in the action
and that demand introduces a whole host of complications
that require creative solutions.
And we'll be talking about that more in just a minute.
Now, with all that in mind,
You can see how planning one of these illustrations
is an exercise in problem solving.
Luckily, the demands that I'm talking about
rarely contradict one another outright.
However, they rarely all serve in the best interest
of achieving an elegant composition,
which is my primary concern.
So the struggle for me becomes finding my way
to an aesthetically competent visual solution
while also accommodating external requests
that severely handicap my ability to do that.
And to demonstrate how this works in practice,
what I want to do now is highlight
three specific challenges that I come up against
pretty frequently.
and which have a significant impact on how these illustrations tend to turn out.
And to make it easier to distinguish between them, I've given them each a catchy name.
So we have the Mandate, the Black Ball, and the Chimera.
I'm going to explain each of these one by one and show examples of how they impact my work.
So we'll talk about the Mandate first, and it's basically my shorthand to refer to that last parameter I mentioned earlier,
where I'm required to include player characters in every key art illustration that I produce.
This tends to be extremely problematic,
both compositionally and narratively,
because if you're going to put an extra character in a scene,
that character needs to have a reason to be there.
He has to have an important role
because we don't want to give the impression
that our players are essentially spectators to the action.
Additionally, player characters are deliberately conceived
of as blank canvases onto which players
can imprint their own stories.
So there's nothing specifically unique
about raw player characters' identities or backstories
that enables viewers to engage with them.
And that means that the relevance
to the illustration's narrative
has to be derived performatively.
That is, they have to be doing something.
Unfortunately, as with any game type,
there's a limit to the types of activities
players can actually participate in while playing an MMO,
some of which I've listed here.
And we could depict scenes of players
engaging in these activities,
but that would violate some of the other items
on our list of goals and parameters, right?
For instance, as a rule, available player activities
remain the same for each update,
but key art is supposed to be focused on new content.
So I can't just do like a crafting illustration
or a fishing illustration and call it key art.
There's nothing exciting about that.
And in part, that's because those activities
don't lend themselves to a compelling narrative,
and our key art is supposed to be fundamentally focused
on the main narrative of an update.
The activities that I listed on the last slide
may represent ways that the players
experience new story content,
but they don't represent the unique appeal of that content,
and that's something that the key art is supposed to do.
Furthermore, the activity depicted in the key art
can't be so specific to an individual quest
that it ignores the larger role-playing theme of the update.
Now, when new systems are introduced in an update,
things get a lot easier for me.
For example, when we launch a new guild
that players can join,
then we can specifically depict players engaging
in the activity defining that guild.
So the Thieves Guild is obviously a fraternity of thieves,
and so the key art for our Thieves Guild update
could logically focus on player characters
committing a heist.
Likewise, the Dark Brotherhood is a group of assassins,
and so the key art for that update
naturally depicted player characters
performing an assassination.
Similarly, our Morrowind expansion
included the new Warden player class,
so we had an obvious opportunity
to showcase player characters
utilizing the new class's skill line.
And then finally,
Our Homestead update introduced a new player housing system,
so an ideal solution was to show player characters
inhabiting a private home.
These pieces fulfilled the new content
and main narrative parameters because they each more or less
represented the marketing focus of the update,
and because they established a new role-playing concept
for us to highlight.
But without a new system to feature,
the marketing push typically focuses
on a new playable zone or dungeon or a story-based theme,
and finding ways to meaningfully include player characters
in those becomes a real challenge.
In these cases, I have to ask myself the question,
what's the difference between a player character
and an NPC, visually speaking?
It's a question that doesn't really have a specific answer.
For example, one of the two compositions you see here
was rejected for a lack of player characters in it.
Which one is it?
Let's go for some audience participation here.
I know these are just unfinished line drawings,
but raise your hand if you think the one on the left
failed to include player characters.
Okay, and then raise your hand if you think
it was the one on the right.
All right, so people who chose the left were correct,
but I'm not surprised that the room is torn.
It's an unfair question, because oftentimes
the player character designation is only clear
if you already understand the backstory of the quest design.
And that's information that most consumers won't have
when they first see the image anyway.
In short, there is no significant visual distinction
between a player character and an NPC,
which is kind of the point.
So what's the executive team's way
of identifying player characters in these sketches?
Well, in my experience, they seem to recognize
player characters in key art
according to the following parameters.
They're looking for a cluster of three figures
of different races, who are typically foreigners
to the location of the new content.
and preferably outfitted with gear indicative
of different player classes.
Now, these parameters have never been
explicitly defined for me.
This is just what I've gleaned over time
based on which of my compositions have been rejected
and which have been greenlighted.
But the hidden cost of having to accommodate
the player character mandate is that it forces me
to forsake a lot of great off-screen story moments
because there's just no way to inject
player characters into them.
Okay, that is the mandate.
So now let's talk about the black ball,
which is basically the mandate's opposite.
So the black ball represents the kind of seemingly random blanket prohibitions that executive stakeholders sometimes place on certain compositional elements.
One of the more problematic of these is the directive that I can't show main characters that are turned away from the viewer.
Now that might not seem like a big deal at first, and it's certainly an understandable request given that heroic character backs have become something of a trope in marketing imagery.
And admittedly, avoiding the overused example shown here is not a bad idea.
But there are also many cases where it's compositionally and narratively useful to depict the main character facing away from the viewer.
And the reason for that has to do with the limitations of single-image visual narrative.
We're going to get deep here, okay.
Fundamentally, the spatial link between a figure's face and the object of their attention results in two parallel image planes that face one another.
And it's generally impossible to see the fronts of two surfaces at the same time when they're facing in opposite directions.
Cinema deals with this.
by cutting between multiple reverse shots.
So one shot shows the character's POV,
while a second shot will show the character's reaction
to what we just saw.
But in key art illustration, we don't have the luxury
of multiple POV shots, so oftentimes,
we're forced to choose between focusing on the character
or focusing in what she's looking at.
And doing the latter typically means
we see the character's back instead of her face.
Now, while focusing on the character
is certainly the primary conduit
for evoking emotion in the viewer,
the character's object of interest
is oftentimes more powerful.
in being narratively informative.
Why is that?
Well, in its simplest form, you can think of narrative as the presentation of cause
and effect.
So first, there is an inciting incident, and then drama emerges from the way the consequences
of that incident play out.
For example, if an earthquake causes a tsunami, the predictable consequences of death and
destruction are likely to follow.
In character-centric illustration,
whatever challenge the characters are shown
to be confronting is what occupies the role of cause,
and the character's reaction to it represents the effect.
As a rule, an effect is more easily inferred
than its cause, so it's easier for a viewer
to guess at what a character's reaction
to an incident will be than it is to guess
at the situation that was responsible
for producing that reaction.
The viewer needs to see evidence
of whatever situation a character is facing
in order to understand what's at stake
and to sympathize with what they're experiencing.
So returning to our tsunami example,
if we want to plan an illustration
that conveys the essence of the rudimentary narrative
we've set up here,
and we can only focus on one of these story beads,
which image should we keep in order to retain
as much of the story as possible?
I would argue that the first image is more useful.
Consider if we were to take that first image away
and only see an image of death and destruction,
well, there are any number of situations
that may have led to that result.
including a tornado, a fire, or some kind of military action.
But if we keep only the inciting incident,
well, its resulting consequences are usually
much more predictable.
Conversely, an illustration that only
focuses on a character's reaction to a conflict
without showing what that conflict is, well,
that robs us of some very powerful storytelling tools.
And since we want to show both the cause and its effect
within a single illustration.
The problem with the black ball demand
is that it requires me to make two facing planes
visible to the viewer simultaneously
from a single point of view.
The most straightforward way to do that
is to view the scene side on,
but that forces the composition to be set up
like everything is occurring on a theater stage,
which is pretty boring.
Of course, it is possible to find other solutions
to this restriction, but the black ball
still significantly limits the types of images
and stories that I can effectively tackle in ESO key art.
Okay, so that's the black ball.
And just to review, the mandate forces extra elements
into the key art, while the black ball restricts
the options I have at my disposal
to incorporate them gracefully.
And collectively, they limit my ability
to generate clear, concise compositions for new key art,
which in turn leads to the third major challenge,
which is the chimera, expanding the scope of a composition
to accommodate disparate marketing goals.
This one's the killer.
The chimera basically refers to efforts
to shoehorn extra compositional elements,
such as player characters.
into a narrative that wasn't designed to fit them.
More often than not, this comes about
when stakeholders propose their own solutions
to the problems created by the two preceding challenges,
and it's by far the biggest source of scope creep
I encounter with the key art.
So as an example, let's take a look at the set of comps
that I developed for our 2017 third quarter update,
the Horns of the Reach.
And each comp you see here depicts
an off-screen story moment extrapolated
from the content of the main quest.
Now, while I knowingly omitted player characters
from the top two sketches,
the bottom two were conceived to allow for certain figures
to be interpretable as either player characters or NPCs.
In spite of that, the executive team preferred this sketch
from the top row.
But since it didn't include player characters,
they requested that I modify the composition to add them in.
Now, that was problematic because the ritual
that I'm showing take place here doesn't allow.
for the player to have any active role in the scene.
Players don't actually participate in
or witness this ritual in game,
it's only mentioned by NPCs,
and player characters just wouldn't make sense
within the context of the story
that this composition was intended to tell.
But due to production time constraints,
and because the stakeholders
had already endorsed this composition,
I had to find a way to fit player characters
in there somehow.
And my art director's solution was to expand the image.
by framing this composition with player characters sneaking up on the ritual in order to stop
it from being performed.
So that caused the scope of the illustration to expand immensely.
It also created this strange image within an image effect where the foreground scene
of the player characters framing the action that's taking place in the background makes
the original scene seem even more vignetted and remote.
Not to mention, it more than doubled the total surface area
that I had to render and resulted in a lot of after hours
and weekend work to get this thing completed
before the deadline.
And the real kicker was that for the final ad campaign,
somebody decided to crop the image back down
to my original composition anyway
for most social media posts, so we are not a fan of that.
Get that out of there.
There are two relevant takeaways from this example.
The first is that adding characters
dramatically increases production time.
While my producer tries to accommodate me when the scope of an illustration changes,
oftentimes the additional work required exceeds the additional time available for me to complete it.
So it's in my personal interest to avoid character bloat.
But more importantly, showing more oftentimes doesn't make the composition better.
In fact, it may overcrowd the image, complicate the read, and make the picture feel too busy.
Now the image within an image framing device
that ended up being used in that last example
is worth a little more discussion before we move on
because it's an idea that gets suggested semi-frequently
as a way to stretch a single illustration on ESO
to include more complex plot elements
than it can comfortably hold.
And to show what I mean, let's take a look
at the selected sketch for the Cigic Order key art
that I painted for ESO's Summer Set update
where we can see all three challenges at play.
So first, the chimera issue is represented
by the picture-in-picture effect created
by imagery appearing inside a magical holographic vision
at the top of the sketch here.
And that's because in the corresponding content,
the mages of the Psijagoda were spatially removed
from the events of the main quest line,
so I was asked to include this floating,
magical snow globe element as a way
of symbolically representing the threat
that the players would face in the main story.
Also, the mandate came into play
because my original drawing didn't explicitly
include player characters.
So my art director requested that I restructure
the composition to fit a trio of player characters
into a horizontal crop format.
And finally, the black ball restricted the options
available to me to make those changes
because I couldn't position foreground characters
with their backs turned toward the viewer.
So adding the triad of player characters
created a very unbalanced image composition,
so I was able to successfully argue
to get one of those player characters removed.
And the final composition ended up
being reasonably effective.
with the exception of the picture-in-picture motif represented in the center.
It's difficult to parse exactly what it is that we're seeing inside that magical sphere,
and the fact that its meaning can only be understood symbolically doesn't do the narrative
any favors.
It was a struggle for me to even get the illustration to this level of readability,
and since then I've used it as a cautionary example to dissuade similar suggestions
from more image-within-an-image compositions.
So, now that we've covered the major challenges
that limit my options when conceptualizing the key art,
I wanna show some of the tools that I rely on
to maximize the narrative impact of an illustration
without overloading and breaking it.
And as a case study, I'm going to walk,
to briefly walk through the development process
of the key art I created for ESO's Dragon Bones update,
which I painted back in December of 2017,
and which was released the following March.
And as we'll see, most of the creative work for the key art
is front loaded to the earlier stages,
while the actual production and rendering of the image
is a rather mechanical exercise.
So the whole process starts with an initial brief
from my art director, which essentially amounts
to a really basic overview of the new content,
along with his ideas for particular story moments,
or important visual elements that he thinks
we should highlight in the key art.
As I mentioned, one of the things my art director
really likes to emphasize is a narrative focus
for each illustration we do.
It's important to him that each image tells its own story.
Now the Dragon Bones update was a dungeon pack,
which in the cadence of the ESO release schedule
tends to mean that it's relatively thin on story.
But the basic gist of it was that a necromancer
had discovered the bones of an ancient dragon,
which he intended to reanimate
and use it to kill all of his enemies.
The player's goal is to stop him,
and in doing so, collect cool loot.
So maybe not super original when viewed at a high level,
but it's definitely enough to get us started.
So after talking with my art director,
I do some more research on my own,
which includes reading the design documents
generated by the content designers,
looking through the concept art
that's been done for the update,
and depending on whether it's been built yet,
I fly through the play space to get a feel
for the environments the players
will encounter while playing.
So what do those story elements that I mentioned
determine for the key art?
Well, right away, I knew that this key art
was obviously going to have to showcase
a reanimated dragon skeleton.
It was the central focus of the dungeon pack,
and you can't call something dragon bones
and then ignore those bones in the marketing campaign.
Also, since it's unusual, even in Tamriel,
for a dragon's bones to come back to life,
I knew that it would be important to show
the player character's shock and surprise
at encountering a giant living skeleton.
I also needed to provide some explanation
of how or why the dragon's skeleton has become reanimated,
which meant I needed to create a visual link
between the necromancer and the dragon
so that the viewer understands
the causal connection between them.
And then finally, in order to convey the enormity
of the threat the dragon poses to our heroes,
it would be helpful to emphasize the scale of the dragon
compared to the size of the human characters.
So with those cues as a jumping off point,
I started doing some very rough thumbnail sketches,
and you can see how these are all really built
on the elements that I just talked about,
especially the scale difference
between the necromancer and the dragon
and the player character's reaction to seeing it.
The sketch in the lower left-hand corner
had the most developed narratives,
so I started fleshing that one out first.
As we discussed, a major storytelling constraint
of key art illustration is that we're confined
to telling our story within a single image.
And that makes it difficult to convey multiple story beats
that take place over time.
One of the ways that I sidestep that issue
is by using different characters to represent
different beats or moments in time.
A successful reading of the image is therefore dependent
upon constructing the composition so that the viewer's eye
notices each of these story beats in the order we want,
and we can see that playing out in this first comp here.
So the initial read in this composition
is clearly the necromancer silhouetted
in front of the dragon's skeleton.
And based on his pose, we get the sense
that he seems to be casting some sort of spell on the bones.
Next, we notice the figure in the center foreground
who appears to be sneaking up behind the necromancer
with his sword drawn.
Along with that figure, we also pick up
on the foreground figure on the left
who is urgently gesturing towards something
on the right side of the image.
And that carries our eyes to the figure on the right
who seems to be startled by a light glowing
from the eye socket of the dragon's skull.
We also realize that the central foreground figure seems unaware of the glowing eye lights,
suggesting that they've only recently begun glowing sometime after he took up his current position.
Now, of course, when we first look at the image, our minds take all this in within a second or two,
but the order that we notice this stuff influences our ability to easily grasp a story,
and learning how to direct a viewer's eyes to move through a composition
is an important aspect of storytelling through illustration.
The artist has a number of tools at their disposal for directing the viewer's gaze.
This isn't really the focus of today's discussion, so I'm not going to go into detail with these,
but by playing with the relationships between lightness, color, scale, and proximity to the viewer,
the artist can establish lines of action along the edges of major shapes,
which is what guides the viewer's eyes through the composition.
And there's one other important composition and planning tool that I think frequently gets overlooked,
and that is that
In the West, we're taught from an early age
to process visual data by reading from top to bottom
and left to right.
That means that when a viewer approaches a work of art
for the first time, their eyes will automatically seek
to enter the image from the upper left corner by default.
So it's important to take this into account
when planning for viewer eye movement
because it gives you a reliable start point
where the viewer will enter the maze of your illustration.
And just as importantly, if your goal is to have
the viewer's eye first enter the image
at a different location, then you have to build in
a lot of extra visual cues to counteract
that top left corner bias.
So with that in mind, when we refer back to our dragon bone sketch, we see that I'm using the dragon's upper arm bone like a highway to lead the eye in from the upper left directly into the center of the image.
From there, our eyes will continue to move around the composition following lines of action created by other major shapes.
Our eyes naturally stop to rest at any location where one line of action ends and another begins, and these areas thus become the focal points of the image and the location of different story beats.
So after taking in the necromancer,
The bright high contrast line created by the dragon's nose channels our eyes down to the character in front,
where the angle of the sword and the direction of his body, his face, swings our focus back to the left,
encouraging us to engage with the figure position there.
Next, our eyes pick back up on the high contrast edge created by the rim lighting of the dragon's forearm,
and continues from left to right along the upper arm and spinal column.
Now arcing our focus over the top of the image like this
is an important step, but you could also say
it's a dangerous one, insofar as there's any danger
in illustration, because in tracking along
the strong rightward descending shape of the dragon's spine,
I'm reinforcing our eye's predisposition
to move from left to right, and the risk
is that the viewer's attention could drop
right off the edge of the image,
which is obviously not what we want.
So that's why it's important to build interesting shapes
like the dragon's horn and the rim lighting
along the figure's outstretched arm.
which provide a directional counterforce to bring our focus back toward the center of the image.
And at this point, we see that we've established a circuit of visual interest,
which invites the viewer to retread the moments of the story in a clockwise fashion,
and in so doing, encourages them to spend longer engaging with the artwork.
And when you spend as much time painting these images as I do,
you definitely want to squeeze every second of your engagement that you can out of them.
So not to belabor the point, but quickly going back through that narrative sequentially,
this is the full story that we'd be trying to tell if we had more than one image available
to do it.
The necromancer begins casting a spell on the bones, our heroes sneak into position
near the skull, the dragon's eyes light up, some of the heroes notice the eye lights and
react, and then finally the dragon wakes up and our heroes become overmatched.
Unfortunately, we only have one image at our disposal
to tell this story, and technically,
this snapshot has to occur at a single moment in time.
So I'd say that what we're seeing in this comp
is taking place right about here,
somewhere between beats three and four.
But of course, the first four beats
are all represented to some extent in the comp,
even though some have already occurred.
Because the story beat of the glowing eye lights
is the last stop on the viewer's guided tour
through the composition, our eyes interpret it
as having occurred more recently.
than the other beats in the image,
even though everything is ostensibly occurring
at the same moment in time.
But based on the way I've structured the composition,
I'm providing clues to what has happened in the scene
just before the moment we're witnessing,
and giving the viewer hints of what is likely to happen
in the moments to follow.
So in this case, the dragon is going to wake up,
and these guys are gonna be in trouble.
In this way, I'm establishing a story
with a beginning, a middle, and an end,
all within just one image.
Now, the feedback that I got from my art director
on this sketch,
was that he wanted the player character to have more to do
than just sneak up on the bad guy.
And this is yet another example of the problem
created by the player character mandate.
Searching for solutions to that problem
led me to this composition here,
which shows our quest party attempting
to steal loot from a dungeon.
Obviously the dragon is the first major read here,
but the critical element of this story
is our hero's ignorance of the danger they're in.
So like this guy is so focused on breaking into the vault
that he's oblivious to the massive reanimated skull
positioned right above him.
The lookout on the right thinks he might have heard something,
but he's looking in the wrong direction,
while the coiled posture of the figure holding the pickaxe
tells us that he's just clued into the real danger from above.
And then over on the left, we have a confrontation going down
between one of our heroes and the necromancer
who's being held at sword point.
It's clear that our questing party believe they have the situation under control,
but the necromancer's glowing staff
indicates that he's magically controlling the as-yet-unnoticed dragon,
so he's not as helpless as he looks.
storytelling problem with this composition is that the necromancer isn't
prominent enough in the image. Using the eye movement analysis we talked about
before, the necromancer is one of the last reeds and the nature of the
relationship between him and the dragon isn't very clear. So to try to solve that
problem I kept the same stage but repositioned the actors to cede some
control back to the necromancer. So now he's the one in the position of power
above our heroes and notice that the player characters each have different
levels of awareness of the dangers facing them.
So, like, the guy closest to the necromancer is still clueless,
while two others are spotted with the spellcasting necromancer,
but the lookout in the foreground is the only one who's noticed the dragon might be waking up,
which we're again indicating by the eye lights in the skull.
And by using the same color for the light in the dragon's eyes and the necromancer's magic,
we could really underscore the idea that the necromancer is the one in control here.
Now, as I mentioned, the narrative I'm constructing for each of these compositions
involves at least some of the characters being unaware of the threat posed by the dragon.
This is another technique that I lean on
to expand the narrative weight
that can be carried by a single image.
Because when the viewer knows something
that the characters don't, it creates a tension
that anticipates the character's discovery
of the information the viewer already has.
And this allows me to indicate characteristic intentions
and expectations prior to a watershed moment
while simultaneously enabling the viewer
to infer how the character's emotions will change
in response to this moment of recognition.
So essentially what we're talking about
is a plot reversal captured within a single image.
So in this next composition, and this is the last one,
I promise, I distilled that idea down even further.
I got rid of the treasure hunter subplot
and replaced it with a direct confrontation
between the Necromancer and our player characters
who seemingly had him cornered.
But the Necromancer is smiling deviously
in spite of his predicament
because he knows he's about to get some major backup
in the form of the fog-shrouded dragon
he's summoning to protect him.
Like the other comps, this one includes
one of the player characters depicted in the exact moment
that they realize the dragon is awake.
In this case, it's the figure furthest to the right.
So this is basically a pictorial form of anagnorisis,
which refers to the moment in a story
when a character makes a critical discovery
that changes the stakes emotionally.
Including the story beat does two things.
First, it adds an immediacy to the danger.
because clearly the guy on the right is about to alert his friends and everything is going to change.
And second, it also makes it clear that the dragon is indeed a threat.
Otherwise, it's possible that all these guys could just be ignoring the dragon for some reason,
thereby undercutting his narrative significance.
Or perhaps the viewer could misinterpret the dragon as actually being allied with the player characters.
The character experiencing anagnorisis tells us that his reaction is the same one that everybody else would be having
if only they saw what he was seeing.
It's a useful tool for clarifying character intent
in complex compositions and expanding
the dramatic tension of a scene.
In any case, my art director liked this image,
but he wanted it to have more story beats
and to make it seem like our party of adventurers
already had their hands full with other threats
before the dragon even enters the ring.
So basically, he wanted to raise the stakes.
So I added in some reanimated human skeletons
for our adventurers to fight off,
which also allowed me to promote the foreground figure
on the left to our hero character.
still poised to confront the necromancer directly
while his buddies take out the skeletons behind him.
And then finally, my art director felt that we needed
more indications of the location setting for this scene,
so I added in some architectural pillars
to imply that we were in a massive subterranean ruin.
So, with four potential options at this point,
I did a color toning pass on each comp,
because while a composition may look great
as a line drawing, when you introduce value and color,
the readability and focal points of the image
can change greatly.
It's important to block all this stuff in early on
so that I can catch any major problems
before we invest too much time into a flawed composition.
At this stage, the color toning mostly breaks down
into warm and cool color influences
meant to reinforce narrative cues
like the relationship between the dragon
and the necromancer as indicated by the same cool glow
to their magic effects.
Nevertheless, everything at this stage
is still just placeholder.
And I typically end up redoing the line drawing,
the gray-scale values,
and the colors once a specific composition has been chosen.
But once I complete the rough toning pass,
my art director submits the options
to the executive stakeholders,
and then the other executives reply with questions,
comments, and concerns about various sketches,
and their consensus opinion results
in one of three possible verdicts.
So first, they may reject all of the comps outright,
in which case I need to determine what it is
about those options that I provided
that's not working for them.
so I can do a brand new round of sketches
that will hopefully be more successful.
And this iterative back and forth process
can produce as many as three rounds of unique comps
before one sketch is finally approved.
And approval is the second possible outcome.
But more often than not, they deliver a third verdict,
which is a provisional approval.
And basically this means that they like one of the comps,
but they want me to make some changes to it
before I start full on production.
So for the Dragon Bones key art we're looking at today,
they did end up green lighting the last
of the four compositions I developed,
although that's not always the case.
So even though we had the green light
to go ahead with production on this composition,
we still wanted to refine some image elements a bit
before I dove into detailed rendering work.
One thing I wanted to do was introduce a warm light
into the scene to contrast the cool shafts
of moonlight coming in from above.
And so in order to justify that light source,
I changed the pose of the figure on the far right.
and put a torch in his hand.
And even though it isn't represented here yet,
we also decided to add flames scattered across the ground
between the Necromancer and the Front Warrior,
which would add a warm fill light
to pop that Front Warrior off the cool background behind him
and also create a symbolic separation
between the two characters.
I also tried out a couple different poses
for the Necromancer,
and we ultimately settled on this one,
because by dropping his left arm like this,
we create some additional space in the image
for the dragon's head.
which you want to establish as a focal point.
And it also opens the space between the necromancer
and the front figure here, so we can imagine
that their eyes are locked on one another,
reinforcing the story beat
of the confrontation between them.
Now, you might have noticed that throughout
this entire sketching process,
the figures I've been drawing are all semi-naked bald dudes.
Has anybody noticed that?
That's because in the early stages,
it's simpler to sketch a generic human form.
to indicate the position of shapes and volumes,
rather than allow myself to get caught up
in trying to capture specific details.
And it's also because even this early on in the painting,
I'm using photo reference of myself
to inform the poses for the characters.
And you can see some of those references here.
And there are a couple of benefits
to using myself as a reference model.
And the most important of these is that I have some idea of the mood that I want to convey in the pose,
so I can kind of become that character myself without having to direct a model
who has no idea how their pose fits into the image or the story of the illustration.
But I think the main point here is that having adequate reference is absolutely essential to producing high-quality key art,
and I would argue any art.
And I lean on reference heavily throughout the entire painting process.
Any day that I find I'm really struggling with what I'm doing,
I realize it's because I don't have good reference,
and then I have to go search for it or create it myself,
and then things get moving again.
So although all the figures look vaguely like me
at the beginning, we obviously want to represent
a more diverse cast of characters in the final painting.
There are nine playable character races
and two genders in ESO, and at this stage,
we decide on race and gender assignments
for each figure in the painting.
Of course, some of this is defined by the narrative.
like if I'm depicting specific NPCs or if the scene is intended to take place in an area of Tamriel where a specific ethnicity is dominant in the population there.
We also want to represent at least one of the beast races since they're a signature part of the Elder Scrolls series.
And in the interest of representation, when the narrative allows for it, I also try to represent a diversity of races from the real world as well as a mix of male and female characters.
More generally, I just want to say that...
I believe that as artists we have a responsibility to be sensitive to cultural representation
in our work and be responsive to prevailing cultural climates, which in turn our work
helps to influence.
On the one hand, it's so weird to think that my paintings of a fantasy medieval society
have any relevance to contemporary culture at all.
But the truth is, whether I intend it or not, every painting I produce makes a statement
about how I personally view the world around me.
And each painting also contributes to a cultivation of imagery that collectively shapes the way
our players view the world too.
And I'll give you just one example
of how this has been relevant in my own illustrations.
So the second piece that I worked on
after starting at ZOS was for ESO's Thieves Guild update.
The update takes place in the province of Hammerfell,
which is the home of a primarily dark-skinned people
called the Red Guards.
And it was therefore natural that characters
with darker skin tones would feature prominently
in our key art.
But the composition that developed
during the sketching process depicted a lone member
of the Thieves Guild evading city guards
after pulling off a heist.
I was working on this illustration in the months following the Freddie Gray protests
in Baltimore, and it occurred to me that it might not be the right cultural moment to
showcase a black man being chased by law enforcement.
On the other hand, however, populating the image with white characters in an in-game
location known to have a light-skinned minority seemed inescapably like marginalization.
So I voiced this concern, and I even sketched out some alternative racial treatments for
the primary character.
But initially, the executive team was focused on establishing continuity.
with the main character that had been depicted
in an earlier illustration for the same update.
So I continued with production
with the character cast as a Redguard.
And the image actually got fairly far into production
before the decision was finally made
to recast our hero thief as a Khajiit instead,
which is the version that was eventually released
to the public.
Now, if we'd gone ahead with the original Redguard character
we may never have been called on it.
The connection might not have resonated
in the way that I feared.
But the point is that with every decision you make
in a painting, it has the potential to make
a specific statement to your audience,
whether you intend that statement or not.
So the most responsible approach is to be deliberate
and circumspect with every choice you make in your art
in order to avoid inadvertently making statements
that you or your company might not intend.
Anyway, getting back to the Dragon Bones key art,
once the race and gender selections are chosen
and approved, I start the line work stage of production.
where I go through each figure and modify the anatomy
to match the body type of the race and gender
intended for each character.
I also draw clothing, armor, and gear
on top of the anatomy drawings,
and I tend to design the gear using inspiration
from in-game armor sets,
which I combine with influences from photo references
to inject more personality into the characters' outfits.
And with the line work stage complete,
it's finally time to start painting.
So as I mentioned before, most of the creative work
for the key art is front loaded.
And honestly, by the time I'm done with the drawing stage,
most of the important creative decisions
have already been decided on.
My topic for today is not intended to focus on technique,
but in the interest of being thorough
and to give the session a satisfying conclusion,
I'd just like to quickly walk through
the remaining stages of my process
so we can see how this painting finished up.
Now after the line drawing,
My next step is to establish diffuse color values
for the characters.
So I use the lasso tool in Photoshop
to create selections of each material
represented on each character,
and then on individual layers,
I fill each selection with a unique color.
So for example, the skin will be on one layer,
the leather armor will be on another layer,
the metal trim will be on another, and so on.
And the real value of this step
is that it allows me to control click
the layer thumbnail of each material
to restore the corresponding selection whenever I want,
so I can use them to define masks
for adjustment layers later on.
Moving on from there, I render the lighting information
in the scene in grayscale,
before introducing the color bias of each light source,
and then finally combining all of this
with the diffuse material colors I established earlier
to achieve a rough approximation
of the colored and toned lighting environment for the scene.
Now, everything I've done up to this point
has really just served to establish an underpainting
that I can use to start painting on top of.
But now I can finally start the direct painting stage,
which makes up the bulk of the rest of the process.
So.
This is where I finally lose the drawing.
I reduce the opacity of the line work layer
and then begin painting in new layers on top of that.
My process tends to involve a lot of adjustment layers,
which I prefer to keep live so that I can revise them
later on if necessary.
And the downside of this approach is that it eats up
a ton of memory, so eventually I end up using
breakout PSDs to work on each character individually
in separate documents.
I focus on the characters one by one,
treating each as its own mini painting
before reincorporating them into the larger composition.
And in this case, the dragon counts as a character too.
So once I'm done with the characters,
I focus on the surrounding environment,
building in some features from scratch
and also incorporating some in-game screenshots
in the background that get heavily painted over
to save on painting time.
A lot of surface texture is generated
through a combination of noisy brushes
and photo texture overlays.
And then in the later stages of the painting,
I also do a final dirt and grime pass
to help things feel convincingly aged and lived in.
I add in cast shadows for the characters and special effects
before doing a final color grading pass,
which is often one of the most important steps
of the entire process.
This is where I finally establish a cohesive atmosphere
for the illustration and rebalance the lighting and colors
to increase readability and emphasize compositional elements
in a way that better supports the narrative.
And that is basically it.
Aside from cleaning up the layer groups
to help the marketing and web guys
more easily navigate the file,
I pass it on for publication.
And then the whole process starts all over again for the next one.
So that is the end of what I had prepared for today.
So I just want to thank everybody for coming.
I hope you found it worthwhile, and I will be glad to take any questions that anybody
might have.
First of all, I have no experience as an artist, but...
That's so much better.
This is incredibly insightful.
I had no idea.
See, if you're not an artist, you can't tell me
that I'm wrong about everything you just said.
Well, yeah, it's the composition.
Anyway, sorry.
I've noticed two things.
There's actually a question,
I hope this doesn't come off the wrong way,
but in the initial sketches that you were...
Given you have these these concepts of like the black ball and the mandate, but you still didn't include
Characters and those initial sketches that just something from like your own point of passion that you're trying to like be like look
This is good
See more of this so that you can get it or is that something?
That you've now scrapped in your design process
Yeah, that's a good question. I'm glad you asked it because it's something that I knew I had left out of this presentation.
His question is why do I keep offering up sketches that don't include player characters from the beginning
if it just creates problems for me later down the road.
And part of that is because we're doing this for three and a half years
and over that length of time we've had different...
We've had different brand managers come in and out
of the project on the Bethesda side.
And so they have different preferences.
And so the concept of what defines a player character
and how important that is has shifted over time.
The other thing too is that,
because I mentioned three of those challenges,
but there are a lot more that weren't as important
to talk about.
But one of them is that there are oftentimes
specific angles on the story content
that they're trying.
to push and a lot of the time the two things contradict each other.
So you can't tell those stories and also have player characters there that are doing something
important.
And so my initial solution is always to say, look, we can do it this way, but there's this
hard and fast rule that they typically come back to.
So that's why.
Yeah.
So in some ways it's like a springboard for them to give you alternate feedback?
Is that?
Yeah.
I mean, that's fair.
Yeah, I think so.
I know that I'm not supposed to ask follow-up questions, but there's no sword or there's only swords like how come nobody has anything but swords
I'm like looking at all this being like is that a hammer?
Well, so a lot of what I should I think there are
She says there's a repeating the question. He says there are only swords and why aren't we using other weapons?
I think there are examples of other weapons in some of the key art the specific one that I broke down
It just worked out that way. I don't know. I don't have a good answer.
In a lot of the other sketches though, I'll typically just use a sword as like a stand-in weapon,
and then typically I'll end up modifying the pose once it gets approved to a more specific weapon.
Because it doesn't make sense to bother with that kind of detail if the sketch is going to be thrown away anyway.
Well, thank you so much.
Yeah, thank you.
Hi, great talk, great work, great project.
My question was in regard to getting started with your composition.
I always find that the most difficult part of composition is getting started
because when you get started, it's not a composition yet.
It's a subject or it's a frame.
And my question was going to be do you start with a subject or do you start with a frame?
And it looked like in the breakdown of those really simple sketches of the dragon
you were really focusing on the subject and not quite yet considering what the frame because there was no outline on those sketches.
That is true. And so yeah, I mean I think the way I just work naturally I will
do I start with a subject or a frame when I'm
when I'm first beginning the compositions,
am I worried about how all those elements
will fit inside a particular crop format?
The answer is no.
Typically, just the way I work,
I will start by drawing just a character
on a massive PSD that doesn't have any bounds to it, really,
and see where it takes me.
And one of the reasons for that in this case
is because the,
The key art that we make, and I left this out of the talk,
but there are a lot of actual format and crop specifications
that I have to hit.
And what that means is that I have
to build a lot of margin area into every illustration
that we do.
So oftentimes, I end up painting this huge scene of a world
that we only crop in on a small window of.
The illustration I'm working on right now is like that.
I've got so much that we're going to have to crop in later.
stuff outside of that will be wasted work,
but that's just kind of the way it goes.
And I wanted to say as part of that,
there is a sort of paralysis in the early phases
of doing a concept.
I'm not sure if you ever feel like you might be
getting ahead of those requirements or desirements,
and whether or not you feel like,
whoa, I can't, like there's a pressure to demonstrate
that you're making something or that you can make something,
but also you know that there's stuff out there
that's not being expressed yet,
you don't wanna start getting ahead of that,
so like, how do you?
Is there a way in your process to manage that?
Well, I think I could take your question a couple different ways, but what I would probably
say is, I think maybe I would rephrase your question as, am I ever concerned that the
people who see my artwork internally will make a judgment on the quality of the composition
I'm developing before I really get to a point where it's fully been expressed?
And the answer to that is certainly yes,
but it becomes less so over time because there
is a level of trust that gets developed.
And they've seen enough examples.
They know how it's more likely to turn out.
And so they gave me the benefit of the doubt.
I don't know who was first.
Do you want to go over here?
They always make these mics for tall people.
So my question, it is a technical question, so sorry.
But I noticed that you had some meshes
in some of your sketches, and I was
wondering if your 3D modeler gave that to you already rigged
and you just put it in the pose you wanted,
or if they posed it for you, or if you did it yourself.
And I also wanted to know what, like,
you don't have to give me actual time hours worked,
because I hate it when people ask me that question.
But I want to know what your timeline in the whole production phase was.
Well, I mean, I would say overall, like what typically gets slated,
that the entire production is supposed to last about eight weeks.
And we and I do I do overshoot that sometimes, typically
because there will be problems develop or the art director or someone else
will make will decide that something's not working.
And then I need to go back and kind of, you know, retool the illustration.
And that adds time.
So sometimes it gets pushed.
But eight weeks is what we shoot for in production schedule.
As to your other question, which was,
where do the 3D meshes that you kind of see hints of
in some of my sketches come from?
The answer there is, it definitely varies.
So I started my career as a 3D production artist.
So I certainly have the ability to build those myself.
And I'll typically do that for environments
or to build like the structure.
Sometimes I'll do like a really rough gray box scene.
Other times I'll go into ZBrush and turn on Dynamesh
and sculpt like a face or some kind of object
that I want to get from a different angle.
And then finally, in the case of what we looked at today,
that dragon, I think it's probably what you're talking about,
there was a really early like proxy for the dragon,
and that I did not make, but that was, it already existed.
And I just took the Maya file, or it was Max file,
but I work in Maya.
I took the file and I cannot rig,
and it was not rigged itself,
so I just basically used pivots
and put it in the position I wanted.
And that is still faster than just trying to draw anatomy
that doesn't really exist anyway.
So you don't wanna go too far into debating with yourself
whether or not it looks right.
So yeah.
Awesome, thank you so much.
You're welcome.
And then over here.
Hi, Lucas.
Thank you for the talk.
It was really informative and it was really awesome.
Like your paintings are really awesome, I think.
Thank you.
So just one small question is like,
when you're doing like these key paintings,
how important is for you to do like all the characters
like with exactly as they appear in the concept art
or exactly as they appear in games?
Do you have to do it like so that they are like,
like faithful representations of those
or are you able to also like change this?
these concepts to suit the needs of a certain painting.
Right, so the question is how much flexibility do I have
in changing the appearance of the characters
or other things for the key art,
even if they don't match the concept art
or the final in-game models?
The answer is I have a lot of flexibility.
And it didn't necessarily start out that way,
but I think that my art director kind of has,
he understands and firmly believes
that the illustration is meant to be
an aspirational depiction of what the game is
as opposed to a realistic one.
So I'm allowed to change things, make things look hopefully better and higher fidelity than they would in game or in the concept.
And also, I'm given a lot of flexibility with what they, with the costuming.
So oftentimes I will use pieces, like armor pieces from the game,
but the thing is about the way that we do armor sets in ESO,
there, it's like
it's a very compartmentalized modular system.
And so everything kind of has to look similar.
It has to be very form-fitting to the character.
We don't have, we can't have fabric hanging off
and things like that.
And so one of the things that I like to do
is just use pieces of that,
but build kind of something that's more of like a,
that looks more like a home-built kit.
You know, things that the character may have found
and decided to incorporate into their outfit.
And yeah, and adding different kinds of wear and.
and fabric hanging and things like that.
So yeah, I definitely get flexibility when it comes to that.
And it rarely does it get pushed back.
Do I get pushed backwards?
Like, no, you gotta make that look the same, so.
Okay, thank you. Yeah.
And if that's it, thank you guys so much.