Hello, everyone.
If you could please turn off any mobile phones and noisemakers
before we get started, that'd be great.
But I think it's time to get into my talk, which
is architecture for level design.
I'm Claire Hosking.
I've got a master's of architecture
and a bachelor's of design in architecture.
I've written for Polygon in the past,
and I make my own games based on procedural architecture
and that kind of thing.
So what I'm going to talk to you today is about how level designers, how architectural
design can help level designers achieve their intended mood and add depth to their levels.
And since I don't know what kind of activities you want to put in your game, I'm going to
presume that it's not going to be combat necessarily or puzzles or story pickups.
I'm just going to focus on making individual spaces worthwhile.
So the first thing I was thinking about when making this talk is what would be most useful
to you because architecture covers a lot of different things.
So what I really want to focus on
is the kind of geometry and layout design
that level designers do, and how you
can use that to kind of emphasize and accentuate
materials and all those later stages of the design process.
Whoops, wrong button.
So basic considerations.
One of the great qualities that brings mood to space
and to cities is the typology of cities.
The typology of cities is the layout of the city
and the pattern that it adopts in response
to all the considerations that people have around them.
So the weather, the topology, all of that kind of thing.
But all of these things tend to relate
to some basic considerations about space, circulation,
psychological comfort, and visual interest.
So this is from a 1979 study by urbanist William H. White
called the Street Life Project.
They went out and studied and mapped
how people use public space.
And they produced an excellent documentary
called The Social Life of Small Urban Spaces,
which I'd really recommend watching
if you ever want to create a city
as part of your level design.
And what they found is that when people are standing or sitting,
they tend to pull back towards the edge of spaces.
They like to put their back against something safe,
and they like to look outwards towards a vista.
And interestingly, the most interesting vista for them
to watch is other people.
And we also know that when people
want to go between two places, they go in a straight line.
So one of the most successful urban spaces
has a main direct route between two parts.
which has people all walking along it,
and then at the edges it has somewhere for people to sit,
and then behind that it has a defined edge,
and people will come there and sit there
and watch the world go by.
And if it's a less linear space,
say more of a plaza or a park,
you can put other activities as central focus,
like a fountain or an ice cream cart
or a ball game, et cetera.
And people will take the focus
if there's something for them to do.
And this typology tends to repeat itself at all levels.
A room is organized around a focus.
Those rooms organized around a focus.
Houses cluster around a street or a square.
And plazas and cities kind of organized
around the center of the city.
And you can break up all of those
into small units of implied rooms and that kind of thing.
So if you're looking to make passively interesting space
in a game that functions like real spaces do, you can use this.
And so if the player is a spectator, they go to the edge.
And if they're a traveler or an activator,
they go to the center.
Architects tend to summarize these factors
into the idea of positive and negative space.
So positive space is this well-defined space
that has an organizing focal point.
And negative space tends to be leftover space, ill-defined,
often concave space with no real organizing
focal point or axis.
And roughly, people feel comfortable in positive space,
and they tend to move on and feel a bit uncomfortable
in negative space.
So this also works in video games.
So here's a good example from The Walking Dead,
where negative space is used to kind of disconcert the player.
It's not just the emptiness and the abandoned cars
and the sickly green tinge, like the art direction, that's
producing the sense of desolateness here.
There's this amorphous, ill-defined space
of the suburbs that creates a sense of unease
and that you want to move along from.
And the urban design has no direction to it.
And that's perfect, because this is a particular part
in this game where the player doesn't
know where they should go.
And so this is kind of showing you
that it's like the layout itself creates the mood.
It's not just the accoutrements of home,
which already feel very familiar.
It's kind of the space that you move through
that's able to set a lot of the tone.
So in order to do this.
William talked a little bit about how architects use the idea of a party,
which is a diagram that shows the organization of space.
And it can show just the physical layout of space,
but it can also express kind of the tonal layout of space,
and what approach you'll be using.
So this is by Peter Zumthor.
It's the party for the thermal baths at Vals,
which is generally regarded as a modern masterpiece of mood and tone.
So it establishes the original diagram,
establishes the sense of heaviness
that he's trying to achieve, which
translates into these rooms that are designed
as solid blocks that have been inserted into the plan,
and then smaller spaces carved out of them.
So the layout itself has a solidity to it
that is then reinforced by the way
the materials have been treated.
And the layout itself allows the materials
to be treated like that.
So party helps you consider if you want the qualities of space
to be like boxy, or amalgamations, or iconic,
or woven, or folded, or piled up,
and the way that affects the way the player interacts
with the world and the qualities of space and play.
So architecture creates meaning through atmosphere
rather than symbolism, as I was talking before about the focus
of the domestic qualities.
It's not so much about, like, you
can see that the houses have gabled roofs
and that kind of thing.
It's more about the geometry, the material, the texture,
creating quite a domestic space that
sets the necessary tone for the audience,
like if that was something you wanted to achieve.
So here's a really good example.
This is also by Peter Zontor, who
is a well-known architect.
He's won the Pritzker Prize, which
is like the big, you're a great architect prize.
It's a lifetime award for your work.
He's also one of my favorite architects.
And so this is Brutaclaus Field Chapel.
This is a chapel for shepherds.
It's in the middle of a field.
There's no way that you can put priests in it, or put bells,
or any of that kind of thing to tell you what it's for.
So how does Zumthor use space, and design,
and that kind of thing to create something
that feels suitably sacred and draw people to it?
So firstly, rather than create a steeple and a pitched roof
with a cross on top, it uses this warm and mysterious form
to attract people.
I think this was something that Journey understood really well,
is it's one thing to make it really clear where
your player has to go, but it's another thing
to make it really inviting.
And in order to get people to go somewhere, as an architect,
I can't use horror or urgency.
I can't damsel their loved ones or give people fetch quests.
So, Zunto chooses a strategy that's much more about sneak peeks and arousing curiosity about
what's up there and how the next corner might change your perceptions.
So this curiosity here is created
by the tapered corners, which show the mass
and make it obvious that there's something in there,
inviting us to circle around.
It's very relative, but in our culture,
this kind of simple unit with shallow angles
can have a kind of arcane connotations.
You can see this used in other chapels,
but also video games that are trying to go for something
that feels quite otherworldly.
In the Rothko Chapel, it's used to kind of generate this platonic ideal of worship that
is transcendent across different religions.
And so yeah, these geometries kind of hint at otherworldliness.
So similarly, it leaves off decorative detail.
And while detail is used a lot in games to do environmental storytelling
and to clue players into what era and class your world is set in,
leaving it off, likewise, creates the ambiguity and the mystery here
that's drawing you towards it, because you don't know how modern or ancient it might be,
what culture or group it belongs to just yet.
And likewise, the soft indents and texture
are beautifully human scaled.
And that kind of plays into having left all that off
and having used quite simple forms.
It allows that to shine.
Rather than use a more traditional church or cathedral
door, some use almost this sci-fi door.
And in a nice piece of attention directing,
rather than using the red flashing light where
the detail shows you where the door is,
the door is actually pointing you towards the detail.
Because this is not about knowing
where the next place to go is.
It's about taking in each point along your journey.
And so, so far, it's used kind of the position, the color,
the shaping, the formal arrangement
of the dots on the outside to express that there's
something here.
It contains something.
And that it's Christian.
And it's within the next step is that you step inside.
And it's full of stars.
This is probably, these are all the little holes
that are left over when you build something out of concrete.
You have to put ties through
between both sides of the formwork.
And Zumthor has chosen to leave them open
to create this kind of, this sense of infinite space
and like deep kind of meaningfulness.
It's probably the most literally holy chapel in the world.
Sorry.
And as you can see, there's not a whole lot of traditional Christian tribal
civilism.
No boats, no fish, no doves.
Instead, the architecture itself points directly at the sky.
The sloping fluted walls carry the eye upwards, and the dark starry interior suggests an endless
universe.
And you can see the thick, heavy walls and poured iron covering on the floor, which you
might be able to see there.
create this sense of meditative weightiness that settles the space and encourages you to dwell.
So the form making itself accentuates all these materials that have come in
and it creates an experience for the player all on its own.
So the carved space cannot be taken from one vantage point.
It's impossible to stand back and find
one position where the whole space is framed.
It pushes you too close.
So you have to actively construct
a mental image of the space, and it can only
exist inside your head.
And this itself kind of gestures towards the ephemeral
and the idea of something that exists
on a different plane.
And so, yeah, so this is how architecture
can create a sense of space without necessarily all
the symbolism.
And there are games that do this really well, too.
So for instance, if you look at the way
that the idea of home is portrayed in Last of Us
and Soma, you might notice the first level layouts.
I've only got the Last of Us here, unfortunately.
You might notice that the first level layouts are rectilinear,
not much interpenetration or variation in the volumes.
Pretty clean, simple, familiar, generic.
But importantly, that sense of order is echoed
in the way the architecture is constructed.
We have these solid joints, simple cornices,
simple skirtings, all very matte.
So thematically, it establishes a locus of order
that acts as a contrast to the oncoming disorder,
which will be characterized by a very different
set of tectonics, that of encrustation.
And so here, you can see that both the level layouts
and the world itself become these very melded layers
of material, these knobbly surfaces, this rust and dirt
and moss and mold.
And so at the same time that the level layouts become
less rectilinear, it's used to kind of highlight this art.
And so this is a great example where
the construction of the architecture
echoes the level design, how the mood is established
both in organizing principle and material expression
of the space in a way that has storytelling purpose.
So creating specific characters in a space.
Here, two things have to evolve at once.
Since the way you shape a space can emphasize materials,
and simultaneously, the perception of material qualities,
that is weight, sturdiness, complexity, et cetera,
influences the perception of shape and scale and proportion,
the kinds of things that you have control over
in shaping your levels.
So this is an example by Zaha Hadid of how the layout of the space is helping to highlight
the tonal qualities of material.
Hadid is also a Pritzker Prize winner, also a major worldwide architect, also a favorite
of mine.
She mainly works in digital architecture, she does a lot of procedural stuff, and works
a lot in concrete, not so much in steel, which is why this one is kind of interesting.
So here to create an appropriate atmosphere
for the activity of diving, she's
designed a set of boards that kind of fill you
with the feeling of lightness even before you step off
the edge.
Level design-wise, it's been separated
into these individual podiums, like creating a journey that
requires you to step out onto these suspended stairways.
And it's not like traditional diving boards, which
are joined into this central column,
and you don't get to actually step out and experience
that space.
The space has also been cleared of other distracting elements and the ceiling is quite high and
the walls are without many right angles so it creates this sense of smoothness.
Moreover, the same level of layout sensibility
is echoed in the way the materials
have been treated and shaped.
So the steel forms, these light, fine railings,
you can see their return in these curved details that
are set apart from the platform.
The concrete has been shaped to these very plastic forms.
So the mood of the layout and the mood of the materials
and the way they meet each other all have this sensibility.
And the choice that Zaha has made has allowed this to occur.
So there are games that do this really well, where the spatial qualities create tone and
emphasize materiality.
The first two Bioshock games, where the construction details are these chunky pieces really solidly
welded together.
And if you look at the level maps, you can see chunky spaces with heavy-duty connections
between them.
And this makes sense, because it's a heavy place, weighed down by a lot of atmospheric
pressure.
So yeah, it's the actual layout of the space and how you move through it.
And you can't just reskin this and expect it to work really well in all fictions.
So Bioshock Infinite takes a similar sensibility, but again, it still feels weighty even though
it's meant to be in the sky.
So in architecture, you would look more for...
using details and material rather than narrative fiction.
It will just create a sense of lightness.
So this is the Holman House by Durback-Lockjackers,
which there are details like there are reflective mirrors
on the columns.
The lights seem to fall from the sky
through holes in the ceiling.
And the windows continue down past the edge of the floor.
So there's a sense that the whole building
is floating even when you're in it.
There are games that do this well, so Mirror's Edge is trying to create a really light feeling
that you're traversing things.
And they aren't very well...
Sorry, I'm talking too fast.
They're not welded together, but sit apart, sharply defined.
The space around you almost seems free floating.
Subtracted, boxy elements insert themselves
into your path and fragment space.
Steel is used not just because it's visually light,
but it creates these fences that are blades jutting up
into the level.
And that moves the camera up and down very quickly
and enhances that sense that you're up in the air
and you're kind of floating around.
So this geometry fragments and incises the space.
And you can see that the art direction has this fineness,
this sharpness to every join.
And that these level design choices allow that to be shown.
You can talk about that it's not just a visual metaphor.
It's the difference between the player working their way
from mass to mass to mass to mass
versus hopping around a fragment in space.
I know obviously the Shock Games are shooters
and Mirror's Edge is a traversal game
and Olympic diving is something totally different altogether
but I still think it's worth considering
how you adapt these principles from one game to another.
One of the last things I want to talk about is that, for me,
the consideration of architecture in games
isn't about does your door work the way a real door does.
It's a question of does, because real architecture doesn't look
very realistic always either.
It's a question for me of space and material, not necessarily realism.
Sometimes it feels like games aim for a kind of solidity, like a need to fight the virtualness.
But for me, it's a question more about consistency, and that's kind of what we're trying to do here.
I think a big part of what's...
makes architecture captivating is that by compositing disparate materials with the same tonal goal,
you kind of reveal the truth about the universe and its latent possibilities.
And I think that's true of games as well, because when you show how all these different layers can achieve the same thing,
you kind of tell something about the space that you're creating and the kind of vision that you have.
And so when I say detail, I don't mean something out of Detail Magazine.
It's not whether it's familiar.
It's like, is the massing doing something
besides separating one bit of content from another?
How do you think about the way you're using mass?
Is it a solid wall with holes punched in?
A dividing plane that's been thickened in places?
A frame within a space?
What metaphor do you use
to kind of express what you're trying to achieve
at that level?
I want you to use form the way that I use form,
to create identity, to emphasize material,
and to create a coherent whole
that has a distinct atmosphere.
Thank you.
All right, cool.
Questions?
Hi.
I was wondering how you feel about repetition
in the architecture in games, such as modular levels, level
design, and using the same concrete texture
for every piece of concrete in one game.
I have interesting feelings about that because I work a lot in procedural design.
So for me, like, repetition is, yeah, it's a device that you can use within that
and that's like one parameter that you can set.
And it gives, it can be used for familiarity or, like, as you,
as I'm sure you're criticizing more that it can be used for boredom
and like, it can cause boredom and that kind of thing.
or yeah.
But yeah, I'm wondering how you think it can be used usefully, like to the best advantage?
Yeah, for sure.
It depends what you're trying to create.
If you want something to constantly echo something
throughout your game, then it can do that.
If you think about cities that have really consistent
architecture, where it's often everywhere throughout,
it creates a sense that the people in that world
had a particular material that they had to use.
and that they evolved to use that in a particular way
and that they've gone about it and just done it everywhere.
If you go to Santorini, it's really like the Greek island.
It's very like that.
Every house is constructed in the same way
because they only had limited options.
So that's kind of, to me, that's what they would say
architecturally about a world.
But yeah.
Thank you.
No worries.
Hi.
Hi, Dean.
Thanks for your talk.
You were saying you want to apply consistency and so forth.
So you're saying that normally in video games right now,
would you think that we're a bit limited in our way of thinking
of designing in terms of architecture,
that we should apply more of the current architectural field
towards game design?
I'm not sure about that.
It was more that I'd never heard it expressed in this way.
I can definitely see it happening in games.
So I don't know if people are limited,
but I don't know if there's the design emphasis on that.
Because there's very much, particularly in games that
have a very strong tradition of level design
for particular purposes, that's less experiential.
So maybe for more experiential games, this is more relevant.
Yeah.
Okay, something to think about. Thanks.
Of course.
Hi, you mentioned the documentary about city planning earlier?
Oh, The Social Life of Small Urban Spaces.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, it's really, really good. You should watch it.
Anybody else?
No?
Okay.
So, we'll move on to the next topic.
Okay, what do I do? Oh, okay.
All right, everyone, 4.40 is the next talk.
Thank you very much for coming.