What is it that makes some games super replayable over time?
I think it's all about offering.
Your player is a consistent challenge that's going to grow with them
as their skill level grows.
And one way you can do that is by offering a really competitive AI.
Race for the Galaxy is a digital game
based on the original tabletop board game.
And it integrates a neural network driven AI
originally developed by Keldon Jones.
And what's really special about this AI
is that it doesn't use any human generated training data.
It generates all of its training data by itself,
which frees it from human bias, which is great
because human generated strategies can be fallible.
Now, not all games are going to be good candidates for a neural network like this.
You're going to want a game with high stochasticity, meaning lots of random space for a neural network to explore.
Games with a fixed number of inputs, so you're solving a very specialized problem with your neural network.
And games where canonical configurations of pieces and space...
It is not critical to determining who's going to win your game.
And I'll get into some of the math on that at the upcoming GDC talk,
Race for the Galaxy, a neural network in production.
So you should come check it out if you're
interested in learning a little bit more about temporal difference
learning for board game AI.