Okay, hi, my name's Scott Benson.
Thanks for coming out.
I worked on this game, Night in the Woods.
I was the co-creator, co-writer, artist, animator,
just some other stuff.
It's an indie game.
Everyone does everything at some point.
Thanks everyone for coming. I thought maybe 5 people were going to come out to this and there's at least 6 or 7, which is fantastic.
This is good. Audience interaction is great because there's going to be some jokes.
So, there's some people from the Night in the Woods team here. You're kind of just getting my take on it, but anyone who worked on Night in the Woods, can you raise your hands?
Okay. Thank you.
Well now that that's over with of the 9 that was the first game I ever worked on
is my first time getting giving a talk at GDC you may be shocked to find out
and
so I should say a friend of this talk would be different if someone else is
giving the talk like with Alec you probably get more like a bit but the
technical design aspect of it and kind of he's you know the coder and the
composer on it the co-creator of it.
And so you kind of get his take on it with with Bethany.
She's a co-writer on it you'd get take more of the history
and kind of where she's from and her experiences that make up a lot of kind
of the bedrock of a lot of what ended up in the game with and Becca are
publishers that Finji right there you'd hear a lot of horror stories about
trying to adjust deadlines and kind of trying to herd the cats across the
cat field or whatever.
Let's hear John Manning is here you hear about like yarn spinner and some
of like the cool solutions with a yarn the dialect system that we ended up
using.
and creating I guess there at this and M who's there too you hear about like
her fantastic work on like the sound design, but you are unfortunately stuck
with me for the next 45 minutes or so I'm going to give a warning for anyone
who's watching this talk latest party be a little cursing because I'm going to
get excited and it's going to happen and I think there's one slide that has a
swear word in it and I'm
So I guess the night was the first game ever worked on I'm not a developer
with like years and years of like strains of successes. I was like some
like dumb punk kid artist to like years later, but like got stumbled into
making a video game and it just kind of went well so that's why you have to
hear from me also we have a lot to get through and I don't know if I can fit
this into the time so let's get going.
The way I skip slides already high that was supposed to go before.
And this is the name of the title of the thing.
of the talk. All right, part one. So, travel back with me, if you will, to twitter.com.
June 3rd, 2013. Alec Holoka, who co-created this game Aquaria, actually won awards at
the IGF here. 25 years ago? How long ago was it, Alec?
25 years ago, back when the IGF was all ColecoVision,
and they made this amazing game.
And so he contacted me and said, hey, you're funny on Twitter.
and I like some of your animation work would you like to make a video game and
I was an independent animator just doing like in the animation like contract
work illustration kind of trying to get by was self-taught didn't go to college
just this is like the long end of a long line of like that's just trying to get
by and I ended up kind of accidentally falling into doing animation and stuff
up right before the site help co-found
an international.
independent animation collective late night work club. I'm Jake Armstrong
did that logo my logo for just way worse. So I put that one up
there. You know late night work of dot com and check out our
stuff. It's all free and it's all good. But so when Alec asked
if I want to make a video game. I was like I guess like
the year before so I played a game called a super brother
sword and sorcery which is a brilliant amazing game.
and uh...
before then video games are kind of like you know i i i know for example like
people make rockets and go to like the moon and stuff but i have no idea how to
do that
and video games are kind of like that like i wanted to since i was a kid i was
interested in
game design and just you know like i i liked games a lot kind of just as an art
form and uh...
and also just for like fun
and but I never had any idea what to do with them or what I could do with them
at all and
but the sword sorcery which I loved it kind of pitched itself in its credits as
like a collaboration between a dev team and an artist and a musician and I was
like oh wait I can do one of those. I was like a mixed media collaboration or
something like.
in like my past it would be like oh someone does like a little comic zine and then like a band
record like a seven inch or something with it and you put them together it's this mixed media
collaboration project and I was like ah I get that and sword and sorcery um at least for me
gave me permission not in the sense it's like not in the like authority figure sense where someone
says okay now you can do this but in the sense of like when someone says demonstrates to you
or out and that says hey you can do this you know there's something that you have to offer.
or another part of your life, it's like you can be this,
you can think this, you can feel this way.
Sometimes you just need someone to go,
oh, yeah, you can do that, that's valid.
So Alex sent me an email, this is an actual email,
and our ambitions at the front were really funny.
I'm gonna do a dramatic reading of this real quick.
Alakaloka.
I don't have a plan or anything, but I think it'd be cool to make an atmospheric exploration,
chilled out, moody type thing for iPad.
Maybe non-linear, but some story elements.
Love your art style animation in the Vine you just posted.
Here's me.
Pssh.
No plan?
Yeah, I'd love to.
I know next to nothing about how to create for this medium, but I would love to do something.
Been trying to edge in that direction.
and would love the experience.
And making cool stuff is cool.
Thanks, Scott.
Also, thanks.
The clip is part of a blah, blah, blah.
Alakaloka.
We should start up a Google Doc and brainstorm.
See what comes to mind.
And I said sounds good and that was basically how that started so we worked
for a while like a few months in that summer kind of coming up with like
this thing it was like this atmosphere kind of mystical like silent
protagonist. She had like a little Cape that fluttered when you when you
jumped there's is pretty going to be some just like kind of like very nice
mystical stuff some storybook elements for going to be some like humming
ancient obelisks all the stuff this is just what you did in indie games in
2013. So we
So we were doing that, but we kind of weren't feeling it.
It was cool, but it wasn't really grabbing us.
And then this one night in, I think it was August of 2013,
I was sitting there.
I'm just going to, it was thunderstorming outside,
humid, rainstorm in Pittsburgh, lightning crashed,
just so you can get the idea.
and um... the uh...
i was watching this really like great art movie called return of the living
dead
and um... it's a fantastic movie it's a cinematic masterpiece
and um...
i was sitting there and i was thinking like this game is cool i want to make this game and now it's cool
and i don't know what to do like maybe all my ideas are bad and
stuff and then um...
I was watching it and so return of the living dead has this these great like
these punks it only existed in 80's movies which are great they all names
like you know like thrash and suicide I'm razor you know like they're being
like man this isn't just a costume is my way life and it's great and then they
fight zombies and it's fantastic and I was like it reminded me of kind of like
the punk kids that like I kind of came up with and like the punk adults that
Bethany and I kind of rolled around with and.
I was like man, no one makes games but us.
And so I was like, maybe we could do something with like that.
But I wasn't good at drawing people.
I was good at drawing animal people,
like kind of little cartoon people.
I was like a huge Richard Scarry fan when I was a kid.
And also like, I liked them in kind of like a subversive way.
I saw this flyer like 13 years ago.
And I was like, it just like, was like such a cool thing
of taking these kind of like early, like you know.
20s, 30s kind of like cartoon animal people and then like putting them in this context
It was like a level of like kind of like playful subversiveness that I like and so I started drawing a little animal people too
And I was like maybe I could kind of come up with some stuff or whatever and so I just sketched out these characters
And they basically didn't change until we ship the game
This is the first sketches of them
and I sent this to, well I didn't send this to Alec yet, around about that time too, I
just recently played a game called Kentucky Route Zero, drink every time this game is
mentioned in this talk.
And what was cool about Kentucky Route Zero is Bethany and I, Bethany is from central
Pennsylvania, I've lived in western Pennsylvania for half my life, so it's just kind of part
of who we are.
We um,
Kentucky was one of the first games where I was like,
oh,
I know that place,
not Kentucky,
but it's kind of off the highway places that are kind of like in the general Appalachia region.
There was,
there was just so much there.
There's so much truth to it and so much like,
okay,
so for example,
um,
The only times I think I'd seen Pittsburgh in video games beforehand were...
So there's The Last of Us,
and it's in a big post-apocalyptic ruin,
and you're fighting people and there's monsters and stuff.
It's a great game, but it's not exactly the most positive depiction of Western Pennsylvania.
The only other time I'd seen Pittsburgh in a game was
The Pit, Fallout 3.
Which...
It's not...
it's a slightly exaggerated version of Pittsburgh.
A lot of just wrought iron and people killing each other
and being generally unhappy.
And so like, I hadn't seen a lot of representation
of like our area and kind of just the people
that live there.
This guy lives next door to us.
there so I was like I'll be cool and I was like similarly to with the
characters I was like no one makes
games about where we're from or something. So I was like hey why don't we do that like
that would be cool. So I had
I wrote up this big, this like little pitch thing to Alec and I was like
oh yeah here's like here's some sketches here's some ideas here's like kind of what the story would be
and I sent it
and I was like this sucks this is going to end now because all my ideas are stupid
and then Alec's like no that's better let's do this and so um
So we kind of embarked on this like really, really quickly.
I'm scrolling my notes here.
Check this out.
The game design vogue at that point, I think,
was to make these kind of very minimal stripped down
experiences, you know, like silent protagonist talks
it's in kind of like ruins.
It was like super cool.
And also a lot of it was like hone down your mechanics
to like one thing, this kind of minimalist,
almost like Apple product design of games.
And that's really cool.
Like some of my favorite games are like that.
But we were like no actually let's make a game where no one shuts up ever.
Let's a big busy town. Lots of people who get this never never shut up.
Lots of writing that in no way efficiently points the the player to the
next destination as quickly as possible.
And just this big kind of shaggy thing that you that kind of was just like
there is a kind of full of life and full of energy and we're going to tack on
all these things to it and we kind of this syrup these designs like really
really quick.
and this is like these are the original
to concept things and cycling between them this is very cool and um...
so we kind of slapped together this uh...
kind of just uh...
the version of uh... maize street that's mayor main character that steve
scruggins is that
jerk and um...
And we were like we want this town that you can walk around this huge world.
We want to make this big world that you can explore and we also knew that we
wanted you to spend a lot of time in these places going back and forth that
was like a part of the game that we want to do like it was part of the routine.
I think Alec use the term ritual early early on these kind of like
building these rituals and building these routines like you can do in real
life. But we're like it's going to drag just to walk back and forth so the game
became a platformer like because jumping is fun.
basically. If you ever play Fallout or any of the Bethesda open world RPGs, I never walk
in those games, I'm constantly just...
bounding along the ground, I'm like the savior of the universe, just here he comes.
But with that, we'll come back to this in a little bit, but you could be expressive.
You could be like, oh, I'm hopping down the street and bouncing off of cars and bouncing
off of mailboxes and all that.
And that was pretty cool.
And that also enabled us to build up.
So now we can make tall buildings and hide things in the windows and do all that kind
of stuff.
And so soon, May was bouncing along those power lines.
And that was how that kind of came to be.
At the same time we knew that there's going to be a lot of talking like better
words and kind of coming out of animation and having friends that were
in like independent comics and magazine making stuff I want to do something
that was more interesting than just like a kind of a text box up front
because text boxes can be a little stale sometimes and they can also kind of
distance you it's like here's the game down there and then here's you and then
the text boxes somewhere in here and there's like this distancing we want to
do that we wanted this were bubbles to feel like they were part of the
environment so I kind of sketched out this like
these bubbly little comicky word bubbles and
this little waggly font.
And Alec kind of mocked something up,
this really great thing of generating and
doing various things with those,
which is really, really cool.
And we knew at that point...
that there were certain themes that we wanted to tackle.
Like, all of us had dealt with, you know,
mental health issues in our life,
had dealt with depression.
I was, I had dealt with something called dissociation,
which I actually didn't know was like a word
until we started making this game,
and someone was like, oh, that thing,
you're talking about this dissociation.
I was like, wow.
So, and there was that.
Also, all of us had been involved with the church
in the past and had since like lost our faith.
And all of us like had like,
we were all in our early 30s at the time.
now we're very old and the and we had some distance on the time period of
maze life. You know, she's around 20. And we thought we could comment on
that now we have some distance on it and there's some similarities between
that time in life in the time that we're in in our lives to there's this
is this transitional moment like may is like when you're 20 like you're
not a teenager anymore, but you're not quite an adult like people aren't
like people expect you to have responsibilities aren't super taking
you seriously enough to sell you alcohol at least in the US.
So, we had these kind of themes and they would grow and change, which we'll get into a little
bit later.
But with that and the dialogue and the...
the moving around we kind of had the basic building blocks of this thing now.
It's funny because people consider night in the woods a times like a nostalgia piece we have like none of us who are making the game had a lot of nostalgia for this time period of her life and actually a lot of the game.
Thematically is about how nostalgic can kill and nostalgia can really be a very bad thing just even like on a societal level.
But it was definitely, it was just something that we felt like we could explore at that time.
And I'm kind of glad we did because we went to some interesting places with it.
So Bethany and I were like broken in debt at the time.
And Alec was like, OK, cool, we're using Unity.
We should all get like Unity license.
And I was like, we don't have any money.
And this was before Unity was free for a while.
I actually don't know what it costs now,
but back then it cost $25,000 and we could not,
it didn't, but we couldn't afford it at least.
And I couldn't afford to take any time
off of trying to find work to do it.
And Alec was like, hey, let's do a Kickstarter.
And I was like, that's not gonna work.
And he was like, let's try it anyway.
And we're like, okay.
So we...
In the process of doing that we had to mock up a whole bunch of scenes which
means that we had to do a lot of decision-making right up front about
what this game was going to be so the good things and very bad things about
kickstarter is that you have to make a commitment of this is what our game is
like you know up from but we mock these things up and Alec made this really
great trailer track and it kind of start to take shape. Just these ideas
there was a feeling that was kind of coming out of it.
That was a little different than we had like first like thought about there's
moments in a project or any sort of idea where it starts becoming what is going
to be that happens like a lot of you know it's not like we had this idea and
then 3 years later we spent up the best version of it is like it involves a
grows and changes and we're able to kind of talk about like you know it it the
vibe of it kind of started coming through of like the town and like where
it was and what people are dealing with and
So I was like, yeah, our trailer's cool and everything,
but no one's gonna buy our weird,
you know, no one's gonna be interested
in our weird animal people in the Rust Belt game.
This wasn't a huge selling genre in 2013.
So we put up the Kickstarter and then we hit our goal within 26 hours.
And then we made four times our ask within that 30 day period.
Now, bear in mind, our initial ask was for $50,000, you know,
for three of us to work full time on it for years.
That's a very, very low number is what I'm saying.
But it was really.
exciting suddenly people are interviewing us and we were like news
you know this thing just kind of took off and had a life of its own
and it was not the first time that I I definitely forecasted doom and things
kind of worked out
so around about that time was when Finji came along
Alec had some previous a previous relationship with the Saltsmans and had
worked with them and
the
And so they came on as kind of our publisher,
just kind of like crossing T's and dotting I's
and like sending us up for, you know, talks like this
and stuff for like a really long time.
And none of this would have been possible without them.
So after a Kickstarter, like Alec and I,
it's like you wake up the next day
and you realize you've married someone.
Like we didn't know each other, like almost at all.
And we wanted to get something out,
but in part because there's like that thing,
like when you make a Kickstarter
that everyone expects you to like fail
or like rip people off.
So we wanted to like make something really fast.
and also just to work together to get something out some of his got to finish
something and so the kicks are ended like at the near the end of November
and then like 10 days in in December we made a
a little game called longest night which is kind of cool little thing.
And we could the stars would go around you and you could kind of connect with
the mouse of the different stars make a musical notes and then.
when you can then like after you kind of revealed the consolation the
characters down there with kind of expounding converse on it was our first
time like again like making something kind of feeling out a creative process
for kind of being trying to be flexible with the mechanics and stuff is my
first time trying to write these characters are draw them in like in in
ways that weren't in the trailer. You can see Greg kind of looks like a
ventriloquist dummy down there just like you know.
It was early days, but it was this kind of foundational moment.
And we made it like, we seriously released it like an hour before each of us went home
for Christmas.
Like, Alec finished it and he went to the airport in Vancouver and flew back to Winnipeg
and Bethany and I got in the car and were just hurtling through the night to central
Pennsylvania.
And I remember looking at my phone and seeing like, oh, um...
This is weird. What a weird year this has been as I'm watching people like on Twitter going
Oh Night in the Woods, they released a game. That's weird. Is this what the whole game is gonna be like?
I don't like this if this is gonna be the whole thing, but it's kind of a cool small thing and I was like wow
people on twitter talking about our game this is so weird 7 months ago I'd never
even met Alec was a thing about doing video games at all but now we'd released
a tiny little game and this is our full-time jobs. So here's the thing I
could keep doing this where I'm giving you the play-by-play of like every
month but I look and I did that talk last year to 2 and a half hours. So from
here I'm going to kind of switch to talking about some of the design
lessons kind of giving with design history of the rest of the game.
And just some general things that we came up with.
There were rules for us and things that we discovered
as we went through.
I was told that one of the purposes of these talks
is to be helpful.
Hopefully some of this is helpful.
So we didn't start working on the game full time until Valentine's Day the next
year because when you start a kick starter you don't just go I'm sorry
kick starter goodbye to jobs like you know you don't know if it's going to
if it's going to work out so we had we had like stuff left over that we still
had to finish like Alec had work I was making a cell phone commercial
animating it and and all that so we can really start working, but like right
after that.
the GDC was coming up and we made this little demo for it because we wanted to debut it at GDC.
So within like six weeks maybe, we made this like really super early demo.
Like I don't even think we have it anymore. I kind of wish I did because it would just be...
hilarious to look at now and Alec brought it here and demoed it and
people are like oh this is cool, but also this part sucks and like all
that and with the kind of you know feedback you get and so we took that
more like OK cool we can fix this part and do this and whatever this jump
doesn't work what we're thinking and
then soon after afterwards it was announced, you know we've been talking
to Sony and they announced that we're going that we're going to launch on
there.
on ps4 and they said hey come to the 3 this year
and we were like okay, we'll have a do we can't go to the 3 we'll know
we're not taking no that's ridiculous
but we spent the next couple months kind of polishing up and expanding on that
gdc
uh... demo
and um...
weed uh...
What one thing that we learned really quickly was that kind of a general rule
that I just put into words yesterday. This is a really nice way of saying
that we decided early on that like this game is going to be about characters
and in a in a story in a place and that was going to lead we're going to come
up with like our one mechanic and then like 2 different permutations on it
throughout the entire thing and build all of it around that bill the themes
build everything
around that.
that's applause next door so we I was like it's really raining out there so
the but we decided like yet that these moments these like other things are
going to kind of drive what we were doing mechanically with the game we
decided that really early on a really great example of this was we so we just
play this game called gone home which you might have heard of this like era
defining brilliant little game gone home and.
One of the things we liked about it was a lot of gone home was you're wandering around a house,
but then you're just like, oh, it was a water bottle.
You could pick it up and spin it around and look at it.
We jokingly were calling it first-person rummaging.
Like, you're like a raccoon.
You know?
Like, this is how a raccoon experiences your trash can.
And we thought that was really cool and we're like it would be cool to like be
able to like because you're in the game, you're kind of in like a side
scrolling view and like we want to get you up close into the world, you know,
to mess with the garbage again like a raccoon and so Alec had this in this
moment of brilliance came up with the name for it up pause mode.
it's a great little pun that I've been laughing at for like three years.
So there's a thing, you know, like in movies or TV shows where they'll have a real animal
sitting there and they'll have like a fake paw, right?
And they'll be like driving like or something or playing ping pong or like stirring soup
with a ladle.
And it's just like a stick with like dog fur on it and like a fake paw at the end.
For some reason, Alec, Bethany, and I think this is the funniest thing in the world.
And so that's how we designed maize paws.
That's why they're just on sticks.
And one of the reasons, when I talk about design following
the moment is because we're like, oh, we want to do this
thing, let's just make a mode where that works.
And in doing that, we, so we.
we're making this a 3 demo and we we built all these things we built this
town out we built this little story line to go through we've wrote so much
stuff and we at the end were like we should there's a we could put that a
scene where you don't accept the end of this with your could debut pause mode,
you know, and we can explain to everyone see get a pause but also you could
pause in games anyway, whatever and so like we
we so we kind of put that in like last minute like the day before we had to
ship it off to to eat 3 and so we want to eat 3. Here's our game next to like
under like under these giant jumbo tron's of like the order 1886 and
Metal Gear solid 5 and then here's like our game where you're like sitting on
the counter talking to your mom and we're like no one's going to play this
no one's going to like want to read this much on the GDC or on the 3 floor
all these acronyms and
we had like headphones and stuff so people would like put on this like
headphone and they had funds and they would just drift off like we thought
that
is to be about 15 to 20 minutes to get through the demo people spend like
almost an hour in it just like everyone a dialogue that may have a little
journal you can get doodles in that we ended up using the game and they and
people would like every single thing and
you know it was this really kind of like moment like there's one point a
woman was.
playing and she turned around and she took off the headphones after spending like 45 minutes
at it and she had like tears in her eyes
and she came up and she's like I've just never seen a game that was just made for like me
before and she like gave me this hug and I'm like
this is an experience I'm having on the E3 floor
right now
and I remember another thing was like so you know again people getting their faces
shotgunned off on these jumbotrons behind us
and this one guy finished it
and turned around and said
uh... guys this game that you're making is really dark
The other great one from that is a guy went up to Alec.
He played for a little bit.
And there's a part where you're talking to your mom and stuff.
And he kind of puts the thing aside.
He turns to Alec and goes, when does the adventure begin?
It was just this whole range of things.
Here's Alec and I when we first met.
Alec has a beard then.
He doesn't have now.
So this is evil Alec.
This is his evil twin, you can tell because of the beard.
So people had these really close experiences with this.
We won some awards at E3, which we're like, whoa,
I still have this in my house, because the first time anyone
was ever like, you made a good thing.
But you know what people like the most?
The donuts.
of all these other things. Everyone was like oh my God, the doughnuts, the doughnuts like it was so great. But when we started off the game, we were thinking like, oh, this may be some metroidvania ish stuff. Gonna hop around and
uh, and unlock these different things and
like unlock these different areas and all that is gonna be progression. Maybe some like big puzzles and like some more like kind of traditional narrative.
platform of things, but by this point, like all that was out the window. We're like, we're just gonna make this weird game
We're like reading your journal and drawing in it and you're like eating doughnuts and you're hopping around on rooftops
You're feeding rats with pretzels that you stole. These are all things that happen in the game and
Looking through telescopes and all these other things it changed and it got weirder and it's because we were
Open to like kind of like I said letting the design kind of follow the moment and it kind of started evolving
One of the things we started doing a lot was improvising.
We would just be like, oh, there's a knife fight part in the scene.
Let's just make a knife fight.
Let's see how that goes.
And we'd mock it up.
And a lot of times, it would be like, OK, that works.
And then we'd flesh it out and work on it a bit.
but a lot of these kind of different things kinda came from just oh yeah let's do that
that's cool
and uh... so like for example
uh... that led to all these like little like small things we called exceptions
they were exceptions to your normal uh...
uh... rules of gameplay and uh... so
like the knife fighting was an exception uh... the game is not about
you know bass playing for example
But the game is about being in May's position.
And one of the cool things about improvising and doing
these little things is after a while,
you just stop really caring if these things can
carry a game on its own.
There's like a tension that you want
to make sure every minigame could be its own game, right?
It's the most polished, balanced thing.
But the imbalance can actually be fun
if it doesn't last very long, or it can reveal character.
We don't prep you at all for this bass playing game when it comes.
And a lot of times we've watched people streaming, they're like,
oh shit, why am I playing the bass now? I don't know how to do any of this.
But in the game, Mae doesn't know what she's doing either.
She hasn't played bass in years. She doesn't know the songs at all.
So her panic is your panic at that point.
You failing and not being able to play this mini-game
is like, you know, if that's what happens to you,
fits perfectly well with the plot.
of what's happening and
that was like a lot of fun and that was just like that kind of like
like a bit our path and going we can just try a bunch of different stuff and
if it fits with the game like that was just do it okay, cool.
My favorite example of like a weird improvisation thing was so there's a
part where may kind of dies for a little bit. After she gets electrocuted
so long story and the and how sitting at the coffee shop in our
neighborhood were like we were like half the game.
And I was like, you know, it'd be funny if.
the little bonzi buddy desktop friend that Mae has,
Sharko the shark, on her laptop.
It'd be funny if he appeared to her in the afterlife.
That'd be funny.
And so I was like, oh, this is hilarious.
And so I wrote in, I kind of wrote it out
and I sent it to Alec and I was like, does this sound good?
And he's like, oh yeah, no, that's really funny.
And so by 7 p.m. that entire scene was in,
just art, music, everything, you know?
And that's it, and it didn't change, I don't think,
from there till release.
And it's one of my favorite kind of moments of the game and a lot of these
little moments that we're trying to like design
ended up being like some of our favorite and a lot of people who played the
game's favorite moments in the game.
And this leads us to another thing go simple so that you can be generous.
We talked a lot about generosity when we were making the game.
A good example of a really generous game like that kind of rewards poking around
just kind of keeps giving you stuff.
use cram so much interesting things and there is symphony of the night
into this Castlevania game you guys know something here than it is and so
I think this might have been like they thought that they weren't going to be
able to make another one maybe this team or something they just crammed all
these ideas into like boots that you can get to make you one pixel higher and
like little jokes everywhere like when you beat the you can beat the castle so
that it flips upside down you be again it's all different is like all the
different things and you're like fighting and hacking and slashing all
over the place but there's this one room kind of spoken up in this kind of like
howl of tones like among some people.
who are into the game.
So you're in this cathedral in Dracula's castle
because Dracula's apparently a churchgoer.
And off to the side, there's this room
and the music is really somber, it's really calm.
And all that's in there is this confessional booth
and you can sit down on either side of it
and eventually a little ghost will appear
and either kind of confess to you
or kind of take your confession.
And sometimes they stab you,
but you can't do anything else, that's it.
It's just a room to have this weird moment happen.
And so the idea of having these kind of calm moments,
these little like off to the side places
that you can just sit.
There's a lot of places in our game where you just sit.
And sometimes you'll end up talking to someone,
sometimes it's just there for sitting and that's it.
But us being able to be generous and like try to like put.
all these like little moments in the game that if you poke at you'll be
rewarded from
we could do that because we kinda went simple
so another thing is just going low-res on stuff another game we talked about a
whole bunch when we're making it is Final Fantasy VI
uh... there's a part where you're uh... you know
opera low-res and uh...
uh... they got so much performance out of their little like cast of little sprite
characters like flopping all over the place and like crying and
like living and dying and all this stuff and you buy it when you're watching it
it's like little puppets or something that lack of expressiveness that low
fidelity sells it and gives them like so much range that if you are doing
like full on like capture and I could own everything would take you hundreds
of millions of dollars.
Billions of dollars and take you forever to do, but you can do it with so
little and we didn't have access to a whole lot at the time we're running
our dialogue out of twine and.
But that that wasn't giving us everything we needed and was like I think creating a lot of more work for Alec to kind of get from there to it being in the game and so out of that was born a yarn which is a name that I came up with based on twine and that was my big contribution to the project and it it allowed us to do a bunch of different things.
John down there, John Manning, and his team expanded on it with Yarnspinner,
and eventually we had all this functionality in it,
and it was such that even I could hop in there and do...
like you know these like long dialogue sequences and stuff and one of the
things we have doing speaking of low fi was we we started making it so that
will to trigger animations of like different expressions and common things
we would use emoticons so end up with a mace as a line smiley face and
she'd smile at the end of it or she'd go like this or wave her arms,
Greg's whole this that's an emoji emoticon like and that was kind of
again like you know there a lot went into it is a pretty simple solution.
of doing that, doing that, just mixing and matching these kind of like lo-fi things.
Speaking of lo-fi, we had to make the characters kind of based around it, these simple characters
that just walked and talked and didn't do much.
I didn't have a lot of help when it came to the art for most of it.
My friend Charles Huttner came on and helped out.
He designed Bruce, who is one of my favorite characters in the game.
I think he's one of the best-designed characters.
He designed this guy.
He didn't make it into the game.
But...
I think one of the things is that like, this kind of like, you can have an opera with 16
pixel high characters and sell it.
You know, like a lot of people remember that Final Fantasy opera scene and are like, I
cried.
And you look at it and it's just like these little guys going, you know?
You don't need a lot.
You really don't need a lot.
Like, no matter how many facial polygons you have,
you're never going to suddenly, like, happen upon emotion
or human drama as, like, a hardware feature, you know?
No matter how much, how good your facial capture is,
how many polygons are in your face,
like, that's not going to create emotion.
You have to do that with the actual characters
and the story.
and all these things that aren't as sexy to talk about.
Expressiveness was a thing we talked about a lot.
We made another supplemental game the year after,
longest night, called Lost Constellation.
We made it about five or six weeks at the end of 2014.
And that's a
we were kind of sprinting through it that becomes a problem later on in this
talk and um...
expressiveness was i think i think i'll talk about a lot news just like it
giving the character the abit the player the ability to come mess around in that
world
and express themselves
we are in the game you're kind of uh... talking uh... it's framed as like a
fairy tale that may's grandfather is telling her
and when she was when she's young wandering through these woods and you
make the snowman and you can put these little found items in them and the
people on those items like inhabit the snowman like like regular snowman and
the
and like oh cool how about when we make a way for you to take these various
items and you can make the snowman faces yourself and so these are just a
couple of pull off the Internet
things that people did you know same.
the same items, but people just made so many of them and they and they love them
and we we have to put in a little camera button you see down there in the lower
right that would export a like a ping or a jpeg or something to your desktop and
people like posting them it was really neat little moment. I like this guy.
And that that expressiveness.
like paid off and people of them we we we were trying to and we we brought that
back into the main game in a lot of different ways. Last consolation is also
proof of concept for a lot of things we want to try in the game particular came
to exploration.
I think about exploration is I I think the exploration is one of the highest
things the best things you can do in a game like it both as like a like a
developer and like as a player like exploring finding things finding
secrets like seeing the whole like layout of of of something in like is is
one of the I think that the best things you can do in a game and that doesn't
just come with like exploring like a landmass it's exploring a story it's
exploring dialogue it's exploring characters all those are different ways
of exploration.
And, but exploration doesn't mean a lot if you can't miss things.
Like it becomes this precious thing, this interesting thing if you can miss it.
Like there's a thing when you're a developer where you want to make sure everyone sees
all of your beautiful work, right?
Like we can't let anyone miss anything at all.
But we wanted you to be able to miss things if you didn't think to go and poke or whatever.
Not to like punish you, but to allow there to be kind of the unknown out there.
that people could have different experiences.
Lost Constellation, we had a whole storyline
in our tiny little game that we made in five weeks
that you don't see if you don't think to go
and do certain things.
And people responded to it.
There's, to end this little design section,
there was a part in Lost Constellation,
this little throwaway bit,
that involved all the things I just talked about.
Designing for the moment, improvising,
trying to be generous, low-res solutions,
and expression and exploration.
There's a cliff.
in in lost constellation and we're like OK, what do you do with the cliff. I mean
the player could just jump off and we can have a death state we don't want to
do that this reset like now so like but what if
if you jump off the cliff that little May since the framing devices is the
story being told the young to little May what if she's just jumping in and going
and she jumped off a cliff and the grandfather like no she didn't just shut
up and keep telling the story and like haha like what if you jump off the cliff
again.
And Mae's like, she jumped off the cliff again!
The grandma's like, okay, all right,
we're just gonna keep going.
And you could do that 15 or 17 times.
And we just kept adding this little story.
You could just keep doing it.
Eventually he starts reading her a kid's book
that she hates called Charity Barity.
which is this little like very like cloying like it's all in
rhyme. Everyone learns a lesson. He starts reading the book to
you if you keep jumping off the cliff and eventually he's like
okay fine. I'm not I'm going to stop telling the story if you
don't don't shut up and that's when we put up the invisible
wall. That was a moment at it's one of the tiniest moments in
our games, but this one that I'm one of the I think the most
proud of because it it was all those things and it was just a
moment of us. Let's just try this and it worked and like
almost no one finds it at all.
I've watched a whole bunch of people play this game,
like five people have found it, you know?
But it's a great, great thing, I think.
And it's something that I'm really, really proud of.
So those are all like design things.
This is like the design talk,
but there's a lot of things that go into design
that aren't just like mechanics, right?
The game has a lot of ideas in it,
has a lot of context in it.
And a lot of the things that we did,
we wanted to
We had some things to say we had some some ideas and they came out through it
unsolvable puzzles and and unproficient which I found as an actual word
yesterday.
May isn't a character that is good at things really other than hopping on
things like she's not smarter than you should not make better life decisions
than you. She is not tougher. She is not more clever like so many games are
about people who can do amazing things but that's a really.
constrained kind of story that you can tell
like the story of the person who is really good at something is so many
games and that's like a really specific thing or like the story of for example
the space captain who can sleep with up to half of the people in their ship,
you know,
depending on how they play their cards that super attractive,
extremely charming boss is a very,
very specific kind of character and you have to tell specific kind of story.
But that is such a constrained kind of story that you can tell.
By giving May, by not giving her that level of proficiency,
by not giving her puzzles that she can solve,
May is not going to bring back...
like the mining industry to her town may is not going to suddenly cure all from
mental health problems, you know the game of the game is for coming to terms
with both of those things. Those things don't have a really quick solution to
them you can't power up and get rid of all that and meet immediately all those
things are difficult with mental health you can get help and that's a thing that
may kind of like you know learns I think throughout the game, but a lot of these
other things like these are struggles you don't necessarily have access to
all the time.
And that leads us to a thing, kind of a pun,
and the piggybacking on that idea is,
Alec early on was really gracious
and let Bethany and I kind of go
where we wanted with the story.
And he, like, you know, obviously collaborative,
but he trusted us a lot at the beginning,
which was really cool.
I had early on played the game called Cart Life,
Cart life was I think the first time I saw some my own experiences with being
broke and being desperate and being afraid in a video game and to the point
where I couldn't finish that was having panic attacks by the end of it.
We went on to be it came clear that we couldn't write about these people and
these places that we knew without going into the actual politics of it and like
that scary sometimes in games.
But we kind of can avoid it it would be.
The themes that we had of mental health, of capitalism,
of loss, of loss of belief in God,
the removal of a central organizing force in your life,
which a lot of these things have that feeling to them.
You kind of can't just take those aesthetics
and slap them on.
So we talked about it really directly.
One character reads this poem where,
how far is Silicon Valley from here?
I'm in it.
Okay, cool.
We talked about burning it to the ground in this game.
We're kind of kidding, but like, but we wanted to talk about that
because you know from where we were sitting there's this massive
level of inequality and power and wealth and all these different
things and we don't have access to that.
Everyone we know is like desperate and just trying to get by.
That's where we were honestly before this Kickstarter.
And so we were just trying to be honest about it.
And there's a lot of things where games,
like games that are celebrated for their mature politics,
often will just take the aesthetics of a struggle
and then look at it solemnly and go,
yes, this is, we've made a serious game.
We're very grown up as video games now.
You know, you could.
You know, you have like these kind of famous devs who are like,
yeah, we're going to use all this really charged imagery,
say from like, you know, Jim Crow or something.
And we're going to put that in a game.
And then like, let's say the character goes to an alternate dimension
where suddenly all the black people have the guns
and they're just like killing white children everywhere.
And then the takeaway is extremism is bad.
Like, the, it's, it's tourism.
It's a kind of tourism. You take these struggles, you take these real live issues in these real live places,
and you just say,
yeah, that's a thing. We're grown up,
and that's, and then we will make some kind of just general, well, both sides are bad or,
you know, conflict is bad. We should just really check it out type of thing,
you know, where everything is just kind of this
equivocating thing.
And it's celebrated in games, and it drove us nuts,
because everybody hates a tourist.
to quote pulp the sun common people so we were just like no we're going to
speak honestly about the things not to like preach at people because we
weren't trying to make a game that was that was trying to blow people's minds
like did you know that there's poor people in a place called the rust belt
that are like getting screwed over by capitalism and it's this really
whatever we're doing that we're trying to make myths for ourselves we're
trying to talk about these things that we cared about.
and people like politics and games if we can look at it kind of from like a not in my backyard way
like it's over there we went away and we saw a political struggle so if you talk about like
labor if you talk about thank you i just got the i'm gonna have to wrap it up soon thing if you
talk about you know labor if you talk about labor in the games industry if you talk about the need
for workers to kind of organize in that space people certainly suddenly start getting whatever
if you can talk if you talk about that happening on like a space colony somewhere people are like
all right well in the future they'll have to deal with that
But if you talk about it now, people suddenly start like,
oh, it's in my backyard now.
People are like, oh, this might affect me.
This is really, really uncomfortable.
If you talk about GDC, you talk about the unpaid labor
and underpaid labor that goes on here,
and the profit that's made by the company here,
all these different things, people start getting really,
whatever.
I think that being able to just be honest
and make kind of mythologies of our own
about the people we knew
and the things that we struggle with
and just kind of not bullshit about it.
that was kind of like a really kind of big thing.
Bethany did so much like research and so much like looking into kind of her own
past and the place where she's from and it was like and the kind of issues there
and that and makes up so much of the bedrock kind of the dirt underneath this
game that you know and like for every time that y'all talk about anything I
just talked about and it makes you kind of like someone uncomfortable there's 10
people who are like thank God someone said something.
right. A thing that art can do is tell people that they're not alone.
That is one of the best things that can do.
Being able to speak honestly
about these type topics and just be upfront about it
and not be, and not kind of try to just
have this kind of, these aesthetics of it means that you can kind of connect
with people in a way that you can't otherwise.
One of the last things is just do what you can with what you have.
You know, Bethany and Alec and I all brought the things
that we were okay at to begin with.
We learned a whole bunch of new things,
but we were just like, let's see where this goes.
Let's see where, you know, what we can like pull out of this
what we can kind of make and kind of collaborate together.
This is one of the first times I think all of us
were in a room together back in like 2016.
And here's us like a year later, much more tired.
Some of the hard lessons that we learned from this was
crunched, we crunched ourselves nearly to death.
Me, literally, I almost died by the end of it,
according to my doctor.
I think that, that was a hard lesson.
We sprinted and sprinted for like three and a half years,
and it took like a lot of,
like I'm still dealing with health issues from it,
from our launch like a year ago.
Imagine if you're in a place where,
like we're doing that to ourselves,
imagine if you're in a place that,
your employment is in danger if that isn't done.
These projects can just chew you up and spit you out.
But we released the game.
People liked it, which was really shocking to us.
I'm sorry, shocking to me.
The theme of this is I never think
anything is going to work out.
And then Alec goes, I think it'll be OK.
And then it works out OK.
We got lucky.
We got really, really lucky.
People would say, I think because we tried to be honest,
you know, people would say,
hey, playing this game, like, saved my life.
That's not us.
Like, when you make art or we make whatever,
whatever you put out there is only part of it.
Like, other people meet you there, you know?
people were coming and kind of meeting us there
and having these experiences and these kind of deep experiences.
And we were having these kind of deep conversations with people.
And we were just lucky.
We were just really, really, really fortunate.
From the Kickstarter, our Fingy was
able to get us funding to kind of sustain us
for the back half of it.
never before was a game designer.
Bethany never worked in games.
Alec had never worked with us.
All these were chances that just happened to work out.
This is not like the key to success.
We got lucky.
Loads and loads of like amazing people do super great work
and it just doesn't kind of work out in the same way.
But one of the great things about making art
in conclusion is that
We committed to something that can only come from us.
We threw out a lot of rules, and we committed to the moment.
And we put stories and characters and themes first,
and went where that led.
Bethany and I were novices, and we had no experience in games.
And Alec brought us on and trusted us.
And we ended up pouring just ourselves and our lives into it
in healthy and unhealthy ways.
And it led us to this game where we could just be honest.
And people were really gracious in responding.
Art can tell people that they're not alone.
Art can challenge and motivate.
and agitate art can change people's minds and our can just be a place to go
you know if it is an easier unpleasant we have people who are like I just have
to go back this game every now and again to the music and is being they're
talking to the mom there every morning is this like safe
cool space for me.
We also people who like this change change my outlook on a bunch of things
to change my politics has changed my relationships with others has changed my
relationship myself this put a name on a disorder that I have.
Let's put a name on how I feel at work.
Because we were just honest.
We didn't really know how to do anything else.
Art can show you kind of an image, good or bad,
where you kind of recognize your reflection in it, like me here.
People would talk about this scene where Mae kind of tries to hype herself up for a party,
but it ends up kind of just talking about how she's gross and unattractive and weird.
And someone's like, I thought that was the only person that felt like that.
I'm like, I'm 36 and I did that before coming here, you know?
Um, so...
Games can forge those connections with people, you know.
The art that we make can forge those connections.
They can tell each other that we're not alone
and we can affect each other.
And people said that that's kind of what this game did to,
good for them.
And I don't know what more you could ask for as a creator,
right, is to have people come to you and say,
this thing that made this connection between us
and all this like worked out
and we had just this moment together and I didn't feel alone.
So that's my time, everybody.
Do we have any time left for questions?
We have time for questions.
Okay, those are the mics.
If anyone wants to ask a question.
If I somehow didn't address one iota of this game, please ask.
Please ask.
Hi.
Oh, you have to introduce yourself and say, I'm Bla from Bla.
Okay, hi, I'm Lisa from New Zealand.
So I wanted to ask, because I haven't read anywhere,
why did you decide to have random little creatures
and animals like squirrels and cats running around
when it's a town of cat people?
That was God's original plan for the world.
No, the animal people in the game
are just how I drew cartoon animal people.
There's just regular animals.
Why are there humans and yet there are apes?
Checkmate.
No, there's no reason at all.
There's no reason.
People are puzzled about that.
That is actually the number one question we get, is,
there's a cat, but there's also cats?
So, yeah.
I hope that's a sufficient answer.
Other mic.
Hi, I'm Sienna from Los Angeles.
Hey, hey.
And I have kind of a process question,
like a writing process question.
So one of the things that you guys did really well
in Night in the Woods, I felt was the fact that
you really had this town that felt like
the people's lives in it were progressing
separate from you and you were just kind of
eavesdropping on them.
Like for example, the two dudes at the bar.
Right, every day had their relationship evolve a little.
And I was wondering if when you were, how did you go about writing those scenes?
Did you choose to be like, I think there should be some people here, and then you figured
out the whole thing?
Or as you were going day by day, did you kind of feel like you needed more?
Yeah early on I think we just had some general ideas we wanted the world to
feel alive without you like Alec made these great like what we call it squirrel
tech like the squirrels with a run around we made this great random car
generator like you'll never see the same car in the game twice and stuff so we
wanted the world to feel alive in the like the world didn't need you basically
if may was not walking on the street those 2 dudes outside of the outside of
like the football bar we're still going to be talking is still going having
their ups and downs in life.
And so that was it like I think early on it was just a funny idea and then as we
went on it became more and more complex that there would be whole story lines
and all sagas if you were around for you miss it like the like I was saying
within the exploration part, but if you paid attention. It would be something
that would would give back to you and you can learn more about it. I think
one of the reasons why some folks have like really short play times and some
people spend like 20 hours in the game.
It's because some folks are really attuned to that,
and they'll go and seek it out, and there's a whole lot of places all around that.
So after a while, you just get an eye, a feeling for writing these little arcs
and these little mini-dramas.
They're like some of the most interesting stories in the game, I think,
are these tiny little things.
And understanding that.
And sometimes we had it so that they would only start when you triggered them the first time,
but a lot of times it was just ongoing.
And, you know, you would just kind of pop in and pop out,
kind of like you do in real life, because that made the world feel fuller.
and it made exploration mean something.
So yeah, after a while, it just became kind of second nature
to do.
Thank you.
Other mic.
Hey, I'm Jasper from Australia.
And I, yeah, sort of following on from that,
I was wondering about, there's a lot
of different moments in the game,
as you talked about, that have some relation
on the overall game and some that are just self-contained.
And.
To me, that was really nice because it kind of represented
like how life is.
Sorry, excuse me.
And I remember you tweeted a while ago about maybe you were
frustrated that people kind of felt that these were all
linked and that there was some sort of overarching thing that
happened that linked every single thing in
the game together.
And I was just wondering if you could talk a little bit
about that.
Yeah.
The football fans that were just mentioned, they're behind
the whole thing.
full game. No there's there's a thing in a lot of kind of like it's been going on
for a while but like right now I think it's a big thing of like everything has
to be meta everything has to be like plot a like gear a of the plot here
this turn a gear over here or else this is just what do you even doing and
having this here if you have a missing character they have to show up later as
that mysterious person
you know if there's like a villain you don't know who it is it has to be your
dad you know it has to be like
this little like
christopher nolan ask puzzle box type things and those things are cool
but it's not like how you can do like you know that's not the way to do
uh...
I'm getting the wrap it up thing here.
And I think that's kind of a frustration and we wanted to avoid that.
We wanted to have these episodic moments because we just liked episodic things and stories.
And we wanted to have these little closed off sections just so you can find, you can
stumble into like the confessional room, you know, the story version of that.
All these little things that fleshed out the world and maybe got across ideas.
expressed character and themes and all these things like so many things exist
in the world just for that the 2 guys outside of the smelters bar, you know
they don't exist to you know, you know be main plot points there there in the
world and you can follow their little story and their little life you can
kind of get like involved that way and it's I for me that's over and for us I
think in the game that's really a lot of the beauty of the world is right.
It's not just this thing that your character goes through and drives all of
it. It exists without you and
you other characters having their own agency has nothing to do with you
makes them more human and makes the story in the world more human and I
think we wanted to just have a lot of humanity in the game.
So there's that okay. I think that's all the questions I can take what we're going over to the wrap-up room,
which is apparently right around the corner.
Yeah, it's it's around the actually don't know where it is.
It's right around the corner over there.