Okay everybody, settle down, settle down.
It's the final day of Game Developers Conference.
Everyone have a good conference this year?
Yeah!
Surprisingly good, amazingly good.
I have no complaints except for maybe how late I was out last night.
I'm sure like many of you.
So before we get started on the Game Developers Conference, a few quick words about something
else that's happening at the Game Developers Conference.
That's the metagame.
Any players of the metagame here in the audience?
Yeah!
Thank you.
Well, on behalf of Local No. 12, which is Mike Edwards, Colleen Macklin, John Sharp,
and myself, we want to thank all of you for a really fabulous, incredible conference game
this year.
I think...
I've been doing conference games at the Game Developers Conference every year for the last
12 years, and the metagame I think really is a sort of unqualified success.
It's really been a great time.
And you guys have been so great, and we've gotten so many requests from people that want
full decks of the metagame, that as of this moment, I am prepared to announce...
that just about 15 minutes ago we launched our Kickstarter page
to raise money to print metagame decks for all of you to order.
So look for us on Kickstarter and thank you
of Players and Game Developers Conference and our sponsors
the NYU Game Center and BBC and the IGDA
for helping make that happen. You've been fabulous.
After this session, immediately after this session at 1.30 at the IGDA booth in the South
Hall is the final tournament.
Even if you don't have a lot of cards, you might qualify for a local number 12 t-shirt
just for showing up.
And if you show up, you definitely will help determine the winner because like all the
other metagame matches, it will be a vote by the bystanders.
All right, without further ado, let's get down to it.
The Game Design Challenge GDC 2011.
Now, yeah, let's hear it.
Okay.
Game Design Challenge.
We have an absolutely sort of like face-melting roster of Game Design Challenge on stage here today.
You know...
The Game Design Challenge is about challenging game designers, how about that, to think about
really unusual, difficult game design problems.
It gives us a glimpse into how these incredibly talented and brilliant designers think about
problems and it also gives us a glimpse into new ways of thinking about games that might
spark ideas in their work or in your work or in the industry as a whole.
I've been doing the Game Design Challenge for a long time.
We've looked at...
It seems like the love story last year was real world permadeath where Jenova Chen, our
returning champion, had the winning entry.
Here's how it works.
About a month or two before the Game Developers Conference, I let our panelists know about
our theme, and they have to put together a concept that they're going to pitch to you.
The only restrictions are that it really has to be for present-day technology, and other
than that, they can present it however they wish, and I think we're going to have some
unusual and interesting presentations today.
I always try and pick a theme for the Game Design Challenge that somehow is a riff or
parody or reflection of something that's in the air of the game industry at large.
And, you know, some of the things that are going on this year really have to do with
the explosive growth and maybe controversy of games played on social networks, like Facebook.
You know, these games are pervading our lives in unusual ways.
They take over our time.
They're sort of appointment-style, asynchronous gameplay.
They make us...
The idea that games are potentially a lens for looking at everything and the entire world
and all of our social relationships and societal structures and cultural artifacts as games,
within the lens of games.
The funny thing is that human culture has had...
An idea of putting a sort of metaphysical frame around everything that we do and who we are
and how we behave and what we should and shouldn't do and kind of grading and judging our actions.
And some might call that religion.
And so the theme this year of the Game Design Challenge was merging these two ancient forms
of human practice, right?
Merging games and religion.
And what would that mean?
So the challenge that I gave...
Our intrepid designers was create a game that could also in some way be a religion.
And not a game about a religion, right?
Not a game which tells a story of a priest who has a spiritual journey or something,
but rather a game that really in its practice and in the way it operates on its players
or in society is also in fact in some way a bona fide religion.
I can't wait to see what these guys have come up with, and I'm sure you can't wait as well.
You all have a really big part in the Game Design Challenge every year, which is to vote
on the winner through applause, so listen carefully.
And I think that I want to share with you guys the prizes.
So the winner will get to pick which of the three prizes they want, but everyone gets
a prize.
First, we have this New Testament Pocket Edition, which I can now...
I've done some Bible thumping at the Game Developers Conference.
We also have the Book of Mormon, another great book,
and L. Ron Hubbard's Dianetics, just for a different flavor.
So, this is what they'll be competing for.
Alright, without further ado, we are going to bring up Jason Rohr.
Jason Rohr is a legend in the art games movement.
He's made wonderful games like Passage that have moved many of us,
and recently released his game,
inside a star-filled sky. Let's hear it for Jason Rohrer!
And also the Dianetics Prize is awesome because I actually went to the college library and was reading all the Scientology books that they had there
when I was thinking about this.
So yeah, so Scientology is close to my heart.
Okay, so Chainworld.
So a very old purpose of religion was to explain
physical mysteries in the world, you know, like these huge mountains, they're so impressive,
they fill us with these spiritual feelings, like where did they come from, how did they
get here?
A good example of this comes from Aboriginal Australians, which have this spiritual idea
of a dreaming or dream time that kind of existed before humanity.
This is a painting by a famous Aboriginal artist, Clifford Possum, of a dreaming, of
a particular dreaming from Aboriginal spirituality, and if this painting looks like a map, that's
because this painting is a map.
So, over time that purpose of religion seems like it's mostly been replaced by science,
and like this particular sub-purpose of religion has been replaced by technology, right?
So maybe as a coincidence or maybe because of this, I'm not sure, religion kind of turned
inward, right?
So we don't explain physical mysteries anymore, we explain non-physical ones.
Mysteries about death, mysteries about how one should live one's life and things like
that.
But we still have physical mysteries, and I'm not talking about like gravity or unified
theory of physics or anything like that.
We still tell stories to explain them, very simple physical mysteries, not complex, esoteric
ones.
As an example, this is my grandfather.
This is the guy holding the pen, pointing at the map.
This is from 1961.
He's standing next to the Ohio Highway Director and two Ohio State Senators, and he's pointing
at a map because they were talking about this.
This is I-77, Interstate 77, goes all the way from Cleveland down to South Carolina.
and as Google Maps shows at the blue line here.
And back then in the 60s, they were building this thing.
Part of the interstate highway system.
And my grandfather was the first mayor of Fairlawn, Ohio,
a tiny little village.
And right after incorporating, they were like,
well, here comes this highway.
We're going to put it through the center of your village.
We're going to bisect your village with it.
And he, of course, as mayor, said this was going to ruin our village
and put up a fight with the state and so on.
It lasted a number of years and there were some lawsuits
and that kind of thing.
But in the end, he won.
So this is where they wanted to put the highway,
where those red dots are.
And this is where they ended up putting it, in the circuitous route around Fairlawn
into some countryside that then became the fastest growing commercial area
in the country back in the 80s and 90s
because this big highway passed through farmland right near a populated center.
So now, to this day, millions of people who drive on this road every year
take this long circuitous route because of my grandfather.
It's like my grandfather's dog leg in I-77.
So, uh...
So I knew my grandfather and I remember him, but he died when I was like eight or something like that.
My real memories of him have become vague and these larger-than-life stories like this have grown in importance.
There was recently a newspaper article that got passed around my family about this thing my grandfather had done,
which is how I found out about it.
And the physical traces he's left behind have grown in importance too.
As another example, at a recent family reunion, we took a drive around Fairlawn.
As the first mayor, the legend has it in my family that my grandfather designed this sign.
If you go to the Fairlawn City website, you see the sign.
And if you drive around Fairlawn, you see it today.
And we took a trip to this park where
there's a big stone edifice with a sign embossed on it.
And we all stood in front of it and got our picture taken
at this family reunion.
On that same trip, we also drove past the house
that my grandfather built.
At least that's what we always said when I was growing up,
double brick construction in an era of timber frame and so on.
So how are these places not like shrines?
And how are these visits that we take to them
not like pilgrimages?
My grandfather has become less of a man and more the idea of a man, as the real details
have faded and been replaced with these imaginary details that we're kind of filling in.
You know, remaining photographs of him become like religious icons, and we also hold on
to these supposed utterances.
I never heard him say this, but we'd say that he said it, right?
And I actually gave Chris Hecker this piece of advice at the top just last week.
So...
Uh...
Anyway, yeah, so I still treat this as kind of this holy wisdom passed down from my grandfather
that I'm willing to foist upon a friend, right?
Like Proverbs.
And so what is an idea of a man, an ideal man, but a god?
And our connection with him becomes very spiritual and religious as time passes.
And this is more dramatic the farther we go back in time, like I never even knew my great
grandfather but I've driven past the house that he built and I've seen a couple of photographs
and I have all these imaginary details that have filled in about him, all these stories
that I've heard about him.
So, the same process happens for historical figures, like if you're really into Abbeck's
painting, you know, you go off to Long Island and visit Jackson Pollock's barn, where he
did his famous splatter painting, drip paintings, and you know, it's like this shrine, all these
things are preserved, the paint splotches that he left right when he died, his cigarette
butts, his shoes, they're sitting there, you can walk up to them.
And it really is like a pilgrimage for people who are into this kind of thing.
And taking this process to the limit, we get deep human mysteries like...
Stonehenge, we imagine the druids, when we think about Stonehenge, we really do imagine
them somehow magically lifting these things up or figuring out technology to do this.
You know, I guess even though supposedly the druids didn't really build the thing, but
we still think of them, right?
So here's my summary of this humanistic religious practice that I'm observing in the world.
We become like gods to those who come after us.
Okay, so what I want to do is foster this kind of religious practice through a game design.
So, here's a metagame that sort of comes close to doing that.
A game where, instead of everyone playing the game at the same time out in the world,
one person in the world plays the game at a time,
and they're the only person playing it, and then when they're done,
they pass the game on to the next person, and they play it,
and they're the only one in the world, and they pass it on, and pass it on, and so on.
So, this also, along with starting to get close to this predecessor-successor relationship that I'm talking about,
this spirituality has the properties.
of religious practice like the chain could be a secret practice.
There's mystery about the nature of the game because you don't get to talk to everyone
who's playing it.
There's this one person, mysterious person out there in the world playing it and you're
waiting your turn.
You're waiting to be chosen.
There's this anticipation.
You might get to have this experience sometime in your lifetime and you might not.
But it doesn't really foster the predecessor-successor spirituality and the connection that I wanted.
When you start a game normally, you sort of assume that the start state that you get when
you start the game is the start state.
When you start playing The Witness...
and this is like the reality for you.
This is what has been laid out for you.
It's your in-game foundation.
It's like, you know, like the game designer is God,
and they create the start, like that's Jonathan Blow there with the crown,
and he creates the start state and the witness.
And understanding the witness is in a lot of ways like understanding that one God.
Like, what did he put here for me?
Why, what is this supposed to mean?
What's he trying to communicate?
And we really do think about the game designer a lot of times
when we're playing a game and trying to understand it.
But what if your start state wasn't actually a start state?
What if it was someone else's end state?
And as an example of this, I mean, this is a simple reconnection of that chain game I talked about before.
Like when you start a Mario level and you're in there, you see some configuration of blocks,
and so you sort of think of it as a given.
And when you see this, you might say, well, that must be put there for a reason.
I'm small, I can't break the blocks.
Maybe I'll look for some coin blocks right under the bottom,
or maybe I'll get big and try and slide under there and break through to see,
there must be something up there, that must be there for a reason.
You assume it's a start state created by the designer.
But what if it was really somebody else's end state
from a start state that looked like this, right?
So there's a story here about how that tunnel came to be,
and it wasn't really put there by the designer on purpose.
It was sort of a side effect of how the previous player got through the level.
I think a chain platform is a really bad idea
because the challenges can be spent, right?
This turtle is spent,
and the second player gets maybe a less interesting game
or maybe a confusing game.
The previous player pretty much ruined that part of the level for the next player.
But what about a game that has these properties?
So you have a goal to accomplish.
Modifying the game world is a natural side effect of pursuing that goal,
but modification simply changes the terrain that the next person will face
without ruining the terrain for the next person.
It's being modified, but it's not being ruined.
It's like creating maybe new challenges along the way.
And the platformers may be too simple to have those side effects have that property.
So in a game with those properties, you might not realize how your modifications of the world will be perceived by the next player
as you're playing along doing what you're trying to do, or you might realize it and modify the world's intention.
The way my grandfather might have been thinking about what successors would think about the state of Farallon
when he made the choices he did about how to redirect the highway and so on.
He might have been thinking about posterity.
And as the next player, you'll wonder how the world came to be in the state that it's
in.
You know, like, wow, what was the previous player doing that left these grooves in the
game state?
These gouges in the train?
You know, what's this road for?
Where does it lead?
What was this, what was, what did it mean?
And you'll tell yourself stories to explain how these things came to be.
Just the way, just the same way that we tell stories about Stonehenge and have this sort
of spiritual connection with these people.
So I ran in circles for a while trying to come up with a primary game to plug into this chain metagame.
I tried to invent a new game with these properties, but my mind kept circling back.
I was trapped in the gravity of an existing game.
A game where you modify the world as a side effect of pursuing your goal,
and a game where you leave traces behind and discover other people's traces.
And it also happens to be, and I think it's probably true for a number of people in the audience,
one of the most spiritual experiences I've ever had with a game.
in my entire life, I think, and I think a lot of people agree.
So my game design is a Minecraft mod.
Or a Minecraft metagame, a game that's played with Minecraft.
So you receive the game on a USB stick.
In fact, it's this USB stick right here.
This is the only one in the world.
And I've written some scripts that are on this stick
that make the game, glue the game together,
but Minecraft is also on this stick,
and it's the only Minecraft world that's on this stick.
So this is kind of like the ark. This is the sort of holy object that gets passed down.
And here are the rules.
So this is the canon law of ChainWorld.
So you plug this into your computer, you run Minecraft via one of the included scripts that's on here.
You don't just run Minecraft directly.
You start a single player game when Minecraft starts up and you pick ChainWorld as the world you're going to go into.
And you play until you die exactly once.
And while you're playing there's a couple of sub-rules.
You can't erect wooden signs with text.
to communicate to somebody in the future.
And suicide is permissible.
So you don't have to keep playing until you die naturally.
Maybe you play for a while and say, I'm done, I'm going to commit suicide.
And immediately after dying and respawning, you quit to the menu.
So after dying, you respawn, you've lost all your items, you're back to the default state,
and you're back to the spawn point, and then you quit to the menu.
And then allow the world to save, because Minecraft does that automatically.
and you exit the game and then my script is kind of waiting in the background there and
it will automatically copy the world that you've modified back onto the USB stick, replacing
the ones on there, and it also deletes it off your hard drive.
So then you pass the USB stick onto someone else who expresses interest, not just like,
hey, you want to play this?
I don't even know if you play Minecraft.
You've got to find someone who's already sort of interested in the idea and interested in
the idea of participating in this religion.
Find a seeker.
Right?
Um, so, and then you never discuss what you saw or didn't in ChainWorld with anyone,
although I'm going to break that rule here in a second a little bit.
Um, and you never play again.
You're only allowed to play once in your lifetime.
Um, so, I was player one.
And I had all these plans and I wanted to construct these things for the next person to discover.
And my seven-year-old child was with me and he's coming up with ideas and we're playing along and then...
I'm not going to tell you how it happened because you'll probably run into it too because it's still waiting for you there.
But I had one of the most heart-breaking and poignant deaths that I've ever...
way too soon...
that I've ever experienced in a video game in my entire life.
And my child who was sitting there was in tears.
And he wanted to tear this out of the back of my computer and stomp on it.
We didn't do anything for them. We didn't leave anything for them to discover.
Oh my god, what do we, you know...
Yeah. So, someone in the audience is going to get to be player two.
But, you know, according to rule number seven,
you know, it has to be someone who expresses interest.
I didn't just want to throw it into the crowd or have it taped to one of the bottom of your seats.
That would break rule number seven.
So I need, you know, someone in the front row who's gonna...
I can't give it to a friend, it can't be a friend.
Yay!
So, that's Chainwhirl. Thank you, everybody.
I think I might be a convert, although I've also been told I'm a religious slut, so maybe
I'll experience a few religions before the end of the session.
Okay, that joke did not, maybe not comprehensible.
We'll all wake up in the middle of the night chuckling about it.
Next I'd like to bring to the stage someone who truly is a legend of the game industry,
John Romero, who among other things is responsible for games like Doom that helped invent what
we know as the contemporary computer and video game.
Without further ado, ladies and gentlemen, John Romero!
All right. I'm not walking around this time.
Got to get my thing up there.
OK, I'm glad that I didn't do the same thing.
I think it's a great idea.
OK. DPI. It's a DPI button right there.
Yeah.
OK. Awesome. OK. Here it is.
What is a religion? I'm asking that question. A religion is a deity. It has worshippers.
There's a lot of devotion. There were some religious events in history that were game-like,
such as the Crusades, which excelled at deathmatch. Did a great job.
But I decided, you know, I kept on coming back to the Trinity, to the deity, to the
worshippers, and to the devotion.
Nice.
In the beginning, there was...at God.
And actually, there were a whole lot of gods.
Lots of numbers.
But then, rose the one true God, God 6502.
located in Cupertino.
But then God 6502 had a son. It was Messiah 6502
here in San Francisco.
And the Messiah 6502 soon collected followers.
First,
the first twelve are the apostles. Now follow on Twitter immediately
Messiah 6502. Anybody that's on Twitter.
We only have 12 apostles.
We have, actually, let me check it out.
Because I know that some people already kind of jumped on the
Messiah was discovered a little bit earlier by several people.
And we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 right now.
Messiah is trying to get followers.
And you guys can't see that right now?
OK.
Okay, that's okay, I don't need to show everybody.
Okay, one, two, three, four, five, six, I think we have twelve.
All right, wow, we have way more than twelve.
For those of you that can't see, John is looking at a Twitter page with followers of a Twitter user called...
Eleven, twelve, okay.
All right, I got the first twelve.
Let's, I'm going to need the...
Let me pop this up real quick.
Okay, we have 12 apostles.
They need to come down to the front of the stage, so I'm going to need the lights to come up a little bit.
And those apostles are Christine and Norman Truffle.
FF Paladin, if you guys are in the room.
So we know that there should be people in the room.
More internets? Is more internets in the room?
I need my colored stuff here.
Okay, each of the apostles is going to get a stack of paper.
Squirrel tweets? That's alright. Alright, squirrel.
Ian Bogost.
Chelsea Howe. Is Chelsea Howe here?
Jane McGonigal.
Yes, you made it.
Let's see, Paul Rylands, Richard Lemarchand, Brian Cash,
John Sharp, and Colleen Macklin.
Did we get all 12? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
Is that 11? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
The 12 are all here?
All right.
No, no, each of the 12.
needs to come up and get one of these and then stand right in front here.
Over this way. Here you go.
Okay. You're ready.
All right, now, let's go back.
OK.
So the apostle rule is you each have a pad of sticky notes
to gather followers in the audience.
And you have to find followers and return here
after precisely two minutes.
Go now.
All right.
All right, they're going to try and convert everybody
as fast as possible.
If you've been converted, you can resist conversion.
You know, you can be atheist.
Don't take a piece of paper.
Sometimes it's involuntary.
You know, you don't have to stick to one apostle.
You can trade paper with other people if you like.
All right, you guys can crusade if you want.
Crusade all over this room.
Feel free to check into Mecca GDC on Foursquare.
It's right here in this room, Mecca.
You can meditate in silent prayer if you're not getting converted.
I see some paper getting shredded up and thrown in the air.
You can drop your beliefs immediately if you want to be converted.
You can throw that paper down.
Start a holy war mentally with somebody else.
Stare them down.
Everybody's got almost like a minute left.
Alright, when you're done converting people, come back up to the front.
I feel that, uh...
Remember, you guys can resist this conversion.
Maybe if you don't like the Apostle, you can throw away the paper.
Okay, time's up.
All apostles come to the front.
All right.
If you didn't hand out all of you, if you didn't convert everybody, that's great.
Everybody back.
Don't be desperate.
Oh, you can't convert the Messiah.
Ha ha ha ha!
Oh my God!
Yeah!
Alright.
Is everybody back?
As a impartial judge.
Colleen...
you're not supposed to get them all converted there.
Ha ha ha!
Ok, that might have been disobedient.
Um, ok, now the winner...
is the apostle with the most miracles.
And the apostles are all up front here.
If your apostle marker has a star on it, then you've received a miracle.
Hallelujah!
Yes!
Disciples with miracles, come to the front.
Yeah.
Everybody come up to your apostle.
So we have to kind of spread out if everybody's been converted.
Now everybody, all apostles count your miracles.
Gather your followers with the miracles.
Lime is over here with the squirrel.
Okay, count miracles.
Okay, the apostles have to count the miracles, stack them up, like gather the miracles.
All right now, has everybody counted miracles?
Have all the apostles counted?
Okay, then.
Alright, all the followers can go back if you've handed off your miracles to the apostles.
Then the apostles can come out front.
Um, I guess, if you've, well, if you've counted them, you know how many?
Need to know how many.
Okay, you have three?
Nice, okay.
What are the, let's find out who the winner is.
So, so,
You're, uh,
Pink, you have, you have three?
Three?
Oh, well that's not, that's not real. It's a real sticker.
Six real ones.
Five?
Okay, six is the, six is so far?
Anyone else?
Five.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Maybe I missed a count.
Huh?
Right, right.
Six.
Anyone else with six?
No.
Oh, Squirrel?
All right, the winner is Squirrel, the apostle.
Yes, but Squirrel, don't go away yet.
Of course, we all know that that's not the end.
You're going to have to come up here on stage because...
To win the game, you must kill me, John Romero.
And now, I present to you the new Messiah.
Thank you.
And while I believe that Lime is the only true path, all paths lead to truth.
All right, thank you, John Romero!
For that truly unique entry into the annals of the Game Design Challenge history.
Next we have our returning champion, one of the founders of That Game Company, responsible for favorites like Flower and Flow, the man standing just beside me, Jenova Chen!
Ladies and gentlemen!
All right.
So first of all, I resist this, because it is not
religion to my standard.
OK, so when I was presented this challenge,
I found it's particularly difficult,
because I am supposed to be an atheist from China.
So I was trying to guess what is a religion,
and did a lot of research.
In fact, I did so much research that I
realized this is the final opportunity for me
to put everything straight about my own belief.
So I take this presentation very seriously.
In China, we do believe in gods.
And we have gods who created the world, gods who created humans.
But it's the believing part.
We don't necessarily believe in a god of Earth.
What can we believe about?
I mean, in my opinion, the Chinese gods
and the Egyptian gods, all the old religions,
they represent the unknown.
Why is certain things a certain way?
We don't know.
Well, there's a god for that.
But.
According to Wikipedia, a religion is not really about having gods.
It's more about creating truths and values that can change people's lifestyle.
They can define morality, promote certain behavior, disregard certain behavior,
and really change our life values.
So if you look at the religious map, I find it interesting that all the Western religions,
they have God as a symbol to represent those values.
While the Eastern religion, like Buddhism, Daoism,
all these things, they more focus on the actual life value
and what is the way you to live.
I mean, gods are there.
Some of them has mythical characters,
but they don't really represent the way of living.
So Daoism is actually, Dao means the way of life,
how you're supposed to live.
In my opinion, I think that is what religion is.
It's about how you're supposed to live.
And there's confusion.
Confucius is more considered as a philosopher,
but many people in China believe in its value
and living based on the moral standard he created.
So for a while, I was a believer in socialism, Marxism, Maoism.
And eventually, it's replaced.
Chairman Mao failed at convincing everybody
that's the right way to live.
Then comes Chairman Deng. He promotes Dengism, which is pragmatism.
He really thinks we should develop economy to make everybody happy.
And for a long time, people believed in that. They put economic growth ahead of everything.
And until today, I think not just in China, but also in America, there's this new religion.
Actually, I see this on some online dictionaries that consumerism is a religion.
I think there's a way. It does promote certain value.
When they say, the consumerism beginners, right?
And I noticed that all these philosophies or religions
essentially are trying to lure people
into some kind of happiness.
Even the socialism, look at the propaganda they have there.
But they actually failed.
This is more of a kind of recreation of that.
My understanding, my view on religion,
is that it is a core value that, through a particular set
of practices and dogmas, that's developed
based on the time and the environment it is in.
I mean, the final goal is really to make people
who believe in it feel happy.
And to do that, all religions have
to address two of the biggest problems a human can face,
which is.
Number one, the boredom from a lack of purpose.
Many people kill themselves when they don't have a purpose.
The other one is the fear for death.
That's the most common issues that religion has to solve.
And in order to do that, religion
has to explain the origin and the meaning of life
and to create a belonging towards something that's bigger.
So even if you do die, you're not afraid.
There's something else that continues.
Of course, as a religion, it is an organization
and it needs to spread this ideology to many people,
to spread the way of life and their values.
And it needs to adapt to the changing environment
and to survive the test of time.
And that's what other religions left today so far.
So as a designer, I want to construct
my own religion, which itself is very insulting.
So my inspirations are usually from mythologists.
Everybody knows the hero's journey, monomyth.
From psychologists, the founding father of positive psychology,
people researching on what makes people happy.
And this guy, because we need to survive
and we need to create something that is better,
that is more adapted to the current environment,
will be a religion that can really survive today.
And then other thing is what's happening around.
You know, that's my inspiration.
But as a designer, I want to make something simple
and intuitive because kids today don't have time
to read manual, they don't have time to read Bible.
It has to be very simple.
Right?
We all just figure it out.
So,
I wanted to make sure this religion
definitely create happiness.
There's a very famous chart about happiness.
This is,
At the bottom is the GDP of the country, and at the top is the country that has the most happiness.
And a lot of people who believe in consumerism say,
see, you need to consume more so you can create a higher GDP so you will become happier.
But what they don't see is the other map, which is often shown in the positive psychology.
This is a map about the percentage of Americans who are very happy, which is about 30%.
And you can see from 1955 to today,
the economy has skyrocketed like five times.
People are making a lot more money.
They can consume a lot more.
But the happiness percentage is now increasing.
What does that mean, then?
Another chart from psychology.
This is the average income of America and the happiness
curve.
And you can tell that once you have over 60,000
annual income.
The happiness level does not increase at that point.
But if you are making lower than that, yeah, more money
does make you feel slightly happier.
But this chart addresses a point that is, once people have money,
that's not enough.
That money doesn't drive the happiness
to a higher percentage.
There needs to be something else.
And if you look at the science of happiness,
everybody familiar with Maslow's basic needs of human?
And
All the lower stuff can be addressed by money.
Once you have money, you have shelter, you have food,
you have a family, you can afford something.
And if you do make money, you do have a respect from others.
But there is a top one, the self-actualization,
the purpose.
That happiness, the money doesn't address.
In Joseph Campbell's work, every single mythical story,
every religious story that's been told about a human, which
He calls us hero.
Hero is really everybody.
Has to go through this path.
And what's important is that the hero, in the end,
has to bring something back to his community,
to something that's bigger than himself.
If the hero goes through all this journey
and only benefit himself, this story would not be told.
And this is not a happy story.
But then.
If we do say our goal is finally contributing
to our community, many people don't get to do that
until they retire.
What about the rest of their life?
How can you make sure the rest of your life is actually happy?
And we are designers.
We make games.
So we know how to make a life activity very fun, very happy.
And we use flow as flow theory.
We want to create something that is, you know,
that has a balance between your own ability and the things you're pursuing.
But then what is this thing in my religion that is really worth pursuing?
The religion has to address this next problem, which is the purpose of life.
Where are you heading to?
What is worth living?
Very difficult issue.
Okay, I'm trying to address this here.
So there are various religions, various things that
tells you why you are born.
In a certain scene, like when I was in China,
I was told that we are born to really realize communism
and really defeat the capitalism and the imperialism.
But that didn't really gel with myself.
The consumerism says you should consume more.
You should make more money.
And then that's more successful.
You will be more happy.
But I think that might work in today,
because we have all this knowledge.
But I think it wouldn't work for people
from a million years ago.
I mean, the human existed for a long time.
Before they could even use language,
how could they understand the discount?
All right?
So I think even before human, there's other lives.
A lot of people think religion is only for human.
But doesn't every life deserve to have a purpose in order
to live?
Many people who lose their purpose
wanted to kind of throw their life away.
But I wonder what animal does these days.
So I think if there is something that is so intuitive,
it needs to survive through the test of time.
So if it works for today's people,
it needs to work for people who don't speak.
So I think that purpose is so primitive,
yet has to be so profound.
And I'm trying to compare the simplest life form,
like a single cell and a human,
and try to see if there's anything shared between them.
And I think there's something in common.
You know, for life, it needs to have the right to be born,
to grow, and to propagate, and to die.
And I think if we really want to find a purpose,
we could say propagation is probably
the most interesting part of the purpose of life.
Okay?
So...
It's not wrong to say we're born to give birth to children.
But I think as the technology and the society evolve,
there's a better way to propagate these days,
which is the propagation of ideas.
You can do way faster.
Like I'm propagating to, what, how many people here? 1,000?
Can I give birth to 1,000 people?
So I think propagation is a good purpose for life.
But then what's the bigger purpose?
I think on the macroscope, everybody is trying to spread their ideas.
So, you know, this is kind of like a natural selection.
I mean, everybody tries to spread their ideas as much as possible,
but then the idea that survives and the most adapts to the environment will stay,
and it will be most optimized.
I mean, that's how evolution works.
That could also be how idea works.
I think it's a refining process in a macroscope that everybody contributes to make the best
thing they could do to this world and the best and most adapted idea will survive.
And it's a cycle, you know, once you are done, someone else would continually propose ideas.
It's a refinement of mankind.
It could be also a refinement for, you know, the definition of life in the future.
But then...
How is the selection being made?
And who is making these selections, and why?
This is the area of unknown.
And this is probably what the god is there for.
And god has been always this image
to explain things we couldn't understand.
But people always associate god with the technology
and the knowledge they have at the time.
Initially, gods are animals.
And then they become elemental, like Earth's mother.
and then become the stars, and then they become the human.
But now, up to today, I mean, our knowledge right now
says we can chase everything back to the Big Bang,
but we don't really know what happens before that.
So it's almost something happening
in the other dimension.
So I don't think the god in my religion
is going to be a human character anymore.
It's the other dimension.
So for every religion, it needs to have a value and a dogma.
What do we do for this religion?
Well, we promote anything that enhance the opportunity
for propagation on ideas.
Instead of making you feel happy by consuming,
we make you feel happy by influencing each other.
We wanted to enable a flow experience of everybody
to be in their life to propagate ideas.
to others, trying to influence others.
We also want to protect the rights and the fairness
of everybody's, you know, we are all life.
We all have rights to propagate.
So there are things that we don't like, such as monopoly.
And especially, you know, like when the company monopolized
the market and not really propagate and evolve itself.
It's really slowing down the whole process
of human ideas, evolution.
So then what is this game?
I'm very happy to find someone already believing
what I believe, but they're just not good game designers.
So what I'm trying to do is to give them a little bit help
and make their things into a game.
First of all, how many people actually watch TED videos here?
Yeah, we have all these people already.
But how many of you find it's very difficult
to navigate the website?
Right?
It's a problem.
I think they should be watching my talk.
So it's a very passive site.
And you can see the slogan is a nun, right?
Ideas was spreading.
It's not cool.
And if you look at the speakers, all the people
who represent ideas, there is no.
There's nothing to represent them.
I mean, the speaker don't have an account.
It's just basically a database.
So first thing I want to do is to make this thing active.
Make it a game.
It needs to be interactive.
Everybody needs to be involved.
I will change the slogan into a verb,
like influence with your ideas.
This is going to be a platform where everybody
will have their own account.
What I want to do is to make the spreading of idea
into a flow experience on the TED website.
And to do that, there are a couple of things
I need to address.
First of all, TED has no immediate feedback.
How could that be fun as a game?
If you look at all these videos, there's not even a view count.
You can't even tell which idea really spread it.
We can learn something from YouTube, right?
At least there's a view count.
You can sort all the TED videos to see
which video is the most popular, which I couldn't even
do right now.
And the second thing is, view count
doesn't represent whether you actually
influence each other.
Maybe we need to do something like, I'm inspired by this video.
Then you can really track how many people have
been influenced by your idea.
Then the other thing is, we need to have personal page
accounts, like Twitters.
I mean, people have followers.
But instead of followers, we need
to have people who is influenced by you.
We really need to be able to track that, have some charts,
really doing all the Web 2.0 stuff.
So you know the video and the ideas you posted there
actually.
So this is a demo of a game that I'm working on.
I'm using the Chinese version of Twitter.
On the top right, there's a pop-up that basically tells you how many people are starting to follow you.
I think it's a lot better than the email spam I'm getting from Twitter.
The other thing is they implemented the badge system, which is kind of like the fourth...
You know, what people are doing in augmented reality
is they just give you additional incentive
to try to create more influence.
And the Chinese Twitter actually have a very complicated level
up system for the badgers.
So the other thing is, for a game to really work,
to really promote a certain behavior,
we need to have a feedback loop.
Just having badgers is not a real game.
It's just kind of fake, impractical feedback.
But if the feedback actually contribute back
to the core gameplay, it will make the game fun.
A racing game, you drive faster and you win more matches.
You can buy a faster car so you can drive faster.
People who play Diablo 2 get addicted
because killing is actually making you kill better,
and you just continue wanting to do more.
So for TED, I wanted to implement a feedback
group of people spreading ideas.
Then they win badges.
They win honors.
They win points.
And then these points convert into a bonus system,
which actually help enhance the promotion of the idea.
They can be cross-promoting.
If you really have a badge, you can
use that to maybe send an advertisement to 100 people,
really get more people to watch your videos.
And then people would really want to do more
and to win more badges.
And they have more influence they could do on the website.
And the last thing is, TED doesn't have any social
mechanics and operation.
So these days.
Online games and the online community requires operation to drive people to want to do more
gameplay.
I think one thing people can do is to do the most influential people of the year based
on the TED website instead.
I really drive people to want to push more and want to be able to influence more.
So basically, I haven't even named my religion and name yet, but here's TED, the game, and
Sorry.
OK, well, whatever.
It's a game for, right now I'm going
to name it Propagationism.
That's it.
Thank you, Genova, for that highly philosophical
and enlightening.
Presentation. Now, we have a few minutes left for our three panelists to get questions from you, the audience.
So, this is your opportunity to ask questions, because again, you are going to be deciding who wins the game design challenge.
Is it going to be Jason with Chain World? Is it going to be John with Messiah 6502?
Or is it going to be Jenova with Propagationism? Yes.
Go ahead.
I have a question for Jason.
Are you worried about people maybe charging money for the propagation of your pen drive,
or is it all fair in religion?
Panelists, mics on?
Thank you.
Ah, there we go.
I actually thought about it.
You know, the collection basket or something.
There's no rules about that, I guess, and religion doesn't seem to have rules about that either.
Okay, John, this is for you. How come you're still alive?
How come you're still alive, John?
I'm just a myth sitting up here.
Alright, well, I finally understand your haircut, by the way.
That's not an insult!
I almost wore a robe.
Hi, for Jason, another question about rules.
What happens when people game your religion?
Dig a big lava pit underneath the spawn point?
or play more than one time after dying. What happens then?
Oh wow, yeah, someone could cause an apocalypse.
Yeah.
There's actually a lot, I mean, I'm not supposed to talk about what I saw in ChainWorld,
but it just so happened, you know, passed down from Notch's procedural generation algorithms,
that there is a lava pit right near the spawn point, which makes suicide convenient at least.
So yet another question for Jason.
How do you feel about the potential of...
False chain worlds propping up in the world.
Right, those would be like the 12 theses nailed to the church door or something, right?
Exactly.
Yeah, no, that's sort of maybe anticipated.
Thanks.
This is for Propagation.
Negative feedback loop.
You had a positive feedback loop, but what about a negative feedback loop
so we don't get a bunch of Microsofts?
Oh, jeez.
I think there is a lot of things to talk about.
I personally was talking with my coworkers.
We didn't really talk about netting loops,
but we did talk about what thing we should support,
which thing we shouldn't support.
And I realized creative religion is just the beginning.
If you are the pope, there are many issues
it's very hard to address.
For example, like patents.
In gaming industry, we don't like patents
because, in my opinion, it stops propagation
of other people's ideas.
uh... in limit other people to be able to do things but at the same time patents
are trying to protect
the people who tried their really hard to propagate
if i'm the pope for propagationism
i will have a hard time to tell whether we should support that
or disregard that and uh... i have to look into more like negative loops
to really say something is wrong is very difficult
that'll happen in vatican two or something
All right, those were excellent probing questions.
Unfortunately, we're going to have
to move to the voting section of the game design challenge.
Now, I'm going to ask up, as I sometimes
do in past years, previous game design challenge participant
to help me judge.
Steve Moresky, you have me sitting conveniently
on the aisle.
Why don't you come up and you can listen?
And this way, if something goes wrong during the judging,
here's the guy to blame.
So here's what I want you folks to do.
Think about who you want to applaud for.
You can obviously applaud for all three, but we're going to be listening to who gets the loudest applause
as I stand behind each of our panelists, and I'll stand behind them in the order that they present it.
Okay, are we ready? Here we go.
Jason!
John!
Jenova!
I would like to announce the winner of the Game Design Challenge.
But before I do, I really want to thank all of our panelists.
Let's thank all of them.
I think in many ways this was an unprecedented year in terms of the really the scope and kind of philosophical
depth of the challenge and I also think that we we had an unprecedented depth in terms of actual
playable games two out of three and also real real deep thinking I think from all three of our
all three of our panelists so let's let's really thank them all once again it's really been a fantastic year.
And I want to remind all of you that people on the stage should not be the only ones thinking about these strange, interesting, and important and crucial ways that we can invent new games.
We all can be doing games that challenge all of us.
I'd like to present the Game Design Challenge 2011 award to Jason Rohr. Jason!
I get offered the Book of Mormon all the time for free, so I gotta take Dianetics.
Dianetics! What did I just say?
Okay, and our other two panelists will get their conciliatory prizes.
And let's give them all one final round of applause for 3XM Presentation.
See you next year! Game Design Challenge 2012!
Thank you!