going to go ahead and get going here. Welcome, everyone. Today we're going to talk about our
company's failure at trying to get a competitive fighting game publishing label going. Just
from the premise there, I'm sure you already know some answers yourself. Let's get going.
If you're not familiar with myself or iron galaxy, I started iron galaxy in 2008. I was at
Midway as a studio tech director before that. We ended up falling kind of backwards into
doing a bunch of fighting games. And we were doing a bunch of fighting games and we were
We started off doing a lot of tech outsourcing, that sort of stuff, and then we kind of
worked with Capcom on three really kind of well received ports of classics like Street Fighter
3, Third Strike, Street Fighter 3, Third Strike Online Edition, Darkstalkers Resurrection,
Marvel vs. Capcom Origins, and then kind of parlayed that reputation from doing those kind
of cool ports into years later taking over Killer Instinct from Double Helix when Amazon
bought them. We did Killer Instinct Seasons 2 and 3.
And that's relevant for this talk because a lot of what we think about when we're getting
this publishing label started is like, who is our audience?
Who knows us?
If you know Iron Galaxy, it's probably from the fighting game stuff we've done.
They're probably fans of ours, right?
Also hate windjammers a ton.
Thanks, Pat.
Another thing you might notice from is dive kick. If you're not familiar with dive kick, it's
the first thing we ever self published and it's kind of the foundation for all the stuff we
tried later. Dive kick is a really weird story the way it happened. One of my designers, Adam
Hart, was working on some of the Capcom stuff and he came to me and said, hey, I got a
little thing I'm working on on the side with some friends. I want to run it by you, though,
because it might be considered competing with the stuff we're working on here. Okay, let's
hear what is it. He's like, well, it's a game, it's a two button fighting game.
I'm like, two buttons?
He's like, yeah, there's literally not even stick movement.
It's just two buttons.
One button jumps in the air.
The other button does a dive kick.
I'm like, okay.
He's like, there's two characters.
They're called Dive and Kick.
I'm like, okay.
He's like, every character is a thousand health.
Every dive kick does a million damage.
I'm like, okay.
He's like, and it's called dive kick.
I'm like, that's the dumbest fucking thing
I've ever heard in my life.
Go make it.
Good luck, Godspeed.
And I laughed at him behind his back.
until I played it.
And then I played Divekick and I instantly fell in love with it.
Like I kind of talked about like falling ass backwards
and doing a bunch of fighting game stuff,
but I've always loved fighting games.
And fighting games are, at their core,
they're about a couple of things.
And the spacing, right?
Like knowing how far you are from your opponents,
getting yourself a good position
where they're in more danger than you are.
They're about mind games and reading your opponents,
being able to predict what your opponent's gonna do
and punish them when you predict them correctly.
And Divekick has all that, right?
And it also doesn't have like the,
hey, I gotta make a Z with the stick
and hit three buttons exactly the same frame
to do a Shuroken or whatever.
It's like, it takes all the complexity out of fighting games
but it still keeps the essence of what's great about them.
And so it's like a no-brainer, we should do this at IG.
People know us from fighting game stuff.
So we bought it off of Adam and his team and brought it in-house.
And we worked on it for about a year,
kind of taking it from that initial prototype to getting it out.
We put it out on PS3, Vita, and Steam.
Yeah, it ended up being a pretty big game.
One of the things I was really worried about with Divekick was the value proposition.
Because if you look at Divekick, it looks mental.
It's like there's nothing there.
And it would be really hard to convince people how to play it and what it was about and all this.
So we wanted to make sure it was loaded up with stuff.
So we had 13 characters in there, a bunch of backgrounds,
really robust online offerings and some single-player stuff.
So this was the first thing we ever published.
We had to do everything ourselves.
And we've worked on a bunch of games,
like Microsoft, 2K, WB, whatever, ZeniMax.
But this is the first thing
Suptanet's been responsible for.
But I've been in a few meetings,
how hard could it be, right?
So first thing you do, obviously,
is identify your market.
I read that somewhere.
And we decided to target, thank you, we decided to target the FGC.
We knew that audience the best.
You know, like I said before, if you're in the FGC, you've probably heard of Iron Galaxy,
good, bad, or indifferent.
So we wanted to pick that, it's like, okay, that's our core.
One of the challenges of showing off Divekick is...
Like I said, you look at it and someone explains it to you, it sounds ridiculous.
The only way to get people to like it and see what we saw in it was to take it to all these
shows. And we targeted a bunch of FGC shows, we went to Southern California regionals,
Northern California regionals, we went to CEO, we went to UFGT, which is now Combo
Breaker in Chicago.
We went to Evo. At Evo we ran a 350 person side tournament before the game ever launched,
which is insane. We streamed the whole thing. It was really, really cool.
And sure enough, when we took it places, people loved it.
It wasn't that they liked it, they loved it.
I remember the first time we showed it anywhere was PAX East in 2013.
Adam showed it at his show, but it was just a prototype.
This was the first time we showed the full game.
And we'd never done a booth before. We had to figure out how all this stuff works.
We're spending all this money and doing all this stuff,
and I was just afraid tumbleweeds would be blowing through the booth.
But by like halfway through the first day, people were lined up six, seven deep, right?
And Divekick was the talk of PAX East.
Like, it's not hyperbole.
Like, couldn't go anywhere without people like,
have you seen this Divekick thing?
It was all like really, really well.
And it was all really, really easy.
And I'm becoming more and more convinced this publishing stuff is super easy.
So then the game comes out. It did about 200,000 units across all platforms. We eventually also put it out on PS4 and Xbox One.
The game did awful on those platforms. That's more an issue of timing. It was way too late to put a sequel out, or a sequel, to put another port of it out.
And I think people had enough dive kick in their lives at that point, right?
Most of the original launch ended up coming from Steam, which really surprised us.
Because we're targeting FGC, we're targeting fighting game players,
and if you go to these tournaments we went to,
they're playing on PS3, they're playing on Xbox 360,
they're not playing, like the weird Mame and Melty Blood kids are playing on PC.
Sorry, Melty Blood fans.
But no one's doing it, no one's playing it, right?
And so when people are buying Steam,
we kind of realized we actually targeted the wrong audience.
we should have targeted the people that buy an indie game a month,
or they buy a coach co-op game for their friend.
So this was like the first sign that, like,
okay, we kind of, you know, Divekick seemed to do okay.
It could have been a lot better.
And thinking about it more deeply,
I'm talking about Divekick a lot
because it's kind of the foundation
for everything going forward we did.
And you can't understand why we failed
with the next rev of games
without understanding what Divekick did.
So most people, I think they'd be like,
hey, 200,000 units, that's amazing, right?
Well, we actually lost a little bit of money with Divekick.
Not a ton, but some money.
But we had great platform support.
Sony was an amazing partner for us.
They gave us some pub funding from the pub fund thing
so we could do the Vita version,
which is also the best version of Divekick
if you're into that.
They took us to E3 and they gave us an hour stream
where they set up a press versus press tournament.
They had Dr. Scholl as one of the characters from the game.
They had cosplay they paid someone to come in and do.
Sony was an amazing partner for Divekick in a lot of ways.
Really great reaction to live events.
Everywhere we brought it, it killed.
It just destroyed, right?
good press and enthusiast following.
Like, it was really weird,
like whenever we talked about Divekick,
people would write articles about it.
Like, if I wanted to tell this story
of how Adam tricked me into buying Divekick,
like people would write about it every time.
We put a trailer out, they'd post on their website,
it'd go on Polygon, it would go on Giant Bomb,
it would go on IGN, and we didn't even have to email them.
They just would see the trailer and put it up, right?
Again, it's all super, super easy.
But how do we end up losing money given that?
Clearly we ship too much of a game.
I think, I don't know how many of you are split like IndieDev
or like big studios like ours.
We have 120 people at the Iron Galaxy, right?
And one of the jokes I like to make is like,
someone can't like drop a pencil and pick it up
without costing me $10,000, right?
It's like nothing is cheap at Iron Galaxy.
Everything's expensive and it's a huge pain in my ass.
And when you work on a game like this for a year,
it adds up.
So, it's pretty clearly, one of the core things I believe about Divekick, we could have done
a lot better, even if we ended up being the exact same game, the exact same marketing
plan, if we would have launched with 8 instead of 13, and then put 5 characters out over
the next 6 months after launch, we would have had a longer sales window, it would have been
longer and better, we would have made a lot more money just from that one tweak alone.
And plus, if the game didn't sell,
then we just could have stopped working on it
and saved more money, right?
We marketed the wrong group.
Like, if we took the money
going to Northern California regionals, Evo, CEO,
and put it towards going to stuff like, you know,
Comic-Con or an anime show or whatever,
we would have reached the audience
that actually ended up buying the game.
And I'm sure we would have sold more units just doing that,
spending the exact same amount we did in a smarter way.
And then we squandered the goodwill with the press.
What I know now about publishing and like best practices
and handling PR launches and marketing and all this stuff,
like the stuff we did right and a better job at
with all these next round of titles,
if we would have done the best practices with Divekick,
we would have sold a million units.
Like I firmly believe that.
Like the problem with Divekick is everything was too easy
and we didn't have to work at it.
So we just thought everything would just kind of work out.
That being said, business is always full of failures,
and you're gonna fail a lot when you're running a business.
It's about what did you take away from that experience,
and what can you package up going forward
to reuse on an ongoing basis.
So, we now have a publishing experience.
We know what it's like to submit to the ESRB.
We know what it's like to hire an external QA team to check for bugs for you.
We know what it's like to deal with Microsoft and Sony and all the weird
quirks they have about publishing on their platforms, right?
We know what it's like to deal with like the vacuum of information that can be
steam sometimes. Right. Um, and that's super, super valuable stuff.
We have a built an audience now,
200,000 people bought dive kick or got tricked into buying it, whatever it is.
Uh, and they love it.
And.
They still, like there's message boards that talk about Divekick, the Divekick website, all this stuff.
So they're Iron Galaxy fans for life, which is super awesome because that's something we never had before.
A lot of the work we did before is behind the scenes stuff.
Like we help a developer or a publisher ship their game on time.
We do a version of a version of a version of a game.
And it's not super glamorous and it's behind the scenes.
But this is the first time it's like, oh fuck, I love Iron Galaxy, this is great.
So we had that.
better understanding of the market we have to sell to.
I've talked about this a lot.
The one thing I didn't talk about though is with the FGC stuff,
is like, we really, when I say we targeted the FGC,
it just wasn't by spending on events.
We really leaned into like trying to get credibility with them
in a way that was kind of dumb.
Because it's like, you know the FGC, they got like a reputation,
like I love that community and it's filled like with loving.
like people that build things, like build groups and friends.
But it's got a reputation for being like really rough around the edges,
and it's earned that reputation by and large fairly, right?
And so our marketing was like that.
When we talked about the game on streams, we talked about it like that.
I'm sure it was off-putting to people that weren't part of that community, right?
We found our voice, right?
Divekick was the first thing we ever did.
We got to do the trailers like we wanted.
We did weird, funny, like infomercial style trailers.
We got to do whatever we wanted, and it was fun.
Um, yeah. So, we want to take those assets and flip it into a new publishing business, right?
And the core premise for the business is, okay, what did we do wrong on Divekick?
Above and beyond, like, everything else, we probably just spent too much making Divekick.
So how do we get around that with other things?
We don't have anything internal we're working on right now that kind of fits the bill.
So let's focus on, like, finding other people's games that are competitive, right?
Because, like, again, if you think about who we are as a studio...
Our fans play competitive games.
They play fighting games.
We know that.
Let's not try to sell adventure games.
Let's not try to sell first-person shooters
because no one that knows us knows anything about us
in that context, right?
So let's focus on competitive games.
Find ones that are near completion
and do micro-investments, essentially,
in games that are near completion
and be an amplification for whatever marketing or stuff
they want to do.
Sorry.
I was pointing at Tim Rogers.
Oh, Tim.
And the execution on that, we had a handset of core rules
for games we were going to sign.
Again, find things that you think you can recoup on
the first day.
If you think about games that's close to done
with micro-investments, say we make a $25,000 investment
in a title.
Say we price it at $15.
If we have to sell 3,000 copies across three platforms on the first day of recoup.
After Divekick, I didn't think there was any way in the world we couldn't do that.
Divekick taught me, like, no, if we just do our things and publish the games like we did Divekick,
there's no way we do that. It's fall over easy. It's impossible to screw that up.
We wanted to offer developers...
things other publishers couldn't.
Because we're a developer first and foremost
who happens to publish, right?
And we could help them figure out how to get through QA,
work on stuff like UI or whatever it is, right?
So we also didn't want to do one title.
We wanted to build three and we always want to present them together.
The thinking being, I think this is actually one thing we did that was pretty
smart. So, uh, you never show just one game in isolation, right?
You show all three are together at all times.
So they're associated together in people's minds.
Like, uh, they don't see like the gun sport trailer.
They see the video ball capsule force and gun sport trailer.
So if they buy capsule force and they like it,
or they bought dive kick and they liked it,
they're aware of the other three things they can do.
And it kind of just use them to amplify each other.
And then just do the same marketing and PR stuff we did for Divekick.
Take it on the road a lot, show it to people why it's great, do streams, do all this stuff,
and then obviously cash large checks.
This is, if you take away one thing from today's talk, make it Mefford's Law,
first law of game development.
Nate Mefford, I started working with in 2005, he's a programmer.
He's without a doubt one of the smartest people I've ever met.
And Mefford's first law of game development is,
the worst thing that can happen to a young developer
is to work on a successful game,
because you end up thinking you had something to do with it being successful.
I just soak it up.
And this was Divekick for us, right?
Like Divekick, everything was easy.
Whenever we wanted to talk about Divekick,
people would write about it.
People picked up the trailers.
People, like, they wanted to talk about Divekick.
There was an enthusiasm about Divekick.
And we thought it was us.
We didn't, it's not this game that's amazing, right?
It's us and this mechanism we're building around it
that makes people so interested in it, right?
And once you lost focus on that,
it kind of re, it makes you realize
that every mistake you made was avoidable.
Let's talk about those now.
So,
We've got this new, by the way I didn't realize
Method's first law of game development applied
until I was writing this deck.
So, recent binding for your boy.
I gotta stop doing that.
We signed three games.
First one we signed was Capsule Force.
It's kind of like got a Nidhogg screen push mechanic to it.
It's got 80s Japanese anime kind of aesthetic to it.
It's really cool, I love it.
Gunsport we signed.
That's the first one's by Cloudbit, Eric and Kat.
Second one was Gunsport.
It's a Necrosoft with Brandon Sheffield and his crew.
And I fricking love Gunsport, right?
Like it's basically volleyball with guns, right?
And so instead of like bumping and setting like lame-os,
you're shooting a ball across the net with a gun.
It's like totally cool.
VideoBall, I fell in love with VideoBall
as an electronic sport.
The way to describe it to people if you've never seen it,
like the shorthand that doesn't do it justice
is it's like asteroids meet soccer, right?
So, assign those all at once,
and then we launch the label.
I'm trying to get the volume here right.
So, again, we're gonna talk about all these things at once,
and this trailer is kind of the first time
we should have realized something we were doing was wrong.
Because when we put out trailers for Divekick,
they'd get picked up, they'd end up on every single website.
We wouldn't even have to tell them that they were out.
We put this trailer together, Tim's friend Vito did this,
it's really good.
It's funny in the way we like to be funny.
It kind of doesn't take itself too seriously
in a way we like to treat ourselves.
And it shows off all the games, I think in a flattering way.
And no one watched this trailer.
right? Like if you look at the views of it by YouTube, it's super, super low.
And we were used to getting like 50 to 100,000 views in a week on dive kick
stuff. Right? Um, so this is a video ball.
And I knew each game from a different way. I met a capsule force.
I got introduced to from the devolver crew, uh, gun sport. I,
I think I branded, I saw Brandon playing it somewhere. No, I heard,
I heard Chris Charla talking about gun sport and I had to check it out.
And Tim, when we were showing off a dive kick.
Tim was showing off video ball with his publisher for the game at the time.
It was Midnight City, and their booth was always by our booth.
And so I got to know Tim and hang out with him and play a bunch of video ball.
And I love video ball.
So to be clear, I think all three of those games are super brilliant in their own way.
And that's why we decided to publish them.
Okay, this makes a lot of sense.
But again, like, showing them all together like this.
We did all this and no one bought the games, right?
We went to shows, we went to PAXs.
We did an amazing booth at this last PAX East.
We had a billion people come through and play these games,
but their sales weren't there.
What ended up happening, Capsule Force launched first
on PS4 and Steam, just never found an audience.
We could never get excitement up for it.
We do a stream for Capsule Force
and 44 people would watch it.
You know, and we do streams for Divekick.
Like, this is like amazing.
we do like a character reveal stream for Divekick,
we'd have like 1,500 to 4,000 people watching those streams.
That's like more than we get for killer instinct streams,
which is like mind-boggling.
Gunsport and Video Ball both end up taking longer
than we originally imagined,
and we had to make some tough choices.
Like, we don't have an infinite supply of money
to keep dumping into this publishing venture.
It was like a fixed budget thing for us.
And so we just had to cut one of them
so the other one could live.
So we ended up cutting Gunsport.
And to be clear, I can't wait to play that game
when Brandon gets it done.
Like, I think Gunsport's brilliant.
And then we did Videoball. Videoball launched in this last August, I think, on PS4, Xbox One, and Steam, and it still hasn't recouped yet.
So, given all that, let's think about the faulty assumptions we made and why everything broke.
Obviously, there's Mefferd's first law of game development, right? But there's more kind of specific things about that.
We kind of thought that we had an audience of fans.
and it's core to who we are, and they love Killer Instinct,
and they love Divekick, and they're gonna,
just because we say these games are good,
they're gonna buy them, right?
It turns out, and this is something I figured out
way too late as well, it's not that people like Divekick
or Killer Instinct, people like very specific things
about the games they play.
Some people like the sensei quotes from Divekick.
Some people like that when Mr. N runs backwards, he squeals.
In Killer Instinct, some people like the shadow system
or whatever it is, right?
And if you're giving them an offering
that doesn't have those very specific things in it,
they won't care.
They don't give a shit about it, right?
So it's about really understanding that the games you make
and you pour your heart and soul into when you publish,
what do people actually like about them?
You need to have those conversations with your consumers.
So if you're thinking about leveraging them later,
selling more things to them down the road,
you know exactly what you're selling to them, right?
And you can't get, like you cannot get too micro
with that discussion.
Like, there's no level of detail that's insignificant
when you're talking about that aspect of it.
So timelines and budgets of the game would be small and predictable.
This is literally the dumbest thing I've ever done. So, uh,
and I've had some doozies. I, we're a game developer, right? And if you tell me,
Hey, here's an idea.
We're going to give you a short timeline and a little bit of money.
Or do you expect a good result?
And my answer would be no fucking way
do I expect a good result.
Like, these things take time, they take money.
They're done when they're done, right?
Like everyone knows that about games.
Like they're done when they're done.
But yet somehow we wanted to find things
that were like on a short timeline
because we think they're near the end
and make micro investments in them
and expect that a good result, right?
And that's just not how games get made.
It's not reflective how games get made.
Any business model you create for funding
and publishing games needs to take into account
that you don't really get to say when the game's done.
You get to say when it comes out
and it's either done or it's not.
And that's something that is very challenging about publishing.
And I don't really know, short of being absolutely cutthroat about cutting things early,
I don't really know a good way to fix that other than just have bigger budgets.
And then lastly, kind of talked about this one already,
if we just spent more time going to Comic Con,
spent more time going to whatever, all the other kind of core shows,
we would have done a lot better not reaching out to the FGC directly.
That's more specifically for Divekick.
So kind of wrapping up here, there's two slides of learnings.
Ted talked this first one already.
People like very specific things about the games they play.
It's interesting, like, think about it like this.
Like, what is on your game bookshelf that you play, right?
And if you think about what you like about all the games on your bookshelf.
You'll notice trends, you'll notice things like that.
And it's really easy to look at Steam
and figure out what games people are playing
and figure out, should I even bother trying to market it
to this group or this group?
Find people that like this game.
Does that make sense to try to market to people that like?
samurai gun or whatever it is, right?
That's really easy to do with Steam and Steam Spy.
Make a minimum viable product.
This is really, I mean, you can only do this
if the game allows it, but like I said with Divekick,
if we would've launched with eight characters
and put the other five out over the following six months,
our sales curve would've been longer,
we would've made a lot more money,
we would've had higher engagement,
and all those things are really good
for commercializing these things as products, right?
Have a plan to extend the game if it finds an audience.
This one is, it's hard,
this is about finding a balance, right?
Because plans are cheap and building things are expensive.
Right? But if you don't have enough stuff, people will never buy it because the
value propositions off and factor into the MVP discussion. How do you do it?
So like these two things are kind of like very coupled together in my mind.
You can only ship an MVP. If you have plans,
you can easily execute on to make more stuff later, right?
And follow up with it if it finds an audience. Right. Um, and then finally,
hype just can't be created. This is like, you know, again, this is us thinking,
Oh, we made the hype for dive kick, not dive kick, made the hype for dive kick.
And it's an easy mistake to fall into with success,
to think like, oh yeah, this was good because of us.
And it's really, no, it's the game.
It's always the game.
Yeah, so whatever your original business plan is,
like it would have been really easy
to keep pouring money into GunSport,
to keep pouring money into CapsuleForce,
to keep pouring money into VideoBall,
but I don't think we would have gotten a better result.
Like VideoBall, GunSport, CapsuleForce,
the market is so much more competitive now
than when it was when we launched DiveKick in 2013, right?
And I don't think you can do small-scale publishing
on the budgets we were talking about in this day and age.
I just don't think it works, right?
And so pouring more money still would have been
just a little bit of money in the grand scheme of things.
Like, you know, these aren't like $2 million video games, right?
So I think one of the things we did right
from an Iron Galaxy perspective,
it was very painful to have that conversation with Brandon
and explain to him.
that we're walking away from GunSport and he can have it back.
But from Iron Galaxy's perspective it was absolutely the very right thing to do
because it just wasn't going to end well.
VideoBall wouldn't have ended as well
and we had to kind of pick our battles there.
This is a good one. I think this is...
If you're doing streams and getting 44 viewers...
If you're going to shows and not getting a buzz, you know, if you're doing trailers and they get 10 YouTube views on YouTube the first day, you need to think about what the fuck you're doing. You're doing something wrong, right? Either something's wrong with the game. Something is wrong with your approach. Something is wrong with your outreach. You're doing something wrong, and you need to reevaluate even doing it at all, right?
Good job. That's me.
Don't artificially limit your potential audience.
This is a mistake we made on Divekick. I kind of already talked about it.
We just leaned so hard into FGC stuff and had kind of a rough edge around everything we did with Divekick.
I'm sure it turned away potential consumers.
In fact, consumers that were the people that ended up buying the game.
Finally, if you're working as a publisher, you have external dev teams, probably.
Don't assume anything about the external dev teams.
One of the bigger mistakes we made was, okay, we shipped, I think Iron Galaxy at this point
has shipped or helped shipped over 100 products in eight and a half years.
No one's done that.
Right?
and you get really good by shipping things.
And these teams we work with are all very capable teams,
but they just don't have that much experience, right?
And so we did not ask,
we asked them questions we would ask ourselves.
We didn't ask them questions that you would have,
you should have been asking us eight and a half years ago.
And so I think we should have been more proactive
about a lot of things.
I think we should have been more involved.
They all would have hated every second of it, right?
But I'm sure it would have been better
if we were more involved in every kind of,
even creative decisions and just talking stuff out.
So, remember, Mefford's first law of game development.
Any questions?
Oh, sorry.
Hey man, good talk.
I was kind of hoping to hear more
about your conference strategy.
Was that purely for like player acquisition
or were you doing other stuff?
And when you talk about big shows like Comic-Con,
being a smaller company, do you ever fear
about getting like drowned out next
like the Avengers or something?
Yeah, so the question was, he wants to know,
what's our show strategy?
What do we try to get out of showing things like PAX?
And are bigger shows worth it for a smaller team?
Yeah, it's strictly about acquisition and user engagement.
You can try to set press stuff up at shows,
but they never come.
It's really challenging.
The other thing that's really great about shows is as a developer,
you build up a network of other developers that are your size and have your same problems.
And that's like, it's like valuable on a different axis than getting fans of your company in your game.
Getting drowned out at Comic Con is absolutely a big thing,
but you need, just don't spend a million dollars going to Comic Con.
You know, find a place where you can sit at a corner of a table with somebody or whatever.
Spend proportionately on what results you expect.
Yeah, simply put. So, cool.
You were talking about how you had a 120 person dev team.
Yeah.
So, and you were talking about you're publishing these three other games.
What were you working on in between while you were publishing these games?
So the publishing team was very small.
It was me, it was a guy named Eddie Caperez, and Felix.
That was essentially the publishing team and QA.
Chelsea, who's my business partner,
runs all the other games.
We've done, the big stuff we were working on
at that time was Killer Instinct.
That's like a 75-person team.
We did Elder Scrolls Online, the console versions of that.
That was like a 35-peak team.
just tons of stuff and the teams get smaller.
We have some projects that are like one or two people.
Like, oh, we're doing the 4K operas
for a game I can't talk about, unfortunately.
Stuff like that.
So, lots and lots of different kinds of projects.
Some creative, some ports,
and some are just working behind the scenes
to get stuff shipped.
And do you think, you know, that publishing part
that you said, you know, you end up being unsuccessful,
do you think it impacted, like, budget-wise
a lot of your other titles?
So I'm guessing I don't have to repeat these because he's on a microphone, but just in case did
this publishing failure
cost us other opportunities and like this was money we set aside to set up a new business venture. It was very budgeted
It was very measured, which is why we just couldn't keep dumping money into the games, right?
So no, it didn't really have any impact. It just meant like
you know, instead of starting our own indie game,
start setting the next dive kick,
we invested in these other external titles, right?
That's what it disallowed.
That's the opportunity it took away.
Thank you.
No problem.
I think we've got time for one more, maybe?
We good?
All right, thanks everybody.