Hey Patrick, GDC Talk is in 15 minutes. Are you here?
Basically, I might have made a wrong turn at Albuquerque.
But you're all prepped and ready to go, yeah?
Yep, sure. Can I hear your opening again?
So, I talk about the Firewatch event system, which allows dialogue to interrupt-
Oh hey, Will, I found a free coffee!
Anyway, uh, the system allows dialogue to be interrupted without losing the conversation thread.
Oh yeah!
And how the object interacts work in the same system.
Then you were going to talk about our content authoring-
Magpie!
Tools?
Well, I have no idea where I am.
You need to get here like, uh, now.
I swear to god if you interrupt me like this on stage-