everybody a reminder to uh either uh silence or skillfully
muffle your cell phones. And also a reminder to please fill
out those surveys that they'll be emailing out to you guys. If
you like what you've seen it'll really help us presenters and
it'll help GDC give you more of what you want.
So uh thanks for uh all coming out to my panel. Um I know you've
got a lot of choices, I mean Nintendo's going on right now
and Nier Automata is going on right now and I'm like wow
that's uh that's a pretty tough crowd to go up against so thanks
for uh showing up to uh Primal Rage 2. So uh that's what I'll
be talking about today. I'll be talking about Primal Rage 2, a
game that was cancelled and never made it to release.
Project cancellation is a developer's greatest fear. Years
of life effort can be destroyed, often caused by circumstances
beyond our control.
So perhaps, like some of you may have endured,
it happened to me, and it changed my life profoundly.
However, this story takes some twists and turns,
and has a different ending than you might expect.
So I'm Chris Tang, I'm the senior game designer
at Indie Dev Genasia Hitsparx Games.
My current project is a tentatively titled Strike Harbinger,
a hyper exciting high speed, high frame rate
spiritual successor to the arcade rail shooter
coming out hopefully in the next year
for PC, arcade, and console.
While I'm not a programmer by trade,
it's the first game I've done all the gameplay code
and systems for, so I'm particularly proud of it.
Also, our character crossover partner, FX Unit Yuki, is a newly developed indie action
platformer for the old NEC TurboGrafx-16 Super CD console format, I don't know if anyone
remembers that, uh it just went to get its discs pressed, so it should be available sometime
soon.
I did some additional writing and design on that.
Going way back, I have experience working on the Tetris franchise, Transformers, many
Capcom games with Street Fighter 3 and Street Fighter Alpha 3 in particular, the Primal
Rage games at Atari of course, and console titles going back to the Genesis and NES days
at Tengen like Gauntlet 4 and Rampart.
I also have a competitive gaming background and am best known for being the Sega World
Champion as broadcast around the world on MTV in 1994.
I'm also the 1990 NWC Los Angeles City Champion and the Hawaii State Nintendo Champion.
I'm still active in eSports as a commentator for the Tetris World Championships going on
nine years now, and I am the voice of the boom Tetris for Jeff meme that has been going
around lately, which is kind of an embarrassing story.
You know about the boom Tetris for Jeff?
Yeah, if you haven't heard of that, it's like, there's like a video with like 7 million views,
and at the Tetris tournament a couple years ago, I kept saying, boom Tetris for Jeff.
And now anytime people see someone make a Tetris, they'll comment like, boom Tetris for Jeff.
It's got like 10,000 comments, and most of them say boom Tetris for Jeff.
They made like a t-shirt for it, and there's these compilation memes with like screens
exploding and stuff. It's pretty crazy, but yeah, that's my voice. It's my fault.
So yeah, it's been a pretty crazy run.
But this story starts off with my life at Atari Games.
So at the Nintendo World Championships in 1990,
I met one of the supervisors at Tengen.
So that's the console division of Atari Games.
Not to be confused with Atari Corp,
which made the computers and the consoles.
I began working there a couple of weeks later and started doing odd jobs like QA, product
evaluations, game counseling, manual writing, and translation.
I was quite possibly the youngest person ever to regularly work there, and I was living
my dream at a very early age.
Even back then, I had a deep interest and respect for the history of Atari.
Iconic developers like Ed Logg and Earl Vickers, who worked on favorites like Asteroids, Gauntlet,
and 720 Degrees, roamed the halls.
I even got to work with some of them.
Back then, fanboying about early game developer legends and telling them how much I appreciated
their work might have freaked them out.
I spent my lunches studying replay and game machine trade magazines on the floor of the
executive's office, immersing myself in the history there.
Atari resembled a tech city where there was a department for whatever needed to get done.
Wood shop, metal shop, video lab, PCB design, sound studio, administration, and the cafeteria.
With the incredible talent and resources there, the potential for the future felt limitless.
There was no other place like it, and there was a strong culture there that was all its
own.
Some of the friends I've made there are friends for life.
I consider them like family.
There's a reason why we still have Atari reunions years after its closure.
I don't even know if that's a thing in other companies.
So for me, this was a very exciting time.
Everything there had a huge impact on me.
It's where I grew up.
I wasn't sure if I fit in due to my age and lifestyle,
as most devs there back in those days
saw games as only a job,
and they never played them outside of work.
Whereas to me, video games were my entire life.
But I'm glad that things in this industry
have changed for the better in this regard,
and a much higher proportion of people
who actually play games and love them
are working on them now.
So.
Not long after I started working at Tengen,
Street Fighter II was released in the arcades.
After work I would go to Sunnyvale Golf Land,
which was a ground zero of fighting games
where Capcom put their games on location test.
It was the original site of the Evo Tournament Series
going back to 1996.
I won many competitions and this trophy
is from the very first official Street Fighter II
tournament ever held on May 30th, 1991.
I came in third.
The karate dude on it's pretty cool too.
So my expertise didn't go unnoticed by the company.
Atari wanted to get in on the fighting game craze,
and it was developing one with robots called Cyberstorm.
It was in bad shape with poor gameplay,
and they put me on the team
to try to salvage what was there.
Even though I was able to improve the gameplay considerably,
the robots that were in the game didn't look cool,
and they had stiff animations which couldn't be fixed.
The game was ultimately canceled,
but because I didn't like the game,
it didn't really affect me much.
However, it was the first time I got to innovate a feature.
It was the first game to have a combo meter.
Fighting game players loved to find and perform combos,
but Atari didn't know much about those mechanics.
So I devised a feature where if a character was hit
and was hit again before the character
returned to their ready state,
a number would count up how many hits
and reward the players with a point bonus.
The game went out on test at Golf Land
before it was canceled.
A few weeks later, people noticed that the test versions
of Capcom's Super Street Fighter II
started incorporating a similar feature
with the same wording right down to the point bonuses
that nobody uses anymore.
I guess I won't be too offended, they did end up hiring me later on.
So while I was working on Cyberstorm, another project started codenamed T-Rex.
I knew the game's programmer and would play on the Research Street Fighter 2 in the game
room and he'd have me check out his project after I kicked his ass.
It evolved into what we now call Primal Rage and once I was available to work on it full
time I joined their team.
So I won't go too much into Primal Rage 1 as it was released and well documented.
It was a fighting game with dinosaurs and beast-like characters.
My role on the Rage 1 team was gameplay-centric.
I implemented character gameplay, collision hitboxes, move animation timings, AI scripting,
general game balancing and tuning.
In the arcades...
The stop motion beast made the game very popular with kids and casual players.
It wasn't a huge hit with the fighting game fanatics, though.
There were things I wasn't allowed to fix.
The special move inputs were not like other games, and they were really awkward.
Kids couldn't find the moves, so the players that were most interested in playing the game
were the least able to enjoy it.
Still, the game did very well.
It was considered the number one arcade game of 1994,
and when it came time to port the game to home consoles,
they went all out.
More than 10 platforms, Super Nintendo, Genesis,
Game Boy, Game Gear, PlayStation, Saturn, 32X,
PC, Jaguar, 3DO, Amiga, and even the Tiger R-Zone.
It sold a million units right off the bat
and enjoyed a certain amount of success
in a market that was tough and unforgiving.
and it became a very successful brand for Atari.
Virtual knights such as comic books, toys, novels,
and apparel were made.
We were even in talks to have an animated series produced,
but we turned down offers since we wanted
better production companies to be involved.
Otherwise it would have turned out like Double Dragon.
The toys were very good.
So Primal Rage became one of the games in the spotlight
as video game violence was a new hot button topic.
Primal Rage has this fear of gore
with characters able to do things
like punch each other's brains out
and eat the human tribesmen.
And then there was this.
Golden Showers.
In addition to the blood, gore, and violence,
there is an especially infamous finishing move
where one of the ape-like characters urinates
on their defeated opponent, burning their flesh away.
When angry parents found out,
it was pulled from some store shelves,
and the game made its way into the headlines.
Our team took it in stride,
as I guess any publicity was good publicity
back in those days.
Even back in 1994, games were starting to receive updates
with new ROMs to fix problems or add features
in the hopes of improving the earnings income performance.
We released at least two updates
and planned for a third which would add a boss character
since the game didn't have one yet.
But the success of the game assured
the development of a sequel,
so we decided to skip the version three update
and the boss character for a full-blown Primal Rage 2.
Primal Rage made good earnings from kids and casual players, and they played against a
computer.
But that wasn't the kind of coin drop that Street Fighter or Mortal Kombat games were
making through competitive play, which was the kind of earnings that management wanted
if we were to make a sequel.
So those two ape-like beasts, Blizzard and Chaos,
were by far the most played characters.
Even in Killer Instinct,
which is another 1994 fighting game,
less humanoid characters like Riptor and Sabrewolf
were the least picked, despite them being powerful.
Fighting game players just preferred characters
that could hit with their arms and legs
instead of biting or using their tail.
Since our game was practically all beasts,
what could be done to make a successful sequel
with Primal Rage brand?
And the solution was kind of strange.
So, I recount the day when Dennis, our producer, ran into my cube and proclaimed that he figured
out the solution.
Mighty Morphin Power Ragers.
The idea was to have titan-sized human avatars that could morph into a beast form and back.
Players could hit the top row of buttons, which would morph the character into beast
mode, performing a flashy auto-combo sequence and morph back.
Players could also pick a beast character that could conversely morph into their human
form.
Experts could also pick a third meta version
that could morph at will but didn't auto combo.
This dynamic would make it so that the game
was accessible to beginners with the easy super moves
for the normal versions, but still be deep for experts
who could do manual combos with the advanced one.
At first I was like, what, is this gonna work?
But I ended up loving the idea
because we could have proper human combatants
while retaining our theme and maybe get some new
cool gameplay mechanics in the process.
This was a risk that the human characters
would not be well received in a game
known for its dinos and beasts.
And so here are our character designs,
and here's some concept art that I was able to rescue.
So some of the only ones out there.
Production on our human characters
went in the order that you see here,
with Arak being the first.
Each human avatar combatant has a corresponding beast god
that they are connected to,
and retained design elements of their sponsoring deity,
God Beast.
They are leaders of their tribe,
chosen to channel their powers.
Here you can see them with their corresponding beast god counterpart.
In the story, Necrosan, the game's final boss, banishes the beast gods, who must then physically
manifest themselves to the tribe's avatar, granting them special abilities and titan-like
size in the process.
And here's the other characters.
As in the first Primal Rage, not all player characters are good guys, but a mix of virtuous
and destructive personalities which tend to match their prehistoric beast counterpart.
Diablo's avatar was originally conceived to be a female,
but the proposed concept was weak
and we were lacking a villain-esque male character
in the roster, so we ended up with an executioner
like Sinjin, which worked out really great.
While we were creating the eight new humanoid titans,
we also needed to create one new beast god
to fill out the roster.
Slashfang, the saber-toothed god of combat,
has a familiar humanoid body type despite being a beast.
Also new was a final boss character, Necrosan.
His story brings together the lore
of both Primal Rage games.
He's an undead bone dragon being the spawn of an asteroid egg that caused the cataclysms and emergence of the beast characters of the first game.
Now fully matured, he threatens to drain the life force of every living thing on earth.
And in case you missed it, Necrosan is Japanese for Mr. Death.
Now even though they were only in Primal Rage 2 as a game, both Slash Fang and Necrosan made it into toy form.
Necrosan is particularly valuable as it was worth several hundred dollars sealed in the box, like the one from my collection I have pictured here.
Cha-ching!
So, images of the Primal Rage 2 character designs did end up in some magazines and comics.
Additionally, the core story of Primal Rage 2 featuring the human avatars was conveyed
in the Primal Rage novelization.
A fun fact.
slash fang's avatar, his full name is actually
Xiaoming Tangquan, which happened as a result
of the team being unable to agree on a name.
It's a mashup of all the Asian core team members,
two of the programmers and myself.
Our product manager came up with it on the fly,
and while the intent was borderline racist,
the situation was hilarious and everybody liked it.
That's Dennis, our producer, posing in the main hallway to the Rage Lab,
and on the right, a posable wire puppet mold pole for Slash Bang that I used to design his moves.
The game was initially formally initiated as a project on March 1st, 1995,
with a budget of 2.3 million dollars, which for a game in that era was a very large sum.
We were a team of 20, the largest team in CoinUp
at the time, mostly art, animation, and programming.
Additional costs associated with stop motion
included the manufacture of the armatured puppets
to be animated, specialized stop motion animators,
we got these guys from Hollywood, they were really great,
and graphics processing support staff.
The stop motion process also added a great deal
of time to the schedule, which is an art burden
much greater than that of traditional 2D pixel art,
3D pre-rendering, or real-time 3D.
So this is a rare Polaroid photo that I took
of the final armatured production puppets
used to create stop motion for the game,
back when they were brand new.
They have since disintegrated and no longer exist,
or what's left of them looks like a T-800.
The puppets were painted in garish odd colors
to be able to do palette swaps
and to read well for photography.
On the right, you can see a completed standing ready
sequence for the Kena character after being animated,
processed, and implemented into the game.
Like on Rage 1, my role was gameplay-centric, now expanded.
I got to design mostly everything from the ground up,
character attacks, effects, hitboxes, balancing,
the CPU's AI, and the overall fighting quality.
Implementing AI behaviors is an interesting thing
in a fighting game.
They become like your children.
You're teaching them how to fight
and handle various situations, and they take after you.
When your product is out in the field,
you really hope that they can fend for themselves and put on a good show.
Sometimes you make one character feel so fun and powerful
that you then have to go back and make all their siblings just as strong
and hope that the whole family ends up being badass and awesome.
I also wrote lore and story for the universe Bible that our licensees use for our toys,
comics, novels, etc.
I was super happy I got to write content that ended up on the backs of toys
since I was a big fan of stuff like G.I. Joe and Transformers that had stuff like that.
Because of the high cost and lengthy process
of stop motion animation, we had to be sure
every frame was one that we wanted or needed.
Moves started off as a concept video or sketch,
which was adapted into a 2D storyboard
that could be flip-booked and tweaked.
Once approved, our stop motion animators
would bring them to life with the armatured puppet
moving it one frame at a time to be photographed.
The photos would then be cleaned up and scaled
by our interns in the graphics processing dungeon.
And only then could they be put in the game.
So I'll be showing you some videos of this process.
Most of the hand-drawn storyboards let us cut frames and determine whether it was good
enough for stop motion.
So this sequence that you're about to see was not one used in the game, but it was the
only hand-drawn storyboard that survived to this day that I have.
So the in-game move at the end was the closest final animation I could find, so sorry about
that.
That's Steve Riesenberger, our production coordinator.
Great guy.
That's a hand-drawn animation.
and the closest sequence in the game I could find
that looks like that.
So it was a pretty involved process.
I don't remember how to close that.
And this next video will show many moves
from their video sequences, or their video references
to their final in-game animation.
Note how fast some of these animations got
once they were implemented into the gameplay.
This is a lot of fun.
That's Felix.
He's the Atari IT guy.
That was nice.
Just happened to be trained in Filipino stick fighting.
That was good.
You don't want to mess with that IT guy.
I got to do the beasts too.
Fuck.
Yeah, the cameraman is Luis. He was the storyboard animator.
Great guy to work with. Totally miss him.
Cool.
Suicide.
Dennis, our producer, hamming it up.
Excellent.
You might notice that these were all shot all around the company in the
cafeteria, weight room, conference room, random empty rooms.
Holy shit.
So yeah, we tried to use the blue or green screens
if we could, but sometimes we would just do it
wherever we could to get the job done fast,
and sometimes stuff got wrecked.
Whoops.
Okay, so that was how we got some of our animations
and move designs done.
And as you can see, I was pretty into what I was working on.
I was a huge fan of fighting games
and did Shoryuken and Hadouken on my friends
all the time in real life.
So creating new moves for fighting games
and getting to act them out as part of the job
was pretty awesome.
Our game was a product of the time.
Nothing like this would be made now due to the cost,
because stop motion talent and necessary infrastructure
just wouldn't exist now.
We had 1,500 to 2,000 frames of animation per character,
full unique frames as parts of each pose
were not reused to save money like other games.
This quantity was way up from 400
from Primal Rage 1 per character,
with the total being even more massive,
going from seven characters to 17.
Lots of memory.
So to facilitate the animation, custom hardware had to be created along with special routines
on the software end.
The first few frames of animation were stored in ROM, and when an animation was called up,
it would load the remaining frames off the hard drive into RAM for playback.
This was untested, cutting-edge, theoretical technology.
It was hoped that the frames would be loaded fast enough to be displayed in time.
It was difficult to get it right, and it caused graphics glitches when it didn't.
We were also loading music, pre-rendered background angles,
and FMV movies off the drive, some of them at the same time.
So we were getting a lot of use out of it.
Hard drive use in arcade games was rare at this time,
and the term streaming hadn't even been coined yet.
The game was ahead of its time in doing things
that weren't possible or practical for home conversions.
It created an experience that you could only get
in the arcade, but that was a double-edged sword,
as a home port attempt would not have been up to snuff,
and that may have caused potential problems
for the game's existence going into the future.
And despite some great things and ideas in motion,
there are many difficulties that contributed
to an eventual cancellation,
so now we'll take a look at some of those factors.
So Primal Rage was a very ambitious project,
even by Atari game standards.
We planned to ship in the summer of 1996,
but that schedule slipped,
due to the lengthy stop motion process
and hardware migrations.
For budget and political reasons, management stuck us on Jaguar derivative hardware called
Kojag, which was underpowered and performed worse than the Primal Rage 1 arcade hardware.
Killer Instinct had raised the bar for graphics, so we had to be competitive.
Trying to run on the inferior Kojag hardware cost us dearly in time, effort, and morale.
A bit later, but just in time, an arcade variant of the PSX Sony hardware became available.
It was capable of quality in 2D and 3D,
and gave us translucency and effects
that look impressive to this very day,
as well as play field scaling necessary
for a fighting game with huge characters.
Though relying on this non-internal hardware
may have led to other factors
contributing to our cancellation,
we could now make this a competitive product,
despite some additional delays
as a result of having to migrate again.
So.
The process, taking something from concept
to eventual implementation in the game, was too lengthy,
mostly due to graphics processing time.
It took months to get a character playable,
and that made my job that much harder
since the whole game had to play well as a cohesive work.
Puppet design and manufactured lead time
made character pre-visualization impossible.
People to this day sometimes feel
that the human characters look a bit freakish or ugly,
and to be honest, they didn't look
quite how I would have wanted.
But by the time the ball was rolling, nothing could be done.
A physical model for graphics meant absolute commitment.
What our characters have looked better or cooler
with smaller heads and more realistic proportions,
we had no way of knowing.
But this doesn't take away from the beautiful results
of stop motion animation.
It's just that the time, expense, and inability to pivot
was simply the nature of the beast, no pun intended.
We never had a basic but polished vertical slice
of the game.
For example, a single playable character fighting themselves,
one background, with a few moves and effects,
running solid and looking good.
While we knew what we were shooting for,
we were never able to demonstrate that
to a decision-making entity,
and that made it much more likely for a plug to be pulled
before we were looking representative of our final form.
The technical hurdles, such as hard drive streaming,
also contributed to instability
and a general glitchy look during development.
The game went on field test before characters were completed or balanced, and they lacked
their finishing moves.
Slips in schedule may have been the cause, but showing a game before it's ready can ruin
its chances for success.
Capcom fighting games of that era on test were indistinguishable from their finished
product.
On the other hand, Primal Rage 2 went on in test when it was still buggy, incomplete,
and unoptimized, and it earned poorly on test as a result.
Kind of unfair.
So aside from our schedule slipping and other production
issues, there is a major event that happened right
in the middle of our project.
In March of 1996, Atari Games was sold to WMS.
They're the parent company of Williams Midway,
the makers of Mortal Kombat and the manufacturers of Killer
Instinct.
So nothing to take away from the great creators
that they had there, but the management people that owned
them ended up buying us.
There were other bidders in contention,
such as Nolan Bushnell, but unfortunately, we
were bought by our direct competition.
Despite being told that things would be business as usual, a restructuring and reduction in
force followed.
Entire departments and long-time positions going back to the 70s were eliminated.
The family which had existed since the beginning of the video game industry was being disassembled.
The loss of morale was apocalyptic.
Even those who weren't laid off started to leave when they saw the writing on the wall.
Skipping ahead, this led to the closure of the company in the next six years,
when it had existed for 25 previously.
The amount of history and legacy destroyed caused by this event is immeasurable.
So for us, Primal Rage as a brand ate into Mortal Kombat,
which was highly successful for WMS.
The new management's commitment was put to the test
when we asked what characters from Mortal Kombat
we could use due to the merger,
and our request was outright refused,
despite a history of sharing characters
within their own point op products,
and then them having used Mortal Kombat actors
to promote Nintendo's killer instinct.
I don't think they wanted our product to be released no matter how good or profitable
it would have been.
It felt as though we were bought only to be gutted and then eliminated like Leland and
Tradewest who WMS had purchased before us and there was no trace left of them.
I didn't think our project was in danger, though, since Primal Rage was such a strong
brand with licensing deals in process.
I continued to work very hard, as I knew we were entering the home stretch.
At some point, I was told to dial it back, to wait to hear back from management, just
in case things went south.
But being young and stubborn, I did not, and secretly worked late into the night and didn't
care if I was told not to.
I wanted to see our game become the best it could be, because I envisioned players around
the world having a blast with it.
But that was not to be.
The game was canceled.
Within a couple of work weeks left in the year,
we were given a chance to wrap things up
before the project would be mothballed.
Team members were encouraged to join other projects
to avoid being laid off.
So a special meeting was announced on the day we were,
we sent off our distributor milestone
for national field testing.
This was likely the first version that had mostly stable,
complete characters with some fatalities.
It's probably the version that's out in the wild right now.
At that meeting, on December 5th, 1996,
our project was officially canceled.
Checking the dates, it's apparent that the decision
was made long before the milestone had been seen,
so that meant we pretty much never had a chance.
It would have been very difficult to produce
a straight to home conversion of the game.
Consoles of the time could barely pull off
an acceptable Primal Rage 1,
and it wouldn't be until a decade later
with the PlayStation 3's hard drive installs
that a proper Primal Rage 2 could be made.
With the time I had left, I kept working hard
and polished things up to the very end.
I didn't know any other way of operating,
and I'm not even sure if I went home.
I remember the last day when we were all in the lab and I was hammering on things until
the last second and my last batch of edits almost didn't get in.
And now I wonder to this day if the final lab version is out there somewhere waiting
to be discovered.
So cancellation for a game feels like non-existence for it.
You can't convey the art of gameplay through pictures or video.
It must be experienced.
I was probably more devastated than I realized, and I was still in disbelief.
I think subconsciously I was preparing to deal with the loss in some way so that I could
move forward.
I came back after the holidays and had to face the reality that the game was not going
to be released.
I did not join another team, despite there being another fighting game project I could
have gone to.
I sort of chose to be laid off, and even though I was very loyal to Atari games as a core
ideal...
It wasn't really the same company anymore, not after WMS had taken over.
I packed up my desk, preserving what I could, and said my goodbyes.
Our producer arranged for me to have a Primal Rage 2 prototype cabinet set aside for me
so I could come and pick it up at some point, but that would prove to be a bit difficult.
So how did I deal with what happened?
How did I move forward?
Helpless, crushing heartbreak and despair was about to overcome me, and it seemed that
all was lost.
By some miracle, I had a job lined up at Capcom Japan.
While Primal Rage 2 was my life in so many ways,
working at Capcom was also a dream.
They made the games I already loved.
And the problems I had trying to get a quality game
made at Atari would be a non-issue at Capcom,
who, back in 1997, still knew how
to make great fighting games.
When I left Atari, I intended to come back and visit,
get more of my stuff that was left
with coworkers and friends,
including that Primal Rage 2 arcade cabinet
and a Turbo Duo and dev kit,
which is worth a lot of money now, but I didn't.
They had a reunion that same year in 1997
and I didn't even go.
Out of sight, out of mind.
Working at Capcom Japan was a perfect job
to help me forget what had happened,
giving me a sense of advancement and purpose.
I was living my dream of working on games
that players truly loved.
However, I did miss being intimately involved
with the design of a single game
as much as I was with Primal Rage 2.
While I contributed to many Capcom games proudly,
their fighting games would probably still be okay
without my help, at least in 97.
Atari actually needed me, and I kind of missed that.
I'm unsure if this happens naturally in the process of moving on, but my memories and
perception of everything that I had been involved at, at Atari, had began to erode.
I treated it as if it had been a bad relationship with a bad breakup.
I remember...
I began to remember Primal Rage 2 as being this horrible, ugly, buggy mess, a terrible
game that I didn't want anybody to see, something I should be ashamed of for its failure to
be released.
And I think this had a lot to do with the game being in such a bad state for so long,
up until the very end, and that's the impression that stuck with me.
Perhaps this was some way of coping, to devalue my memory of it, to make it easier to forget.
In these years, I didn't talk much about Primal Rage 2 and tried to avoid the subject.
So a couple of years later, there was another fighting game at Atari that was under development
that had gone through various incarnations until its final form, Tenth Degree.
And it was finally competitive with Capcom fighting games in terms of art style and gameplay.
Friends of mine, formerly of Capcom, were actually in charge of the design.
But I learned too that it too had been canceled.
It was a little vindicating since, in my mind,
I felt since it was better than Primal Rage 2 in some ways,
might have been more deserving of release.
And since it got canned, it's like,
well, what hope did my game have, right?
So my supervisor at Capcom and I went to Atari
to see if there's any way we could salvage the project.
But nothing became of it.
I didn't think to try and get my remaining belongings,
like my Primal Rage 2 machine,
or maybe rescue some of its assets,
which is something I kind of regret now,
as it was probably my last chance.
After the cancellation of countless projects in February 2003, with less than 30 employees
remaining, Atari Games, then known as Midway Games West, was closed.
The home where I grew up, along with its history and what remained of Primal Rage 2, was gone
forever.
I mistakenly believed I would always be around,
and I could always go back whenever I wanted.
But time happens, and the world changes.
Whenever there is a company closure,
the history and resources that are lost or destroyed
is immeasurable, especially for a company
that had been standing for so long.
I further pushed back the memories I had of working there
and the joy that I felt being a part of it.
I felt the same helpless, crushing despair
I felt when my project was canceled.
But the next time they had a reunion, I definitely went,
and I would never miss another one again.
Years passed, and time marched on relentlessly.
In the post-2000 era, arcades began to die and production of new arcade games slowed
as they fell out of style.
An era of emulated arcade games began, and while most of them would become playable on
computers through emulation, Primal Rage 2 did not.
With its special custom hardware and unorthodox graphics delivery methods, that made sense.
But later I found out from one of the programmers that they had booby-trapped the code to prevent
bootlegging and reverse engineering.
The lack of emulation meant that it would remain unplayed by the public, sealing its
fate to be forgotten.
I continued to feel rather disassociated with Primal Rage, although it started bothering
me that I didn't go back to pick up my Rage 2 prototype arcade machine.
The prototype arcade machine appeared at California Extreme,
a retro arcade show here in the Bay Area in the early 2000s,
but either the buttons or monitor didn't work,
and that made me super sad.
When I saw this as either an act of information charity,
or maybe like leaving flowers on a grave,
I left a primal rage to official move list
that I had made for the distributors
and duct taped it to the cabinet.
Pictures of this flyer would circulate
on the internet thereafter, adding to the game's mystique.
Sometime in the mid-2000s, out of curiosity,
I did a random web search to see if anything
on Primal Rage 2 had ever surfaced,
hoping to find something along the lines
of emulation progress, but I didn't find what I expected.
This is how I found out about a website called DeviantArt,
and what would later come to be known as Rule 34.
Apparently there were fans of Primal Rage 2 out there, and oddly fan art and fan fiction
of it existed, particularly of the female characters.
Though I was slightly horrified, I marveled that enough people cared about, from what
little there was out there, to be fans of these otherwise non-existent characters.
So more time passed, and as such, things that become old become new and cool again through
nostalgia.
The kids that had grown up with Primal Rage in the arcades and in their homes were now
remembering the game with fondness, despite its flaws.
So at conventions and gaming expos, I started to talk to fans about Primal Rage alongside
things like Street Fighter and Tetris.
Also around this time, YouTube started to become a thing, allowing people to share their
nostalgia, views, and playthroughs on all games.
In 2013, a video called Primal Rage 2,
a forgotten legend appeared.
This shared information that was known about
Primal Rage 2 at the time,
like the game's teasers that appeared
in comics and magazines,
the broken state of the emulation,
and some prototype footage.
The views and comments revealed
that there was some desire to see it revived.
For whatever reason, I still felt the game
was this wretched thing that should remain buried,
so I dismissed it and chose not
to take part in the discussion.
And then, everything changed.
The Galloping Ghost Arcade in Brookfield, Illinois
acquired a Primal Rage 2 prototype board
and put it on a cabinet on their arcade floor
and announced it on YouTube on June 21st, 2014.
For the uninitiated, the Galloping Ghost Arcade
is one of the best and most notable arcades in the world,
housing 700 plus arcade games
with a new game released on their floor every Monday.
But prior to this, I had never heard of the place before.
The arcade live streamed Primal Rage 2 on Twitch
for the next few days for all the world to see.
I learned about the game being there
and I watched the stream.
The game looked better than I had remembered it to be.
I was also taken aback by the positive things people were saying about the game and how
great they thought it played.
I ended up interacting with the people of the arcade through the Twitch chat, and some
of the things that I knew about the game, like how you pick the secret characters by
holding up on the select boxes, even though my memories were still fuzzy.
I watched the stream through its entire run, fixated on my unseen work and those who were
experiencing it for the first time.
I started to realize that maybe I had forgotten that at the very end of the project, maybe
the game didn't look so bad after all.
So this was a mostly complete, multi-million dollar, AAA game from over 15 years ago, from
out of nowhere, was suddenly unleashed into the internet era.
For most games, one could Google up an FAQ or watch a playthrough on YouTube, but nothing
of the sort existed for Primal Rage 2.
Its secrets were fresh, real, and ripe for discovery.
Those that were playing it were excitedly uncovering the game's special moves, combos,
and finishers as they went, and the world watched along via stream as they were being
discovered in real time.
The arcade staff and players knew their stuff about fighting games, and as I watched them
play and enjoy it, my perception of Primal Rage 2 began to change.
One could say that this is when my healing truly began.
And Primal Rage 2 made news headlines.
It got covered on all the major sites, Joystick, Kotaku, Polygon, Structoid.
This I did not expect.
And especially the meaning of this,
that Primal Rage 2 exists.
It's kind of nice after all that happened.
After the word got out,
players began to travel to the arcade
just to see and play the rare prototype game.
Doc Mac, the owner of the Galloping Ghost Arcade,
and its related businesses mentioned
players coming in from around the world,
and a couple who hitchhiked their way
across the country to come and play Primal Rage 2.
So pilgrimages were actually a thing.
Oops.
But this would only be the beginning of something
even more amazing.
The Galloping Ghosts Arcade, while already specializing
in rare games, now fully realized the impact
of making something unique and historic available.
Games that never saw the light of day
now had a potential home where they could be maintained,
protected, and most importantly,
made available for people to play and enjoy.
Many other prototypes would then be put
onto the arcade floor, including Beavis and Butthead,
Freeze the Cat, BioFreaks,
and the infamous Tattoo Assassins.
Galloping Ghosts also began to actively collaborate
with creators who had unreleased games,
restoring them and sometimes even finishing them
to make them playable by the public.
Jeff Lee of Qbert fame worked with them
to put Argus and Arena on the show floor,
or the arcade floor.
and Brian Collin, who made Rampage,
worked with them to produce Deathstalker the Specter Files,
which was a canceled Laserdisc game.
Its footage was shot in the 80s,
so they had to convert it to digital,
and the entire game was redone in a modern engine.
So now you can go to the game and play it
as an arcade machine, but you can also order
the full arcade unit from them and purchase one.
So it's definitely a significant effort
in preserving games that would otherwise be lost forever.
On March 28th, 2015, I was invited out to the Galloping Ghost Arcade for their Developers'
Day event and finally got to play a fully functional Primal Rage 2 arcade game, something
I hadn't been able to do for what felt like an eternity.
And likewise, from watching it on the stream, it was better than my mind had pictured it
after all those years.
What was even more amazing, though, was finally seeing the arcade itself, so filled with great
games and history you won't find anywhere else, and meeting the incredible people who
could make a place like that possible.
On their Planet Hollywood style developer VIP autograph picture wall, at least in this
photo, my photo appears underneath Ed Boon, the Mortal Kombat guy, among other legends.
It's pretty cool.
So I didn't know this trading card existed
until last November when I was being inducted
into the International Video Game Hall of Fame in Iowa,
and someone came up to me for an autograph,
and he showed me this card,
and it mentions me being reunited with Primal Rage 2.
So when I went back to the Galloping Ghost Arcade
the next day, I was like,
hey, no one told me they made a card for this.
And then Pete Hahn,
the Primal Rage high score world record champ,
who actually works there,
was like, oh yeah, do you want some?
So I have a few of these to give away to you guys
if you can find me after the presentation.
So that might have wrapped up the story quite nicely,
but then the unimaginable happened.
In 2017, Primal Rage 2 finally became playable
through emulation.
Long time efforts being made by YouTube user Gruntzilla94
progressed significantly.
And in March of 2017, he released a modified version
of MAME called MAME for Rage 2
that allows existing Primal Rage 2 ROMs
out in the wild to be playable.
While emulation isn't 100% perfect yet,
and there are glitches and crashes,
it did more than the minimum that fans had hoped for.
In some ways, the emulated game runs better
than the actual hardware, as loading data within emulation
is faster than that of a 1996 IDE hard drive interface
that we didn't get to optimize,
leading to better frame rates and more consistent animation.
A game ahead of its time that's able to scale up
to the future for better performance is interesting indeed.
With the game now able to be played by the masses,
it would now have YouTube videos and streams on Twitch,
exposing it again to a new audience.
And boom, Primal Rage 2 blows up in the news again.
Maybe more people cared about the game than I thought.
But my favorite article to come out of all this
was the end gadget one.
2017's hottest new fighting game.
Going from working your ass off on a game
that never got to exist,
to have it become 2017's hottest new fighting game
20 years later, even if it's said in jest,
that's a beast god tier level of vindication.
I was completely floored.
But the real payoff and what really healed me
as a game developer after having their dreams canceled
so long ago, was getting to see players
play the game and enjoy it.
So there are a couple of videos here.
Fair warning, there's some colorful language,
but for some reason, seeing people react this way
to something you've created is really quite satisfying,
as you'll about see.
And I also cleared it, so they said it was okay.
Yes, I did it!
So this is at Galloping Ghosts in 2014
when they were finding things in real time.
Oh!
Oh, shit! Yeah!
I did a fatality!
Yeah!
That's not a little kid, by the way. He's a grown man.
Oh, oh!
Fatality!
We got a new one!
Well, there we go!
Holy shit!
Fatality!
Oh, shit!
Did you guys see that?
Did anyone see that? Please!
And this is from 2017, uh, Super Best Friends Play.
Oh my god, that's super strong.
Do it! Do it!
Are there fatalities?
There are fatalities.
Any idea?
OHHHHHHHHH!
That was awesome I think!
Okay, so now the weird part...
Oh god, am I blizzard?
Yeah, you can like...
Oh shit!
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I'm blizzard!
Right, so and then you...
Oh my god, Matt, you're so strong!
Holy shit!
Realizing through the arm of a dinosaur!
No, you're a Saber Tooth Tiger!
That's cool!
I turned into Slash Fang.
Slash head. Yes. Against a bunch of dinos. Yeah, it had no body. But you fought them in the coolest stage.
You fought them in like a bunch of karate karting.
Holy shit!
He's got a lot. He's got, he goes, he goes ham.
Chaos. Unclear what's, what's strong yet.
Oh.
Oh! It lasts.
Why didn't this win the fan vote at EVO?
I don't, because people just don't know what's quality.
Yeah, that's true.
Holy shit! Do that!
That thing's fast.
That's nuts
Yeah big combo
He's got a TV. Yeah. Yeah, I remember yes that I say that in an alternate reality where this did come out
primal rage would have been a franchise
That was super good
Whoa!
Oh!
That is so elaborate.
One Bloodborne, please.
And it's Necro-san.
Oh, Necro-san.
Oh, my God.
That's perfect.
Oh, my God, that's the best.
Yeah, so...
I finally got to see people
enjoy the game.
that was like an incredible feeling and a real gift.
So years of just not knowing what it would have been like
to have people play it,
to suddenly having people play it was a thing.
So after people finally got to enjoy it,
it made me take a look back and look at it with new eyes.
In one sense, it's a demon that haunted me for a while,
but in order for me to learn, it's something I had to face.
So seeing humans in their dino game is somehow offensive to some Primal Rage fans.
I mean, I get it, I love the beasts too, but they are still in the game, and this game
wouldn't have been made at all without the humans.
So if new players are able to pick up the game, and they can do it easily because they
have familiar humanoid characters, I still feel that we're justified in the decision
to include the humans even now.
Players often comment positively about the impressive animation.
I appreciate the aspect of this project more and more now,
as the animation makes the game unique,
and it's helped it to age visually very well
when other games of the era have not.
I remember this game as a broken, terrible mess.
The new players playing the game were saying
how complete and polished it felt,
despite being an incomplete prototype.
I still think it's a bag of horrors in that regard,
because it never went through any balance testing whatsoever.
It was just my best guesses.
But then they'll say how it was more complete and finished than Street Fighter V, and then
I gotta high-five them.
One thing I do get smug about is how people say the gameplay is so much better than Primal
Rage 1.
I never remind myself that's how I tried to get Primal Rage 1 to play and I wasn't allowed
to and then I get sad again.
So nothing's really changed there.
In the 20 or so years of fighting game evolution and the rise of eSports, people who know their
stuff discuss Primal Rage 2 using modern fighting game design terminologies and dissect it as
if it were made today.
I feel so vindicated when those players say that Primal Rage 2 still holds up as a well-made,
fun fighting game, and that's one of the key things that changed how I felt about the project
and why I can look at it positively now.
So what can we learn about all that's happened here?
Let's take a look at what I learned,
and maybe that can apply to other situations.
So having an impressive, polished, vertical slice
as early as possible is a must.
Looking and being viable is really the best defense
against cancellation, and not always a good place
to be at in your project.
If you have a piece of your game that's playable,
fun, and cool, it increases everybody's morale,
and arms you with something that you show off
and be confident about, even in the face
of someone above you who makes decisions.
I should have taken what was going on in the company buyout more seriously.
Even though I wasn't in the immediate layoffs, the shockwaves caused major disruptions and
morale loss.
To this day, I believe that if the company wasn't sold off, Primal Rage 2 would have
been released.
But, you know, after all is said and done, I think I'm kind of okay with how things played
out in the end.
I wish I had been more appreciative and encouraging of my teammates.
There are things that happened since the cancellation that helped me heal now, but I'm not so sure
about the others on the project, whether they know or care, especially since some of those
like our main stop-motion animator, Pete Kleinow, had passed pretty soon after the project was
over.
I wish there was a way that I could bring the reassurance I have now back in time to
make the work more of a joy to those involved, no matter what the outcome would have been.
I did what I could, but it's never enough.
You can never preserve enough history.
If something's certain to be trashed, if you're not there to protect it anymore, try to save
it.
If you can't take it with you, take a picture, make a record, tell someone who can protect
it or save it.
Company buyouts and closures need to be done more responsibly.
Maybe more steps need to be taken so digital history can be preserved by those that can
do something about it, before it's all thrown in a dumpster to be never seen again.
I especially didn't take enough photos of the project, and especially people.
Digital cameras weren't a thing yet, so that's an excuse, but it's still not an excuse.
The random motion capture videos that you saw here are absolutely precious to me, and
are one of the key pieces of history that I have.
The reactions to those little bits that I've shown of it have had a huge response from
fans and allow a better story of our development to be told.
Also getting to see my friends and co-workers and the building I used to call home.
That's priceless.
I regret not checking in and keeping ties with my remaining coworkers.
I think more preservation would have been possible had I been better about this.
Also, huge regrets not going back for my Primal Rage 2 machine.
I think that failure on that end multiplied my negativity about the game due to the added
loss and the fact that the company closed so soon after.
I realized I had shut out a lot of the pain in order to move on and in order to survive,
but you can only do that for so long.
Sometimes you have to go back and fight your demons or make amends to have a better closure.
It's not always possible, and sometimes crazy stuff has to happen first, but once you actually
get over things in a positive way, you'll be better for it.
So what went right, and what am I glad that I did,
and what would I do again if I had the chance?
Maintaining my work ethic, even when all seemed lost,
even if others told me not to.
This was a happy coincidence in that I was so young
and motivated and that everything mattered so much to me.
I really knew no other way,
and that's just pretty much stayed the same ever since.
A lot of the quality of the gameplay came from best guesses
and long, lonely hours to do it,
since the game never actually went into full test
or preliminary balancing.
So always do your best
and there won't be a chance for regret.
Releasing pieces of Primal Rage 2 in the form of toys, comics, books, etc.
A trail for fans to follow.
If there's enough pieces of the game out there to generate interest and make people look
for answers years later, those people may help to revive or maybe even rebuild your
cancelled game at some point in the future.
Preserving what I could.
Documents, art, and data.
Glad I did that.
Something may be important someday.
So a tip for you time travelers out there.
Time to get a 20MB mailbox off of a...
Any kind of large file off of a computer from the early 90s prior to the invention of USB
is no trivial task.
Be prepared.
Reaching out and being encouraging of your fans and projects by establishing a friendly
and positive dialogue with your fan community.
They understand the hard work that went into these games and have knowledge and respect
for it.
By appreciating their efforts, whether it's making YouTube videos or working on emulators
or things of that nature, it can drive forward a future for a product that might not otherwise
have one.
What else is, the YouTube revolution absolutely made what happened with Primal Rage 2's emulation
possible.
It's where it all happened.
A dialogue was started, and then findings were posted, and it got people excited, and
efforts were encouraged.
Community motivation is a powerful tool.
Even my interactions there have had a positive effect, whether they were intentional or not.
And I can't say how amazing the Galloping Ghost arcade is, for them to invest so much
effort into restoring games and providing a place where people can play rare and unreleased
works.
But there are many organizations like this,
whether it's an arcade, a museum, a yearly convention,
or events that host them.
These are invaluable resources for players and developers.
So even if they aren't helping to preserve or revive
your works, considering contributing to their efforts
so they may continue operating.
Finally, some of us are in here in this room today
to find out about gaming history and learn from it.
For that to happen, knowledge has to be shared.
And this is especially important
for canceled games and endangered knowledge.
This is why I love GDC and have been attending for so long
and I'm happy to finally be able to give back
a little bit of that.
So if you have a story, whether you share it
with other professionals or fans of your work,
someone may learn something or become inspired too.
So project cancellations are usually stuck in past tense,
something bad that can't be changed,
work wasted that will never be seen.
But this story ends a bit differently,
and I've made a video that shows some personal resolution
as a result of Primal Rage 2's revivals
and how it ties into the present and the future.
A witcher versus the beast of Mechina!
Killer instinct versus Primal Rage!
So I didn't work on The Witcher 3, but I thought this reference to Primal Rage, clearly in the context of 1994 since it also mentions Killer Instinct, was really interesting.
It made me think.
All these years and I had shoved Primal Rage games so far back into my mind that I never did anything like this.
I never connected what I did later to what I did before.
Kind of like a lost opportunity, so maybe I should change that.
Because eventually, I did get over my shame.
I learned to be proud of my work.
I learned to be proud of my work, and why is it showing my PowerPoint on the video?
Hold on a second, okay.
So all these years, and I finally got over my shame.
I learned to be proud of my work, canceled or not.
And now maybe I don't mind mentioning Primal Rage every now and then, even here in this
last project I did something on.
Because, you know, it's a prehistoric level and it kind of fits.
So I go back to the Galloping Ghosts Arcade
every now and then, every year,
thankful for their efforts.
I was able to donate some cool Primal Rage stuff
to their living museum of all things Primal Rage.
Their prototypes didn't have a bezel and control panel
as the game got canceled while I was working on them.
So now I'm working with the arcade to get them done,
assembling art and other lost resources I've since found
to finish the cabinet and make their machine truly complete.
But that's not all.
It turns out they were interested in what I was doing next.
My current game project, the tentatively titled Strike Harbinger, was first unveiled at the
Galloping Ghost Arcade.
They will be helping us to produce the eventual arcade version.
All three leads in our team, including myself, are ex-Atari Games creators.
And with that, we want to carry on the hopes and dreams of where we once came from.
As bizarre as it sounds, my current team and project might not be where we are today.
had Primal Rage 2 not been cancelled. And despite the hardships along the way,
it led to many other things that were good.
Maybe Primal Rage 2 will be a part of everything I do now.
And maybe this bone dragon boss came from out of an asteroid egg. Or maybe it didn't.
So that might have been the end of the story,
but this story kept writing itself
even after my talk got accepted at GDC.
So now you get the special surprise ending.
At the end of 2017, YouTube user GreenGeode,
who was on the forefront of research efforts
regarding PrimalRage 2's data
and the inner workings of the game,
posted this video.
I did not ask him to make this, nor did I contact him.
And I'm gonna have to quote myself.
I can tell this was not representative of how far we came because Talon's slide is still
super broken and it really bugs me.
The crazy slide can be fun in a broken state, but it makes the whole game look unfinished.
LOL.
So it seems that there's still a desire to see Primal Rage 2 completed someday,
and what you see here are the very first efforts towards continued development of Primal Rage 2 going into the future,
by way of patching the game with various fixes, which someday may even be used to update the arcade machine at Galloping Ghost.
The only thing that's going to get cancelled now is the apocalypse.
Someone noticing my conversation on YouTube resulted in a bug fix for a two decade old game,
so you never know what good it can do to share a bit of history and to discuss your stories too.
I look forward to further interactions with these passionate fans, at least in an advisory role,
to maybe see it get closer to where it would have been had it not been cancelled.
I feel fortunate that by twists of fate, one of the most devastating things that happened
in my life was eventually turned into something positive.
Cancellation did not have to mean non-existence.
I can only hope that others of you with a cancelled project or bought out company
may also find a way towards a better outcome.
Sometimes you can't fight fate,
but you can roll with the punches
and make the best of a situation.
It may take years, or in my case decades,
but never give up hope.
Learn from your experiences, good or bad,
project released or project canceled.
A win quote I wrote for the character of Ryu
in Street Fighter sums it up quite nicely.
Whether we win or lose,
all of our battles make us stronger.
Here's some contact info and resources if you want to find out more about what's going
on with Primal Rage 2 going into the future, or for myself for that matter.
Please support these Primal Rage 2 YouTubers, this story wouldn't have been possible without
them.
And if there's time I can take questions, so please approach the microphone.
Hi, this is more of a comment than a question.
So going back about 17 years now,
I've been preserving unreleased games over the internet.
And it's involved about five figures
of lost money on my part.
It's involved fighting a lot of collectors
who wanna like hoard these things away
in their like goblin treasure hoards.
And it's involved a lot of like kind of stalkery emails
to developers and things like that.
to see this talk at GDC has been just really gratifying for my work over all these years.
I'm really happy to hear it. There are people that hoard this stuff, but then there's also
people like Galloping Ghosts who actually want to put them out for people to play, and I think
that's great. A place like that can live, and the games get to live too.
So I just wanted to thank you.
Oh, thank you.
It's kind of an emotional moment for me.
And thank you for any efforts that you do to preserve games.
I didn't have anything to do with this one, but there's a lot of others. Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Hi, uh, given the resurgence that Primal Rage 2 had on the
internet, is, do you think there's any possibility of
future installments in the series?
So I get, I get asked that a lot. A lot of it has to do with
who owns the IP now, which is probably, uh, Warner Brothers,
because they bought everything that Atari Games had for a
while, they brought out a version of Gauntlet. Um, if they
want to do an official one, then they would have to find a
developer and do it.
if they wanted to reach out to me, I'm busy right now, but I can advise them.
There has been some interest. A lot of fans contact me and
I've been kinda like thinking, well, what would a spiritual successor be like?
So, you know, if the IP goes up for sale again,
I might, you know, take a look at that. So that might be official, but otherwise
Werner Brothers is kind of in their hands as they own it now.
Thank you. You're welcome.
Any other questions?
Okay.
Have you been in contact with any of the sort of dumpster divery Atari collectors who might
have assets that you're missing for this game?
Hmm. Um, I'm in contact with some people that do have a lot of the Atari stuff. Um, actually
the owner of AtariGames.com has a lot of the stuff and he has been doing some things to
preserve it. He's been sharing his photos. Uh, some of the photos were actually, uh, from
ones that he had posted. Uh, so they're, they're out there. Um.
Cool. I don't need to introduce you then. That's why I was asking.
Okay. Yeah. I, I know Scott. Oh perfect. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah, he's the one who, um, I, I put the flyer up on his machine. Yeah.
Oh nice. See it all it all works out. Thanks. If there's any uh no other questions uh y'all can
come up here and grab a card if you want.