Hi everybody, thank you for attending this talk.
My name is Florent Morin.
As you can tell by my wonderful accent, I'm from France.
And I'm going to try to explain to you
how in our game, Bury My Love,
we try to make the player feel helplessness.
Helplessness is not a feeling that is often explored in video games,
but when you tackle certain topics, you just don't have the choice.
And that was our case.
I'm supposed to remind you to turn off your phones,
and also if we don't have time for any questions at the end of the talk,
we can meet in the wrap-up room of Overlook 2022.
Thank you.
So, very quickly, who am I? I'm a former journalist.
I've been a journalist for 10 years before I started making video games.
And then I founded The Pixel Hunt in 2013.
And The Pixel Hunt is a video game studio that specializes in reality-inspired games.
What are reality-inspired games? Well, I'll come back to it in...
A moment. Our latest game is Bury My Love.
Now, I'm sure a lot of people here have already played it,
but I'm not sure everyone has, so here's a quick trailer
for you to get familiar with the project.
So, Bury My Love is a reality-inspired game.
It is a game that is directly based on true real-life events.
In our case, the story of migrants who fled from Syria
and are still fleeing from Syria today
and try to reach Europe in hopes of a better life.
It was written by the help of Dana.
Dana is a Syrian woman who left Damascus in 2015
and who's now living in Germany.
And we met Dana because of an article
in French newspaper Le Monde,
where she was telling the story
of how she kept in touch with her family via WhatsApp
for all the journey she made.
So this was a very inspiring story and we decided to make a game that would mimic the
way migrants use messaging apps because you may or may not know that nowadays almost every
migrant has a smartphone and for them that's not a luxury, that's actually the only way
they have to keep in touch with their friends and families, so that's very crucial to them.
Then again, when you make a reality-inspired game,
there are ethics you have to respect.
And they are actually quite close to journalism
or documentary filmmaking ethics.
So I was already familiar with them
before I started making games.
Things you could, you should do is to respect reality.
You have to gather a lot of documentation,
you have to be really sure to really know
what you're talking about.
And you also obviously have to listen to the people
who actually experience the story
you are telling in your games.
There also are things that you should not do.
And the main and most important thing,
and the thing that is really different from classic games,
is that you should not be too player-centric.
A lot of games focus on the player and on fun.
And sometimes that makes players a little bit
like untitled brats.
They expect that the game is built around and for them
and for the pleasure.
That's not what we did for Birmingham Love.
That made us get some.
some hefty comments, but still we are happy with it because it was mandatory for the topic
we wanted to tackle.
So I pushed the wrong button because I'm so scared.
What we learned actually listening to migrants, we've been listening to Dana, obviously we've
been chatting with Dana over WhatsApp, asking lots of questions, but we also listened to
lots of other migrants and read and...
saw things. And what we learned is that no matter how you prepare your journey, things
will go sideways. There are too many things that you cannot control, that you are not
aware of, too many policies that change.
So you will need to adapt.
You will more often than not have the feeling
that you are not in control at all.
Also, being connected with your loved ones
is nice because you have them in your pocket.
You can give them updates on your situation.
But it's also very hard.
because they are always with you
while not being physically with you.
So if something bad happens to you, what should you do?
Should you tell them?
Should you keep them from knowing
because you don't want them to worry?
Should you lie to them?
This is difficult.
And it's also difficult on the other side,
when you're someone who's stayed in Syria
or who's already in Germany,
and you're waiting for news and you don't get news.
Whereas you know you could get news because they have a phone.
What happens? What's going on?
This is very difficult to live through.
And for those who stay, or for those who are already arrived,
helplessness is the feeling that they get the most.
And this is the feeling that they have the most trouble
dealing with.
So that's why we designed our entire game around this feeling
of helplessness.
We wanted you, as players, to obviously not live their lives,
because it's just a video game, but to empathize
and to understand what those people go through.
So how did we do that?
How did we convey this feeling of helplessness
as a game design?
First of all, we put you in a position.
where you are not on the ground.
It's not you who travels.
You play as Majd, Nor's husband.
And I don't even like to say that
because you're not really playing as Majd.
Majd is a character on his own,
and sometimes he will say things
that you would probably not say
because maybe of cultural differences or anything.
So it's not even about you as the player,
but the character you are impersonating
is not on the ground.
He's not the one who is.
living things. So that's a kind of a special situation for a video game.
So to make you understand that, we thought we had to make a very living Noor.
We wanted to convey to you the feeling that you were talking to a real person,
that Noor was really alive. And how did we make that?
First, we tried to make her as consistent as possible.
Noor is brave, she's zestful, she's independent, she's also fairly stubborn.
And she has a tendency to trust people too easily.
Those were our writing guidelines
that we tried to keep along the way
when we were writing the 110,000 words of the game.
Because we wanted you, no matter which path you would take,
to feel that you were really connecting
and bonding with a real person.
Then again, Noor lives through very tough times,
and sometimes she will lie too much.
This comes from a testimony from Dana,
and I think it's one of the best proofs of love
that you can even give someone.
You are living through a very terrible situation
and you don't want to tell your loved ones
because you don't want them to worry.
So Nour lies to Majd, and she lies to you.
And sometimes if you're very careful,
if you read her, all her message very carefully,
you will notice all the time that she told you something
at one moment, and then you realize
that it wasn't the complete truth.
So that makes you feel helpless.
Why did she feel compelled to hide things from you?
Because they are terrible things,
because she thought you could not do anything about that.
That's up to you to imagine.
And also, Noor hesitates when she talks to you.
And this is also an important way to make you feel
that she actually leaves things.
One very quick technical point.
To make Bermuda Love, we used Inkle Studios
scripting language, Ink.
And because it's open source, and because it's awesome,
and because the people at Inkle Studios are super dope,
so thank them.
Okay? And in the script we put some commands, and for instance, these fake commands,
followed by a time in milliseconds, will make this little animation of Nouri's typing
appear on the screen, then disappear.
So you would think as a player, oh, she wanted to tell me something, but she changed her mind.
Why did she do that? And you don't have the answer.
You just have to imagine why.
Also...
Majd is not on the ground, but he loves Noor,
so he wants to help her very, very, very bad.
So he will feel compelled to give advice,
even though you don't have enough information
to know which advice is good or which advice is bad.
So sometimes you will give Noor bad advice
and you will maybe feel bad about that,
but it came from a good part of your heart.
You wanted to help her.
You just didn't know what the consequences would be.
But the main feature to make you understand that you are not on the ground is the fact that
Bury My Love is a game that consists of 99% of waiting.
You are actually not playing the game.
You can put the phone in your pocket because Noor has to do things
and she doesn't have time to chat with you
and so you have to wait for a new notification for her to come back to you.
She's the one who's leaving the things.
You are just the one who is there for her.
if she needs you, but she doesn't always need you.
How did we convey that?
First, we had three states for Noor.
The basic state is that she's online,
so she appears online like in every chat applications.
But when we add a little command line on the script,
wait for 30 minutes and be busy,
then the status turns to busy.
So you know that she's still connected,
she's still there, she's normally okay.
But she can't talk to you because she has things to do.
But sometimes, there will be waiting times
where Noor will appear as offline.
And then you will start wondering, what happened?
Why?
Why is she completely offline?
Doesn't she have battery in the phone anymore?
Is she in a zone where there's no signal, no coverage?
Or is something worse happened?
Well, you will not know until Noor is back online.
And as you are not on the ground,
you will not decide when she will be back online.
Also, we did not hesitate to populate the game with very,
very short sessions.
For instance, in this screenshot, you must wait for
20 minutes for her to come back.
And she just comes and tells you that she's approaching
the border and that she will be away from coverage.
And so she can't talk to you anymore.
And then she's.
off again. So you have a notification, you read three sentences and then you can put
your phone back. We try to do that in order to make you feel that she's the one leaving
the things and you are not. The second point is that even when you can talk to her and
even when you make choices, you are often not really in control.
To explain that, I have to give you a little detail about how Noor works as a game character.
She's defined by three variables.
The first one is her money. She leaves her country with a sum,
and she will have to pay smugglers to pay for...
a bed to eat food and everything.
And sometimes you will reach situations
when if she doesn't have enough money,
she can't do some things.
But there are two other variables
that are more psychological.
The first one is the love,
the love relationship between her and you.
And sometimes you will give her advice that will maybe make her love you less or love you more
and you will not know that.
And the third one is her morale. Is she doing okay?
Did she live through something that was really bad for her morale?
Those three variables are evolving during the entire game.
And this is important because sometimes, very rarely in fact,
you will have direct decisions.
When Noor doesn't know what to do, for instance,
should she go to location A or location B,
she will ask you and you will be able to tell her what to do.
And if she's in a good mood, she will listen to you.
And sometimes she will not listen to you because she's stubborn.
But you will then have direct decision.
Okay, go that way, I think it's better,
and she will follow your advice.
But that's very rare, actually, in the game.
Most of the very important decision
that you will have to make are blind.
I mean, when you make them, you don't know that they are actually important decisions.
You just know that they are decisions that might seem trivial, or that might seem not
very important, but that might have very important consequences later on.
We keep you in the dark on that for the very same reason.
We want you to not feel in control.
And also, there will be decisions that you will not even be aware you are making
because you will not make a conscious choice.
For instance, very often in the game, you will answer Noor with an emoji.
And you see in this example that you can answer with three different emojis.
And two of them will give her a plus two in her love for you.
and one will give her minus six points in love for you.
That's actually very small values, it's not a lot.
But it's cumulative, and decision after decision
after decision, your relationship with her will evolve,
and her morale will evolve.
And then she will reach a point in her journey
when she will need a special...
a certain level of morale or a certain level of love for you
to take a decision or another decision.
And he will reach that point and take the decision accordingly.
So you will not have a direct control on the choice,
but the choice will happen anyway because it's cumulative over time.
But in any case, those variables are never displayed.
They are never visible to the player.
We don't want you to check for every choice you make,
like you would do in Reigns, for instance,
when you have a direct feedback over the variables of the game.
We want you to follow your guts and to give her
the advice you think are best.
And we came up with this idea after a long thinking process.
In the beginning, we thought we would add
to the status bar a mood indicator that would vary
depending on the level of love and level of morale
that Noura would feel.
and that would give you a little clue about how she felt.
But we felt that it would be too extra diegetic,
that it would feel too much like a game
and not enough like talking to a real person.
So we decided to put this away.
What we did is at some moment in the game script,
we changed some expressions of Noor
depending on her condition.
So the only way you have to know how she feels
is to really, really pay attention to how she talks to you.
The third thing we wanted to put in the game to make you feel this helplessness
is that we wanted to be clear that for migrants life is not fair
and also that death is part of the journey.
We actually had a very long discussion among the team about this question.
After all, we spend a lot of time building
the relationship between you as a player and Noor.
So making her die can be terrible.
And also, we are talking about the real lives
of real people who really are risking their lives.
So would it be disrespectful to put death in the game?
But actually, we thought that it was the contrary,
the other way around.
it would have been disrespectful not to put death in the game because they are risking their lives and you should not ignore that.
So, there are 19 different endings in the game and some of them are very bad, including death situation.
And there are 39 ways to reach one of those 19 endings.
And as you can see, some of them are really bad.
But the majority of them are somewhere in between and that comes directly from the documentation phase where we...
noted that for most migrants, when they stop migrating,
that's because they are stuck somewhere.
They have to wait in a camp for their administrative status
to evolve, and they don't know.
They are stuck in limbo.
And we wanted to render that in the game also.
But let me give you an example of how death can occur in the game.
And you will see how unfair this is.
This is the smuggler sequence.
I'm sorry, but it's a slight spoiler to the game.
But again, it's a conference, so I have to unveil things.
And in the smuggler sequence, you are in Izmir.
It's a Turkish city not far away from the Mediterranean Sea.
And Noor wants to take a boat to cross to Lesbos in Greece.
So the first choice you have to make is decide together
which smuggler she's going to see to cross the sea.
She can decide between a smuggler she doesn't know
but has met on the ground or another smuggler that was.
that she vaguely knows through mutual acquaintance.
So you have to choose that,
and you don't know which one is the best.
You just have to trust your guts once again.
Then she asks you, did I forget something?
Do you think about something I should take on my journey,
on my boat journey?
And you can advise her to take.
seasickness medicine or a flashlight.
Why should you decide to tell her one thing or another?
I don't know.
You should decide because you think one thing is best,
but you have no reason, no particular reason to decide.
And depending on those two choices, you can reach three, four different endings to this sequence.
In one of the combinations, Noor ends up okay.
She crosses the sea and it's tough, but she arrives fine.
In two of them, she makes it, but the journey is very, very complicated
and she's in a trauma because she sees things that are tough.
In the last one, you get to an ending.
And in Bury My Love, every ending is an audio log.
And this is the audio log you get.
Majd, I don't know if you're going to get this,
but I'm freaking out.
If the rescue team don't come soon, we won't.
We won't hold on.
Whatever.
I wanted to tell you, I love you.
I love you.
I love you, I love you, I love you.
Oh shit!
I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you, I love you.
Well, let me tell you something.
If I was a player and I played a game like that,
that's after two choices that I didn't have any idea.
of how to take them, how to make them,
ended up like that, I would want to punch
the game designer in the face.
Please don't punch me in the face.
As a game designer, I think it's important
to make you feel helpless and frustrated
and feel that it's terribly unfair because it is,
but simply because what we are talking about here
is a terribly unfair situation, so sorry.
Actually, the only thing migrants have is to live by the moment.
They know better than everyone that it's not the destination that matters.
It will matter at a time, but they take one day after another.
And it's the journey that matters.
And that's what we try to do also in Bury My Love.
We wanted you to feel that way, to care about the journey,
to care about the good moments that you may encounter,
to care about the bad moments that you may also encounter,
and to understand that there will be many unexpected ones,
many surprises, many moments where you will have to adapt
to compensate for your lack of control.
So to render that, we made another thing that any good game design teacher would advise strongly against.
It's that there is no safe points in Birmingham I Love.
Even when you reach an ending, you cannot start back from one part of the story and decide,
oh I made this decision but it was very wrong, I want to go back there and change my decision.
You cannot do that in Birmingham I Love.
You have only two solutions when you reach an ending.
The first one is to restart from day one.
And why is that?
That is because for us, Noor is not a real person,
contrary to what I told you.
For us, Noor is a metaphor for the thousands
and hundreds of thousands of persons
who actually did this journey.
And we wanted you to feel that way, that every time you play Bury Me, My Love,
you play someone else, you play a new person that is trying to face a new situation.
But you have another possibility. You can also never play the game again,
and that's not a troll, I really mean it. I'm completely okay with that.
You can never play the game again because, ultimately,
Burying My Love is a game about coming to terms with the idea
that no matter how much you love someone,
there are times when you simply cannot save them.
Thank you.
I hope you have questions because I've
been rushing through the presentation
to be lucky enough to discuss it with you.
Hi.
My name is Jeremy.
It's great to meet you.
Thank you so much for doing this and presenting.
It's, uh, I don't even know how to, I have words.
I have a lot of questions.
I'll ask one for now.
Why is it important for you for players
to feel helpless when playing this game?
And how does getting your players to feel that
make them care about the situation?
I'm not a... how to put that?
This is not advocacy.
I don't care about changing the player's mind or anything.
I'm not an NGO. I don't have an agenda.
Nor do I want to make a political statement.
When I documented for this game,
I was so overwhelmed by all unfair and...
and terrible those situations were.
And I thought to myself, if we, in the situation we are in,
privileged situation we are in,
can have a game that can give us a glimpse
of what it is to go through those situations,
it is worth it.
We should try to do a game like that.
So that's the main reason why I wanted to make this game.
And that's why I decided to...
design the whole game around this idea that the player should feel the same way.
Thanks.
Welcome.
Hi.
So first of all, congrats on having the guts to make all those tough decisions,
going against the usual conventions of the game design.
But my question is about, so that audio log thing was very
powerful, very emotional.
When you built that, how did the community react to it?
And did their reaction affect how you guys ended up handling
that kind of thing, that emotional stuff?
Actually.
It didn't have any impact because we weren't in an open development,
so we didn't have any feedback on the game.
Why? Yes, we ran playtests.
But they were mostly functional playtests,
and we had some questions in the playtest
on the writing styles and the endings,
but we didn't really care about those.
We really wanted to be sure that people knew where to click,
but the story was ours.
And I think that it's important.
You know, I've had lots of discussions
with the people in the games industry in France
about, are there authors?
in video games and they say no, it's a common work, there's no authors, we're not filmmakers or anything, and I get that.
But I also think that some games should be the work of authors, and they should decide what they want to make and
regardless of what
the audience may or may not think. And if we make bad choices, then the game will be bad and it will be on us.
But you know, that's like every piece of art. It's our responsibility.
OK, thank you.
Hey, I actually have two really quick questions.
First, I wanted to say a really good presentation.
It was cool seeing how you treated Noor as a person.
And you're able to have her maybe decide not to text you,
which is really cool.
But my first question is, as a journalist,
do you see yourself having more stories, maybe
in a similar context, maybe not, in the future with more games
coming up with Pixel Hunt?
And my second question is, where'd
you get that shirt that's pretty rad?
Threadless.
OK, that's a good shirt.
OK, for the first question, I definitely
intend to make only reality-inspired games.
But that doesn't mean that it's only inspired by the news
or the real events.
Actually, my next project is about something
much more intimate.
what it means to be a person, and what is important for us.
So it won't be directly linked to something that happens in the world,
but I think we are all part of the world, so we are all something that happens in the world.
Cool, sounds great. Thank you.
You're welcome.
He asked what I wanted to ask already, so I just wanted to congratulate you on almost
making an entire room of grown-up people cry with that audio.
It's by Chloe Hollings, and she's a very, very talented voice actor.
And the French voice actor, Bayard Reyes, is like...
I cried while recording the audio with her.
It was amazing.
It was very sad, actually, but you know what I mean.
I do agree, that's a really red shirt.
Thank you.
I almost came with another one, so I'm pretty glad.
Thank you very much, it was a wonderful presentation.
I have a question for you.
Is the game actually waiting for you to make a decision, or it's like an ongoing process?
So basically, whether you interact with a character or whether you're not.
It's like a continuous journey.
Do you have to play the game for it to complete?
Yes, definitely.
And that's actually something that's a bit subtle.
And I'm very frustrated with my English right now
because I can't explain it the way
I would want it to be explained.
But the idea that you choosing an emoji over another
can completely change the whole story.
such a mundane thing as an emoji can have a little, little impact on Noor.
But that's just the thing that makes her drop or that helps her to keep going.
this is really important.
And lots of people have told us, but this is a linear game.
I don't have the impression,
I'm not under the impression of making any choice.
And they did not replay the game,
so they did not notice that they could have two playthrough
and never see one single scene in common.
And that's actually a compliment,
because I don't want them to have the feeling
that they have power and control over the story.
I want them to live the story and,
and just leave it in the moment as those guys in the real life do.
Yeah, I understand. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
So, thanks everybody. That's it.
I had something else I should tell you, but I don't remember what it is.
Oh yeah, don't forget to rate this talk.
Thank you very much.