Let's start with this conference, how we almost wrecked our second game aptly named The Wreck.
If my keyboard works, of course.
So I put the same t-shirt I had in 2018, so you can play the 25 million differences game, you know, between me then and me now.
My name is Florent Morin.
I'm from France.
I try to work on my accent, but it's not working.
I'm a former journalist.
I've created The Pixel Hunt, our tiny video game studio, in 2013, I think.
And in this studio, I'm a writer, game designer, producer, creative director, and I wear way too many hats.
We did a first game in 2017 that was called Bury Me, My Love, and as every game we do, it's a reality-inspired game, a game that tries to talk about real topics of the real life.
And today I'm here to tell you a little bit, a little story.
This story starts, I forgot to start my timer.
This story starts, oh, and I forgot to specify that I'm very bad at PowerPoint, so I'm sorry for the quality of the slides that are coming, yeah.
Bear with me.
The introduction of this story is, once upon a time, a tiny video game studio in France made a game called Bury Your Love.
So you may have not played it, but
By indie standards, it's been a huge success for us.
It sold over 100,000 copies over five years.
And when it was out, it got very, very positive feedback, both from the press, the players, of course, and also it got awards.
Actually, we were nominated here at GDC in 2018 for Best Mobile Game.
So yeah, it was really humbling, but it was also really great for us because we got the feeling that we were living a fairy tale, basically.
And so that's the first chapter of the story, the fairy tale.
We had a very successful game.
We had lots of desires to work on new games.
So the question that started appearing in our minds was, no what?
Well, the answer for us at the time seemed very simple.
No, let's use what we've learned to make another game.
Only, of course, when you have a first game that's successful,
Then you tend to grow ambitions, so let's do it bigger and better, of course.
That's easy, right?
We've done it right the first time, we will just do all the same things all over again and make it even better the second time.
But what had we learned in the process?
First, we know how to make a game.
So I'm not saying that the path to releasing Burying Your Love was a walk in the park.
Of course, there were problems, and of course, because game development is game development, there were issues.
But we shipped on time, and we also shipped on budget, and we shipped bug-free, although that last point is debatable.
But I would argue that most players were very satisfied with the game, so we were very satisfied.
And my belief at the time was that it's not that hard, really, to make video games.
Sweet, sweet summer child, yeah.
And then, just before releasing,
Bury My Love, I got in a car accident.
It was a pretty bad crash but luckily enough we weren't hurt.
Nobody had anything.
But it gave me an idea for a new game.
When you're a game designer, I think everything gives you ideas for new games.
But this one was interesting, at least to me.
I thought that making a game about being in a car accident and seeing your life flash before your eyes and remembering things from the past was actually an idea that was interesting.
Actually, it made me think of an old French movie called The Things of Life that does exactly that.
But in the form of a game, I had never seen something like that, so I thought it's a good fit for us because it's reality-inspired, it's not seen before, and my idea was to tell an intimate story and something quite intense about a character whose life would be turned literally upside down by what was happening to them in this car accident.
I was pretty convinced that it had to be a very good idea and a very easy one to implement.
As I said, sweet summer child.
The cool thing about being European, and that might be a little bit odd for people living in North America and pretty much all the rest of the world, is that we've got something pretty cool called public funding.
In Europe, it's actually really cool.
In Europe, you can apply to, for instance, a European Creative Media Europe prototype fund, and you can get some money to start working on your game.
That's what we did with the first draft of what The Wreck, so our next game is called The Wreck, would be.
And we got 50,000 euros to begin with.
The only rule when you have public funding is that you have to match that amount with private funds.
So we found ourselves with a budget of 100,000 euros to spend and I thought I was smart and I thought we could just make a vertical slice directly rather than work on a proof of concept prototype because 100,000 euros is a lot of money.
So I thought we were just going to get ahead of ourselves and directly start working on something that would both work as a prototype to show what we wanted to do as a game and also basically be the first part of that game.
We also knew how to build a team, so that's exactly what I started doing for the second project.
We hired excellent writers, Olivia Wood and George Lockett from the UK.
They are very talented and so I asked them to join us in this adventure.
We hired an art director who is very experienced, Alexandre Grieta, because I knew that he would be able to develop a visual universe that would be striking and interesting.
And then I got a little carried away.
We hired a dev, sound guys, another dev, a voiceover director, Sarah Elmaleh, who did an absolutely stellar job on the game.
And basically, we were pretty quickly a full-fledged team.
And so I was thinking that the project was shaping up.
I was really happy with the way things were turning.
And I was also very in love with every single member in my team, very in awe with all their talents.
So I led myself into thinking that such a talented team could not fail, of course.
And we also learned along the way with Barry Malove, we learned how to convince partners.
So Barry Malove was actually a co-production, so we learned how to just negotiate with people and convince them to invest in our projects.
And that's when we met Alexis Garavarian, who is the head of Column Knights.
Columnites, for those who don't know them, are an investment fund that they invest in projects, not in companies.
So if they like your game, they will give you some money to actually make the game, and then they are pretty hands-off.
But as you'll see, they still are very keen on providing feedback.
Alexei liked the project I pitched to him and also he really loved Bury My Love.
He had played it and really enjoyed it.
So he was really keen to see what we were going to do next with our next project.
He gathered with his board and together they decided that they will fund our game, but as we didn't have a prototype yet, they would only give us that much money so that we can actually make a prototype.
And then we would have a review after that pre-production phase so that they could evaluate the direction we were headed.
And that's when the fairy tale turned into something of a cautionary tale because, of course, Conan Knights are very experienced and, of course, they had concerns.
First, the new project, The Wreck, seemed quite far from Bury Me, My Love.
Bury Me, My Love is in 2D, it's text-based, it's basically a glorified choose-your-own-adventure book.
and the wreck was in 3D, it implied lots of gameplay, more gameplay mechanics.
So it was really different from the first project.
So of course, they warned us, they told us that there were challenges to overcome with this new project.
And also, they were slightly worried that that might be a little harder to tell a compelling story that way.
Because what they loved about Burmy, my love, is the storytelling of the game.
And of course, if you do a game that's more like a game, a little bit less like a story, it may be more complicated to tell the story in a very compelling way.
But even though they had all those warnings, they trusted us.
So they decided to give us a green light and we started working.
So we worked for roughly nine months, almost a year actually.
And the result was a 30 minutes vertical slice.
So something that would look not like a prototype, but like something that we could actually use in
the final game.
And that's how it worked.
You had a central crash scene.
So you would begin the game driving a car, and very quickly you would get into an accident.
And then the time would slow down, so the crash would happen very slowly, and the main character's bag would open up, and objects would start flying around, as you can see in the last pictures done right.
And you would use those items to access some of the character's memories.
So you would point at the objects and it would just like spark new memories in the character's mind and then suddenly you would be teletransported to the actual memories.
And we had three memories to explore in this version of the prototype.
And each memory came with a custom puzzle minigame.
So three different memories, three different mini-games to play with and to understand the rest of the story.
And we had an idea that we thought was a very good one at the time.
Spoiler, not so much.
We decided to go with two very different visual styles.
So what we wanted to have is to have a style in the car crash that was very realistic, because it was in the present, and we wanted it to feel like it's happening right now, right before your eyes.
So we tried to go with something that would look really realistic.
But then when you would access memories, the memories were VR painted because we thought that the brush strokes that you can actually see in VR painted models would convey the sense of weirdness and this dreamlike feeling that you have when you think about memories, basically.
So we thought that it was a really good idea to have this difference between those two styles and to be able to alternate between one and the other.
Basically,
everything is perfect.
Or maybe it's not.
And then that's when the story begins to change and evolve into a horror story.
Because we sent our prototype to Cologne Knights and it was time for honest feedback.
First,
They thought that the gameplay was clunky.
Sometimes you didn't know what you were supposed to do, and when you did, you could have trouble doing it.
Sometimes you would try to do what you were supposed to do and not achieve that.
So it was clunky.
You can say no big deal, that's what prototypes are for, you can still try to polish it and make it better, but that was not the only issue.
Another issue was that the art style, the very intelligent choice that we made, was not working very well, actually.
It was all over the place and another problem with that is it was very complicated to identify the wreck as a game because if you would put two screenshots of the same game next to each other, they would look nothing alike.
So it would be complicated to just communicate on the game and to just show this is what the wreck looks like because it doesn't look like one thing.
that didn't work very well.
And the third problem is that the writing was good, but not memorable.
Actually, the writing was really excellent.
Olivia and George did an awesome job writing the first draft of the prototype.
But the problem was that because you were troubled by the different art style, and because you had that gameplay that got in the way of really immersing yourself in the story, you wouldn't really
get the full intention of the story and you would not really feel engrossed by it.
So for a company that's supposed to make story-heavy games with stories that are really memorable, that really didn't work.
The fourth point that they gave us as a point of feedback was that the game felt experimental.
So at least that's good, right?
It's amazing to be experimental.
Some very cool IGF-nominated games are super experimental.
You can be proud of that.
But if you look at the full quote by Alexis Garavagnon, that's the rest of the quotes.
So, yeah, it was experimental, but not in a good way.
It felt like, he told me afterwards, because he didn't want to be too cruel at first, but he told me that it felt a little bit like a student project, but not a very masterful one.
So, you know, yeah.
Ouch.
So, we got this feedback, and I reacted in the only reasonable way you can react when you get such feedback.
Denial.
I decided that they must be wrong.
I was really sure that they didn't understand, they didn't get what we tried to achieve and so on and so forth.
And then I got back home and I started to work a little bit on that and to think a little bit about what makes good feedback.
And I came to the conclusion that good feedback has to first be kind and trustful.
People who give you feedback should always do that because they trust you and they have trust in your ability to actually use that feedback to make your game better.
And that was definitely the case with Cologne Knights because they really loved our first game and they really believed in our ability to make something great for our second title.
So yes, the Cologne Knights feedback ticked that first box.
It was kind and trustful.
It has to come from people who are experienced.
So that's not a golden rule, of course.
When you do playtests with the players, they are not necessarily super experienced in game making.
But when you gather feedback from people such as Alexey, who used to be the head of ID at Xbox,
and who has probably tested thousands of games, or Lindsey Rostal, who is the head of Timberline Games and who is part of the board at Cologne, part of the committee at Cologne, and all those other very experienced games people, you can't just overlook that feedback, and you have to pay attention to it.
It has to be specific and actionable.
It has to not be too personal, like you can't give feedback such as, I don't like it, it's not my test, I don't know why but it's not working for me.
Feedback has to be very specific and very precise in what it tells you about what's not working in your game.
And that's exactly what Columnite did for us.
They pointed out what didn't work specifically, and they didn't tell us how to fix it, but they told us it needed to be fixed, and that was really informative for us.
And that's the other point, right?
Feedback, good feedback aims at bettering the game instead of redesigning it for you.
Because when you ask feedback from game developers, they tend to put themselves in your shoes.
I would have done things completely different.
I invest myself and my creative process in your game, and I tell you how to completely redo it according to my views.
This is probably not the best feedback you can get.
The best feedback is probably the feedback that understands what you are trying to do,
and tries to give you the best advice to make it better, especially as you consider that failure is a step towards success and not something definitive that will never be overcome.
And that was the case.
They told us, you know what?
You failed with this prototype.
We still believe that you can do something that works.
So consider that as a step towards success.
So, yeah, I had to step out of denial, sadly, and I had to come up with a strategy to face that situation.
So I came up with a methodology that I'm going to explain to you now, and I call it the cry method.
Yeah, really efficient.
So the cry method is three points.
First, consider, then refocus, and then ultimately, hopefully, yield something better.
So consider what works.
So we had to do some forensics for our first prototype.
What worked in it?
Well, the story setting and the theme were interesting, definitely.
Like we had very good feedback on that point, making a game about a car crash with a woman who has trouble in her life and tries to understand what's happening.
This was a setting that was
not never seen before, but really interesting and really in the genre of Bury Me, My Love, so it was something that worked.
The fragmented narrative design was promising.
The idea that you should visit several memories as many puzzle pieces that you have to then put together to understand the full pictures, that worked too.
the memory exploration in and of itself is a cool concept.
The idea that you can have a memory but not understand it perfectly and then move over it and work on it and finally get some kind of epiphany that something you didn't get before now you understand was a good concept and something to keep.
The voiceover worked really well to foster immersion, even if in the first prototype, Sarah worked with very talented artists.
So that worked well, and that's definitely something we wanted to keep.
The art style, the art styles, I should have put a plural there, were nice.
The problem was not the art style per se.
The problem was not Alexandre Greta's work.
The problem was that we should be more coherent and pick one and stick with it.
And there is a lot of personality.
The game was unlike most games and definitely tried to explore something that is not that explored in the video game space.
So all those things worked and we wanted to keep them.
But then we needed to refocus on the things we are good at, as at the pixel lens.
So definitely we're not really good puzzle games designer, especially compared to all the other very excellent puzzle game designers there are in games.
I mean, some of the most amazing games are puzzle games.
And what we tried to do was to find, to give the player something to do in the memories, because we didn't trust in the rest of the proposition enough.
And that didn't work.
So we decided to get rid of it.
And we are not really good experimental game creators either.
As much as I would like to, I must acknowledge that we are better at telling grounded stories that are just good stories than trying to really experiment with video games as a medium.
But we're good at telling those reality-inspired stories.
We proved that with Bury My Love, also with other projects that we did before, and that's something that really we decided to focus on with the second prototype.
We're good at character-focused narration.
Like, all of Bury My Love is only dialogues between a couple, and it keeps you on the edge of your seat for a few hours.
So that's definitely something we need to keep exploring in our next project.
And we also are good at making games my mother can play.
She only played, actually, two video games.
Sure, she's my mother, but she's also very computer illiterate.
And that's one of the values that we wanted to carry with the Pixelant, making games that would be easily approachable by basically anyone, even people who would never define themselves as gamer.
So yes, those complicated puzzles, not a good idea.
Let's drop that.
So then it was time to yield something better.
Still not a prototype because the curse of, one of the many curses of narrative games is that it's fairly complicated to prototype a narrative game.
You can't gray box it and expect it to give the full experience.
But we would work on something shorter, simpler, and more focused.
It was important to just regroup on one or two main objectives that we wanted to reach with that new project.
I would strongly advise against the CRY method, because we had less money.
We had spent a lot of money on the first prototype, and colonnades were kind enough to give us some more, but not that much.
So we had to scale down.
Most of the second prototype was made with only two persons, Alexandre Grieta and myself.
and with an all or nothing approach.
Basically, we knew that it was our last chance to show that the project could actually exist, and that led us to very questionable work ethic.
We had long days of work.
We probably neglected our families in the process, and that's something I hopefully will never do again because it was really stupid, and I don't regret it because it had to be done at that point, but I really want to do everything possible to avoid that next time.
you
And all the more as to do that, you need an awesome partner.
Very few Indies have a second chance.
Actually, very few Indies have a first chance.
So it's really great to have found a partner that really believed in us and that was able to give us, extend the funds for us.
But yeah, it's really something that I felt extremely lucky to have had and that I would advise you not to count on.
So basically, the CRY method
It's trash.
You should never use it, only if you really, really, really have to.
So the result was a 20 minute proof of concept prototype that was really, really closer to what the final game actually is today.
It was a 3D visual novel with a straight forward flow.
The memory exploration mechanic was still there, but it was not a puzzle game mechanic anymore.
It was just about moving around the memory and finding clues so that you're able to understand what's happened.
And we had a consistent art direction, which was one of the most important part of the feedback that we got.
So this time everything was perfect.
Well, nothing is ever perfect, but everything was comfortable enough for us to jump into production.
And that's
what we got two years afterwards, the third chapter of the story, the coming of age story, the growth that we had.
So first, let me show you what the end result is through a little trailer for The Wreck.
All right, I'll tell you this story.
Is, is she going to die?
We just found out that mom might die.
Does that mean nothing to you?
Everything that happened to us, did end this.
There was a reason.
Why the hell do I feel so alone?
Do I really have to be so angry?
Do I really hate my mother?
Memory is weird.
You suddenly remember these moments without knowing why.
Until you realize it's trying to teach you something crucial.
No one can live like this.
Not really.
But we can change.
Everyone can change.
I have to leave it all behind.
It's funny that I only realized now that The Wreck is a game about being able to change, and that's probably the best asset we had during production, being able to change.
Because what happened is what I call the second game syndrome.
It's really hard to be very keen to live up to a first success.
Our success was not huge by any means, but it was already a big thing for us.
And we wanted to prove that we could do something else, something even better.
We didn't want to make a second text-based adventure because we felt like maybe we are up for something even better.
And we wanted to prove ourselves right.
But we were still relatively inexperienced.
I would say very inexperienced.
Just because you've shipped a game, or even in our case, several small games before that, doesn't mean you've got it all figured out.
I don't think anybody has it all figured out in video games anyway.
The risks with this second game syndrome are first being miserable because of course when you live in delusion and then suddenly the brick of reality crushes the
Strawberry pie of your illusions, you feel really bad.
And you also make the people you work with feel bad.
We had to scale down for the second prototype.
We had to just keep people insecure, although they were very talented and they worked really well.
And that's really something I'm not proud of.
And that's why I'm sharing it with you today.
Just so you can avoid those kind of experiences.
And just so you can avoid tanking your game.
Because Bury Me, My Love is a game that really could have not existed at all.
So I'm really happy that it does.
So what would be the solutions to that second game syndrome?
The first would be not to romanticize success, not to look novel gaze too much, and not to consider that you've got it all figured out because something worked for you.
But you have to remember what you enjoyed and what your players enjoyed in your first game.
Because that's how you grow.
And that's how you grow as a person, as a designer, as a creative director, sure.
But that's also how you grow as a studio, as a company.
And it's really important to have a
have a long-term view about how you are going to develop.
So how do you respect your studio's DNA?
How do you come with a second project that, yes, is not the same as the first one, but, yes, also is in the same style and the same things that worked for you the first time?
You should preciously try to work on them and take a fresh look at them and see how you can renew without necessarily changing everything.
Another point that is very important, of course, is to leave your ego behind.
I think I'm very guilty of that.
And my ego and my inexperience were the things that put the project at risk at some point.
And so, yes, you have to forget about that.
And you have to just think that you have to address it like it's your first game and like everything is to do all over again so that you don't fall in the same pitfalls that I
fell into.
And the last and most important advice would be to be ready to get some kicks in the butt.
Because I think it's the most important part, being aware that you can have flaws in your process and in your project.
And knowing that you know people that can actually help you and give you feedback that is sometimes harsh to hear, but also life-saving, is something you have to be ready for.
And that would be the best advice I have to give to you today.
Thanks a lot for coming.
I hope you'll like The Wreck, because in the end, that's probably our favorite game so far.
So yeah, I hope you'll like it.
Thank you.
If you have questions we still have a little bit of time I think because there's no session afterwards so you can ask them.
And again it's Friday so yeah I understand.
Since the Wreck was so challenging, did you find, I'm not sure if you started on your third game, how do you, you know, be energized to do it again?
Are you a little traumatized?
Like, oh no, we're going to do it again.
Yes, I am, but I'm also very happy with all the things that we've learned and I also know things that I will never do the same again.
So I'll be probably, hopefully, way more careful with the next game.
So I feel actually confident and I also know where to set the boundaries and where to set the limits and what to be very careful of.
which doesn't mean by any means that we won't make any mistake, probably we will again, but hopefully not the same mistake so we can learn and I can give another talk in five years in the next GDC.
Great, thank you.
Thank you.
Your introduction really reminded me of my own position in my company, like being a writer, designer, manager, director, creative director.
So it's good to see someone else doing so many things.
Too many hats.
It's tiring though, right?
Sorry?
It's tiring though.
Oh yeah, it's tiring.
And you can't do one thing just as well as you want to.
Yeah.
So I joined a company that was making their second game, and we're at the cry phase.
I mean, I'm going to come back and I'm going to say, OK, we have this method I saw in this talk because we just got the really harsh feedback, or not harsh feedback, but good, but...
Hard to hear feedback just this week from another colleague, right?
And is there any further advice, having feedback that requires you to fundamentally change your game?
And basically, how do I go and apply the CRY method?
Yes, I think feedback that requires you to fundamentally change your game is not what I would call good feedback, because you can't ask that from a game dev, you know.
They have an idea, they have a vision, and they want to make a specific kind of game.
So coming to them and telling them you have to do something completely different is as good a feedback as saying you have to stop it completely and start again a new project, which can be a good idea sometimes.
But it has to come from the devs,
draw their own conclusions.
So that's why I would say that you you should probably not listen to that feedback too much but you should try to find if there is feedback that can actually keep the core idea of your game and make it way better than it currently is.
So never disregard feedback but
If you want to keep your core ID, if you still believe in it, if you still believe it's going to work, that's not the feedback you're looking for.
You're more looking for feedback that can specifically apply to points in your game that you should change, I would say.
I see.
We do agree with the feedback though, so it's a long story, it's complicated.
Thank you so much for the talk.
Maybe we can exchange cards later.
Yeah, sure.
Okay, thanks a lot and have a good rest of GDC.