Thank you all for getting up early this morning,
or alternatively, not having gone to bed yet.
Feel free to keep your cell phones on ring
so that when they go off, it'll wake people up.
This is a talk a bit different to my usual talks.
However, I do tell you things that I've never,
I haven't actually told anybody else before.
about the origins of mud.
So you're getting some historical data here.
And 50 years from now, interviewers
looking to rake up dirt on the origins of these virtual worlds
will come to you and say, what did he say at that conference?
And you'll say, I don't know.
I was asleep.
Right.
So the reason that I've been asked to talk here
is because I co-wrote.
the very first virtual world, MUD.
Almost all today's massively multiplayer online role-playing games
descend directly from MUD, but that isn't actually relevant.
What's relevant is that we hadn't ever played one before.
So, it wasn't that...
We were first that was important, it was just the fact that when we wrote it we were unaware of any others.
We weren't the only people in this position, these things, we were always going to get them,
they'd been invented many times, about six or seven times independently,
and we would have got them anyway, whether Roy or I had done it, somebody else would,
and perhaps other people did do it.
But the important thing from the point of view of this talk is that when we did it,
we didn't have anything else to base it on.
which means we had to establish some principles, some guidelines.
We had to form some views on what it was we were making and why we were making it.
Because it wasn't just a simple case of, well, let's take that one there and make it better.
Because there was nothing to take to make better.
And that's why...
talking about here may be of interest because you get to find out why some of the things
that are in MMOs are in MMOs.
I hope you've all picked up your future antiques.
These are 25 years old, so older than some of the people in the audience.
Yeah, they've all got to go, so if you need them for, I don't know, jimmying open Yale
locks or something, just take as many as you want.
Now, this isn't meant to be a history lesson.
I'm not going to be just standing up here and telling you this happened and this happened
and this happened as historical chronological facts because that's not interesting.
You want to know why it happened.
There are some other things which typically when you're talking about historical things,
areas I could go into, but I'm not going to go into them.
Like why doesn't my zapper work?
So I won't be talking about how large our computers were.
You know, they would fit in this room.
Wong would fit in this room.
But that's not really relevant, you know,
the weakness of the computers.
It'll get mentioned once a bit later, but that's about it.
I won't be telling you how great text is over graphics,
because that's an argument that I've won many times
and still lost.
Thank you.
I won't be telling you how great permadeath is.
But hey, because God uses it, it can't be bad.
I won't be telling you how great it is when you've got customer
service of 10 customers per one customer service person.
That's really good to have.
You can really keep your players in line.
Except nowadays, you've got to pay these people.
So it's a bit more expensive, a bit harder.
So I won't be going into any kind of detail
about how we used to manage the games back then.
And I won't be trying to tell you how we extracted money
from them and what legal systems we used or rather didn't care
about.
So none of this, which might be of historical use to some people
to you to find out how do things work in the old days,
because of intellectual curiosity.
I'm not going to be talking about that so much.
Instead, what I'm going to be.
aiming at is discussing if I am to create a world, which is what Roy Chubshaw and I
wanted to do, how shall it be, what's the world going to be like, and why? That's the
question that I'm going to be answering. Oh, this is a picture of a snowman standing in
a furnace in World of Warcraft. Right.
When Roy Chupchell started to work on Mudd,
his main, the main thing that interested him
was the kind of the machinery.
It was like building one of those,
what do you call them out here?
Those machines where you turn the crank
and all these different things happen,
Rube something or other.
Rube Goldberg, okay, yeah,
we don't call him that in Britain.
We call him after our particular same guy.
who are equivalent, but I don't remember his name either.
So Roy was kind of like, I want to build this intricate machine
and then set it going and, whoa, look, it works.
But also, he was interested in making
a world that was separate from and hopefully superior
to reality.
You see, when you're 17, 18, 19, you
don't figure that it's going to take.
50 years to make one of those.
You just think, well, I can see how to do that.
Yeah, yeah, I'll start.
From my point of view, I was more interested
in the world creation side.
I wanted to build.
It was the world making that was my interesting thing.
However, I also had a fascination with systems.
Roy was mainly, he wanted to make a machine that worked so he could get this world working.
I wanted this world working, but I kind of liked making the machinery that would work
it.
So we sort of balanced quite well.
Roy could have done the other stuff, but it was just that's where his interests mainly
lie and I could have done the other stuff, but that's where my interests mainly lie,
but we both did both things.
So from both these points of view.
the point of view of wanting a machine which was operating a world so that you, when you
entered the world, you felt you were in it.
And from the point of view of creating a world that was separate from the real world, so
it didn't feel like the real world, it felt like a different world, it was important for
both of us that the players would feel that they were part of that world, that when they
visited it, they were in it.
the underlying systems were all wrong, then they wouldn't feel like they were in the world,
and then that wouldn't validate it. But if they felt it was right and it was natural
and it was working how it should be, then that would validate it.
Likewise, if we wanted people to visit a world that was not the real world, it should actually
be persuasive enough that they would think, yeah, this is kind of good,
this is a real world in its own terms, you know, just like
when you read a book and you're immersed in a book and you're transported off to
Middle Earth.
It was like that sort of idea.
So, nowadays it's called immersion.
We just wanted, we didn't have a word for it back then,
we just wanted you to believe you were a part of the world.
Because then, once you've got that,
then it shows that your programming is working.
If you want to see, if I put the marble here,
all the dominoes and everything collapses
and it all goes out in this wonderful spread,
and it works, well that kind of makes you feel good about your programming.
but it also meant that we could give people what the thing was about, which was pretty well liberty.
We wanted people to be able to escape the confines of the real world,
to try on new identities, to be new, not so much new people,
but to try and find out the people they really were.
I've explained this before in the past, where we had...
Computing department, 1978, England, not a lot of girls around.
Actually, yeah, I was going to say, after 30 years and it went in different.
I managed to marry one of the two girls, two years below me.
So there's not a lot of girls around, not a lot of social graces, everybody sort of
tries not to interact with the rest of the student body, because if you speak to a girl . . . . . . . . . . . . .
and you're
basically a nerd or a geek or whatever, I'm geek son of nerd
and it doesn't really matter what you look like, how charming you are
they're going to say, alright, you see this, this is your heart.
So it's not really, you know, they wouldn't ever go because they're completely outgunned.
But if you've got a virtual world, then people can go in there and they can practice their social graces,
not like girls, but just actually practice being social to people,
helping each other, talking, chatting,
which you wouldn't really want to do normally because,
well, you know, people might talk.
So.
the worlds were created, and that was kind of the thing, we wanted to make a world which was separate from the real world.
Now when Roy first started working on MUD, the first thing he wanted to do was to make sure the technology worked, that he could actually have the mechanism that underpinned it all.
And that took him about an hour, programming in machine code, macro ten assembler.
Yeah, I can send messages from one player to another player.
via a mechanism which I could also use for storing a shared world. Okay, there you go.
Roy's a really fast programmer. The next thing he decided to do was to implement the physics
of the world. He didn't know what the world was going to look like at this point. He was
just building the physics, building the mechanisms that underpinned what the world would do.
That took him about a month before he started hitting walls and he couldn't do things on
Maybe I shouldn't break it down to molecule level of chemistry.
Maybe I should just have like liquid.
Now, supposing today somebody came along and said, hi, look.
I've just won the lottery.
Here's $30 million.
You can go off and make your own MMO.
I don't care if it sucks.
I don't care if anybody plays it.
Just go make one and have fun.
Well, you might think, well, what shall I make it?
Shall I make it like a, hey, I've got an idea.
I could make it like a fantasy world.
You might think of what genre it was going to be.
You might think, oh, OK, right, it's going to be this guy.
All right.
And you sit down and maybe you draw a map just so that, oh,
yeah, I can have the good guys over here and the bad guys
over here and this big block in the middle for my future
expansions.
But you wouldn't think what's the physics going to be like.
But this is actually premature.
That's essentially a marketing point.
what kind of game would I like to play?
But you're not making a game that you're...
If you're a game developer,
you don't make games that you want to play.
You make games that you want to develop.
Because if you want to play them, you're a player.
Developer, you're a developer.
And I get prospective students come to me,
and I interview them.
One of the questions I ask them is,
why do you want to study computer game design?
And they say, well, ever since I was a small child...
I've always been fascinated with computer games.
I love playing computer games.
Okay, so, do you like beer?
Or, why aren't you doing a degree in brewing?
Because...
Brewing is nothing to do with drinking beer.
It's to do with making beer.
Developing computer games isn't to do with playing games.
It's to do with developing the game.
Um...
So...
If you start thinking like this, you're thinking like, what are my players doing?
You're kind of defining the people who are going to play it.
But that's kind of premature because you're already falling into a mindset of
what kind of people are going to play, not what are the tools in my toolbox that I could enable.
Sometimes when you see a tool, it can help you think of some other group that you haven't thought of.
So if you start by developing the...
thinking about the world, then you're already making assumptions about what it's possible
to implement. If you start by working on the physics, what can we implement, then that
could go beyond what you supposed to be possible. So if you start writing your game and you're
basing it on the previous game that you liked really, but except that 10% that was no good
that sucked and you want to...
write your new one that's the same except with 10% better that doesn't suck.
Well, that's a nice evolutionary approach, but
you might be missing some things that you think aren't possible to implement
because the previous person didn't implement them.
But maybe they didn't implement them because the previous person to them didn't implement them.
And maybe they're perfectly possible to implement, you just haven't really thought of it.
You're just following a paradigm.
But if you don't have a paradigm, like Roy and I didn't...
you have to think about these things from scratch.
So Roy was thinking, what can I implement?
And then knowing what I can implement,
what can I use it to implement?
Roy and I figured that there was another good reason
for trying to put physics and other basic science
into virtual worlds.
This is news to many people in this part of the world, but there's this wacky theory called
evolution where humans have, so the story goes, developed over millennia.
The way they are is pretty much because if they hadn't been like that 40,000 years ago,
they would have been eaten by bears.
One of the things that the human brain has got through evolution
is an ability to understand the world and process it in an instant.
I can look out here and I can see people
because my brain is taking all your images and converting them into people in my head.
I can't stop it, I just see it because it's being done automatically for me.
But if I was to look out here and I think,
what the hell, that's a Dalek, that's not a person, that's actually quite bad.
that would be something I would notice because it's different to what my brain is doing automatically for me the whole time.
If I look down here I can see that I'm above the ground.
But I don't have to think about it, I just see it because I've got stereoscopic vision
and all these millions of processes are going around in the back of my head and saying,
you know, that's kind of a bit further away than that.
So the brain will do all these things for you.
But when there's a dissonance, when there's something different between...
what you see and what happens, then the brain notices,
and, well, that's not all right.
And that's the point at which either immersion is broken
or you require an explanation.
So what we wanted, when we were designing MUD,
we wanted people to believe that they were in the world.
Therefore, we should put as few barriers.
to them to persuade them that they weren't in the world as possible.
If you're playing and things keep happening that don't make sense, you will notice it
and it will interrupt and too much of that and you will think, well, I'm not actually
in a world, I'm just looking at this series of inputs which are not in any way natural,
they're all different.
Because of that, we tried to make the world appear to be as realistic as we could.
So things should happen like you'd expect them to happen.
And when they didn't, that's where people should think that there was a reason for it.
So if you go into a world and I close a door and a window opens.
Well, hold on, I tried to close a door and a window opened.
Now, either that's a bug.
Oh, did I type door?
Oops, that should have been.
window back in the code, I'll just change that. Or, you say,
oh, there must be some kind of connection between the door and
the window. Maybe if I shut the door and the window opens, that
means I can get out of the window and then people try to
get in. They would get in and the window would shut and they
wouldn't know where I'd gone. Ah, yeah. But, so you can have
reasons for things, but you've always got to have an
explanation for them. If there's no explanation, then either
it's a bug or they shouldn't notice it at all.
So, one of the, the rule that we sort of had was,
if you haven't got a reason not to conform to reality,
conform to reality.
So if there's no reason not to do something,
not to do something the same way that real life does it,
well, do it the same way real life does it.
Because that way, people aren't constantly being
challenged to suspend their disbelief in this world.
if their brain is saying, yeah, that's how it should happen,
that's how it should happen, that's how it should happen,
it's much easier to become immersed.
And this was a theory.
Roy and I actually discussed this, and that's why we did it.
Well, that's why we made it more simulationary
than you might do today.
Conform, when I say here, it's not actually in great detail.
So for us, it's things like.
If you're carrying an icicle, well, it's kind of going to melt after a while.
Maybe if you stay in a cold area, it won't melt.
But if you go into a desert, well, it's going to melt, isn't it?
Because it's ice.
Why would anybody carry ice around and it not melt?
However, we wouldn't go to the level of Q equals HA T2 minus T1.
That's only just part of the equation.
You've actually got to...
figure out the reduced surface area due to the melting ice and then you've got to integrate
it over time. It's kind of tricky, but most people don't do that sort of thing in their
head. To a player, if you are playing a game and you've got an icicle and it doesn't melt,
well that doesn't make sense. Why didn't it melt? Is it like a magic icicle? Well in that
case, can I do things with it? Zap! And yet, in World of Warcraft, I've got a, my warlock
is carrying around the...
same glass of milk in her backpack that she's had for four years.
That should be some kind of living cheese by now.
Plays don't count as dirty nudges, but it should make sense.
Why hasn't it gone horrible?
And there are actually, you know, game play opportunities you can do with things like
if you've got ice melting.
So, when I talk about physics, it's not down at the collision detection, billiard ball
level, it's this kind of thing.
Light cannot pass through a closed wooden door.
If I'm in a room and there's no light in the room, there's light outside, I shut the door,
I can't see.
That's the kind of thing.
Of course, most MMOs don't have doors these days.
You walk into an inn in Goldshire and, hey, no doors.
But who stole all the doors?
Is there like a stack of doors somewhere?
Um, what happens when you pour four noggins of water
into a glass that holds three noggins?
You could do this in mud.
Got a glass here that holds three pints.
Jug here holds four pints.
Pour it into there.
You end up with a glass of three pints and a jug of one pint.
Yeah.
How many MMOs can do that today? Why can't they do it?
Plate armour doesn't float.
Yeah. I know that
these special carbon fibres where they incorporate
bubbles into the plate armour. Barbarossa was
like a middle European
leader who, on the Crusades...
got really hot and decided to go for a swim in a stream.
He was so desperate that he didn't take his armor off.
And he never came out.
So when I talk about physics or anything like this,
what I'm basically saying is that it's
what an uninformed player would regard
should happen without evidence otherwise.
Be fine.
hit you with a sword, what should happen is your head should fall off.
What would happen is that you would get a nasty nick and then I would be eating that sword.
But that's... it's just what should happen.
And if things happen as they should happen, that means you don't have to concentrate on believing the world.
It's just flowing there.
And the more it seems to be real because everything's behaving how it should do,
then the more inclined you are to believe that it really is real.
Now, this was really useful.
I mean, in a text world, there's not a lot of pictures to persuade you that this is what's
going on, and people really did get very immersed in just this simple world.
However, although the principle of mimicking reality was carried forward, the reason for
it wasn't.
You know, if people played MUD, thought, well, that's kind of cool, but I could do better.
and so they went off on their own and some of them were better and some of them, or I
should say most of them were drivel, but, you know, that's the way it works, evolution,
some of them work, some of them don't.
But if you don't know why something's there, then that means that you're more inclined
for operational reasons or for the design reasons of your own to ignore it.
If you do know why it's there, then you're making a more informed decision.
And over time, people have kind of left this
simulationary aspect behind, to the extent where
it's not so much they're simulating reality,
they're simulating the previous MMO that they played.
These are some of the things which are natural
in today's MMOs, which would have...
they would have been mocked by the players of the 1980s.
I mean, they would have actually pointed at us,
what do you expect to play for me with this in it?
If the goblin was carrying a sword, why was it hitting me with a stick?
It's got a sword. You kill it, it's got a sword.
What kind of dumb goblin? I wonder if people kill them.
They carry swords and they think they're for lighting cigars.
This is one of my favorites from Lord of the Rings Online.
I can dye armor.
Okay, just a moment.
Okay, so I've got plate mail and I can dye it.
I'm like, dye doesn't, doesn't that kind of maybe need some absorptive quality on the part of what you're dyeing?
But hey, okay. But I can't paint it.
So, you know, I've got this paint, I've just made this paint, worked at my crafting, I can make the paint,
but I can't paint my armour. I can only dye it.
Even this plate armour, it's like metal, you should be able to paint metal, surely.
Ah, but you can paint the walls of your house.
That's what it's for. You go into your house and you can paint the walls and think, oh my God.
they made it pink.
That's because they want me to level up my
paint making so that I can get some decent colour
instead of a pink wall.
But I can't paint any other walls.
It's like wall paint.
It's special paint that only works on the walls of my house.
Wow.
So, it just doesn't make sense.
And yet people are saying, oh, yeah, this is...
I think I kind of carried through by the visual aspect, but that's only really, can only really
take you so far. I can build a snowman in a fire and neither is affected. Yeah. You
try that in real life. You build a snowman in a fire and see whether the snowman or the
fire is, one of them is going to lose. But in World of Warcraft, no, it's just a kind
of, oh, look at the light it throws on the fire. It's magic fire and magic snow and magic
men.
I should do another one.
How come here I am, killing something, and if I step two yards that way, they'll notice,
but here, ha, I can see them, and I'm slashing away and I'm fireballs, boom, boom, boom.
But so long as those fireballs don't actually warm the people that are in the distance,
I can do it.
Aren't I stupid?
Well, yeah, really, I mean, you walk into a dungeon, armor clattering.
then there's gonna be traps set up.
There's gonna be all sorts of things happening.
And you aren't gonna be attacked by one guy
while the other one's saying,
okay, well I'll just see how this is going.
Oh God, they killed him.
Well, I guess I'll step up to the plate.
You guys stay back there.
Hmm.
This would just not make sense in a text.
I mean, we'd get things like,
okay, so you're being attacked by a goat
and in the same room there's this, like, thief guy
and, well.
maybe he would attack you if the goat was doing really well,
he might join in on the goat side,
but on the other hand, if the goat was looking like it was going to be defeated by you,
he might leave because he doesn't want to be the next in line.
I mean, that's the kind of little, you know, tiny little decisions that they would make,
but you don't get that these days, any of it.
It's not that these are challenging, they just haven't been considered.
I'll give you an example.
This is something from MUD2 rather than MUD1.
So this would be about 8T7, something like that.
We have these two things, a baton and a bow.
OK, they're basically just these pointers.
And if the bow's over there and I wave the baton,
it teleports me to the bow, drops the baton to the floor.
If I pick up the bow and I wave the bow,
it teleports me to the baton, and the bow drops to the floor.
So just a little teleport thing so people
can get around quicker.
the bow, say, into a well.
It would fall down the well.
Anybody who happened to be in the well could see it going past
and might be able to grab it.
It landed in the bottom where there's a river.
And it was picked up by the river, carried away
through an underground crevice that you couldn't really get through
for humans. There's only things like small than people could get through.
And then it would get to this grate where it would lodge.
And there there was a secret room.
So if you drop the bow in there and it would fall down, float down the river, get caught in it,
you could wave the bat and it would teleport you to where the bow was.
You pick up the bow, you're in this room that no one else can get to.
You can store all your stuff there, you can do whatever you like there.
You can be nasty to people and you're fleeing from a fight and then teleport there and they can't catch you.
So it was really kind of cool.
So one player did all this, realised he was safe from attack
because there was no other way into the room.
And he was right, there was no other way into the room.
MUD2 also had a keg of gunpowder.
Because we had this wall and there was this cannon facing it
and there was all this little puzzly thing where you had to go and get the gunpowder from a really hard place
and stick it in the keg, and you had to go and get this cannonball and stick it in
and then you had to set fire to it with something that wasn't too hot
because that would set the gunpowder off, but just something hot enough to set it off
and it would bang and you'd go in and get a bunch of points.
So he had this gunpowder. That's what it was for, but because it was gunpowder, any fire next to it, it would go boom.
So another player took the gunpowder, put it in a coracle, one of those little hide things that Iron Age people used to go on rivers.
Put the gunpowder in the coracle, set fire to the coracle, dropped it down the well.
The coracle goes down, lands in the water, doesn't get put out yet because the coracle is still burning.
floats down, catches to the end where it's stuck on the grate.
This guy's asleep in his safe room.
At that point, the fire spreads to the gunpowder.
Boom, guy is killed.
Ha ha ha.
Serves you right for thinking you were safe.
Now, OK, that's a bit of emergent behavior.
But that would work on a machine which
had 50 players on 33 megahertz.
In other words, that would probably work on this.
my remote control. So, it's not sophisticated. This isn't hard to implement. Why don't we
see any of it? One thing is saying, well, this is just too hard for the players to understand.
No, no, what's hard is if you're explaining why, when you drop something in a well, it
doesn't actually fall down the well. That's hard.
The default is it should fall down the well, and the rivers should flow.
And that when you get into a river and you've got a backpack full of biscuits,
when you get to the other side you've got a backpack full of biscuit mush.
And that makes sense.
But it doesn't make sense for it not to have any of these effects.
Another argument against it is it leaves the door wide open to exploits.
And it can happen.
But it only happens when you don't have a consistent physics
to do it, when you don't handle things consistently.
If it's always the case that the gunpowder will explode
when it gets too hot, then you don't get the kind of exploits
that you would do if it only explodes
under certain very specific conditions,
like it will only explode if it's in a cannon
or in a fire spread.
It's hard to explain without going into details,
but essentially, if you arrange your objects
in a class hierarchy with multiple parents,
which is probably another talk, then you
get a lot of this functionality for free.
So you only have to account for exploits at a high level,
like explosive objects.
And then it's accounted for everything
which could possibly explode.
So you can cover.
this kind of thing, but it's when you've got, this all works for the gunpowder, but it doesn't
work for the sticks of dynamite. That's when you get the exploit. There are, however, more
legitimate reasons not to put this kind of thing in. One of them is it can annoy players.
So my World of Warcraft character has, well, one of them has 10,000 gold pieces. Well,
how much is a gold piece weigh?
British sovereign weighs about just under 8 grams.
So if I've got 10,000, that's 80 kilograms,
or in American, 176 pounds, or in English, 12 stone,
which is like what I weighed about 20 years ago.
So here's my life, some mage walking around
carrying a fully grown man on her back.
Now, yeah, you can see how that might be, okay.
Maybe we shouldn't simulate that area because that would really annoy the players.
But on the other hand, it could actually add some gameplay reasons.
The deeper the physics, the more you're able to write more subtle puzzles.
So, all that thing I was saying, you simulate reality in the absence of a reason not to.
Well, exasperating the players is a reason not to.
This is why in the movies...
whenever you see somebody going to the lavatory,
you know something bad's gonna happen.
Because no one would ever show you going to the lavatory
in a, you know, what's the American word for lavatory?
Restroom.
No one would show you going to the restroom in a movie
because we don't really want to know
about the personal habits of movie star characters,
but if they are going there, you think,
oh wow, that dinosaur's gonna so stomp on that outhouse.
So, it's like that in MMO.
In real life, everybody has to visit the bathroom every once in a while,
unless they're British royalty, when they get somebody to remove it using a hose.
The story of Princess Diana, correct?
Or if you're in Star Trek, where you get it beamed out of you.
So there's...
But it's not really anything to do with the game.
You're simulating for no purpose.
So you can just abstract that out.
Doesn't really serve a purpose, I'll keep it out.
People aren't going to notice so much,
but occasionally they might.
Ah, there's a fire, I've got to put the fire out.
Whoa, I don't have anything to put the fire out with.
Although, hold on, I do remember drinking a bottle of water about half an hour ago.
I'm carrying enough water inside me to put the fire out.
Therefore, I should put the fire out using natural means.
You could do that in mud.
You could actually piss on the fire and it would put it out.
Unless you were a female character.
We did take...
There were more than cosmetic differences between male and female characters
for some things.
The frog wouldn't turn into a prince if a male kissed him.
The line being,
he's a prince, not a queen.
Which was put in there because the gay players asked me to,
believe it or not.
So yeah, taking things out because it annoys the player is one thing, but it can squander
game play opportunities, you can get things out of the way.
Today, the modern virtual worlds, I'm assured by Google, translate that rectum universitas
is virtual world, I don't speak Latin and I don't see why anybody else should.
It's really quite superficial today as well.
Why are they so superficial?
You can do it a lot more detail and get more out of it.
This lack of understanding of immersion has now extended beyond the physics.
There are some things that people do just for a laugh, which break immersion.
So you go into the bank in Stormwind and the characters, this is...
they've got the names Olivia, Newton and John.
Hey, that's like Olivia, Newton, John out of Greece.
Yeah, yeah, well what's that got to do with World of Warcraft?
You just spoiled my view of...
that I'm in a fantasy world.
Just because you couldn't actually think of any decent names.
So...
Is it really?
actually all that bad, you know, just a few jokes, you know,
tells people it's a safe space to go and this is where you can be,
hang out rather than play the game. Well, there are arguments for that,
but the point is, you have to think about it first.
If you didn't think, should I stick with names which are comical,
or should I go with names which are more immersion-making?
If you didn't think it, then, well, you've made a mistake.
I'm not saying you shouldn't have people with these kind of names if you want to,
but you should know the consequences of it and decide,
OK, on the whole, making Stormwind feel safe and breezy and a place where you can hang out with your friends,
because it's kind of a real world interface for WoW, yeah, that would be a reason to do it.
But if you don't think about it beforehand, and you just do it because,
well, people seem to like a joke, well, you're missing something.
It's just a superficial level.
This is also something that people from the text mundane would be horrified with.
Lotterings online. I typed salute. What does it say?
It doesn't say your character salutes. No.
It says you salute smartly.
No, I didn't. My salute was like this.
It wasn't smart at all. It was sarcastic or offensive or Hitler.
But it says I salute smartly.
But I didn't say I wanted to salute smartly.
You're saying I saluted smartly.
I didn't salute smartly at all.
I saluted pathetically or ironically
or over-enthusiastically.
I could have done all these things, but no, no.
It just says I do it smartly.
Why add that stupid extra adverb?
Do you want your players to be immersed or not?
If you don't want them to be immersed,
that's fair enough.
You don't have to.
If you do want them to be immersed...
then you should do some of the more simulationary stuff.
But the thing is, you should actually ask yourself,
do you want them to be immersed?
And then on the basis of that, make your decisions.
Oh, here we go.
This is Dagna the Dwarf out of Dragon Age Origins.
She's this little perky, preppy, very enthusiastic, eager-to-please character.
Why is she in...
Ah, irritating!
Um...
Okay, so...
Once Roy had done all the physics, it came to me to do the world.
We call it content now.
What setting was I going to give it?
There was no paradigm before and I could have chosen anything.
And I did look at multiple settings.
I wanted something that was of Earth because I wanted people...
I didn't want it to be so crazy that people couldn't understand what was going on.
I wanted it to be immersive.
So it had to be of Earth but not Earth.
So it had to be in some ways familiar so people felt they knew what it was like, but unfamiliar in its familiarity.
So everybody kind of knows what the Wild West is like, but if you go to the Wild West you don't know if it's the kind of Wild West where all the skoom arms are armed,
or if it's the kind of Wild West where all the cattle are vampiric, or what.
But you do know some things about the Wild West.
I decided to root it in English folklore.
These days, this is kind of called fantasy.
It wasn't back then.
There were very few fantasy things around.
As far as I was concerned, it was English folklore I was
using, dragons and things like that.
I experimented with this in a board game that I'd made about
five years earlier.
So I did know the basic settings.
I'd made some changes to the board game.
putting some Dungeons and Dragons kind of characters,
and that hadn't worked out.
It didn't really feel as if it was as arcane
as I wanted it to, so I'd take me out.
So, it was the same here.
I wanted the kind of the more pure form.
I wanted to make people think they knew enough
about the world that they felt that they could survive in it,
but disquieted enough that, well, you know,
I've read these stories.
Actually a lot of it was Germanic folklore.
But I've read these stories where the goats are going to come out and attack me.
I don't know if this is a friendly goat or not.
It wasn't friendly. It was mad.
So I didn't use any of the other things.
I'd read Tolkien.
What Tolkien gave was a notion that you can create a self-consistent world,
but I didn't put any orcs in the mud.
I'd read Robert E. Howard, because I was a boy.
I didn't put any orcs in the mud.
I'd played Dungeons and Dragons, but I didn't use any of those things.
I just went for English folklore.
But that wasn't the only thing I could have used.
I thought of several things I could have used.
Here are some of the other things that were on my short list of what I could have done.
The Three Musketeers, Era France.
I played a game called En Garde, and Three Musketeers, Era France, is really fun.
if you're a male. It's not so much fun if you're a female, because there weren't actually all that many female musketeers.
And on the basis that we thought female characters should, female players should at least maybe have the option of playing a female character,
and they don't want to just be playing like mistresses. So we rejected that.
But it was on the shortlist. Scheherazade's 1001 Nights. That is an excellent area.
Of course it wasn't so excellent in 2000 or whenever it was when the Twin Towers were hit,
but prior to that it was certainly excellent and it will be excellent again.
Because that is such a rich culture, everybody across the world knows about the Arabian Nights
and it's got that kind of magical otherworldliness about it that I really wanted.
That would have really worked well.
Another idea I had was an escape from a prisoner of war camp thing
where you're trapped in a...
in like Kovitz castle and you're trying to escape.
That was kind of a bit depressing though.
It wasn't when you escaped but then you couldn't play anymore because you'd escaped.
And this would be a surprise, the Camelot of Arthurian legend.
That was also on my list of things because I quite like the symbolism in that.
But eventually I went for the English mythology.
And the reason I did that was because it's a continuum.
The mythology, it just goes back and back and back and back
and back in time.
It's not a fixed point.
The others are all fixed points in time.
But with a continuum, you can go back.
And what that allowed me to do was to, I could use time as a
metaphor for menace.
See, when you come across something in today's MMOs,
it's like, oh wow, this is a zone rated 31 to 35.
I'm rated 28.
It's going to be a bit tough.
But back then, we did have what would be equivalent of zones,
but the way to flag it was, that I chose, was using time.
So if it came from like the 1930s,
which was about as late as we got,
then it was gonna be pretty well safe.
You know, a bit different, but you kind of understand,
you know, it's got gramophones and everything.
But if it comes from the 1800s,
a broken down tin mine, well, that's a bit more dangerous.
And if it comes from Neolithic times, you know,
stone circles, then you are going to die.
And I use it as a metaphor for many.
Now, how many designers today have the luxury of using metaphor?
Well, you all do, you just don't.
Why not? Why are you designing games?
Um, okay, so I'm not going to gloat at your misfortune for not having my genre choice.
Um, I'm trying to point out you still have the choice.
You can still do what these things that I'm telling you about.
You just don't have to just take it as a day job.
Why are you creating MMOs?
If you want to make, do it for making money, well, why aren't you working in a bank?
My wife works for a bank. She gets three times as much money as me.
If you're doing it because you like playing the games, well, that's back to the brewing
argument there, you know, playing isn't the same as developing.
Besides, you won't be developing the games, you'll be developing the tools that somebody
else will be using to code the back end of a horse.
You actually developing the game, only a few people get to do that.
If you want to do it because you want to bring joy and spread and help the world, well...
go work on a charity.
You know, they pay more as well, even though they're charities,
especially the animal charities.
So why are you doing it? Well, you're doing it because
somehow you want to express something.
And yet, people don't express things,
even though they've got the tools right there before them.
I chose fantasy because of what it
delivered in terms of resonance,
very similar to the real world, and dissonance.
Whoa, this bit isn't the same.
This is important. This is something I have to think about.
That's why I chose what you'd now call fantasy.
But today people don't choose fantasy for that at all.
They choose it because it's a well understood trope
and it delivers solid, knowledgeable things.
You just know what's going to happen.
And in today's world, if you're being progressive,
that means that your dwarves aren't drunkards
who speak with a Scottish accent.
So in Dragon Age, Dagner, she's...
this little perky speech with an American accent.
It's great in Dragon Age.
All the dwarfs speak with American accents,
and all the humans speak with English accents, which
makes them sound like Hollywood villains,
but not to an English player.
Yeah, it's great.
And you notice that in Dragon Age.
Wow, these are dwarfs, but they're not stereotypical Cossack
dancing drunkards.
And the elves don't hug a tree after breakfast.
They're actually rounded individuals.
It's been thought through.
I love Dragon Age.
Played it all the way through, and then played it all the way through again.
Because I have no life.
LAUGHTER
We didn't have dwarves in mud.
We had dwarfs.
As in Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs.
Not Snow White and the Seven Dwarves.
Many players today don't even know that the word dwarf,
when pluralized, means the same thing.
It's an S on the end, not a V-E-S, because Tolkien couldn't spell.
If you're inventive in today's MMOs, then it's saying, well, look, we've got these new character races.
Races, that actually sounds pretty bad.
Isn't that kind of racist?
Or we've got this new class hybrid.
This is what we're calling our paladin, except we don't want you to know it's a paladin,
so it's like...
two-thirds fighter and one-third healer, maybe, or maybe this one's 40% fighter and 60% healer.
Oh, yeah. But, and we're calling it a, I don't know, lawgiver or something. It doesn't really
matter. We, in text mods, there were mods that, they had 100 classes, 100. And, and,
character races, you know, they would advertise it on the basis that they got 30 different
character races. Well, that's good. When I start off, I'm really going to know what to
choose here.
Which selection of vowels with no consonants or consonants with no vowels am I going to be?
Do you even need classes?
Oh, yeah, this is a picture of a dead ox from South Africa.
Right, now, some of what Roy and I envisaged because we were, I was 18, he was 19, was overambitious.
We hoped that the world we were going to create was going to be rich and meaningful.
Oh man, when's this talk supposed to finish?
Like five minutes?
Ah, you say that, but you haven't got the tasers.
Roy was hoping that the game would be sufficiently richly featured to be self-sustaining,
so that what you did in the game would be enough to give you goals for things to do.
So he didn't put a game mechanic in it.
He set it up as a game, but with only a partial rule
set implied by the physics.
So he didn't actually build in points and experience
and things like that.
But it was more EVE Online than Second Life.
You couldn't add random stupid content,
but you could act within the context.
However, the DEC System 10 wasn't up to this.
So.
we discussed it and we decided eventually we're going to have to gamify it, which meant
we're going to have to put, as part of the physics of the world, some game aspects. So,
things like experience points, for example. In real life, you don't have experience points
because the physics of the real life don't support it, but in a game world where we put
it in, so, yeah, that was the, it was a major change in our philosophy. I recognized that
you didn't have an obvious sense of purpose from it.
You went there and it's kind of an Alice in Wonderland, wow,
fantastic, what a wonderful world.
But there was nothing really to do there except for
curiouser and curiouser.
So I decided to put in what these days we call an
achievement system.
And I went through a number of options for an achievement
system, including equipment.
So the more equipment you had, the better the equipment, the
higher you were.
That we ruled out because we didn't have the disk space to store it.
Skills. If you were good at fighting, good at this, then your skills would increase and then you'd be better.
Levels. So you do things, you get experience points, every so often you trip a thing and you go up to the next level.
Experience points without levels. You just do things, you get experience points, and ha, whoopee, I've hit 20,000 or whatever your own goal was.
Linked quests. You do things ultimately to try and get there.
achieve some objective, which would be quite hard, and the more you did it, then you'd
get harder and harder ones, kind of like a choose your own adventure.
That we went against because it was too, too structured for what we wanted.
I did have some other ideas which I looked at, but they were a bit wacky, like democracy.
You go up a level when everybody votes you go up a level.
to go with the levels, which, because I'd seen it from Dungeons and Dragons,
and I knew that you could use it as a,
for a variety of tasks rather than just one task.
Why should my sword play ability go up for having bartered with
the level thing, you just go up generally.
They're easy to understand,
and they gave players, because it was a level, it gave you
a sense of your current place in the social order.
Now.
This is where I'm going into an area that I've not really explored before.
I've explained about levels.
I mean, they've got a bunch of really good things there.
They give you intermediate goals, and they give you a sense of having achieved things.
And that is why I chose levels.
The thing is that some of the other things on that list would have done that.
Equipment would have done that.
Skills would have done that.
So, although that is what, I mean, if levels, that is the main reason I chose levels,
but I had also to choose between some of the other things I could have had.
It's not that levels are the only thing you can do for that.
And what tipped the balance in favour of levels was that word, current social order.
See, Roy Trubshaw and I, are there any British people here?
Yeah, okay, right.
you kind of, you maybe understand some of what I'm saying a bit more.
We raged against the British class system.
My accent, to you, the Americans,
sounds as though I'm
intelligent and erudite
and a Hollywood villain.
But in Britain, it sounds as like I work on a farm.
Yeah? Because I've got a northern accent.
Roy Chubshaw, he's from Wolverhampton.
He speaks with a Wilbur Hampton accent.
What do you think you're doing?
Oh, I'm not doing that.
I'm doing this, you'll go, what do you think you're doing here?
That's the sort of Wilbur Hampton accent.
And he sounds like he works in a factory.
And when you've got accents like that, either you adopt them,
you change them to something else, or you're stuffed.
I didn't see why I should change mine.
Roy didn't see why he should change his.
We should change the world instead.
We made our own world where accents didn't matter.
Do I hate voice over IP?
Yes, I do.
So this was our response.
We put in a level system because that led you out of the class system.
We only had 10 levels, you can do that kind of thing when you've got permadeath.
Each level had its own personality.
So you saw somebody at level 3, it was a swordsman.
You knew what being a swordsman was.
It's a level 3 thing.
It doesn't really matter.
You get a sense of what the level was and when you rise up you get a better level.
For example, the level just before you got to the top, level 9, was legend.
Crucially, all that stopped you rising a level was your own expertise,
your own skill, your own desire to go up.
There was nothing stopping you from going up a level because you were a girl.
or because you were slightly socially inept,
or because you were from the north of England,
or because you were a Scot who didn't drink.
There was nothing to stop it. It was all down to you.
It was like meritocracy.
And it was a kind of meritocracy that everybody could succeed.
All they had to overcome was their own sense that they shouldn't succeed.
And this is why we put in levels.
So all these people who are playing games now with levels in it,
you don't know it, but you're actually raging against the British class system.
It was a political statement.
I've not told that to anybody else, well, my wife,
and Roy Chubshaw, obviously, but other than that,
this is the first time I've told that.
This award I got here, no way would I get that in England.
No way at all, not a chance,
because I'm not like...
the right kind of person in England. Here, I'm a foreigner so you'll accept my strange
and wacky ways, but in England it's a, oh yes, what's a nut. You've done well, Piers
Howard, haven't you? Other English people would either be nodding their heads or thinking,
well, I don't... Er... I can't help it... I was born in London!
Now, the people who wrote... I'm sorry I'm over...
If you want to leave because it's supposed to finish,
then, you know, feel free. I won't zap you with my laser.
People who wrote MUDs who followed,
and the MMOs that followed that,
they didn't know any of this.
So, they just took it and added other things in,
and they didn't understand the soul behind it.
Why it was there, why it worked,
what it was saying.
So they liberally added many more levels.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, we've got a hundred, we've got two hundred levels, we've got so many levels that are coming out of our ears.
We don't even measure our experience points in integers.
We use floating points.
You laugh, they do!
They have no understanding of what they're doing.
The point...
You have to understand what you're doing. I don't mind people having a million points to go up a level
if they know why they're doing it. And that reason isn't merely,
well, let's just follow the curve around this level, you need a million.
Why do you need a million? Why? Why?
Well, because in the past it's been put... No, no, no, no, no, never mind in the past.
Why are you doing it?
At the moment...
Equipment, you know, gear is the preferred achievement system of the level cap.
Once you get to the top, you know, you can't get more than level X.
18 World of Warcraft for the next few months.
So, how do you advance? Well, gear. That's what you do.
Now, why are they doing that?
Well, because that's obviously the next thing to, you know, just, it's a way to do it.
But hold on, what's it saying?
It's actually.
kind of consumerist. What it's saying is
the more stuff you have, the more important you are.
Now, that's a consumerist argument.
I'm not gonna make any judgments about consumerist
arguments, because if you give me stuff, I'm gonna be just as happy as anybody else.
But, if that's what you're wanting to say, if you're trying to make a
point about doing a consumerist game, then
why not do a consumerist game?
Why bother with the leveling system at all?
Why not have the end game as the game?
Start off with everybody's the same level,
and the more stuff you get, the more stuff you get,
and the better it is.
And you don't have to level your characters
through 80 levels of what you've done before.
See, if you know why you're doing things,
what point you're trying to make.
then you can remove the distractions
and press on with what you're really trying to say.
If you say, OK, I'm selling this game in the West,
West's mainly consumerist, therefore,
let's give people what they want,
give them all the consumer goods they want,
well, why bother with a levelling game?
That's not anything to do with that, that's British class system.
What are you doing that for?
If you don't know that, then
you're just going to end up with these hybrid games.
And some people tootling around
in Elwynn Forest
because they like to tootle around in Elwynn Forest.
shooting bears and running from Hogger, and other people who love getting up at four o'clock
in the morning to blast other people out the sky in EVE Online.
This is a man in a shop.
Finally, I'm sorry I'm really going over here, I'm going to turn to combat.
Roy thought that combat would be handled by the underlying system of the game, so the
physics of the world would handle combat.
The very first thing I personally implemented in MUD was an ox, and if you hit it with an
axe it died.
And in true simulistic fashion, that was just how it would work in real life.
You hit an ox with an axe, it's going to die.
One blow.
But that wasn't a lot of fun.
Well, it was kind of fun, but not as much fun, not the kind of fun where you think the
ox might actually hurt you.
It was the kind of fun where, ooh, a toddler!
So, easy fun as Lazzaro called it.
There are two ways to implement combat.
Manually, hit ox with axe, and the ox is simultaneously typing,
gore player with horns, ahhh.
Or as a stream, where one of you starts the fight,
and then this exchange of blows coming along.
Those are kind of the two ways to do fighting.
Roy implemented the second one, because it was getting close,
he had to finish his degree, and that was it.
He really just had to do it.
implement something, that's what he did.
I took his code and interspersed the other kind.
So what happens, you've got a stream of interactions,
but there are individual things you can do to adjust the stream.
So you might try to set fire to their clothes
while you're fighting.
Well, then they have to try and put the fire out.
But at that point, you might decide to try and steal
their potions or something.
So there's all these things you could do during the fight.
So this is pretty much how things remain today.
You've got a stream of, you activate the fight,
things happen, boom, boom, boom, it tries to hit,
you try to hit.
And then there are things you can do to intersperse it.
I'm going to shoot off this fireball.
That isn't part of the fight.
The fight's just me hitting them with my sword,
but I'm going to shoot a fireball off.
That's an interspersal into the stream.
The range of things you've got is wider, but the choice is narrower.
We had different weapons affecting different monsters in different ways.
If you come across something that's a fire elemental, then you don't want to shoot fire at it,
because, you know, that's kind of good for it. You want to shoot water, this sort of stuff.
But we didn't have formal character classes, so we didn't have somebody being a mage.
because they signed up to be a mage. They were a mage because they used magic more than
something else. We didn't have races either. We think that's a bad thing. I still think
that's a bad thing. It's like saying, you're an elf, where are all the half-elves? Where
are all the quarter-elves? Where are the elf stroke dwarfs? There aren't any. You're essentially
saying that when you're born into a race, you have to stay into that race. I think that's
racist. But people don't think that in the play of the game anyway.
So, a lot of the character cost stuff that was taken out in the Deku Mud days and just
from D&D for no reason other than it was in D&D.
And it changed an emphasis in the game.
The first 10, 15 years of MMOs were all to do with being yourself, but now it's more
to a guided experience rather than finding your own fun.
I got a different rant there.
about that. The thing about the tanks and the DPS and the healers, that came about purely
because of the way space was implemented in Deku MUDs. That's pretty well the only reason
we have tanks. You don't have to have tanks. I think I'm now starting to run into the set-up
time of the next talk. There is a next talk. Combat was one of the weakest areas of MUD.
I wasn't pleased with it at all.
And yet, it's gone on pretty well unchanged.
Why hasn't anybody experimented?
You get very few experiments.
Aja Conan had a bit of hit location.
I had hit location in 1980 in a space game I wrote.
It was a graphical game as well.
It had like up arrows for when your spaceship was going,
and left arrows and right arrows and a V,
and asterisks for stars.
It's as if.
you intend to man shop it.
Woman shop is where you go to a shop
to buy something for somebody, and you say something you like,
and then you go to another shop, and another shop,
and then three hours later, you choose
the best thing you've seen.
Man shop is where you go into a shop,
and you see something that'll do, and you say, I'll have that.
And it's like that with designers.
It's like, this will do.
I'll just have it.
I can't be bothered to carry it, to look at every single shoe
in every single shoe shop.
I just want a pair of shoes, that's going to work, I'll have it.
But don't they know they can do better?
You can do better than that.
It's as if they don't know that they can do better.
It's like it's part of the inventiveness of multi-user games has been lost.
Roy and I had to think of the mud from our first principles.
We didn't have a paradigm to work to, we had to make all our decisions for particular reasons.
That's not just us. As I said at the beginning, we weren't the only people who invented these things.
Mark Jacobs, Alan Kleitz, Bob Alberti, John Taylor, Kelton Flynn, Randy Farmer, Chip Morningstar.
I would mention the people who wrote Avatar if I could find out their names.
they would have similar anecdotes.
They will have a reason that they did these things,
not just because it just sprung from their minds.
But, oh, that sounds kind of cool.
They will have had a reason for doing that.
They would have been saying something.
If you ask them, I'm pretty sure that they
will be able to tell you that.
My objective here today in this talk is to make two points.
Firstly, it behooves you all to understand what you're
designing and why you are designing it.
The why is important. You need to know why you're doing it.
And the second point is that all these choices that Roy and I had are still available to you today.
You can still make those choices today.
It's not like they've disappeared in the past.
I'm just telling you what we did so you know that you can still do it.
Oh, there was one other thing. Normally my slides look like this.
So...
Why don't I just give you 26 slides and a too long talk, speaking in steampunk?
Well, on the face of it, obviously, it was because I'm giving you something that's old,
oldie-worldie, and I can tell you all these things about the past with a past flavor.
But actually, I was criticizing today's game design principles, and this was a contrivance.
It was just something there which covered my...
that my real purpose behind things
in the guise of the new history lesson and the thing is
that's what mud was, a contrivance
it was something was looking to be a game, looking to be fun
but actually it was Roy and I ripping into
our awful situation in
in the British class system. Roy and I were the first people in our families
ever to go to university, ever.
We were very lucky. These days we wouldn't have been able to afford it.
Neither of us came from wealthy backgrounds.
What we wanted to do was to say unpalatable things about the real world
through the protected frame of a game.
We were saying things like,
this real world sucks, you assholes are doing this.
It wasn't that we had chips on our shoulders,
it was like blocks of, like, mountain.
We just did not like what was going on
and we wanted a place where we could be rid of all that.
And we like programming as well.
But you can do the same sort of thing.
Why are you working in games?
You must want to say something.
You have to want to say something.
It doesn't matter whether you're working on a conveyor belt game
making things for Facebook.
At some point, you'll think, I really want to say something.
I'm going to say it.
And say it.
That's what I'm telling you.
If you're a game designer, you have
to have some of your soul in the game design.
because otherwise it's just superficial.
There's no vision to it, no substance to it.
You have to have some of your soul in it.
And that's the biggest lesson that I'd like to give you from here.
I'm not saying throw away the paradigm.
What's worked in the past,
if you understand why it was there,
then you can use it.
But you must understand what's in the paradigm,
then you can throw it away.
Okay, here we go.