I'm Zach Gage.
This is building games that can be understood at a glance.
If you're not familiar with my work,
I've made a bunch of games that you may or may not
have played, like Flip-Flop Solitaire, TypeShift,
Really Bad Chess, Sage Solitaire, Tharsis,
Ridiculous Fishing, Spell Tower, Lose-Lose,
and a couple others.
Anyway, I've been making games for quite a while on the phone,
almost since the beginning of the iPhone, actually.
And one thing that really struck me very early on
was how different the experience of finding
new games for the phone was versus other platforms.
Mostly how I was finding new games
was by looking over people's shoulders.
So over my friend's shoulder at a bar,
over a stranger's shoulder on the subway,
or at what the person next to me on an airplane was playing.
Sometimes I get really into the game,
and I start playing it in my head.
And I would start critiquing the actions of the person
quietly to myself.
And whenever I started doing this, one thing I noticed is I'd want to download the game myself.
And sometimes the name of the game was on the screen, so I could just write it down.
And other times I'd have to ask, and people were always really excited to tell me what the game was like and why they loved it.
So I ended up asking a lot.
And as I started making more and more mobile games,
I really wanted to build games that could do this for other people,
that could sell themselves to strangers who were looking over other people's shoulders.
That's kind of a mouthful as like a strategy,
so I'm just going to call it my friend Kevin proposed
calling it Subway Legible Games,
because we both live in New York,
so that's what I'm going to call it.
Okay, so obviously one caveat for this talk
is nothing that anyone tells you is going to be
the one thing that makes you successful or not successful,
but I do think that finding success with your games
relies upon having a lot of little tricks
that really fit your own practice and capabilities.
and leveraging those tricks as best you can.
And for me, designing for subway legibility
has been a really powerful tool.
And the reason why it's a powerful tool
is that effectively it solves three problems for me
at the same time.
And since I make most of my games totally by myself,
any time I can solve three things with one solution,
that's a really big win.
So what are those three things?
Well, designing for subway legibility
does three things for you.
One, it makes implementing your tutorials a whole lot less work.
Your game is easier to comprehend naturally
because you're presenting information and game state
in a way that is designed to be naturally
accessible to people who are playing the game.
This means when you sit down to make your tutorial, which
probably, if you've done it, you would
agree is the absolute worst part of making a video game,
half the work is already done for you.
Having a better tutorial means more people will enjoy your game
across any kind of skill level, and so that's great.
Two, it improves organic discovery.
When your game is good at teaching other people to play,
it'll draw in more viewers, and every player and every streamer
of your game can focus on conveying how awesome your game is
instead of explaining to everyone over and over again how the game works.
Three, easier marketing.
Your screenshots and your GIFs will need little to no context,
and that makes pitching for coverage or going on viral on Twitter.
Way easier.
People say a picture is worth a thousand words,
but that's only true if people can understand
what your picture is about.
Okay, so you're probably thinking,
all right, Zach, it's so easy to make indie games,
or to make Subway legible games
when you make these tiny little mobile games.
What about my big fancy PC game?
Is that even possible?
Yes.
This is a screenshot of Into the Breach.
which mostly everybody regards as a brilliant tactical strategy game,
and I regard as an incredible example of information organization and UI design.
This screenshot is one that went around Twitter before the game came out,
and I think if we look at it, we can figure out why pretty easily.
If anyone looking at this can immediately tell
that it involves huge mechs and giant city-sized bugs,
the word mech is literally written on the screen.
It's turn-based, you have a bunch of units,
these bugs are doing something bad.
Things are exciting and literally on fire.
The kind of tile you're standing on has a tactical effect,
maybe like Advance Wars.
And it's science fiction and it involves time pods,
which is actually written on the screen also.
These guys are geniuses.
That sounds pretty exciting to me,
and I can already imagine what the game is like.
So how'd they make all that so clear?
So some of the things I cover in this talk
might seem unbelievably obvious.
But I find that the best design rules are always simple.
and obvious.
And that's because they need to be simple enough
for you to break them sometimes,
and they need to be obvious enough
that you're gonna remember to actually do them.
Back when I was in college studying design,
I was introduced to the principle of the three reads.
At least that's what my design teacher called it,
so that's what I'm gonna call it
when I explain it to you now.
It's the key to all of this,
and so if you come away from this talk
and you only remember one thing that I explained,
make it this thing.
The easiest way to understand the three reads
is by thinking about a concert poster.
Imagine you're making a poster for some event
that you're going to throw.
Let's think about how posters are experienced.
Generally, we see them on the street,
and that means that the audience that a poster can greet
is primarily limited by how far away you can actually
read the poster.
A poster that can only be read from 10 feet away
is going to reach a lot less people than a poster that
can be read by 30 feet away.
I promise I will get to how this affects games.
That means we want to have the text on our poster be big,
but we don't want all of it to be big,
because if it was all big, that'd be really confusing,
and we'd barely be able to put anything on the poster.
So what should be big?
Probably the things that would convince people
to walk closer to the poster.
So essentially, we're trying to design a poster
that's gonna pitch itself to people passing by.
So first things first, who's performing?
In our example, David Bowie, rest in peace.
There's our target market.
If you like David Bowie,
you're gonna walk closer to the poster.
If you don't like David Bowie, I don't really care about you.
So that's the first read, the first thing that people see
when they look at the poster, and it's meant to draw in
the people that you wanna talk to.
The second read is for people who have approached the poster
and are now looking for more information.
We don't really have to worry so much now
about the size of the text, we can make the text smaller
because people are close to the poster.
So this is what would be in the second read.
When is this happening?
Where is this happening?
what kind of show is he gonna be performing.
So hopefully now the viewer is interested,
they like the venue, they're free on Tuesday,
we can make it to the third read,
which is where we tell you how much it costs,
remind you of the address, specify the time,
and throw in all the little extra details
that we need that nobody actually cares about,
like who's presenting the show.
No offense if you're a show presenter.
So there you go, that's the whole thing.
That was pretty simple, right?
Talk over.
So this kind of design structure works not just for rock posters,
but it also works for video games.
Let's go back to that screenshot.
What draws our eye first in this screenshot?
The giant grid.
It feels a little bit like Advance Wars.
It has clearly what looks like a player-controlled unit.
Something's on fire. There's a bunch of bugs.
What do we see next?
Whoa! Look at all these things to think about.
It's turn-based. I have three people.
My health seems to be the power grid.
I guess I have to survive four turns, I have a mech,
and it looks like depending on where I place my units,
there are special tile effects.
So, wow, it is gonna be like Advance Wars, maybe.
And then on to the third read.
Oh, my units have health, too,
and there are bonus objectives,
and look at all this crunchy tactical data,
and also time pods.
The screenshot takes you from, hey, this is like Advance Wars,
all the way through to, wow, this
is so much more exciting than Advance Wars,
just by how the information is laid out.
So obviously, this kind of clarity
can help with your promotion.
But how does it also help us make better tutorials
and improve word of mouth?
So something you might be familiar with
from making tutorials is that generally when
you teach something new, you want
to introduce the rules in a specific order
so that players can build a mental model of how
the game works.
starting from the broad strokes and then moving inwards
towards more specific rules.
Huh.
Actually sounds a lot like how the three reads worked.
The first read pulls you in, and that's the core of your game.
The second read fills in key details
or big, unintuitive rules.
And the third read gives contextually important
information, like the time of the Bowie show
only matters if I'm free on Tuesday.
And that gives you contextually important rules,
like what tile a giant bug is targeting
only matters if you're thinking about how to deal with that bug.
So a good tutorial teaches you things in the right order,
and good design shows you things in the right order.
Let's look at my game Spelltower as an example.
So in Spelltower, you're trying to keep stacks of letters
from reaching the top of the board,
and you do this by spelling words that removes the blocks,
and then more stuff gets added from the bottom.
Let's look at the three reads here.
First thing.
We want players to see just the letters.
They need to look at the letters
and think about what words they can spell.
When you're comfortable finding letters,
you need to think about which columns
are close to getting to the top
and which letters are special and extra helpful
for reducing the height of your stacks,
like the blue letters will reduce a whole row.
And then finally, on the third read,
is the information that only contextually matters.
Things like what your high score is,
which tiles can be used,
and which ones need to be in at least four length words.
The layout reinforces how to approach the game,
both for the player, but it also reinforces it
for every single person who ever looks
at the game over their shoulder.
OK.
That's it for how to do the three reads properly.
And before we move on to advanced concepts,
I do want to take a quick look at what this can
look like when it goes wrong.
This is Slay the Spire.
This is a game I enjoy quite a lot.
And in fact, it's a game that a lot of people enjoy,
and it's done really well for itself.
So I don't feel terrible subjecting it
to a little bit of constructive criticism.
If you made this game and you're in the audience,
thank you for making this.
I really like it.
Slay the Spire actually does a really great job
teaching the player how to play it.
It's got one of the best tutorials
I've seen in a really long time.
Every single thing on the screen tells you
what it does when you mouse over it.
And the way that all these concepts are given to you
is at this perfect leisurely pace
so that when you arrive at a screen like this,
you understand every single thing that's going on.
The problem is when someone starts
watching over your shoulder, or more often with a PC game
like this, when they start watching on Twitch,
they might not know what's going on.
So if you've never played Slay the Spire,
you probably wouldn't guess that the most
important information on the screen
is actually these little icons.
These icons, more than the health,
More than the armor, more than the cards in your hand,
explain the current state of a battle.
Not only are they tiny, but even if onlookers notice them,
they have no idea what they mean.
These should be in the second read,
but they're in the third.
On top of that, the screen has a lot of empty space on it,
but it still manages to look very busy.
Nearly everything on the screen is a tiny icon
with a little number on it.
What are these things?
And how can you have something but have zero of it?
And why is my health in two places
and two different colors?
And what are these decks, and do they really
need numbers on them?
Couldn't the cards just be shown by the size of the deck?
And you might not know it from the presentation,
but the one on the right is actually the discard pile.
These aren't two separate decks.
They're all the pieces of one.
The problem isn't that all of this information is displayed.
It's that it's displayed at relatively the same scale,
and that the stuff that you really, really need
is actually the smallest.
Here's what the reeds of Slay the Spire look like.
First read, two characters, a hand of cards,
an enter button, and the mana.
This is looking pretty good so far.
Second read is practically everything else.
And third read is some small numbers
and the all-important status icons under the health bars.
So see how you can kind of barely
tell the difference between the second and the third reads
here?
That's a pretty big sign that something is really overloaded.
Do want to remind you, I love this game.
This is just constructive criticism.
And also, I want to remind you that this game does a great job mitigating a lot of this with really solid animations
which is actually what I want to talk about next.
So hopefully by now you have a sense of what the first, second, and third read of something should look like.
And now I want to cover a little bit of advanced stuff that you can't do with a poster.
So unlike traditional print design, video games can move and they're interactive and that provides you with a couple additional options as a designer.
One of these options is using movement and animation
to temporarily raise or lower the read of a game component.
And Blizzard does this really well in their game Hearthstone.
So pay attention when I run this video to the size changes
and how your eye follows them.
Hearthstone is a constant wave of things
being brought to your attention in the first read
and then fading back into the second or third reads.
It's really masterful, but it's also a lot to consider
if I was going to break this down the way that I broke down
into the Breach screenshot,
it would probably take this entire talk.
So instead, I want to look at a much smaller example,
which is how I'm trying to solve a rules comprehension problem
in my game TypeShift.
This is what a puzzle looks like in TypeShift.
Like in Spelltower, your first read is the letters.
Your second is the tiles and the background,
and your third is the menus and the minor decorative elements.
A longstanding issue I've had here
is that some players jump to the conclusion
that your goal in a TypeShift puzzle
is to find every single word in the puzzle, which makes sense,
because that's how most word-finding puzzles work.
But actually, in TypeShift, your goal
is to use every letter at least one time.
So I tried to make this clear in the tutorial
by literally telling people.
showing you that you're making a word turns your tiles
bluish green and that your goal is to turn them all green.
But that wasn't good enough for many, many players.
And the problem is that when the color tiles,
that the color tiles in this game are on the second read
and when they change color,
it's just as players are finding a word.
So you're a little distracted and you don't notice.
And so players interpret the color change
as a decorative event.
So this is what it looks like when you find a word.
I'm about to launch an attempted fix that uses animation
to bring tile backdrops temporarily into the first read,
and I'm doing that animation right after they find a word,
so hopefully when they're not distracted by something else
and focusing on something new.
So that looks like this.
It's a very small adjustment,
animating the color change across the letters
instead of having it pop in,
but it reinforces the importance of the color
as more than a decoration.
It becomes an informational animation.
and informational, that's not a real word.
I never would have come to this change
if I hadn't been considering the problem
within the context of the three reads,
and so we'll see when I launch it how it works out.
Another thing you can do in a game
that you can't in a poster is provide
hidden toggled information, which I call the fourth read.
In Really Bad Chess, I needed to have a bunch of menus
on the screen to allow you to use undo's,
check scores, or quit the game,
and those ended up looking like this.
Unfortunately, those menus are horribly distracting.
The problem is that in chess, the pieces are really small
and they're really detailed.
And so when you have big graphical elements
on the screen, it's very easy for them
to overwhelm these tiny little pieces on the board.
So to solve this, I made it so that whenever you tap away
from the menus, whenever you're focusing on the game,
all of those menus slide out of the first read
and into this sort of toggled fourth read.
And now if you look at it, the board and the mode
are squarely in the first read.
They're the things that your eye goes right to.
And everything else looks pretty balanced.
And if you tap up on the menu area, the menus come in.
And now they're in the first read.
But that's totally fine, because they're
what you're looking at and what you're looking for.
And it's always all right to have that in the first read.
And everything feels very natural.
OK, the last thing that I want to look at,
well, I got through this pretty quick.
is my game Sage Solitaire,
which is probably the most complicated layout
I've done in a mobile game.
When I was designing Sage, I had to include
a lot of specific extra information on the screen
that could be a little distracting,
because there are a lot of specific rules in Sage.
My initial layout for it looked like this,
which is, I think, a total mess.
The first read is the cards, and that's great,
but read two is basically everything up top,
the name of the hand.
the decorative stack of cards, the bonus suit, the trashes,
everything blends together.
The problem is that most of these things
shouldn't even be in the second read.
The stack of cards is just a decoration element, basically.
The bonus suit is important, but you only need it sometimes.
And the trashes are also important, but also not
important all the time.
There's actually something up there
that you do need to know constantly,
and that is the name of the hand that you're trying to score
and how much it's worth.
If you didn't know how to play this game,
looking at the screenshot would not teach you how to do it.
It wouldn't tell you what was important.
It wouldn't really tell you anything.
So my solution was to break the screen down
into a big play area that has the first and second reads in it,
and then a small side area that has all the third read
information.
So let's break it down.
First thing you see is the cards.
The second is the name of the hand and the cash-in button.
And then last, you see the trashes, the suit, the score,
a hint button, and your used card pile,
nicely out of the way.
There's also a little bit of a kind of trick in this layout,
and that is normally it would be sort of an issue
if the things that were taking up
the entirety of your second read were contextually visible.
So right now, the cash-in button and the name of the hand
Where do those go when you don't have a hand selected?
Does that ruin the layout?
Does it make it confusing that there would be no second read?
Well, so actually, I don't get rid of both of them.
And I use one very deliberately as the only thing
in the second read.
And that is I leave the hand button,
and I just change the text to tap for hand list.
That's the only thing in the second read
in this entire screen.
And the reason I did that was very intentional.
And it was that even though Sage Solitaire is a solitaire game,
It's very different than a solitaire game.
Usually in solitaire, you're trying to make piles
and move cards around in piles,
but this is all about making poker hands.
And that's very irregular for a poker game,
or for a solitaire game, and it does a couple things.
One, you'd never expect it
if you were looking over someone's shoulder,
and two, if you are a solitaire person,
you might not even know the poker hands.
And so leaving this big piece of information
as the only thing in the second read
guides everybody who's looking at it.
So eye to that piece of information,
and it tells them, A, this is a game about making hands,
and B, if you are literally playing it
and you don't know the hands,
here's a giant button that you can press
that's gonna help you.
I think it's very easy to look at this layout
and be tempted to make the hand list a small button
that sits off to the side,
but if I'd done that,
it wouldn't have helped people looking over his shoulder,
and it wouldn't have helped normal solitaire players
feel more confident and able to play this game.
So there you go.
That wasn't so bad.
Let's recap.
You have three standard reads.
The first one pulls you in and explains the core of your game.
The second one fills in key details or big, unintuitive rules.
And the third gives you contextually important information
or contextually important rules.
You also have a fourth read that comes from toggled information
and the ability to move things up and down in the read structure
through movement and animation.
And if you do all that stuff correctly,
you get subway legibility.
It becomes much less work to make a great tutorial.
People see your game out in the world or on Twitch
and they get it and they want to get it.
And explaining what your game is with a screenshot
or an animated GIF becomes extremely simple.
So I hope that was helpful.
Thanks.
We have time for questions.
If you'd like to ask Zach a question,
please come to one of the mics in the aisles.
And while we're waiting for folks to come up,
I have a question for you.
Yeah.
So what do you think the concept of the three reads
means for designing trailers?
Oh, boy.
I definitely think, in general, you
want to approach a trailer fairly similarly.
You want to have the thing right at the start that's
going to draw people in.
And as your trailer progresses, you
can get more and more detailed about what's going on.
I actually think.
Maybe almost more important than that is just keep your trailer short.
Your trailer shouldn't be more than a minute.
And most people will turn off a trailer after like 10 seconds.
So if you don't hit them right in the face with something that's really compelling,
that's probably not good for you.
But one thing that is nice about doing a trailer,
even though it's incredibly annoying unless you love making trailers.
is that it really helps you refine what your pitch is going to be,
because your pitch to most press and most of Twitter
is actually the same as the beginning of a trailer.
Your first 30 seconds of a trailer should show what your game's about,
why it's special, and how it works.
You think that's why in Hollywood trailers these days
they do that mini-trailer thing at the start,
where there's like a whole bunch of action?
Have you seen that?
Where they have really quick snippets of what's going to be
in the rest of the trailer?
Because that's like showing you up front some of the meat.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Though also in Hollywood trailers, they have a voiceover,
so they get to tell you exactly why you care.
That's true.
Anyone have any questions?
Speechless.
So my question is about, let's say,
In, specifically I work in arcade games mostly,
but this is probably true in the App Store too,
where everyone's trying to get your attention,
everything's trying to be as loud as possible
to be grabbing the player's attention.
And do you have any tricks for being subway legible
in the context of also competing with the flashbang
of all the other games in the market that are around?
Is there anything that you've found kind of...
grabs attention without being overwhelming?
Sure.
I think the first thing that you need to think about,
at least I can speak to the context of the App Store,
is that most people actually don't understand
how the App Store works.
And they don't approach the marketing in the App Store
in the way that is going to make the most of it for them.
And if you do that, that kind of puts you
on another level already.
That is very helpful.
The thing that you need to understand, at least,
about the App Store is you need to sit down and look at,
like, what are the pieces of information
that people are going to get right away?
And how do I use that information just good enough
to be able to get them to the next piece of information?
So in the App Store, you get.
an icon, you get the name of your game,
and you get a small subtitle.
And you need to make the entire case for someone
to click your game based on those things.
But more importantly, you don't have to make anything else.
You're not trying to sell your whole game on that.
You're just trying to sell them to tap on the icon.
And so when you're designing an icon,
you can think about what do I need
and what do I not need in this.
Told by the icon that can't be told by the name.
What do I not need to include?
So for example, a lot of times when you're making a word game,
you have to convey that it's a word game.
And so how do you do that?
Do you put a lot of text in the icon?
You can do that if the name of your game
doesn't necessarily clearly show.
So TypeShift, you wouldn't necessarily
know that that's a word game.
It could be an app.
So the icon better show something
that looks like a word game.
But if your game is called.
crosswords five, then you can put a happy smiling face
on your icon and everybody's already gonna know
it's a word game.
So that's the first step.
And then when people tap on it,
then what's the next thing that people are gonna see?
Well, here, you're effectively at your second read.
You have someone as like a captive audience,
and now you just have to sell them on your game.
And what you generally have is a...
a short video snippet that better be really exciting right away
because people are on their phones and it'll go away.
And then you have a series of images that people can slide through
that I typically use to explain why the game works and what's special about it.
And then that's really it.
Nobody ever actually reads the text.
If people read the text, they're already sold on your game,
so you just have to not screw it up at that point.
You don't really have to keep selling.
Yeah, I also want to say just as a total side note,
I really never thought I would be up here
giving a talk about promotion.
This is so fucking weird for me.
I like want to make fun, weird art games that people like,
but I guess you got to learn how to do this stuff
to make that work.
All right, thanks, Zach.
Everybody, please make sure you fill out your surveys
to give Zach feedback on his talk.
But before you go,
please give him one final round of applause.
you