Hi, good afternoon.
Thank you all for coming.
God, there's so many of you.
I'm super excited to be here and even more terrified.
And I come here today to talk to you about quests,
nonlinear narratives, and how we manage to put all of them
into Horizon Zero Dawn.
Now, for those of you who might not know, Horizon Zero Dawn is an open-world action role-playing game,
exclusive for the PlayStation 4.
It is set in a lush, post-post-apocalyptic world,
where gigantic machines have taken over and humanity is no longer the dominant species.
This talk will be composed of two parts.
First, I will delve into our research into quests,
linear and non-linear narratives,
quest systems, quest building methods
in already existing games.
In the second part, I will talk more about
how this research led us to the development
of our own systems and methods and what exactly they are.
Now, I know it might be a little bit unorthodox
for an engineer to speak at this specific summit,
but I think there's a good enough reason for that.
And first of all, although right now I'm employed
as a programmer at Guerrilla Games,
my background is a little bit more diverse.
I used to work in a mobile company
where I had dual responsibilities as a designer,
where I also worked on narrative and quest systems.
And before that, I had probably one of the best jobs possible
which was being a professional game or dungeon master.
Secondly, I kind of hope that an engineer might bring
a little bit of a different perspective to the common
issues that we as game developers face regarding
building game narratives and narrative-based games.
And thirdly, quests are very interesting concepts
in themselves, and by quests I'll be talking about
the things which you might find in role-playing games,
not necessarily what you might encounter in literary
studies, although these two tend to be closely related.
Now, as some of you might be aware,
there are two perspectives from which
one can look at video games.
One is the narrative perspective,
which understands a game as a form of a narrative.
Second is the ludic perspective, which understands the game
as a set of rules.
Now, Quest has been proposed as this way
to combine these two perspectives
into a single concept.
And that is partly because to exist, they need both.
And I allow myself to quote Jeff Howard from his really cool
book, Quest, which treats exactly about this topic.
Quests are about action that is meaningful to a player on a level of ideas, personal ambitions,
benefit to society, and spiritual authenticity. And the word meaningful is exceptionally important
here because it also refers to the concept of meaningful choice, which is one of the most
important ideas in good game design.
The meaning of quests emerges from strategic actions,
but these actions have thematic, narrative,
and personal implications.
Through quests, the player interacts
with both the rules and the narrative
and draws meaning from both of them.
So to summarize all that, quests are this place
in a video game where game design, writing,
and technology all come together.
So to be able to discuss this topic,
let's have a quick look at a structure of a typical quest.
Quests are usually composed of multiple
discrete phases or steps.
Quests usually follow this typical structure
of having an obvious start, obvious middle, and obvious end.
Each step of a quest can be considered
a single piece of a greater quest narrative.
Often, a step is connected with a quest log entry,
which informs the player about their progress so far,
and forms also sort of a written narrative
of the player's personal progression through that quest.
Also, a quest step can be connected to one
or multiple objectives which inform the player
about the tasks at hand.
And usually, progressing through a quest
yields some sort of a reward which has a tangible value
in the context of the game.
So if we have a game which story is told mainly through quests,
we will need a system which will allow for creation and management of such quests.
And the shape of that system, its structure, how it functions,
and most importantly how we understand it,
has far-reaching implications into what kind of quests we can build,
and by turn, what kind of stories we can tell.
So as some of you might be aware,
guerrilla games used to specialize in first person
shooters and action games in general.
So when we set out to build Horizon,
we had nothing of the sort.
So in order to fill the gaps in our knowledge,
we decided to look at games that came before
and also have a look at how other teams
have approached this particular problem.
And when looking during pre-production at various games,
we found multiple, multiple, very different approaches.
But all of them had this common denominator.
And that was that all of them could have been placed.
on a scale which describes how flexible they are
and how strictly they define what the quest
in the context of a particular game is.
With systems that we could call relaxed
on one extreme of that scale
and systems that we could call strict
on the opposite extreme of that scale.
So what is a relaxed quest system?
Well, at its extreme, it's a no system at all,
meaning it has no centralized way of managing
quests and their progression.
It even doesn't have a defined concept of a quest.
And any logic that exists to drive a gameplay forward
is implemented by the designers directly
into the scripting language of a game engine used.
Because such an approach doesn't put any limitations on us,
in theory, any kind of story that can be expressed
through a quest is possible.
However, this does come as a great cost of complexity
and high time of implementation.
So, in theory, we could create intricate stories
which use sophisticated storytelling techniques,
which do use complex structures,
but these kind of quests would be also
very complicated to create.
However, these kind of systems have been used very successfully, especially in the early
days of computer role-playing game development.
So we're talking about games like Might and Magic or Wizardry.
But also recently, a lot of role-playing games built on top of RPG-making platform also use
this method, partly because the RPG maker doesn't seem to support a system of its sort
out of the box.
So, on the opposite extreme of the scale,
we have a strict quest system,
and it's sort of a negative of a relaxed one,
meaning it does use a single centralized way
of managing all quests and their progression,
meaning each quest has a defined,
strictly defined, rigid structure.
And any gameplay that exists in this game
and is based upon quest is not scripted out by the designers,
but built from predefined elements.
And as you can imagine, such systems severely
limit what kind of quest can be created.
However, it does have a positive impact on the complexity of implementation, time of
implementation, and actually also communication and cooperation between teams.
Because everybody involved in building quests has the same idea of what a quest is, how
it's structured, and how it should function.
And such systems have also been very successfully used, mostly though in hack and slash games,
which are known for their mechanical depth rather than the narrative depth.
So we're talking about games like Titan Quest or Sacred.
Nowadays, it's actually quite rare to find a game which
uses a system that exists on any extreme of that scale.
And that is because our audiences over time
have started to demand more intricate stories and also
more sheer amount of content.
So most teams are trying to find this middle ground,
this middle of explore, this middle of the scale
to find this perfect balance between story complexity,
freedom of expression, but also scalability and development
time.
So if you were to put the games that we looked
during pre-production of Horizon on a graph
that represents that scale,
it would look something like that.
So on the right-hand extreme, on the relaxed side,
we would have older RPGs,
like Vampire of a Masquerade Redemption or Gothic,
and also RPG Maker-based games.
On the left-hand, stricter side, we would have games like Sacred or Titan Quest, the mentioned hack-and-slash games.
And somewhere in the middle, exploring this mentioned perfect balance, would be modern RPGs, like The Elder Scrolls V, Skyrim or The Witcher 2.
The other thing worth looking at is how do we actually merge rules with a narrative to create quests?
Well, there are actually two approaches, which seem kind of obvious.
First is to write a story, and then by injecting mechanics into it, and rules and challenges, add gameplay.
Or the other way around, first to create these challenges, rules, and mechanics, and then wrap a story around them.
Now, these two methods have been used pretty much ever
since we started building narrative-based games
and have been perfected over the years, tend to work well,
and have produced magnificent results.
However, because we are translating narrative
into logic or vice versa, sometimes cracks
and inconsistencies can show.
So regardless of our best efforts,
sometimes we might get a bit of a dissonance
between the rules and the narrative.
So once we learned all that, we needed
to decide what our quest system would look like,
what kind of stories we would like to tell,
and what kind of tools we would need to be able to tell them.
So we came up with four high-level requirements
for our quest system and quest-building methods.
So first of all, common types of quests
must be quick and easy to create.
And I think that's very understandable.
I mean, in any game, the content which is most common
should be the quickest and easiest to create.
But in Horizon, it had an additional meaning.
Horizon Zero Dawn was supposed to be an open world game
from the very start.
And open world games require a lot of content,
a lot of stories to create this feeling
of a living, breathing world.
Not necessarily complex ones, but still interesting.
Secondly, complex quests must not be complex
to create and manage.
So although we were okay with having a lot
of relatively simple quests and relatively simple stories,
we still want to have this grand narrative,
these memorable stories, these quests which embed themselves
in the player's imagination and memory forever.
So these two couldn't be in conflict.
Our ability to create content quickly
shouldn't hinder our ability to create intricate quests.
Thirdly, focus on non-linearity.
So again, Open Horizon was supposed
to be an open world game from the very start.
And open world games offer the players freedom,
of a player choice, and ability to approach any problem
from multiple angles.
And we needed our stories to reinforce these roles,
to reinforce this feeling of freedom.
Therefore, we needed quests which are non-linear
at their base.
We needed quests that can be progressed by a player
from multiple angles and in multiple ways.
We needed our system to have non-linearity
at its very core.
And fourthly, finally, provide a base common language
for both the rules and the narrative.
So this addresses the issue I mentioned earlier
of translating the rules into narrative
and narrative into rules.
And we didn't really set out to solve that particular issue,
and I don't think it actually can be fully solved.
but we at least wanted to make one step in the right direction
meaning we at least wanted to give the designers and the writers
this ability to have the same set of ideas and same set of concepts in their mind
we're starting to build quests
So after defining our requirements
and after throwing some ideas on how we would approach
this particular issue, we decided that our system
would live more on the stricter side
of that already mentioned scale.
And I think that makes sense.
Again, we need a lot of content,
and more rigid structures are good for quick development
and really improve good communication
and cooperation between all teams.
So we knew what we wanted.
Now we needed to detail our approach.
We noticed that a lot of games, even the ones which do feature
magnificent non-linear narrative, still construct quests as sequences of steps.
So even though the player has the ability to deviate from the written story,
they are still faced with a linear script to follow.
And we wanted to approach it a little bit differently.
We wanted to present the player the probability space instead of a linear script to follow.
So we need a way to visualize our probability space.
We need a metaphor that will represent it.
And a probability space can be well represented as a graph.
So our first idea was to grab graph theory.
So for those who might not know,
graph theory is one of the fundamental branches
of mathematics and studies the properties
of the formal structures that we call graphs.
These graphs are understood as networks
of points connected by lines.
So essentially graph theory is this formal study
of connections between things.
However, that would be wonderful if our target audience
of these methods were mathematicians
and artificial intelligence researchers.
But we needed the system to be usable,
easily understandable for people
who might not have this kind of technical knowledge.
So we need to look for our metaphor somewhere else.
So I went back.
in memory to the time where I still had this ambition to become a comic book author.
And I started trying to remember the techniques and methods of forging stories that I learned
back then. And I remembered something that I really liked, which I know as the wall of sticky notes.
So what is a wall of sticky notes? Well, quite literally, it is a wall filled with sticky notes.
But what is special about this method is that every sticky note represents a single plot
point, a single scene, depending on how granular you want to be in the plot you're trying to
create, while the whole wall or the board that we are using is the story that you are
trying to write.
The other special thing about this method
is that the lines that you see between these sticky notes
represent the cause and effect relationships between events.
That means that the event that is represented
by the sticky note where the line starts
is the cause of the event represented
by the sticky note where the line ends.
A simple example.
Sticky note one, scene one.
The protagonist enters a village.
A distressed villager approaches them and asks for help
for a horrible menace has entered their fields
and started killing everyone, preventing them from working.
Scene one, post it one, the player enters the village
and is asked for help.
Scene two, sticky note two.
The protagonist enters the fields, guns blazing,
killing everything that moves,
clearing the whole field from the infestation.
Battle with the horrible, horrible insects.
Scene two, sticky notes two.
Scene three, sticky note three.
The swarmed queen, upon realizing
that her minions were slain,
awakens and engages the player in mortal combat.
However, our protagonist emerges victorious.
the battle with the swan queen. Scene three, sticky note three.
And our final scene, our final sticky note, the protagonist
gloriously returns to the village and is given rewards in
the form of bags of wheat or something like that. So,
We have this very simple story, this chain of events,
one flowing from the other, connected by cause and effect.
And we created a chain, but as you can imagine,
a single event doesn't need to cause a single other event.
It is absolutely possible to be the cause of multiple.
So we can create this sort of a web of cause and effect
relationships between plot points.
So once we create this web of relationships,
we can start writing our story
and start fleshing out our scenes.
So we can either go chronologically,
or from start to finish,
or we can scramble it about
and go all Quentin Tarantino on it.
But regardless of the methods that we use,
when the story is written, we have a very good idea
of what event causes which, and it makes us less likely
to have logical plot holes.
Well, I really like this method.
I figured, hey, let's see what happens.
So how did we translate our wall of sticky notes
into our quest building methods?
So we decided to represent a quest as a graph of steps.
Each step is a scene or a major event
in the greater plot of the quest.
Initially, only start steps are available to the player.
But as the player progresses through a quest,
meaning as the player completes the steps,
meaning as the player experiences the scenes
defined by the nodes of that graph,
different parts of the story open up before them or close.
And once the player reaches one of the end steps,
meaning experiences one of the end scenes,
the quest will end.
Now I'll show you a very simple example
of how that actually would work.
So the player starts their quest by talking to a villager
and being asked for help.
Now, after that, the start part of that quest
is finished, completed, done.
However, two options open before the player.
In the step A, in our scene A,
the player has the ability to go guns blazing
into the field and kill everything.
Or can instead try to approach the Swarm Queen
and maybe work out some sort of a solution.
Now, what is important here is that these two additional steps
are possibilities that the player gets.
And also, as you can see, there are no lines between them.
That means there is no relation between these two steps,
meaning the player is absolutely allowed
to first talk with a Swarm Queen and then
go into the field, kill stuff.
or first go guns blazing and then decide to talk to the swarm queen
or can actually ignore any of these branches altogether.
However, if the player decides to be aggressive and kill all the insects
then the option of slaying the swarm queen opens up before them.
And now, as you can see, there is a relation between talking with a swarm queen
and slaying the swarm queen.
That red line represents that if the player experiences
the scene in step B, the step C becomes impossible.
It is removed from the plot.
It is no longer accessible.
That, but, what is important,
there's no line in the other direction.
So the player is still able to talk with the Swarm Queen
and then be a douche and kill her.
But regardless of what they decide,
slaying her or talking with her,
the option to end the quest opens up before them.
So by traveling through this quest graph,
the player has multiple ways to progress through a quest,
and in turn, multiple personal narratives are possible.
And all of these possibilities are created
just by defining the cause and effect relationships
between scenes.
So the way this would work in practice is that the writer would imagine this web of possible events
where each event unlocks other possible events, in consequence, creating our probability space, the Kreutz graph.
The designer would have the same graph in their head,
however the nodes of that graph would have a very different context, a more rules-focused context.
But because the initial step would be the same,
meaning both the writer and the designer
would start with the graph and build on top of it,
there would be less translation needed
between the roles and the narrative.
So now we have a graph, our grand story structure,
but how does the player progress it?
So each step is understood as a scene,
and that scene must have a major verb
which defines what action the player needs to perform
in order to progress.
And sometimes we also define a target of that action.
So the player can obtain an item,
kill a monster, talk to an NPC,
and in our system we supported a finite amount
of these verbs.
I'll give you two very simple examples
of how that would work in practice.
So, the simple scene.
The player, after searching through rubble,
finally finds and picks up Amulet of Yendor.
Plus one for anyone who knows what Amulet of Yendor is.
So the major verb in this scene is pick up,
meaning the player takes and puts in their inventory.
And the object of that scene, the target of that action,
is the amulet of Yendor.
So in game logic, this would translate to obtain,
put in inventory, and the game object is amulet of Yendor.
Meaning once the player obtains,
puts in their inventory the amulet of Yendor,
the quest will progress.
Second very simple example.
In the arena, the player defeats all six opponents.
So the main verb here is defeat, which translates into
our game logic to kill.
And our six opponents, because we are in an arena, are
gladiators.
And there are six of them.
So once the player kills the sixth gladiator, the quest
will progress.
So to summarize all this.
Lists in Horizon Zero Dawn are built as a graph of steps,
possible plot points, which are linked together
by cause and effect and defined by actions
needed to be performed by the player.
So while using our methods, we managed to succeed
in some areas and not so much in others.
And I would like to tell you about
the most interesting cases.
So let's talk about the good stuff first.
So first of all, the graph structure did indeed assure
that we could create naturally and without any hacks
or workarounds non-linear quests.
Meaning everyone in the team involved in building quests
was thinking non-linearly and it was
our main mode of operation.
Secondly, having this limited set of verbs
which defined actions required to progress the quest
made it indeed simple to create our common types of quests.
However, because we supported a wide enough variety
of these verbs, we didn't hinder our ability
to create more sophisticated ones.
Another very interesting success that we got,
which was actually quite unexpected, was our player jobs.
So we noticed that certain simple patterns
which use specific verbs recur quite frequently.
And because our system was relatively strict,
we managed to automate creation of quests
based off such patterns.
And in the end, this ended up our player job system.
So we allow the player to generate a quest for themselves
during gameplay for certain particular purposes.
For example, bartering with a merchant or crafting an item.
So the player can choose a recipe, press a button,
and that will generate a quest which will guide the player
through obtaining all the necessary items
and then crafting the item.
However, from the perspective of a player,
a generated quest and a handcrafted quest
are not possible to distinguish.
And the most interesting problem that we faced,
that I really would like to talk about,
is...
the time travel problem. So when you read a book, when you watch a movie, when you read a
comic book, once a scene occurs, it occurred, right? When an event happens, it happened. It
cannot unhappen. It cannot unoccur. It's there in the timeline forever. It's there written on
these pages forever.
However, during gameplay, that's not always the case.
Sometimes, for the sake of clarity
and for the sake of not confusing the player,
and sometimes for the sake of streamlining the gameplay,
we allow for the story to roll back.
We allow the story to go to the previous state.
A good example of that happening in Horizon were our bandit camps.
So, bandit camps were very simple quests.
The player needs to find a bandit camp, the player needs to enter the bandit camp, and
the player needs to perform certain activities in that bandit camp, which is usually slaughtering
of innocent bandits.
And the thing is that because we had this open world
and paradigm in our heads and wanted to give player freedom,
once you enter the bandit camp,
it's absolutely possible to leave it.
But the story already progressed.
According to the plot, according to the quest log,
you have entered the bandit camp, kill all the bandits.
And leaving made it actually kind of confusing for the player what's next to happen.
So we needed to move the story back one step when the player left,
so that from the perspective of the player, they need still to reach that bandit camp and do whatever they need to do.
However, because our system was so deeply rooted in a story writing metaphor, that was not supported.
However, we realize that this is an issue
and we are currently working on fixing it
in a non-hacky, non-horrible way.
We managed to work around the issue in the end,
but we still are looking at a very appropriate solution.
So, to close this up.
The system that we created in our method served our purposes
quite well.
A team that never created a quest-based game before managed
to create almost 150 quests of various complexity.
And as I've been told, some of them
actually were quite well received.
And also we had these unexpected successes
of being able to create these player jobs, which
is one of the coolest quality of life features that we have.
But the system is not perfect.
We still need to improve it.
So we still need to fix our time travel problem.
And in the end, the list of verbs that we had
didn't sufficiently meet our needs.
Some were made redundant.
Some of them were overly specific.
But we'll just need to revise them,
and everything will be fine.
So that's it.
That's pretty much how we.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, if anybody has any questions,
I'm cool to answer or something.
Two minutes, two questions I guess.
Hello, so have you run into any problems
with the completionists?
Because in this web of possible actions in your quests,
there's always...
one way to get the most benefit of.
And people sometimes will feel like
I'm not playing the game 100%
if I don't go through all the possible steps
I can do certain quests.
Do you have any?
Well, the idea was to actually not...
make it not even possible to play the quest in all possible ways in one single sitting.
But for completion's sake, there were key points in every quest, like one of endings or something
like that, and these counted to the completion ratio of the whole game. So although we did
have non-linearity, we also had these choke points sometimes for these specific purposes.
Yeah, another question?
Yeah, just something quite interesting that you mentioned.
You mentioned a single player action,
you know, causing and having a causal reaction
on multiple threads in a way.
And in this complex graph, how much interplay is there
between the different threads in your graph
and how do you manage that complexity?
Because that can easily exponentially, you know, explode.
Okay, so the question was how do we manage actually
the complexity that the graph,
complexity grows exponentially with every node added.
But specifically with the interplay of,
if there is much interplay between the threads
in the quests, if that makes sense.
Yeah, essentially if I understand correctly,
if there's interplay between certain parts of a quest,
how do we manage the complexity of that?
Well, we have very good tools.
So essentially we create a specific editor
that allows the designer to see the state of a quest exactly,
which nodes are blocked, which are available,
which are completed during play through of a quest.
So by playing a couple of times
and seeing how everything lights up and lights down,
it's also possible to figure out
what is not going okay, what's not right.
Plus we had some debugging tools specific for these purposes.
But in the end, nobody created such complicated quests
that they were impossible to figure out what's wrong with them.
Okay, but there wasn't that much interplay between quests?
Between quests, not so much.
Okay, cool.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, if anybody has more questions,
I'll be in the wrap-up room further away in the corridor.
Thank you.