Um alright hey thanks for coming to our talk. My name is Patrick Hackett. This is Drew
Skillman and uh our talk is called 3 years of Tilt Brush. So uh really quick if you're
unfamiliar with Tilt Brush it's a virtual reality painting application. It's currently
available for the HTC Vive and the Oculus Rift with touch controllers. Um Drew and I
created Tilt Brush 3 years ago and for the next about 45 minutes we're gonna talk about
the point up until now.
So when we first started writing this talk,
what we did is we put together like a timeline,
like we laid out a timeline, took a bunch of events,
put them in chronological order,
and then as we went through them,
the story that came out of it,
what we realized is that it's just two naive game developers
applying game development principles
to a whole bunch of situations that were not video games.
And sometimes, a lot of times, it was very beneficial for us to think in this way.
And then there was other times where it was clear that, like, we didn't have a clue what
we were doing.
I just wanted to pause for a moment.
As a show of hands, like, who would identify in this room as a game developer?
Awesome.
That's a great mix.
Okay, but really the important part,
and really our hope of what you take out of this talk,
is that game development principles work outside of games.
And again, this talk is gonna cover
the past about three years.
So starting mostly in August 2014,
and then leading up till now, September 2017.
And we put in this timeline right at the bottom,
and we'll put dots on it so you can kinda follow along.
Awesome.
So before we get to Tilt Brush, I
want to talk about some of the back story
and give you guys some context on where we're coming from.
Patrick and I, we have our indie roots.
Really come from a game studio called Double Fine.
That's not far from here.
A lot of you may have heard of it.
We worked together there for probably eight years.
And that's really the story where the story begins. We stumbled into a project
For the connect called connect party later became or actually it was happy action theater
Then it later became connect party and that that without we didn't realize it at the time, but that
It was a magical moment where we kind of got pulled into this
This awesome world of mixing technology and art and game development and trying to push on new technologies
in just innovative new ways
We got so excited about it, we decided
to formalize these efforts.
We invented a name for ourselves.
We called ourselves the Department of Future Tech,
which was kind of a joke, but also really serious.
And we tried to get as much cutting-edge hardware
as we could.
You can see the Gamasutra article we wrote
was really just like begging people
to give us their crazy VR gear, their depth cameras,
their AR gear, we just wanted it all.
And we also jumped on the DK1 Oculus Kickstarter.
We immediately started doing late night game jams at work
with the two of us and a bunch of other people
from Double Fine.
Here's Tim Schafer, the head of that studio,
checking out just random prototype
we put together called Moon.
Here's a Razor Hydra duct taped to a Nerf gun.
And this I think is one of the first times
that a bunch of us got to try six degree of freedom tracking
for the first time, albeit, you know,
very mediocre six degree of freedom tracking.
So that's rotational plus positional.
And this is Paul Dubois, it's a pretty dark GIF,
but that's Paul Dubois, a coworker at Double Fine,
and he's on the Tilt Brush team now.
And you can see he's got some hydras duct taped to his head.
Actually, you probably can't see, but take my word for it.
So we're just playing around with all of these new toys
when suddenly there's a huge shift in the industry.
Can't really like, it caught us by surprise.
Facebook bought Oculus for two billion dollars.
This was the first signal that things were happening,
like it was not just like late night game jams anymore.
And around the same time, we were incredibly lucky
to get to try out Valve's Tag Room.
It was absolutely, vastly beyond any of our expectations.
Anyone who's had a chance to try it
knows how pivotal that moment was
and how transformative it was for the whole industry
and we're all here largely because of that Tag Room.
And around the same time, a coworker at Double Fine,
Lydia Choi, left to team up with ex-Bungie dev,
Brian Sharp, to build a virtual reality sculpting tool.
So over the course of just a few weeks,
it became super clear to us that there was a VR train
and it was leaving the station and we needed to be on it.
So that's what we did.
First lesson in being naive,
the train didn't leave for a little bit longer.
But we formed a company, called it Skillman and Hackett.
clearly influenced by watching too much Mad Men at the time.
Uh, and we got to work immediately. We weren't, we weren't really doing games. We had
this motto of not necessarily games.
We were doing a lot of the same stuff though, it was just, you know, a lot less people.
Uh, in fact we were working
down the block.
We were a block away working at a Drew's apartment.
And really at the time there was just a ton of room to explore. We picked up some contract work to pay the bills and then really just spent our remaining time mashing different pieces of hardware together.
In general at the time we were using the Kinect, Kinect 2, DK2, Hydra controllers, Leap Motion, cell phones, and then really just using Unity to glue all this stuff together.
So some random examples of like prototypes,
things we were making at the time.
We did a series of music visualizers
for what would eventually become the Gear VR.
We worked with Leap Motion.
At the time they had an update to their SDK coming out
that had greatly improved hand tracking.
And so we built a couple of like showpiece demos for them.
This is another one with Leap Motion,
but this was like VR in Leap Motion,
so it was taking the Leap Motion
and mounting it to the front of the DK2.
This was a user interface mock-up
for how you could manipulate a map in VR.
Another project we did was a collaboration
with Tyler Hurd.
We'd worked with Tyler at Double Fine previously.
He was now independent.
He made this short called Butts,
and we helped him bring it into VR.
And yeah, so that brings us to the point in the story
where we really stumble across virtual reality painting.
Here, this is one of the earliest gifs we have
of the prototype that would eventually become Tilt Brush.
And arriving at this prototype was really to quote
the great Bob Ross, it was the result
of some very happy accidents.
So,
I'm gonna describe to you the prototype
that we were trying to make,
and then share a couple of the happy accidents
that led us to virtual reality painting.
So this prototype, the idea was it would be,
this, I should, a little more background,
this was over the course of like probably one day.
So this was not a serious prototype.
This was just like a what might happen thing.
The idea was, take a chess game.
use an iPad as input, but you're wearing a DK2 headset,
and then if you can track the position of the iPad
in 3D space, then you can use it as input,
and you can reach out and touch in VR
and move chess pieces around.
So the chess pieces could be rendered in virtual reality
coming off of the iPad.
You could reach out, move stuff around.
At least that was the idea.
The first happy accident is that it's way easier
to use a Wacom tablet as input for a Unity experiment
than it is an iPad.
It's like, oh, the Wacom just behaves like a mouse,
you're done.
So in the spirit of working fast,
we substituted the iPad for a Wacom.
And the second happy accident is that I added
debug trail rendering lines to the chess pieces
because they were, of course, broken and behaving
in all these weird ways.
So now I've got...
So now I've got a stylus and I'm moving chess pieces around,
but the chess pieces are leaving these ribbons in the air
in that perfect sweet spot.
Because if you've done, you know, like positional,
you know, full six off VR tracking,
you know that there's this sweet spot right in front of you
where it just feels absolutely amazing.
And that's exactly where I was drawing.
And we had, you know, these are the same ribbons
that we've been using for the last,
what are five, six years on every single game we made
and every single prototype we made.
It was all using just ribbon rendering and visual effects
and particles and layering all this stuff on top of it.
And then the last point is that
you could rotate this chessboard
and then move the chess pieces around.
And so now you really were drawing in 3D space,
but absolutely by accident.
Bob Ross would be very, I think, proud, I like to think.
And really one of the reasons that I'm such a proponent
of rapid prototyping is that they really do let you
find these happy accidents.
And also, if you do a bunch of prototypes,
it can help develop your intuition,
which is a point I wanna stop on for a moment.
Rapid prototyping, it builds your intuition.
So we'd been working as fast as we could
for the last four months, and we'd done a ton of prototypes,
and that gave us the perspective
so that when we saw this one, we knew it was special,
we knew it needed to be pursued.
The question is, what next?
So we have a prototype we're really excited about.
Where is it gonna go?
And there were a few things we had going for us
in terms of providing context for where we could take this.
And the first was we had a music visualizer UX experiment
that Patrick had made from much earlier in the summer.
And it explored keyboard mouse input with the DK2 headset.
Now back in these days, there was no VR controller,
like those didn't exist yet.
So keyboard mouse was really the only thing
you had to work with.
And this experience was really compelling.
It was kind of surprising, but it worked remarkably well.
And this UI would become kind of the signature Tilt Brush UI.
And the second thing we had was a really cool additive
kind of particle bloom-based style that was built up,
I mentioned, from many years of experimentation.
And we'd done enough prototyping in VR with it
to know that it would work really well.
It was like a very, very obvious fit.
Just take all the work we'd been doing
and slap it on the lines that were coming
from this Wacom stylus.
And third.
We were still super good friends with the team
that had left Double Fine to work on that virtual reality
sculpting tool, and now that tool
is maturing into Oculus Medium.
And everyone's simmering in the same crate of juices.
You can see we're all lined up around Brandon Street,
just a few blocks away from here.
And so we knew that there was a precedent being set
for VR art tools, and that helped us connect the dots
along with the ribbon rendering,
and along with the other work we'd been doing.
So we started to paint a picture
of where we might be able to take this.
We still had a lot of questions over whether painting
would be viable as a form of VR content creation,
but we knew we wanted to give it a shot.
Right, okay, so Drew throws this prototype over the wall.
At the time, it's literally named VRChess.zip.
And I say over the wall because the dirty secret
of Skillman and Hackett was at that time,
we didn't have source control.
And so we're passing this thing back and forth.
In this GIF, the first thing that I added,
you could see the first glimpse of the UI.
It's fixed flat in front of you.
There's a color picker, some different brushes.
So we continued to work on this for a couple of days,
and we got a very well-timed email from Johnny Ross.
If you don't know Johnny, he's the co-founder of Mindshow,
which is a really great storytelling VR application.
We'd met Johnny at an early San Francisco VR meetup,
exchange contact info.
At the time, he was running VRLA,
and he contacted us because he had an idea for another event.
He was setting up the Proto Awards, which was going to be the first virtual reality
award show.
He wanted it to coincide with Oculus Connect One, reaching out to people he knew to see
if he could dig up some entries.
Luckily for him, we did have something we wanted to submit, and unluckily for us, really
what we had was a two-day-old prototype, and the conference was in three weeks.
So these kinds of forced deadlines were common to us
from games and to be honest, better or worse,
they're a hell of a motivator.
We really thought that the proper unveiling of Tilt Brush
could be at Oculus Connect with the submission
to the award show, maybe we win an award.
And so to do that, we wanted to put together
all the materials of a proper product.
So we needed, in three weeks, a name, a logo,
a website, a trailer, and we actually had to get this thing
to a point that we could submit it to an award show.
So we got to work.
All right.
Names are hard in general.
These are some chat snippets I dug up.
And we had a lot of bad names.
Virtuous Sketch, Super SketchBox.
I remembered looking through this that at one point
I woke up and I was positive.
I came up with the perfect name.
I was so excited.
Told Drew it should definitely be called SketchUp.
Drew reminded me is a very good application that already exists. Uh we liked Tilt Brush
initially when we came up with it but honestly we thought it was a little bit too limiting
because we recognized that this application could be much more than painting.
For the logo, we worked with Drew's sister and brother-in-law who run a graphic design
studio outside of Seattle.
They had already done the logo for Skillman and Hackett, and we, whatever, we bought them
a really nice bottle of whiskey to kind of expedite the order through.
When I was looking through old email, I thought it was funny that I was concerned the colors
in that first logo were a little too Google.
And also you can see that I was I got pretty excited when I actually saw the one that would become our logo
And really I apologize for the cursing in these slides like we didn't really expect to be presenting this stuff ever
We weren't trying to come up with a slogan but uh
Drew came up with a slogan one time and so we mocked it up to see you know how it looked
Looks pretty good to us.
Couldn't use it.
And then we got a trailer cut.
And so, it's important to remember that this was,
this was made for the DK2.
It was centered around keyboard and mouse.
You can see the old UI in this video if you look closely.
It was based on sitting at a desk
and so the UI was this cockpit experience around you.
It's fundamentally different from what you would experience
if you've tried this on the Rift or the Vive.
And that was it.
All the pieces done, ready for OC1.
So yeah, as Patrick said, we got it together.
Name, logo, website, trailer,
and an actual playable prototype
as opposed to the two day old experiment that we had.
And we jump on a plane and we head to Oculus Connect One.
The first thing we do is we set up camp in the demo area
and we skip every talk and we just start putting
every single person we can find
through this hot off the presses demo.
And a bunch of things were really special
about that first Oculus Connect.
There's an electricity in the air.
Anyone who was there knows that it was just like
a very special time.
But there are two connections in particular
that were critical to the future of Skillman and the Hackett
and also to Tilt Brush,
although we didn't know it at the time.
First was Chet Faliszek, who I'm sure many of you know.
We tried to track him down and did,
and had to convince him to let us put it on Steam.
You know, for those not familiar,
Chet has had this huge role getting the whole VR industry
off the ground, and he's definitely
a big part of why Tilt Brush exists today.
Second connection we made was Andrei Deronichev.
He's a product manager at Google.
And I think Tilt Brush would have existed without Andrei,
but it never would have become part of Google,
and it never would have received the global recognition that
followed after we joined.
Okay, so we weren't actually just there to play test
and put it in front of people,
we were there for the Proto Awards.
That was the big motivator and the source
of this kind of deadline that we imposed on ourselves.
And Tilt Brush had been nominated for Best GUI,
which ended up being the first award that was announced,
and we won.
But we were woefully unprepared.
I think I remember being shocked and surprised and going up there with Patrick.
I think that I swore and Patrick thanked his mom or something.
But it's worth really calling out that what this ended up being for us was one big play
test.
You know, the importance of play testing is one of the most important and critical lessons
we took away from our time at Double Fine.
And we were paying super close attention to the expression of like every single person's face after they tried the demo,
looking for responses, trying to see what people liked.
And at the Proto Awards, you know, we saw that Tilt Brush resonated with the jury.
On social media, it blew up.
You can see that unexpectedly,
we'd left this experimental slogan
somewhere on our website,
and it was getting scraped by social media.
We felt embarrassed about that.
The launch video hit 100,000 views within a few days,
and so the results of this public play test were clear.
The world was interested in virtual reality painting,
and we wanted to give them more of it.
It's also worth calling out.
that this was the moment when we really stopped being a rapid pro prototyping team and pivoted
to become a true product team. Alright so now we're home from OC1 uh we're going to
Very excited about the positive response,
itching to get back to work.
At this point, we're in about start of October 2014.
We're moving really fast,
adding a bunch of features, features, features.
These GIFs show off a bunch of different brushes
that Drew was experimenting with at the time.
And we started really having long conversations about what a brush could be.
We proved that ribbons were satisfying, but what if brushes were particles?
What if they were light?
What if they were sound or models or behaviors?
We started adding features like the ability to export animated GIFs, to import models,
real-time lighting.
And while we're adding all these features,
we made it a point to go to like every single local VR meetup
to show off the build, get feedback,
meet everybody else in the scene.
It really was this large running user test with the public.
And around early October, we received a mysterious summons
from Valve.
They invited us to Seattle, didn't offer much information.
You're not going to say no.
And at this point, this meeting is fairly well documented.
It was the unveiling of the Lighthouse technology
to a small number of developers.
a chance to give feedback and kind of an ask to, you know, do you want to participate in
what will be the unveiling of this new headset built by HTC. It was an awesome couple of
days of brainstorming with, you know, like-minded VR folks. But what this resulted in was Skillman
and Hackett obtaining a V-1 Vive headset.
So we had officially achieved the unthinkable goal
of getting tag room quality VR in Drew's apartment.
So by every metric that mattered to us two,
our company was an outstanding success.
It also meant that we had to rethink our entire
applications user interface.
The six DOF controllers were way better
than we expected them to.
And remember, like, Tilt Brush was this
desktop based experience.
You build things right here.
And the possibilities that room scale VR gave us
were totally uncharted.
And so we had to rethink all of these things.
At the time, I sent an email to all the other developers
explaining that we got our kit set up.
And I included this image to show how we felt at the time.
It's Neil Armstrong.
Unfortunately, now we're getting into November,
we've been focusing full time on Tilt Brush,
and we hadn't been doing any contract work.
So that means we didn't have any income.
But what we did have.
was a plan for not only how to build out Tilt Brush
as an application, but how to build it out
as this ecosystem.
Part of this ecosystem relied on lots of users
consuming these VR sketches.
And at the time, we were really convinced
that if you create something in Tilt Brush,
it should only be viewed in VR.
So we needed a product that could reach a lot of users.
There's no better candidate than that,
than Google Cardboard.
So we reached out to Andre.
I asked him for an embarrassing picture,
and that's what he gave me.
And lucky for us, Google at the time,
they had a big cardboard push
that was coming that December.
So we worked with them and got Tilt Brush Gallery
ready for their event.
Tilt Brush Gallery was a cardboard application
where you could view a fixed number of sketches
that Drew and I had done.
They were all preloaded on the application.
Doing this was another big force sprint for us.
But the work that we were doing was also
going to be immediately beneficial,
because we had to turn our attention to the Vive
shortly after that and start optimizing
for 90 frames a second.
So, uh, as Patrick said, we got the cardboard version of the app launched, or at least a
demo of what it might be. Um, and next on our list was, uh, seeing what would happen when we
took the keyboard mouse version and really pushed on those six DOF, uh, six DOF
controllers, those six degree of freedom controllers. Uh, Valve, uh,
offered us an opportunity, a super generous offer to go hang out with them in the
Bellevue office and embed ourselves with the VR team and see what we can make
happen. It was an incredible, incredible generous offer. We took them up on it and
we called it Valve Camp. So our goal was to build a GDC demo experience. The
reward, if we were successful, was going to be inclusion in Valve's GDC showcase
and the unveiling of the Vive.
But we'd only have two weeks to do it, two weeks in valve camp. Uh, the experience
itself needed to fit inside of a three minute window, kind of a three minute time box. And
of course our approach was to lean on those, you know, indie lessons from Double Fine and
uh, in our independent days. Work hard, focus test constantly and iterate like mad.
But Tilt Brush in its current form was way too complicated.
We put people in front of it and play tested it on Valve
employees and other people.
And it was just way too much for people to wrap their
heads around.
All these features, they didn't make sense to people.
in classic style, we cut, cut, cut.
We really just cut everything.
Our goal was to distill the core
of whatever was making Tilt Brush resonate with people
and cut away all the fat, cut away everything
that was distracting from that experience.
And so goodbye refractive brushes,
goodbye audio brushes, goodbye lighting,
goodbye model import, goodbye volumetric brushes,
just cut, cut, cut.
But it was worth it.
Those cuts were replaced with a massively simplified paintbrush and palette style interface.
We tried probably ten different types of true VR six degree of freedom interfaces,
but no one was able to wrap their heads around them in the three minute window.
That three minute window ended up being so crucial to honing the experience.
But the paintbrush palette interface, it was working.
It was coming in blazingly hot towards the very, very end
of that two week period, but we were feeling good about it.
Our confidence was growing.
We asked Chet for one last play test,
and he offhandedly said he had someone in mind.
So we go back to our desk, we're ripping apart the build,
and we get a tap on the shoulder,
and it's, to our surprise, Valve CEO Gabe Newell
is our last play tester.
And the funny thing about VR play tests
is that the person in the headset
can't see the developers.
And that means you don't have to mask your expression.
So you've got a picture of Patrick and I
watching Gabe in the demo and just making a face like,
ah, while we watch Gabe start to use
the new interface and brushes.
And we also didn't have to hide our relief when
he said that he liked it.
And when Gabe Newell says that he likes something,
you feel pretty good about it.
So at that point, we called it.
GDCdemo was done.
and we headed back to San Francisco. Uh, in our carry ons, we had new upgraded V0 prototype
hardware to play with, did a week of bug fixing and then the vibe was unveiled. Uh, this was
another one of those super special times where my old apartment turned into one of the most
like futuristic studios in all of San Francisco, at least for a few weeks. Uh, we were trying
all the other devs demos. We're trying alchemy stuff, all kinds of things. You can see Patrick
is fishing in the top right corner there.
And the VIVE reception couldn't have been better.
It was enormously positive that year at GDC.
And Tilt Brush made it into the GDC demo loop
and was receiving tons of great press because of it.
All right, so now we are post-GDC, March 2015.
What do we do now?
Reception at GDC was really stellar.
It was clear to us that
continued effort pushing on it, Tilt Brush could be a huge success.
It was still the two of us at the time, which is great for keeping overhead low,
but also, you know, limits the speed we can move.
And contract work was really just not appealing anymore.
We wanted to just keep working on Tilt Brush.
What are our options?
Being in San Francisco, going to these meetup scenes,
we're often encouraged, strongly encouraged,
to take on VC money, so that was certainly a ready option.
Joining a larger company would provide resources
for the team, or we'd just keep moving forward
as we'd been going.
We'd pick up some contract work, try to pay the rent,
and then just do as much as we can in our free time.
This was hard.
We thought leaving Double Fine to start a company was hard.
It was actually very hard.
This was a magnitude harder.
So what do we have to consider here?
First and foremost, we live in San Francisco.
It's expensive.
Contract work is gonna require time.
All the time we put toward that
pulls away from Tilt Brush.
Creative ownership is an absolute must.
I mean, honestly, it's how we ended up in this position in the first place.
It's why we created Skillman and Hackett.
And this was a unique project.
We'd done, as Drew said, we'd done lots of prototypes.
We knew, we recognized that this one was going to be special, and we thought that it truly
deserved care.
So on April 16, we announced that we had joined the Google
VR team.
We had a lot of conversations with Andre and his team about
the direction of the industry.
It was clear that where we hoped it would go, they hoped
it would go.
Andre really recognized that Tilt Brush was unique.
This move would allow us to keep the lights on.
And the important part to us was that we were going to hold
creative control over the project.
So really, in Google, we had found a perfect match
for Tilt Brush and a partner that we could
grow this industry with.
So that brings us to April 2015.
And we had those kind of like broad meta questions,
where are we going, how are we gonna do this,
what are we doing, we had them figured out,
but that meant that it was time to get back to work.
We had to ship Tilt Brush.
The tentative date for the Rift and the Vive
were the holidays, so we knew that we had
about eight months to integrate ourselves
and our work into this new company,
turn the demo, the GDC demo,
into an actual product and launch.
Our strategy was going to, again,
be to apply those indie game dev lessons
from our previous lives of rapid prototyping, fast iteration,
extensive play testing.
But we just had to do it at Google.
And everybody was on board with that.
People were excited for us to kind of bring
the approach that had been so successful
in our independent studio to Google.
But it was less clear how to do it.
And a big question is, would it work at a company like Google?
One of the first hurdles was really understanding just how
to apply them at all.
Patrick and I had never worked at a big company before.
And we were, let's say, a bit naive, or a lot naive.
And one of my favorite examples of this is our
approach to getting help modeling our environments.
This was right at the beginning.
We just started at Google, and we just needed to make some
more environments.
It seemed pretty simple.
So our idea was let's just hire our good friend and collaborator, Tyler Hurd.
We'd done VRButts with him.
We'd been working with him for a while.
And this is how the collaboration worked when it was independent and
we were working with him on Butts.
Said, hey Tyler, you wanna work together?
He said, sure, send the contract over.
And this is what the contract was.
It was made in Microsoft Paint.
And equally good is the file name.
Um.
So, so this was just, this is a good example of kind of where we were coming from.
And Google legal team, the Google legal team is really, really, really, really great.
They're really great.
They soften the blow, and this is not a joke, they soften the blow with homemade cookies.
You guys cannot do this anymore.
You are at Google.
You can't make contracts and MS Pay anymore.
So that was one hurdle.
Then we also needed to accomplish a bunch of firsts
for the first time.
And we had to do it before the holidays.
We needed to launch on an engine that was new to Google.
We needed to launch on hardware that was new to Google.
And we needed to launch on a distribution platform, Steam,
that was also totally new to Google.
And Patrick and I really didn't understand the magnitude
of these challenges.
Again, we were naive.
We're coming at it from mile a minute indie development.
Who cares?
I'm just paying contracts.
Get it done.
And luckily, Google stepped up immediately and they helped us.
It turned into a big team effort with a lot of folks
behind the scene pushing to make this happen.
And so we were able to get these firsts accomplished at Google,
but it was way harder than we expected.
Another challenge was growing the team.
Around this time, VR was exploding.
People from games were getting absorbed into VR left and
right, and it was super hard to actually just go from the
two of us to a team like we'd imagined.
It ended up taking a lot longer than we expected.
One of the great things about life at
Google is Google scale.
Google operates at this massive scale, and it afforded
us some really special and unexpected opportunities.
Uh, one of them is that we got to collaborate on this mixed reality launch
trailer with a visual effects team and a creative agency that did work on the
Martian, uh, which was, you know, coming from, I have a visual effects
background, so I was super excited about this opportunity.
Um, we actually gave them like, we approached it in a very indie fashion.
We gave them our source code.
So they had our unity project.
And they were, you can see this is behind the scenes footage
from the shoot, they're doing camera matching
and then re-rendering from Unity
and compositing things back together.
It had that like indie vibe approach,
but it was way bigger and more coordinated effort.
Another great example is that when we joined Google,
they sat us next to the Google Data Arts team, which
you may be familiar with some of their work.
And if not, you should check it out.
They do incredible, incredible things.
And they sat us down right next to these guys.
And so of course, through hallway conversations,
we just ended up doing a collaboration that was
called Virtual Art Sessions.
And they had two connects on the opposite side of the room.
They would capture artists volumetrically,
capture all their paint.
And they built the whole thing into a WebGL experience
that you can go check out.
Again, massively bigger in scope than anything we would have bitten off ourselves.
We did a collaboration with Glen Keane, legendary Disney animator, and worked with him on a
future of storytelling presentation.
And in addition to kind of resulting in a video that went viral and exposed a bunch
of people to Tilt Brush for the first time, I got to try my hand as a roadie.
You can't see me, but I'm in the darkness back there running back and forth.
Right before this video gets taken, someone, another stagehand steps on a power supply
and shuts down the Vive.
And I was like trying not to throw up as I clicked buttons and rebooted machines and
was waiting to see.
Because this was back when...
everything was just so hot off the presses. You never knew what was going to happen. It was
absolutely terrifying. We even did a Mountain Dew NBA collaboration. Definitely,
definitely not indie. So yeah, a bunch of examples of Google scale there.
And really the way, you know, looking back,
the way I see it is we went through trial by fire.
We had nine months of really tremendously
hard growing pains, but we came out of it
on the other side with a 1.0 Tilt Brush release.
But way more important than that is at this point
we had a team, it wasn't just the two of us.
We were shipping Tilt Brush with the team
and it was, you know, it was better than we could
have imagined thanks to all the new faces
that we had working with us now.
All right, so now we're into 2016.
We're a little bit more comfortable,
really trying to retain this independent spirit.
In particular, we maintained a really fast pace,
instrumenting six-week sprints, led to a lot of launches,
and us bringing back all of those features we had cut.
brought back animated gif export, export to FBX,
added a teleport tool, which was a huge oversight
to begin with.
Later in the year, we added the ability to scale
and rotate the scene, started building out more pro tools.
And a pain that we kind of just had to become accustomed to was we are now in full production on live product
And this means that it is of the highest priority
It still is the highest priority that we do not break existing art
So any new change that we put in can't affect the art that was created in a previous build
Before you know we had launched we could safely prototype scrap throw things away whole concepts doesn't matter
But now we had to live with these choices
In addition, we were rewriting huge sections of the code
because you can imagine,
this was all like prototype quality code
and you can't build off of that.
and we were hurtling walls.
Drew and I had this motto during the Skillman Hackathon
that you run as fast as you possibly can,
and if you hit a wall, you just turn and keep running.
Unfortunately, we're now in a place
where we had to solve those hard problems.
So you can't just turn, you have to hurtle these walls.
Or as we like to joke, sometimes you're running so fast,
you just blow right through the wall.
We continued to prototype as much as possible, though.
Most of these prototypes will never see the light of day.
This was a prototype I did for a Connect the Dots game
that would be inside Tilt Brush.
It was pretty much as fun as Connect the Dots is.
This was a portal brush that using the camera
on the front of the Vive allowed users
to peek out into the real world.
This was an early version of constraining brush strokes to planes or other shapes. And this
would actually eventually ship as our guides feature. Early version of the audio reactive
mode. And another early version of a feature that just shipped a quick tool interface.
So in addition to prototyping like mad, we were still play testing like mad.
Again, the indie spirit at Google wanted to keep it alive.
And it had gotten us really far.
We talked about how it was huge, Oculus Connect 1, really defined Tilt Brush those two weeks
at Valve Camp.
It was through those play tests that Tilt Brush really
took its final shape.
And at Google, we wanted to go even bigger.
We wanted to play test on casual users.
We wanted to play test on our peers, our co-workers,
other Googlers.
But we also wanted to try something new.
We wanted to see if we could see what would happen when we
play tested and worked with some of the world's most
accomplished and impressive artists.
And we did it through a program called Artists in Residence.
And so through this program, we engaged with about 60 artists
and worked with people, well, people like Glenn King,
who I talked about earlier.
On the right here, this is Victory Dance by him.
And this was before we had World Transform.
So every one of these strokes, Glenn
had to actually walk to and place in room scale, which
is a crazy time to think about.
Like he probably walked 10 miles to make this sketch
over the course of a week.
He was crawling, climbing on things.
It was just a demonstration of this grit
that the world's best artists have.
It's unbelievable.
And he would give us feedback
in the form of beautiful drawings
and sketches of strokes he wanted
or brushes that he wanted to be able to use.
Another great collaborator was Peter Chan.
He's another legend.
He did a bunch of work at LucasArts and Double Fun Games.
He's worked on a bunch of Hollywood movies.
And this piece is called The Rescue,
and it's the opposite.
We worked with him while we were developing
the World Transform feature.
And so he used this world transform feature
to build this huge kind of like epic snowscape
that completely brought Tilt Brush to its knees.
It was so massive.
It runs at 90 frames a second,
but it takes a little while to load.
So we need to optimize our loading before we can share that.
And here's some feedback we got from Peter.
Again, it's just beautiful getting feedback from artists.
Chris Pernowski from Tipmouse did this sprawling comic that you explored and like walked around
room scale reading these panels.
He also took incredible notes and we captured, we used Chris for some promotional footage
and so he actually wrote this in his notebook which I think is hilarious.
Write fake notes in notebook for shoot.
I am writing these notes now.
And again, another collaboration with Tyler Hurd.
I'll let the GIF do the talking on this one,
because it's really weird.
It's weird and great.
Siguyn Chung is a New York City based artist,
and she does beautiful work,
but she also really pushed us on our export.
She was asking for splines that she could bring
into the rest of her workflows.
Just a cool example of some of the unusual things
that artists ask for that maybe a regular play tester
wouldn't.
So all this art and tons more is on the tiltbrush.com slash air website.
I think it's an incredible reflection of, of Google scale.
And it's also something that never would have happened as the two of us and a
little tiny, my old apartment.
Um,
I want to take a moment and call out the incredible team
behind this program.
Again, Patrick and I could not have done this.
This is like tons of people making things happen at
Google, and those people who built this program and the
artists who participated in it had this pivotal and critical
role in defining the path that Tilt Brush would take.
So that's like an example of Google scale, right?
On the opposite side, when we're working at Double Fine
and more generally in the video game,
or independent game scene, we learned how important it is
to participate in and really take care of your community.
We spent a lot of time doing this at Skillman and Hackett,
attending all the local meetups and meeting folks,
and we really tried to carry these ideas into Google.
In particular, I spend a lot of time on Twitter.
This is a capture of TweetDeck.
where I search for Tilt Brush as one word and two words
because people aren't consistent with it.
We also maintain Tilt Brush at Google.com,
which is very strange for Google.
They do not normally have public facing emails
for their internal products,
but it's been an enormous help for us
to communicate with the community.
Glowing example of this is having a Twitter conversation with a gentleman named Tim Adley.
He had reverse engineered our save file format a long time ago, was creating 3D models with
it, followed up over email, and well, eventually we hired him.
I also maintain a ridiculous spreadsheet of feature requests.
It's in no way scientific, but it's a great pulse on feature requests that come in through
that email or through Twitter.
And this really does help shape our future roadmaps.
And really the only reason I'm showing all this stuff is to emphasize that the community
should help shape your product.
We've said this a few times before, but at Skillman and Hackett, we gained so much from
attending all those local VR meetups, so we wanted to pay this forward a little bit.
So we hold developer meetups at our office, where we let people demo their experiences
that they're building, or just eat pizza.
This was kind of a scary moment.
This was the moment that our community kind of started to take on a life of its own.
Marvel worked with three artists, Danny Bittman, Steve Teeple, and Stuart Campbell
to create promotional art for their upcoming Doctor Strange movie.
Now, like the art they did was amazing, but the crazy part
about this is we didn't have any idea that they were doing it.
And we didn't know about it until the sketch was done and they sent it to us.
It's like, hey, check this out.
And it was this sobering moment where we recognized that people were making a living off of this
tool that we're building and maintaining.
And I really like to think that the lessons that we learned about community management
from the independent game scene has had just a huge influence on the product.
You know, it's really the dialogue with your community that allows us as product creators
to empower the real storytellers.
So that brings us to January 2017.
Team has jelled.
We're pitting our stride.
We've kind of figured out how we can operate at Google.
It was a challenge, but we figured it out.
And that means that now we can move way faster than we were.
And we're doing all kinds of cool things.
We're pushing in new directions.
We launched something called the Tilt Brush Toolkit,
which lets anyone bring tilt brush art into Unity
and preserves shaders and materials.
The purpose of this is to allow people to breathe life
into their tilt brush art.
So some examples here on the left is a music video
that Titmouse Animation did.
And on the right is a game called Palo's Wing
that was published on Steam.
We're also launching fast, and the launches are bigger now.
They're a lot bigger.
We've launched on Oculus.
We're adding new lighting features, custom environments,
detachable panels, a bunch of polish.
And we finally got to something that was on a roadmap
30 slides ago, sharing.
We got deep sharing integration.
And what that meant is that anyone
can share sketches and view sketches
from VR.google.com slash sketches.
And we even have support for other Google products inside of
Tilt Brush.
This is the Blocks library, which is support for Google
Blocks that happened in our most recent launch.
So that's it.
So two and a half years in,
and we've been running this grand experiment with Google,
and we've proven that it can be successful.
We've capitalized on the benefits of Google Scale,
tried to really maintain these core principles
we pulled from the game industry
and from Skillman and Hackett.
And we hope that these are lessons to show
that these game development principles
can be used outside of games
in very different atmospheres.
And it's also a validation of prototyping as an exercise for production and recognizing
when you should really drop everything and start running at an idea.
So we want to say thanks, but really quick before we jump to questions, a couple things.
Okay, it's common in games to have a credit section and a special thanks section.
So we wanted to let you know that there's a hidden credits
sketch in Tilt Brush that as far as we know
has never been found.
And we're not gonna tell you how to find it,
but I just wanted to let you know that it exists.
And likewise, we want to, I mean, there's so many people
that were pivotal in Skelman & Hackett
until like the last three years
have been this wild, wild ride,
this incredible rollercoaster.
But I do want to thank a few people
who were pivotal in the creation
of our indie studio, Skelman & Hackett.
That's Tim Schafer, Aaron Davies,
and as mentioned earlier, our friends on the Medium team.
And a huge shout out to Chet Falicek and Andrei Deronichev.
who saw something special in Tilt Brush and actually did things that brought it to life
and I honestly don't think we'd be standing here without them. So, tons more people to
thank, tons more people. I see you out there. Thank you.
Thank you.
Yeah, so questions?
I think we've got a few minutes.
So I'm a designer, not an engineer.
So I don't necessarily get into arguments
about tabs versus spaces or Unity versus Unreal.
But you did mention that Tilt Brush
was being built within Unity.
Is that still the basis of what the product is constructed in?
Or have you gone lower level?
Yeah, no, that's a fantastic question.
We are still built in Unity.
We've been optimizing aggressively in order to like,
in order to accommodate the work that people make,
which has been explosively growing in scale.
But we haven't hit the limit of what we're able to do
inside of Unity yet.
There's still optimizations to be made.
There's still a lot of room for us to grow there.
So currently we're still in Unity, yeah.
So I actually tried Tilt Brush, I love it.
It's an awesome program, it's very immersive,
and I spent hours and hours with it.
But my question is more on,
because I'm also looking at Quill,
so I'm wondering what your guys' thoughts are on Quill,
and maybe where you see,
if you're going in the same direction,
or if you're not going in the same direction,
where are you taking Tilt Brush?
Yeah, that's a fantastic question.
I love Quill.
Incidentally, I had that picture of like,
Double Fine, Skelman & Hackett, Medium,
also that's Quill, and it came later in the story,
but that's also where Quill is,
so we had lots of conversations with Inigo
and those guys, they're incredible.
I think that for us, Tilt Brush,
we've just taken a little bit of a more broad view
on what a brush can be.
I'm not gonna speak for Inigo or the Quill team,
but from the outside, it looks like they're very
laser focused on unlit strokes and animation.
I've seen a lot of animation, but they're really,
it has a very beautiful, beautiful, specific look.
In Tilt Brush, we've taken much, I think, more,
open-ended approach to brushes.
Patrick mentioned that earlier, we were like,
what can a brush be?
Like once you're in VR and you're laying strokes down,
well those strokes can turn into anything.
We've really tried to push that in terms of particles,
unlit brushes, lit brushes, animated brushes,
objects, lighting, set design.
So that's really like kind of where we've been focused
in our efforts.
But I think they're, you know, Quill's a beautiful tool.
So I like it too.
Thanks.
I wanted to ask about the impact.
of your product, not that you've generated necessarily,
but that the artists that use your product generate.
So the first part of it would be,
what's the biggest impact that you've seen
from artists that use your product so far
and in the future, you know, like a pencil, for instance,
has a big impact, not by the person who made the pencil,
but by the people who use it.
and this is really a new medium.
Sorry to use that word.
And so I'm curious how you plan on evolving your tool
to allow artists to have impacts,
whether that means like entering into the movie industry
or the video game industry,
or having Donald Trump sign a new executive order
in Tilt Brush or whatever it is.
That's an idea.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, I think the answer there is consumption.
And I think that that is almost a VR level problem.
Like I said at the start, we're like, oh,
if you build in Tilt Brush, you should only view it in VR.
But then we saw how powerful it was to.
for people to integrate Tilt Brush
into their standard pipelines.
So we added export features and a lot of care
so that you could take it out of Tilt Brush.
And then we even added much later
the ability to share to the web
and so now you can view sketches on your phone.
And so I think to maximize impact, you need to maximize that part of it.
You need to maximize the ability for someone to use Tilt Brush or Quill or
any other VR content creation application, and then get it out.
I'll just add that I for me when I'm working on Tilt Brush, I like to I
Nostalgically think back to like as a kid using like super paint and Mac paint and like these little pick giant pixels
Maybe it's a 200 by 200 canvas or whatever and the tool was the tool was ridiculously immature, but it still
Made me think in a way that I think my brain was ready when like actual art creation on computers happened
and so
I don't see it necessarily as a short-term effort, but it's more like you said, like
with the AIR program in particular, our biggest goal is just to legitimize it as a new medium.
We want people to understand it's a new medium and to be thinking about how it will impact
their lives, even though, you know, who knows, like how that impact will ramp up, but it
feels like it's on a, you know, there's only, it's growing and it's going to be changing
people's lives.
Thank you.
This is less a question and more just a comment, but really love
till brush first tried it at a private valve demo. And I think
my exact comment was this is the coolest shit I've ever seen.
And work at the NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
We actually use it to prototype UX for AR, VR experiences
that we build.
So not all of them, but occasionally we'll go into it
and we'll say, well, what do we want?
And we'll start drawing it out until brush, and then we can
actually go and refine it and build it in our own tools.
But it's a really great way to sketch that out.
So thanks for making something like that possible.
Yeah, that's awesome.
That's incredible.
Let us know what you need, what's broken.
We don't want any rockets crashing.
Hey, uh, so given that we now have ARKit and ARCore, have you thought about building Tilt Brush in AR?
Yeah, I mean, we've always talked about, uh, uh, we want to build tilt brush for whatever
platforms make sense. You know, like, um, we built that cardboard viewer a long time ago,
uh, tilt brush gallery, uh, a long time ago, but it didn't ever make sense for us to try to
build a creation experience for cardboard because we feel that it requires six off head
tracked, six off controllers. Thank you.
Hi, I love the tilt brushes selection of the paints,
but also the UX decisions and how it uses
the metaphor of the palette.
And since you guys are so, one of the very early VR apps
that was available, I was curious what your process
was like and how long it took to arrive
at that sort of decision.
Yeah, that mostly happened at ValveCamp.
You know, like when we showed up there, we had this DK2 version that was all cockpit.
And I think we had a slide in there that we pulled out that
was making fun of ourselves for not capturing more...
like iterative footage from that time because a lot of our, um, a lot of the things we tried
would show up later. You know, what we first had, okay, the panels are around you. And then we
thought, well, you're in this room scale experience. Maybe they just float. Maybe they just hang out
and you can move them around, but then people didn't know how to interact.
We tried what we refer to as Batman belt,
where you press a button and they attach to
what we could guess is your hips,
and then you do this, but it was distracting.
Flavors of all of those that had springs attached to them
that would follow you around.
And eventually it just, whatever.
You know, like, let's try one more thing
where we just, you know, dismiss this controller.
I think there may have even been a time
when we were talking about Tilt Brush
would be a one controller application.
And we thought, well, let's use it and maybe attach the panels to it.
And then things grew out of that.
Yeah.
It was really, I mean, to your point, it was very unexpected.
We didn't think that prototype was going to work.
We were just really lucky to be working on it at Valve
with a dedicated playtesting room and people running through
who were actually able to give us a thumbs up, thumbs down.
So that really helped us find it.
Awesome, thank you.
Hi, most mind blowing thing I've experienced in VR
is scale change in Tilt Brush.
And I'm wondering if you could tell me
if you have any further plans
for developing that functionality.
Yeah, I mean, that feature took longer than we hoped to actually push live
because it's a delicate balance between simulator sickness.
You know, we had we had prototypes that you could flip the world over,
like the environment over that made me nauseous immediately.
And so that's why you can you know, you can only spin and scale.
There are flavors that we've talked about of, you know, being able to manipulate different canvases, different layers,
and have full control over those, but yeah, that's it. I mean, it really is a balance.
You need some sort of frame of reference if you're going to start whipping the whole world around on you.
The squirrel helps.
Yeah, that was Drew's idea.
Excellent presentation. Thank you so much.
Has there been any discussions to expand Google Tilt Brush into a kind of Adobe After Effects for VR,
or to allow for hotspots and interactivity inside various scenes?
Yeah, that's probably on the spreadsheet of future requests.
You know, one of the things that we've really tried to hold onto as we build Tilt Brush
out is that core experience that was received so positively during GDC, during the unveiling.
There's still a lot of people, I see on Twitter, that tweet things like, just tried out VR,
tried Tilt Brush, love it.
right? Flattering, but it's also like we just gave a presentation on we've been working
on this thing for three years. And so there's...
it almost feel like there's a little bit of an obligation we have to keep the experience
for the first time room scale VR users. And so that's our balance. It's like how do you
how do you maintain that piece while expanding for our pro users and enabling artists and like
really graduating it to the 2.0 version of Tilt Brush. Yeah the only the only thing I was going
to add to that is just that.
We've also stayed true to our rapid prototyping roots,
and we literally have hundreds of crazy prototypes
exploring every single thing we possibly could.
And we are gonna try and follow the pattern
defined in the deck,
and let the magical prototypes guide the way.
And we've had a few of them,
but the fun thing is no one knows what's gonna happen,
and which ones are gonna win,
and where they're gonna lead.
So, I'm just kind of along for the ride.
Awesome. Hey, thank you guys so much. Thank you. Thank you