Hi, my name is Conny and I'm the writer, art and creative director of my game studio called Youmai.
We created the story-driven adventure called Sea of Solitude, which I will talk about today.
I will give you a short introduction about my background, so you see how it all influenced Sea
of Solitude.
I started my career with 17 at the biggest German comic house in Berlin,
drawing for their monthly comic series.
As I had loved video games since I was a child,
as soon as the first games academy opened up in Berlin,
my chosen hometown, I applied and successfully got an internship.
and became a game designer. I worked mainly as an art director in the games industry
up until I founded my own company, Yomai, together with Boris Monza, one of my best friends.
Sea of Solitude is our first multiple platform title.
The first big 3D game we made and the first story-driven game.
We are so proud that we finished it at all with the small 12-people team we had being back then.
Our vision was when humans get too lonely, they turn into monsters.
And first, I want to show you how that looks like.
I'm no child of destiny
And no fortune's son
I've just chased you so long now
I'm too weak to run
A new day is here
But nothing is new
Alone in my room
I tremble
Today I will talk about the art direction of Sea of Solitude in depth.
I will often use the acronym like SOS.
So just so you know, I don't cry out for help when I say that.
I'm going to talk about how emotions informed and inspired the visual style of the character.
We will cover a lot of ground, looking at how the style of SOS is heavily influenced by emotions,
what aspects were important when building our version for Berlin, what makes our Bessel so
special, why the monsters look like they do and how limitations inspired features.
So in SOS you play a woman named Kaylee who suffers from such strong loneliness
that her inner feelings, that the anger, feeling of hopelessness, worthlessness,
turn to the outside and she becomes a monster. On her journey
to become human again. She one by one meets her family members who each suffer from different
kinds of loneliness and become monsters too. First I want to talk about the general idea that became
the base of like everything and influenced every area of art and design. We wanted to make a game
where we
would start from one emotion and build like everything around it, literally turning the
inside, the inner feeling out. K is basically a representation of me and the path I went through
to overcome my struggles. I wanted to share my journey in the form of a game. If we look at her,
someone spilled ink over the otherwise colorful painting.
Her presence on the screen is a personified void,
if you will, representative for the loneliness
and hopelessness of her situation.
I can tell you from the feedback we got after the release
massive inspiration I drew from real life experience that on one side this approach
to develop a game is one of the biggest chances like from personal
background then there's the biggest chance to be artistically unique and successful but
It's also one of the biggest risks for the development of a game,
as you constantly, sometimes like for years, need to deal with this topic.
So drawing your game story from your own life can be very tough.
Seeing Kay every day, being confronted with my personal struggles at work every day.
So basically I always had my baggage with me. Mechanically and artistically I wanted an
iconic gadget on Kay's back that represents this feeling of emotional ballast.
which tea isn't processing in a healthy way.
In the game you put manifested struggles or worries
in this backpack to clear the environment of it.
As the game progresses, this backpack gets bigger
and bigger until it bursts open.
an overwhelming K all at once with the struggles she put in there and causing her to have a
nervous breakdown. The backpack also serves as a visual help to spot K even in the darker areas of
the painting. My show's narrative perspective was not just literally telling and showing you what
happened but putting it all
in a metaphorical world so people could make up their own mind, put in their own thoughts and past
into sea of solitude. Another cornerstone of SOS is my artistic background as mentioned. I started
my career as a comic artist and I'm in general a huge comic fan.
My first big comic love had been the manga Akira.
I especially love the comic style semi-realism.
So not completely realistic but like a mix of the two.
Like for example Akira.
And I tried to put it into Sea of Solitude 2.
So the last cornerstone is my origin.
I was born and grew up in a fishing village,
directly on the shore.
My family had been fishermen, are still fishermen.
So swimming, boat driving, the sea guards water
are very common for me, it's where I'm from.
Those points, the metaphorical narrative,
of my personal story, party, my professional background,
and the love for comics,
and me growing up directly on the shore,
had been the base for all artistic decisions.
Let's start with the environment art.
The story of Solitude plays out in Kay's mind.
That means that what she goes through in real life,
we see through her inner eyes.
For the setting, I chose Berlin, the city where I live now for 20 years already.
I tried to make a more romanticized version of Berlin. For example, the Japanese actors portray
Germany often, like in Ghibli movies, like Kiki's Delivery Service here as an example.
So we partly took original places from Berlin.
and remodeled it for Sea of Solitude.
One example is the above ground subway station called Bülowstraße.
Here is the in-game version, you see.
And here is the original in-game.
original. We reduced the detail to a minimum necessary to fit our style, but still kept
the most prominent details to keep it recognizable. The overboarding feeling Kay has throughout
the majority of the game is isolation, and that she is desperate to try and connect with
people.
with these basic emotions of her, I decided that the city should look as empty as possible.
Really no sign of life above the water, like even plants are missing. I didn't want to show
a post-apocalyptic setting which would have washed out the metaphorical meaning.
So it's a normal, modern, clean city.
It's just empty, as if the people just vanished from one second to the next.
What we did so was putting everywhere on the ground
sand to enhance the feeling of an ocean.
So here you can see some signs of disruption in the far corner.
So only the outer circle of the city looks like this.
The further away you get from the center of the mind of Cain and of the city,
the houses begin to vanish or crumble down and they begin to sink
into the ocean and are crooked and even the streets and trains are damaged.
Throughout the prototyping phase, we encountered an interesting challenge.
Berlin's houses include like rooftops and walls.
They are like problematic for interesting level design compared, for example, to New York City.
We look at it here, like the houses in Berlin have rather like clean design,
like nothing beside balconies stick out of the walls, like very much. No ACs or
outer fire escapes and we Germans rarely put advertising posters on top of buildings or
something.
So all of these things that are often seen on American households are missing in Berlin.
So on top of these design issues, we Germans grew up with...
a ton of American media, be it movies, music, comics. It almost feels like home to us because
we are constantly having it in the media, how America looks like and what they are doing.
So it almost feels like home, but it isn't our home. So it took us quite a while to create and
explorable gameplay, like explorable architecture that still looks like somehow like Berlin.
So we basically extruded like everything more than it is in reality. Here are like
some examples like the flat two-type Berlin house wall.
So if we extruded it, so light and shadow display would be a bit more intense,
so that depth, but also most important that the households and the rooftops become
explorable pathways. So the constant, I'm sorry for the image here, the constant urge
to put in American architecture had been quite big, but we soon saw that even when we accidentally
put just one detail like a typical iconic American rooftop water tanks, which you see
on the right, and suddenly our complete effort to portray a European city had been destroyed.
So another basic design for me is less is more. To achieve a distinctivity of
solitude environment art, I tried
to design it with as few details as possible.
But still, every detail needed in there to make the architecture believable.
For me...
To make architecture believable, the most important aspect to get it to feel right is to understand
its function and to include the aspects that are needed to put and hold it into the place where
it's meant to be. So a tiny example is like the balcony railings. The metal plate
that is tied to the wall with the boltings to hold the construction in place is something
that I wanted the artist to add, this little thing. While other parts like decoration and
aspects could be reduced to a minimum. We applied...
Okay, we applied everything I said to circa to exactly 159 unique buildings.
At least 90 of these buildings were used at least twice or up to four times revisited.
like twice or up to four times within the whole game, which made the design of the city and the
polishing so challenging with only one 3D artist beside me, one extra 3D artist and two level
designers. So, and I explain now more in detail, we come now to the biggest topic of the whole
production, water.
So I love games very much where I constantly roam in the same environment.
So it is more memorable.
Like it starts feeling like home.
Like Resident Evil or Dark Souls or Gone Home.
Like some examples.
So when I did the first
level design sketches. I tried to apply what I call the spaghetti level design. So you come back
always to the same area again or often to the same area again to different perspectives. In our case
the different perspectives are like rising and lowering the water level. So it was a key to that
yeah and it also became one of the most unique features.
For the SOS art-wise, but also like gameplay,
the water is like the biggest symbol we have in the game.
You're literally walking or swimming
through a flooded world.
And this flooded world is like flooded
by the main character's tears.
So her very own ocean of tears.
From the very beginning, I wanted to,
the water to feel as cozy as possible and clear as if you look into a swimming pool,
but even without realistic refraction, so that you sense that it is no real water,
but might have a different meaning.
The clearness combined with the spaghetti level design lets you see areas underwater
and the water surface that you like later in the game will have access to.
Here are some crappy examples, some examples of the water settings that we could adjust like
wave speed or wave height, foam color, foam distortion, foam, the fog underwater, like
yeah, regulate everything of this, every of these aspects.
The key design rule I gave to my environment artist was I want the SOS environment to look
like a holiday.
destination with many islands and gentle beaches. It took us a while to find the right angle
and color of the rooftops so they are really giving you that beach feeling while still
looking like rooftops.
Like a lot of rooftops normally are like this in Berlin and we had to find the area that
it almost looked like the beach but still like the Berlin rooftops. It was really
a challenge but interesting. Those aspects combined like the clear water, the spaghetti
level design and the beach feeling of the rooftops are one of the key elements of the distinctive
environment art of Sea of Solitude.
I knew we had several heavy topics we talked about in SOS, so I felt like giving the game
a light-hearted visual appeal as often
as possible was really important and essential.
And that we don't flood the player with negative feelings all the time,
from all angles, like everywhere.
So this was really important to me to achieve that light-hearted feeling
to compensate for the sappy topics.
We have a strong color palette.
with many different weathers, so we tried to achieve that.
Same as the water height is affected by the emotions of Kay,
the weather is also affected by her mood and connected to her mood.
So from very early on, it became clear that the sunny weather
that represents the feeling...
of positivity and adventuredness needs to be present as often as possible.
When we made the first roadmap of color schemes based on the emotion Kei is going through in the
game, there was way too much darkness. I remember how playtesting
made us almost feel like depressed as the sad story and the sad color scheme over a long period
was just it was just way too much. So I started to try to give the negative weathers like the
rainy weather for example and where the huge underwater creature is lurking a more positive
vibe of colors especially for the water. I tried to give
the water looks scary. I tried to make it look less scary by making it appear to glow from the depth.
I made the background fork lighter than the fork goes by. And I gave it a bit more purple and blue
as it would have initially.
yeah it was important to put it in to help calm the tense feeling.
So in the second level I wanted to portray the heated situation between the parents of Kelly,
the boiling suppressed anger of them both, of the parents. It was clear red was the main
color of choice here. But same as in the rainy
weather, we mixed, we needed to mix some more calming colors such as yellow and brown into the
scene. The glowing effect of the water being able to see far and clear what's going on beneath the
water surface was important again to fight against the too intense feeling of the story
portrayed in that level. It was really important that we added it.
And as you can see in level 2 and 3, the water and the sky are covering much more of the screen,
really like drowning the city in the colors because the water level has risen so much
in these levels already. So as often as possible we put sunny weather parts into the game.
to let the player relax before we pushed them into like tension again.
So this color scheme of the boyfriend's level
had been the easiest to achieve.
Like we show someone who hides his depression
behind appearing like totally fine and happy and healthy,
showing this whole city of the game and suddenly, suddenly
it's sick.
fluffy white snow cover was fitting perfectly to the mood we wanted to transport there.
So this all white and cozy feelings came right before the final level. Our main character
finally faced her own issues. We're portraying a breakdown, the absolute feeling of being completely
alone and numb.
It was clear I wanted to have it as dark and black as possible.
No colors, dense fog.
So I hope you can see anything here.
In general, we had many issues with our main color, black, in the game.
How dark can you turn the game before it becomes hard to watch or understand where you are?
A huge issue is the many different monitors we needed to adjust the game colors to.
I always wanted to go as dark as possible, but when we tested the game on another PC,
it was often like simply pitch black.
We prevented total navigational loss of the player by adding two thick.
One was a subtle light source around K, so the player could always see what is around them.
The second important help was again to make the background fog lighter than the fog close by,
so you have the silhouette. With that you can always see like this silhouette of the
clearing which functions as landmarks. With those tricks I could finally have my
pitch black parts to. So one of the biggest challenges when we created
Tea of Solitude had been our manpower. Creating a game of that size with a team of 12
made us come up with a unique design process.
As I mentioned before, I had been not only the art director, but also the brighter main game designer,
had with the level design, did the level design schedules, and did the level art with one other
level artist beside, and had other responsibilities like the company had.
So in the first years of the concept phase, I just had one program helping me with like
Sea of Solitude and we needed to work on other games too that kept the company afloat while
we were finding the right approach for Sea of Solitude. So it was like a really just two people
team at the beginning, me and one programmer. So I basically just had time to do one key artwork.
for the environment art at the beginning.
So I did it in my favorite 2D tool, like Photoshop,
Adobe Photoshop.
I usually work with like many layers in Photoshop
and often use like the so-called blending modes
for those layers, like multiply, like overlay and transparency.
I use transparency, gradients and masks.
I love using all this for my style.
So when I finished that one key artwork, I walked up to my one programmer and showed him exactly
how I made this key artwork in Photoshop and asked him if he can reproduce
this immunity as a tool for 3D environment.
so that he creates something in unity that I can work the same way I would work in 2D photoshop.
Because of the tiny team size, we early on decided to not use any textures
in the environment. So even like cracks on the wall and the leaves are triangles.
and that had been a huge advantage as we didn't need to unwrap anything or texture,
we could scale and squeeze the models freely. We also didn't need to spend time creating textures
as mentioned and because of this we could build almost a whole city district, like a real whole
city district was just.
one environment artist needs. So to bring life to the
untextual environment, I asked my programmer for various tools to help me. Coloring the shadow
and ambient occlusion was really important that I could like really color it however I want.
We also misused the specular component of the materials in Unity and used just slightly
different colors within this specular gradient.
So when you move through the world of SOS, this effect brings more life into the world
without you really noticing it.
It makes SOS look less blunt.
That was a really cool check, I feel.
So, I used the gradient.
in Photoshop create like distance fog and also ground fog like for this concept art I did.
So the specialty in SOS had been that I needed fog over and under water but the fog over water
shouldn't affect everything underwater and vice versa. So our programmer Dirk
step by step built me a Vasa system tool in Unity,
where I could almost use the same workflow
I had in Photoshop.
With that...
I didn't need to spend time painting artworks, but I could directly build a one-to-one example for
my whole team, where they didn't need to interpret my drawings, but could see like the final product
and use that as a blueprint for everything they needed to create and see of Solitude.
So remember, we were only 12 people, we need to iterate fast.
And if you do the same, I advise you to build tools that makes you as flexible as possible.
So that brings me to the second biggest art direction aspect next to the environment art,
the monster design. In general, we have two different types of monsters.
in SOS, K's monsters and the monsters of the family of K.
All of them are based on the human behind it, mixed with the biggest emotion they have.
These aspects manifest into their monster form.
When I did the very first sketch of Monsters in Sea of Solitude, I sat down in front of a blank paper
and I imagined how I would feel when I'm at the absolute lowest point, like angry and sad.
So I rather scratched over the paper and then drawing anything particular.
and a black ball of lines came out of the session.
So I started to bring this basic idea
of how manifested anger and sadness could look like
into a human form.
While doing so, the wired lines
turned slowly into a feathery fur.
Then I imagined that in order to still go on in life, not giving up,
even though you go through all these hardships, you need to still have a flame of hope burning inside you.
So I drew this monster with red, orange light shining from the inside out
and through their mouth and through their eyes. This is the base of all monsters you
encounter in the game. A black appearance with red shining eyes and mouth.
A short comment before I go deeper into the family monster designs.
The stories about the parents and about the brother are not taken from my life.
I have no brother and my parents are now happily married for over 40 years.
40 years.
So those stories are inspired by colleagues and friends.
The brother monster had been the first family monster I did a concept art of.
The brother gets bullied in school by his former friends and he suffers from harsh self-doubt.
Like unsure for a long time if he is a problem in this whole issue.
So the longer he is in this situation, the stronger his buddhies are harassing him.
The first of the strongest emotions he has is this urge to just want to fly away from this situation.
Like the birds he used to watch through the school windows during lessons.
This is why his monster version appears like a huge bird, in particular a raven mixed with a human body.
He is constantly surrounded by his own weather, which reflects his emotions too.
The second emotion next to the urge to fly away is fear to be seen.
He wants to hide because his buddies start harassing him as soon as they see him.
So I created a thick fog around him, almost colorless, where he hides inside.
His water is special, as it is the only one where you can instantly die.
As mentioned before, the water stands for the ocean of tears, desperation, sadness.
So his emotional state is already so bad that we decided to make his water deadly.
When Kay falls into that water, hands of the Buddhists obstruct, grab her and drown her.
The father of Kay,
to leave his wife, as they married rather early
in their life and just grew apart.
They tried over many years to fix the marriage,
but sometimes it just didn't work out.
And the longer they tried, the unhealthier
the whole situation became.
As he, the father, struggles to openly tell his wife what he feels and rather avoid confrontation,
he starts hiding from her by working way too much. So I drew his monster version as a big chameleon
mixed with a human. I wanted to show with little details like that he is still wearing his wedding
ring.
even as a monster that he loves his family.
We encounter him first on the skyscraper
where his office is.
I wondered that the building looks almost destroyed.
The father monster and the mother monster
fighting for a long while already.
She tried to get him out of the skyscrapers
and with this, she destroyed it almost.
Also, I designed the interior of the building, or I had the idea for the design of the interior
building as rather empty and cold. Same as the father feels. He sits on top of the building,
angrily, angrily crying out.
His screams produce steam streams that comes out of every vent inside the skyscraper and
push K, the player, away.
The father monster tries to avoid touching the water, the ocean of tears, like the plaque,
as he is unwilling to really deal with his own issues.
He can't even swim.
The mother monster
looks like a giant octopus mixed with a female head.
She is about 10 times a lot bigger than the father monster.
I imagined like a loving mother that desperately tries
to hold the families, the whole family together,
tries to hold onto like everything
and keep it from crumbling apart.
So she needed many arms and I immediately thought of an octopus.
The mother monster is often completely underwater and that means that she is constantly worrying
and sad but as soon as her daughter or husband shows up she comes out of the water and at least
try to appear confident. The mother monster and father monster share a huge
weather surrounding them. So we have this dramatic like red and orange colors throughout most of their
level. It stands for the end of their partnership but also the heat of tension surrounding them.
The water level is much higher than in the brother's level beforehand as both like the
mother and the father suffer from a profound loneliness within their relationship.
that affects the whole family, including their children.
The final argument those two have
in the destroyed version of the home in the game,
it looks like a bombed crater.
I hope you can see that in the concept.
When the player comes to the home at first, it's still intact.
and it's also the only place next to the end of the game where you see plants and vegetation,
plants and vegetation in general. It stands for that Kay feels most healthy there at her home,
so she can see the life which she can't throughout most of the game.
So you can see it there.
So the monster, the boyfriend monster, is the most unique one of all family monsters.
Kay's boyfriend suffers from depression, but tries to appear fine to the outside.
He is doing pretty well until he falls in love with Kay and is finally forced to open up about his struggles.
So when we meet the boyfriend monster first, he appears like a shiny white wolf, like white
lone wolf.
Throughout the development, the whole development of Sea of Solitude, I educate myself about
mental health a lot, but also about metaphors, symbols, and so on.
The lone wolf is a typical symbol for a man that tends to act independently and spend
more time alone than in groups.
And it is not only him I portray shiny and white.
In his level, the whole Berlin district
where SOS takes place is snowed in.
And he is like really, really good
at camouflaging his real feelings.
So he put the whole game under a cozy white snow layer.
So every time he interacts with Kay in the game and she touches him,
part of his white perfect camouflage falls off and we see the black dog beneath it,
which is a known metaphor for depression. I again designed him part human and part animal.
Kay.
The main character itself, I wanted to portray in a different way.
And as ripped apart into her basic emotions,
all of these emotions coming to life.
And she needs to interact with them throughout the entire game.
I took her strongest emotions like self-doubt, joy, self-destruction, hope and willpower.
The playable character represents willpower.
She looks much more like a human than every other monster as she is the closest to recovery.
But of course I wanted to design the main character more human, so the player can project
themselves better onto it.
Kay is actually completely naked, which was important to me to portray how vulnerable
she is in the state of change and transition to a more healthy life.
The only thing Kay wears is her backpack.
It carries the baggage we all carry throughout our life.
She doesn't know how to cope with all these emotions
she's going through.
So the backpack becomes bigger and bigger
throughout the game.
until it's like really huge and it bursts and forcing her to finally overcome her own struggles
or all deal with all her emotions. Zeddout is the first other monster you meet, uh,
you really interact with and meet in the game. Um, all of Kay's monsters are partly
her human body. So self-doubt, I choose to mix her with like the human body and with a snail,
like especially with a shell. Self-doubt as an emotion always feels to me
as it ends up trying to hide somewhere, like it's hiding, self-doubt and you hide.
Mostly, of course, at home.
So a snail shell is in their home.
The self-doubt monster also has teeth like a small child.
I wanted to show that what comes out of the mouth of self-doubt is nothing educated,
but rather like blunt or warm.
often true, but so more childlike.
The self-doubt monster shrinks over the course of the game
until she turns from self-doubt to healthy doubt.
So first she is house high and super scary.
So at the end of the game, Kay can't even take her
in her arms, she's like a baby,
that this healthy doubt incites.
Self-destruction is a mixture between Kay and a siren and a shark.
Like she tries to lurk Kay back into the water, into the ocean of tears so she can swallow Kay again.
When I started scribbling her, she was rather soft at the beginning,
self-destruction, and a whale, like a whale. But the more her role became clear,
like the main antagonist.
and the representation of self-destruction.
She more turned into a super creepy being
with this huge sharp teeth.
Okay, so just her torso,
yeah, just her torso and her eyes
are in front of the head.
and not on the side, reminds us that there is also some human part in it.
If you look really closely, you can see that the feet
of Kay's body meld together to form a fin in this monster.
She is always like underwater.
The ocean of tears is her natural habitat.
So self-destruction, same as self-doubt.
shrinks throughout the game so that K can almost lift even self-destruction at the end.
Self-destruction is probably the monster you see the most on the internet.
The way she behaves and the way she swims is something we are very proud of
because it needed so much work to get it right
and so much attention with complex collision checks to
to turn her around like this the snaker animation that gives her like
this sine curve style
So much work.
So joy
Joy, yeah, we put joy in the category of monster
Even though she doesn't appear that way at the beginning and is rather special in general. I think of joy
as a rather innocent feeling
In innocence I connect with her childhood. So I choose to draw joy as a child version of Cain
She wears a yellow raincoat
So she is completely invulnerable to the ocean of tears.
She even can fly just to be sure that she never touches like the water.
In the boyfriend monster level, Joy finally shows her monstrous side.
She turns into an obsession monster and attacks Kay.
When she tries to get in, when Kay tries to get in the way
between Joy and the boyfriend.
Obsession has sharp teeth and I changed the color to purple for readability purposes.
Another entity in the game is a boat of teeth that she drives.
It stands for the hope of K. It also carries the sunny weather with it, like a sphere,
which he gets from joy at the beginning. He gets the sunny weather from joy.
It functions as a safe zone. I wanted to design the boat in a robust but simple way,
like hope itself. It is not an emotion
that is loud or profound.
And I feel it is the most important of them all.
The houseboat is the new version of the family's home.
So underwater, you can see the broken pieces
of the family home.
So above the water, it is a new home, a new houseboat that will carry all family members
with Kay into the new chapter of life, built from the old life.
So I often get asked what movies like comic books, books or whatever inspired me for Sea of Solitude.
I then always try to come up with art I love, but the truth is that I didn't look at any other art
or any other art to get inspired for Sea of Solitude. It came from the inside.
art-wise, like the visual I drew from everything I learned, the visual like everything I learned
so far and the style I have developed throughout my life so far. For the story I just let out what
I already had in my mind, my feelings. There had been a dangerous situation in between when I looked
at other art for once too much.
When the last Guardian, the game, the last Guardian came out, I was so excited about it
that I almost studied like this design of Trico, of this huge animal in the game.
At the same time back then I was still designing the monsters of SOS and at some point my co-workers
came to me and said like Connie and your monster design looks so different now almost like
Trico. It was like a little bit like a shock as I didn't realize this until the moment they told
me about it. Like oh gladly I still could revert the damage back then I have done.
So what I learned through the whole production of SOS,
be it for the art, the story or every creative process,
draw from what is inside you.
Then it will have the biggest chance to be unique.
Adore other's art, but be careful
to not adapt it accidentally.
I stopped looking at others art too much at some point and I think this is why
the Solitude became a bit more unique. From now on I will always follow the path of first
looking inside me, take the strongest emotion or thought I have at the point in my life
and use that as a base for the art or the games I want to create.
This way it will likely have the personality, have personality and will be unique.
And I think that is the key we all, all the artists out there, want to achieve. Thank you.