What successful product managers do differently in free-to-play games?
Well, this was actually the question that I asked myself some six to seven months ago
when I was offered a role as a head of product management at Rovio.
And the thing is, even though I had the experience,
so I worked as a product manager first at Digital Chocolate,
then at Supercell and Rovio, and then in more of a...
game leadership roles as an executive producer at Zynga,
and then studio lead at FunPlus.
So even though I had the experience of working as a
product manager, hiring product managers, and managing
product managers, I never really sat down and
conceptualized what makes a good, successful product
manager, and most importantly, what do those successful
product managers are doing differently.
So I approach this in the typical core loop.
What I mean by that is in order to really find out what
the successful product managers are doing differently,
I first talk to my friends, my colleagues, and people I know
from various amazing companies like Facebook, Zynga,
Wargaming, Natural Motion, FunPlus, EA, you name it.
And I ask them two questions.
Firstly is, what makes a great product manager?
And the second question was more detailed.
And that was, can you tell me about a situation where a
product manager was succeeding, when they did more
than you expected?
Based on these questions and based on the multiple answers
that I got from my friends and colleagues, I sort of
deconstructed the information.
and conceptualize it into different themes.
And with those themes, I got back to my colleagues
and friends and got more feedback,
again, deconstructed our feedback, and so forth,
and so forth, until this place.
So as a result, I got five elements
that successful product managers do differently
in free-to-play games.
But before we jump in into those five elements,
let's talk about what do product managers actually do.
And the first thing that you might think of
is they animate a lot their presentations.
And you're absolutely right.
But in addition to that.
What product managers do is actually tasks of both highly creative elements,
like defining, designing, and managing key features,
discovering and creating growth levers,
but also very many analytical tasks,
such as building quantitative models,
owning and analyzing game metrics,
and overall just managing the business performance.
But the role is actually even more complicated, because it
changes not only based on these tasks, but it also
changes based on the lifecycle of the product, whether in
pre-production, production, soft launch, or live
operations, as well as the culture and the organization
of the company.
So the way I see it, and the way I like to present it, is I
would say product managers have two key goals.
The first goal is owning the business side of the game.
And what I mean by that is that in the internal battle of CPI
versus LTV, the product managers definitely
represent the LTV side.
And they focus on the metrics of growth, of retention, and
the monetization.
And their design thinking and their overall goal thinking
starts with those metrics first.
And they make their decision based on that.
The second key goal that I feel product managers have is
Helping the leadership make decisions.
And why I have an image of a hit man is,
okay, product managers don't really have the,
we don't have the ability always to pull the trigger.
But because we do the analysis,
because we do the due diligence,
and because we do a lot of the designs,
we essentially have the power to adjust the aim.
And that's why product managers' goal
is to support the decision making.
All right, let's go to the details.
The first thing that I feel successful product managers do
differently in free-to-play games is they use data to find
the low-hanging fruits.
And what I mean by low-hanging fruit is something that
requires minimum amount of engineering work, minimum
amount of work actually from art, perhaps, but has a
significant impact.
Let's start by talking about what isn't a low-hanging fruit.
So the normal process of product management or feature
updates, it goes through basically this cycle.
You start off with the analysis.
You end up in a hypothesis or design.
Then you prioritize that design based on the cost of
the work and based on the impact.
And the next step is execution of that design, after which
it's further analyzed.
And then more hypotheses arise.
Pretty standard approach.
To give a more of a
clear example of this type of approach would be, let's say,
League Update and Clash of Clans.
So as you probably are well aware of this game and have
played it before, the way the leagues function and the way
the update would have come is the analysis shows that
players were abusing the matchmaking system by dropping
their trophies.
And that sort of created a double whammy in the sense
that those players abusing the matchmaking systems were able
to.
be matched against weaker players, they were able to raid them quite easily and thus get
resources and progress faster through the content.
On the other hand, the players that were raided by much stronger opponents were feeling a
little bit discouraged and that would probably affect their retention quite significantly.
Based on this analysis, that derives both from quantitative metrics as well as qualitative,
the hypothesis or the design is made to reward players to stay at certain trophy level and
most importantly push them to acquire more trophies and thus be matched against even
harder opponents.
Because this design...
has a big effect and it solves a big question in the game.
It gets prioritized high.
It gets executed.
And then with further analysis, the numbers are being tuned.
And the leak feature is getting improved and improved
with every update.
So this is not a low-hanging fruit.
This is what you're expected to do.
So let's talk about a low-hanging fruit.
A game called Dragons of Atlantis.
I don't know how many of you are familiar with this.
But just to remind you, this was a Kabam game.
It could be described as Game of War minus key social features
plus dragons.
At the time, it was fairly successful.
And the product team and Kabam were having a good time.
But the game had some problems.
And the key problem was that they
were experiencing a churn of players between citadel levels.
So the way it worked is.
you upgrade your citadel or your city hall,
and that unlocks several more upgrades,
both for your troops, your research, your buildings,
and then you grind through those,
and then you can upgrade your citadel level again,
and so forth and so forth.
The problem was that they didn't have
as much levels for those citadels.
And because of that, the citadel levels were...
quite far away from each other, and they were getting further and further away.
And players were honestly just turning out.
The metrics were going down as they were progressing through the games, and then players just felt
it was too big of a grind to go to the next level.
Based on the normal approach of analyzing, hypothesizing, prioritizing, and executing,
the product team would have come up with a suggestion of doubling the content of the
game, implementing that, and so forth and so forth.
But that's a very slow approach.
So instead, the product team on the game
did something much more simple and more effective.
They simply doubled the amount of Citadel levels
without it really touching the amount of level ups there are.
So instead of unlocking 10 new things when leveling up
to level 6 of Citadel, you just unlocked 5.
And then on the seventh level, you
unlock the rest of the 5.
As a result, with this small update,
they were able to increase all the metrics from retention
to engagement to monetization.
Let's go through another example of an easy low-hanging fruit.
And it's a game called Angry Birds Match.
And if you haven't played this game,
I would describe it as Candy Crush Saga with Angry Birds
and events.
And events is actually the important part of this game.
Let's talk about... yeah, sorry.
So events are an important part of this game.
And there's two types of events.
There's the seasonal events that last for two weeks or three weeks.
They're pretty large and visually they're very different.
And then there's the small events that are happening between the bigger seasonal events.
During their latest... not latest but...
A couple of events ago, when they were running the Valentine's Day event,
what they did differently is, at the end of the event, they added a leaderboard.
So as the players went all through 70, 60, 80 different levels,
instead of finishing the event, they ended up in a leaderboard.
And that leaderboard was active for as long as the game was active.
The product manager on this game, Matteo Speri,
analyzed the data.
And what he noticed that adding the leaderboard actually
significantly increased the engagement.
Because it kept those highly engaged players progressing
through all out event.
And instead of them finishing the event and waiting for the
next one to start, they actually stayed in that event.
And that brought a significant increase, not only through
engagement, but also through retention and
monetization elements.
So based on this finding, as the event ended,
He made a hypothesis, and that was that when running our
smaller events, those who last between 24 to 72 hours, what
if we make a little change?
And that change was that after you finish the event, you can
finish it again.
So you can get double the price, and that's it.
It's just a small data tweak.
As a result, the KPIs, or the baseline revenue, pretty much
increased 20% with a small data change.
So successful product managers are able to look at the data
and make quite significant changes without big use from
engineering team.
But even though the small hanging fruits, even though
we're always looking for those, that's always not the
case, because sometimes you just can't find them, or
sometimes the target is just too far off.
And that's when breaking down those bigger goals, that's
when working on bigger features.
You're supposed to.
And the successful ones are able to break it down
to smaller targets.
So let me give an example of how not to do it.
And this is my personal example.
So this is an old game.
It's a Facebook game called Army Attack from maybe eight
years ago.
And I was running this as a lead product manager.
And I had the goal of increasing the baseline
revenue by 20%.
And instead of taking the smart approach of really breaking down where the revenue comes
from, maybe thinking about adding some core features, increasing the retention, I went
with a much straightforward approach, which was this.
As a result, yes, the revenue increased and the leadership was very happy, but not for
a very long time.
Because what I ended up doing is I just changed player behavior, player purchasing behavior.
created more work and created cycles in our sales.
And overall, just wasn't very smart.
So let's talk about a smart example of breaking down big
goals, a game called Dawn of Titans.
I'm sure all of you played it.
And those of you who have played it probably know that
it's a highly event-driven game.
A PM on this game, her name is Kim Gelderbaum, not anymore a PM on this game, but when she
was, she was given a similar goal than I was, and that is increase the revenue, increase
the revenue of events by 20%.
And her approach was significantly smarter than mine.
First, she looked at the low-hanging fruit.
Can we increase the funnel for the event, the DAO of the
event, by 20%?
Because that would basically do it.
And the answer was no.
So what Kim started doing is she started
looking at the data.
And more importantly, she started looking at how the
best players in the events are behaving.
And she found out that the best of the players were the
most engaged, that had made the most sessions.
They were the most active.
They spent the most time in the game.
And most importantly, they were very active in chats.
Based on that, she tweaked the event structure in a way
that the next event was really designed to push players
to act as those engaged players.
And those highly engaged players were
pushed to act just in that way, or even becoming more engaged.
Next, she built levers in order to push players to act in the way that was designed.
And after that, she created a custom dashboard together with data scientist team that will
allow her to follow the event structure, the event progress in real lifetime in order for
her to pull the triggers at the right time.
As a result, Kim was able to hit her target to a T at the right time.
and just overall broke down a big goal into smaller,
actionable targets and did her due diligence.
So, third thing, turning numbers into a story.
And as I tried to show in the slide before with the gun,
it's basically saying that.
As a PM, you have a power of affecting the aim, affecting the decision making.
And as a game lead, I mean, this is often what you experience.
There's constantly new ideas coming in left and right, and they're just dropping on you.
The quest, the raid bosses, everything that you should be doing, and this comes both from
external and internal, and you know, you need to prioritize your roadmap and you need to
make the right decisions.
And sometimes...
it feels like the right decisions aren't
made in the right time.
So the successful PMs are able to turn those numbers, turn
those analysis more of a story and sell it through that.
As an example, let's get back to Dawn of Titans.
Before there were events for Kim to optimize and grow,
there were actually no events in the roadmap at all.
The two PMs working on this team.
Mr. Anil Dasgupta, who's probably in this room, as well
as Lawrence Clark, they created a hypothesis that by
adding events to the game, they would be able to increase
the baseline.
They showed the examples from App Annie, like games like
Puzzles and Dragons in the east, as well as Grease games
in the west, such as Crime City and War of Nations, I
believe, they were all.
increasing their baseline by running very good events constantly.
But that wasn't enough to convince the leadership that events should be done.
So instead, this happened.
It's a pop-up of a sale.
But it's actually not just a sale.
So what the guys did is they created an event by themselves.
They tweaked the gotcha a little bit so that the likelihood of getting a very rare titan
was increased by tenfold, and that event would run for about three days.
They added a pop-up to the game, and they added also a message to the Facebook community,
just informing players that this kind of event was going on.
As a result, they were able to get some numbers for the story, and the numbers were good because
the game hit its highest ARPDAUS during that time.
it ended up in the game, in the roadmap being prioritized with the events
and the game running through the event cadence.
Example number two.
Clash of Clans and Japan.
So, sometimes...
So why telling a story through the numbers is important?
Because sometimes we just don't have enough data.
We think that something is really important, and we just
don't have enough data to show it.
And it's great to have A-B testing, it's great to have
sequential testing, it's great to have the analysis.
But sometimes you see something else being done by
others, and you're trying to pull that data, but it's just
not as concrete.
And that's when telling a story is important.
And that was kind of the case of the launch of Clash of
Clans in Japan.
So before the game was launched or relaunched in Japan.
The KPIs were very good for the audience, but it wasn't localized or culturalized.
The normal approach when you're seeing good KPIs is basically you contact your localization partner,
you set up the order for that localization, it comes in, there's a QA,
and then it goes to the next update and hopefully it'll increase your number a little bit.
But the story of Japan was a little bit different.
At that time, Puzzles & Dragons alone was making more money than Clash of Clans in Japan than Clash of Clans in Japan.
At that time, the Puzzles and Dragons were making more money in Japan alone than Clash
of Clans throughout the world.
So that meant that there was a big market.
The second part of the story was that highly successful Western games such as Farmville
and Candy Crush Saga were not that big of a success in Japan, despite going through
the normal localization route, despite doing the marketing, despite doing their due diligence.
So the team looked for a way to be big in Japan.
a plan was created and that plan would take actually three to four times longer to implement
than to simply pushing out a new localization update.
Yet the story behind it was that it really put the game
into a position where it could be successful in the
Japanese market.
And thus, the leadership decided to go through this
slow, more riskier route.
And as a result, the game was actually, I believe, first
Western mobile game that hit top 10 grossing in the
Japanese market.
Four, leveraging the knowledge of the peers.
This is an interesting topic, and it's actually...
OK, so leveraging knowledge of the peers.
There's two elements in the knowledge leveraging.
The one is that there's so much information coming both
internally and externally that a product manager needs to
handle at all time.
By external information, I mean the information that is
coming just through the market change.
You're looking at the market.
You're looking at what's going on.
You're looking at your own category.
You're looking at the games, what kind of
updates they're doing.
And then there's the internal information.
As a product manager, you're pretty much expected to know
not expect it, you have to know what's going on with your game, you have to know how your
cohorts are behaving, you have to know how your updates are influencing them.
And that knowledge is constantly increasing as well.
With all the new A-B tests, with all the new game launches, it's almost impossible to keep
the track of that yourself.
And that's why leveraging knowledge of your peers, of others, is important.
A good example of a culture of knowledge sharing is Zynga.
At Zynga, the knowledge sharing is being run by the team called Central Product Management.
And the knowledge sharing is actually divided into three different categories.
First is the numbers reviews, and sort of a general business updates that are done every
three to four weeks.
During those updates, basically PMs together with GMs go through their game, kind of update
what's going on on the business side, what have been done, how that affected, and what
is being done in the future.
Then you have a more...
intimate setting of knowledge sharing, and that is product launches.
So during product launches, the product managers actually show what kind of different A-B tests,
what kind of different analysis of the new features have been launched, and share that
detailed information with their peers.
And thirdly, there's the knowledge sharing of competitive insights, where there's a specific
team just looking at different type of games that have been launched and deconstructing
those games and providing product managers with that information.
Now you might ask, what this has to do with a successful product management?
I mean, this is just a description of a process.
True.
But it sets up this next example.
Angry Birds Evolution, or more specifically, the lead product manager
in this game, Dylan Tredere.
What he did was really interesting.
So as the game launched, as he went through soft launch and
launch, there was constantly more and more
need of information.
People were asking him both internally, as well as outside
the team, what's going on, what has he been learning,
what are the A-B tests, and so forth and so forth.
So instead of being a sort of a
reactive knowledge share, he set up a meeting every Friday at about 2 p.m. that lasts between
five minutes to 35 minutes. This meeting was called Numbers Review and everybody was pretty
much invited to this meeting and it turned out from kind of like a reactive knowledge
sharing to proactive knowledge sharing. And instead of him trying to answer those rapid
questions, he would have people come in on that specific day.
But it didn't just do that, it did something more.
So the meeting was really successful, and it's successful
in terms of you went there and actually learned more about
the game.
And what we decided to do is we actually pushed it forward,
and now it's something that we do company-wide, where we
have
a one numbers review meeting where product managers and product leads are invited and
we go quickly in about one hour through the key updates as well as key A-B tests and sequential
tests and analysis of the different features and that kind of grew up into a knowledge
sharing meeting.
So what Dylan essentially did is he created a knowledge sharing group where that wasn't
really before.
Another example of knowledge sharing is this blog,
Deconstructor Fun.
Actually, do you mind raising your head for a second if
you've ever heard about it?
OK, that's crazy.
So Deconstructor Fun, I started writing this blog
about six years ago.
And it was honestly just something that I did in order
to improve my own learnings.
And it's still something I do just to learn.
And
Throughout the time, there's just more and more games that were launched, more interesting
games, and the games got deeper, and it's almost impossible for one person to really
cover those.
At the same time, there were great people who started writing their own blogs, such
as Anil S. Gupta with Both Guns Blazing and Adam Telfer with Mobile Free-to-Play.
And it's kind of turned into this weird...
I don't know for them, but it turned for me into this weird kind of competition where
I was trying to write better deconstruction instead of learning.
It's just, it was weird.
So what I tried to do with them is I asked them like, would you like to learn together?
Would you like to work together?
And happily, they said yes.
And I learned that I didn't know anything.
So by surrounding myself with really smart people that I
truly respected, it really leveraged the knowledge.
And in short, what I'm trying to say is, you might think you
know something, but until you surround yourself with people
you respect, who are able to criticize, who are smart, you
actually don't know shit.
And final one is understanding why different people like
different games.
Quite often, surprisingly often, I've talked to product
managers, and they weren't that interested
about games, per se.
They were doing this for something that they felt would
progress their careers and progress them to become
somewhat service managers, e-commerce people or app
people, but the most successful ones are the ones
who are actually.
who actually like games.
And it's not just about liking games, because everybody in
this room loves games.
There's Fortnite players, League of Legends players,
Candy Crush Saga players, you name it.
But what really separates a successful product manager
from others is they're able to
to get deeper into the games and actually understand why do different people like them?
Not just playing always Candy Crush Saga or always Fortnite or always League of Legends
and not just outsourcing this question to the qualitative research team but actually
attempting to answer it yourself.
That ladies and gentlemen concludes my presentation and please open for questions.
Hello. You mentioned Clash of Clans had a strategy to go to Japan and that they were really successful.
I'm really curious to know what was that strategy?
So the strategy, like in details of what the strategy was?
Yeah, as detailed as you can be.
I'm a bit brief.
I'll be very brief and I'll just say that the strategy involved creating a lot of partnerships
with local partners in Japan as well as focusing on culturalization of the game and getting
the stamp of approval so that the Japanese players felt that this game was made by Japanese.
Okay.
I expect somebody to ask the question of what's the difference between designer and product
manager.
Hi, great talk.
I am a data scientist who's working with the PMs oftentimes
about how to improve the monetization and the metrics
that we really care about.
I was wondering if you can give us any tips about how
to communicate with the PMs from a data scientist
perspective, and especially when talking about the
statistics and numbers.
Yeah, for sure.
I'll tell you what the data scientist told me.
And that was basically the question of why.
Like why are you looking at this specific number?
And instead of answering always to what the product
managers are asking you, ask them why are they asking that.
And then you get to the root of the problem.
Hey, great talk, thank you.
Thank you.
Quick question, where do you see the lines being drawn
between design, product, and production?
Okay, so it all depends on the ownerships.
Let's put it this way.
So if you have to break it down into very clear
ownerships, I would say that the product manager would have
the ownership of the business side of the game, so making
sure that it's a successful product, per se.
It doesn't mean that the product manager is the only
person who makes those decisions, but he owns that
part. The design owns the part that the players like, love,
and just enjoy the game.
And the producer owns the fact that the updates are coming on
time, that they're not.
that they're not filled with bugs and that the production is going forward as planned.
So that would be a very high level divide of those three.
All right, thank you.