Hi, everyone.
I'm Soren Johnson, and welcome to You Have No Idea How Hard It Is to Run a Sweatshop.
And I'll just say I'm very pleased to see everyone who came out for a talk with this
type of title.
So here are the published games that I've worked on over my career, some of which I
will touch on over the next hour.
I also do a podcast where I interview game designers
about why they make games.
The episodes tend to run long, so check it out
if you have any four-hour road trips coming up.
So the talk I'm about to give is something of a sequel
to one I gave in 2010, which was entitled,
Theme is Not Meaning.
I argued then that we need to stop
assuming that a game's theme or setting determines its meaning,
and instead that meaning comes from the mechanics themselves.
Since then, I've spent a lot of time thinking about games
which do a good job of constructing meaning
from their mechanics, and also about ones which do it poorly.
I'd like to talk about some of these examples today,
examine how best to build meaning in our games.
Games have great power to affect players,
but, and I'm going to be bringing this up
over and over again, that power can so easily slip
out of the designer's hands, and sometimes end up
delivering the exact opposite message
from what the designer intended.
So first, let's talk about soccer and the 1994 Caribbean Cup,
where they introduced a unique rule concerning golden goals,
which are overtime goals that instantly end the game.
In this tournament, golden goals would now
be worth two goals instead of one, which
could matter if two teams are tied in the standings
and need to use the difference in goals scored
as a tiebreaker.
So here are the standings before the final game
between Barbados and Grenada.
Let me explain what we're looking at here.
These columns are the number of games played
and the wins and losses so far.
Note that if Barbados beats Grenada,
there will be a three-way tie.
In a three-way tie, each team will have three points in the standings
because each win is worth three points.
So, in the event of a three-way tie,
the team which advances is the one with the best goal differential,
which is goals four, subtracted by goals allowed.
Thus, even though Barbados is currently in last place here,
if they can beat Grenada by two goals,
they will advance from the group
by having the highest goal differential.
Remember when I said earlier
that a golden goal is worth double?
That's called foreshadowing.
Near the end of the game,
Barbados is up by exactly two goals
with a score of two to zero.
So if the game were to end at that moment,
Barbados would have the goal differential
they need to win the tiebreaker.
But then, in the 82nd minute, Grenada scores,
and even though Barbados is still winning the game,
they will not advance because they have lost a point in goal differential.
Barbados needs another goal, or they will be eliminated.
So, if Barbados can score a third goal in the final eight minutes of the game,
the standings will look like the chart on the right.
Barbados will get back to a plus-one goal differential,
win first place, and advance to the next round.
Five minutes pass and Barbados is running out of time
to score the third goal they need.
If nothing changes, they will win the game,
but be eliminated.
However, someone on the Barbados team
remembers the special golden goal rule
and realizes that if they score on themselves
and force the game to overtime,
they would have a full 30 minutes to score a golden goal,
which would then be worth two goals
and put Barbados into first place,
as you can see on the right.
And so, this happens.
Barbados brings the ball back to their own side and
intentionally scores on themselves.
Obviously, Grenada figures something is up, and they
quickly realize that they now have two very different paths
to first place, represented by both charts here.
So either they score a goal to break the tie, you know, the
old-fashioned way.
Or instead, they intentionally score on themselves to lose the
game but win the group by goal differential.
Which leads to what must be the most unusual soccer game of all time, because Barbados
now needs to defend both of the goals.
And Grenada just needs to score in either one, leading to this totally, totally normal
arrangement of players.
Ultimately, Grenada fails to score another goal,
and the goal goes to overtime.
Game goes to overtime.
Naturally, Barbados does score a goal in goal,
now worth double, and goes on to the next round.
Their plan to score on themselves
and win in overtime actually worked.
Here's the response of Grenada manager to this outcome.
I feel cheated.
The person who came up with these rules must be a candidate for a madhouse.
Our players did not even know which direction to attack, our goal or their goal.
In football, you're supposed to score against the opponents to win, not for them.
Of course, Barbados did nothing wrong.
They're just playing by the rules of the game.
And the rules put them in a situation where scoring against themselves made sense.
I've certainly had the same experience where a rule or mechanic I've added to a game
ends up creating some perverse incentive
that leads to the exact opposite player behavior
that I wanted to encourage.
One way to put this is that nobody knows anything.
Here's the rest of the quote from screenwriter William Goldman.
Not one person knows for a certainty what's going to work.
Every time out, it's a guess.
And if you're lucky, an educated one.
Certainly, that could be said for video games.
I would never have bet on an ultra-detailed dwarf simulator
using ASCII art,
or on a game with one winner and 99 losers,
or on a turn-based game that plays itself,
or on a twin-stick shooter minus one of the sticks.
Much of game design is determined by constraints
which are out of the hands of the developers.
Dota 2 and League of Legends both inherited their design from the original Warcraft 3 mod, Defense of the Ancients,
which had two distinctive mechanics that were just baked into how Warcraft 3 worked.
Creep Denial, which means being able to kill your own minions and last hitting,
meaning that the experience points go to the last hero to hit the target.
Dota 2 kept Creep Denial.
and both games kept last hitting,
which suggests that their existence is a happy accident,
as no one actually, quote-unquote, designed them.
They were just inherited constraints from a game in a different genre.
So is game design just sorting through accidents like this to see what works?
Consider the case of Fortnite.
which started as a game about building forts
while fighting off waves of zombies.
Even after Fortnite blew up
into the world's largest battle royale game,
these building mechanics stuck around
as this weird inherited vestige of the original game.
It took epic years to finally do the obvious thing
and just get rid of them entirely,
so that the end of a Fortnite match
was no longer this strange, frantic building contest.
Indeed, it's hard to describe Fortnite
as intentional design at all
when you draw the strange path things took.
Here's a rough history of the various games and mods
that led to Fortnite Battle Royale as we know it today.
Arma is a realistic tactical shooter,
while DayZ is a free-form survival game,
while PUBG is a 1 versus 100 cage match.
Nobody planned this all out, it just sort of happened.
Fortnite was more discovered than designed.
So, when we design a game,
are we really just throwing darts?
Do we have any idea what we're doing?
Another problem with game design is that we often overcorrect
for whatever lesson we just learned.
With Offworld Trading Company,
because the game had random maps,
each game started with a short exploration phase
where you scanned the map and found your colony,
and with only part of the terrain revealed.
We learned quickly during early access
that the multiplayer community
didn't want exploration at all,
because it added luck,
and they wanted no luck at the game's start.
So we added a mode with a fully-revealed map
for these players.
So when we built Old Worlds multiplayer,
we assumed that we would have a similar multiplayer community,
which would want us to minimize randomness.
So with great effort, we maintained a no characters mode,
where the game has literally no characters, no events, no families,
nothing that could add randomness to the game.
However, almost no one uses this mode.
To our surprise, the multiplayer community loves the randomness.
They love seeing and adapting to fresh events each game.
The lesson here is that every game finds a unique subset of players
from the audience that you think you are targeting
and from the ones that you aren't.
You might have made the same mistake if you listened to my GDC Offworld Postmortem.
None of us really know what we're doing.
Remember that at GDC, we are talking about why we think we were successful,
not why we actually were successful, which is essentially unknowable.
Like the chart says, half of what you hear at GDC is BS.
Half of the rest doesn't apply to your game.
Most of what remains, you can't implement.
The rest might be useful, maybe.
Keep in mind, this chart itself might also be BS.
For example, the type of thing you might hear at GDC that turns out to be wrong,
we've been told for years by product managers that people buy cosmetics
in free-to-play games so that they can peacock,
to show off their skins in front of everyone else.
Well, in Valorant, all animations, graphical effects and sounds
are only visible to the purchaser.
Your enemies don't see them.
So it turns out people will pay for cosmetics,
even if they are the only ones who can see them.
Besides the question of whether we know what we are doing as designers,
what about the question of whether games can teach us anything about our world?
Or maybe, let's actually set the bar lower
and see if games can at least teach us anything about sports.
To do that, we need to talk about baseball analyst Boris McCracken,
who, despite his preposterous name, has no relation to either
Zach McCracken or the Alien Mindbenders.
Instead, Boris McCracken revolutionized our understanding of baseball
with an idea he first published on Usenet in 1999.
He called it DIPS, which stands for Defense Independent Pitching Stats.
The basic idea is that while pitchers do have control over balls and strikes,
once the batter hits the ball, the results are no longer in their control.
In other words, barring a strikeout or a walk,
pitchers don't control how many hits they allow.
This may seem like a fairly simple observation,
but baseball is a very old game,
and for over a century,
everyone had assumed the opposite was true,
that some pitchers were better at getting outs,
getting batters out, than others.
The initial response to McCracken's idea,
which threatened to turn our understanding
of pitching upside down,
was shock, disbelief, even hostility.
Although Bill James, the patron saint of progressive baseball analysis,
was initially skeptical, after doing the research,
he determined that McCracken was correct,
and that he felt, quote,
stupid for not having realized this 30 years ago.
So, why am I talking about dips?
What does this mean for video games?
Well, one part of the appeal of games
is that they can theoretically simulate the real world
and teach us about it.
that we can make choices and see those choices be modeled accurately.
But to use just this one specific example,
how could a game written before McCracken's insight on pitching
have any claim to accurately model baseball?
The programmers writing these games
would absolutely make some pitchers better than others at preventing hits,
because that was how everyone thought baseball worked before McCracken.
And of course, if garbage goes in, garbage comes out.
These games could only simulate a faulty understanding of how baseball works.
To underline this point even more, consider this article Bill James wrote in 2015, arguing
that baseball managers were using their starting pitchers incorrectly.
For decades, teams have used a five-man rotation, meaning that there is a new starting pitcher
every fifth day so that each one can pitch at full strength after four days of rest.
James argued that teams should instead use a three-man rotation,
but with much lower pitch counts, relying more on relief pitchers.
Let's say someone wanted to test this theory with a baseball simulation.
Well, even with a sport like baseball that is ideally suited for simulation,
as it is essentially a term-based game,
there is no way to get good results on a three-man rotation
because baseball simulations are written by trying to get their internal numbers
to match real-world results,
not for some deeper understanding of how baseball actually works.
which would then produce accurate results.
Because no one has ever tried a three-man rotation in real life,
no one knows what would actually happen,
how a pitcher would hold up to pitching every three days
instead of every five.
Game designers would just be guessing.
So, what can games simulate?
Strangely, the best example I can think of
is a game trying to recreate a situation
much more difficult to simulate than baseball.
Life as a border guard in a totalitarian country.
Papers, Please succeeds because instead of trying to simulate reality,
it's trying to simulate the personal tensions someone in this position might feel.
The game puts you in difficult situations as a border agent,
processing immigrants who have compelling stories for why they are trying to cross the border.
Would you stop a young girl fleeing from abuse just because she doesn't have all her papers in order?
Who will let you in and who will you keep out?
Sorry, who will you let in and who will you keep out?
What laws will you enforce
and what will you turn a blind eye towards?
However, letting people in illegally
can lead to citations which carry fines
that might lead to your son dying
because you don't have enough medicine.
Is this an accurate simulation?
I mean, who knows?
But it creates a genuine emotional conflict
which we can all relate to.
Is there a right thing to do when helping someone in need will hurt your family?
Losing your family is a loss condition, so you can't just perform as a paragon.
Through this tension, Papers, Please! gives players an understanding of why resistance against an oppressive system
is so hard for people with real lives, and thus, why the powerful are able to stay in power.
So to put it simply, games can simulate empathy much better than they can simulate reality.
Speaking of which, here's a classic line in one of the game's most famous simulations.
SimCity doesn't actually simulate a real city.
It simulates the inside of Will Wright's brain.
Except that's not exactly true.
Very crudely, here are the two poles of 20th century urban planning.
Le Corbusier, who was a proponent of top-down, rationalist city planning,
which separated residential, commercial, and industrial areas.
In contrast, Jane Jacobs challenged this idea with proposals for mixed-use development,
which reflected how cities traditionally grew without central planning.
When Will Wright talks about urban planning,
he is much more likely to praise Jacobs than Corbusier.
Her more contemporary ideas are the ones
he would commonly refer to
in his sprawling game design talks.
For example, in this interview,
when asked about the inspirations for SimCity,
the one urban planner he mentions is Jane Jacobs,
not Corbusier.
However,
Wright was not making a game in the abstract.
He was trying to create a whole city
on a very real Commodore 64.
And the ideas of these two designers
required very different types of coding.
Jacobs' mixed-use urbanism,
which focused on pedestrian flow,
would require agent simulation.
which would be much too complex for an 8-bit system.
On the other hand,
Corbusier's residential, commercial, industrial superblocks
could be handled by much simpler cellular automata,
which is what Wright chose to use.
In other words, the limits of the technology
determined what type of city SimCity would simulate,
regardless of what Will Wright might actually have believed.
So, SimCity ended up with a famous residential, commercial, industrial split
that a rationalist planner like Corbusier might admire,
and which, it needs to be said, is to today considered bad urban design
that leads to crime, slums, and general economic and social decline.
As an admirer of Jacobs, Wright probably understood this too.
So that leaves us with a question.
What meaning should we take from the first SimCity
if it represents an urban model that the designer himself doesn't even believe in?
Is this intentional design?
Accidental design?
Something else?
There is actually a successful city builder
based on this type of agent simulation,
based on the type of agent simulation
needed to support Jacob's ideas.
Faro doesn't use districts.
Instead, its systems are built around little walkers
that move around your city and do their jobs
so that the layout of your streets
and the adjacency of your buildings actually matter.
The game is considered a high watermark for city builders
and a testament to how choosing the right model can matter.
So next I'd like to talk about another game, Kent Hudson's
narrative simulation, The Novelist, which explores
the story of a title character who
has trouble balancing his three biggest priorities, his wife,
his work, and his son.
The game presents you with choices over the course of nine chapters,
moving you up or down in those three different categories.
The inner math is zero-sum,
so if you gain two points in your marriage,
you lose two points between your work and your son.
However, after playtesting, Hudson realized that his game's meaning
was the exact opposite from what he wanted.
My game was telling players you can't have it all.
Life is zero-sum. You can't win.
I don't believe that statement to be true, but people were taking a message from the
game that I fundamentally disagreed with.
Games can escape the intentions of their designers just so easily.
I think one of the issues games like the Novelist face is that it's hard to find human meaning
in a game with just simple math at its core.
Yet games absolutely can teach us about ourselves.
Telltale's Walking Dead games provide a great example of this by showing you how your choices
compare to everyone else's.
If you are one of the 25% of players who kill Stephanie,
you might reflect on why you made that choice
when so many others didn't.
Maybe the best way for games to be about people
is simply to inject more real people into the game.
Let's talk about another example
of designer intent gone awry.
This is Spent, a well-intentioned game
that wants to build empathy for the poor
by showing players just how difficult their life can be.
how they sometimes need to choose between paying the gas bill, repairing the car, and
attending their grandfather's funeral.
That's a bold goal, but is it effective?
One researcher actually aimed to find out.
Here's an article from Psychology Today about an experiment she ran to see how effective
spent was at increasing empathy for the poor.
She writes, after I analyzed the results from the study,
I was dismayed to find that playing the game
had no effect on positive feelings towards the poor.
In fact, the game had a negative effect on attitudes
among certain participants, including some people
who were sympathetic to the poor to begin with.
The problem is agency.
When holding the mouse and making the decisions,
it's very natural to assume that the poor
have the same agency that you do as the player.
Consider this choice right here.
Should you spend the money to attend
your grandfather's funeral?
The problem is that it's very easy for the player to not spend the money
by just hitting the skip memorial button,
and then end up thinking,
why do these poor people have such a hard time saving their money?
One very interesting finding was that the game did produce empathy
when people watched the game instead of playing it.
From my perspective, this is a devastating finding,
because the whole thing we as game designers
have been going on and on and on about for decades
is how games are empathy machines,
because they put you in the shoes of someone else's life.
But here we see the exact opposite effect,
and to make it worse, a passive, non-interactive medium
is the one that produces empathy instead.
However, maybe things are not so dire.
Why, for example, does Papers, Please succeed where Spent fails?
The answer is actually just game design.
Papers, Please took the time and energy to give bite to your decisions,
either from what happens when you turn away those in need
or from how your acts of defiance hurt your family.
In Spent, there's no actual cost to pressing the skip the memorial button
and saving the money, which prevents the player
from actually empathizing with the protagonist.
However, even if designers take the time
to build out all the mechanics needed to create real emotional tension,
things can still go awry.
Consider Sweatshop.
A game designed to raise awareness
about the hostile labor conditions in modern sweatshops.
Indeed, this game earned the honor
of being banned from the Apple App Store
for its depiction of child labor
and unsafe working conditions,
which perhaps hit a little too close to home for them.
The game puts you in the role of the sweatshop manager
who, in order to meet increasingly unreasonable
quota demands from the corporation,
has to cut corners by lowering safety standards,
hiring children, and pushing workers past their limits.
This is what Simon Parkin, one of the designers, had to say about their intentions and the game's meaning.
Whereas a film documentary might piece together the sweatshop story through footage and anecdote,
the game allows players to experience the system from the inside,
with all its cats' cradle of pressures and temptations.
A game can present the system in a more objective manner,
thereby building a different sort of empathy and understanding.
However, trying to get a game across with interactivity is playing with fire.
This is what journalist and game designer Tom Francis said about his experience playing Sweatshop.
At the end of it, I thought, shit, it's hard to run a sweatshop.
Previously, I was like, oh, it's terrible, these conditions in the sweatshop.
Now I'm like, man, you don't know what pressures they're under.
It's hard to meet these quotas.
The problem is that the game puts you in the role of the manager.
So your empathy is for the pressure he is under instead of the workers.
you end up understanding why managers make the compromises they do
and why children end up being mutilated.
Now, there are a couple of different ways to look at that.
If players are able to step back and think about what they just did,
it's sort of amazing that a game could get you to kill kids to hit your t-shirt quota.
But I think it's just as likely that,
in less obviously baleful situations like a sweatshop,
players will always subconsciously identify with whoever they control in a video game.
What does that mean for games where you play the king,
the queen, the ruler, or more generally the status quo,
the existing power structure?
Perhaps the most famous example of a designer's intent
being thwarted is Elizabeth Maggie's
The Landlord's Game from 1906.
It was designed to show the negative effects of rampant capitalism
with an alternate set of rules to show how all the players
would be better off if they adopted a tax system
where rents were paid in the public treasury instead of into the landlord's pockets.
The original rule set contains a very interesting passage
that lays out the designer's intentions.
Maggie points out that players will quickly realize
that under the default monopolistic rule set,
one player will own everything on the board.
The landlord's game was Das Kapital,
made of cardboard and dice.
She invented player elimination to prove out the evils of Monopoly.
Unfortunately for Maggie, collecting rents from your properties and pushing your rivals
into bankruptcy proved to be a lot more fun than having all the money going to the public
treasury and today the game is known as Monopoly, minus the socialist tax rule set.
The lessons here are subtle.
Monopoly absolutely does demonstrate how a capitalist system
will concentrate wealth in the hands of the few
and impoverish the many,
which is what Maggie intended, after all,
by somehow doubt that this is exactly what she had in mind,
or if players perceive of the game as a critique of capitalism.
Fun is an insidious requirement for a game to be played,
and perhaps more importantly, replayed.
Games that aren't much fun tend to just disappear,
and we have to grapple with that as designers.
The very nature of a game makes it extremely difficult
to express a strong position on an issue.
In order to be a game with different potential strategies,
Prison Architect has to suggest that rehabilitation
and punishment are both equally viable options.
The game shape box it is in
prevents it from picking a side,
regardless of what the designers think.
What it can do is show the problems with each path.
You can punish prisoners by searching for contraband every day,
which means your addicts will go into withdrawal
when they can't get their drugs and act out violently.
On the other hand, you can create job training programs,
but that lets the prisoners get their hands on screwdrivers
and other items that can be turned into weapons.
You can have visitation programs,
but then you'll discover a pipeline of drugs being smuggled into the prison.
The game is not, and never could be,
an accurate simulation of prison, because that's impossible.
But it can help players understand the tradeoffs, compromises, and tensions that they may not
have considered before playing.
Now let's talk about DEFCON, a game about nuclear holocaust.
We really are hitting the high points, aren't we?
An interesting study was conducted on how playing the game affected players' opinions
of nuclear war.
The experiment separated the subjects into two groups.
A control group that read articles
on the dangers of nuclear war,
and a treatment group which played DEFCON instead.
There were significant differences
in how these two groups changed their opinion
after the experiment.
Although the control group became more worried
about a nuclear war in the near future,
the DEFCON players strangely became less concerned.
On the other hand, the game players were more pessimistic
that they would survive a war.
The researcher's conclusion, based also on qualitative data,
was that playing DEFCON was more effective
at showing players how destructive nuclear war would be
so that they then assumed that our governments
would be more incentivized to never resort to it.
However, there is one important wrinkle
in the overall results, which are divided up here
by high, medium, and low frequency gamers.
Note that every single group became more concerned
about the threat of nuclear warfare, except for one.
the high frequency gamers in the treatment group,
meaning the ones who play games the most frequently.
The hypothesis is that core gamers quickly saw past
the setting and no longer saw a game about nuclear war
and instead saw an RTS with an unusual art style.
This highlights a huge challenge for trying
to communicate using game design.
If you are working within familiar genre constraints,
over time, both the game's setting and meaning
will eventually disappear.
A similar finding showed up in a study run by Dr. Stephen Blessing and Elena Sakosky
based on a Jeff Engelstein thought experiment about whether players of Ink and Gold would
change their behavior based on simply changing the setting of the game.
Ink and Gold is a push-your-luck game where you delve into an ancient temple for gems
and artifacts, but risk losing it all the farther you go.
To see if the setting affected players, they re-skinned the game twice.
First, as a firefighter game where you rescue victims instead.
And second, as an abstract version where you're just playing for points.
The results they found were that players did change their behavior
based on the setting, at least at first.
This graph shows how often players return to the base,
which means that they have stopped pressing their luck.
In the firefighter setting, this means rescuing less of the victims,
while in the abstract version, it simply means scoring less points.
In this experiment, the firefighters would push their luck more,
taking more risks to save more people.
However, and this is the important part,
by the fourth game, the results had largely converged
and players of all three versions were playing the same way.
Players were now seen past the setting
and just optimizing to scoring the most points,
whether they were called gems or victims or just points.
Setting can matter, but we need to be aware
that players will eventually gravitate
to the game's inner logic and start to ignore the setting.
The more the setting and the rules are disconnected,
the bigger a problem this becomes.
These four games have very different settings and meanings
with a very different set of messages
and emotions for the player.
And yet there are significant parts of these four games
that play out the exact same way,
could even be built on the same shared code base.
Putting players into an established genre dulls the designer's intent because over time
players will stop engaging with the message and meaning of the game and instead just fall
back on instinct.
They are now playing shooter number 34, not a philosophical game about a submerged dystopia
or jaunty adventure with a lovable rogue or contemporary high-tech military thriller.
Instead players are warped back into their dorm room in 1994 and booting up Doom.
Meaning is not a layer built on top of someone else's game.
A game's meaning starts with its basic building blocks,
the core actions that the player is going to be repeating over and over again.
Conflict between designer intent and player behavior
actually predates video games,
as it is a common issue with historical war games.
One of the basic challenges of war game design is how to encourage historical play
when no one knows what the likely or even plausible alternate results could be.
For example, could the South have ever won the Civil War?
And how to recreate the pressures that led to bad decisions,
even when we all know the outcome.
Maybe Napoleon should have known better than to invade Russia,
but even my kids know not to start a land war in Asia.
A good example of this problem is Volko Arunke's Labyrinth, a game about the war on terror
that starts in 2001 and pits the US against Al-Qaeda.
It must have been a difficult game to design for many reasons, one of which is that many
of the US's historical actions, such as the invasion of Iraq, backfired horribly, which
players would presumably want to avoid.
However, when you read the rules for the game, it comes across like a Bush administration
neocon fantasy world.
The mechanics enable a domino effect of Western support throughout the region.
Establishing a democracy in one Middle Eastern country will cause it to spread to its neighbors,
just like we were told would happen in Iraq back in 2003.
When I first encountered the game, I was actually a little shocked,
because it's easy to assume the designer had fallen for this neocon propaganda.
Years later, the designer actually addressed that question head-on.
What if you, as the designer, have a different view
of how the world works than the historical contestants?
To get your players to behave historically,
for your model to work and produce
historically plausible outcomes,
you have to incentivize your players
the way people at the time were incentivized.
What was the US administration's strategy
and what did they think would work?
I have to allow that to work in the game.
Otherwise, the US player doesn't play
like the US in the War on Terror,
regardless of whether Volko thinks those ideas are correct.
This raises the question of what is the point of a historical game?
Is it an attempt to model history?
To actually experiment with alternate outcomes?
Or is it to help us understand why people made decisions
that we find baffling or shocking today?
With Labyrinth, Runke is not trying to recreate history.
Instead, he's trying to recreate the historical mindset of the time.
As we've covered, the ability of a game to simulate the actual world
is extremely limited and thus misleading.
Labyrinth shows a clear example of an alternative,
simulating the pressures, the desires,
and the fears of historical actors,
which can be much more illuminating.
The study of the past is not just about what people did,
but also about why they did it.
And a game can probably do a better job
of teaching the question of why people made choices
they did than any other media.
Let's move that question to a different era,
the medieval world of Crusader Kings.
Now, they could have made the game with a very different focus.
Maybe how best to conquer the world,
or what is the fastest way to advance out of the Middle Ages,
made it more like Civilization, in other words.
Instead, they lead into empathizing with medieval rulers,
putting you under the same pressures that made it difficult to maintain a dynasty
and keep your realm from fracturing.
Which leads to...
lots of posts like these.
How to kill off your hair.
Is it worth it to kill off your brothers?
Indeed, what is the best way to kill off your brothers?
Now that's an interesting question for players to ask
because fratricide was actually official policy
during a certain period of Ottoman history.
For example, when Selim I assumed the throne in 1512,
he quickly executed his two brothers.
Muhammad III had 19 of his brothers and half-brothers murdered.
Eventually, they began imprisoning their family members instead,
which was quite an improvement.
So Crusader Kings certainly meets Runke's goal for a historical game,
to encourage players to behave historically, regardless of whether the designers,
regardless of what the designers of Paradox think,
who presumably have neither killed nor imprisoned their own brothers.
It requires creativity for a game to recreate a historical mindset,
as opposed to being just a historical reenactment.
For example, Europa Universalis includes a randomized new world mode
which makes the game less realistic,
but instead more true to the human experience of the age,
of being an explorer and not knowing what is over the horizon.
There is a similar issue with Victoria,
which designer Chris King outlined a number of years ago.
Historically, colonies just didn't pay.
They tended to be a net loss for the controlling countries,
as it costs more to subjugate, manage, and defend
than it brought back home to the colonizer.
However, a game about 19th century Europe,
in which those nations did not race for colonies,
even if to the detriment of literally everyone in the world,
would clearly put players in an ahistorical mindset.
In Victoria, they solve this problem by making colonies
a necessary part of their economic model,
providing the raw goods and eventually markets
to the players' factories and businesses needed.
It's not a realistic model of history,
but it is a realistic model of what 19th century Europeans
thought was important to them at the time.
An important consideration here is whether players
will understand the line between the game
incentivizing historical behavior
and the game espousing a worldview.
In Cole Whirly's infamous Traffic, you play English aristocrats who are profiting from
selling opium in China during the 19th century.
You are playing bad people doing bad things, and the designer underlines this by how victory
works.
The money you earn in China gets converted into frivolous prizes back home in London,
including my favorite, a fancy hat.
The game is telling you that it knows you are doing bad things, and you shouldn't feel
good about the fancy hat you ended up with as your prize.
A game's framing can matter a great deal to help players separate a historical mindset
from actual reality.
What if, at the end of Civilization, instead of telling you how much land you conquered,
the wrap-up screen told you how many cultures you destroyed, and how many languages disappeared?
I started my career very passionate about making games about history.
Games that could sit next to a book or document as a legitimate secondary source on world
history.
My history thesis paper in college was a game that simulated the life of a shopkeeper living
in early modern Oxford, based on my research in the Oxford Shire archives.
It didn't just model the change in prices over time,
but also your standing in the local Mercer's and Grocer's Guild,
as well as your family life, as the line between personal and business affairs
was not as fixed back then,
so you have to worry about your children and their future.
Two years later, I started working on Civilization III,
and I was super pumped.
I had just read Guns, Germs, and Steel
and was inspired to make the video game version.
However, I quickly ran into the goofy reality of video games,
of how players will twist your games into what they want to play.
I learned that you can't just put horses and wheat and pigs on one continent but not on
another and expect players to be okay with starting in the wrong place.
And then I met the twin evils of civilization.
Infinite City Sprawl, which is how the game encourages cramming cities into every possible
spot on the map, and the Eternal China Syndrome, which is how once the initial expansion phase
is over, the game becomes static and dull.
These effects have nothing to do with history and everything to do with players
seeing past the historical setting to the game's inner math.
So, after making Civ III and abandoning the idea that I was making a history simulator,
I had to ask myself, what could I actually communicate with Civ IV?
Why make that game at all?
In doing so, I started down a path that led me to why I make strategy games.
Here is the Civ IV civics screen.
In Civs I through III, you adopted an ideology.
Monarchy, despotism, communism, democracy,
which came with a bunch of bonuses and penalties.
Basically, judgments on the designer's part
on what those ideologies meant.
I dropped that entirely for Civ IV and implemented a build-your-own-government system where you
choose where power lies, the type of economy, how the legal system works, and so on.
You could have a police state with a free market, or you could have slavery mixed with
free speech, or you could mix universal suffrage with state property.
The whole point was to defy ideological labels to get the player to see past them.
If the 20th century has a single theme, it is that ideology itself is a failure.
Dogmatic leaders used ideologies to demonize the opposition,
which usually meant helping the strong to terrorize the weak.
From Nazi death camps to the Soviet gulags, to China's Cultural Revolution,
to America's McCarthyism, the 20th century was full of ideas
that gave power to autocratic leaders,
not afraid to destroy the lives of those who resisted.
Much as we hate to admit it, those leaders were often supported by masses of people
who believed in the stories those leaders told, the ideologies they espoused.
Demagogues love the labels that ideologies provide because they obscure and dehumanize
the opposition.
Both sides of the Cold War made liberal use of the terms communist and capitalist to define
and differentiate each other, even though the U.S. government has slowly adopted communist
programs piecemeal over the last century.
Why exactly was the US, a country with Social Security, Medicare, welfare, a minimum wage,
labor laws, and trade unions, killing people to keep communism out of Vietnam?
In fact, if you took a typical red-fearing, union-busting industrialist from 1923
and sent him 100 years into the future and explained to him how America works now,
he would probably assume that the communists won after all.
Labels exist to separate and control people, and I wanted the civic system to encourage
people to look past these labels and at the actual choices a society needs to make when
governing itself.
It was no accident that I attached Mount Rushmore to fascism.
Carving mammoth statues of your country's leaders into a mountain is fascist, even if
we do not live under Capital F Fascism.
Our own self-labeling as a capitalist democracy does not protect us from charges that our
country is damaging the world when our policies hurt real people.
I often get asked whether Offworld is a free trade game,
or an anti-capitalist game,
or some other statement on the world economy.
I don't think games should make broad statements like
capitalism is good, or capitalism is bad.
It's just too simplistic, and as we've discussed,
injecting a heavy-handed message can so easily go off the rails.
In Offworld, if iron costs more than steel,
something has gone wrong,
and you win by taking advantage of those discrepancies.
There's a reason why everything costs what it does.
Sometimes that goes beyond just supply and demand
to government policy and cultural factors,
but there's always a reason.
And if we don't like what something costs,
we should find out why instead of just complaining about it.
More broadly, I made Offworld for the same reason I made Civ IV,
to push against dogmatic, ideological thinking,
the idea that there is one solution to everything.
In a good strategy game, the answer to every question,
which resource is most important,
what should I research first,
must always be, well, it depends.
The point of having to make tough choices
and to adapt to the environment
is that there is never, ever,
just one right approach to every situation.
Ideologies inevitably lead to a belief
that there is one set of solutions to the world's problems.
And I believe that a good strategy game
always challenges this type of thinking.
So let's go back to the question about whether games can teach us anything about our world.
I hope I have demonstrated the folly of thinking that we can simulate the world,
even on a scale as small as a baseball season,
while still showing the value in using games to build empathy for others across place and time.
How can we do more of that and how can we do it better than we have so far?
Okay, now I'm going to tell you something that is definitely in the 10% useful chart,
in the 10% useful part of this pie chart.
We game designers have no idea what we are doing.
To be a good designer, you have to abandon the idea
that you're anything other than an explorer.
You know how we all feel like we are impostors?
Well, what if we were actually right?
It's actually bad to lose this feeling.
If you think you have figured out game design,
your career is over.
We are not creating order systems.
We are creating chaos for the player to find order in.
I would extend this quote to say that designers who try to make ordered systems put their
intentions, the meaning of their game, at risk, because players will break those systems.
Players don't care about the imaginary game you have in your head.
Indeed, players understand our games better than we do.
When evaluating design talent, the most important trait I look for is humility.
Designers need to be able to hold two contradictory ideas in their heads at all times.
to hold true to their design vision,
even when success is uncertain,
but also to always assume that their vision is meaningless
until they see it in the hands of real players.
They need to have both a big enough ego
to follow their own path,
but a small enough ego to assume
that they are probably wrong.
So, why make games at all
if the players ultimately take them away from us?
Why am I still here trying to climb up that hill?
Well...
What if that infamous Barbados-Grenada match was actually the most interesting game of soccer ever played?
Maybe it's amazing that the soccer team ended up defending both goals.
Maybe it's amazing that the socialist landlord's game turned into the capitalist monopoly.
Maybe it's amazing that Sweatshop created more empathy for sweatshop managers than for the suffering workers.
Maybe it's even amazing that spent somehow made people less sympathetic towards the poor.
Strictly speaking, these four examples are all failures,
but the way they fail doesn't at all suggest that games are useless.
Instead, their failures show us just how powerful games can be.
Right now, we are like children playing with fire.
We don't know what we are doing, or we might end up setting the wrong thing ablaze.
So in the spirit of humility, I don't have the answers
for how to make sure our games don't end up conveying a message
that is the opposite of what we intended.
But I do know of some games that have succeeded better than others.
And I bet you do, too.
Just remember that simply stating that your game is about X or Y
doesn't make it so.
The only people who truly understand your game are your players.
So if you want to know what your game means, make sure you ask them.
And thank you for your time.
Alright, thanks everyone. Be sure to fill out your evaluations. I know I'm supposed to say that, I actually did it this time.
And, I know it's a broad talk but we do have time for questions if anyone wants to ask anything.
Hello Chris.
Great talk. I wanted to talk about Fortnite.
Okay, that's funny, we were just talking about this last night.
I play way too much Fortnite, and I wanted you to...
The arc you laid out was slightly wrong in that the pros don't play Zero Build.
And I'm curious what you think, since players are the ones who are the final arbiter of what the game is about.
Zero Build is kind of considered a thing for casuals, like get those people out of the game,
and building is where the actual magic is, which I think actually is true.
There's that aspect of the question about pros versus amateurs in games.
And then the second thing is like, one thing about building is they managed to not fuck it up.
Like they took, they made the game as a fast follow to PUBG, obviously.
The building was in there, they left it in there.
They were, and it, the pros like found the amazing thing there.
And Epic eventually, after trying to slow it down and stuff, realized, you know, this is where the real game is.
kind of reading the game, listening to the game, and the players, and like doubling down
on that is really important, I think.
Right.
So I did spend some time, you know, I saw that they, you know, they took out building,
and to me building was always like, it's so bizarre that this is part of this game, because
obviously that was not, that was not the, sorry to put this, you know, PUBG or whatever
does not have building, right?
Like that's not always a key part of what made the game work, right?
And Fortnite...
did, you know, whatever, the fast follow, right?
They're like, we're gonna, we're gonna adapt,
but we've got all this other baggage that comes along with it,
and we'll just see if it works, right?
And so, you know, it's like that for sure is accidental design, right?
Like, who knows what happens?
Maybe that's great, maybe it's not.
And so, yeah, I spent some time trying to figure out,
because I saw that, okay, great, they took it out.
Or at least there's a mode without it.
So that means they at least have understood that.
And I couldn't quite figure out what the community thought.
I saw that some people said that that was good,
and they were happy with it.
But I knew that like...
You know, it's possible that that would not,
but that's kind of the whole point.
Like, I know that the player's gonna choose
one of those paths or not.
Yeah, I mean, it was a parallel mode.
They didn't actually take it out.
They removed it.
I understand, yeah.
Like, I mean, that's good.
Like, first of all, that is a great way to do development.
Right, like if you're making the radical shift to your game
and you can make it that simple, like go for it.
I mean, it's them admitting they don't know.
Yeah, exactly.
Right, this is, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, yeah, it kind of just comes back to the idea
that like, it's, you know,
And it's also interesting that different layers of the game,
people have different opinions, right?
Like Casuals versus Hardcore, right?
They have a different purpose when they're playing the game.
No, and in fact, streamers came back to play Zero Build
because those people all aged out,
because you have to be 12 with 12-year-old reflexes to build.
Like, it's so crazy now.
And then, you know, somebody like Tfue or whatever,
who's 23, just can't do it anymore.
But they came back for Zero Build.
So it's like, it's a very high-dimensional space
they were playing in.
All right, does anyone have a non-Fortnite question?
Yeah, hi.
So I was curious with those games that were considered failures, it seemed like
that, and maybe this is a bit reductionist as a way of looking at it,
it seems like the best thing to affix those would have been to find the right,
you know, POV instead of, you know, maybe playing as a sweatshop owner, you're
playing as one of the workers. Do you think that a lot of those problems
could have been solved just from changing the vantage point of where
those games were being designed from?
Um, possibly. I mean, the hard part is I'd really have to think through how to,
what's the right way to make a game about sweatshops. And I don't necessarily think
that the game is a failure. I think it's, it's complicated, right? Like, I think for some people,
they'll play the game and, you know, they'll, they'll go down the path of like, oh, I'm making
the, you know, do these choices.
And, you know, like maybe later they'll be like, wow, I can't believe I did that stuff.
You know, I see, you know, it makes me think Sweatshop is horrible.
Whereas other people... I mean, I think generally speaking,
what I was really trying to get at was that...
I don't think anyone plays Sweatshop and comes away thinking like, I guess Sweatshops are fine.
I don't think anyone actually thinks that. I was trying to like use that point to kind of illustrate
like, okay, fine, but guess what? We have a bunch of games where you play the government.
Or you play the status quo, or you play the king, or whatever.
And we need to think about, OK, that framing very much
affects what you think is OK or not OK.
Where are we engendering empathy?
Yeah, exactly.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thank you very much for a very inspirational talk.
It was fantastic.
In his 2006 GDC talk, Glenn Hawking
described the self-exploration systems.
that would drive player values into conflict.
Maybe that's a solution to make people conflicted
about their values instead.
As you were asking the question,
I was really realizing,
oh, I forgot to repeat the questions.
And then I need you to repeat your question.
Okay.
In his 2006 GDC talk,
Exploration from Spaces,
from,
Systems to Spaces to Self, Clint Hocking has proposed a self-exploration system, a method
of attaching core verbs into various hidden values that would drive those values into
conflict and make players question about themselves.
Maybe that's a solution to make people conflicted about their own values instead of the objectives
of the game.
Okay, could you give me an example?
I'm trying to understand what you mean.
I understand.
Clint Hawking has suggested an Ultima 4 where there are various hidden values that the player
did not directly see, but sort of allow those specific values to explore themselves.
You mean that to be less explicit about these are your values, it's more like you're performing
them or like you're giving a chance to be them?
Is that what that means?
Right.
Like...
We usually have in games that you lose, you make enemy NPCs lose morale, but you don't
feel like you've broken their will, sort of drive their conflict to let them actually
experience what they were doing.
Right.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean I think that, I think a lot of times in games, you know, we can...
But you put labels of something, this is honorable,
this is good, this is evil, this is whatever, right?
But like, you know, we should be,
what's much more interesting is like,
what's actually happening.
Like, you know, this is why I say at the end,
like just saying something is X or Y
doesn't kind of make it that way.
Right.
So, yeah.
Thank you.
Cool, thank you.
Hi, I was wondering what is the origin story of this talk?
Like, what made you wake up one day and say,
I'm gonna teach a master class on empathy in game design?
Right, okay, so I got that one.
The question is, what is the origin of this talk?
So I've been basically squirreling,
like I mentioned, I gave that talk in 2010.
And that one, that was really initiated
by just being bugged by the rules of Ticket to Ride.
That was like, it's a really bizarre game because if you ask, you take anyone, you say,
hey, have you played Ticket to Ride?
Like, yeah, Ticket to Ride is great.
What's it about?
Oh, you're a train company and you're building trains, train tracks across the country
and you're monopolizing markets and you're controlling everything.
And it's like, yeah, that's right.
That is what it's about.
Then you crack open the rules, like, no, it's actually about a contest
to cross the US the fastest or hit the most cities or whatever.
It's like a...
across the US in 80 days type thing, I don't know. Um, and it makes no sense, especially
because like the mechanics don't support that at all, right? Like, there's no reason why
one person can, you know, why, if someone gets the, you know, Chicago to St. Louis route,
why can no one, anyway, I'm going on too long, but anyway, the point is, um,
There was this huge mismatch, and I was like,
okay, it really made, the designer does not have the right
to determine what the game's about
when the players clearly realize
the game's about something else, right?
And so, you know, I kinda did that talk,
and then, you know, I just kept noticing
these kind of examples come up of like,
a designer was trying to do this,
and then it ends up, kind of ended up in the wrong place,
at the opposite place, and so, you know, I,
I just wanted to frame that for people to remember that it's a spirit of humility.
It's very easy to get the stuff wrong, and I thought it'd be important to highlight places where it's gone wrong,
but also places where people have done a really good job with it.
I don't know, I hope that's a good answer.
Thank you.
This is kind of following up on things going wrong.
I was interested in Spent, where it was a more successful message when it failed as
a game, like when it was a screen recording rather than something with player agency.
When you're thinking about how to get across a message,
if there's times when you feel like sacrificing things
that are generally considered traditionally just good game
design works best for the message,
rather than always shooting for best design that then also
conveys it.
Are there places where you have to sacrifice things,
like player agency, that maybe is a worse quote unquote game,
but ends up being better in terms of message?
If that makes sense.
You're asking?
Let me just say that, I mean, to me the issue with spent is that they needed to go farther,
right?
They needed to kind of build out the rest of the world, which is like, you know, more
gameplay like surround it so like you actually see what's happening.
Could you kind of like, what are you asking exactly in that context?
Yeah, because I guess I was thinking about like things like feeling like a lack of agency
and like one of the ways to do it is like make people feel like there's, you know, like
cost to their decisions.
But do you feel like, in general,
are there ways where you can make people feel bad,
I guess, and have it be a,
like would it be sort of like papers please,
or are there, I don't know, sort of less?
Right.
Yeah, so the question is how to make people feel bad.
Yeah.
Well, that's a good question.
Maybe that'll be my next talk.
I've often kind of wondered about this, because in Papers, Please, it's just a simple thing.
You don't even see a picture of your son. You don't see you guys throwing the ball back and
forth or whatever they do in their dystopian country. They don't have a name. You just see
son. Son is sick. Son is dead. We're humans, so we map our lives onto that. You don't necessarily
have to do all that much, so it's kind of amazing that that kind of works.
The thing that pops in my head is the...
No, no, the guy who does the comic book,
Understanding Comics, Scott McCloud.
Yeah, you know, like that thing of like,
okay, the thing we can most relate to
is just the simplest happy face, right?
Like it's kind of like in that ballpark, right?
Like you don't, you actually, if you give a lot of room
for the player to map their lives onto,
it kind of like, there's probably more there,
so maybe less is more in that regard,
but you gotta do something, right?
You gotta give some bite to it.
Awesome, thank you.
I think the fact that it allows that there's a stage before dead, the sick, matters because you fail.
So there's a similar conversation happening right now in AI ethics about what they're
calling the Waluigi effect.
This is a real thing, Google it.
But basically the idea is that in order to teach an AI to be anti-racist...
You are essentially also teaching them to be racist.
Right? Like, you know, whatever.
Like, don't do X, don't do Y, don't do Z.
All you have to do is invert those things.
And now suddenly, you know, so you can teach them to be an anti-racist
and then suddenly say, oh, by the way, you're a secret Nazi.
And then it pulls the mask off and suddenly, right?
And so one of the questions that's kind of coming up is like,
how bi-directional is that?
Right, like can you then say you're a secret, like, and yeah, if you can sort of bring,
maybe we can bring this back to the, like, to the games going opposite to people's design intentions,
how easy is it to, do we think, to like flip it back? Right, if that makes any sense.
How easy... Okay.
Can you explain just the actual question?
Sorry.
So, like, you talk about...
So, you talk about games that are failures.
Right.
That convey the opposite of what they mean.
Is there another layer you can put on top of it to get it to once again convey...
To convey your intention. Oh, I see. So like if a game is such a failure
Then like you could theoretically get the negative of it. It's only a success
Or is there is there a gravity towards badness or like can we like actually
Somehow you like fail on purpose and then end up
End up in a good place
Right, so, I mean, to some extent, that was my section on framing was about that.
Right.
Like, if, you know, all these things, you know, it's...
Definitely there's nothing in my talk, anyone, like anyone who interpreted this,
like, this is, this is like absolutely good, this is absolutely bad.
Like, you know, like, even, even stuff like spent, you know,
it's kind of interesting to see some of the stuff going on there, right?
And...
Hmm.
I'm sorry, where do I put this?
So...
Yeah, it's, you know, you have to delve in difficult areas if you're dealing with, like,
okay, you're playing people doing bad things, you're taking bad actions, and so you're going
to have to, you have to figure out, you have to think about the framing of it, right? I think
that that's super important. I'll need some more time to think through a better answer.
Maybe we have time for one more?
So you think in some of these like situations where the emotional response is sort of
mis-applied, like it creates the empathy just in the wrong spot, you think a lot of it
could just be a matter of like over-subtlety, like kind of without, for lack of a better
term, being too cute? Like I think of games like uh this War of Mine or uh, and of course I
blank on the name now.
Uh, Frostpunk, where, oh, you're, you're basically playing a totalitarian dictator, but we're sort
of being explicit about it, so we can kinda make you feel bad in the right place. You think,
like, maybe it's a, just trying to be too subtle all of a sudden is the thing that makes you
misapply that empathy?
Um, the question is, is being too subtle causing us to misapply the empathy?
Yeah, like is that...
Like being really, you know, like going into like, like, like, hey, you're playing a sweatshop manager and, you know, that's not, you know, you already should feel bad before you start the game, maybe, right?
Like, uh, yeah, I'm having a hard time thinking on the spot to like figure out exactly what to do about this.
But, um, uh, yeah, I don't know.
I mean, that.
You know, I do think a lot about, you know, people, a person playing a game where, you know, they're controlling a country and the country does bad things, right?
And they don't think about their own responsibility because that's just...
They don't think necessarily about...
They don't necessarily apply that to their own thinking about the world because, you
know, that's just what you do in a video game, right?
And to some extent I don't think we'll ever get away from that a little bit, right?
Because like it is still fun to play Civ and conquer the world, but you know, we need,
we...
We do need to be a little more, yeah,
I think we do need a little more explicit
in games like that to, I don't know,
we don't need like a Civ content warning or something,
but like, you know, like warning, you know.
Warning might be colonial.
Yeah, you're gonna wipe out cultures, right?
But yeah, I mean, I think it's,
you want to think about having some correctives
in the presentation of the game
to account for that, for sure.
Awesome, thank you.
Okay, all right, thank you everyone.