Welcome to the second annual Been There, Done That.
Industry veterans share their experiences and advice.
My name is Kim McAuliffe, and I'm just
here to introduce the session.
But I'm going to hurry up and hand you off to Lauren.
Hey, everybody.
Hi. Thanks for coming so early. So, I'm kind of, sort of, probably in almost a similar
spot as a lot of you guys. I'm 24. I was just in college like three years ago.
And so I have an interesting kind of perspective on academia and the industry
and how they kind of compare and contrast.
So I'm going to share a little bit of that with you because you might be kind
of thinking about, oh, you know, which way maybe do I want to go?
Do I want to go to school?
Do I want to go straight to industry?
So hopefully I can shed a bit of light on that.
So a bit about me, I work at Hangar 13, we just shipped Mafia 3, I'm a systems designer,
designed the economy, did some dialogue systems stuff, and before that I was at Zynga as a
designer, that was my first job out of college.
And then in college I went to UC Santa Cruz, they have an amazing games program.
Woo-hoo!
Yeah, go slugs.
Yeah, we have a great games program, very supportive.
And there I worked on such games as IGF Finalist Prom Week
and a game called Xylem, which was a weird puzzle game
for DARPA for some insidious thing.
So academia or industry, what's right for you?
What kind of is the deal with these?
So for academia, one of the main things is that it's just so much about exploration,
about the fringes of our industry and our craft,
and that's one of the most exciting things about it.
If you're interested in just going out and, like, you know,
exploring and really developing, like, weird shit, like, this is the way to go.
But college is also extremely self-guided.
And my experience is like undergrad,
I did a lot of research with graduate students.
But just anecdotally, the graduate students I've worked
with, it's even more self-guided.
And you can end up staying in a grad program for years and years
and years if you're not extremely focused in on what
you want to do.
The game to the bottom left is Xylem.
And the way I found that was just asking professors,
hey, what can I do?
I'm interested in doing something interesting.
And they were like, oh, yeah, we have this opportunity.
So you really have to just go and get it yourself.
And you need good discipline to really do
anything of substance.
One thing about academia is you definitely shouldn't think of it as just a stepping stone in your career.
You should think of it as, if you're going to commit to it, really commit as a really important part of your career.
And get the most out of it as you can.
If I just went to school and took my classes, I wouldn't have tried to go above and beyond and do cool shit.
No to bad stock photos.
So yeah, some benefits of academia are
you'll learn really cool critical thinking skills
that kind of help you think in a different way
than just industry.
I approach problems kind of differently maybe.
And you can really push the boundaries of our medium.
And you'll also end up with
just an installed group of people
that you know in the industry right off the bat,
the people that you work with in college.
downsides, because these may not be downsides for you, but projects are really long-term.
I've heard from a lot of grad students that they feel siloed from the rest of the industry,
kind of over here in this weird corner. Your findings, although they will be cherished by
academia, they may not make it into the industry at large for a while, because the industry has...
Well, I'll get to that. Next is industry.
So you're kind of just thrown right into the deep end of the pool on this one.
I just got to Hangar 13 and they threw the engine at me and they were like,
all right, learn our scripting shit and you can do it. All right, go.
So this is self-guided in kind of a different way.
So you kind of have to be confident in, and even if you...
aren't completely confident at the beginning, just know that you can
eventually get it and just try.
I couldn't find a stock but a diverse group of people working, I wonder why.
But it's great for learning how to work in a really diverse, big group,
potentially.
The industry is extremely fast-paced, as you might have heard.
You work under a lot of pressure.
You have like deadlines, like academia has deadlines, but like industry has deadlines
that are based on, you know, money and other people's jobs and like really high stakes.
And in industry, there's less experimentation.
Sometimes I'll try to propose something
that I think is really cool,
but it's always, can you prove it out?
Even if it's a new concept,
is it kind of rooted in a solid foundation
that we know it'll succeed and do well and make us money?
So for industry, it's cool to just kind of see,
and really get down and dirty into the,
actual work, I don't know. I mean, academia is actual work too, but anyway.
And then you can work on really big projects and learn a lot of new tools and stuff.
The downsides are that it can be a bit unforgiving. This is going to ring in a second.
So yeah, you kind of just have to...
But yeah, and you kind of just have to really throw yourself into it.
And you can't really make too many mistakes.
Well, you can, but only within reason.
Like, academia, you can really explore who you are as a designer
and what you want to do.
And school is for making mistakes, but industry, it's less so.
And morale, you know, whatever.
It kind of depends on personality type.
So which is for you?
Depends on, you know, kind of just what you want to do
and based on kind of both of these analyses,
like what fits your personality, your goals,
and the trajectory of your career.
And you can always merge the two if you want.
Like I did, you know, you can...
Do academia first, then do industry.
They both inform each other.
They're not as divorced as you would think.
So that's always something you can do.
And shoot for the stars, because you're awesome.
Thanks.
I think it's movie.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Hey, friends.
Sorry, it's Friday GDC.
I've, of course, lost my voice.
My name is Brittany Albert.
I've been a professional producer in games
for almost nine years now.
I started my career at Fitzel,
primarily working on the John Delife
and Scribblenauts franchises.
I briefly flirted with Free to Play Mobile
at Drop Forge Games.
And I'm currently at City State Entertainment,
overseeing the engineering team
on a PVP-focused MMO called Camelot Unchained.
I'd always had the plan of becoming a programmer in the game industry.
After high school, I preferred my undergrad in computer science.
I was fortunate enough to get an internship one summer where I had an opportunity to work
on game pipeline tools.
But not everything was sunshine and rainbows.
The work just wasn't satisfying.
I felt like I was punching a clock in the morning and evening.
I got some in-the-moment satisfaction through code, but it turns out that my original career
choice wasn't all it was cracked up to be.
In college, I'd work on game projects with other classmates.
In addition to programming, I would
have to wear the producer hat and manage
the scheduling for the team.
And working with my college cohorts
taught me that a producer's job is more than just moving
Post-It notes from left to right on a corkboard.
It's making sure that your team has what
they need to be successful.
It's problem solving, where the problems affect
the people you care about most and see every day,
and the people who are giving their all
for the sake of the game.
So sure, production can be summed up as kind of like cat hurting, but ultimately it's about
being the person who cares most about the well-being of the team.
Simply put, the team builds the game, the producer builds the team.
So at the conclusion of my internship,
I made the realization that while I loved solving programming
problems, I got so much more satisfaction out
of helping people make games that they are proud of.
So after lots of school and a pile of debt,
I decided I wasn't going to be a programmer.
Maybe you've had this thought too
about changing the direction of your career,
whether it's changing from one discipline to another,
entering the game industry from another industry,
or going into a management role after being
an individual contributor.
Society often sees changing a previously made decision
as a very negative trait, so we tend to shy away against it.
I'm here today to tell you how to do it,
so it's far less scary.
First off, prepare yourself to ask a lot of questions,
starting with, why are you thinking
about changing your career?
Maybe your interests have changed and you don't want to do the same thing forever. A
change of pace is nice. Uh maybe your current path isn't for you. Whether you just don't
see yourself in it long term, uh you don't like where you're at or you just don't have any
future prospects. Maybe your decision is financial. You might want to make more money
than you currently are. Conversely, uh you may be shying away from jumping because you
can't necessarily take a pay cut. Before making the switch, I'm going to talk a little bit
Ask yourself, do I need a new role or just a new job?
Is it the environment that's not working for you
or the work itself?
Maybe you're just not feeling the game you're working on.
Maybe the game you're working on is awesome,
but the team could be more supportive.
Maybe the team is amazing, but your boss is a total asshole.
Changing career path isn't going to fix that.
So is there something keeping you from changing your mind?
I resisted becoming a producer for a long time
because a lot of classmates in college would say,
oh, of course you're gonna be a producer
because girls aren't very good at programming.
And I wanted to stay in engineering
so I could prove them wrong.
But proving someone wrong is great in the moment,
but that's not going to provide me long-term satisfaction.
So you've asked yourself all these questions
and you're still like, yeah, I'm gonna take the jump.
So how do you do it?
Set goals for yourself.
Define a positive meaning and definition of success.
Develop realistic expectations for what
it is you're trying to do.
For me, this was starting out producing
a small engineering team.
And if I could do that successfully,
I wanted to branch out to disciplines I didn't know
very well, like design and art and audio.
Eventually, I ended up leading production on a full title, but that doesn't happen overnight.
Setting an unobtainable goal at the beginning may not give you the positive reinforcement
you need to keep yourself going along.
It is critical that you find a mentor in what it is you want to do so you have a person
you can ask for advice as you chart your new territory.
If you can, find a mentor in your gender, race, or sexual orientation because there
will be unique challenges that you'll face.
It may not be wise to jump right in.
Go on a trial run before you can make the leap.
Verify that your initial interest in a new path
could pan into something,
or if you should even go that route at all.
One way to do this is to ask your manager
to try out some of the responsibilities
your new position would entail.
We once had a programming intern
who had an interest in production,
and she had asked if she could spend two weeks
shadowing producers, and those two weeks taught her
she in no way wanted to be a producer.
Be flexible, know that you might have to add extra work
to your current responsibilities in order to try this out.
Know that it might not be a clean transition
into your new role.
Be prepared to train your replacement leaving a new role.
You are taking on a lot of work in this scenario.
And with all of that, things might still go wrong.
You might fail.
But success at anything is really hard
and you can't fail if at first you didn't try something.
you will have to pay your dues again.
Regardless of what you did before,
you now have to prove yourself in a new role.
I hadn't shipped a game as a producer
before moving into that role.
I had no background.
Your relationships will change.
Who you talk to every day will change.
What you can talk to them about,
who you hang out with after work may be different.
When I moved into a different position on the org chart,
I couldn't always go to the bar with my team
because my presence isn't going to let the team fully relax.
As a producer, I've been put in positions
where I've had to fire my friends.
So even though I feel like I've made the right choice
in changing careers, all the sunshine and rainbows
I was looking for aren't really totally there.
But maybe your new direction doesn't actually work out.
This is just a bump in the road.
Don't worry.
You can go back where you came from,
or try something new again,
or go a completely different direction.
If making games was easy, everyone would do it.
Sometimes it sucks.
But everything that is worth it takes time and work.
And with that, I'm going to leave a little motivation.
I'll leave you with some wise words
from my personal hero, Dwayne The Rock Johnson.
If something stands between you and your success, move it.
Never be denied.
Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Nekles, and I'm the UX designer working for Ember Entertainment.
Today I'm going to talk about enjoy the challenges which make you stronger.
Let me introduce myself briefly.
Before working for Ember, I was the UI artist
working for Fifth Cell, and I got my master's degree
in human-computer interaction
and a bachelor's degree in fine arts.
I'm very excited to be here today,
sharing my first 18-month experience
in the game industry with you.
So, first of all, I want to talk about
why I choose to join the game industry.
Like 18 months ago, I was a graduate student.
I regard myself as a user experience designer
because that was my major and I really love it.
I've applied hundreds of jobs, went to kinds of meetups,
talking with hundreds of people,
and interviewed with different companies.
But I still have no idea where will be
the starting point of my career.
But I've never forgot one particular Tuesday.
I went to interview at a game studio in Belleville, Washington.
After that, I started to realize that the way of designing game experience
is so different than designing most softwares.
It's more fun and delightful.
It also contains so many sparkles and details.
So I started to fall in love with games and determined
to start my career in game industry.
The first challenge I met was lacking of game-related experience.
For me, game industry is like a brand new world.
I started to learn game design courses online,
and fortunately got a great mentor.
He helped me a lot during the work,
and I learned a lot from him as well.
The work started getting easier as I learned more
about game and the developing process.
But something just happened unexpectedly.
I lost my first job after six months.
That's truly a heartbreak hurt.
and the company was shut down.
So I have to face my second challenge in the career.
How can I get another job within 90 days?
So why 90 days?
Because some of you may know, as international students,
we have a limitation that we have
to get a job within 90 days after graduation.
Otherwise, we will not be allowed
to stay in the US using the current visa.
I was panicked and felt helpless, just like many of you may experience the worst moments
in your lives.
But luckily, I received many help from others in the industry, and that was when I met Brittany.
She helped me getting out of this disaster and referred me to this new job.
There is one sentence that Britney told me that I will never forget.
In the industry, people always help each other.
There are many lifelong challenges that we have to face in our career,
but it's the challenges which make us stronger.
Please be prepared for the challenges and be ready for the changes.
Here are a few tips I want to share with you
as your career start.
Keep reaching out to people in the industry
and try to learn from them.
Don't be shy.
Keep practice your hard skills
and your soft skills as well.
So when you're practicing your hard skills,
you would be better to go to the meetups,
know more people and have coffee talks with them.
And keep helping others just like how they help you.
Be confident, be curious, be diligent, and be grateful.
Thank you.
Hello, I'm Mary Olson, I'm the executive producer of our internal development team at a studio
called 343 Industries.
I'm going to talk from my part of the panel.
I'm going to be sharing my talk on what it means to lead and affect positive change from
anywhere you are on a development team.
So I'm going to use my background in audio as an illustration, but really this applies
to any area.
So here's a quick view of my career path for some context.
So I started playing music as a kid,
which led to an education in sound engineering
and experimental music.
And then in 1996, I started working on games
as a sound designer, then an audio director,
switching to production as an audio producer on Halo 4,
a lead producer on Halo 5, and then now today, I'm an EP.
So, there you go.
Few of the games I showed.
A common thing that you may experience if you're an audio person or if you hang out
with any audio people is the feeling of persecution.
Audio is often an afterthought, not always prioritized
on the same level as art, design, and dev.
And even if you're in an environment like 343, which
actually puts high value and priority on audio,
it's still downstream from everything else,
and often up against kind of a brick wall of deadlines,
release dates, or events like E3, and things like that.
So, while the audio team is pushing to meet their deadlines in Quality Bar, they're also
impacted by any delays or dysfunction that come earlier in development.
So all of this is exacerbated on large teams that ship big games all at once, but the principle
scales to any size of team or release model even as well.
So, because of this, team culture, health, and process,
which you see above the dotted line,
as well as every aspect of a game, which you see below,
all have a direct impact on audio in a game,
and then also, ultimately, the game itself.
So, any area that can be improved
throughout the studio and the game
also have a direct positive impact on audio,
and therefore, the quality of the game.
So with all those factors affecting audio,
let's look at what audio is actually
responsible for in the game.
So here's what you're actually improving
when audio is in a healthy position.
So the impact is quite big.
So with all that in mind, every audio person
has to make a choice.
This was clear to me early on, and I've continued to make this choice over and over.
And by the way, this choice is not limited to audio.
If you've ever found yourself bitching about another team or disciplines, they screwed
you over, the work you're doing, you know, the work you're trying to do, that mentality
kills collaboration.
And sometimes it kills whole games and whole teams.
So we all have this choice to make.
Are you going to be a victim or are you going to be an advocate?
I am suggesting that we all become advocates and be the change we want to see.
Not necessarily with weapons.
But what about stepping on toes?
On our team, we have an empowerment culture, and making the right kind of changes is encouraged
because we acknowledge that it makes better games.
But even if you don't...
there's still hope.
Because I'm not actually suggesting
that we all go out and take over
and run other departments or areas.
That's not actually exactly what I mean.
With the wrong approach to change,
it can go horribly wrong.
If you do feel another part of your team
is like screwing you over,
go do something about it.
But do it in the right ways.
And here are a few suggestions for how to do that.
Focus on the end result.
So focusing on the end result is critical
to moving past personalities, egos, and details
that sometimes just get in the way
of trying to solve problems
and trying to affect change in the right way.
So anything that gets in the way of the end result
is focusing on the end result rather,
can really help clear that stuff away.
Be humble, check your ego at the door.
Can't stress this enough.
I know so many extremely talented people.
who are limited and sometimes crippled by their ego.
If you approach a situation to improve it,
check your ego because if you don't,
it will kill any chance at a positive outcome
because it's about you rather than about the end result.
When you do try to go improve something,
people are typically way more willing
to collaborate with you and listen to you
and work with you if you've built up trust over time.
I could give a whole talk about that, so I'm gonna move on.
Don't storm the castle.
So if you storm in telling people how to fix everything
so that you don't get screwed over,
you may not get very far.
Puts people on the defensive, it's not productive.
This leads to listening.
So find out why something is the way it is now.
Understand the situation fully,
and then that's the starting place
for trying to make it better.
And then how can you help?
Figure out how you can help.
A lot of times, things are broken or things can be better
just if people have a little bit of help
or have somebody to collaborate with them,
which leads me to collaborate.
Don't go into a situation with a preconceived solution.
So making games is all about collaboration.
So is solving problems.
Be creative.
So we all are creative in our craft
when we're making games,
but also be creative in how you're approaching problems.
Work hard.
Doesn't always involve putting on a gas mask and gloves
just to get that perfect sound,
but sometimes it does.
I'm not really suggesting that, but.
But be perseverant, roll up your sleeves,
be willing to do the work.
And if you have ideas and that's it,
then you usually don't get very far.
And keep a sense of adventure,
so in games and in life.
So I hope this has given you some small motivation
to lead and affect positive change
from wherever you are in your career or on your team.
Thank you very much.
Hi everybody.
Oh, a little scratchy.
I'm going to grab my water real quick.
Thank you.
It's been a long GDC week for me as well as many others I'm sure.
My name is Sela, I worked at Xbox for a long time,
then I worked at Dropforge Games with Brittany,
and now I'm working at a company called VReal,
working in the VR space as a programmer.
Today I wanted to talk a little bit about saying yes
and saying no to things, because those are challenges
that I've had in my career that it took me a long time
to learn how to do, because it seems so easy, right?
Yes, no, but it's really not.
So the first thing I can suggest to say yes,
to try something new regularly.
Go out there and when opportunities arise,
if you have the time and the chance, say yes.
Don't stay inside, go out and have new experiences.
Get a new perspective on life and try things.
Even if it's just because you wanna have a new story
to tell later the next night.
The best stories kinda come from the best experiences
and it's just a really great way to broaden your horizons.
Some of these things are going to be really scary and I just have to say get over your fears.
Some of it is related to imposter syndrome which I've had a lot in the past.
I've talked about it in the past at GDC.
You are good enough though.
Some of these things aren't because like I don't know I don't want to jump out of a plane
It's not really my thing. I don't want to go with bungee jumping. That's not really imposter syndrome, but it's something that scares me and by
Exploring things that scare me I find that I grow as a person in this case you can also practice a little bit
so
speaking in front of a giant crowd at GDC, hi everybody.
You can go to Toastmasters and you can practice ahead of time
when the stakes aren't quite so high,
so that it's more comfortable and more familiar
when you finally have the opportunity.
There's a saying, give a man a fish and you feed him for a day, teach a man a fish and
you feed him for a lifetime.
And I think that's kind of true across the board.
If you say yes to everything, every single time, you become the go-to person for something,
which is great for a while.
but you also become somebody that is just doing the same thing over and over and over again.
So in order to broaden your horizons and free up your time,
make sure that you teach other people how to do things as well.
So, great, I'm going to have this new opportunity, if it turns out I'm doing it all the time,
I'm going to go and now teach you how to do it so that every time you ask me,
I don't have to bother.
Some of this is because I'm a programmer and I just like to automate things,
but, you know, that's just how it kind of goes.
Also, it's really important to set expectations.
If I want to go and play Overwatch later tonight,
this isn't really acceptable.
I need to have a really low ping,
and I can't draw packets.
Again, programmer, like these kind of things.
So setting expectations is very important as well,
so that when people come to you with things,
they understand your time is valuable,
and that when you are saying yes to something,
that it's worth your time, it's worth their time,
and everything is great.
Otherwise, you'll get a little overloaded.
So there's kind of a little bit of a balance there.
And that's when you have to start to say no,
because if you said yes to too many things,
suddenly you end up in situations that aren't very good.
We like dogs, they're not always allowed.
So my favorite example here is I was out at brunch with some friends recently, and one
of them suggested I go out and do some aerial silks, because aerial silks is something that
she was doing and is very exciting.
So I almost joined the circus, but I really had to think hard about that.
I didn't have the time, and I needed to make the compromise.
Maybe after GDC I'll do it.
I don't know.
But I needed to make sure that...
I can limit everything.
Because saying no is really, really hard,
and sometimes you just have to let people down,
which in a trust fall, maybe you don't want to do.
But 95% of the time, all you're doing
is setting acceptable boundaries
and making sure that other people
can take care of themselves.
I like to think, what's the worst that can happen?
Most of the time, people might get a little bit miffed,
they might get a little bit angry at you,
but the long-term repercussions aren't there.
So, just make sure you don't get flooded,
you wanna make sure that you don't get too overloaded,
and you wanna make sure you understand
why you are saying no to things when you do.
You wanna make sure you own that decision
because you can't let people reverse that
and walk all over you.
You also want to make sure that you know why.
Is it because you don't want to do it?
Is it because you're overloaded?
Is it something you might want to revisit later?
Understanding your own self is just very critical here.
Because time is money, we only have a limited amount
of time in our lives, and we need to use it
to the best of our ability.
You need to learn how to hand things off to other people
and realize that you don't have to do everything yourself
and you can't do everything yourself.
And you can't do everything that everybody asks of you.
You want to say yes to things, but you also want to say no to things.
So I had a couple of exercises here, and we're running a little low on time, so I'm just
going to skip through them.
But what I'd like you to do, if you get a chance, is go grab our slides later, say yes
to things, say no to things, and I'm going to leave this up here for just a second if
anyone wants to take a picture, move on to the next one, and then go.
It's pretty exciting. I'd like to think these are decent exercises and I hope that they can help you all out in the future.
Here's the last one. I'll leave that up while I let... Who's next? Tara.
Thank you very much everybody.
Applause
Hello everybody. My name is Tara J. Brannigan. I'm the head of community and customer service at Flare Games.
I've worked...
There we go.
So brief bio, I've worked at a lot of different companies.
I'm not gonna tell you how old I am,
but you can probably get a picture there.
I started out in QA doing testing at VMC Games
for the original Xbox.
It didn't really pay super well, though, so I moved to this high-end travel company,
working in the tech department, doing kind of web-based QA.
I learned a lot more about the fundamentals of QA in that role.
But in the back of my head, it was always, but it's not games.
I need to go back to games.
It just kind of ate at me.
So when the opportunity came to go to Halo 2 Vista, I jumped on it.
However, that was a contract role.
And I really wanted to be full time.
And I was told that if I wanted to be full time,
there was this awesome program management role
and I should apply for that.
So I said, what the hell?
And I went into production.
I worked on 1 versus 100 in a variety of roles.
I was a tools PM, I was a prototype PM.
If you ever won a prize playing 1 versus 100,
you are welcome.
And I also worked as an art producer on Project Spark for about, I think it was eight months,
but I'll come back to that in just a little bit.
So during 1 versus 100, I was given the opportunity to work in community.
And at that point in time, I had zero interest in it.
It was not something I wanted to do.
I hadn't even considered it.
But I had some bandwidth on the team.
My manager thought I'd be really good at it.
And I understood how it made the whole product better.
So I said, OK, yeah, I'll do it.
But I am going back to production.
I am going to be an art producer someday.
The thing is, I really fell in love with that.
I saw the power of that role.
I got to connect with not just the team,
but the people who played the games,
who really fell in love with what we did.
And I got to bring that back in and share it with everyone.
So that's kind of been the focus of my career
for quite a while.
I've also worked in on a bunch of other things.
I've lived in various countries, the U.S. obviously, New Zealand for about three and
a half years, and most recently Germany.
In short, staying in one company, role, or even country is great for a lot of people,
but I'm not really one of those people.
I like to wander.
So you're getting started in your career.
My first piece of advice is to have a plan.
You want to set objectives and hold yourself accountable.
Getting from point A to point B is a little hard
if you don't have any idea of where you're going.
And if you're anything like me,
you want to have other people hold you accountable too.
Sometimes having that little outside force that says,
hey, you said you were going to get into public speaking.
Here's this great event.
Why don't you apply for it?
Makes a huge difference.
But you also want to be open to change.
Opportunity rarely presents itself at the right time,
because there's not really such a thing as the right time.
I didn't want to go into community.
It wasn't on my agenda.
But this opportunity for me to learn something new
about the industry that I loved popped up.
And if I hadn't taken that, if I hadn't said yes,
I wouldn't have found my passion in the industry.
So other people are going to have opinions on what's best for you and your career.
And it's good to remember that this comes from a good place.
Like your friends, your family, your managers, they all have a clear image of who you are.
But that's from their own perspective.
So they're going to give you advice that's based on their view of you.
But no one cares about your career as much as you do.
And that is a really terrifying thing
to realize, that somebody isn't going to plot your career out
for you.
That is dependent on you.
People might give you nudges, and it's
great to get advice from people.
But at the end of the day, you're
the one that lives with those decisions.
So I said I was going to come back to Project Spark.
The first leap is absolutely the hardest.
So in my early 20s, I would have killed somebody
to get that job.
I was going to be an art producer on a AAA title.
I wanted it so bad.
But older 20s didn't actually want that anymore.
And it was scary.
And I had people telling me, particularly back then,
community was not a very well-respected role.
And I was told that it was almost career suicide
to go from this role with that credit
into just community management.
So I had to dwell on that for a long time.
And it kind of came down to, if I don't do this,
I am going to regret it.
And I got an opportunity to go PopCap Games, and oh my god.
That has made all of the difference.
I will say that it gets easier.
Taking charge once makes it a lot easier to do so again in the future.
That's not to say it's easy.
Every big jump I've ever made has given me that anxiety and stress and, oh my God, am
I doing the right thing?
But you have to think things through.
You have to get advice from other people and move forward.
So a little bit more about that dream versus reality.
Nineteen-year-old Tara was super in love with Weta Workshop.
I've always been a practical effects nerd.
And for me, that was just the epitome, like, oh my God, it's so good.
I have to work there someday.
So 33-year-old Tara last year got an opportunity to work at Weta Workshop.
The thing was, my career had changed quite a lot in that time, and taking that role meant,
one, contract position could be gotten rid of at any point in time.
working on just one project rather than a larger brand
initiative.
And I was no longer a manager.
I wasn't growing in those ways anymore.
And it made me realize that those things were actually
very important to me.
But because I had built up all of these years of, oh my god,
I need to work at Weta Workshop.
This is the best place ever.
And I had told so many other people who told me,
like, oh my god, I'm so happy you're there.
I almost didn't respond to this recruiter.
But thankfully, I have a very kind and loving partner
who reminded me that you always talk to the recruiter,
even if you're not looking, even if it's not the right time.
And I fell in love with the company.
They have the values that align with where I want to go.
It was a place for me to learn to manage people
with a manager that is going to teach me those skills.
So long story short, I worked on an amazing board game,
I met some really cool artists,
I learned a lot about Kickstarter,
and then I said goodbye to that project
and now I live in Germany working at Flair Games.
So in short, don't let the person that you thought that you should be get in the way
of the person that you actually want to be.
It's really easy to get hung up on this view of yourself that you've had for years and
years and all of this investment that other people have put into it.
But again, at the end of the day, you're the one that lives with it.
So trust yourself.
You're the hero of your story.
Don't let player two or three or the mob of the internet tell you what you should be doing
with your life.
Be selective.
Look for workplaces and environments
that are going to help you grow in the ways
that you want to get to.
And remember that there is no one right path.
All experience is valuable, and failure
can lead to amazing growth.
I still use things that I learned in QA,
and in production, and outside of the game industry
in my day-to-day work today.
That is all part of the whole of me at this point.
So in short, keep calm and go on an adventure.
And P.S. learn how to negotiate like right now.
Tara Van Wheeler's got this great piece
called Minute Zero and the Gender Pay Gap.
Highly recommend it.
Don't care what gender you are.
Absolutely check it out.
Great tips.
And that's me.
And I gotta say, if you wanna connect,
connect on Twitter,
cause I'm never not on there.
And on that note,
here's some really awesome other people you can follow.
Hi, it's me again.
And we're a little short on time,
so we're gonna do the lightning version of my talk.
So my talk is Don't Be a Hero,
Team Up for Game Career Victory.
And to help me out today,
I've enlisted the help of Ms. Marvel, a game developer.
So.
Quickly, my backstory.
I've worked at some of these companies,
well, all of these companies.
I worked on these products.
I currently work for this company that I formed,
and this is my mission statement,
to make games that inspire people
to love themselves and each other.
And my most recent project is The Mirror,
which is a text-based RPG about mirrors and body image.
So real quick, what's a team up?
So your career is not a solo journey.
We're all the star of our own stories,
but sometimes we make guest appearances.
So team ups are the parts that we play
in each other's stories.
Sometimes they join our show,
and sometimes we're the guest star.
But usually, they're fun, powerful,
and mutually beneficial.
So what's a game industry team up?
In the context of the game industry,
team ups go beyond just the teams
and the companies that you work with.
These are the deeper relationships
that you purposely build during your career journey.
They're the heroes that you admire
and the mentors that you work with.
They're the industry peers who become confidants
and sounding boards, resources, and friends.
They're also the aspiring game makers
that you take under your wing and mentor.
So why team up?
Three reasons.
To develop your personal superpowers
to get better at your job, to be more effective now
to make better games, and then also
to create new opportunities in the future.
All of this can be summed up in make better games.
Let's start with developing your personal superpowers
by teaming up with mentors and heroes.
You won't usually have direct access to your industry heroes,
but you can follow them on social media.
Following them on Twitter is a great start.
Learning from their feed and what they talk about
and post and retweet, this keeps you informed.
It leaves you an opening for potential meaningful interaction.
And then with mentors, mentors won't usually come looking for you.
They have to be found and persuaded.
And you have to show yourself worth the time investment
by actually taking the advice that they give you
and setting goals together, doing what they advise you to do.
Mentors can help you set boundaries for work-life balance.
They can help you navigate who you are
versus who you want to become professionally.
And they can help you take the initiative to get there.
They can push you to accomplish more than you would
on your own.
Okay, so let's talk about peer team ups.
So if you get one thing out of this talk,
I want it to be that investing in your peer relationships
will have the biggest impact on your career
and your body of work.
So,
That's my first point.
Choose to invest in the people that you work with now
and choose to work with the people
that you're already invested in.
Trust is key.
Making better games, I think Mary and Tara,
a couple people touched on this already.
Trust helps you make your games faster and better.
Feeling like other people are invested in you
fosters trust on your team,
and then you're able to work more efficiently,
uncover problems faster.
Nobody's hiding that they're in trouble.
or that they're behind.
And then as you finish games and career paths diverge,
that trust remains.
And it's not just about efficiency
and making great products.
These peer team ups will also be important support
for you during your career.
You can't do your best work without a support network.
These people and these relationships will cheer for your triumphs.
They'll pull you through a world-ending layoff or studio closure.
They'll let you vent when you really need to blow off steam.
They'll help you figure out how to fix it when you fuck up.
They'll encourage you to take care of yourself when you're burning out.
And they'll remind you that you're awesome.
And if you're lucky, these team-ups can lead to not just industry partners, but also some
of your best friends.
So let's go back to that thing about trust.
So as your paths diverge, that trust remains.
This is how team ups create new opportunities,
that third point.
So new opportunities come from past team ups.
At senior levels, most of your new gigs
will happen this way.
And this isn't nepotism, it's risk management.
It's good hiring practice.
Senior developers are expensive,
and a bad hire can torpedo an entire team.
So the best case hiring scenario is when someone comes in
that another person trusts that says,
I would definitely work with this person again.
So this might be how you break into the AAA space
and join your dream team.
Or it could be how you all quit your jobs,
you and your peers, to launch your own thing.
The bottom line is that teaming up, investing in people,
And leaving behind teammates who trust you
is always to your benefit.
So in conclusion, create epic team ups in your career
to develop your superpowers, make better games,
and create future opportunities for greatness.
Thank you.
So we have five minutes for questions, which is awesome.
Somehow.
Oh, please come to the mics.
Hi, my question is for Tara.
I've met somebody who's been trying to get into community management.
I have some background in social media, but every time I've sent in an application, they've
told me that, sorry, you're not who we're looking for, and we're moving on.
Is there any advice you could give or what kind of skills employers are looking for in
regards to finding community management?
I think my best advice is to start with actually managing
communities, even if they are personal, fan base.
Being able to show that you have not only worked with people
directly, but helped foster a positive community,
even if it's one you're not getting paid for,
is huge, because nothing beats that actual experience
of having to tell someone else, you are out of line.
This is the reason you're getting booted.
Being able to talk through the perspectives of kind of the passion behind community management
and the foundations of how to get there goes a really long way.
I will always hire somebody who is very passionate and knows a little bit about the role versus
somebody who's been doing it for 10 years and is jaded as hell.
Thank you.
Are there any other questions?
Come on, people.
Yay, come on.
Hi, many of y'all spoke about obtaining a mentor.
How would you go about doing that,
other than following on social media?
Is there another way, a better way, I guess?
So the question is, how do you find a mentor?
Ask.
Find someone that, at this conference,
that you respect and ask them.
And one of the things that I have really started doing
is always saying yes, because asking is very, very hard.
Know that mentorship means something different
to everybody.
I have a mentor in South Africa,
and we just email once every four months.
I have mentors that are much more high maintenance,
and I have to have dinner with them once every month.
But figure out what that relationship is for you,
figure out what you want out of it, and then just ask.
It never hurts to ask, and if they are too busy,
they can usually refer you to someone.
I just want to echo really quickly what Brittany said.
Ask someone here at GDC.
I've been asked at GDC before, and I have also said yes.
And everybody who's been doing this a while
wants to help everybody out.
So everybody, ask for mentors.
It's great.
We all want to pay it forward.
Thank you.
So first, less of a question and more of a compliment
on having an all-woman panel for this.
I think that's fantastic.
And I think that should be applauded.
Second, this is my question,
what if you don't think there are any mentors?
Like, I know part of that is humility,
but part of that could also be
there's things you wanna do that no one is exactly doing,
or the path you've taken doesn't seem to fit
into anyone else's narrative.
I totally relate to that.
And I think one thing you can do is pull out,
like set objectives for types of mentorships.
So you don't need the total package,
you know what I mean?
So what is it specifically that you're trying to learn?
Maybe you have a bunch at that point.
So you find people who you respect for different qualities
that you wanna embrace or improve,
and go after those,
and it just becomes piecemeal at that point.
So you take a different approach
than trying to find somebody who really lines up
with all of your goals.
Thank you.
Hi.
I don't have a voice either.
This one's a little bit different on the mentor subject.
What if you have a mentor who isn't quite living up
to your expectations as the mentee?
Ooh.
Break up, dump them.
Yeah, break up with them.
Yeah.
I guess first, make sure your expectations are clear
and that there's no miscommunication
about what the relationship was supposed to be.
But it's a...
at-will partnership.
There's no reason you can't just say
this isn't working out anymore,
or have more than one mentor at a time.
I've done that before.
Yeah, highly recommend getting more than one mentor.
Everyone has different experiences,
and you're going to learn from everything.
Thanks.
Hey, Brittany.
You brought up mentorship, so I guess I'll ask you,
but this applies to everyone.
At what point did all of you figure that you might be able to be mentors as opposed to just looking for them?
Was there a threshold there where you made a decision or did someone approach you and then that was the first time you thought about it?
So the question was, at what point did you realize that you became a mentor?
It happened really organically.
Like when Kim put this talk together and it's like industry veterans, I'm like, I'm still
a baby.
What are you talking about?
Like it feels really weird to be a mentor when I have so many mentors myself.
Like I still have so much to learn.
But like I have three new mentees this year at GDC and it's been amazing.
So just know that someone looks up to you,
and someone finds your opinion valuable.
Don't say, I want to be a mentor.
Just let it happen.
And I feel like that's the best way to build a relationship.
Awesome.
My question is, I believe, for Lauren.
You said that there was a pretty big gap
between what academia is interested in doing
versus what the market wants out.
of academia, have you had any thoughts on better connecting those goals, either one
side or the other?
Well, I love both sides and I've always tried to make it a point to stay in touch with both
because I think both have a lot to offer each other.
I just think that industry is really focused on being profitable and making sure that you
Because it takes so long and so much money to make a big game, even a small game.
So you have to...
And software development is already really, really risky.
So to add in, like, hey, I found this really awesome paper that we could incorporate this
into our dialogue system.
It's like, is there any precedent for this?
No.
I don't know.
And then at that point, it's like, do they trust you as a designer to do this?
Yeah, I think that there's a lot that they can do to cross pollinate each other.
Industry can maybe help refine academia's focus, deadline issue thing sometimes.
And then academia obviously can introduce really cool, interesting new ideas to the
industry.
So I definitely think they need each other.
Unfortunately, we are out of time.
We have to get started for the next session.
There is a wrap-up room on the other side of West Hall, so if you guys would like to
keep the conversation going and maybe build some of those mentorships, go right ahead
over there.
Thank you for your support.
Thank you all for coming and seeing us as well.