Everybody surviving GDC so far?
That's about how I feel.
The post-party day talks are always the interesting talks.
First a couple of housekeeping reminders.
Please remind attendees to fill out the session evaluation email they received from surveys.it and international.com after each session they attend.
Also, if we want to just continue this afterwards,
there is a wrap-up room afterwards,
although this, I believe, is the last audio session.
This is the wrap-up room.
Headlining.
Yeah, definitely.
Obviously, turn your phones to vibrate.
It's always embarrassing when an audio person
has their phone ring in a talk and whatnot.
I'm very excited.
I was asked to moderate this panel set up
by some of the folks at Smule.
And we kind of were trying to figure out what really made sense in terms of interactivity
and the kinds of stuff that goes on.
And we ended up with this notion of where does the game end and the instrument begin, right?
There's a whole lot of interesting things that, you know, device, you know, massive amounts
of compute power, you know, from historical standpoint right here can give you as well
as the kind of cool things that are, you know, happen whether it's Morpheus or HoloLens or.
Magic Leap or Connect or all of these sorts of other kinds of things or plastic guitars.
And so it really essentially has opened up a whole big genre of categories of...
I don't even know what to call them.
You know, Mew applications or something like that.
Cool ways to make music and have compute power really help you do it.
So I would like...
We have an incredible set of expertise on the panel in terms of this goes.
Matt Bosch, John Moldover.
Nick and David.
And I'd like you to go down and introduce yourselves
and just say a little bit about who you are
and what you've been working on.
Yeah, my name's Matt Bach.
I work at Harmonix Music Systems.
I got my start working in rock band hardware,
designing drums and guitars and making sure that they worked,
and then worked on all the rock band pro stuff.
And then from there, I started prototyping for Dance Central.
I worked on all three of the Dance Central games, and most recently I creative-directed Fantasia Music Evolved,
a collaboration between Harmonix and Disney Interactive.
It's a reimagining of the classic 1940s film Fantasia.
I'm David Young, I'm at Smule. I am on our content team, which is the team responsible for all of the music or really any other content that comes out in all of our different music apps.
I currently handle all of our pre-production, scheduling, licensing, which is a whole fun thing if you want to ask me about.
And all of that for our music releases, and before that I was a content producer for Smule for over a year.
There are a lot of variables to consider when you're making effects in a web application.
I love those instead, but that's okay.
Yeah, so I work at Ubisoft San Francisco.
Ubisoft San Francisco is a newer studio.
It's actually right down the street,
3rd and Brandon, but we're mostly known for Rocksmith.
And as far as my involvement with Rocksmith...
I was working on it from the beginning, before it actually even was at Ubisoft.
So I was one of the original people working on it, designed a lot of the game along with
Paul Cross and now Hiko, the producer on the project.
Three of us kind of built up the studio from there.
Amazing experience coming out with Rocksmith 1 and then Rocksmith 2014, the most recent
one.
And that's what I'm still currently doing.
Rocksmith is still alive and we're releasing DLC 3-5 songs every week.
Yeah, we'll get into more of that later.
Hi, John Mulliver from Smule, senior programmer over there.
And we're neighbors with this guy, so we're in town.
And hello to you guys in the front on the left.
You can feel free to come forward.
Let's see, so I work on Magic Piano at Smule.
I do a lot of that and sing karaoke.
And before that, I've been at a bunch of game studios around the Bay Area.
I worked on DJ Hero for Activision for a bit.
And nowadays I'm working on music videos at Smule, which is kind of cool.
And, yeah, that's good for now.
So how have people who have been working directly on technology that...
You know, sort of empowers people to learn music or make music in ways that we don't think, you know.
Normally music is you take piano lessons and you, or you study the violin or you, you know, do marching band or whatever.
But it seems like devices and some of the early Smule and current Smule products are very, you know,
let's make it easy for somebody to get up and sound something cool.
So how, what kind of, you know, thought or empowerment goes into making these kinds of things such they, they're...
cool instrument musically, but at the same time, not just something where it does so
much of the work for you that you're really just kind of pressing a bunch of presets.
I think whatever application you're using, whatever input devices, whether you're just
touching the iPad or whether you have a controller or an actual instrument or even just your
voice, whatever your input device is.
The point of it, like you said, is to get somebody participating with the music as quickly as possible.
At least coming from learning guitar, this is like a classic problem with guitar.
You go out, you buy a guitar, for some reason you're inspired, maybe you're in college or something,
and you bring it home, and you have a really hard time making the chords,
and you don't know what you're doing, and you go and look at tablature, and that doesn't...
help you. It's harder to read it. And maybe you do know exactly what you're supposed to
do with Tablature and you take the time to put into it, but you're really disconnected
from the goal. And the goal is just like, I want to play along with a Bon Jovi song
right now. I don't want to wait months and months and months.
And sure enough, you pour months and months and months into the guitar, and you're still not really getting to what you want.
Like, as far as our goal, and I believe that this was the same for you guys,
it's about what is the least amount of effort that I need to be instantly be able to play with the music and connect to the music,
because that's what I want to do.
And then once you get that, you've actually inspired somebody, you're motivating them,
and then you can take them to do whatever else you wanted.
So, I'm going to go ahead and pick it up.
I agree mostly. I think our battle is on that front end where
you wanted to make it super easy for somebody, but, and you mentioned in your original question
is, do you make it...
it's so easy that you're like oh I'm just pressing buttons, or I'm interfacing it exactly when it's telling me to interface
and then at that point I'm just, I have a set of commands and I have to follow them
I'm thinking about more about following the commands than I'm actually expressing
the idea of music and the expressivity, which was a...
You guys' presentation yesterday kind of touched on a little bit which was cool
and so, yeah that's like, with Magic Piano and John can talk more about that but its like
the, you know, as the little fireflies drop down, they'll wait for the player and, you
know, there's the ebb and flow of actually having some control over tempo and dynamics
and stuff of that nature.
Yeah, I think we found, like Nick said, like getting there quickly is super critical. For
the majority of our users, at least, who are not like, I want to learn guitar, they're
like, you know,
mobile app users, maybe gamers, music lovers, it does not take very much for them to feel,
like get some ownership over it. It really was enough for them just to be like, oh I
can change this. Like I have some amount of control. Yeah it's not intimidating at all.
Right, right. Definitely don't want to intimidate them for sure. But it, it didn't, it doesn't
take a whole lot to give them that, that feeling. Um, of course like, um, exactly how you do
that, um, is actually.
you know, a lot of work, the presentation, and like teaching people what seems like it should be
super simple interface, like tapping a glowing thing on the screen.
Actually, it doesn't always elicit that from everyone.
That's probably the bigger challenge, I think, actually, is how do you like educate people
like from nothing, with as little friction as possible.
Spent a lot of time on that, actually.
In Fantasia we're building a lot of new gestural instruments
kind of based on some vague concepts of things like chaos paths, the like,
looking at accessible tools that people already use for these types of purposes.
And one of the things that we found that really helps people understand that
they've put in some arbitrary gestures that's super duper accessible,
they're just moving their body.
But the thing that changes that from just being some arbitrary movement
to making them feel like they have some authorship
is really just sort of abusing repetition.
We will record the thing that you do and just keep playing it back to you.
And you hear something once or twice in a row,
you start to recognize what its melodic contours are,
and then you start to feel a little bit of ownership of it.
And so we really used the joy of repetition
to give people a sense of ownership and authorship
over the thing that they were doing.
And that's cool, too.
I think all of our applications are going to a point where
You want to do the thing where you're getting somebody participating right away, right?
Because you want them to connect with the music and have fun.
And it's especially important for Rocksmith because these are people who have probably given up guitar once before, right?
I mean, a lot of our user base were people who had guitars in their closet and they just couldn't connect to it before.
But after you get them actually playing, connecting, and playing their favorite songs and relating to it somehow,
you want to go that other step. You want to say, you're not just repeating music that's coming at you,
you're feeling like the notes you're playing are your own. You're feeling agency over what you're doing,
and you actually are putting in more. You're starting to actually make your own stuff.
Like a decision we made early on with the first Rocksmith is we don't, like, knock your...
They're giving you places to start putting in more and start putting in more of you into
it.
And in fact, a lot of your apps where you're actually sharing things and sending them back
and forth between friends, it's implied, right?
You're supposed to be doing that.
It's like, I've sent this to you.
I didn't just copy someone else's homework and send it to you.
I actually sang on this thing.
It's me.
It's my voice.
I put in my own little, like, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah,
ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah,
Now it's your turn to do something with it.
That stuff is implied and actually makes the experience so much better.
Well, and it also goes to the fact that music, yes, it can be a personal, secluded thing if you want it to be,
but in the grand history of humanity and culture, music is a very collective experience that you want to share
and interact with people even across cultural and language boundaries.
That's a big reason why we push that share stuff besides the fact that you have more engagement.
And it's totally an important thing to get to that point because I definitely remember when I started playing music,
it was not about playing with other people. It was about hair in my face, in my bedroom, lights off.
Not playing in front of anybody, like I definitely had stage fright and didn't really want to communicate with anybody.
Branching through that as a musician is really, really important because that's the point, right?
Like you said, it is a social event. You're supposed to be playing with people.
You think that's one of the reasons that some of the social music games, like rock bands specifically,
there was a phenomenon where all of a sudden there were lots of soccer mom rock band groups.
And I think back a little bit to, you know, if you watch Amadeus, what do people do at parties?
They play piano and sing, or play harpsichord and sing.
So do you think this, you know, talking about the sort of solo experience versus the group experience,
is that something that's made much easier with the devices we have now?
Or is that, is it almost sort of, in the way Facebook is sort of isolating it,
are we going the other way on that a little bit?
Right, is being social, making music, doing something on your own and sharing it?
Or is it more of a...
collaborative thing in art. Do you see that being reflected in products or the way things
would go in the future in terms of digital music making, digital personal music making?
Right out the gate I guess I'll say that our mission statement is connecting people through
music. So we are completely on that. So yes. Yes and yes. Absolutely. I'll let you guys
I think in general there's something that has kind of like a little bit happened with
our society where we don't connect with music as well as we maybe used to.
Like you said, like, oh, people used to have fancy parties where they got around and played
piano and everyone sang, right?
Like, nowadays, or at least especially when I was growing up,
like, I was really insecure about singing and didn't, like, openly do it.
And, like, there wasn't, there wasn't, like, a lot of musically coming together
and things besides, like, the required, like, singing classes
in, like, elementary school or something like that.
Um, I think in general, like, for some reason, we've kind of, like,
branched away from that.
Not necessarily with just singing or playing instruments,
but even, like, connecting over music in general.
Like, um...
Like, America used to be the central location for swing dancing.
You know, like, that's a way of connecting with music.
Like literally, you're dancing on the beat, right?
We used to be the hub for that.
Now we're not.
Sweden is.
All the other countries across the world have been like,
swing dancing's so great.
You guys came up with this.
It's like, yes, we don't do it anymore.
I mean, we do, which is in a very, very niche group
of what it used to be.
So I really like seeing types of mediums and types
of applications that actually connect people back together
musically like this.
Oh, go ahead.
I think rock band is certainly a communal experience.
I think to a degree that the fear of singing in front of people
is part of the reason why rock band is a great product and a great experience, right?
You get one person doing karaoke and three other people also get to participate
in what rock band is without having to take the risk of singing.
I think that's certainly a big part of it.
As we've continued to build all of our games, multiplayer is a thing that we
kind of insist on having and we want to create shared musical experiences in your living room.
And people do a lot of sharing of their sort of skilled performances in rock band or the like on YouTube.
I tend not to think about that necessarily as musical sharing so much as proficiency sharing,
kind of bragging to a degree.
But with Fantasia, because every single performance that you're doing is generative in some way,
we have opened up YouTube sharing for that.
And you do hear very, very different interpretations of all these different songs.
People feel a bit of ownership over them,
kind of looking at the YouTube comments and responding to each one.
And I think they're connecting with people
through the kind of unique spin that they've taken on a given song
and spreading that out across the Internet.
It's possible for them to do that in their own living room
with their own friend as well.
And all of the sort of different compositional elements in Fantasia
we've also built for multiplayer.
So you can do it in a sort of trading force kind of way
where you're creating half the phrase
and the person creates the other half of the phrase.
And those moments, we always see people look together,
smile after they've done that,
and then go back to playing the song
because they built something together.
And, you know, the best feeling, I think,
like of ever being in a band is just...
The drummer starts, bass player comes in, guitar player comes in, and someone starts singing.
And when you're a part of that, it just feels amazing.
Even if your band is absolutely terrible, even if the drummer's not playing in time at all,
that sort of feeling of all coming together towards the same ends is just ineffable.
It's amazing.
I was about to say that's exactly like...
You know, all of us up here are musically inclined,
so we've all played music with a lot of people,
but there's a moment where...
Everyone in the band looks at each other.
It's like, that moment that just happened, and is happening right now.
That, like, we all just clicked.
It was the most awesome music thing that we all just innately did together.
It was this crazy, connective thing.
And good luck recording that moment, too.
Yeah, I know.
It was definitely awkward, or, yeah.
I sort of think of those bursts of SoundCloud comments as the internet doing this, right?
Like, the producer is, and has everyone kind of looking at them at this moment,
because, you know...
They've picked out some particular part of the song that they like,
and you see a million comments pop up at the same time.
You know, if it's a dubstep song, that's definitively where the drop is.
But in other types of music, it tends to be where interesting quality changes have happened.
And I think you get that almost same feeling of eye contact, of validation.
And you kind of are getting to do it in a larger and larger group, which is kind of amazing.
That's a funny thing. I haven't thought about looking at dubstep songs on SoundCloud and being like,
there's just one location where all of the comments are going to be.
For sure.
Oh, the beat dropped here.
There's some analytics here, for sure.
Yeah, right. Back to Brian's original point, I wanted to say, in the simulator,
like, the Magic Piano app, I think, is a more solitary experience.
But I don't think it's, like, further, I don't know, isolating people.
I think that there's those people that want to play in their bedroom and they just want to get into a song and do it in a, you know, personal way and just get something out.
But yeah, I think that phone app technology can indeed be like putting people in their own virtual world and taking them away from the moment.
We've all experienced that. There's probably some of you out there checking your Facebook right now, and that's cool.
I was doing that during the talks earlier.
and that's cool.
It's alright, if you want to do it, that's fine, I guess.
And you could levy that criticism on our apps,
but I thought the interesting thing about Sing, actually,
and like these guys were saying,
the coolest musical social experience, I think,
is being with people in the same space,
that shared moment, is the magicalness of it.
So, what can you do with mobile?
What can you do with an app?
Well, there's some other spaces you can still be social with in a different way.
And I think with the sing karaoke,
we get people to sing who like maybe aren't quite outgoing enough
to actually go to a karaoke bar or they don't have time to.
They don't want to get in front of a room with other people, strangers they don't know,
but they really like singing those songs
and they'll sing them when they're comfortable in their own room
and then they'll share that recording.
And so...
In the bathroom where they sound good.
Yeah, you gotta get the, you know, gotta get it dialed.
You gotta get the side reflections of the bathroom, that's ideal.
Yeah, but they'll share it and, you know, I listen to these people singing the songs a lot.
And they're terrible sometimes, or average,
because that's what people are.
But they really just enjoy the music.
And it is a genuine social connection.
And they'll share them, and their girlfriend or whatever
will sing the duet part.
And it's pretty cool.
It's really exciting to me to see just ordinary people
making music, doing their own thing,
not worrying about, am I as good as my favorite musician?
No, it's not about that.
We're just making music.
So before Brian hits us up with another question and departs us from this, you said something about recording, which was really interesting.
Or you were talking about that moment when you're all playing together and you look and you're like, yeah, this is the moment.
And then I said something actually about recording.
If you try to record that moment, it's gone.
If you guys are musicians and you've ever jammed with people,
you'll know this thing where you try to record your jams,
because you're like,
they're so brilliant, we come up with the coolest stuff.
When you put down a tape recorder or anything,
it's nothing. You've got no ideas.
It's only garbage.
And you will never capture that moment.
And I think it's really interesting.
We had this same kind of thing with...
It's just kind of capturing these moments in general.
And like, when you are impromptu just doing something with someone else
and you don't have a lot of expectation, you don't think about it that much,
those are when those moments happen.
It's almost like they happen outside of the recording.
It has nothing to do with it.
It's the fact that it is just like a spontaneously kind of combined thing
that makes those magic moments actually come to the front
and makes you actually experience them.
Yeah, recording.
And recording in general is just more of like a solitary experience.
Like to a degree. I mean, okay, so I've been playing guitar for like 17 years, 18 years at this point.
But I also took a long detour into electronic music.
And that is solitary recording experience.
That is like, I am up all night because I had like a triple shot latte.
And it's four in the morning and I'm tweaking knobs on this synth for way too long.
Like, I really like...
The idea of this doing it on the fly, of even the stuff that happened with the later games
where you could just drop in in the middle of playing, like, oh, I want to play with
my friends, just add them now.
It's that really informalness makes these moments kind of happen instead of pushing
it to a more structured experience like recording would be.
I think it is nice that recording does enable folks who might have a lot of performance
anxiety to be able to do their performance on their own terms, in their own time.
and then share that with the rest of the world.
And I think that's a really nice aspect of app-based karaoke, right?
There's so much about the karaoke experience that is just in being you,
being the person singing that song.
But, you know, if you are paralyzed with fear at the point in time
when you have to sing in front of other people,
it's not really a thing you can do anymore, certainly.
I think there's plenty of singers out there who kick everyone else out of the studio when
it's time to do their vocal takes.
It's a thing where you want to be alone with yourself.
But it's nice that those alone moments can be shared and that you don't have to have
a microphone set up and preamps and whatever else.
You're just giving people that.
It's a thing that I'm sure we've all done, recorded and shared music, but enabling other
people to do that is amazing.
We saw a really interesting, I guess...
representation of this when our, so we have a sing,
sing is our karaoke app and karaoke can kind
of be a bad word and a divisive word.
And so, you know, we're trying to do everything
we can in the app to make it not the
side of karaoke that people hate, which is the
drunk person in a bar slaughtering a song and
everyone like wincing and listening to it.
These are the times I like karaoke.
It has its moments, but I don't know if I need to sit down and hear that as a musician.
But we didn't have video up until October, and once the video switch happened, you don't have to perform on video.
The entire element of, well, at least I can still hide behind my, you know, my profile image and just record this.
Now it's like, oh, now you're going to see me in my bedroom, like, performing, and it's messy, and I...
A lot of people, like, do their makeup and do their hair and get everything ready, and...
Just the interesting seeing the ways that people got more engaged because they're on video and then the other people that got less engaged and just stuck to still doing audio only because they were intimidated by being on video.
It's different personality types. Some people like to perform more and like that aspect and are artists in that realm and will put a lot more energy in there.
Whereas other people are just more of that don't like performing but still like music so you get the like in the closet recording musicians like myself.
You know, the people who say, like, okay, the rest of the band, I'm kicking you out of the studio.
Or, I'm recording my vocal tracks at home to get this done.
Yeah, different personality types interfacing with music in different ways.
And the cool thing that I see in our apps is that we have inroads for all of those different types.
So there is, like, an inroad for the person who wants to record by themselves.
While there is also a way for everyone to just play together and not worry about recording and stuff like that.
More roads.
There's a way in which just proposing that this thing is a game
takes the stakes down.
Like if you're telling someone, OK, you
need to perform a musical phrase, write some music, versus, hey,
just like, we're playing this game.
It's all cool.
Don't worry about it.
There's a way in which it just gives you an excuse to be expressive.
And that kind of framing of that musical experience, I think,
just makes the whole thing less intimidating simply
by framing it in a different way for the player.
Also, too, when you say it's a game, people don't mind being told what to do at first.
You know, whereas if you're doing an artistic endeavor of whatever sort, like, I don't know
if you, how many of you took a lot of art in high school, but it seems like even the
people in high school are like, oh, you should be drawing this.
This is our project.
Oh, no, I want to draw that.
I want to draw this other thing.
You know, it's like suddenly, oh, this is who I'm supposed to be, so I'm going to do
whatever I want.
Gamers are very used to saying, hold X to run.
Okay, thanks for telling me that. I'll hold X to run.
This doesn't have anything to do about me being artistic.
I just need to know the tools.
Which is ironically what they were trying to teach you in art class in the first place.
You mentioned making an artistic expression.
Is that the ultimate goal of your products?
Is there a continuum between artistic expression and have a really good time?
Or is that just play around with stuff?
Different personalities, different goals.
Or is this something you're, is one of the challenges sort of trying to morph people
somewhere along that continuum and have them start as fun and before they know it they're
doing something kind of artistic?
So something that we definitely did with the, with Rocksmith 2014, with the second Rocksmith,
is that we didn't try to assume where people wanted to go or what they wanted to do.
or how they wanted to learn, or what they should be, or anything.
We opened it up so that...
and we made the UI very much kind of follow this flow,
where if you just want to learn a song, let's say you're a guitar player,
or you want to learn how to play guitar, you just want to learn a song.
Great. Let's say you want to go do lessons first.
You can do that first.
Let's say you don't even care about any of that,
you just want to play mini-games.
We let you go wherever.
And then the system adapted around that to say, okay, they chose this song, they're doing
this, they're doing this, this means that they kind of want these things, they kind
of want to go this direction, let me start teaching them this way, let me start suggesting
things to them this way and tell them about other places in the game that they can go.
To answer your question, it's like different personality types are after different things,
right?
And it's like the...
I guess the person who would just want to get every note correct and play it with exactly the right tone and exactly the right way and reproduce this thing as accurately as possible would be in our terms somewhere along the lines of the completest, right?
Where in a normal game they would be the person who's like, I beat every mission, I beat every side mission, everything is perfect, I've done everything I possibly can.
Whereas there are other people who will play a song, maybe not learn all of it, like maybe
kind of improvise or screw around on top of it, maybe afterwards turn off the game and
like take that little bit and turn it to a song of their own.
Different goals for different people.
And we didn't really, with Rocksmith 2014 we left it open so we didn't make any assumptions
about who you were and what you wanted to do.
We let you kind of go with it and guided you along the way to your goals.
The mission statement of Harmonix is to offer non-musicians the experience of making music.
I think over the continuum of the various Harmonix products,
we started with a joystick-based jazz freestyle product called The Axe.
It was really, really early on in Harmonix days.
And then from there, we really focused on performance simulation.
I think Fantasia was the moment when we got back to the aspect of sharing the process of making music.
with a broad population.
That certainly has been, I think, an overarching goal, an overarching agenda for the entirety
of the company.
We think we were hugely successful with things like Rock Band of sharing the feeling of performing
music but it's a quite different thing to share the feeling of ownership and pride that
you might get when you have done a particular unique thing that only you could have done.
And so certainly as we're going through the process of building Fantasia.
We're trying to figure out what types of interactions would net sufficient complexity such that the outcomes would be unique every single time.
There are millions upon millions of outcomes.
It was really hard to paint outside of the lines.
Essentially, what we did is take a lot of what we understand,
the rules that bind western music,
make the system know those rules,
and not ever let people do things that are outside of those rules.
So we do allow people to make this sort of artistic expression.
It's certainly a thing that we think is core to that game,
core to the promise of that game.
But we lower the stakes by making it very difficult.
and it's not impossible to make what sounds like a mistake, what is traditionally a mistake.
Make it hard for them to sound bad.
Put any of yourself into this and we're going to make it sound good to some degree.
That is something that I feel music games are going in the direction of
and can do more and more and more of.
Because right now you see there's a lot, especially on your phone,
if you download a lot of music making apps for the phone,
there's very few of them that are actually geared towards games.
and make music and have fun?
There are a couple, don't let me say that there's not.
But you'll very quickly run into the area where you're like,
whoa, I downloaded a DAW, a digital audio workstation,
like Pro Tools or Logic basically is on my phone.
All the buttons are super small.
Okay, I've gone over the deep end.
That's why I like stuff.
I was talking to David before this about Smule's rap app,
where you just record your voice saying anything,
and then it takes a little bit of processing time
and then turns it into a rap.
And they have a video online.
where I don't know the guy's name, but he was doing a
Beavis and Butthead Cornholio and just like reporter just reciting Cornholio almost like Shakespearean, you know
And then it just turned it into a rap and I'm like, oh, that's great
It's doing a lot of stuff you put in whatever input whatever piece of yourself
Right that you want to put in doesn't have to be Beavis and Butthead can be whatever
And then it takes that and actually turns it into a song afterwards.
And you can see all of the...
You can start to hear all of the intelligent, like,
oh, yeah, we're grabbing this.
That's clearly the same as that.
We're going to make a phrase out of this.
They don't know what we did, but we made a song out of it.
You know, like that type of,
you can't screw this up ways of making music is great
because I feel like there's a lot of...
In general, I mean, we've faced a lot of this with Rocksmith, but there's a lot of intimidation
to playing an instrument or making a song.
If you just put a guitar in somebody's hands and say, play your own song immediately, and
they've never played before, like, that's it.
They're never going to play guitar again.
You have to approach it very carefully.
I think there are lessons that are coming from not only from games,
but also from DAW and hardware manufacturers and the like.
You look at things like Ableton Push
or the most recent set of complete keyboards.
A lot of these features are just to get rid of any of those exact same types of mistakes.
You sort of set your push grid to exactly the scale that you want.
Now you're dealing with what kind of was a piano,
but now is a subset of the keys that you would want to play.
It's a thing that's useful for people that are musicians and could ignore those notes,
but they know they aren't going to need them because their song is in one key, it's hanging out there.
I think those types of accessible interfaces are happening both on the instrument manufacturing side.
and from the game side.
There's interesting places where they meet in the middle.
I think we've seen a lot of cool products,
things like Cosmic DJs, a game I really love.
It's a game where you sequence little things
and they'll build a song for you.
Fract has these similar types of creative elements.
And I think seeing music technology move in that direction
as music games move in that direction,
it seems like there's a really generative
and interesting space forming in between those two things.
It's not something I...
We have anything that solves that in any way, but I worry a little bit that going too far in this direction eliminates the possibility for a casual music person that's using any one of our products to experience music either for the first time or on the side, and that's not their main thing.
The happy accidents that happen when you don't have those restrictions.
Sitting down at a piano and accidentally plunking that wrong note, but then being like,
wow, hold on, that was actually really cool if I just like change this thing.
And all of a sudden you're in this totally new area and it was all because of a happy accident.
I think a lot of great moments in music happen out of happy accidents.
It's too different.
Yeah, you're right.
We've, uh...
Back to your initial question, like, that continuum, we're on the continuum, we start
at having a good time, we need to make sure everyone's there, and that seems to be kind
of like the bottom line, literally the bottom line.
And then where does it get to?
Artistic expression?
Well, we've kind of capped it by making sure everything sounds good and there's happy accidents
don't happen.
So we've, like, limited that universe of what you can do.
artistic is a pretty strong word. I don't think we ever use that, right?
It's kind of scary. I regretted saying it when I said it.
No, it's good though. I appreciate it. But yeah, it is...
I think you're absolutely right and that's a problem.
Are there people who are like losing?
yeah I can take negative feedback. I don't need my stuff to always sound good.
You know? I can deal. Like are we just losing all those people?
Some people can take negative feedback, some people can't take negative feedback very well.
There's kind of two philosophies on this. This isn't just in music,
and I'm so glad I have a segue to talk about this, but like,
there's a lot of suggestive media out there now, right? Or suggesting media.
Like Netflix, like your Facebook timeline.
like Hulu, there's plenty of other things that suggest to you what you want.
And the more and more stuff you go in that direction,
and the more and more stuff you buy,
the more and more radicalized you end up getting.
And it really kind of narrows your focus on the world.
So this is kind of like becomes a problem because like I think a general philosophy is you want to be a well-rounded person.
The more ways you have to enjoy life, the more of a well-rounded person you are,
the more chances are that you're going to enjoy life or enjoy the thing that you're doing.
Destiny just gave a talk where they were talking about this and I'm obsessed with the game, sorry.
But they were talking about this and they talked about their goal.
They were doing all of this data mining on their users,
and their goal was to make people well-rounded players.
Because then if one of their venues kind of dropped off,
if it's like, oh, my friend stopped playing,
now they don't stop playing.
They have so many other ways of doing this, right?
And it's kind of like the same thing with music.
In this talk of like, where do you let the happy accident happen?
and where do you guide the person to the happy accident, right?
I think in general, music has been, like music and music games have been a little bit behind
the curve of getting there.
I think like, I don't know, I think we have a little bit more of a way to go until we
get to the Facebook newsfeed point where it's like, wow, we have radicalized people to an
insane degree.
They don't know what notes sound like out of the major scale.
We need to just throw in some Locrian.
We need to just shake them up, you know?
I don't think we're there yet, although I am totally behind what you're saying.
Why do we need to do that? Why do we need to shake them up?
What if they're happy just listening to major chords?
Oh sure, and most people will be, and that's totally fine.
But in general, like, and you know, that was the complaint people had with Destiny.
I don't want to play as a titan, I'm a warlock.
I'm like, why did you give me a titan helmet, damn it?
In general, I really have a philosophy that it's a goal to be a more well-rounded person, just in general.
It will give you more of a way to enjoy life, enjoy music, right?
Like something that I did when I was in music school.
If I found a genre of music I didn't like, I'd just put it on and listen to it and try to figure it out.
I really wasn't into reggae when I was in high school, just really not.
It took me a long time to figure out how to get into reggae.
I wouldn't say it's my favorite thing, but the thing is I understand now.
I feel like, especially with music in general, it's so polarizing.
Metal fans are metal fans. Blues fans are blues fans.
There's things to enjoy on both sides, and the merging of that only makes your users more robust to the stuff you have to offer them in the first place.
What is better in us projecting musical experiences and giving people interfaces?
blitz, and I don't like, I can't do that wrong, I don't even know that wrong node exists because
I don't know that that's a scale. Uh, versus people who, oh no, I want to know all of the
dark secrets of music, and like I want all 12 node, no I want, you know, there's the,
there's the.
There's different kinds of people.
You can have these three notes right now.
Later on, we'll give you some more notes.
It's like the Oreo experiment.
DLC. You can pay for those extra notes in the scale.
The piano as an instrument has internalized just as much of Western music logic as anything else.
Like, we're saying, oh, here's all this open possibility, right?
But there's plenty of frequencies that exist in between the notes and the piano.
A piano dictates to you what kind of music you're going to make,
like any sort of app or any sort of thing we're designing.
And I think, far be it for me, personally,
to be able to say what the bounds of artistic expression are and...
to suggest that some particular type of musical complexity
makes for more valid or more well-rounded work.
From my perspective, I love a lot of weird and strange novel genres of music
that exist, sort of gamelan, but there's contemporary music like, say, Jersey Club.
Electronic classical noise music.
Built contemporary.
For 12 minutes, and you're like...
In a 15.4 setup, yeah.
Right, in a 15.4.
There was a performance space down here a while ago that was so awesome, so awesome,
but it was the most niche thing ever.
I forget, I think it was, I forget the name of the studio,
but it was a performance space for really, really specific artists,
and it was this room about this size, and there were projectors all along the side,
so it was like a full 360 view, and it was, yeah, 15.4.
a
radios turned up and he was just mixing five different radios and it has nothing to do
with what we're talking about.
John Stuart Mills, the founder of utilitarianism, was a really interesting thinker.
And at some point in time in his life, he decided he was going to commit suicide.
And the reason he wanted to commit suicide was because he'd done some math.
He looked at the notes that existed that we could hear,
and the bounds that he thought music had,
the types of instruments that could be played, etc., etc.
And he realized that there was a mathematical formula he could build
that would create all the music that would ever exist.
And he was like, it's not worth it, I'm getting out of here.
And I think what he misses is that music is bigger than that, right?
We certainly have the option to have all sorts of timbre,
we have vocal performances,
we have a lot of opportunities for specific...
or for specificity that exist outside of musical complexity.
And I think when, you know, you read a lot of the things of like,
oh, music is narrowing and all music sounds the same now,
and you can see New York Times articles about this like maybe once a year.
I think we don't give enough attention to what timbre means, and what sampling means,
and what calling back to previous types of music means.
I think there's no way we can ever run out of musical possibility, and I think that
The same notion that underpins the idea that we could run out of musical possibility
is the same kind of strange notion of saying,
oh, we need to give people this much space to express themselves.
One cannot run out of musical possibility within their lifetime.
So, quick thing on that is that,
all right, let's look at where music is heading in the,
that's a loaded topic, absolutely, but...
It, tambour is a huge, huge part of that.
To the point that, we've talked a lot so far on this panel about just pitch.
But if we're talking about guiding users and allowing experience back and forth, I think
tambour and especially in like the upping of the limit of people's, you know, the general
public's acceptance of like harsh sounds, and then you get into the whole semantics
of what do you describe.
as and all that stuff. But, how do we incorporate the idea of musical expression through
timbre more than just simplistic pitch and rhythmic constructs?
We got, does everybody know what timbre is? Yes? This seems, it's a,a small audience who
really knows what they're talking about as far as music goes, so we're not going to
explain timbre. But, um, yeah no it's, it's the difference between uh, uh, uh, something
It's the difference between one style of music and another, like all of the different timbres of instruments.
A lot of the times the notes are the same, the rhythms are the same, the content is the same.
You can even have the production be the same, but the overall sounds of what the instruments are making
connect to people in different ways to an incredibly polarizing point, which is silly.
Because it's a harmonic spectrum that you're not even identifying notes in.
That was something where there was this visceral connection between a human gesture and the
timbre that comes out of it.
So in a sense it would seem like you have the ability, sitting here in your chairs at
work, to sort of have influence on these things.
Is that something you directly think about?
Or are you more heavily pitch-focused in figuring out how to make happy mistakes, because most
musical mistakes are very unhappy mistakes?
I'll say we've been very much pitch-centric with all of our recent stuff, and I can't really talk to the future of stuff, but I don't know. John?
Yeah, yeah, it's interesting to put it in those terms, but we are very pitch-centric. I mean, we... I've been pushing for the drums app for a while, man. I want the DJ Drums Producer app, but it's not coming this year.
But yes, I think Timbers is not quite, I don't know, it's not in the consciousness yet in that way, you know, for better or for worse.
It is to the degree of like, I mean, the instrument that you're...
like you have an interest for example.
Like it like in session mode in Rocksmith you get to choose between the
different guitars and some of them actually share riffs, some of them are
literally playing the same thing. So the difference between, not all of them, we have a ton of riffs
but, the difference between one instrument and another instrument could
just literally be the tone that we put on the chain, basically the amp that they're going through.
But that's enough to make you go, yeah, that's my metal guitar.
That's the one I'm playing with.
That's what I relate to.
I just wanted to say I absolutely
love the Ocarina app.
I remember the first iPhone that I got,
I don't know if it came out on the original
or how early it came out.
I don't exactly remember.
I was playing with it for so long, for hours, and I flipped over to the other view and realized
that there was the world and I could listen to other people and immediately got freaked
out that someone could have been listening to my horrible, horrible, happy accidents.
But it was also another moment of being really like, that was when I saw like, oh man, this is such a cool thing.
I'm actually like connected to all these other people.
I can listen to this random girl in Japan play the Zelda theme perfectly.
Which drove me crazy because I couldn't do it.
But I, I, just that was like a moment of seeing like, wow, this is where, this is where music is going.
Like actually being able to connect with people again in this way.
Yeah.
The Ocarina, by the way, it's like a flute basically.
It is that flute in The Legend of Zelda.
Yeah.
I can't reproduce the sound.
I'm not going to try, but...
So, like, with AutoRap and with, say, like,
effects loadouts that you're doing in Rocksmith,
I think there's an aspect that you are,
to which you're taking genre conventions
and kind of formalizing them
and then letting people sort of reflect those back at them.
How much do you, like, put into trying to understand
the kinds of guitar sounds that you want to have
and how those are sort of related to genre?
And how much does sort of genre convention impact
the kind of stuff that Shmuel's making?
So, uh, at least at Rocksmith we have a guy, Brendan West, who is like the gear...
He's got any band that you bring up with him, he knows what piece of gear they used, how
they used it, how they wired it together.
And that's super important for Rocksmith because we have all the individual pieces of it, right?
And we call them authentic tones.
We call them authentic cones because we do an incredible amount of research to make sure
that what you're putting in there, whether it's licensed gear or something that, you
know, it represents gear that they used.
is as accurate as possible. So we know like, oh, this distortion pedal literally did come before that wah, literally did do this, and like we actually look at video evidence and stuff, so it's very important. We don't really make any assumptions like, metal guitarists use this, or, you know, these type of classic rock guitarists use these. We go to the source and say, this is how it was. They were using this amp. And like for the licensed gear that we do have in game, we hook them up with those. You know, it's like they were using that 1969 Marshall with the
with a slanted cab in this configuration with the microphone position like that.
It's, that is a great question because in AutoRap we had something where
the app was very like the project managers were very protective.
Like no it's only gonna be hip hop and like R&B and content and stuff that is very
you can quantize rap to really easily and then there's a hook that you
that auto tunes to in the choruses.
And then just recently we started flipping it. We put all about that bass in auto-rap.
We have country tunes in auto-rap. And taking stuff that never had rapping associated with
it in any way and allowing the algorithm that's exactly the same to chop up someone's vocals
and now that Florida Georgia Line song is totally a rap song.
and we didn't change anything to the structure of the song except for adding the vocal element.
And it was super cool to see that and they've actually been super popular,
though it's impossible to gauge really is that just because
All About That Bass was the number one song for three months.
Yeah, enough.
In general, music allows you a lot of awesome
oh my god WTF moments, right?
Like, one of my favorite bands a couple years ago,
it's not a band, it's a guy, Girl Talk.
And he just, he went and using Ableton, Ableton Live, the empowering a generation to make a style of music that would have never existed otherwise,
hacked up all of these songs and just put them together and blended all between them and made incredibly intelligent, like, quick blends between stuff.
And if you ever listen to it, it's like an album, like, it's like an hour and a half of just straight nothing but constant, like...
only the hits dance music that is just blending to it. So it's mashup stuff.
But like, yeah, I mean, it's an hour and a half and then you're like, done.
But having those, being able to combine things in hilarious or like ways that you wouldn't have expected is like a huge part about music.
Like that's why with Rocksmith with session mode.
It's a mode where you get to play with an AI band.
You can hook it up however you want and play with it, and they actually listen and adapt to you.
This is the short of it.
But you have 76 instruments to kind of choose between and hook them up however you want.
So it's like, yeah, we organized them into genres that were, again, genres we derived from the gear that we know that people use.
But at the same time, you can put the metal guitar with the upright bass and the...
and the world percussion drums and then with a click if you want to play with a click for
some reason or with a kazoo or with wind you know like you can combine this however you
want and then set it in harmonic minor and make the weirdest most epic kind of emo thing
possible and it's it's hilarious like giving people the ability to do that it's like it's
another way of connecting to music I mean you guys know the the hilarity of the musician
joke right?
that the average person doesn't get.
The punchline is,
and then he was using the Pentatonic minor.
It's like, oh my God.
To get back to that question,
David, could you answer maybe
how much does the genre drive...
Probably at least you could tell about the content releases, right?
We must think about that a lot.
It's kind of crazy to think about...
It's popular. Is pop actually the most popular genre?
Because like when you have 20 million active users at any one time,
thinking about what the whole broad spectrum of them are going to be interested in
and the niches and applying to them and all that is tough.
And so, yes, you have to get the pop, the hot 100 content and all that,
and the stuff that resonates with the pop culture and is even number one in Brazil.
But, you know, we're putting in, we're coordinating with the Icelandic Rock and Roll Hall of Fame
and putting in this really awesome flamboyant Paul Oscar.
You know, we're putting his music in because you have, when you have such a niche thing,
like you were talking about that awesome 18.10 system that created noise music.
You know, if that was...
Everyone that was there, I'm guessing, was super into it.
No one was like, eh, yeah, like, I guess.
Only in San Francisco, but something like that exists.
So, like, the people that are going to go sing that Icelandic music,
even though the country only has 300,000 people,
like, they're going to be so into it.
And that's, like, that's awesome.
Cool. One last final thing before we take a few questions.
I'm just having a fun time listening to this.
Um, you know, obviously, you know,
Technology has changed music making fundamentally, you know, probably since people were banging bones together from
when the piano forte was inventioned and you could suddenly play both soft piano and loud forte.
Or the engineers said, well, Mr. Guitar Player, you can plug it into this app,
but just don't turn the volume past about 8 because then you won't get an accurate representation of your guitar sound
and it will distort, which of course is bad.
Technology has changed fundamentally the kind of music that is made.
How do you see, just sort of in a quick wrap-up thought, what you are doing
as fundamentally changing the nature of humanity through music?
I think there's a lot of pieces of music technology that have created genres, right?
I think we wouldn't have what we think of as contemporary electronic music without the
TV-303 and the 808, right?
These are things that have enabled particular types of expression.
And I think, you know, if there's like a lofty aim that I could possibly have for a thing
that I would build, you know, it's a thing that is expressive within a limited set of
means that can, you know, sort of...
be generative of its own type of genre work.
Because I think genre is a powerful way of limiting a palette
and allowing someone to sort of identify with the thing that they've made
as part of that genre.
And I think that's sort of a big part of what we're doing.
We're playing around with remixing Fantasia.
But a thing that, from a long-term perspective,
I sort of aspire to be able to create.
kind of an environment that has its own sound and its own feel that is generative of a particular
type of genre of music.
For us, we view music as the original social network, which is kind of a buzz phrase, but
I think it encapsulates what we're going to try and do going forward.
And that is completely...
to take this community that has kind of built itself and that we've nursed along of people
that are all casual or closet singers that are all collaborating together and 700 people
sing a group duet of happy and all the stuff that's happening without us even pushing it.
We're going to keep massaging and pushing that further and pushing this collaborative
environment to a point where people don't need to worry so much about sounding bad because
you have a positive community behind them and just the idea that music
can be good, it can be bad, but it can be expressive no matter what it is in there, and it can
be incredibly personal and incredibly connecting to a huge number of people across cultural
boundaries, across a whole bunch of different boundaries, and I think going towards the
future, yes, it's more about connecting all those people amongst all the different instruments
and the different personalities and everything, and using music as a conduit for that.
I got three points.
Let me see if I remember them all when going through this, because I thought of it while
you started speaking.
Now that might be gone.
Uh, first one is...
I just screwed myself, I knew it a second ago.
First thing is the, I think we're actually coming up to,
like I feel like we're behind where music used to be.
And this is maybe just an idea I just started thinking about now
when you were talking about like, oh, you know,
people used to get around the piano and play songs and sing together.
I really feel like what we're doing now with the music applications
is kind of getting people back together,
connecting people back to music again,
which is something that is actually, I feel in a lot of ways,
actually departed from our culture.
and we're not departed but definitely gone to an individual basis instead of kind of connecting as a community.
So in one way I see that that's where we're going, but that's just to get us back to ground zero, which is nice.
Second thing is that, second and third thing at the same time, I feel that new instruments or new ways of connecting with music are...
new windows into creating music. This is why a lot of musicians, and I'm sure you guys
know, you maybe started with guitar or you started with piano, but then there was some
point where you were like, I want to learn how to play drums, I want to learn how to
play bass, I want to learn how to play this. This natural incantation came out and you
started to play with those other instruments and it made you play different. It made you
play different things. You thought up different ideas. You started making music in a different
way. That's incredibly important. So all of these new things that we come up with, whether
it's controlling it on an iPad or.
a controller or DJ thing or maybe just even clicking around with a mouse and a DAW.
All those different ways are actually influencing how music sounds.
Like you were talking about with the 808 or with Live or things like that.
The last thing I'm going to say is where we, all of us, are actually pushing music technology,
specifically in the field of games.
pushing this music technology gives the kind of like, gives the pro audio user more technology
to make things, to make different tools and different things that actually didn't exist
before to get to kind of experiences that are new, right? Like a lot of the, a lot of
the tech that I know you've made with going through and actually analyzing the raps and
stuff like that or the stuff we've done with session mode.
in the way you're going to make a product.
And then when you're done making that product,
you're like, huh, we had to make a lot of tools to get here.
And you can actually wire them together this way.
And it's like a way of growing on where you're at
to actually make more tools to then go to the second point
to make music in a different way and actually bring it further.
This probably overlaps a lot with those guys, but definitely filling in the gaps between traditional instruments and what Nick was describing as a solitary EDM producer in his bedroom.
Hopefully, you know, a lot more different ways for people to make music at different levels of commitment from the like, I just want to tap.
the phone in time, versus like, I actually am going to dedicate years of my life to learning
an instrument, right? There's a huge range of people in between there, the guys who have
given up on guitar twice. So we can make tools for those people and let them keep making
music instead of like, have you ever had that conversation? Like, oh, I really wish I still
played guitar. Like, oh, we got you, bro.
Here, use this, you know.
We're making that kind of stuff to fill in the gaps.
And hopefully it'll be at all ranges,
from the amateur up to the professional,
and making those tools a little more usable
so you don't have to dig through a synthesizer manual
to learn, what the hell does this one knob do,
and why can't I hear any differences?
Actually, we don't really need to show you that,
so we're not going to.
Also, I think Adult Contemporary is
going to make a big comeback.
Brian?
Build contemporary to make a big comeback.
Gotta write that one down.
I think we've got time for a question or two.
Anybody's got something, then we're gonna have to wrap up or go to the wrap-up room.
Hi there. First of all, I just want to say...
Hmm? Finger?
No, sorry, I was communicating with the background.
First of all, I just want to say thank you to everybody
because I started off doing music with these rhythm games.
I started off with music games. That's my bread and butter.
That's what I just love to do.
If it weren't for those, if it weren't for Amplitude
or Rocksmith or Rockband or Sing or Guitar
or anybody else just keeping up this genre of game
that seems to be dying, I think.
I mean, I just want to thank you guys so much
because this is just such a big part of my life.
The question, like, since I'm such a big part of the community, of the music game community, I know that a huge part of it is of the fan bases to have like original, like user-created content.
Whether it's like creating your own songs and implementing them in the game, which is a little bit rare.
or if you just like take MP3s off of the internet and just like throw them into TapTap or Vendor something.
Because I know that that's such a huge part of just like the grassroots community,
but in my conversations that I've had with developers, it seems like it's difficult to acknowledge that that's even happening.
Because like you can't just say, hey, look at this cool dude who took a thrift shop MP3 and just put it in our game,
because then you get, because then you're condoning piracy,
and then you have a whole bunch of copyright issues to deal with because...
You're not licensing their music.
So my question is, do you really see this user-generated content as more of a boon to the game or more like a hindrance?
And is there a way to promote this user-generated content without overstepping copyright boundaries?
That's a super good question. It lends itself to a whole panel discussion.
We have enough time for quick answers, and then we need to take it up into the hallway.
I'll absolutely talk to you outside of this, except to say that we can't say much except
you're absolutely right, and you may be happy in the future.
I don't know what any of his questions mean.
I'm going to say that you don't ask the easiest questions on a panel.
We tried really hard to absorb that energy with Rockband Network in the height of the
Rockband days, let people off of their own content, offer it up for sale.
It's a thing we knew was happening and we wanted to have happen and we ideally in the
future will continue to support.
We love the community's input.
It makes Rocksmith so much, so much better to have a really strong community and we've
actually been fortunate to have people who care so much.
And we like that community input and we like having people actually help each other and do that.
Great. It was great to hear. Thank you.
So yeah, I'd like to thank Matt, John, Nick, and David. Thanks for spending your time here.
And I think this is the end of the GDC audio track for 2015.