Welcome to GDC Showcase. I'm Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra. I'm joined
today by a very special guest for today's AMA session, Gavin Moore, creative director on the
new Demon's Souls for PlayStation 5. I see people have already started putting in questions,
and if you haven't, go ahead now, start submitting your questions via the question tab in the chat
box there in the bottom right. We'll try to get through as many as we can.
And with that, Gavin, thanks for joining us, and please introduce yourself.
Hi, Chris. Thank you so much for having me here today.
It's great to be with you all the way from Tokyo in Japan.
It's a little early here in the morning, 7.15, so excuse me if I'm just going to drink all my coffee here.
When remaking and remastering a game, how do you decide which bugs from the original to keep or
fixed or fixed based on modernizing it, player expectations or other reasons? Is that...?
Yeah, thanks Jay for that really difficult question, you know, that early in the morning
to start off with. That's a really, really, really, really difficult process. There are a lot of bugs
that actually become meta in a game, right? And
It took a long time.
Demon's Souls took three years to make,
and I can tell everybody out there,
nearly every day we had those discussions.
We went through that list and we ticked them for,
yes, it's going to be fixed,
or no, it's not going to be fixed
because the community want to keep that sort of bug.
So we look at a lot of background online
to see what people are talking about
and what they're into and what they're not into.
It's a very, very difficult decision.
I mean, there's no real yes and no answer.
It's not black and white.
It's something we investigate.
Yeah, that is a great question.
Like for being seven in the morning, that's really good.
We're going to go to Steven real quick.
How did your role as the creative director
change in a good or bad way over the course of the Demon's Souls
remake project?
So when I was asked to come on board with the project right at the beginning by the executive producer, Asakura-san,
I spent many sleepless nights, I can assure you.
This is a PlayStation gem.
It's a PlayStation classic.
It's beloved by so many people across the world.
And to take on that responsibility is not taken on lightly.
So I would spend sleepless nights worrying, first of all, what Miyazaki-san would say.
And then I would spend the next month not sleeping, worrying about what the fans would say.
And then eventually you just have to, you know, hitch up your trousers and get to work basically,
and believe in what you're doing and believe in the passion. So over the course of the game,
I think my trepidation was overtaken by my passion for what the game is,
because it's such a spectacular game. And so...
I wouldn't say that I wasn't passionate at the beginning,
but the more I delved into it, the more
I became passionate as a creative director
to make sure this was the best experience
for a whole new generation of gamers.
Thanks for that.
We're going to go on to another one from Emilius.
Any advice you have for an up and coming designer with dreams
to become a creative director?
So it took me.
20 years to get to where I am now and I've been in this position for 10 and it doesn't get any
easier and the one thing you have to keep is your passion and your drive and if you can't get out
and out of your bed in the morning because it's raining too hard or it's too cold to go and work
on that game that you love then you shouldn't be working on that game so keep the passion.
The other thing I would say is good advice to anybody out there is that
it when you start a game
You start off with a core experience that you build upon.
And over the course of making the game,
how many ever years that may be,
things change and the game evolves
and it takes on a life of its own.
So don't be afraid to keep re-evaluating what that core is,
because you might've put a feature into that game,
which you thought at the beginning was great
and was working, but a year or so down the line,
it might actually be hindering what the game could become.
So always examine what you're doing
and...
be brave enough to cut something out of the game
as much as you want to add to it.
You take one from Alexis.
How do you think one is able to maintain
the soul of a game in a remake?
That's a great question.
So when we look at doing a remake or remaster,
we've gone well beyond remasters now.
They really are true remakes.
We try and identify, as Alexis said, the core,
the soul of the game, and that is what we keep.
You know, working with Bluepoint was incredible,
working with Marco and Peter, the chief technical officer,
and how they work and how they sit their engine
over the top of the existing engine
and strip away everything apart from what we identify
as that core or the soul,
which for Demon's Souls is the AI and the gameplay.
And then we build everything back on top of that.
So the collision, the camera, you know, obviously the graphical elements,
the sound is built over the top.
So even in Demon's Souls on PlayStation five, you're still running the core
programming essence of the original on the PlayStation three.
It's very cool.
We'll take one from Chris that's getting some upvotes here.
When creating a game as difficult as Demon's Souls,
how do you balance difficult gameplay
with intuitive mechanics and usability in general,
making game hardcore but engaging and fun
to keep enough users playing?
Is that something you could speak to?
Yeah, at 7.30 in the morning.
Yeah.
It's not as difficult as people may say.
I think a lot of the frustration
with the original game of Demon's Souls
and how people thought it was too hardcore
came around because the actual system it was running on
wasn't capable of running it properly.
And the frustration of the load times and dying
and then waiting two minutes for it to load,
to run back and die again.
I mean, it just made you pull your hair out,
as you can see.
I played the game back in 2009.
So...
Um, so keeping the original core of the game as we, as I just talked about
maintains its essence.
So you're not changing that in any way.
So you're going to keep that heart core feeling.
Um, but we have to think our games change over time and how games evolve and how
gamers change and expectations of what a triple a title, you know, have changed
in 10, 12 years.
So it was important that we.
made those decisions very carefully about what we would add and what we wouldn't add,
how accessible the game should be. You know, obviously making a game on the PlayStation 5
with new features, you know, super fast SSD, you know, the new controller with the haptics feedback,
this was always going to change the game. We had to be very careful how we were going to implement
those, you know, user experiences without changing the original.
Melissa asks, what kind of challenges have you faced
while working in Japan on games as a foreign developer?
I don't experience anything,
any challenges in the sense of being a foreigner here.
Japanese people are very open in the workplace
and in society to everyone.
I think the challenges are the way
the working practices here are different from in the West.
It's very common for a team, any team member in the West,
to speak up and speak their mind.
It's not so common in a Japanese development team,
but it is something that,
you know, in Japan Studio that we worked on very heavily
to make sure that everyone has a say in the development of the game
and to say it's OK to speak up and to speak your mind and to be creative.
I mean, everybody that works in games is very creative.
And if we're not listening to them,
then we're losing precious results.
Tremaine asks, hey Tremaine, seeing you around this week.
Can you walk us through a typical day
of being a creative director, such as any pressures,
responsibilities, enjoyment, et cetera?
The 7 a.m. AMA is, live AMA is probably one of them.
Yeah, one of those.
I usually get up around half past four
I just scan my phone for all of the emails and the messages and stuff.
Get to work, you know, start work around, you know, half six or seven.
Games are a global experience now.
So I would have calls in America, both in central time in Texas and obviously
in the West Coast in California throughout the day.
Then I would get online.
Obviously, this is all work from home for a year because of, you know, 2020 and COVID.
So.
I would get online and talk to my team, go through every aspect,
and then even I'll get online with Europe.
So I could be doing everything from playing the game,
writing up notes to different members of staff,
chatting with the art director in Texas about the way
I can't see how the game plays down this corridor,
or this character doesn't look correct,
or it could be talking to a composer, or, you know.
in California or, you know, going in into the, you know, music recordings in London or, you know,
being in the voice recordings in London, directing actors or, you know, everything,
every aspect of the game has to be covered in the general day. And everybody is just
as important as everybody else. You know, it's a massive team effort.
That sounds like a lot of work.
It's a lot of fun too.
Yeah.
Valerie asks, with Demon's Souls, you got to develop a Souls game.
How different is it to direct a Souls game from any other game?
What are the main challenges with Demon's Souls?
I think Demon's Souls challenges that it has legacy, it's history.
You know, it's the first of its kind.
It's a game that spawned a whole new genre of gaming, you know,
and there are incredible expectations.
and you have to be very, very careful in what you're doing.
As a genre of game, I think the basic rules
of how a game plays and the user experience
are generally the same, regardless of any game
that you're playing.
You can apply the same rules.
It's just the Demon's Souls with the Demon's Souls title,
you have to be respectful of its legacy.
Samuel asks, the Demon's Souls remake was built only for the PlayStation 5.
Was the decision to target the newest hardware made early on?
So we started off the development on the PC, like all of our titles do. We work heavily on the PC
and then as we get dev kits we continue that pipeline.
The Bluepoint engine is incredible, the way that you can adjust something on the PC
and it will adjust it straight onto whichever platform you're working on
or whatever you can see on your screen.
But yeah, originally we started off on the PC
and then as we started to get specs through for the PlayStation 5,
we started to think about all the different features that we could adjust and add.
But it has always been a PlayStation 5 game
and a PlayStation 5 exclusive.
Gia asks, and I apologize if I'm mispronouncing names,
what is your team's process to identify the soul of a game
that you were talking about earlier when remaking a game?
What's the process?
So that's a lot of discussion.
I think with a game like Demon's Souls,
it was always going to be, it had to be its AI.
It had to be the way that the characters moved.
and the timing of attacks, none of that could change.
And so we spent a lot of time maintaining that.
I mean, we remotion captured
the whole player animation sets
and we added a whole new female animation set
that never existed in the original game,
but all the cadence had to remain the same.
And that was weeks and weeks of motion capture
to make sure that we were getting exactly what we needed
so we wouldn't change that soul.
So I think it was quite easy on Demon's Souls to identify that essence,
you know, the actual core gameplay.
It was much harder, I think, to make sure that we maintained the feeling of the game,
the despair that the world brings across.
You know, we were adding a lot more visual assets into the game
because we had a lot more power than the PlayStation 3.
You know, the PlayStation 5 is incredibly powerful.
And we wanted to showcase that world as best we could,
especially with visuals and sound.
But we had to maintain that feeling of despair
that Miyazaki put into the original game.
Harris asks, as creative director,
how do you balance leading your teams to achieve your vision
with giving them the agency and support
to come up with their own ideas?
It's a lot easier on Demon's Souls to do that because everybody has groundwork to work on.
So everybody knows, you know, a base to work on.
If you're making an original title, it's a process where I would lay down what I believe.
And this would be, that could be a story, that could be game ideas or game mechanics,
level ideas and level designs.
And then I would usually split the teams across each of those levels.
So you would have animators, you know, environment artists, character artists, game designers, you know,
working on each level together as a team. And it's up to them at that point to,
if they come up with ideas, to present those ideas. And for us as a team to come to a consensus about it.
But as a creative director, you have to make that final decision yourself.
and it's not personal in any way.
You just have to look at the whole of the game,
you know, in its entirety and make a decision
that that is the correct thing for the game.
Thanks.
Chris asks, what are some of your favorite memories
of remaking this game?
So as a game, I think some of my favorite memories
are just watching the game evolve and grow.
That's always great on any game that you work on.
You know, to look back where you came from and look at where you
you know, you are at the end is incredible.
Most of my favorite memories are just the great times with, you know,
all the different teams around the world.
And, you know, there's a great, great people that work
both in Sony and at Bluepoint and a lot of fun times together with those people.
Nicole asks, how did designing next gen haptics for the PS5 controller change the game?
So that was one of the hardest things you had to do. I mean, if you're making an original title,
you can make original game mechanics that would literally use the haptics in different and,
you know, novel and exciting ways. We wanted to use the haptics,
um, but we didn't.
exactly know how we were going to do it and it wasn't until we actually got the the controller
in our hands and felt how the haptics would work. Haptics is incredibly different from
the way that just a normal jaw shock would work, just a vibration. It works in you know together
with both sound and visuals all three have to work together so they have to be designed together.
So you can't just add it at the end like we used to do with you know
jaw shock and vibration.
It has to be something from the beginning of the game
that you're thinking about all the time,
because you're always going to add sound and visuals
working in harmony together.
And the only way we could do that in Demon's Souls,
as far as I was concerned,
is to make the combat grittier, right?
And by feeling and sensing the, you know,
the hits and the strikes and the blocks
and the whoosh of Vanguard's axe as it passed,
you know, as you rolled underneath it was.
an incredible sense that I was suddenly, you know,
thrown deeper into the combat.
So it really did enhance the game.
Brian says, hi Gavin,
Bluepoint seems to be one of the studios most dedicated
to high frame rate tech in the business.
Can you speak as to why 60 frames per second
is so important to your studio?
I think 60 frames a second probably is
compared to PC gaming is probably pretty slow at the moment, right?
I know that my son doesn't like anything that drops
below 240 hertz when he's on his PC.
But every time that you increase the frame rate,
you increase the fidelity, you know, you increase the feeling, the emotion.
You feel, you know, that you're pulled into the game more.
You feel like you're a better gamer because the game's giving you more chances.
You're seeing more.
Right? And so it is incredibly important to make sure that any tech that we produce now,
especially on the PlayStation 5, has to run at least at 60 frames a second.
David asks, if you could remake any game you want, what would you remake?
Oh my god.
See, I would have remade Final Fantasy VII, right? Because I just wanted to remake the scene when
Sephiroth kills.
you know, and I was just like, nah, but then they remade it.
So I'm like, OK, they've done that one.
What would I remake?
I'm not sure there are so many great games out there
and so many great gaming experiences that, you know, I would love to revisit
childhood gaming experiences, for instance.
I'm not sure a lot of them would hold up, but in my head,
they were just amazing experiences.
Let's see, who else we got here?
Let's see.
Sorry.
What qualities would you say a creative director
must need to be successful,
apart from the passion that you talked about earlier?
And that's from Emilius.
Oh, there's vision.
You have to listen.
That's incredibly important, right?
You have to listen to the people around you because everybody has an opinion
and everybody around you is creative
and you have to make sure that you're listening to them.
I think there's a famous line in Game of Thrones where Jon Snow is told like,
you know, to be a leader, you have to follow. Right.
I think that's incredibly important.
You have to learn, you know, everybody's job, basically.
not down to the minutia of it, but you have to know what people are going through and what you're ordering them to do.
You know, it's not it's not good enough to go and make that character and go make it like this.
And I want it in a week.
Right. You can't do that.
You have to understand the processes and the workflows and the, you know, how long it takes and what people are doing
and how much of their life they're pouring into your creation.
And therefore, you have to be respectful and treat them with respect.
Tremaine asks, what were some major hurdles, if any,
that the team experienced doing the remake
outside of the pandemic?
Yeah.
Yeah, outside of the pandemic.
I think our major hurdles were always about making sure
that we were being true to the original, right?
You know, we'd learned a lot, Blue Point and, you know,
Japan Studio had learned a lot
remaking Shadow of the Colossus.
And it wasn't until that title was made
that we felt that we could take on Demon's Souls
and do it justice.
And so we knew that we could make a great experience
and we could definitely give you incredibly outstanding
audio and visual and sensory experience
on the PlayStation 5.
but it was always going to be,
are we doing the original justice
and are we always remaining and staying true
to that original vision?
Misha asks, in comparison to the Dark Souls series,
do you feel player progression
is something that needs to be kept?
And she says, I found learning about the progression
in Dark Souls a very useful benchmark.
Yes, probably.
But you have to differentiate the Demon's Souls and Dark Souls are two completely different titles.
You know, the Dark Souls series is a child of Demon's Souls and Demon's Souls is the first of its kind.
And that's not to say there are many design issues and changes that were made in the Dark Souls series.
You know, as the original development team learned more about what they wanted to create and how they felt that game should play.
I think Demon's Souls, though, stands up, you know, even today as a classic.
And I'm just glad we got the chance to remake it and bring it to a whole new generation of gamers out there.
Ibrahim asks, what would you recommend an aspiring game designer from Europe
who wants to work abroad, for example, in Japan?
Learn Japanese.
Right.
Definitely learn Japanese. I've been here 18 years and I'm still terrible, so that will help you immensely.
If you really have the passion, you really want to go to a foreign country, I think the best way to do it is pack your bags and go to the foreign country.
Right, find a means to get there. You know, live your dream, get on that plane, you know, whatever it is, get to that foreign country and then.
you know, really start applying to companies and get your way in.
And it doesn't matter how you get in, get in at any level.
And then, you know, if you have the passion, you'll get to where you want to be,
but it's not going to come to you.
You've got to pick up your boots and get there yourself.
Uh, Tremaine is asking to, for you to remake legend of Dragoon.
Oh yeah.
So yeah, yeah, I would do that one.
Yeah. Let's see. This one just popped up.
OK. Michael asks, how have you balanced creative direction slash vision
with with schedule restraints?
Or, you know, I don't expect to get into like what you were working on
with budget specifically, but those kinds of restraints. Yeah.
Well. I'm not going to talk about budget, but Demon's Souls
is not a cheap game at all.
And it shows I mean, it's a triple A title.
It stands out there on its own.
And we were very lucky to get the backing to do that.
I think schedule wise, you know, you always believe as a creative director,
there's always another six months if you are kind enough to the executives.
And you say, look, it's great, don't you?
You know, and they're like, yeah, but, you know, and we're like,
well, just give me six more months and it'll be even better.
And, you know, with a launch title, you don't get that option.
That's a drop dead deadline. And.
It's my first launch title in 24 years of working at Sony,
and it was a complete honor to make it,
but it was incredibly difficult,
you know, knowing that we had to go into QA and testing
and, you know, pushing and pushing and pushing
to make sure that, you know, the game was ready for that
so we could get the feedback
and then have enough time to implement it.
Always with the thing that, you know, in November.
the hardware is going to launch and we have to be there with it.
Yeah, that's kind of a hard, hard stop there.
Yeah, yeah, it's a hard stop.
Kylie asks, we've got a few more minutes, so get your questions in.
We'll try to get to all of them.
Kylie asks, especially working remotely, how do you keep your team in alignment
and make sure everyone has access to the development resources they need?
Okay, so a year ago, literally a year ago, we packed up everything. Everybody took home their
equipment, set up everything in the house. We tested everything before we left the office to
make sure it would work. So I have literally in my living room, which my family hate, I have a
massive desktop PC, two 4K monitors, obviously my TV.
that I use most of the time, that's why my family hates it,
and a massive PlayStation 5 dev kit
and an assortment of other equipment.
How do you keep them in line?
It's a lot of relying on them as professionals, right?
You know, we don't treat people like children,
that they're professionals and they will do the work
and they'll get on and do it.
They have a passion for what they're doing.
And, you know, you just have to trust in people.
And team structure is very important with that.
It's also very important to make sure
that you're online with them, you're talking to them,
and that you're accessible to them,
whether that's through line, Slack, Zoom, WebEx, whatever
it may be, that they can chat to you if they have a problem
or that they need advice.
Sari asks, how do you as a creative director fight creative blocks?
They put in quotes.
You don't.
There's nothing you can do.
Okay, I have ideas in my head where I've literally stopped working on them for years because I've come up with something in the story for instance that just won't work.
And then suddenly you can be in the shower you can be driving you can be.
you know, cooking, you could be doing something, you just go,
Oh, okay, that's how it's going to work. And that's when suddenly you rush back to
that idea. And you start jotting things down or writing things down. There's no
way to get over a creative block. Right. You know, some people I know, will sit
there and bang their head against the idea forever. And there are some of them
are great, and they can work through it. Me for myself, personally, I just leave
it alone. I'll let it go and work.
a different tangent on the same project or jump into another idea and work on that for a while
until inspiration strikes. Mowing the lawn also helps. Yeah. And any of those normal mundane
daily things where your mind drifts away and you become, you know, you're not involved with it
anymore. It suddenly wants to jump back in and take control again. And that's when those blocks
end up.
disappearing. All right. 10 seconds. Kelly asks,
what qualities do you look for in the members of your team?
Passion, love for what you're doing. Um, they're all skilled.
They all have a lot of experience, um,
and a willingness to learn and are willing to be open and are willing to be
creative.
And that's all the time we have.
That absolutely flew by.
Gavin, thank you so much for getting up in the morning.
I know you're super busy and taking the time to do this.
Thank you to everyone in the audience
for giving us great questions to work with.
Really appreciate it.
Awesome.
Thank you so much, Chris.
And thank you for having me today.
And thank you to everybody out there.
And I hope you enjoyed Demon's Souls.
And I hope we can make new and exciting experiences for you
all there.
And I hope to see you around in the industry.
Take care.