All right, well, welcome.
This is a talk by me, Marty O'Donnell, and my lovely assistant.
Actually, she's not my assistant.
She is a fabulous user research person from Bungie.
And so we're talking about the emotional puppeteer uncovering the musical strings that tie our
hearts to games.
And this came about, even just having this kind of talk came
about because of a talk that I gave last year that had some
musical examples that I will probably share again today.
And Brandy saw the talk, and she came to me as a user
researcher, and she said, hey, wouldn't it be interesting to
know what people's emotional responses are to some of these
pieces of music?
And I'm like, maybe.
I mean.
I already know what it is because I have an intuition about this stuff, and that's why
I get hired and get paid, and I don't want some user research thing somehow stomping
on my intuition.
But we talked about it for a long time, and Brandy had some absolutely spectacularly cool
ideas which we're going to share with you today.
And one of the other things I'm going to say about Brandy...
Which also intrigued me is that she's this absolutely brilliant user research person
that understands numbers and statistics and how to test people.
And no matter what Bill Fulton says, Brandy is able to just determine.
I'm embarrassing her now because she understands statistics.
And even if she doesn't, I can like twist them to meet what I want for my own needs.
So that's good.
But she's also a music major.
She has a degree in music.
And what school did you go to again?
Trinity University, San Antonio, and then the UW.
Oh, excellent.
OK.
And she's one of those very special people.
Like when I was at the conservatory, we had music
majors, and they were in two groups.
There were the musicians and the singers.
And oh, that's me.
But she is a musician and a singer.
So it is possible to combine the two.
Bridge the gap.
All right, so here we go.
We're going to talk about the most important thing.
How many people here are composers or audio people?
Oh, lots.
All right, that's great.
Now, how many people are just?
Producers, game designers, stuff like that.
OK, so there's a few.
Well, all right, you guys are outnumbered.
Because we're trying to convince everybody who is not
a musician or an audio person the importance of audio and
music especially in terms of being able to tell an
emotional story and enhance the emotional journey that we
want our players to go on.
And so this is some tools that we're going to show you today that I think actually confirm
a lot of what we already believe, especially those of us who believe strongly that music
is powerful.
But it's also, I think, some confirmation of that in a way that the producers and the
designers and the engineers especially can see some hard numbers.
So, here we go. When you start thinking about coming up with some great ideas for games,
you have this, like, giant pile of, like, crazy ideas.
And usually you get, you need to put it all together, so there's this magic game development
box that all these ideas get into. And at the end, I think the most important
thing that we want is to have an experience for the player that is this absolutely delicious
experience.
Whatever that is, it's a chocolate fudge something cool.
And what causes players to have this experience that not only
they want to have again, but just makes them feel really
good about themselves?
And I believe that the emotions is the most important thing that sticks with people.
So here's just a little word picture of...
I think they're called word clouds, you told me.
They are called word clouds.
Okay, word clouds.
Of the kinds of things that if we can get the player to feel these emotions...
While they're playing the game and when they think about how they felt after they get done
playing a game, if we can do that, that's an amazingly powerful thing.
And I maintain that music is the single most powerful tool to enhance the emotional journey
of our players.
There's many, many things, many ingredients that go into making our players feel strong
emotions.
But I think as a singular element, music is the most powerful.
And hopefully we'll sort of prove that today.
And of course, you know, music has got a lot of different flavors going on.
So...
You know, the funny thing about this picture is it was originally from something else, obviously.
And we have a little... Brandy has no idea what I'm going to say.
This is what's fun about this, too.
She's very organized. She put this whole deck together.
And then she gives it to me, and I'm like, I'm just going to improvise.
So, it's too bad.
But the original picture was just some guy from a TV show, right?
Yeah, it was. What was that show?
Reaper. Right.
Okay. And I happened to mention that it would be funny if my head was on it.
And we have an internal email alias called Bungie Spam.
And Brandi is new enough to not know the dangers of Bungie Spam.
I didn't know how horrible it would be.
So when I said it would be fun to get one of the guys,
one of the artists, to just stick my head on this picture,
she went to spam, put the picture out, and she just said,
could somebody put Marty's head in this picture?
And as John said, I should have been a little more specific.
So this is the best one.
Certainly the safest.
There were several that came back that would be absolutely inappropriate here, but we had
a good laugh about it.
Okay, so yes, to a certain extent, the composers are the puppeteers of the emotions of people.
I mean, that's what I maintain.
That's what I like to do.
That's what I try to sell people, is what I do.
The problem, of course, is that you can be manipulative, you can do cliché stuff, and
we all have our ideas about how to get out of cliché and how not to manipulate and how
to try to do something that actually enhances the emotions without causing, calling too
much attention to itself.
And so one of the things that I think is interesting about this
This process that I'm going through with Brandy is that when she first came to me about this,
I was a little bit worried.
And some of you know that I have this theory about the goose.
Anybody remember the theory about the goose?
So my theory is that it's important to be nice to the goose.
And the goose is the creature, the living, breathing creature that lays golden eggs.
And the interesting thing about the goose, and people get this wrong.
But, it's not a golden goose. It's just a regular old goose.
But, it happens to lay golden eggs. So, pay attention to the eggs that the goose lays.
Don't be nice to the eggs, because that's not going to get you any more eggs.
Be nice to the goose, because that's what you want.
The goose can be an individual person. Brandy. I have to be nice to Brandy,
because if I stomp on her ideas, then she decides not to share anything with me.
People stomp on my music ideas. I'm like, okay, no music for you.
But, I mean...
And I think in game development, the real important thing is that as a team, teams are
the goose that lays the golden egg.
So the more we can be nice to the teams and the more we can work together, the better
our eggs will end up being.
And so I'm a little bit worried about and suspicious about user research stuff because
numbers are involved.
Numbers are a little bit scary to me because it proves that I might be wrong about something
and I don't want that.
I get that a lot.
And that's just how I feel about it.
I'm sorry.
I'm gonna take a break.
That's okay.
There's always a next time.
And we'll talk much later.
I'm gonna take a look outside.
Bye.
The important thing is to protect the golden goose because you don't want some process
to kill the goose.
So that's why that.
You know, every time I show this picture, I showed it last year too, the whole room
just goes shooom.
But this should imprint in your head, don't kill the goose.
People are complicated, our audience is complicated, the people in our studios that work with us
are complicated, extremely complicated.
Maybe not so complicated.
They're dysfunctional.
But trying to figure out some common way of talking about emotions, especially for
gamers, is not easy.
And that was our first, I think, the first thing we wanted to accomplish.
But the other thing is that...
We want to give the composers some insight into people's emotions, no matter how complex
they are.
Is there some way to distill some language that could apply to specific pieces of music
and actually have it be accurate?
And the reason we want this is we want to be able to have some real tools so we can
go to battle with the suits.
The people who might be questioning what you're trying to do, it's like if you can say, well look, I know this is going to work because my gut tells me it's going to work.
But also look, here's a pile of numbers and here's this nice research stuff that helps confirm it.
But of course, I think that it's important to...
See, now what is this picture?
So apparently that, and Brandy picked this picture out, which is pretty amazing, but
that's, she's the hyena there, and apparently I'm the old guy with the muzzle on her.
But if the tools start to get in the way of the creative process, she is absolutely willing
to be muzzled.
Is that what you meant by this?
Not quite.
Laughter.
It's the, yeah, I don't know, I'm not going to read the notes, but that's the way I look at it.
So there you go.
It's okay. I think I meant that you could muzzle the people who are giving you feedback.
So the users can decide what they're allowed to tell you so that they can't trample you.
But if I need a muzzle, that's okay.
I mean you in the user research sense of view, not you personally.
Fair enough. Fair enough.
Okay, so let's get started with Brandy. I think you have some stuff to show.
Oh, sure.
All right.
Sounds great.
So, let's talk about feelings.
Yeah.
I, I love
them.
Who wants to share?
Sharing time.
Right.
So, the, the first thing we noticed in diving
into this is, of course, that getting people to
share anything about their feelings, or even for them
to recognize that they even have specific feelings, is
challenging.
And what makes it worse is that our, our
group of users are.
Particularly lacking in some maybe emotional recognition there.
And also what we discovered is that music is something that while it has such powerful control
over our emotions, it's also very amorphous. And if it's something we haven't heard before,
we don't have associations to, it's really hard to really pick out or, you know,
kind of get into something solidified.
Whenever you're just listening to this big amorphous thing, even if you close your eyes, it's still hard to really figure it out.
And just so, I'm going to interrupt. Brandy knows I'm going to interrupt. She never knows when it's going to happen.
But this row of emotional people here are some bungee guys that at this moment are actually testing the game.
And it doesn't look like there's a whole lot of emotion going on. I think it's a great picture. Anyway, keep going.
So yeah, so as a quick exercise, I'm going to play a little one minute piece of music,
one of the ones we actually used in the studies that we did.
And just try to start thinking about how it makes you feel and try to see how well you
can kind of latch on to what some of those feelings are.
And close your eyes, because looking at that picture will not help you identify the feelings.
Their mugs are no good.
It's true.
You
Hmm, so yeah, maybe a little mysterious, maybe a little eerie.
It's kind of hard to tell, though.
It sort of goes everywhere.
It's not just one particular sound.
It's this big whole idea.
And what are we going to do with that?
So when I set out to try studying this stuff, we knew we were coming up with a whole bunch
of challenges here, but we wanted to take a stab at it anyways.
So I came to Marty and asked him if he could give me, oh, 10 or 15 music clips that he
thought represented a big, diverse set of emotions, because I really wanted to try to
nail all sorts of things in the spectrum.
And see how much we could learn about it.
And Marty, he's so wonderful.
He gave me a whole stack of 50 clips
that were between 30 seconds and a minute long.
So to narrow them down, I went home,
got a big glass of wine, sat on the couch,
and artfully poured through for hours
just sitting there trying to feel and try to think,
is this one different emotionally than this one?
Actually, I might have meant that.
I think alcohol might be the single most powerful
chemistry.
We can't deliver that with every game, but anyway, there you go.
Oh, man, at the end of those few hours of just going through the pieces over and over and over again,
I was total wreck, emotionally, just going on this fun roller coaster,
and I don't know if it was the wine or the music, but either way, it was slightly traumatic.
But in the end, we came to this set,
and I want to explicitly call out the people who we've used it in their, uh...
The interesting thing about this particular set was like Brandy said, there were probably about 50 pieces that I had actually used for Jason Jones a couple years ago.
One of our lead designers at Bungie, he's actually the founder of Bungie, and we were talking about music and emotions.
I actually wanted to see if he agreed with me.
about like when I listen to this piece, this is the kind of feelings I get, this is the kind of story I have in my head,
and I wanted to see how he responded to it.
So I had already had a lot of music.
And of course he ended up getting tired after about, I don't know, 15 minutes.
It was just too much emotions, too much music.
But I was pretty well confirmed, and I thought it was a good set of music to try to run by somebody.
So I threw it at Brandy and then she came up with this set, which is interesting.
It's, as you can tell, and some of you here, I'm sure, will even recognize some of these pieces.
It's almost none of it is from Halo, except for the last bit, which we'll get to.
But most of it is film scores that I've really enjoyed, that I like, and...
composers for films?
And that ended up being the stuff that, even though we had
a lot of classical music, and some fusion, and some other stuff,
Brandy came up with this, which I think was very evocative,
and a lot of fun to see how it works.
Yeah, and as we heard about this morning, you know, so much of film and game music really
tells a story.
And the interesting thing that I noticed as I was going through all these 50 pieces
trying to find a good diverse set was that one of the things that helped me the most
was to have kind of an intermediate step where I tried to imagine a story that was happening
or try to picture a scene or something that made it a little bit more real for me as to
what it was that I was experiencing when I was listening.
So when we were studying this, that
was actually the very first question we gave people.
When they came to a page, they saw just this text,
and they were asked to listen to a piece of music
and be thinking of what they saw happening here.
Like, what would be going on if this is what you were hearing?
And I'm going to have you guys try that now.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
What was fascinating was that whenever we ran this with a total of 70 people, all 70
were able to come up with really interesting stories for every single piece of music we
put in front of them.
This one is particularly eloquent for our group, but still representative of a lot of
the detail that people could conjure just imagining whenever they're listening to a
piece of music.
And some of them had common themes, you know, sort of post-war type themes came up a lot
for this type of music.
But each one was unique, each one meant something a little bit different to each person, but
it was very fascinating.
Yeah, and this actually shocked me.
Number one, it was, I didn't know the guys at Bungie were this eloquent, number one.
But if I had been asked to say something about a piece of music, I would have said, well,
starts poignant, kind of ends hopeful, and next.
I mean, I'm not very eloquent in terms of the stories, I'm thinking in a completely
different kind of way.
To realize that.
This is how powerful music is to, well I was going to say normal people, to people in general.
I think music is so powerful that they actually have really strong stories that can be evoked
by the music itself.
And that's a really interesting thing to know.
So while we really enjoyed reading all the stories,
there was more that we wanted to learn from this too.
We really would like to nail down a little bit better
exactly what does that mean then for the emotional story.
What is the picture that we can get from people's emotions?
And after we got people sort of into this imaginative
kind of creative mindset, for some reason they didn't seem
to balk as badly when we asked them to then talk
a little bit more about emotions or tell us
what feelings were associated with that.
I ran this on a number of Bungie employees as pilots inside the studio.
And I was sitting in a conference room, this little bitty space, just playing music and
asking them to tell me stories.
And even one guy that walked in looked around and said, oh my god, it looks like a shrink's
office in here.
And that's the censored version.
He didn't even balk once he got a little bit further into it and got a little bit more
comfortable.
So it was kind of surprising that we were even able to get somebody with that much discomfort
to be able to get through this stuff.
So the next type of question that we ask people, and I'm going to play part of that same piece
again and have you guys try to pick out as well up to three words that you think sort
of fit the feelings that you sense as you listen to this piece of music.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
One of the things I forgot to mention that I like about this type of question is that
it gives people a language that they didn't necessarily have before.
So if people aren't used to having to tell us what sorts of feelings they have, this
makes it a little bit simpler to just have a few options to choose from.
And while it may not represent every single possible feeling, because I don't even think
that's remotely possible, at least it gives them a way to start trying to identify some
of those mixtures of things that are going on for them.
And what we got out of this question from the 70 people we were looking at was something that looks like that word cloud you saw at the beginning of the talk today.
You see that the more people who chose a particular word, the larger it appears here.
So each of these words is proportional to the number of people who chose it.
said that feeling was evoked for them in that piece of music.
And what's neat about this is that it's not simple.
You can't put numbers to music and make it simple
because music is never simple. Each piece is unique. It's going to have its own
mixture of emotions.
And it's great that we see that this piece is not only sad to people, but it's moving, it's reflective, it's serene, and it's also hopeful.
So even though it's all those things, it's this really great mix.
And it's great to see that it's not just a simple answer of what do we think this represents.
And what we call it now is the emotional fingerprint.
Because if you look at this thing, no two pieces are ever going to be exactly alike.
There will be some that will be similar, but each one will have its own unique emotional profile.
So something else that is important to know is just how consistently or how far do we
feel specific emotions that we're especially interested in.
So in games, something that is...
typically really important is balancing calm moments with exciting moments.
Because if it's too exciting all the time, people get bored or overwhelmed.
Or if it's too calm, then they just don't feel like they're getting anywhere.
And so being able to know really how much are we getting from people in those two areas
at the times whenever we want them to feel more excited or more calm
is one of the things that we'd like to know more about.
So what we would ask people is to rate their emotional state.
Would they say they were completely calm with this piece, or would they say they were very excited with this piece?
So giving them the option between two opposites.
And for this piece, as expected, it was very consistently calm.
I kind of still want to know who that one guy was.
Yeah, yeah, who's the excited guy?
Excited.
It's okay.
Well, we're humans. It always comes out as some sort of...
Well, I'm not going to name names, but there was...
We were talking about this earlier today, but one of our programmers came to me,
and he's a guy I've worked with for years.
Amazingly smart and he goes, oh Marty you gotta hear this music. I got the soundtrack.
It's the most hopeful music I've ever heard. I'm like, oh well that's great.
And I put it on and I'm like, you're kidding me. It was just like, not even going to describe it,
but it was like, for me, it was probably the furthest from hopeful that I could imagine.
And I still to this day have no idea what causes him to feel hope by listening to this music.
I just felt despair. I mean, it was just amazing. But anyway.
great segway.
One of the other things we asked was where were they on the spectrum between despair
and hope.
And for this particular piece of music, it's really fascinating that people really felt
very despair, very much despair or very much hope and everything in between.
So it's one of those sorts of pieces that
It can mean many things to many different people.
And depending on the moment in your game, that may be awesome.
It may mean that everybody's experience is totally unique,
and it's what they choose to make it.
Or if the story explains something
that is more despair or hope, perhaps
that can sway it more that direction,
depending on where it is in the game.
So that's all pretty neat.
I'm going to hand you back to Marty for interlude.
Yeah, and I love just finding out that, like, there are some chameleon kinds of things that
happen with music.
I think all of us who are composers kind of know that already, that we can juxtapose things
and it will take on some meaning based on what it's associated with.
And those pieces that are not necessarily, like, this piece is obviously calm, but it
can represent both despair and hope.
And that's a nice thing just to know about it.
So part of this talk was something that I did last year, which I'm calling plan vertical
synchronicity. Everybody remembers that, right? Yeah, okay, great. What that is is a technique
that I use for putting, implementing music in games, and I'm taking advantage of...
cognitive bias.
And that is, sort of all humans tend to try
to make order out of chaos.
I don't know why that is.
Maybe it's an evolutionary thing.
But that's why every culture looks into the night sky
and makes constellations.
So the concept of constellations is really important.
Some of the constellations have a practical meaning,
but there's stories behind
The way human beings look at chaos and try to make some sort of order out of it.
And the way I use that is in...
How many of you know about the technique of having...
Pink Floyd's Dark Side of the Moon playing while you're watching Wizard of Oz?
Okay, that's all the stoners in the audience. Excellent!
You just identified yourselves.
So to me that's an incredible example of cognitive bias.
It's putting two completely disparate things together.
And Pink Floyd has said they had absolutely nothing to do with thinking about Wizard of Oz
or looking at that movie or doing anything that lines that up.
But if you line those two things up, you will find as you watch and listen to Wizard of Oz
and hear Pink Floyd's Dark Side of the Moon, you will see things that start somehow making sense
because your brain wants it to make sense.
So I call this planned vertical synchronicity, which is taking something that's one kind
of piece and then just randomly putting another piece on top of it, becoming a layer, and
the listener will automatically try to line those two things up together because if they're
playing together, they must have been intended to play together.
And what's nice about that is that, from an implementation standpoint,
You can start, let's say for example, you can start an ambient piece, and then if something
important happens you can start a percussive piece, and they're both playing at the same
time.
And the player gets the advantage of having something that they do essentially feel like
it's causing those two things to start, and then while they're playing together, things
start lining up and it feels like it was planned.
And it is planned, but exactly the details of how things line up is not necessarily planned.
And how many people here have scored a scene or done sound design on a scene or created
ambience for a scene, and then the director will say, oh man, that was beautiful how you
hit that one moment, and you didn't intend to.
Anybody?
Accidental?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Take credit for that.
Never say, oh, that was an accident.
No, I mean, if you're a composer, say, yeah, I totally planned that.
And that's.
That works well.
Anyway, so here we're going to, I'm just going to show you,
I think the reason that one of the things that was intriguing to Brandy
was that I basically said there's an emotional feeling you get from this ambient piece
and there's a different emotional feeling you get from the percussive piece.
And when it's combined, now you get a third emotional feeling.
And she's identified some fingerprints for this by doing this.
So here's the ambient piece.
You might recognize this, it shows up in Halo Reach and similar things in every Halo
game ever.
And here's the emotional fingerprint.
Not yet, this is that.
This is one of the little stories that people said about this piece.
And there's the emotional fingerprint.
So just as an aside to the composers in the audience,
if you ever want to evoke ancient, just have some men singing something.
As soon as you do anything that sounds monk-like, boom, ancient. You're going to get that every time.
Okay.
I'm giving away all my secrets, but there you go.
Here's the percussive piece.
You know, and both these pieces can be used by themselves just to evoke basically one kind of mood.
Here's the story of this piece.
That's great. Kick the ass.
Yes.
I lost my cursor.
There it is.
Okay.
Now, what's interesting about this is when you do a combination, and remember, like I
said, what's fun about these particular pieces, if they're looping or they have different
sections to them, you can start either one first and start the second one and layer it
on top at any moment you want.
The way I showed it last year was I had somebody just click their fingers and I started the
other one, and it never sounded like a mistake to me.
Here's the combination.
And even though these things don't
intentionally line up vertically, your head can't help but...
There's a reason for that downbeat, even with the background music, the ambient part.
Here's the story.
And here is the new emotional fingerprint.
So, I think it's interesting to see here, what are the things that...
come through from the ambient piece, what are the things that are retained from each
one of these emotional fingerprints, and what are some of the things that like sort of recede.
So we had nothing primal in the first piece, but now primal is pretty interesting, and
we had nothing powerful, but powerful is still there.
But now this new piece we've got, you know, some foreboding rather than mysterious, which
I think is pretty interesting.
So...
Just looking at this combination, you have three unique emotional fingerprints, and if
you have something as simple as an ambient piece, a percussive piece, and then you know
that you're going to get a different emotion for people when you combine the two.
That's a really powerful tool for a composer who's implementing music in a game.
And then I think...
This is you.
Or is this me?
Or you.
You can do this one.
So I'm going to make it up.
What does that have to do with games?
This has to do exactly what I just said.
So this is identifying the music that you're writing,
thinking about this range of emotions,
and knowing that when you implement this,
you can have some data that goes ahead of it.
You can maybe test some of these pieces of music
by themselves in a way that gives you some,
maybe just even confirms your own belief about how people
are going to respond to it.
And then you can use it.
And I think this is you next.
Sweet.
So what we did to try to really understand
how the emotions are preserved or not
whenever we mix them with video games
is that we took 10 of the music clips
from our first study that we ran.
And we also took five video clips from recent games
that lasted about a minute.
And we combined them to make a total of 50 combinations,
completely at random.
So it meant that there were some pieces that were matched
to things that were very, very different from it in nature.
But we wanted to see what would happen, because like
Marty said, people do tend to make order out of chaos.
And they do tend to want to make something fit, even if
it's totally weird from what they would normally expect in
that game.
And we were really curious to see what would happen, how much of this emotional fingerprint is preserved in the final product after we combine these two things.
So one of the examples that we had was a very sad and reflective piece of music that was combined with this exciting stealthy clip from Assassin's Creed.
And this was the result.
All I can say is that this is a game where humanity is un非常在
There's no need for me to put any of this stuff out there.
I just wanted to remind you guys that society is impossible to resist.
More recently I've learned that with all of that stuff going on,
in this game,
things will end up just the way they are.
So don't stop.
It's a game.
And it's hard to get over it.
And...
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
It really shouldn't work.
It really shouldn't.
What's interesting is that the emotions were so powerful
here that we really do see a significant amount of,
at least reflective, sad was decreased significantly.
And for some reason, serene really pulled out.
Maybe it's because there was a little bit of serenity
to people in just the Assassin's Creed clip by itself.
And also it was there in the music too.
And for some reason, this became much more serene
and mysterious.
But was very much related to the music,
but very little related to the visuals
in this particular case.
And we saw this a lot.
Of the 50 combinations that we made,
92% of them had a significant correlation
between the fingerprints of just the music
and the combination of what we got as the overall effect.
So it's just one way of saying that
It's hard for the emotions to not influence your overall emotional impact on people.
Because it's just this very powerful tie to how we feel and what our experience is.
One of the other interesting things here is that we decided to just get five different
kinds of clips from existing games.
and
this is what you're going to see and this is what you're going to hear simultaneously.
And it was still interesting to me some of the clips.
I would be like, oh, that would be a cool way to score that scene, and it actually hits
that moment.
Even like, I think, when the camera pulled away in that and you saw the...
There was a sort of an emotional feeling in the music that somehow kind of matched up.
And that was cool.
I planned that.
So another theme that we're going to see through here is
just a percentage that sort of represents how related was
this piece to the overall effect versus the visuals.
And this is one of the cases where this piece was much more
related than the visuals were.
But we'll see some others that were not quite that way or
were the opposite of that.
So of the 8% that didn't have a significant relationship,
they were pretty interesting.
So in one case here, we had a very hopeful, joyful,
mysterious piece of music matched with Gears of War.
And that's really fun.
See, I can almost make that work. Come on!
That's an example of cognitive dissonance that's just too overwhelming for cognitive bias.
Oh, God. The poor people in this study. We didn't tell them that we were randomizing just random music with the visuals.
Some of the comments at the end of the study would say,
I love Marty's music, but oh my God, what is he thinking?
They had no idea what was happening, so it was kind of a mean trick.
So what we got in the combination here was something that was much more related to the
visuals because people just kind of had to reject the fairies and Gears of War on Ice
aspect here.
We did see some new things crop up, like mysterious, but probably just because they felt fairly
confused.
So, definitely it went both ways.
There were definitely some powerful pulls towards the emotions and the music, and some
that had more powerful pulls towards the visuals.
But what was interesting was that there were definitely differences in the types of emotions
that music would bring about versus the types of emotions that visuals were likely to.
So whenever we look at just the music alone and all the 10
pieces that we considered, any of the emotions that were ever
reached in any of the pieces and how much they were reached
is represented here.
So this says that we were able to reach aggressive, very
strongly, mysterious, creepy, stealthy, a whole huge variety
of emotions.
At least one piece was able to evoke that emotion fairly
consistently across a population.
It's a very diverse palette.
And granted, there were only five videos.
But of the videos we had, they definitely
had some strong pulls to emotion.
But the palette was significantly more limited.
That could have been because we also only pulled five videos
instead of 10 pieces of music.
We did intentionally try to pick a fairly diverse set of videos.
But note that this is on a very small set of information here.
So we could be misrepresenting some of the visuals.
But of what we saw, music was able to produce a significantly greater effect in foreboding,
hopeful, powerful, primal, sad, serene, some of these very complex emotions that I don't
know that we'd necessarily be able to see in games without music and without music being
able to target those things.
Whereas the visuals were incredibly good at stealthy and heroic, even more so than the
music was in these cases.
And also if we look at how much the emotions were able to explain the overall experience,
on average the music alone had about 43% of the experience explained, and the visuals
alone had 33%.
And this is randomly applied music too.
So it's possible that the numbers would be even higher in very carefully crafted or well-designed audio experiences.
So it's pretty fascinating that the numbers for music alone were even as high as they were here.
What's also interesting is that even if these numbers were mutually exclusive,
there's still 25% of the overall experience that's not explained by one or the other explicitly.
Which is interesting, it's kind of fascinating, because that means 25% is totally new stuff.
New emotions that people did not mention for one or the other.
And so what that pretty much means is that you kind of still need guys like Marty.
There's still some black magic, there's still some creativity,
there's still having to use your gut to know where to put these pieces of music
and what the overall effect is going to have whenever you combine two random
things like that, two artistic forms. You're going to get something
interesting besides just what those two pieces are by themselves.
So it's pretty fascinating. So we have one more interlude from Marty.
Yes.
So also last year I showed another ambient and percussive piece that went together.
The interesting thing about these two pieces were that I didn't think they would go together
because they both had their own key center, they both had their own harmonic rhythm.
They shouldn't have gone together.
And I could not make them not go together and sound like a mistake.
They always, whenever I started one and then started the other,
they eventually seemed like they were in sync.
So this is this particular ambient piece.
And there's this music fingerprint.
Now, granted, it's not a strong harmonic rhythm,
but it does have changes that are happening.
I'm just going to stop it anyway. That's what it does.
Here's the percussive, more tense, stealthy thing.
You can see it's in a different key. Related.
And of course, the way I found this is I had these music files up.
I thought I was clicking on one, and it turned out to be these two things.
And it was an accident.
But you should always use your accidents.
So it was fun.
And if you played Reach, you might remember this from the space flight
scene, where these things happen.
I will turn you off now.
There we go.
And so here's the combo.
It's just random, it really is.
There's no money, how many different ways I play these two together,
they'll always end up somehow coming back together.
It's very strange.
So they end in the same key, I don't know why that was.
But, so, what we decided to do then is take something like this
and actually play it with another piece of video.
This is the what?
That's Mass Effect.
From Mass Effect.
And this is what the visuals...
Do I just click on this? Sorry.
Oh no, not that one. Go ahead and keep going through it.
One more. Oh yeah, here's the final combo.
So here's the movie of this.
This is just gameplay.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
Did you want to talk about these numbers?
I'll talk about numbers.
Okay. Numbers are confusing to me.
Poor Marty.
So what's interesting here is that whenever you look at these two, you see that they are fairly similar pieces.
You know, the mysteriousness, but also kind of serene and moving about.
And whenever you combine them, you do get something that is fairly similar to both of these, but is somewhat more...
But in this case, the visual is more connected to the visuals in this experience than the
music.
What is even more interesting is that if we go back one step further to see how the percussive
piece is related to the final combo versus the ambient, we actually don't see very much
of these elements.
And in fact, for the most part, people are completely ignoring.
the contribution of that piece of music, in that they can't seem to reconcile this idea
of something stealthy and tense and exciting and aggressive whenever it's clearly such
of a calm sort of scene.
It's out in the open.
It's not stealthy.
It's kind of just an out-wandering, exploring kind of scene.
And somehow they just managed to not recognize those feelings.
But this piece is even more related than the combo on its own.
The sort of serene, mysterious piece that I guess reconciled better for people
than just the percussive piece on its own.
So what that kind of says is that if you have these two pieces, these two musical elements...
One of them, if it makes more sense, people, their minds might latch on to that, and then
just somehow kind of ignore the piece that doesn't make sense.
So it's, again, making order out of chaos.
You give them things that they can't reconcile, they can't make sense of, they're happy to
latch on to the ones that do.
So pretty fascinating.
I will...
Okay, well I want to make sure we leave time for some questions because I'm sure there are a lot.
We've got a few minutes left, but the thing I want you to remember is that it's important.
Sorry, that image will never get out of your head.
But it is really, really important to talk to your developers and talk about the feelings.
And when I work with the designers, especially level designers and the designers on the game,
I'm always asking, what's the emotions?
What's the emotional journey that you want the player to go through,
even in the smallest encounter and overall?
Because as composers and people who, you know...
Compose music for games. This is something that we really, really can help with.
And it's, it's, it's, you have to be able to figure out a way to talk to some of these
guys about feelings, because their feelings are usually not very broad.
And this is a great way to do it. And then, of course, I think that some of the
crazy stuff is the...
We all know that if we can score a scene and really work on it,
that's going to be the crafted sequence of music,
and we're going to be able to do well on that.
But it's those moments of gameplay that we don't have control over,
the moment-to-moment decisions the player makes.
And if we can figure out ways of crafting an emotional journey for them
that seems to line up, it's incredibly powerful.
And music is one of the best ways to do that.
And then the final thing here, and this is not a super strong ending, but here we go.
I am now convinced that it's okay to use research to support my own inner goose and the overall goose of the studio.
You know, this was a really fascinating experiment for me.
To a certain extent, it confirmed what my instincts were, which is always nice for me to have that happen.
But it also gave me some extra ammunition, and I'm able to talk a little bit more intelligently.
uh... with that with the uh... some of the big brains in the studio about the
importance of emotions and that we actually have ways that we are
controlling that we are actually kind of rational about
and this is a uh... this is a really really great tool
i'm not exactly sure how many use it in the in the future uh...
uh... we didn't we were not asking anybody whether they liked
music or this particular music we weren't asking their opinions about what
kind of music they liked it was had nothing to do with their opinions it all
had to do with
This is the music you have to listen to and this is the, we want you to tell us what your emotions are.
And they didn't even have the choice of like yucky or like I hate this.
So they had to like figure out a way to talk about their actual emotions.
They did write in confusing periodically or boring if they didn't like the visuals or something.
But it's okay, we don't have to know about that part, hence the muzzle.
All right.
I'm going back. I didn't want that one image to be up while we're answering questions.
So thanks for coming. That's our emotional puppeteers talk.
And now we're going to open for questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Brandi.
Thank you, Martin.
If anybody has questions, yeah, line up. There's mics in these two aisles.
And it would be helpful to be in front of a mic.
Go ahead.
The question is when you have two pieces of music lined up on top of each other,
are those literally just two pieces of music lined up on top of each other,
or do you do anything specific mix-wise to make them match in a way that
maybe helps what you want to do or just interested to know more about your process there?
No, I actually, there are times when I might decide that this one piece is a little bit
too loud to match with the other one, so if I know I'm going to have that percussive piece
go over the top of this ambience, I might say, yeah, that'll be better to be down 6
dB or something.
But I'm listening to it, and I know that these files mix best at a certain level, and so
that's just built into the implementation.
I had a question, do you guys know about if there's any more research that had been done
with similar studies, different games?
Not necessarily in games that I could find.
The research I found before about just emotions in music is out there.
In fact, that's actually one of the ways we chose the words that we wanted to include
for how people describe their feelings from that.
Because I was just wondering, if they played the game Tony Hawk, do they do more kickflips
when they listen to loud music?
Yeah, I don't know. I don't know that a lot of people have actually tried studying this stuff.
I think it's kind of a hard thing to nail and we're not...
We can't even be 100% sure that this is really what people are feeling.
But it's interesting to take a stab at it.
I don't think from what I've been able to find that many people have really tried very much.
We did see some... You sent me some, like, really unreadable research,
but it, for the most part, it...
It seemed very simplistic, at least for me, I couldn't take anything from it, it was like
a single, like, I feel sad, or I feel happy and there'd be this, you know, kind of boring piece.
And so, um, that's why when we talked about it I said, you know, the only kind of music I like
is music that has some sort of...
and complexity, something where it feels like it's taking you from a beginning and a middle
and an end. And that's the kind of music most people actually wanna listen to. So how do
we actually have something that happens over time be reflected in a study? So the stories
and the multiple words was really important to us.
Thank you.
Um, I wanted to ask about the word cloud. You just mentioned how you got some of it
from other studies, but would you change the words that you used in the future? Were,
were there some words that you thought didn't?
work out.
Yeah, actually, some of the ones that we found either that people didn't choose because
our particular audience just won't choose them or some that ended up being fairly synonymous.
So I think the words glorious and joyful were very rarely chosen on any of the pieces of
music or videos that we chose.
And even though in other research they found that people associated those words with music,
perhaps maybe our audience just doesn't.
And since we're wanting to keep that set of words limited,
there may be room for a couple of other words
that we didn't get to add in, maybe that other people wrote
in, that it would be really nice to have that space for.
So there are definitely some that can be changed out,
especially if there's a particular feeling that you're
trying to get.
It's certainly important to trade in some of those, but
trade it into a place where it's as synonymous as
possible to keep the diversity available to people.
I had a question for Marty. I remember reading a while back, I think it was about Mark Twain,
but don't quote me. There's a man who was really fascinated by steamboats. He thought
they were just the most magical thing he'd ever seen. And so when he studied all about
them and learned exactly how they worked, he found that the magic was gone. It's like
he just didn't relate to them in the same way, and so he went and did something else.
I was wondering, as a composer, as you delve really into the numbers, do you find that
limits you or liberates you in your writing? Does it change your writing at all?
That's a really good question.
Certainly, I'm going to be on the lookout for that.
But I would say, having as long a career as I've had doing
music, I'm not going to be able to do that.
The, I've read some studies where they talk about left brain, right brain, and the more
you study something that's more of a right-brained activity, the more your left brain is engaged.
So I tend to have trouble just listening and enjoying music.
I have to like consciously put myself in a different space.
And I sometimes call it, I put a different hat on.
So like, when I come in and I'm like, I'm going to try to write some music, I have to
put on this hat that is not analytical.
And I'm just trying to approach, and if I improvise something that actually gives me a little shiver or chill, which sounds strange,
but I listen to what I did and I say that caused some sort of an emotional response in my soul.
So I wanted to hold on to that.
And then the next day I come in and I'm very analytical.
I look at everything that's... I analyze it. I figure out a way to develop it.
I figure out how it's going to be used.
It does take some of the magic out, which is why I probably don't even have the ability
to tell any kind of an interesting story when I'm listening to the pieces.
I almost immediately go into an analytical mode, which is hard.
So I think anybody who's been a composer for a long time probably runs into that periodically
and sometimes you just have to listen to talk radio or something.
I don't listen to music usually in the car, I don't have headphones on when I'm at home.
It's sometimes really hard to have that sort of just initial emotional experience for someone
who's just working in it.
And of course, the numbers situation here is like I'm, you know, I want to make sure
that that doesn't stomp on anything that's precious to me.
But it's really pretty interesting.
So we'll see.
Yeah, and we actually found that if we included any questions that even allowed users to become
analytical, they tended to deprioritize or not even be able to get into writing their
stories or telling us about emotions.
So we completely intentionally left out any sort of critical or analytical types of questions
in this study.
It was all intended to be very imaginative, creative, emotive, to be able to keep people
in that sort of mindset as they went through it.
I think this gentleman was in line.
Oh, OK, sure.
My question is about working with clients.
When a client hires you for a gig and they say that they have these X, Y, and Z specific emotions
that they want the music to represent, and then they send you some examples that are completely different
than what you would do to represent those emotions.
What should be paramount?
Should you go and do what they have asked you for,
or should you blow them away with your interpretation that exactly represents the emotions?
Sure.
That's, of course, you're asking...
a dangerous question of someone who is not going to give you good advice.
This has worked for me and I've done talks about this at other GDCs where I call it the
prima donna technique and for some reason it kind of works for me and I don't recommend
it for everybody else.
But to a certain extent I think any artist that's going to be respected has to have some
strong passion about what they think is the right way to approach things.
And there's a thing in the film business, which is temp scores,
where an editor and a director will get together,
and they'll take something that's existing,
and they'll cut to it.
And then they show that to the composer.
And even at Bungie, when our cinematics team decides,
well, we need to cut this thing, and we need some music,
can we use some of your music?
Or I got this piece I really like, and I'm like, look,
you can cut your scene to any piece of music you want.
You're going to, that'll help you get a pace, that'll help you cut on the beat, that'll help you do whatever it is you want, that's fine.
But don't ever play that for me.
And that's my prima donna thing coming through, but the reason I don't want that to happen is because as a creative person I only have two possible responses.
Either I hear that piece and I hear what they were trying to do, how they cut it, and I try to do something close, because I know that's what they like, or I try to do the opposite of what they did, because I'm...
And, you know, trying to be a jerk and...
But I don't have any fresh approach.
I don't just get to see the scene and think,
okay, what would I like to do?
Now, I don't mind talking to them and having them
tell me the emotional story they want to make sure
it gets through.
That's actually really, really helpful.
But I don't necessarily want to hear what they cut the music to.
And I think that's a real shame because it doesn't allow the composer to really have
a fresh approach.
And getting a fresh approach after being sort of polluted by hearing something else is really
difficult.
So, yeah.
Thank you.
I'm curious about whether you take into account cultural biases in doing these kinds of things
because I feel like a...
A lot of times, the associations that we have with certain types of music are kind of acquired
through just whatever we kind of grew up listening to.
And I'm wondering if that came into play.
Yeah, that's a great question.
And we're almost out of time.
I want to get this last person in too.
Oh, sure.
But what I would say is, like, yeah, as you can tell, the music that was selected and
the kind of music that I happen to like, it's certainly completely from a Western film scoring,
you know, programmatic sort of approach.
And yeah, that's not necessarily going to be reflected in other cultures.
Thankfully, Western culture is so dominant that it pretty much translates to a pretty
good global market.
But I really don't know, it would be fascinating for me to even understand some indigenous
kinds of like Japanese, like some of the Japanese singing, I'm like, I don't even know what
emotion they're trying to evoke.
But I know that there's something really deep and there's a whole story there.
That would be fascinating to see.
Yeah, we did not collect that information about people, their ethnicity and where they were from.
But we targeted only people who live in the United States.
So at least people who have had significant experience to Western culture.
So we're probably seeing a primarily Western response to the information we got here.
Okay, one more quick question.
Most of the music that you've shown and most of the games that you've shown either have this soft and serene or depressing or combative action.
What about scary or lovey-dovey? Because that also exists in games and that seems to be completely missing.
We actually had that, but go ahead.
We did. We had that in there. We definitely had one piece that was completely creepy. Which one was that?
I don't know that it will pull back up again.
But we had one that was completely creepy.
The problem is that we have limited time and we have limited things to show.
But we definitely had 14 pieces of music that intentionally represented.
There was one that was noted to be very romantic.
There was one that was noted to be very eerie and scary.
And so we tried to get at all those things.
We just don't have them all here to show.
But we definitely wanted to get at that sort of breadth of emotion.
And that's the thing I think that especially the composers can take away is that the thing
I felt really good about was that in terms of the range and depth of human emotions,
music can really cover a wide spectrum.
And that's a great toolbox for all of us to be able to take into these projects we're
working on.
All right, so we're out of time.
Thanks very much for coming.
And... 1