to snap to character, building strong player attachment
through narrative.
I really appreciate you coming.
So what does that long-winded title even mean, really?
I mean, I think we can all think of games that we've played
where we encountered characters that sort of stuck
in our minds that we thought about,
and we wondered what they were thinking late at night,
and maybe they remember that horrible thing
we said to them once.
And we can also remember games where we just didn't have
that attachment to certain characters.
We sort of got through the entire game.
and never really felt emotionally attached to any of the characters.
So I want to sort of figure out why.
Like why is that?
Why some characters really stick in your mind?
And why do some characters just not do that?
So that's what I want to explore in the next 30 or so minutes.
I'm probably going to use most of the 30 minute time,
so we'll have some questions at the end,
but I'll hang out on the overlook after this if you have more questions.
This is something that I have had a lot of experience in my career thinking about and
working on.
A lot of my career was at Telltale Games where I worked on Walking Dead Season 1, 400 Days,
the DLC episode, and Season 2.
I was the guy who designed the train puzzle, so for the three of you in here that like
Myst-style adventure game puzzles, you're welcome.
And for everyone else, I'm really sorry.
I was also the co-creator and lead designer of Tales from the Borderlands.
So, and now I'm at Hangar 13 Games
where I've been working on Mafia III
and its associated DLC as a world designer.
So I've learned some important lessons
that hopefully can sort of help you avoid
undermining your player's ability
to connect with your characters.
I've only got 30 minutes,
so I'm gonna just focus on four specific lessons
that I've learned in my time.
Quality time spent, emotional and motivational parody,
balancing pragmatism, and depth and specificity.
And for what it's worth,
there's gonna be some spoilers for Walking Dead,
some for Tales from the Borderlands,
and a little bit of Mafia III.
So hopefully you're caught up on those games.
So here's the first big lesson,
and this is the most important lesson, honestly.
In real life, there's no way to force
an immediate emotional connection between two human beings.
That's just not how people work, right?
Digital characters are no different.
Players need to be allowed the space and time
in the game's narrative to build an emotional rapport
with your characters, to slowly, over time,
learn about those characters and learn to love them.
There's no way to cheat or shortcut this, none, okay?
Some game narratives try and shortcut this
by including a previously established,
usually familial relationship,
placing the player in a parental role
or like an older sibling protecting a younger sibling,
sometimes sort of jokingly referred to
as the dadification of video games.
But the assumption is that humans care about their in real life family,
so that'll sort of relate one to one with caring about their digital family.
But that never works, right?
Family as a word, as a concept, just sort of describes a relationship
that you already have.
It doesn't have any power on its own.
They expect that to sort of impress upon you the need
to care for these characters.
And because your avatar, your character,
cares about your characters, other characters in the game,
doesn't mean that your player is automatically going to.
Additionally, real-life bonds don't just spring to life fully formed like they do in a narrative
that you've written.
Like, when you're born and a baby, you don't immediately love your family.
They take care of you in a very pragmatic way, which I'm going to touch on later in
the talk.
And over time, with emotions, you know, emotional experiences shared with all these people in
your life, you learn to love them over time.
So in The Walking Dead, it was a very specific choice
to not make Lee and Clementine be related to each other.
Really early versions of the story
actually had them related with each other,
but we realized that we wanted Lee and the player
to encounter Clementine
under the exact same emotional circumstances.
So neither Lee nor the player know who Clementine is
when they meet her, which means that they go through
the exact same emotional bonding steps
at the exact same time as they grow to appreciate her,
want to protect her, and eventually sort of come to love her.
I call this emotional parody,
and I'll touch on it later in the talk.
The problem comes in is when the player and their avatar
have offset emotional experiences,
such as a character liking another character,
or even like being in love with another character,
while your player is a stranger.
They don't understand why their character
loves these other characters.
It makes it a lot more difficult
to sort of emotionally merge themselves
with their avatar in the game.
The severity is compounded by how drastic the difference is
between the two emotional states.
Being a stranger as a player and a character,
liking another character, is much less drastic
than a character loving another character
and you being a stranger to them.
In these instances, it's really, really important
to spend the time up front to catch the player up
kind of emotionally with where the character is in the game.
So the opening sequence of Tales from the Borderlands,
this actually breaks this rule
because it introduces Rhys with previously
established friends, but it still works
because it immediately spends all of that opening
letting you get to know why he cares
about his friends Vaughn and Yvette.
You get to know their personalities,
you get to know why they're important to Rhys,
so you can sort of emotionally catch up
to where Rhys is when you start the game.
You very quickly learn that they sort of support him
and thereby the player when he goes through a painful loss,
and they all devise a plan to get revenge
on the villain who caused it.
This allows you to quickly appreciate them
on the same level that Rhys does
before the game goes really anywhere,
before it takes more than the first few steps.
You were there with Rhys.
You saw and experienced that pain firsthand,
which means that you also experience
the sort of consolation that his friends give him.
When they're consoling Rhys,
they're also consoling you, the player.
So the big secret really, if you take one take away
from this talk is emotional connection
will always take time.
That's the big secret.
That's the secret sauce of emotional connection.
Thanks for coming.
So it isn't to say that it must be the same amount.
Everybody sort of has, everyone's unique and different
and players will bond to your characters
at different speeds over different times.
Everyone warms up to real people in real life
at different speeds, so you have to understand
that what happens in the digital world
is exactly the same as what happens in the real world.
It's crucial to give people time to get to know a character,
learn their quirks and their turns of phrase
and little details that they can fall in love with
and give them time to fall in love.
So, we learned this lesson the hard way
when we worked on the Walking Dead DLC episode 400 Days.
If you haven't played it, it's kind of an experiment
in short form storytelling.
It's all centered around a specific location and space
over the span of 400 days.
The idea was to sort of laser focus
on very small specific stories,
give the player just enough time
to emotionally bond with the characters,
make one big emotional decision,
and sort of end the story there.
The problem is that only 20 minutes long is just not enough time to do any of that stuff.
It means that we only had 20 minutes to tell a story, we only had a few characters that
we could introduce, which is just not enough vectors of exposure to get to know who your
character is.
And a lot of that running time is spent doing the very important tasks of setting up the
characters, getting to know the characters, setting up the specific scenario, like the
choice scenario that you were going to be given.
and then give all of that context.
So we just didn't have enough time
to really get you emotionally invested.
On top of that, players could feel that choice coming,
like they played an entire season of The Walking Dead,
they sort of began to predict that emotional crescendo
leading to a big choice moment,
and they knew after completing a few of the stories
that the story was just gonna end right afterwards.
You know, the choices themselves are interesting
on a morally academic level,
but the consequences are always more interesting
than the choice, and that kind of goes.
for every narrative game that gives you a choice.
Thinking in your mind what the consequences could be
while that timer is ticking down
is what a telltale game is, is that choice moment,
is where all of that value comes in.
So there just wasn't enough time to get you emotionally invested in these characters or their stories.
So for what it's worth, I'm really still proud of 400 Days.
I think we really came up with some interesting innovations on our way.
We introduced interesting characters and interactivity.
I think it's totally worth playing as an experiment and sort of a mental experiment.
But this just comes back to why it's so important to give your players the space
and time to get to know your characters.
I want to add an extremely important supplementary lesson to this,
that not all time spent with a character is created equal.
A player who spends their time sort of sharing experiences
with a character will find themselves,
sort of attaching themselves much closer and much faster
than if you just sort of passively occupy the same space
in the world as a character.
Just like in real life, which is going to be a running talk,
a running theme throughout this talk.
is that sharing experience regardless of the emotional flavor,
whether it's sort of sadness, or triumph, or fear, or whatever it is,
it connects you to that character in a very emotionally resonant way.
You have now shared something with this person that you can talk about
that no one else will understand because you were the only two people sharing it.
So, time spent with a character is important, but quality time spent,
sharing an emotional experience, or striving to accomplish something together
as a group, or as two or three people, is way more important.
So lesson number two is emotional and motivational parody.
So a player is not their avatar.
We all know that, but it's our jobs
to be as successful as possible at getting them
to feel like they are their avatar as often as possible.
We want them to sort of share the same emotional space
as their character because it makes it a lot easier
for them for just a moment to remember,
to forget that they're not Lievre,
that they're not Reese, that they're not Fiona.
Just for a moment, we want them to think
that they really are that person.
I know it's a really obvious observation,
but it's really important for the rest of this point.
So back in the early days of video games, motivations were super simple, right?
Stay alive. Kill or be killed. Victory or defeat.
That's all it took to get a player motivated. And survival is a pretty strong
motivator for us as sentient beings. And it's a really clean through line
between what the player's avatar wants, which is to stay alive, and what the player
wants, which is to keep the game experience going and not end and not have to put more
quarters in the machine.
I'll go into this in a little bit more detail later,
but for now, remember that a player's motivation
when they first start a game is to do whatever it takes,
whatever the game asks them to do,
to continue playing the game
and preventing the game experience from ending.
By the way, this specific motivation is super legitimate
and you just need to take that into account
when you are making a game,
that this is not something to discount at all.
So, the introduction of Tales from the Borderlands.
You learn about your main character, Rhys.
You see the explicit motivating event
that sets up the rest of the story.
You are expecting a big promotion.
Your friends have helped you get here.
It's been a long slog and you're really excited.
It's promotion time.
Except your antagonist, Vasquez,
kills your boss and steals your promotion.
So the shock hits Reese the player at the same time it hits the character.
I'm sorry, yes, it hits the player at the same time it hits the character.
So as Vasquez sits there and continues to belittle you and your character,
your ire and your hate for this character grows at the same time Reese's ire does as well, naturally.
So when the game says, all right, it's a revenge plot,
you and Reese are like, yep, that sounds awesome.
You are in complete sync with your motivations.
You don't need expository dialogue
from things that happened off screen.
You don't have to explain motivations.
Not only did you see it,
but you experienced it with the main character.
Reese wants revenge, and so do you.
So, it's really important to remember that the avatar
or the main character of the protagonist of the story
and they're written to be interested
in completing the main quest of the story,
to complete the game.
That's because that's what they're written to do, right?
The player initially is not motivated to do that.
They know it's a video game.
They're thinking about, I wanna play this video game
because it's a video game and I spent $60 on it.
And that's completely fine, that's completely okay
because at first you haven't introduced any reason
for them to not just go along
with what the game is telling them to do.
However, it's vital to remember that as a game progresses,
you're going to be introducing obstacles,
whether emotional or physical,
you're gonna be asking questions of the player,
and every time you do that,
they're gonna reevaluate how they feel
about their motivations and how they feel
about what you're asking them to do.
If their motivation and their avatar's motivation
suddenly sort of become separated,
they're going to completely disconnect from the scenario.
So here's an example.
If you tell the player that the avatar wants to save
a loved one from a scary house,
the character's motivation is,
I want to save my loved one from that scary house.
Their motivation is to go all the way to that goal.
The player's motivation might range somewhere from like,
yep, absolutely, let's do that,
to yeah, okay, fine, let's see where this goes.
Regardless of that, there's a sort of emotional inertia made up of a combination of the character's
motivation and the player's motivation that sort of pushes them forward into the story,
into the narrative.
Now, you encounter something scary, and now they're going to reassess.
The avatar's motivation stays the same.
I still want to save my loved one from the scary house.
But the player's reevaluated.
They might be like, nope, no way, I'm out, I bail.
Now the emotional inertia isn't pulling the players strongly into the game.
It might even be stopped or pulling them away from the experience.
The emotional inertia is a combination of the player and character's motivations, but
the player's motivation is always going to trump everything because it's real.
And this is where you get into experiences where you are playing a game and you're like,
why would I do that?
This seems really stupid.
I'm going to a haunted house, why don't I just call the police?
This seems really dumb.
My avatar is really dumb.
So, emotional and motivational parity.
Remember, you need to keep the player and the avatar
as emotional states and motivations in sync
as often as possible.
It feels risky to spend the first 10 minutes
of an opening sequence of a Borderlands game just talking.
You have to take that risk.
It's super important.
You will not regret it, and you will if you don't.
And be aware when your game is asking the player
to make a judgment call or puts an obstacle in their way
that's gonna make them reevaluate
their emotional attachment to what you're asking them to do.
The next lesson is balancing pragmatism.
So earlier I mentioned at the start of the game,
players are sort of focused purely
on a purely pragmatic task of ensuring
that the game experience continues.
To that end, they're gonna make choices
based on those pragmatic needs alone.
So we as game developers have been sort of taught
and rightly to think of our characters as,
you know, we don't want to objectify them
as abstract game mechanics and flow charts
and state machines and stuff like that.
We really want to imbue them with life and personality
and hide their artificial nature
and allow the player for the moment
just to believe that they're real people, right?
But I argue that it's really important
to allow the player to begin the player's relationship
with a character by leveraging their mechanical value
because this immediately builds
initial pragmatic investment.
Now, I'm not saying that you should stop there.
Pragmatic value alone is a really shallow
kind of investment.
It gives you a lot up front but doesn't last.
But it can much more easily transition that player
into a deep kind of emotional attachment
that we're looking for.
So I'm sure you, if played Walking Dead,
you know the Doug Carley choice at the end of episode one.
But if you don't, at the end of the first episode,
you're forced to choose between
which of these two characters you wanna save.
You can only save one,
and the game has sort of tutorialized at this point
that your choices are permanent
and there's gonna be consequences
that are gonna last for a while based on this choice.
So you understand the gravity of your choice at this point.
So at this point, you haven't really had a ton of time
to emotionally invest in these characters.
You just kind of met them like half an hour ago,
20 minutes ago.
You might have a beginning of an emotional investment,
but for the most part,
you don't have tons of emotional investment,
but this moment is super, super resonant.
Why is that?
Well, it works because you've only spent
some short amount of time with these characters,
but you've also gotten a ton of pragmatic reasons
to keep either of them alive,
which sort of feeds into an overall investment
of either of those characters.
The first time you meet Carly, she's saving her life by shooting a bunch of attacking
zombies and she also proves that she's trustworthy because she knows Lee Everett's, the main
character's, secret, who is a convicted murderer and she hasn't told anyone.
She agrees to not tell anyone.
Doug solves problems and shows how resourceful he can be by sort of helping build and fix
things.
He's also shown that he's willing to put himself in danger to protect other people.
So all these elements provide strong pragmatic reasons
for the player to keep either character alive.
During the choice moment, the player might ask themselves,
which character do I emotionally like more?
But for the most part, they're gonna weigh
the continued pragmatic value of each of their character
against their survival of their avatar,
and therefore the continuation of the game experience.
The majority of early emotional investment
is sort of calculated by players trying to figure out
which choice gives them the best chance of winning the game,
even emotional and sort of like narrative game
like Tales or Walking Dead.
As you can see, 80% of people chose Carly
and 20% chose Doug.
And this is just because the gun was so overwhelmingly
powerful in a game about zombies, funny.
And Doug was more of just a promise,
like he might protect you in the future,
but there's nothing like hard
to really pragmatically invest in there, it was a promise.
It's also important to recognize that even though the choice itself is super pragmatic,
the outcome is super, super emotional.
It's that emotional connection that I was talking about earlier where the player and
their avatar and this character you've chosen to save have all now shared that quality time,
that emotional moment together.
It's an extremely potent moment after the choice.
At the end of Walking Dead episode one, they ask you, why did you save me?
Why did you do that?
And you have moments with them that sort of connect over this shared experience.
If you didn't feel a bond with either of those characters
before that, you certainly start to feel one now.
All players are gonna bond at different speeds
and to different degrees of intensity.
So pragmatic value can sort of help support
or reinforce weaker emotional attachment
to a specific character.
By starting a sort of player like farther along
the investment ladder by just adding pragmatic reasons,
you sort of can help speed up how long it takes them
to emotionally attach to that character as well.
So there's also another use for this kind
of pragmatic balance.
Once the player has had enough time to form emotional bonds,
you can actually force them to make emotional decisions
against their own pragmatism.
It's a really interesting way to mix up the things
that your player cares about.
So here's an early idea.
I had an early idea for Tales from the Borderlands.
We were gonna get unlockable weapons.
So when you played Tales from the Borderlands,
you could unlock certain weapons,
you could put them in Borderlands 2,
and you'd have like a unique gun or whatever.
And my design was to actually tie them
to specific choices that you made
within Tales from the Borderlands.
So for example, you have a friendly character,
you can choose to help him and save his life or he dies.
If he dies, you get a sweet shotgun
you can play around in Borderlands 2 with,
but if he lives, you get nothing.
And your friend's alive, and you have to decide,
what is more important to me?
Is it the emotional value of my friend,
or is it the mechanical value of this shotgun?
What's more, every single time you played
with that gun in Borderlands 2,
you just had to see your dead friend's face.
And you had to live with that decision forever.
And everyone in the game would know what you had to do
to get that shotgun.
You had to be a jerk who let their friend die
to have the shotgun.
You just be reminded of the choice you made
over and over again.
So this got scoped out of the game for a number of reasons, but it might sound familiar to
a few of you who've played Mafia III because completely independent of me, this system
was sort of designed into Mafia III within the sit-downs mechanic.
So in Mafia III, when you complete your takeover of a specific district, a specific piece of
the world map, you sit down with your three lieutenants, who are all criminals, and you
decide who you're going to parcel out to.
And all the sort of mechanical rewards in the game,
all your sort of tech trees are locked behind this mechanic.
So each character has their own tech tree.
One of them might give you a better gun,
another might give you a faster car,
or explosives, or that kind of thing.
So if you want to dive deep into one character's tech tree,
you had to give them a disproportionately larger
amount of property, which eventually would piss off
the guy who got the least property,
and he will actually turn on you,
and you have to fight them.
And it's the whole thing where all of that property
goes away.
What was really interesting though is that 63% of people
did anything it took to keep everyone happy,
which is really, really interesting
because this is a super systems-heavy game
and you get a really, really tangible mechanical benefit
for basically screwing somebody over
to get a super rad sniper rifle
or crazy explosives or whatever,
but it was more important for them emotionally
to keep all their friends happy
than to get a super, super tangible mechanical benefit.
which is really interesting and just goes to show
how super hard it is to balance
pragmatic versus emotional choices.
If you're interested in how the system was built,
there's a talk tomorrow, 11.30, it's an hour talk
by a really talented systems designer, Remy,
who's gonna be doing a talk about how all this stuff
was made, so if you're interested in that,
you should definitely go to that.
So, balancing pragmatism.
Remember, there is value in allowing players
to find mechanical value in characters.
It doesn't overwrite emotional value.
Over time, their emotional value will sort of like,
supplant the pragmatic value,
and the pragmatic value is much less important,
but the pragmatic value can help you get in
in the front door earlier.
And give your players opportunities
to weigh pragmatic versus emotional.
Okay, so the last lesson is depth and specificity.
So, the more specific a character's personality is,
the more believable they are as a person.
Everyone knows someone who has a quick temper
or says, sort of, accidentally says the wrong thing
at the wrong time, or is addicted to 18th century
Victorian architecture, or whatever.
uh... real people are impossibly very unique and you need to allow your
characters that same luxury because it allows players to find those little
endearing qualities that they can really fall in love with
i mean think about excom or a game like excom for example where all you can do is
you can just name your soldiers
but think about how much more emotional investment you have in those soldiers once you name them
after your family or friends or you just name them anything
that's just the tip of the iceberg that's just a name like that's how much you get from
just that
So, as mentioned earlier, as a player gets to spend more time with Doug or Carly after
they make their choice, you get to spend time getting to know them.
You get to learn little quirks about their personality, like Carly was a correspondent,
a news correspondent in War Zones, and Doug likes to make robots in his spare time.
These are little details that can flesh out a character and let players have another sort
of avenue to connect with them.
The most memorable, cherished, and beloved characters
tend to be the ones with the most specificity
written into them.
But that specificity should not come from dialogue alone.
It has to come from their actions as well.
For example, Kenny from The Walking Dead
can tell you all day that he's a fisherman
and give you his backstory.
But what you really learn from his actions
is that he's really short-tempered,
but he's really loyal to his friends,
and that he'll do anything to protect his family.
He never tells you those things,
but he definitely shows you them through his actions.
So I don't mean the quantitative depth of their backstory,
but just the amount of unique traits or quirks
or turns of phrase that really flesh a character out
to be more of a full person.
Like, Reese idolizes Handsome Jack,
or Sasha despises the Hyperion Corporation,
but sort of is curious about what that life is like,
or Lily loves her absolutely awful father.
Why?
It makes you ask, why?
Why do the characters do these things?
Why do they feel these way?
What is it about them that makes them this way?
It makes you wanna dive in and learn more about them.
It's also super important to be careful
where you place these moments of narrative,
you know, these character depth in a larger narrative
without them being sort of introduced apropos of nothing
or in ignoring the tone of the scene as a whole.
Yeah, I've seen this actually happen in games before.
No scene is worth a line or exchange.
So just save them for where you get
the most bang for your buck.
So while adding this detail to your characters,
remember that it's important to allow your characters
to have flaws and have weaknesses.
and make mistakes.
Power fantasy is not emotionally deep on its own.
It's fun, but it's not emotionally deep.
It limits the amount of emotional investment
a player can feel if their character only has good traits.
I mean, how can you empathize with a character
who doesn't feel rage or loss or sadness or defeat?
We feel empathy for these characters
because we too know what it feels like
to want something and never get it.
Lee is not the leader of the group of survivors in The Walking Dead for a long while because
there was a very specific reason for that, which was allowing the player's avatar to
— the power to dictate the sort of goals of the game goes in direct opposition to the
tone of the narrative, the specific goal of the narrative.
In addition, giving the player that much control is way less narratively interesting than forcing
them to make difficult decisions.
So here's an extreme example, but I'll make it anyway.
In Walking Dead episode two, season one, two,
you have to choose how much or who gets to eat.
There's four pieces of food and like seven or eight
or nine people in your group.
So you need to choose out of those people who gets to eat.
Spread across all players, it went down this way, right?
Clementine was first, obviously, and then Duck.
So the two kids.
Number three was Mark, who was a new character
who was just introduced 15 minutes ago.
You knew nothing about him.
And number four is Larry.
Larry is a racist old man who hates you.
He's never been nice to you once.
So like, why is that?
Why, like people don't like Larry,
but they want to get to know him, right?
It's, the two kids are clearly not at all pragmatic choices
as far as like the pragmatic versus emotional goes.
They're not helpful to the group.
They can't really protect anyone,
but they're a very easy emotional choice.
You protect the innocence, right?
Mark is a complete vacuum of information.
So the player's curiosity sort of leads them to him.
And Larry, well, people want to understand him.
People want to know what his deal is,
like why is he the way that he is.
They want to maybe change his mind.
They know he's not a nice character,
but he's got enough depth to his character
that people want to sort of understand him.
On the other side of the coin, it can be just as valuable
to leave intentional empty space about your character.
Not mentioning specific things
that aren't sort of narratively important
allows players to speculate
and fill in missing information themselves.
It gives them a feeling of mutual ownership
over the character.
This is where sort of headcanons and fan theories
and stuff like that.
It's an extremely easy and good way
to give players their own ownership over the characters.
Remember, players will always imprint what they want
on your characters, regardless of what you want,
and that's a super easy way to leverage that,
because it's just gonna let the players
sort of see themselves reflected back in those characters.
So, I've run through a ton of stuff.
Let's wrap up really quickly.
Time spent together is a prerequisite
for emotional connection.
Time spent sharing an emotional experience
or striving to accomplish a goal
is the most valuable time spent.
Pre-established emotional connections
do not shortcut the player into caring earlier.
It can actually have the opposite effect
because their character and them
have a very different emotional place.
Your player and their character should have emotional parity
to ensure that the inertia moves them forward, not backwards.
If your character has previously established relationships,
spend the time to emotionally catch the player up.
Spend the time to let your player
build the same primary motivations as the character.
Let them experience the events
that kick off the story together, if you can.
Give players pragmatic reasons to invest on the ground floor.
Start with pragmatism, but don't stop there.
It's really short term.
Try and find opportunities to force your player
to choose between their emotional attachment
and their pragmatic needs.
Weaknesses and flaws make a character more relatable.
They are relatable.
Ensure that moments of character exploration
fit the tone and the intent of the scene.
Don't shoehorn them in.
Leave undefined space in a character
to allow players to see themselves in them.
And focus on what the characters are feeling
and how they're reacting over their backstory.
Thank you very much.
So I think we have time for a few questions.
And again, I'll hop over to the overlook afterwards if you guys just didn't get a chance to ask
your question.
So feel free to step up to the mic and ask some questions.
Hello. I was really interested in what you were saying about pragmatics leading up to
more emotional connections later on. What can you say about pragmatic elements of the
character coloring the story that the characters place on top of them? For example, a bodyguard
who isn't actually very pragmatically good.
and you're sort of like, you're bad at your job.
You know, like, where it's coloring the emotional situation
to the point where you're like,
well, this guy's just a joke.
Right.
Or something along those lines.
I think that if he's pragmatically bad at his job,
by pragmatics I mean like mechanical value,
like in the game, like he's a swordsman,
he's a magic user, that kind of stuff.
And if he's a bad character pragmatically,
that's going to make it a lot tougher to emotionally, like.
you know fire like the fire mobile game i want to crack the characters but i
like them anyway because they're cool but i'm not an easy battle i just don't
do that because it's a game first and foremost it's a game of its mechanical
mechanics heavy game
But again, like Walking Dead,
it's not a mechanics heavy game.
So like the pragmatic value still had a lot of weight
in that moment.
But I think it's important to remember
that the pragmatic value,
if there's like a negative pragmatic value
or they're like a liability,
like Ben was in the Walking Dead,
it's gonna really hamper how much you can care
about that character.
You can empathize with them.
Like a lot of people empathize with Ben,
but they didn't like him.
They didn't want him around.
They dumped him the first chance they got
for the most part.
So like you have to be careful of sort of shooting yourself
in the knee with negative pragmatic value.
I would ensure that if he's not good at his job,
he has some other pragmatic value.
Like he's like a historian,
he knows a lot of stuff about something.
Like he's got something, some core that he's got use,
he's got some sort of use,
if he's not his primary profession or something.
Thank you.
Yep.
Hey, thanks, great talk.
Thank you.
I'm working on Spy Party, which has got a ton of characters in it, but no linear narrative,
and I'm wondering if you've thought about stuff, like, I mean, one of the things I liked
about your talk was it was very concrete in terms of, like, here's some advice about,
you know, these specific things, but a lot of them tied into, like, you're going to have
time with these characters in an emotional way.
So a game like TF2 or Overwatch or things like that, can you, have you thought about
how character development and, and, like, kind of emotional attachment works in those
games?
Yeah, it's definitely different.
And I don't have experience making those games,
so I can't speak to experience,
but I think about stuff a lot.
Time spent still counts as just like.
I play a ton of games with a specific Overwatch character,
and I feel emotionally connected to that character,
and I love his little turns of phrase,
and I love his little, like,
Torbjorn's camera's closer to the ground.
Like, I love that the first time I saw it.
Like, just stuff like that,
that's just detail that is lovable,
and they have tons of characters.
So, I don't know, like, even like rounds spent in a game
still counts as time spent with a character.
So I don't think you need to have an overarching narrative
in those instances,
because you can just care for those characters.
purely because you are them or you're around them and they have interesting things to say
and you get to know like I wish there was a way in overwatch for me to just
Talk to the characters and ask them questions about themselves or just like even just like
espouse more of their backstories and interests and cares and loves like in their barks, which
they kind of do.
But yeah, I think that that kind of thing is it's just, it's just like inch by inch,
you gain the yard.
And you can get that emotional investment over time if you just give players time to
spend with those characters and give them interesting ways to get their personality
to the player.
Cool.
Thanks.
Hello. Oh. Well, thank you for the talk. It was very interesting. So, all of these apply
to non-player characters, but have you any advice on how to use this with your player
characters? Because, you know, for me at least, the fact that I'm in their shoes doesn't always
make me feel attached to them or even care about them. So, any advice on that?
Sure. Yeah, I think a lot of this advice can actually do the same thing. Like, you know,
Lee Everett is a character.
Reese and Fiona are characters.
They're not ciphers, they're not like silent protagonists
that you just embody entirely and become you.
They have their own desires.
Like there's a moment in The Walking Dead
where you try and like tell the cop like fuck you
and like Lee goes to do it and then he changes his mind.
We don't do that very often because you don't want to subvert what the player wants to do,
but like Lee is a person with a personality.
He can, you know, he can get overly enraged.
He's very passionate.
He cares about these things and not these things.
He likes, like, American history.
Like, he geeks out about American history at one point in the game.
And so all the same things can still apply,
where you just need to give the time with the character,
and you're going to get that because they're the Avatar, but just give them...
a unique voice. Like Lee, when the four options pop up, each of those is one of the things
that Lee would say. We don't have to explore options that Lee would never do. We don't
have to present those options to the player because Lee would just never say, screw this
camp, screw this girl, I'm taking a bus to New York. He just would never do that. So
we don't have to provide those options. So I think just making sure the player feels
like they're getting to know the character.
uh... it it because you get a weird mix of feeling that these you are the ever
it but you're not like he's still a your he's you could use your avatar but he's
also his own person
just make sure they have their own strong personalities that can come out
in dialogue in moments uh... inactions
uh... even if you're telling the players match that zombies face and look
the way that the voice acting like how enraged he is the animation like a lot
of the kids you a lot of like understanding for that guy is
and so it's just a very similar and uh... examples to to these
these examples
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I don't know if we have any more time.
Are we out of time?
No?
OK, so I'll be outside.
You can follow me out there.
So thank you guys so much for coming.