Hi, I'm Dori Arazi.
I'm the Director of Photography at Santa Monica Studio.
Before we start, I kind of want to get to know you guys a
little bit really, really quick.
Pardon me for putting my hands up.
It's kind of bright up here.
Any art or environment art people in the crowd today?
Awesome.
Level designers?
Sweet.
Animators?
Represent.
Dedicated cinematic teams or working cinematic teams?
Cool.
Lighters?
Programmers?
Nice.
Any producers?
Awesome.
Cool.
Any people with like a background in photography?
Awesome.
Well, thanks for coming.
Concept art.
How could I forget?
My bad.
You guys are awesome.
Cool. So before we go on, spoiler alert, we are going to be showing some content from God of War.
If you have not played the game yet, my apologies.
So on God of War, we were trying to create an immersive, interactive narrative experience
that was meaningfully engaging in a uniform manner from beginning to end.
We're trying to kind of challenge the concepts of a game moment versus a cinematic moment
and take the concept of a video game into true interactive entertainment.
Now, saying emotionally engaging is easier said than done.
All of us, probably mostly all of us,
especially people into games,
are constantly bombarded by media.
Movies, TV, games, the little screens
we have in our pockets.
These contents are always trying to vie for our emotion.
And what's happening over time, we get desensitized.
We actually start creating barriers and defenses
to push against that content,
so pretty much we could say sane.
So, how do we break through these barriers?
How do we create visual content that is emotionally resonating?
So we had a theory.
we're gonna try to combine the idea of mentally engaging
our players with emotionally engaging our players.
Not just grabbing them by their mind,
but grabbing them by their gut,
grabbing them by their heart.
And not separately in different beats of the game,
but together and hopefully all the time.
So as we go through this talk,
I'd like you guys to ask yourself
constantly three questions.
One is, how are we experiencing
the things we are looking at?
How do we gauge that experience?
And why are we feeling it the way we're feeling it?
Once we figure out the how and the why,
let's try to figure out what we can do about it
in order to kind of utilize it,
in order to push that engagement experience.
So let's look at what we have out the gate in games.
We have a superpower, and that is mental absorption.
Most of the mechanics we have from the last amazing 20 years
or so of game design is the ability to suck the viewer in
to the content.
And that is a very mental experience.
So if we look at some of the standard mechanics
we have in games these days is navigation exploration,
it's a big boon to absorption, getting us sucked in.
We have puzzles and other engaging mechanics,
it's a big boon to absorption.
We have combat, that's a big mental absorbing parameter.
But we also have story.
And story allows us to engage the viewer in a bit more of a sympathetic way.
And before we move on, let's talk about the difference between sympathy and empathy.
It's going to be critical for the remainder of this talk.
Sympathy is our ability to feel something for somebody else.
It's a feeling for them experience.
Empathy is our ability to get engaged with somebody else's emotion, but actually feel
it as myself, as us, as we.
It's a personal versus an external experience.
The tricky thing with empathy is, at least we found, that you can't engage empathy directly.
It's an amalgamation of different parameters coming together, and we'll get to that in
a little bit.
So we are trying to take absorption and combine it with sympathy to create a sense of empathetic
immersion, a sense you are truly, really there in the content, experiencing it as yourself,
both from a mental standpoint and from a sympathetic emotional standpoint.
So how do we do this?
How do we take absorption and combine it with sympathy?
And not only that, how do we do that in a uniform enough manner
that we can stay consistent within this entwinement
and maintain critical mass to have that sense of empathetic immersion
throughout the entire experience?
So let's go back to some traditional approaches to how to tell visual stories and how to tell
emotionally engaging moments. We'll look at the first person camera, the third person
camera, more traditional styles. If any of you guys have motion sickness, beware.
Cool. So let's ask ourselves, how do we feel about this?
I definitely felt that was me, right?
I was the protagonist.
That was really immersive.
I was very absorbed.
But I didn't really feel much for the protagonist.
There was no emotional connection for me.
There was no sympathy.
And if you guys noticed, the protagonist was
pushing their hand forward towards their female counterpart
trying to say something, but they didn't speak.
And we'll get to why in a moment,
but that's actually a critical distinction
that's a very big problem with a first-person camera.
Let's take a look at a third-person camera and see how that makes us feel.
Cool. So I definitely felt for them, right? There were characters in front of me, I felt for their experience,
sympathy was definitely evoked in me, but I wasn't there. I was kind of like a fly on the wall,
experiencing this whole thing through my mind's eye. So while I did have sympathy, I got a really
big dip and deficit in my absorption. So there's a problem here, right?
The first-person camera has the problem where we engage so deeply in that point of view
that we can't have the protagonist speak or it feels like the words are being inserted
into our brain.
And the first thing we do is we pop out of the experience.
We get a sense of mental and emotional dissonance.
So we can't really tell a deep emotional story in first-person camera.
Third person, while it's really empathetic, sorry,
sympathetic, it's not absorbing enough.
So we can't actually get to sympathy
with a traditional third person camera.
So how do we push absorption onto the third person camera
to create a sense of empathy?
So our theory was this.
Instead of thinking of it as a first-person camera and a third-person camera,
we're going to try to design from an emotional standpoint
something like a first-and-a-half-person camera.
We're going to try to use the third person, but bring the experience from them to me.
In a sense, combining absorption and sympathy to create a sense of empathetic immersion,
a sense that you are truly there, engaging as yourself or as part of the team.
As we were experimenting with this state of empathetic immersion,
we're starting to kind of sputter with successes and get a general idea of
maybe where this can go. We realized how
fragile the state is.
It's kind of like running around with an egg on a spoon.
It's really easy to get a really small bump on your spoon
and drop that egg.
The moment that egg is dropped,
it's very hard to reconstruct it,
put it back on the spoon
and re-engage within that same experience.
But just because we come in with this superpower
out of the gate with our sense of deep absorption,
with interactive media,
we have the potential to be probably
one of the most powerful mediums for engaging storytelling.
So how does all this relate to God of War?
God of War starts with a big problem.
It's steeped in fantasy.
In essence, it says, I am unreality.
We have dragons, we have orcs, we have ogres, we have people that can lift mountains.
That's nothing we can relate to.
And as we were studying that sense of absorption, that sense of being sucked into the content,
we realized that our ability to relate to our environment as something that we recognize
is critical for us to actually be absorbed in the content.
So what we can do?
It's got a bit of a problem.
We tried to find another visual language that has the exact opposite problem that we do.
In this case, it wasn't actually a problem, it was a blessing.
We found the documentary style, actually.
kind of calculate the documentary style for ourselves.
The documentary style has.
the visual approach of telling us that it is speaking the truth.
We are used to seeing it tell things that are true,
that are real, that are relatable.
So in essence, we get a double boon.
We get a grounded experience,
which we're used to seeing from documentary footage,
but we also get a very character-relevant story
that is character-based,
which we're used to seeing documentary stylists use.
So what we're trying to create is a sense of believable fantasy.
A sense that, yes, what I'm watching around me might not be as relatable,
but I believe it.
So all of us here, I will take a wager that all of us here,
can hear with our eyes many different types of film language.
It's like growing up in a family that speaks a different language.
You might not be able to speak the language, but when you hear it...
you completely understand it.
So we're leveraging that fact.
What we're telling the viewer from a visual standpoint is,
hey, this is real.
We're calibrating their mindset to accept reality.
And once their shields are down,
those shields we discussed,
then we hit them with a fantasy.
And they take the fantasy in reference to reality.
One of my favorite case studies for this
was The Exorcist from 1973.
This movie didn't really use a documentary style,
used more of a family drama style.
We'll get back to the documentary shortly after this.
But this movie was so terrifying at the time,
even though it didn't use the amount of gore and shock
other movies did, just because it utilized
these kind of techniques.
So let's take a look at what they did.
Oh, mom, can't we get a horse?
No, we're in Washington.
We'll see when we get home, okay?
When can I have one?
We'll see, Regan. We'll see.
Hey, listen, I'm starting the rotations.
I want to get a personal one.
Oh, Regan, don't!
So really natural acting, very natural lighting.
We feel like this could be a part of our home videos, right?
We are calibrating the viewers to relate
to this as realistic content.
It is very relatable.
And the moment that brain is calibrated
to relatable realism, this happens.
The Holy Spirit.
By this sign of the Holy Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ,
who lives and reigns with the Father and the Holy Spirit.
Deviant!
Amen.
Path, Defender of the Christ.
We hit the viewer with horror.
So what we're doing is, we're taking horror in the context of family drama.
We're breaking down the defenses against horror first,
and then horrifying the audience.
This is brilliant.
So we're essentially taking the documentary form.
in God of War again, to bring in those absorption mechanics from that very raw documentary style
on top of that third-person camera to bring the relationship to the content from them
to me. That way, instead of sympathizing with the character, we're empathizing as the character.
So what was it in the documentary style we chose to latch onto from a visual standpoint?
Our camera never does anything that a human operator can't do.
And that was huge.
That was a huge boon to absorption.
Because we never hit the spoon with something that we are not used to seeing in real life.
We also shot handheld style, which is something that we're used to seeing with our smartphones
and our home videos.
These are things that are realistic.
This is stuff that we're used to seeing every day.
Our shot design from a lighting and environment design standpoint was very naturalistic.
We didn't go the whole soundstage Hollywood style where all the lights are painted and
everything looks fully beautiful and controlled.
The world looks as it would look if it was lit naturally and designed naturally.
The acting was moved away from the big Shakespearean drama kind of style and moved more towards
a relatable character story from the way it was acted.
All of those were great boons to absorption.
but we also did something on a sympathy side.
We staged all the action with a focus
on a subjective character experience.
And what does that mean?
Every scene, and this is mostly for the cinematic content,
the controlled content.
was owned and emotionally driven by a specific character
that we knew and designed ahead of time.
Every moment within the scene gave the viewer
somebody to sympathize with.
And again, that comes back from traditional cinematography
and how to stain shots so they can stay sympathetic.
We never let you go from a sympathetic standpoint.
You always had something to emotionally
or somebody to emotionally relate to.
Another detail we used on the camera side was to constantly keep the camera motivated to move.
And what does that mean?
As a camera operator, I can move the camera because me, as the camera operator, is interested to see something.
What that does is it brings sympathy from the viewer
to the camera operation, and it takes it away
from the people in front of the lens,
in front of the screen, which are your heroes.
So we did our best to never use unmotivated camera work.
Constantly motivate the camera by using motion,
tracking of motion in front of the scene,
following gazes and other little psychological nuances
that help the camera need or want to move into a direction.
Let's take a look at how a non-motivated camera looks.
And again, if you guys have nausea,
any of you, probably take a few seconds of this
and look away.
This is pretty intense.
This is from Cloverfield in 2008.
Oh, my god.
Wait up.
So even though this was technically a third person experience, the camera was so much
had a mind of its own that it was almost a first person experience.
In essence, that camera stole sympathy away from the heroes in front of the lens.
Let's take a look at what we did on God of War.
This is from our E3 2016 trailer.
And this is a action sequence, a combat sequence,
that are actually harder to design to stay motivated.
Let's see how these feel.
Ah!
Oh boy!
Wait!
Do it!
Ah!
Off the ice, now!
So the camera was moving around, zooming around, doing some crazy stuff,
but never in an unmotivated manner.
So if we did our job well, and I believe we did,
you would never notice that there's a camera operator
on set there.
You will just be focused on the action, which brings us back
to the idea of staging and blocking a scene.
If you do want to block a scene in a way
that the camera stays invisible, you
can't just shoot it or film it.
You have to think about how the action motivates your camera
movements and plan for that ahead of time.
So let's move a little bit more towards the absorbing side of gameplay,
the part where your player actually has their hands on the stick
and they're in control of the camera, the interactive side.
So here we have opposite problem.
We have a problem where this is a very absorbing time of the game experience,
but can be very lacking in sympathy.
So how do we elevate that sense of sympathy on the interactive sides?
What we try to do is pretty much put ourselves in the mindset of
shooting a scene and thinking as image makers and as visual storytellers,
what are the processes we are doing in order to make a certain moment
feel a certain way? Quantify them
and then proceduralize them on the interactive camera.
So in essence, instead of having a narrative-driven camera,
we're having a camera-driven narrative.
So it's all about asking yourself questions
of what is it in the world that I can use to latch onto
in order to drive what in my camera?
Is the weather gonna make my camera shake more?
If I look at that deer,
are they gonna look back and run away?
What is it that I can do to drive it?
And what we found is there are so many things you can do
that as you start piling them onto the camera,
it starts distracting from the game experience,
it starts introducing chaos.
So the trick was, how do we bring sympathy
into this interactive moment in the game,
but still maintain order and not introduce chaos?
So on the bottom here, you can see a pretty traditional
narrative style game and how it flows.
Starts with the opening cinematic.
goes into some gameplay, goes back into a cinematic either at the end of the level or
when you achieved some form of achievement, back into gameplay over and over until you
are likely going to get a big cinematic for ending the game.
What we try to do is take the sympathetic parts of the game,
which are the cinematics, and make them more absorbing.
And then take the absorbing parts of the video game
and make them more cinematic, more sympathetic.
And then we did something completely crazy.
We never cut the camera.
Not cutting the camera was what allowed us to maintain a seamless transition from an
emotional standpoint, from our sympathetic moments to our absorbing moments, and maintain
that critical mass in order to fully achieve that sense of empathetic immersion throughout
the entire game experience.
Cuts are very jarring.
They're like a mental pop.
And while we do blink in our day-to-day lives,
blinking doesn't teleport us.
So we can't relate to cutting.
The moment we start cutting,
we start experiencing things more from our mind's eye,
more from a distance
than from the actual personal experience.
So in essence, we are losing absorption.
And if we lose absorption,
we can't combine that with sympathy, and we lose the eye.
So hey, let's not cut, right?
No big deal.
That's pretty tough.
As visual storytellers, we are used to having
certain tools in our back pocket to tell our visual story.
And as we started experimenting with not cutting,
we found that it's like writing a novel
without using punctuation or nouns.
You can't create establishing shots,
you can't cut to reactions, you can't cut to inserts.
You can't use editing for pacing.
You can't use editing for clarity.
You can't cut in and out of your cinematics.
You can't cut between your prime lenses
to get different types of emotions from your lensing.
So how do we keep the content not only dynamic,
but emotionally engaging?
The reason I bolded cut to reaction,
the concept of the A-B cut.
cutting from one person to another, is the bread and butter
of sympathetic storytelling from a visual standpoint.
Without that mechanic, again, we're left only with absorption.
And with absorption alone, we can't have empathetic immersion.
So, why is this mechanic so important
from an emotional standpoint in order to maintain sympathy?
If you look at that little graph on the bottom left there...
and see that line of action between these two people talking,
and for a moment think of this line of action as a line of sympathy.
If I'm 90 degrees to the line of sympathy,
my shot would be very detached and very objective.
It will tell me no emotional story, it will just deliver the content you are looking at.
This is now happening.
I don't want to tell you how you feel about it.
That's a very flat, emotionally relevant delivery.
It's not going to give us that sense of sympathy
we need for empathetic immersion.
As I start dialing that camera towards the line of sympathy,
I start raising my sympathy towards the characters.
So the easiest thing to do is just dial two cameras
to that highest point of sympathy
and cut between them over a dialogue,
which would be the cleanest way
to create a sympathetic delivery.
But we don't cut.
So let's look at this example.
This is a run of the mail script we had to break down.
It's just an opening of one of the sequences in God of War.
In this moment, Kratos' son was ill.
He had to leave his son with Freya, the witch in the woods,
and go get the thing that heals him.
He brings it back.
Freya thanks him for it, does something with it.
He goes to his kid to check his temperature.
Freya talks to him.
He talks to Freya.
There's a whole bunch of back and forth AB dialogue
with three characters, one of them being mute.
So let's take a look at how that ended up being solved.
You have it.
Back of your hand.
I can break the fever, but to heal...
He must know the truth of what he is.
So hopefully you guys felt that that was completely seamless and looked very effortless.
If not, then I'm not going to be happy right now.
Let's take a look at what we actually had to do to make this work.
You have it.
So we push in to a two-opening shot.
We use Freya's screen left motion to motivate the camera to move to give her her moment to establish her having business with this item.
Then we use her screen right motion to reveal a three shot providing empathy between Kratos and his son.
Now we're both facing camera, we can have a dialogue.
We give her motivation to leave her spot,
using her screen left motion with a zoom
to give her her line,
having her screen right reveal Kratos
to give his bee delivery.
And we had over three and a half hours
of this kind of content.
So, good times.
Ha ha.
Thank you.
Another challenge we had to encounter with this no-cut camera is something that is really
quintessential to the God of War franchise, and that giant sense of scale.
Critters has always fought these giant mountain-sized creatures and monsters, and the easiest way
to make a hero feel small is to get them very far away from the camera, make them very little,
next to something very, very large.
How do we get our hero away from the camera?
And if we actually manage to do that, how do we bring him back to the camera without
making it look like we're chasing after him and completely give the sympathy back to the
camera operator? So this is a talk in itself. If you guys want to check out how we did it,
pick up the game. I'm sure you guys can find those spots and see how we did it. On a technical
standpoint, we had to blend between our interactive moments and our non-interactive
moments back into our interactive moments.
having needing to do that right was critical
to get that seamless experience to happen
because if those transitions were jarring,
we would knock the spoon and we'd lose the egg.
So we had to blend navigation,
we had to blend animation, camera animation,
in and out of combat, and that was quintessential
to keeping that egg on a spoon.
That was a nightmare in itself.
So how do we tackle this beast?
We use a lot of different techniques.
I'm gonna be focusing on a few today.
How we treated zooming, how we treated visual defects,
how we treated handheld, previs,
and then how we brought it all together on set
working with the actors.
So zooming.
As we were studying some reference content,
trying to figure out how we're gonna approach this,
we noticed that people don't really zoom anymore.
They cut between prime lenses.
They cut for drama.
We had to actually go back to the drawing board and figure out what psychologically
happens in a viewer when they witness a zoom.
What kind of zoom promotes what kind of emotion?
And not only that, how to blend our zooms into the content because, again, we don't
want to draw attention to the camera operation, so the zooms have to be completely invisible.
What we ended up doing is breaking zooms into two utilities.
Zooming for utility, meaning I have to go from one place to another, maybe a zoom will
help me. And two, zooming for emotional impact and emotional content. So let's take an example
for a zoom for utility here. This is going back to our 2016 demo. We already watched
the scene. You guys probably didn't notice that we had a pretty crazy zoom here. Let's
take a quick look.
Oh boy.
Oh, wait!
I hope he didn't notice I had a big zoom in here.
Um, what we did here,
we used a really wide 24mm lens
to exasperate that big impact
when Kratos slams that troll into the ice.
To get that drama, we need it from a wide-angle lens.
But then we need it to be 20 feet behind action
within probably a matter of a second and a half
to get over the kid's shoulder when he draws the arrow.
So what we did, we dollied the camera back
as we were zooming in, which essentially maintained Kratos
on screen in the same size he was,
making you feel like there's no camera movement,
while we're actually trucking the camera 20 feet back.
Let's take a look at that again in slow motion.
Look at how that environment in the background compresses
as the camera zooms.
We're 20 feet behind him.
Now let's look at an emotional content zoom.
In this scene, Kratos starts off his, you know,
traditional, standard, mean, kind of tough dad.
Very impersonal shot, 24 millimeter wide.
And very quickly after that, we transition to Kratos
having one of probably the only two intimate moments
he has within the game, and that's gathering the ashes
of his wife that he just cremated.
We ended up pushing all the way to 120 millimeters
to get that sense of intimacy and compressed internal space.
This is actually the biggest zoom range we did in the game.
What we also noticed is in order to hide a zoom,
but still make it emotionally impactful,
we can kinda slap it on some motion
that the character does,
utilizing the motion to convey the zoom.
And if it's designed well,
that motion also conveys what the character
is emotionally going through.
In this case, it's a walk from.
his son after he dismisses his son to walking towards his wife's cremation site.
Let's take a look at how that looks.
And we're at 120 millimeters.
And then, of course, we have to find our way back, right?
But that's a different story.
So approach to visual defects.
We actually worked pretty hard to make our visuals look worse.
The whole thing came from the problem of the uncanny valley.
And for those of you who are not familiar with the uncanny valley,
The traditional thought would say that if something looks better,
then it looks more believable.
Kind of like in a linear manner, the more believable, the more relatable.
What actually happens is when something becomes very close to realistic,
our psyche starts judging it in a very harsh manner.
It looks for realism, and it finds all the defects.
There is a giant dip in believability just before you hit photorealism.
And because of the power of our game engine these days
and our amazing tech render teams
and our amazing art teams,
we fell right in the middle of the uncanny valley.
So what we try to do is go back to the documentary style
and find things that we relate to as realistic footage
and slap on top of the image to try to at least,
if not completely skip over the uncanny valley,
kind of make it less, more shallow, less deep.
So we added film grain, we added handheld,
we added crap hitting your lens all over the place,
lens flare, chromatic aberration, we slipped on focus.
All these things that if you were a filmmaker
shooting live action, you would try at all costs to avoid.
But what it did is again spike our brains and calibrate them
toward a sense of realism and helped us skip over the
uncanny valley and relate to the footage without pushing
back against it and then having a giant dip in
absorption.
A quick note on that, having a very strong understanding on
how lenses, real world lenses work, how film backs work, how
photo sensors work.
how images actually get created in what fashion
allowed us to do this in a very realistic manner,
not just by slapping some elements on the lens
and on the screen in our case,
and hoping to achieve a sense of realism.
So our approach to handheld,
that was a big, big boon for us
in terms of getting that raw absorption.
I've heard a lot of people approach handheld
as this kind of programmatic wobble on the screen,
and nothing can be further from the truth.
Each handheld has its own style.
Not all handhelds are created equal.
Sometimes blends of handhelds are needed
in order to create a certain emotion
and drive a certain sense.
we actually went onto the mocap stage and shot our handhelds.
On the bottom left here, you can see me in a mocap stage,
well, the footage generated by me on a mocap stage,
holding the camera and trying to keep it steady.
On the far right, you can see me on a treadmill,
jogging in a mocap studio, trying to keep my camera steady.
to really get your handhelds to feel correct
and really help bridge things like the uncanny valley
or help calibrate the viewers into a documentary style.
You have to treat them with the same amount
of care and seriousness that you treat
your character animations.
What we did find is that handheld is incredibly nauseating.
And as somebody who for the first six months
of his work on God of War had Dramamine on his desk,
I was very passionate about this.
We had to figure out how to take our handheld wholesale
and wrap it in some form of UI that allows the viewer
to either calibrate it up or down to match
their personal user experience, while still maintaining
that emotional need that handheld provides
from a documentary standpoint.
What we also found is in order to diminish the nausea and diminish the motion a little bit,
thinking of handheld from a rotational and translational standpoint separately was incredibly critical.
The rotations controlled the movement of the world and how it bops up and down and around us,
while the translations controlled the parallax of the foreground.
Separating those two allowed us to massage the data,
maintain it looking realistic,
but lower its sense of nausea.
So on the far left, we can see the raw jog motion
that we shot on stage.
On the center, you can see us blending it down a little bit
with a combination of rotation and translation.
And on the far right, you can see that actual data
being applied to a jog in the game.
What you'll also notice is that movement on the screen
has a major factor to diminishing
your perception of handheld.
So that's something you have to account for
when you're blending in your handheld data.
So back to this design of the no cuts.
Previs was critical.
We previs-ed, revised it, previs-ed again.
The idea is to make all your mistakes
where it's fast and where it's cheap.
Don't go on set and try to make your mistakes there.
And also, you don't have to use super high-end methods
of previs, like hand-key previs in 3D or rough mocap.
Find the right element and style of previs
you need in order to deliver what
the shot needs to look like.
Find your designs.
Find your blocking.
Find your staging.
Find it quickly, and quickly enough
for you to be able to iterate on it
within the production timelines.
And again, if you don't have previs, do not go on set.
We did try that.
It wasn't pretty.
So let's take a look at a previous example.
This was shot with a DSLR using a lens
that roughly represented the focal lengths
we were wanting for that specific scene.
We shot this with our cinematic animation crew,
Erica Pinto, Umberto Bossi, and Avieni.
And I found that animators are great to work with,
and they have a lot of fun doing it.
I do as well.
Let's take a look at how the scene looked.
Your bow!
Right!
I'm glad you're okay.
So again, working with your teammates is awesome.
We had a lot of fun shooting this scene.
We slapped it together, put it into After Effects
just to get some lighting cues, some audio cues,
just to find the mood of the scene.
But we found exactly what we needed to do
to make the scene work.
We found the blocking, the staging,
where to hide the zooms, how to stage the scene
to properly emotionally deliver.
So now let's see how it actually looked like in the game.
Shoot.
What was that?
The ball.
So, virtually identical, which is great.
It means that we know what we're doing on set,
we know how to design this ballet between the camera and the actors,
what the actors need to be doing, what the camera needs to be doing,
when, at what pacing, and we don't have to figure all that out on set,
which makes shooting really, really, really comfortable.
One thing to keep in mind, though, about, well, some things to keep in mind about Previs,
If possible, at least for me, refrain from pre-vising in a three-dimensional software.
That idea of needing to use a skill set in order to explore a shot already takes you
one step away from cleanly exploring your concepts.
If you can, explore all your scenes in your mind, draw them down in quick thumbnails,
and then only go into the 3D software where
you're trying to figure out if what you visualized
actually works.
I find I get much better and much more interesting results.
Just because of the realism of game production,
we don't always have the environments
that we're going to shoot in ready when we need to shoot.
So by all means, if you can, try avoiding that temptation
of shooting generic.
And what does generic mean?
Oh, we'll just shoot or design or animate
based on our characters,
based on where the camera's gonna go,
then we're just gonna take that whole thing
and just plop it into an environment,
it's gonna look great.
It won't.
You have to think about how the environment
is gonna look like in your shot.
You have to think about what your character's
gonna be touching, where they're gonna be sitting.
Without that level of interaction with your environment,
your scenes are gonna be flat
and you're gonna lose a sense of absorption
and you will not be able to create empathetic immersion.
So,
Find a good cadence with your level designers
and your concept artists and your level artists
and see if you can find a way to roughly thumb out
areas that will give you what you need in order
to drive your scenes forward without pushing
the production timeline beyond what it can go.
The bottom line is, if you really bust your butt
and work like crazy and it looks like you've done nothing
and things look completely natural, you're onto something.
So how to take this whole thing and work with the actors.
Rehearsal was key for us.
Actors already have a lot on their minds.
They have to find the character,
they have to memorize their lines,
especially in a one-er because in a one-er,
they have to memorize all their lines for the scene.
It's not per cut and not per shot.
So if they now have to memorize the choreography
of what they need to be doing on top of their lines
and trying to perform,
you're not gonna get a good performance out of them.
So incorporating that rehearsal and trying to get them to incorporate the ballet
was very comfortable for them to then take that information on set and focus on acting.
As the shot designer, you have to always keep in mind
that you want to give your actors the freedom to perform and surprise you on set.
You don't want to tie their hands so tight that you tell them exactly what to do and when,
or you don't want to tell them what to do.
why you're bringing them in in the first place.
So it's always a matter of finding that balance,
designing things in a way that will be evocative,
but letting your actors do what they are there to do.
Having the camera itself on set with the actors
is also a huge bonus.
Actors kind of have a broken psychological approach
to how they look at the set around them.
They have one side looking at their actors,
their friend actors, working with directors
and working with the actual emotional content,
but they always have a mind on where the camera is.
It allows them to dial in the performance.
Is this gonna be a facial performance?
Is this gonna be a full body performance?
What am I emoting with?
Is it my voice?
Is it my full body?
Without that, you're just gonna get performances
that constantly feel like they're stage performances,
and that's not gonna squeeze out the kind of drama
you can get from what the actors can do.
What we did find though is that tight close-up scenes,
which are supposed to be the most dramatic ones,
and they are, are the trickiest ones.
Because...
you have to use the actor's motion
in order to motivate the camera to move
and keep it looking seamless.
So we have to dictate to the actors
a lot more of what to do within their performance.
And thankful we had really understanding actors
that totally understood the challenge,
so they were totally game to do this.
But again, it's a matter of finding that balance.
Let's take a look at a close-up scene
and how those look.
This weapon, any weapon, comes from here.
But only when tempered by this.
By the discipline, the self-control of the one who wields it.
That is where the true strength of a warrior lies.
You must never forget that.
So every head bob, head nod, hand gesture,
posture and positioning was explicitly designed
in the scene just because the scene was so tight.
And again, that was much more challenging
in order to create that balance
and allow our performers to perform.
So some key takeaways from this process,
from this attempt, and hopefully successful attempt,
to create a really engaging
and empathetic continuous experience.
From a level design and art standpoint,
approaching your designs like Disneyland design
is incredibly helpful.
Use your environments to hide and reveal content
that has emotional impact to your storyline.
Don't just lay things out in a way that they are
open for exploration and game content.
Think of the story they deliver.
From a lighting standpoint, we need to start looking beyond the idea of lighting for clarity,
lighting for guidance, or lighting for beauty.
But we actually have to think of lighting as a tool to tell an emotional story.
And again, that goes back to traditional cinematography.
From a writing standpoint, the idea of taking your writers and putting them somewhere and
taking your game designers and putting them somewhere else and at the end combining everything
together and everything's going to be great.
We've got to get past that.
Your writers need to work in lockstep
with your game designers and your level designers
and your Disney designs in order to go
beyond the idea of just designing for plot points,
but for character arcs, for how things actually
relate to each other from a gameplay and narrative
standpoint.
From an animation point of view, and this
is mostly from the cinematic animation side,
we have over 100 years of filmmaking
to draw from and understand how.
they took visual content to drive emotional delivery.
While not all these techniques are 100% applicable to game design,
each of them has some level of wisdom that we can utilize
and help to elevate our emotional content through our game cinematography.
We have to bring in those dedicated disciplines in our teams.
We have to bring in that training.
If you want to hear a little bit more about this,
you should go to Erica Pinto's talk tomorrow.
She will be discussing these kinds of issues
more from the animation side, cinematic animation.
She's our cinematic animation lead.
From a team alignment standpoint,
if you do want to hit a goal as crazy
as not cutting a camera,
you have to think of the impact it has
for every single one of the teams
that are going to be engaged within this challenge.
You have to get buy-in from each one of these teams early,
and you have to design pipelines that will allow you
to track data between all of these teams,
not just internally within one team on its own.
And again, going back to Previs,
having a very clear visual target
that helps everybody moving in the same direction
is gonna be critical.
I'm incredibly proud of what we did in God of War.
I really feel like we pushed some very heavy envelopes.
But this kind of media can go far, far beyond the idea of
empathetic immersion.
We have to really grab the kind of tech that's at our
doorstep.
We're going to be able to render photorealism in the
very near future.
We have to challenge the norms and evolve our media.
We truly have the capability of being one of the most emotionally engaging modes of emotional delivery.
We have both the means and the tools to be a new type of art form.
Thank you.
How you doing?
Great talk.
A lot of great information there.
I just had a quick question.
During production, did you develop any specific hardware
to help you with this type of these movements?
I know in behind the scenes stuff,
I've seen the hand-held camera you're using.
But if there was any specifics that you were able to share,
I'd be curious.
Yeah, absolutely. So the concept of virtual cinematography has been out for a while.
We just explored with different types of rigs on virtual cameras on how to comfortably get the kind of visual data we wanted from holding a system.
And then figure out how to take that and utilize it in our animation pipeline.
I would say we took about probably a couple of months to dial that in.
But honestly, it's just like designing any other camera rig.
It's just instead of recording an image, you're recording motion.
Cool.
Thank you.
Yeah, no worries.
Hi.
I'm curious on how different your techniques were,
or similar, for scenes that were during interactive moments
in the game.
Because I recall there was one scene in particular
in Helheim when they were climbing past Baldur,
and he was giving a monologue.
That stuck out to me, and it was during an interactive moment.
So I was wondering if the techniques you use are similar.
Right.
Those techniques are actually very different.
Those moments are probably the hardest to design
because you want to both control the image
and allow the viewer the sense of exploration.
So that goes back into level design.
We designed the environment in a way that, by exploring it,
we know where you're going to be looking.
And we designed it in a way that it's going to show and hide
based on some measured cadence,
the moments we wanted to show from the actual visual story.
Thank you.
Hello.
I actually wanted to know about the previous work
you did for the dragon fighting scene.
I wanted to know how that was done.
Did you create some sort of a 3D model for that?
How did you do it?
Which scene?
The dragon fighting scene.
Oh, the dragon fighting scene.
Actually, that was done heavily by our gameplay animators.
Those scenes are driven very heavily by combat design.
Once the beats of the scene are kind of locked down,
that's when my team comes in and polishes up the visuals
to make sure they speak within the same visual language.
But again, those are heavily driven by level design
and combat to make sure that the gameplay is fun
and then that it also delivers the right visual story.
Okay, thank you.
Hey.
Did you at one point make some tests or something to check if the one take thing is really the right approach?
Did you try to shoot some scenes with cuts or did you like, fuck it?
Right. I mean, man, I wish I could.
The mandate to not cut actually came from Corey, our game director.
He didn't tell us how to do it, he just told us, just do it.
So I could never just go, hey, you know what, screw this, I'm just going to start cutting again.
I can tell you there were many times I very much wanted to.
But all the tests we did were always towards making sure that the runner is going to work.
Hi.
Whoops, that's quite difficult.
First of all, thank you so much
for making such a beautiful game.
I have a question about analytic
and the empathy and emotional connection to the game.
So were you able to analyze whether the users
or gamers having the emotional connection
that you expected?
So based on the scenario you expected,
oh, they are gonna cry at this point.
Were you able to analyze based on analytics?
Right. So we didn't have quantified analytics for the emotional side. That's something that I
believe we're going to be pushing a little bit more into. But we did use our team as guinea
pigs.
So we try to work when we did push a scene toward a level of completion in some level
of isolation so we have enough people to be able to view it and gauge their engagement.
And sometimes we did get feedback that it's not impactful enough.
And it was up to us and the experience we bring in to figure out how to fix that.
Thank you.
All right.
So you mentioned early on that you're,
you called it a theory of how you can blend
the immersion in the game and empathy
to create something special for players.
I was curious if there was a moment where you felt
like that theory was proved in the development cycle
for you, whether it was a certain scene
or a certain challenge your team was going through,
anything like that.
Right.
Honestly, it's really hard to quantify.
It's easier to find when it breaks than when it works, as
weird as that may sound.
A good example would be the moment, again, our E3 trailer
was when we put our things out there to see if they work.
Within the E3 trailer, there was a moment where the sun
kills a deer.
And that was a moment that was both immersive and sympathetic.
And we wanted to see if it brought people to tears.
And thankfully, it did.
So for me, that was one of the moments
where I knew that we're probably onto something.
We can make this work.
Yeah.
You needed an audience test.
Yes.
That's always the case.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
OK.
Hi.
I was just wondering, since you said that there's a few times that you really wanted to cut,
what was like a really difficult moment for you to follow this rule?
Oh, if I can make, oh man.
Like the most difficult, if nothing else.
I don't think, I can think of the most difficult.
When it's difficult, it's just difficult.
The scene I showed you as an example, that opening scene,
opening moment for the scene where Freya uses the heart to heal the son.
That was so incredibly difficult and that was just the beginning of the scene.
We even came up with ideas on how to cut.
Of course we never did it.
But I would say that would be a good example.
I was curious, just so much of the feel and flow of the game is based around this camera work,
but you said a lot of the, or most of the camera work came from the mocap sessions.
In traditional game development, mocap doesn't usually get integrated until a lot later on,
so I was wondering, during development, I imagine there was large areas that didn't have this data yet.
Did it make it difficult to test and play the game and see if it was feeling good
if you didn't have a lot of this camera stuff coming in until later?
Absolutely. So again, that goes back to, I touched upon that a little briefly.
We did everything we could to get something from the environment artist or level designers
or any other team that has to do with the world building
to give us context of what it is we're going to be shooting in.
And then we use that in our previs.
So we try to find the best way we could based on what we had at hand.
to figure out how the scene is going to feel.
And then it was up to us to make sure we maintain
that vision throughout the entire production.
When the environments come in,
when the final characters come in,
but we knew how it was gonna look way beforehand,
if that answers your question.
It mostly does. I was more curious like how for the rest of the team who was waiting to see your stuff in the game
I guess like I was affecting them having it being probably not there
Especially if your previs was not done in 3d software
So you couldn't just stick the previs into the game, right?
Having said that there are solutions for that as well, but it was mostly verbal communication for for God of War
It was about just staying very tight within the teams
Thanks
I hate
A quick question on, so one of the big downsides of a one-er is the, is basically the shoe
leather that you have to kind of fill between.
Were you intimate in conversations with the writing team and the production design team
when you're blocking out scenes to kind of cut the fat between moments to make the scenes
not feel as drawn out?
Right. It was definitely a challenge in the beginning. Our writers never wrote for
Wunners, but as we were starting to do back and forth very early on in production, they
found their way to find that cadence by knowing how I approached their content. So as
production picked up, it was mostly about, hey, maybe we can take that line and move it
down because then I can motivate the camera better. But other than that, it was all
about finding business for the character.
in order to fill in these moments and maintain pacing.
And that's when blocking really, really was critical.
Hi, did you create any 2D animatics, like with storyboards,
or did you mainly go straight to live action style?
So we did try.
What we did find is because there is so much
camera movement and such complex camera movement
to do a runner,
It is, I wouldn't say virtually impossible,
but incredibly difficult to portray that in 2D.
It was really, really critical for us
to find the exact moments and compositions
where people end up in real world space.
And we found that if the storyboard artist was too loose,
they might paint us into corners we can't actually do.
Because we can't just use shot to shot to shot.
So we tried it and it turned out to be more time consuming than any other previous option we had.
We ended up not doing it.
talk about three mediums. First, textbooks or like novels where player feels the
immersion very deeply because all of there is a imagination of a player but
player or reader can't really control the antagonist or protagonist, right? So
there it kind of breaks the immersion or like there is some desire to be left there.
for games where player actually controls the person they are playing,
but now the creator also gets a chance to represent the scene how they want to be presented,
which we have seen with God of War and many other awesome games.
So now here there is an immersion as well as control both from the player.
And now, upcoming technology which is going towards VR and virtual reality,
you are feeling more and more immersive in virtual world,
but now creator lose the control over the camera and how the camera actually works.
is authored there.
Do you think it would affect largely on immersion?
Because it kind of feels like for a long time,
video games as a medium of entertainment
is going to be on a pinnacle of giving highest immersion
and highest connection compared to this other two.
So what are your thoughts on it?
So to understand your question, you want to see how videos might move forward to push
immersion?
Uh-huh.
Especially talking about virtual reality, where you actually lose the control over camera.
Right.
So virtual reality is a pretty separate topic.
Yeah.
Virtual reality is not only a first-person experience, but it is your experience.
I don't think that a controlled experience, like traditional cinematics, would ever work
in VR.
Also, we can't change the camera aspect in VR
because it has to represent how we actually view the world
with our own eyeballs.
So our thought of VR as cinematography is very different,
and that goes a little bit more towards
what I was talking about in terms of a camera-driven
narrative, based on where the player is
and what the player is looking at,
we can bring the world to life based on their choices.
But that's going to be a little different than traditional cinematography,
where we do control lensing and do control things that if you controlled in VR,
you will really disorient the player.
Yep, makes sense.
Hiya.
So, last question?
I was wondering what was the sign-off process on this project,
and how much did you have to reshoot?
in this project.
How much did we need to reshoot?
Yeah, and what was the sign-off process?
So we pretty much showed our previs to the directors.
They got to sign off.
The moment we got sign-off from the previs,
we just did our best to get the previs shot properly on set.
And at that point, there was merely any reshoot.
Thank you.
Awesome, thank you guys.