Just to start, I'm going to be doing a Chicory post-mortem.
We're going to be talking about sort of my approach to the marketing and public relations
campaign that we ran throughout sort of Chicory's development and then through its launch.
And to start, I'm going to tell you, one, this is Chicory.
If you're not familiar with it, I can totally recommend it.
One, we published it, but two, it's awesome.
And other people thought it was awesome, too.
If you have any questions about how we manage that save file
system, I'll tell you about it over drinks.
It was quite a task.
When you can paint everything in an entire game,
there's problems sometimes.
So first off, my name is Becca Saltzman.
I am the CEO and co-founder of Finji.
We are both an independent development studio
and a sort of micro-indie publisher.
This is my information.
I don't close my DMs on Twitter, so feel free to reach out.
And that's our website.
And if you need to email me, it's hello at finji.co.
If you wanna send me a pitch, it's pitch at finji.co.
I run the studio with my husband and partner.
His name is Adam Saltzman.
He sort of runs the creative side of our studio,
so our internal development team.
We are based in Grand Rapids, Michigan,
which is probably a weird place for a game studio.
We kind of love it.
Some of our past games aside from Chicory,
we launch a lot of games, it feels like.
Some of them include Cannibalt, which
is sort of the old Endless Runner.
My husband is the designer on that.
We also launched Overland, which was an Apple Arcade launch
title back in 2019.
And then we've published games like Chicory, Colorful Tale,
Night in the Woods.
Last week, we launched Tunic, which
I'm a little tired.
It's, yeah, it's pretty cool.
It's been like eight days and it's been awesome.
And we also have published Wilmot's Warehouse
and several other like mobile titles,
sort of legacy mobile titles.
Our studio itself is actually pretty small.
I'm giving you this information so you have context
for the type of marketing and PR talk
that we're talking about today.
I am not a big studio.
So these are,
sort of skills that we use when we work on a very small team.
So the size of my studio does matter.
There are about 16 of us sort of across internal development and publishing.
And they're on sort of biz dev, marketing, community management, and
launch operation staff.
There are about four of us, and I'm one of those four.
We have three QA staff and a little over eight or nine development staff.
We also work with a PR and marketing firm in Europe, and this is actually brand new as of 2021 because our
It just got too busy. There weren't quite enough hands to handle our campaigns anymore
And they have been helping us roll out our PR and marketing campaigns, and they embed directly within our studio
And they've been helping with all of our launches so Chicory, Tunic, and our upcoming launches
I run the biz side of Fingy.
I'm also a core creative team member on the community and marketing initiatives that we
produce.
And I'm also a member of the creative team on our internal development projects, mostly
in the narrative and narrative design realm.
So that's just a little bit about me and where I come from.
I approach marketing and PR as a marketing and PR professional.
I worked in media relations before.
games in a different life. I was not always in running Fingy. I had a career before games,
and that career was in media relations. So I'm now going to tell you a little bit about our campaign.
On March 19th,
2020, that date probably looks kind of familiar, because on March 13th my kids didn't go back to school anymore.
Everything about the way that we launched games changed. All of my plans got erased.
We came home from PAX East in 2020 and we're like, okay, we're not going anywhere anymore.
We had this Excel document that we had been using for years for our marketing meetings,
and we had to add a tab that was just, oh god, what can we do now? How are we going to launch
this game? Chicory's coming up on content complete. How are we going to tell anybody about this?
I'm a bit of a doomsday person. I was pre-med in a former life as well, so when I was looking at
the epidemiology and reading the reports, I was just like, oh no, we're not going anywhere.
So I started panicking and started trying to come up with like 300 different backup plans.
In our meeting we put together this tab and we just started like
brainstorming if we're having to launch this game from home, we can't go talk to people anymore.
How do we do that? And how do we do that with our staff of three?
And our new marketing firm in Europe who has never launched a game with us before.
So I'm going to step back a little bit so you sort of understand where we started.
We picked up Chicory after the Kickstarter campaign.
So Greg and his team actually launched this in August of 2019.
We mentored Greg a little bit with Wandersong.
So after the Kickstarter campaign, we approached him.
We're like, hey, do you want to work with us?
This would be really fun to do together.
We've always wanted to do a game together.
So we announced our partnership in February of 2020,
which was right before PAX East, which was the next month.
After that, everything locked down.
We couldn't see each other anymore.
And we had to move over into more of an online sort of PR and marketing beat calendar indefinitely.
We did the June 2020 Summer Demo Fest.
We did Indie Arena Online, which we're going to talk a little bit about later.
We also did, in that time, I negotiated our PS5 partnership, and we announced that in February of 2021.
I'm going to tell you about when Chickory was feature complete.
Put a big O X on that.
We were feature complete with the game in August,
the very end of August of 2020.
We didn't launch until June 2021.
This is an indie title where usually it's like we launch
and we're like hitting the Steam Go button
like 30 seconds later.
We were feature complete.
Like, I mean, gosh.
10 months in advance. You're wondering, what the hell did you do for those 10 months?
And what we did was a massive PR campaign. Because we had sort of all this extra
game development time, we started doing more things online. We found a localization budget
to make the game a more worldwide launch.
And a lot of this was due to the fact that we were sort of trapped.
We couldn't go out and talk to people. We had to figure out how to get a bigger audience from home.
We also had to port the game, it was built in GameMaker,
to PS4 and PS5.
And since we were a launch title, we had to build in a bunch more engineering time
throughout the process.
So back to the timeline real quick.
Announced our PS5 announcement in February 2021.
We announced a timeline exactly a month later,
and we knew that these were going to be separated.
We knew that these were going to be a month apart, even when
I did that February announce.
We put the game in Ludonarikon, and there's
reasons for that, which we'll explain.
I didn't announce a launch date until May 27,
which was two weeks before launch.
People look at that and they're like, you're crazy.
What were you doing?
All of this was very intentional.
There was kind of no, there were a lot of other options,
but there were no better options for this particular title
and the state of the world at this time.
So, we launched the title on June 10th, 2020,
which historically everyone knows that's E3 week.
That's also kind of a,
probably terrifying.
Looking back now, I'm like, why would I do that?
Launching during E3 is terrifying,
especially when you're a black and white game where
you color everything, and it's very cartoony.
But we worked really hard to have some partnerships
to make that work.
So from March, when we announced, until May,
we were actually in and out of the certification process.
If you've worked on new hardware before,
that is kind of a dicey.
time, especially being the, as far as we know, the very first game maker game to come out on a PS5.
Our schedule had to be kind of loose. We had to be able to absorb
any engineering unknowns when we started our porting process.
So, the reason why we felt confident
for being able to pull off sort of the two weeks notice of a game kind of before their
launch date is because of all of the timeline, sort of leading up to this point.
Now, we're going to step even farther back.
Who is the team?
Why did it matter?
And this is a piece of the marketing plan from the very beginning.
The Wandersong team included Greg Lobanoff, who's the lead designer on the project.
We had several past launches between all of the team members.
They included Wandersong, Celeste, Guild Wars 2, Night in the Woods, Untitled Goose Game, and Eichenfell.
Those are just from the team that worked on Chicory.
So if you're looking at like,
why does it have a 92 Metacritic?
Those are the games these designers worked on.
And this little, this super team of mostly Canadians
came together and built this during a pandemic.
We also had three experienced devs
that were leading the new devs on that team.
Lena, Greg, and M. Halberstadt.
are responsible for some of the best indie titles that have come out in the last several years,
and were able to sort of teach and mentor both Alexis and Madeline through the process.
The game also had clear design goals. They knew what they were making,
they knew what they were relying on, and
They didn't spend a lot of time sort of arguing about the end goals of the sort of the design
of the game.
They knew exactly what they were sort of racing towards, which is like a really good position
to be in.
But you have to acknowledge that when you look at a team, you have to look at a team
holistically.
If you don't have a past like that, you're going to have to make up for it so that like
when you put together your pros and cons in front of you of how to market a game.
If you don't have it, it's a con.
Nobody knows who you are.
How do we bridge that gap?
In our case, we had that so we could build off of it,
which is why their Kickstarter.
already had a leg up. Greg loves Kickstarter. He loves audience building. He loves interacting
on the internet. He's one of the few devs who will schedule out tweets for months just
to make sure that he has engagement and he doesn't forget.
Chikri was Kickstarted. It had, sorry, I have to read this number, 2,342 backers. Their
budget was actually pretty small.
50,000 or 60,000 to complete the campaign.
And they ended up with like 87,000.
What they were able to do with this and.
There are a lot of other ways to do this,
but this is one of the many ways to do it,
and Night in the Woods did this exact same thing,
is you are building sort of your very first audience.
In this case, the team already had their first audience
because they had past fans.
With their Kickstarter, they were able
to create their second audience.
And these are players who are excited,
who are seeing this thing for the first time,
and now they're going to have access to
all of these newsletters if you're going to do a Kickstarter properly.
With especially in the marketing,
you're always looking for a way to.
Create levels of audience.
Who are your initial fans?
How are you building a second set of initial fans?
Who is your third set of initial fans?
And you can do this in a multitude of ways.
If this were normal times, it would be like third set
audience would be who you're developing
or who you're meeting at PAX.
And those people at PAX who you're striking up
relationships with, they're going out and bringing
other people over to your PAX booth to create your.
your in-person, real-life audience, and they're going to go out and continue to talk to more
people.
In this case, the Kickstarter, thank goodness, because we didn't know about the pandemic
at this point, this was their second-level audience.
Sorry, dry mouth.
With Kickstarter, you have this opportunity
to have this early audience gathering, the early audience
communication.
And the thing that you're developing at this point
is a term that I find really interesting.
It's one that we rely on internally to Fingy.
We call this a maven.
It's like sort of an old sort of media PR cultural term.
And if you sort of follow pop culture or something,
these are the people who are,
they're kind of trendsetters,
but they're even in front of trendsetters.
They are, it's a sort of media term
for early adopters of things.
They are going to be the people who don't just adopt it,
but they're going to evangelize it as well.
Kickstarter backers are people who will evangelize
a project for a very long time.
It's been a useful word to think of for our games just across the board.
It's a word that I've been using for almost 20 years,
because they generally will end up being long-term fans of your company.
Early adopters of Greg's work or even like pre-Wandersong fans
who came from his early, early work when he was sort of late teens, early twenties,
came into Wandersong.
came into Chicory and are probably going to follow him
into his next project.
And they will continue to talk about this.
They will see a Kickstarter and they
will send it to other people.
They're also the people who will see the 26 updates
on a Kickstarter and send them to other people.
Chicory did 26 updates over 18 months of their Kickstarter
campaign.
Constant communication with their first and second
tier audience.
Mavens have a tendency to also not be ashamed of their fandom.
So I'm, this is embarrassing, and I'm going to say this, and this will probably end up
on like a YouTube channel someday, but I am a Spice Girls Maven, and it's okay, I can
say this out loud.
I love the Spice Girls.
I have no shame at all about this.
The sort of people that you're trying to get to adopt,
your early adopters, your early mavens for your game projects,
you want them to not be ashamed of just being
so enthusiastic about your work.
And you can do this just by, you can support them, obviously,
with their updates.
You can support them by talking to them on Twitter.
You can provide content for them to share,
the kind of content that they're interested in.
People are always going to seek connection to the things
that they love.
And when you provide that connection,
they will share it with others.
Now, after Fingy, so we came into this game
with a reasonable-sized Kickstarter audience.
We had past projects.
We had fans of these creators.
And I had to figure out, what the heck are we
going to do with this?
And my job is I have to design a launch plan.
For a game like Chicory, that's actually kind of hard.
I'd never worked on a Game Maker game before.
I had never launched a PS5 title before.
And I'd never worked with Greg and his team, with the exception of M, before.
I had to sort of take all of their strengths and consolidate them into something that would
be useful to talk about as Fingy the Publishing Project.
One of those things that you have to do...
is you have to, in order to design the launch plan,
is you have to identify the points of intersection
between what the team wants, what Finji needs,
and what our business partner, in this case, Sony, needs.
None of those things align in exact, like, perfect,
in exact, perfect alignment.
We have to look for the places where we intersect,
where our interests are identical.
And that might be, we need to sell a bunch of copies.
We need to be well-reviewed.
We need to be something that people can say,
oh, I was involved with that project.
It makes whatever look good.
Or we support a diverse team.
There's a lot of different places
that you can have intersection with the various stakeholders
on a project.
All of these should be part of your marketing campaign.
They should be the base foundation.
As you're figuring out how to maximize the intersection points where the three parties
involved have common goals, you're able to pencil in possible marketing beats.
So this seems difficult, but if you're looking out in front of you, like I am launching a
game, Sony is my partner, what is an obvious possible mark?
Intersection point we need to launch something they know the public doesn't know the title so we need to launch a title
How do we do that?
Well, we are working for a common goal to an event
They need a trailer on device so they can show it and then they get to be the ones that bring that news to the
World that's an intersection point Sony has a need they need to announce this game. I have a need I need to build an audience
So we're all both working towards the same thing
But using the exact same asset to get there
That's what you mean by working towards a marketing beat,
working towards the same goal.
Now there's a lot of ways to sort of pencil in
your marketing beats between current and future available
assets, interviews, events, what's out in front of you.
And usually the question is like, well, I don't know.
We'll get to that.
I don't know what's out in front of me.
When you're sort of looking at this,
and you're looking at like 18 months until launch,
there's probably like 5 to 20 versions of this.
Well, what if I do this?
Well, then I would go to this event,
and then I would talk about it this way.
And at this event, I could talk about x design.
I could set up an interview for y.
I could participate in this event in this way,
which would cause me to talk about story,
You think about the reason for the event or the talk or anything, and how can you turn
that into something that produces content that people can get a hold of in the news
or on the internet.
I built five of these in the summer of 2020, following multiple distribution paths to launch.
When we decided to go with Sony, when we sort of developed that partnership,
I sort of went quiet with Chicory in the fall of 2020. This was super intentional at this point.
We have a tendency when we know how we're going to launch a game,
where we're like, we leak out a little bit of information and then things go
very very quiet for a long time, it's because I'm holding new
information for what we call springboard times.
So for example, this is unrelated to chicory but it's the most recent example,
I had a launch date for Tunic, and I knew that launch date for Tunic back in the summer of 2021,
but nobody knew that until December because I was holding that for springboard time.
My springboard time was the Game Awards. This is similar with Chicory. I knew that I was content
complete. I knew that I had this PS5 deal, but I had to wait for a springboard time in order
to announce it, which meant that I knew when exactly I would be launching the title.
We also tie springboard times to new assets,
things that people can latch on to,
things that people can share.
We also tailor the message for each channel.
The way you talk to some press is very different
from how you talk to other press,
which is very different from how you talk
to your Kickstarter backers,
to the kids on your Discord.
All of them have to be tailored
to how they're going to be receptive
to the information that you're sharing.
And you always work towards the next news drop.
So cool.
I did some, like, we announced that we're coming out,
oops, I'm sorry.
We announced that we're coming out on PlayStation
in February of 2021 for Chicory.
I knew in March that I was going to be announcing
the range that it was coming out.
It wasn't the date because I didn't know it yet,
but we're like, spring, which gave me a max deadline.
It had to come out before.
whatever June 20 something is when it turns into summer.
We did that all intentional, but we
were working towards that next news drop
when we did the February launch.
And the way that you can always be working towards your next news drop is you prep 90%
done assets for quick turnaround.
When you're a super, super small studio and your partner is like, hey, I need an on-device
trailer and you're like, cool, that's four weeks of work.
Who the hell can do that on the kind of turnaround time that a lot of consoles or business partners
ask for?
Nobody can. I can't do it. And we don't. I had that chicory. I had the February chicory launch
trailer. I had that asset done in April of 2020. We only had to make edits to it. We had to put it
in the correct timeline. We had to add the right bumpers. We were working on the tunic trailer.
That was storyboarded and worked on last fall. Because we were working towards
events that we were hoping to get a hold of well before we actually had it confirmed.
Especially with something like trailers, try to work towards 90% assets. Finishing up 10% in a
week is possible. Doing a trailer in a week will hurt you and it's not a good idea and it's not
going to be a good trailer and it's unkind to all of your collaborators.
You also have to be flexible.
We were up for an announcement in October of 2020,
December of 2020, possibly even January,
I think we had one canceled.
And all of those announcements for getting
our PlayStation announcement announced just fell through.
There wasn't room for it.
It wasn't a good fit.
And we just continued to hold these assets,
because eventually we would have the correct intersection
point.
that would make the most noise.
And if your partner is on board with it,
if your partner is also helping with this marketing,
that will work.
So be flexible.
Now.
One of the main things that we have a tendency to do
is we position our team to take advantage of an external,
we call these, this is the nice way to call these things
when somebody calls you up and like,
hey, I want you to be in an event.
We're like, oh, that's a great external opportunity
rather than cursing.
We used to just curse.
Position your team to take advantage
of an external opportunity before it happens.
People always ask, well, how?
How do you know this?
The industry runs on a calendar and it's not a mystery.
The calendar is the same every year.
When does Apple do their fall announcements?
Second week of September.
It just is.
When do they announce stuff?
March 25th.
There's an announcement in March.
You can just find this information
by just looking at the internet.
You can just make notes.
The platforms also run on a calendar.
The events run on a calendar.
And your game marketing schedule cannot ignore that calendar
unless you are so big that you make your own calendar.
You are probably not that big.
There's very few people who are that big.
For years now, many years, I track every single event.
I have like a Hobonichi, like a paper calendar,
which everyone makes fun of me for.
They're like, why are you not digital?
Well, I like writing things down.
I track everything in that thing for years, and I keep them stacked, actually, behind my desk.
I track when the sales happen across all platforms.
I track events.
I track studio vacations, when Sony goes on vacation at the holidays.
I track that.
I track when they announced major games.
That way I can go back and I can look for correlations between how the calendar moves
from year to year.
When our state of play is going to happen, I can tell you that.
When our Xbox Twitch event is going to happen, I can probably tell you that too.
Because they have internal process that dictates the timeline that these things can happen.
You don't have to know what any of that is.
You just have to look at when they have the events.
Now, we ended up in a position, obviously, with COVID, that we were trapped.
We couldn't go to PAX anymore.
And now we're forced to figure out how to make use of an online
event with a tiny, tiny team.
Online events are going to, are going to then and will now increase launch reach
because the industry has changed.
Like always, like timestamp this talk today on March 23rd or 24th, whatever it is.
It is different from the industry of six months ago,
and it's going to be different from the industry six months
from now.
The online events are not going to go away.
Online demo events are just not going to go away
because we have created a system now
that was hard to create,
where people can access these things.
Steam demo events are awesome.
They happen all the time,
and that was not a thing that really existed
in the form that it is now before the pandemic.
They'd tried maybe one of them, and it was heavily curated.
And now you can just turn your demos on and off
with a button, which is not how it used to work.
If you can't turn people's heads in real life,
the next best thing is at-home access.
And this really does open it up for those of us
who can't travel.
It is not realistic to say, hey, everybody, go to PAX.
You can't do that.
How do you, why do you, like I can't go to the Tokyo game show.
I've never been there.
I really want to go.
I'm never going to make it there.
Who can make it to Gamescom this third week of August?
It's expensive.
When you have these online demo events,
it means that you also can be sitting at the same table
as all the other game developers in the world on a platform
like Steam, or if any of the, Xbox, for example,
also did demo events last year.
I.
And it's up to you to figure out how to make the most of these online events, because it's
not just the event.
I have pointed out, just on here, some of the events that we did, and this is correlated
to our Chickory wish lists.
We have our Kickstarter campaign when the page went live.
We have the first Steam DemoFest.
I think that's actually the very, very first one that they did.
I've highlighted three others.
Indie Arena Online, which was the Gamescom 2020 sort of fill-in.
Ludonaracon is awesome.
If you can participate in that, it takes over the whole front page of Steam
and drives wish lists for the whole weekend.
All of this matters.
These are all marketing beats.
These are all ways to collect your audience before you launch your game.
I put a picture of this up here.
This is my online booth for Indie Arena Online in 2020.
It was and is an online MMO where you walk
through virtual booths.
All of these things, like if you hit Play,
that would take you to the Steam page to play the demo.
It had soundless trailers running on it.
You could.
click over to my merch booth, which was just like my Fingy store.
And you could, we had little NPCs in there, you could sort of see
Chickory Dog in the middle, which had sort of
a twine-like conversation
dialogue system that my community manager, Harris, typed up. And it was all
Twitter linked. It was really hard to do because it was so limited.
And every single one of those people, I think, was named me.
But we just put in conversations, what is the game about?
How can you, what's the quickest way that you can tell people what chicory is about?
This thing was not easy to build in 2020.
It's gotten much, much easier.
They actually changed and overhauled the whole system for 2022.
No, 2021.
It's so cool.
And it's a way to participate in Gamescom
without actually going to Cologne.
You are engaging with a European audience.
that you might otherwise not have access to.
In addition to just building a showpiece booth,
which took about two weeks, it was way harder in 2020,
we provided an entire weekend of online streaming schedule.
We reached out to streamers to play our demo
and we let them stream it on our Steam page.
We provided, we made our own talks and recorded them
with like lower thirds and the whole thing,
and we streamed them on our Twitch channel.
We did Q&As with developers in our Discord.
So we had Greg and his team come in
and talk to fans in our Discord about the game design,
and then they could just go play the demo.
We did, we did our restreaming, we did Twitter initiatives.
So during this time we did
chicory character haircuts.
So we would, we were in the process of adding all the hair mechanics to the game and we were just giving all the characters haircuts.
We also did a draw, draw whatever in the chicory art style, just on a live art stream.
It was awesome.
Like these timed demos were such a cool opportunity
to provide content directly to our fans.
So online event participation, you did it,
but you're not actually done.
You can prep your content in advance.
You can use the tools that just the internet gives you
at your disposal effectively.
It's going to drive online engagement
because that's literally how the system is designed to work.
You can use all of these pieces,
and it's just for a weekend.
So.
We refer to, we have a minimum viable product
when it comes to online events,
where we have a certain number of things
that we try to schedule for each day,
because you don't have to keep it running the whole time.
So for Gamescom, we try to do maybe 10 a.m. to 2 p.m.,
so during our workday,
and that's all the content that we'll provide,
because we're catering to a European audience.
If we're working in the Steam Demo Fest,
we're working more at nighttime,
so we're trying to catch the after-school crowd.
We're looking at one to two things a day, maybe.
If you have a Discord, you can just turn on the radio part,
and you can host an audio show.
We do those all the time in our Fingy Discord.
It's just fun, where you can just have people come on stage,
have them ask a question, talk about game design.
It really does, though, all of this, it will take.
time away from you, especially if you're a small indie team.
So you need to actually build this into your production
schedule.
The cool thing, though, because all of this stuff is online,
for Indie Arena especially, and we did this
with the Chicory team, we actually
started building content in July for this event.
So that way, we didn't have to do this stuff live.
Who wants to do that on a Saturday?
We would run the shows that we had pre-recorded.
And then we had like these five weeks,
we could put it into our schedule and then run the content.
And especially if you're a small indie team or any team,
the next time there's a Steam demo fest,
you want to know what content you can run?
The content from your last event,
because you want to know how many eyeballs saw it
at that time?
Wow, 15?
Let's go for more.
Like you can just rerun your content, rerun old streams.
You can just put them up on your page.
This work is not just like a one-off thing, you can continue to use it.
All of our platform, single day press beats, even for other platforms, increase awareness.
These are also our wish lists.
Our Sony announcements have spikes on our Steam wish lists, our launch date announcements
spike on wish lists, our launch day wish lists.
Every single time that we talked to the public, we had spikes.
If you ask any developer in this industry to show this graph,
I promise you every single one of them
is going to have the same information on it.
Every time you talk to the public,
you absolutely will have wish list increases.
And even when you announce for other platforms,
you will have Steam wish list increases.
This has been this way forever.
And it is really important to internalize this truth
about how Steam works.
Because all of this works for us as developers towards one goal.
When we launch a game, people know that the damn thing
is available.
And they know it's available because they've
wish-listed the game.
Because we don't have huge marketing budgets.
Now, this was a weird one for us,
participating in the Summer Games Fest.
We were sort of coming up on launch,
and we had all of these assets sitting out ready for basically
us to go.
And we needed to be ready at any point to participate.
We had our launch trailer.
We had an accolades trailer, just
ready to put accolades in it.
We had
We had ideas of how this could work,
and it was sort of our job to pitch them.
I mentioned already that we were sort of
at the front of the PS5 launches,
and we knew that we weren't going to get
months of known ramp up on our launch date
because new tech things often have unknowns.
This doesn't make launching a game impossible
unless you prepare yourself.
So when it is time to go, you are ready to go.
So I'm going to talk a little bit just like how did this come together. So we launched actually,
we shadowed, almost shadow dropped. I negotiated a pretty cool version of it. We didn't tell anyone
what time of the day it was going to be launched and we had it as part of the steam or the Summer
Games Fest, which is Jeff Keeley's event. So we mentioned that it was going to be launching in
spring in March of 2021. Our porting efforts were absolutely taking longer than expected because of
sort of our games engine and the new hardware. And we had planned for this.
And we knew that it was going to be like real tight coming into our launch.
It was very hard being patient.
So when it looked like we were going to hit the June date,
which happens to overlap E3, which is kind of a terrible time
to try to launch a game as an indie,
we started negotiating hard for an E3 spot,
using both our contacts at Sony,
but also my previous contacts with sort of Jeff Keighley
and the Game Awards.
There were a bunch of options on the table, and one of those absolutely was a complete
shadow drop, which would have, as I talked about earlier, we had these Kickstarter backers
who are our earliest fans, and of all the people that you want to make angry, you don't
piss off your mavens.
So if we had shadow dropped a game, we would not have told people who are most excited
about our game that it was launching.
They wouldn't know that they could play it right away.
They would have had to clear their schedule to get a hold of it.
And that's kind of a cruddy way to treat your best fans.
Uh, so we sort of negotiated the best version of this, which was, we will tell
our fans that we're launching, but we're not going to tell them exactly when or
how, which means that they also get to participate on launch day in the sort of
like really loud version that we had arranged at the steam or the summer games fest.
So.
We provided a way forward that hit all of our goals
across all three people, or all three stakeholders.
We had our launch day announcement,
which meant the Kickstarter backers
were going to be satisfied.
We had our exclusive partner content,
which meant that Sony was going to be satisfied.
And we had a press push with a known embargo
and streamer push, which meant that Finji
could talk to press and get our reviews in order.
And we had beautiful assets from the team.
It was not hard to do this, but looking at what the end goals were for everyone involved
meant that we were able to come up with a solution that allowed everyone to have sort
of a part in the process.
If anyone ever wants to talk about that, we should do it over drinks.
It's pretty stressful.
So, traditional PR plans are wonderful.
PR, public relations is like talking to media and press and sort of navigating
that, that whole industry and it's very weird.
The thing that's super, super important, especially even with small indie titles
is to understand that press game reviews are awesome, but that's not PR.
That's just what happens when you launch a game.
Public relations and media relations is being able to pitch a story about you to the media
to get them to cover you beyond your press review, your game review.
This is going up and talking to them and being like, hey, I have a really cool dev story.
Let me tell you about it.
Would you like to talk to my team about.
The process of inventing genderless language for a 75,000 word script.
How do you do that in French?
It's a nightmare.
That's a story.
That's a pitch.
That's something somebody would want to talk about and it's not a game review.
Or the intersection of creativity and feeling like you're not good enough in the games industry.
Also a story. Let's talk about imposter syndrome. And let's talk to the Chicory team about that.
They did a whole game about imposter syndrome. Or lessons learned from Wandersong.
Why does Chicory shine in a different way?
Like that's pitching stories that people want to talk about that are not game reviews.
That's traditional media relations.
And we started that in June.
No, not June.
We started that way before June, February.
And we had the stories start trickling out in May and June.
We also did physical press kits.
This is the first time we ever did this.
I almost vetoed it, and I'm so glad I didn't.
We spent money on 150 physical press kits.
And it wasn't your normal garbage swag.
We did watercolor scenes of the game itself.
We sent custom watercolor, like, I don't even
know the cartridges, plus paintbrushes.
We did a donation to schools.
So every one of the press kits costs like $15.
And I did $15 per press kit.
And we donated this directly to.
educators in the United States who are teaching art in schools, which you can pick up from
DonorsChoose just as a charity donation.
And we told people we did that.
We didn't tell the internet we did that, but we told the people who we sent the press kit
to that we did that.
We also did like a custom pin of the lost kittens.
This was all themed directly around
Chicory itself, things that matter to Chicory.
We wanted the press and content creators,
and even the team got them,
to sit down and watercolor a scene,
like in real life and not just in the game.
We also did key distribution to press in tiers.
We tier our press.
Top tier, NDA tier,
they get three to four weeks to review a game.
We also do one week before, day before, and day of,
depending on
if we're afraid somebody's going to break embargo.
We also did a huge asset overhaul.
We checked screenshots, GIFs, trailer cuts.
And we made sure that we worked ahead so all of these things
were ready to go in the weeks leading up to launch.
We also used developer tools for launch.
On Steam, you can just put streams up.
Did you talk to anybody about streaming on your web page
on launch day?
We also had a very small, very modest advertising budget,
which ICO helped us put together,
pointing people at both Steam and the PlayStation store
pages.
And we did test runs of that to figure out
who would be the best audiences to sort of point
at a Fingy game.
And that was actually a really weird process,
because we don't discriminate against audiences.
Finji has an amazing, supportive, furry audience
out there.
We just do.
It's cool.
And providing advertisements to that audience
was like a no-brainer for us.
We have a game that's all the characters are animals.
and they have a great representative audience on Twitter,
that should be part of our audience.
And we did a test on that to see if that was
an appropriate way to use our ad money.
So we always work ahead on all launches
because nothing is stopping us except ourselves.
We love to procrastinate and we are very aware of that.
So we work way, way, way ahead.
That way we are always ready for when something does come up.
You can write your press release for your launch
two months in advance.
You know the most about your game.
You can just put it in a Google Doc and hang onto it.
And you can also research your press context two months
in advance.
You can not procrastinate that, so you're
ready to go when your game's ready to go.
You can pull your Steam keys early.
You can make a trailer that fits into your schedule
and hold it for a year.
I'm holding.
two trailers right now? Three trailers. I am holding three trailers right now and I've had
them done for quite a while. One of them I've had done since 2020 and it's just sitting in a drop box
waiting for the right moment for me to show the world how cool it is.
You can build a burndown list of things to do for launch
and assign them to the right people.
And that right person might be you.
It might be just your burndown list.
We keep actually a master list in Notion.
I have several of these now.
And it'll be like 60 or 70 items long by the time we're done.
And we divide it out between the four of us.
So yeah.
I have time for questions.
I just want to sort of end with, when you limit yourself
to the ways other people talk about their games,
when you limit to the way that you've
seen other people do things, you're actually
doing yourself a disservice as far as how
you talk about your own games.
You're no longer representing your living product.
You're sort of following arbitrary rules
without considering the outcome.
Each game's marketing plan is unique within the game itself.
And that's like a super important design tenet.
You need to be able to sort of create a possibility space
for how you talk about and engage with your marketing
problem as a creative design problem,
and not just like, well, these are the rules.
This is what I'm supposed to do.
As game designers and developers, we do have the opportunity to approach marketing from the realm of design,
and our medium specifically is uniquely positioned to offer up ways to connect with our audience
when you are looking at the problem in a more holistic way.
We have access to a lot of tools, and your game itself has mechanics and themes within
to build a whole interactive process out of those tools.
Chicory had that. It was built into the way it was painted. It was built into the gifts.
It was built into the way that Sony also wanted to show it.
And all the pieces that we did were designed to maximize the systems in place,
the Steam wish lists, the audience building, the collection of more
people inside our Discord. We brought talks into our Discord. They stayed as fans.
All of these things were built together.
We did not think about them as individual process
that we just sort of did once and threw away.
Everything is a stair step.
Everything builds off of each other.
So yeah, if you have any questions,
I've got, I think, maybe 11 minutes.
I usually am able to do a bunch of wrap up,
but I have to catch a flight home at about an hour, so.
I'm not on the plane an hour, I have to be at the airport, or in my car in an hour.
So yeah, if you have any questions, feel free to ping me.
There's a mic there, and I will repeat your question.
And it can be kind of about anything.
Hey, quick question.
Do you have any examples of, you were talking about mavens a lot.
of acquiring that audience when that Kickstarter isn't involved?
There's actually, there's a bunch of ways.
So, it kinda depends on what you're actually gonna do with your project.
We'll do the most obvious
one right now. So, say you have a demo of your game.
You got it up on Steam and you're gonna participate in a Steam demo day.
When that happens, your Steam forums are already open.
People are going to be talking about it online.
It's possible you're going to find somebody talking
about your game on Reddit.
Those are the sort of people.
You want to watch literally everything people say.
They're not going to be like you're never, well,
actually you might.
If you end up at an event or something,
you might actually meet them and learn their names.
But you're going to watch everything
that they say because they're going to talk about it.
They're not going to be able to stop.
It's going to be endless.
They're going to pop up all the time.
We have one actually in Tunic who is a fan
of past work of one of the collaborators on it.
It was really funny because they dropped into our Discord.
People familiar with them were like,
oh no, they're here.
This one right here is a super fan,
which is awesome because once you see a super fan drop on,
you can see people gravitate around them.
because they have a tendency to know more about your project it feels like
than you do and they talk about it better than you do because they just
understand it on like a usually a very personal level you'll run into him as
well like if we ever get to go back to real events like PAX or whatever they'll
come and explain your game back to you
And just, I mentioned this before probably at the GDC talk, wholesale steal their words.
Because whatever they came up with is better than what you are going to come up with.
That's happened more than once.
Of course.
Hey, thanks for the talk.
Uh, I had two things.
Uh, the first was how do you approach, um, post launch content, stuff like speed
running, like GDQ, uh, Chickory was at GDQ.
And I assume that was something you were aware of and involved with.
Uh, and then the second one is when you have these projects that, you know, you
are working on stuff very long in advance, how do you decide what is the project
that I'm going to work on today?
Like, how do you know?
okay we need to be prepping assets for Tunic versus Chicory versus whatever else is still
in the pipeline. Those are good questions. So the first one is about GDQ. So Chicory was debuted at
the Speedrunning Awesome Games Done Quick in January. And the second question is like,
How do you pick and how do you fit in production?
So first, GDQ is really interesting because we actually didn't know how it worked.
We've never really had a game in it exactly.
You can't just say, hey, GDQ, do chicory.
The speedrunning community are the ones who submit, like, I want to do this.
and then they get chosen or not.
So we actually didn't have much to do with that,
other than we crossed our fingers and prayed
that somebody would.
We knew there was an active speedrunning community,
but we didn't really have any ins or a way
to ask them to do that,
and honestly, it's a faux pas, you don't.
So we just really, really, really hoped that they would,
because we knew all the people who speedrun it,
because Greg is super, absolutely loves speedrunning.
When it got selected, so talking about working ahead, we had this dream of doing this custom PS5,
which are obviously very, very hard to get a hold of. My community manager,
because he's on the computer all day and needs to keep his airline card active during COVID,
has been sourcing PS5s for friends and family. That's how I got mine. But he sourced me the
second PS5 in February of 2020.
I had that PS5 sitting in my house for a very long time.
And we started talking to Zandra, and I was like,
hey, you want to paint these plates?
We'll ship them to you.
We didn't know what we were going to do with that PS5.
I just had it done and had no place to put it.
And when GDQ, like Chickory, got into it,
I asked Kevin from Power Up Audio for an intro.
I was like, I got a prize for you.
I don't know what I'm going to do with it.
I have this PS5 that we painted, and this is a cool, charity-focused way to offload
this beautiful thing."
So it was one of those moments where I was, I have a painted PS5, how am I going to offload
this?
I didn't know how, and I was just waiting for an opportunity to do something with it.
And that sounds...
crazy, probably, but it was such a good idea,
an opportunity will come up.
So that's how we got rid of it.
We didn't have anything to do with Chicory getting in,
but once I saw the opportunity, I did something with it.
And I got to donate a cool PS5 to charity.
I don't know who got it.
I really would love to see a picture with this person
who has this beautiful black light painted PS5 someday.
Second question, production schedule.
How do I figure out, like, am I going to make a Glory Society trailer today,
or am I going to do a chicory asset?
Are we going to, like, focus on a gif or a talk or?
When you look at the calendar out in front of you,
you have a pretty good idea of where things are going to slot in.
And you also know what you're working on production wise.
You often are able to slot these sort of things into breaks.
People just can't program and solve things endlessly forever.
Building these marketing assets are like using creative time
in a different way.
And we usually try to slot them in a way to give people breaks.
So a lot of the trailer work was done in breaks between things
before a portion of the game was started
or after it was finished up.
So that way, part of the materials were halfway done.
And then when they sat down to do it,
they were able to knock it out in a week.
We work that way in Fingy internal 100% of the time.
Right now, we're stewing on a pretty big project.
We're not going to build that until the last week of April.
Because we want it storyboarded, we want all the pieces of it already ready to go before we like sit down, so we don't like just bang up against like a wall trying to figure out a way to make it work.
So we usually have a pretty good idea of like these are the things we're going to need in the future, about how much time are they going to take. And as soon as we see that time we slot them in.
So we don't stress people out.
Does that make sense? Cool.
Hi there, and thanks for our talk.
So, let's talk a bit about money.
If you were to kind of count all the resources
involved in marketing, be it, I don't know,
hours of work, straight up money spent on it,
compare that to the money that,
or resources that you spent making the game,
what's kind of the ratio between the two?
For marketing, it's actually quite low.
pretty tiny company so I'd probably probably in total across all of the
chicory stuff and I have to discount I'm not gonna include salaries for my staff
no okay living salaries for well salaries for staff it's a little weird
because they're working on like five projects right now so I'm gonna give you
two numbers so in total like all the things that I spent on chicory over
probably two years
We're probably looking at maybe $18,000 to $20,000 tops.
Okay.
That's like a online booth.
maybe a computer, the PS5 is pricey,
paying Xandra to paint it, shipping that thing around.
We did have a small advertising campaign,
which was I think like maybe 7,500 across both our tests
and the like one week that we did.
And that went really far, it was surprising.
And kind of how, like what percentage of the time
does the staff work on marketing stuff?
So my staff goes full-time on projects when we need to be full-time on it.
So during Chicory's time, we did, they were probably doing at least probably 10 to 15
hours of Chicory work right up until six months pre-launch.
And then it was probably closer to 20 to 25 hours of work.
And that's across trailer.
This staff also does launch management,
so cutting up the assets into 500 different ways
for storefronts.
The 10 to 15 different versions of the trailer
that you need with the different branding on it.
And so this is a staff of me, Harris, Emily.
And then ICO handled the PR.
And they probably did five to seven hours of work.
a week. So, yeah, whatever that budget is. I can't, the number won't help because it's
going to be in USD, really.
Yeah, no, I was more trying to get a sense of kind of the scale of work.
The hours, yeah.
Yeah, the scale of work.
So, if this was only my job, I could have done all of the work solo.
Okay.
Like, it is technically one person's job.
In how many months?
I mean, it's like six months of work.
Okay, so six months of work for one person is kind of...
Yeah, but the way our studio is structured,
like Harris also runs our Discord.
No, of course, but yeah, that's the scale.
Okay, cool, thanks.
Yep.
The thing with PR though,
is it's not six months of full-time work.
It's 18 months of part-time work.
And then one really awful week.
Thanks for the talk.
Oh, of course.
I know we're at time, I saw you, okay.
What's the approach to creating the demo for a narrative game in your sense?
Do you take like a vertical slide as to like the middle of the game and just present it or do you like
Create the first part of the game and present the story up until one point and then cut it off on demo
It's actually a really good question because I've had to do this several times
So the question is how when you're building a narrative game, you're obviously you're in a position where you're gonna spoil a whole bunch of stuff
How do you?
Pick which part of the game you're going to show in a demo.
So I could do a whole talk about demo design,
because it's important, especially if you're
going to be showing this on a show floor.
I have rules about length, 10 to 15 minutes,
especially if it's on a convention show floor.
And you want to drop them into a place
where knowing exactly who and what the characters are
is not required to have a good time with the story.
So, we did two or three different demos with Night in the Woods.
The first one was a very bespoke.
Most of that first demo didn't even end up in the main game.
It was just intro May, get her to a place where you sort of interacted with her friends,
do band practice, throw a gnome off the top of a rooftop, eat some donuts, done.
That's a real thing.
I can't believe I say these words out loud in order, but that's a video game.
The second one, however, cut, um, one of the friend quests.
Um, so you are hanging out with B and you're in the mall and it's again, the
same thing it's showing you're walking, you're doing the mini game, you're
getting an understanding of like sort of the humor.
But there's nothing about it that's
going to spoil the contents of the game.
We never, ever in a demo show the very end of the game.
In a narrative game, we never show the very beginning.
Because the very beginning is like onboarding.
Who are these people?
It's not boring.
It's great.
But it's real boring for a demo.
Because what you want to get them to is the game loop.
And for a narrative game, there's
probably going to be something there for the game loop.
And it's probably going to be cut
from a scene in chapter two.
So find your 10 to 20 minute long scene in that chapter.
And then cut out the spoilers.
So it doesn't actually have to be shippable content.
It can be, oops, it can be like a very custom version of it.
We can even, I guess, build something
that's not gonna be shown ever on the game
just for the demo's purpose.
Oh, absolutely.
I mean, the Night in the Woods initial demo was, I mean, I think it's technically actually
built into the final game, but nothing actually is pulled in.
It was all replaced.
But I can still find it actually in the script, like in the tags and stuff.
Thank you.
Of course.
Any other questions, comments?
Okay, cool.
Feel free to reach out to me.
I'm easily found and very approachable.
So, thank you.