Good morning, if you are in, uh, everywhere but the East Coast of America.
Good afternoon, if you're on the East Coast.
Good afternoon, or good evening, if you're in Europe.
Um, uh, good morning, I guess, if you're in Hawaii?
If you're in Hawaii, it's early for you.
My name is Brian Francis. I am a contributing editor at GammaStriger.com.
I am a community manager with GDC.
I am your host, your invisible voice who hangs out here and plays video games with you.
I'm going to give a quick shout out in chat.
Looks like we got some few folks in here already.
We got Keithulu and Kanakero.
Thank you both for joining us.
What we are here today doing, what we're here today playing,
we're here playing Nowhere Prophet.
We are talking to Martin Nerukar, who is down in the lower left hand corner of your screen.
Martin, how are you doing?
I'm doing fine. It's very warm, as you can see from my choice in the tower.
Yeah.
But it's getting colder. It's the evening.
I can see on your shirt there, you're wearing a GDC shirt from like 2011?
Because it's GDC 2011?
Yeah.
And then Alyssa, Gamasutra Master of Words, how are you doing?
I'm very sleepy, but I am here.
Hello.
Yeah.
It's the tired...
Today we are tired developers conference.
Yeah, I got out of bed very late today as well, so I can...
I feel it.
Yeah, we're gonna do our best to power through that. Thank you all for joining us.
Like I said, we're here to say thank you to Nowhere Profit. It is a science fiction, kind of card based RPG?
I guess you can call it an RPG. Strategy, it's kind of a strategy game more than that.
So it's a mix of kind of a, you're about to see it, it is a, well you might be about to see it, I don't know what's going to happen when I go to these crossroads.
It is kind of a mix of card playing elements with this Oregon Trail slash FTL kind of narrative interludes.
And Martin here is the lead developer at Shark Bomb, the company that brought us the game.
Martin, while I get started on my first part of my Legolas adventure, would you mind explaining the origins of Nowhere Prophet?
Oh god, so no I don't, but it's difficult.
So I kind of started with the first prototypes for what would eventually become No More Profit
back in 2014, like over 5 years ago at this point.
I was basically looking for an abstract conflict resolution system that could manage actual
physical fights and social situations as well.
Because I really liked stuff like in Mass Effect, towards the end of the game you can
sort of convince, I think Saren was his name, from not attacking you, and he instead kills
himself but then you still have a boss fight.
But I liked the idea of going through the world and winning with words instead of with
weapons.
So I looked at sort of abstract conflict resolution mechanics, and the first ones I sort of played around with were timing based, because I needed something that is not like shooter thing.
I, like, thinking of a shooter and then making that map to sort of talking doesn't work for me. So I went in and started with some timing mechanics and then sort of moved to cards.
And from there, ended up with like a card system that I really liked, which is, in fact, really different from what we have now.
And then sort of built the game around it.
And the world sort of came from me looking into my background.
So I'm half German, half Indian.
So that's sort of where the Indian inspiration comes from.
And I always really like post-apocalypse, but I was bored with sort of the...
I'm just going to say white dudes in leather jackets in brown worlds.
So I tried to sort of mix it up with sort of a different aesthetic and sort of have more colors in there.
More colorful people, more colorful sort of a strange planet with like purple sky stuff and different moons.
That was sort of where it came from sort of initially.
Which is funny, because I recently looked at Griftlands, I think the alpha or the beta,
which is the play card game, and they have this sort of two-pronged social and physical combat thing,
which I had to scrap because when I was working on the game it was still the old system.
It was just too much work for me because you mentioned the developer, like there's nobody else here but me.
It's not like a big team, so I had to scrap the social comment because it was just too much to deal with two entire different decks and everything.
Which was a shame, but the right choice in hindsight.
Funny thing, a bunch of the... that guy that's just dying now, that you just lost forever, is Anjin.
He's the art director of the game. So there's like, we made portraits of a bunch of the people that worked on the game and I got them involved.
Now he's gone, Brian, way to go!
I mean, now that sounds like a contradiction of sort of saying it's only me and then I'm saying that's an art director.
Basically, sort of to explain before anybody's confused is that I'm sort of the only full-time developer on the game.
I did all the design, I did 99% of the code, I did a lot of the writing, I did all the interface design, and I did a lot of the art direction as well.
We did this sort of as a two-man team. But I didn't do the pretty pictures, I did very few of the sound effects, and I did none of the music.
So that's all thanks to very talented people that you can see in the credits.
Right on.
Uh, to, to, um, continue, uh, the line of questioning.
So once you, you, you sort of migrated from, you said you had wanted to do
conflict resolution in a way that wasn't, uh, um, that wasn't combat based, that
wasn't shooting, that wasn't sort of moving and dodging, what made you move
towards a kind of this like adventure, like trekking across the landscape while
managing a, a convoy of nomads kind of take?
I mean that's always where it started on.
Like I had the general conflict system and I wanted to put something around it.
And I wanted to have a story about a bunch of people and not just this one hero that
goes and does everything by himself.
The early combat system I had, which eventually got scrapped, was a lot more sort of party-based.
Like you had a bunch of sort of special people each at their own small decks,
and you sort of had this one-on-one, sort of three-versus-three party fights going on.
And, I don't know, I always liked sort of stories about community.
Banner Saga really spoke to me, sort of, from the narrative it kind of had.
And I kind of wanted to do something that's not, as I said, not about like the lone hero.
What were some of the other game design choices you felt like reinforced that decision as opposed to
that and when did you sort of like
Realize you were wandering off course and needed to get back to that
So I mean the most important one was the old system was sort of you had a number of followers
which was pretty much just a number, like you had 17 followers, 20 followers, and then
you had these dudes that were sort of your warriors, which would have their own sort
of little decks and you'd, you know, three of yours against three of the enemy.
And I scrapped that because it...
While the system itself worked, it was a fun card game that I enjoyed playing and that
people enjoyed playing, but it didn't fit the theme enough because all your people in
your convoy were just numbers.
So I took a break at that point, I was really unsatisfied with where the game was going.
I could have finished it at that point, but it was just not where I wanted it to be.
And then I just sort of redesigned the entire game.
A combat system which came back and did a sort of extensive paper prototyping to solve some issues I have with the gameplay in sort of a longer term progression, but also to make the convoy matter more.
And that's sort of where this idea comes from, that actually the people in your convoy are specific cards.
Which I think the whole cards are people and sort of wounds on cards thing and blessing cards is really sort of...
Very good thing that does wonders for no web profit and sort of for the deck building parts of it.
Right on. I am currently learning more about the game.
As you can see, I couldn't say a lot of it before getting started.
Okay, I'm going to jump into my question pile for a minute.
Oh man, our co-worker Alex would like to point out that you have very good hair.
Thank you.
Shout out to Alex for watching.
It's been pink for two days now.
Nice. We are also taking questions from chat.
If you've got questions about the Make Game No More profit.
Um, uh, you are, before the stream we were discussing,
you are currently, uh,
sanding off the edges of some of your AI.
We were discussing about how the difficulty spikes are sort of
uh, jumping a little ahead than where you want, where you want them to be.
Um, uh, would you mind talking about the discussion of like,
realizing that you'd be making an AI driven game instead of like a, you know, card.
I think of a card game, I think of Magic, I think of Pokemon,
I think of something I play with another person.
What was that process like for figuring out your games once you realized you had to be an AI programmer as well as a game designer?
How is that going?
The reason for the game being a single player game is because I really love card games.
I actually currently still play a lot of Magic the Gathering.
I got back into it almost a year ago at this point.
I played 25 years ago.
It's like a teenager in high school.
And I'm getting back into it.
And I really love playing physical card games with people,
because you have your local meta,
and you know you play people,
and you can play in a relaxed manner.
You can make fun decks and make interesting choices.
And I played a lot of Hearthstone,
also as research for the game,
but also played a bunch of online card games before.
And the issue for me was always...
If you play online, you suddenly have this sort of very competitive arena that you're in,
which means it's sort of like going to a magic tournament.
To compete, you need to know what the deck builds are, you need to build the perfect deck,
you need to spend money or grind like my hell to get the right cards or be very lucky.
And then you have a chance at competing.
And that sort of sucks out the fun of sort of building the deck for me,
because it becomes this know the meta and play to the meta kind of thing.
And I never really wanted to go there.
And I like before I designed No More Prophet, I played Dominion.
I'm not sure if anyone of you knows it.
It's a it's a physical card game that is.
sort of the granddaddy of deck building as a concept.
It's a game where you have a bunch of cards, and it's a bunch of cards on the table,
and you have a small deck, which you cycle through constantly.
And you use that deck to sort of buy stuff into your deck,
and you need to buy stuff that allows you to do more things,
but also need to buy victory points, which do nothing for your deck.
So you sort of have this back-and-forth between buying stuff,
or buying stuff before somebody else buys it, or buying victory points.
And it's a really fun challenge of deck building.
I know it's pretty old at this point, but when I played it, I sort of got a really new
access to sort of the fun of deck building, because I remember thinking back on Magic
25 years ago, I always built fun and janky decks, but I sucked at them.
Like, my decks were shit.
because people were building more efficient decks.
And sort of, Dominion, like, I don't know, I guess it's ten years ago or something,
sort of gave me an idea that deck building actually can be very fun if it's not
sort of this thing you need to do before, and you need to do your homework and your research,
but if it's part of the game and part of the resources and sort of the challenges
managing the resources right and sort of, you know.
And that's sort of where this comes from. And then sort of talking about the AI,
um, man, building an AI is hard. It's hard because it's super intransparent.
Like, the AI does things and you hope it does things the right way, but man, it's tough.
I mean, my goal for the AI was always...
It doesn't need to be perfect, it doesn't need to compete on a human level because it's a single player game.
It's not like a multiplayer where on an even footing it needs to match you or be boring.
Because the game has this attrition aspect as you play, you lose resources.
So you want to be efficient in your fights.
Which means the AI doesn't need to be superb, but it doesn't need to be stupid.
It should never make mistakes where you go like, what the hell, why are you doing this?
And unfortunately the game launched last weekend with a bug in there, which I just actually like an hour ago fixed.
That made the idea super thin.
I'm going to write up an announcement about that later, but what it boils down to is,
like 6 weeks ago, 7 weeks ago, I went through and optimized the AI to make sure it runs
quicker and faster so it allows me to do more iteration.
The AI basically simulates a whole bunch of moves, evaluates those moves, and then picks
the best move, and then does the same thing over and over again.
It actually simulates a bunch of moves forward, so if I do this and then this and then this,
how good is the move?
Or if I do this and then this and then this, how good is that?
And then it sort of evaluates the different branches.
It's Monte Carlo Tree Search, if anyone's interested in the actual algorithm behind
it.
But there was this little bug in the game where when I optimized it, I wasn't paying a lot of attention.
And so what happened was, when it would do one move, everything was fine.
But when it was doing the second move, there was an error that changed the game state
and that would always make this move look like it's more valuable than it was.
And the further down it went, the more valuable the moves became, even though the move might have been shit.
But the deviation from the actual game state became bigger and bigger,
so that it would take moves that weren't useful, just because it thought,
oh, in the end it's going to be really good.
And the issue was I basically had a reference to a list and was filling stuff in that list
instead of copying the list and then filling the list.
Happens. Unfortunately.
But finding that one was a bitch.
Right on. I need to do some inventory management over here.
Alyssa, can I throw the question ball to you?
No problem. You had mentioned, like I said, deck building game.
I love, I relate a lot with what you're saying about Magic because I love playing just like fun decks
and I love deck building, but I'm actually crap at any kind of like competitive element
or like taking it beyond just like having fun with it.
So that kind of like resonated with me when you were talking about deck building before.
And deck building with a roguelike game is actually a super good mix.
And it's just really interesting with how you kind of merge those two elements.
So I was wondering if you could talk about how you kind of fell into the roguelike elements of this game a little bit.
Well, I mean, I don't think I fell into them.
It's sort of they were always there.
As soon as I had the core gameplay, I knew I kind of wanted to do a single player thing.
I didn't want to do multiplayer.
Both for sort of pragmatic reasons like I don't want to build sort of networking code.
Also, you know, as an indie, if you make a multiplayer game and not enough people play, then it's dead in the water.
And it's going to be dead forever.
And I didn't really want to go there. I didn't want to run the risk of sort of building something.
And it also felt like it would be bigger than anything I would build.
I would be doing on my own because I knew I was going to do most of this on my own.
Ended up biting off more than I could chew anyway.
This thing is huge, it took five years.
But I'm glad I never picked multiplayer.
And I don't know, the roguelike, I mean, that's sort of the inspiration of FTL, is
sort of obvious from the map.
And that's sort of, we talked about Banner Saga, even though that's not a roguelike,
but I think FTL really sort of gripped me with sort of the replayability.
And I really enjoy procedural generation.
So that's kind of where this came in.
I was like, all right, I really like card games, deck-building games, I like roguelikes.
Let's just put them together and make something cool.
Speaking of the map, the map we see currently, which is this very FDL-like map, is...
It's like the process of three months of iteration, of coming up with different versions, of not doing this kind of map, but doing something card-based or something different.
I just iterated away and came up with a lot of interesting ideas, but nothing that really worked for Noble Prophet.
With a card game, it just ended up being too complex.
And I ended up rolling back everything and going with the basic, boring map.
Which, I don't know, still sort of...
Oh, man.
But I mean the map works fine.
Yeah, it works.
And at some point I was just like, fuck, I need to stop iterating.
I need to do the game, make the game.
Um, so...
That, that, actually, that's a good question.
Why did you think, um, uh, well...
Like, you kind of just said it, like, you, like, you, you, you thought it was boring.
You, you wanted to improve it and make it better.
But, um, I'm kind of at a point where I'm like, wait, like, if it wasn't...
Like there is a- like I guess like we're all kind of- we're making things, we're looking to hope to make the best magical thing that will be perfect in our heads.
What made you think that this, you know, doing something that was sort of similar to what other devs had done wasn't quite lining up?
I'm sorry, that's a weird-
My question didn't come out great, but I'm just sort of like-
It's kind of worth interrogating, like what made you go...
What- what do you think is the- like like the- cause the version I see is super functional, I love the narrative events that pop up.
Um, what sort of makes you go,
Hang on, this isn't everything it could be, I guess.
Well, I mean, I've sort of made my peace with the map because it is functional and it's not the heart of the game.
Like, I mean, the heart of the game is sort of the travel, but whether the map is this kind of map or a different kind of map actually doesn't make that much of a difference.
Let me just sort of, for a few people that are watching, can I share the screen? I probably should be able to.
Yeah, it'll be a very tiny screen.
Oh yeah, fair enough.
I wanted to show some of the early concepts.
If anybody bought the artbook, there's a bunch of early concepts on the map travel gameplay.
We tried isometric views and car-based things.
Sorry, now I lost my train of thought.
I suppose it's kind of one of the things too when you're working as like a solo dev or like on a really small team too, you don't have that constant kind of checks and balances to be like, okay, do I need to keep developing this or is it good how it is?
Absolutely. Like I'm, speaking candidly, I'm very proud of Nowhere Prophet. I'm very happy with the thing I built. But I would never do it again. Because I did it on my by myself. And I just sort of, I
Like this, the example of this map iteration.
We had a lot of cool ideas, like I did a lot of brainstorming with my art director, but
he was also, he was never on an even level because he was freelancing.
It was never sort of an, okay, let's talk about what's best for the game, it's more
like a service provider.
And we had a lot of cool ideas, and I'm looking at sort of the art book there.
But I think at that point it would have been really useful to have somebody to butt heads
with and sort of go, do we really need to do this?
Is it really something that's...
I'm gonna make the game better.
Or is the time invested better elsewhere?
Which is one of the big drawbacks of doing it alone.
There's nobody to sort of keep your weird...
Because at my heart, because you introduced me as a lead developer,
which sort of doesn't quite sit right with me,
because I'm a game designer, goddammit!
Sorry.
But like, keeping the inner designer in check is hard.
I just want to do everything perfect, be innovative, have some cool new ideas,
and don't do it like the other guys do it, because people have seen it.
But you'll never release a game that way.
I spend a lot of time on the map, which is a waste of time, because I ended up with the thing I started on.
But I learned a lot, I had a lot of cool ideas, maybe something of that is another game at some point.
I'm not on a lot of, I only sub in for these GDC streams every now and then, but it's kind
of shocking how often you'll hear a developer be like, yeah, no, I love this game, I love
what I made, but I would never do this again.
And yet, and yet you're kind of thinking about doing it again already, aren't you?
I mean, not Nowhere at Profit, but like, you know, you're already, I mean, you're, you're
working on Nowhere at Profit right now, but like, this isn't the game that makes you quick
video games, if I, if I have that right.
Wow, this got really depressing.
Well, I'm not sure.
To be, I said, to be sort of candid, I don't know what I'm, what I'm going to do
next. People keep asking, and they've been asking even before the game launched,
what's going to be next, what's next for you? And I'm like...
Fuck, I don't even know. Once this game is out, I can stop fiddling with it, and I still want to
fiddle with it. I need to do bug fixes, there's still bugs coming in. I need to improve the AI,
it fixes AI bug, but there's still ways to make it better and less stupid. Then I probably need
to do some small content updates. There's console versions, which I'm not going to make myself,
but I need to be involved in because I want to make sure the controls are right.
And then it's suddenly 2020. This is how it goes.
And then just gonna take a serious break.
Because the key problem on the development pane of No More Prophet was not necessarily
how long it took, I said five years for the first prototypes to release, but the fact
that I did it by myself.
And not all by myself, I had people helping, but nobody on an even footing I guess.
And I would never ever do that again for a project that's even remotely of that size,
because it's just going to make me terribly unhappy.
So it sort of depends, like if I end up with a team or sort of a team I can join or collaborate
with, then I'd love doing something like that again, but otherwise it's small stuff for
like doing it in a different setting or surrounding, because that just did not do it for me.
Right on, I am powering up this army here.
We are 20 minutes or so into our chat.
We hope you folks at home are having a good time.
We'd love to take your questions for Martin, if you've got them.
Martin, I am going to go ahead and get to a different topic.
I sort of skimmed over the art direction.
Like you said, you had a talented, contracted art director who worked with you on this.
This game, I think, still stands out because it uses a...
Like you said earlier, it's not a bunch of white guys in dusters roaming around the desert.
It's instead a bunch of multicultural, though Indian-inspired folks wandering around the desert.
Some with dusters, like our heroes, some with...
Colored robes.
Colored robes, yeah.
What was, I guess, like, you know, even though there was an art director you worked with,
there was still a specific creative influence you were drawing on.
Would you mind, like, breaking down some of what you were thinking about with, you said
you were drawing on your own sort of, you know, your own background, your own heritage
with some of this.
Would you mind, like, explaining how you translated that, you know, like, because, you know, obviously
this is, this is, this is not what India looks like right now, to the best of my knowledge.
I never meant to be, like, I never wanted to sort of reproduce India in some way.
I know it's sort of difficult to say, I mean the whole art direction process was like four months of intensive sort of talk back and forth and sort of figuring out how the game should look.
I sort of started the process with sort of a very strong vision already, sort of like I want these people to be just sort of an Indian inspired world, I want to be very colorful, I want to be on a strange planet.
It's sleek science fiction that's broken down cyberpunk aesthetic.
And sort of actually sort of the other day posted these in the discord.
Unfortunately, I cannot really share them because then it's tiny as well.
I found a bunch of old PDFs of mine.
I just sort of collected artwork I found on the internet and sort of searched for
specific things to give a starter, sort of an inspiration point for what sort of
the art direction would then start off on.
There's a bunch of really cool stuff, like this one sheet called Humans, which is just
like pictures of sort of old Indian dudes with like paint on them and like Arab sort
of head scarves and high fashion and like, I don't know, it's a bunch of interesting
stuff in there.
But I don't really know how I came to that starting point, because I was just, I don't
know, I was looking for an interesting world that I was...
sort of I wanted to make a world as well.
Like I wanted to do so many things.
Coming off of Banner Saga, which really touched me, I really enjoyed the world, exploring
that world.
And that's one of the sort of the points I sort of started on.
I wanted to make a world that is sort of mine, that's unique to me, that's interesting, that …
Maybe I'll make a tabletop roleplaying game in this world at some point.
You know, that's sort of where I started off.
And for some reason, because I like post-apocalypse and because I sort of felt I wanted to pull some of my background in there,
this is sort of where we ended up at.
Funny aside, which hasn't so much to do with the setting but with the art style,
in the early days I was very enamored with low poly styles.
Think of something like Overland, what they have.
I have a bunch of references in here.
One of them is actually from the Overland lead artist, funnily enough.
We actually sort of tried some 3D aspects out but ended up with this sort of, actually by sort of going over 3D, we played around with shaders and some sort of toon shaders.
We ended up with something that was very sort of black, dark sort of shadows and sort of colors.
And from then we sort of, oh this is interesting but we don't want to do 3D.
We sort of ended up, because Anjin is really the art director.
is really sort of a comic fan.
We ended up looking at graphic novels and Hellboy, which has a really strong aesthetic,
black shadows, very slim highlights.
And we used that as a cue to build the visual style, which I'm really, really happy with.
That's one of the things that people constantly give positive feedback about.
The game just looks gorgeous.
Nice, uh, I don't know why this guy's helping me out. He's pushed that rock back there. Yeah, I fixed that bug. It's not gonna happen in the future
At least I hope or at least
Oh, he's just oh well he that's actually clever he's just inciting his guy he's just playing a lot of cards because this guy gets
Bigger. Oh, that's a problem
Oh, that's a problem. Okay, I need to figure this out.
Um, uh, anyway, uh, Alyssa, can I throw the question ball to you?
Yeah, yeah. Um, I'm gonna circle back a little bit, uh, back when you're talking about everyone
clamoring to find out what you're gonna do next. Um, but in terms of your development,
you didn't do an early access period. You did like a beta for a couple months, correct?
No, there was a, there was a first access.
Starting at the end of 2017 on itch only.
So it was available on itch from October 2017 to like March this year or February this year.
Something like that.
Okay so how would you say that feedback in that period affected your development?
Was it useful?
How did you kind of parse through what you were getting back?
It was super useful.
Like the game is so much better for it.
I mean, the thing why I went to Itch and not to Steam was sort of to avoid having a shitty
Steam launch, because if you go out of early access, people don't care as much, then, oh,
I'm on Steam finally.
So I didn't want to run that risk of being this, alright, it's out of early access, nobody
cares, and I didn't need to do the early access for the money, I just wanted to build a community
and get some feedback from people.
And it did a lot, like I said, it was in early access for one and a half years.
Like one thing for example which is sort of obvious is the wound system.
That was sort of in in the beginning but in the beginning followers could take up to three
wounds and would die with the fourth or with the third I don't quite remember and it's
sort of just ended up being to people who didn't really care.
It just ended up too finicky so I did a lot of sort of fine tuning on the wound system
and sort of this is also at some point when the blessing system came in that actually
came out of a streamer that streamed a bunch of times during the first access.
He's actually in the game because during the first access people could buy the game for a more expensive price and then get their face as one of the units.
The steward you're using right now is actually Inky, he's one of the people that came in during the first access and he provided just a basic introduction.
Shit ton of valuable feedback. He's been with the game for over a year at this point and it's helped me rebalance a bunch of times.
And that's just invaluable, especially if you're on your own.
You just end up with one perspective. So having other people is really good.
Nice. Yeah, I remember, I don't remember where I read it, but back when Early Access was starting to become a thing, there was...
People saying like, oh, well, you only get one launch, like even if you launch an early access, that's going to be your impactful moment.
And there's a risk people won't care when you go 1.0.
So what you did kind of mitigated that in a way, because I didn't know it was an early access because I went to the steam page and it wasn't there.
So it just looked like a regular full launch.
So that's interesting.
That was that was kind of the goal.
That's actually if people are interested, there's a blog post I wrote up on Gamma Sutra blog.
About half a year after the early access launch to have the numbers and talk about the feedback a bit.
Also one thing, the blessing feature, that actually sort of came out of the stream as mentioned,
because Plaid, he streamed, and since you can rename followers, whenever a follower would do
the killing blow to the enemy, he would rename that follower based on one of the people from
his chat. Which gave me the idea of adding value to that final blow.
And making that an interesting decision, like who is on the board, who am I going to sort of time this to have the final blow.
Which is sort of where the blessing mechanic came from, which is really nice because it sort of interacts with the wounding mechanic.
Like, do you want to put in some wounded guys because then you can sort of, if they get the blessing because they do the final blow, they get healed for free, which saves you some resources.
So that's sort of interesting as a, I don't know, as of where this thing came from, I guess.
Yeah, well, it's kind of like a.
social feature and also a strategic feature.
Yeah.
I'm going to pull a question from chat where Kthulu wants to know if even though the game
style has changed, is there anything of the original party when they had individual decks
used as inspiration for the leader classes?
Yeah, I mean sort of from the...
from the world building, the idea of technopathy, or I'm not sure how to pronounce it even,
English is hard, I can do it in German, I can't do it in English, I'm just gonna go
with technopathy, was there from the start.
Like there was the idea of these operators, frequency operators that can manipulate technology,
and the initial sort of warrior followers you had were all technopaths.
They were all sort of power people in that sense, and they would sort of defend the convoy.
And the classes, the class ideas and class names and class images are sort of still the same.
Like, I have ideas for more classes because if you have three people, you need more than four classes to put in stuff.
So there's some names and ideas for future classes, but making a class for the current iteration of the game is pretty intensive.
Because you need a bunch of split- you need cards, you need to find out sort of deck builds and how to sort of put them in their different unlockables.
But it's sort of like all the, what used to be individual heroes are now sort of individual classes for their character.
Nice.
How's it going, Brett?
I am hanging in here.
Well, you're doing good so far.
The Witcher's
the Witcher card game and I was thinking a lot about deck building playing that because I've
Noticed that as a my kind of player deck building is a scary feat for me in games like this
I thought I talk too much here about extra miniatures, which is a game
I play where you're essentially always deck building because you're
Changing the ships you want to fly in, that's like building a deck.
But when it comes to putting a deck of cards together that I'm randomly pulling things from
and trying to figure out a combo, that is very frightening to me.
What did you sort of learn about teaching players, like,
hey, you should be thinking about pulling-
like, how did you teach players deck building?
I'm genuinely sort of wanting to know your thoughts about that.
Actually, I'm not sure I'm doing it enough.
There's a rulebook that sort of has a section on strategy and how to build a deck.
But the game actually doesn't do a lot of it, sort of teaching you how to build a good deck.
And it's hard, like...
What's a good deck? A good deck is generally not too big, because then you sort of...
Limit your choices.
I don't know, it's...
It's a good question, I don't think I have an answer for it.
I think I could do the job better than I do.
Um...
Yeah.
I guess technically it's a bad question then.
Um...
Is deck building just actual magic?
Deck building.
It's magic.
Um...
Uh...
I guess then let's talk about the individual cards.
Like, where did you sort of...
Like, once you realize you're doing a card system, it's sort of like...
It's a little bit Hearthstone-y in some ways.
You know, attacking a hero, a mana system.
But um...
Where did you start thinking up card ideas and hierarchies for how these cards would work?
What was your process for saying, OK, I need this kind of cards, I'm curious what your workflow was for designing units as cards?
I went through a lot of iterations.
It starts with, what's my basic attack health stats?
So
gameplay changes that I still wanted to have in there.
Then it was a little bit about giving them different identities, sort of finding different parts in the gameplay that makes sense to sort of build around and put them to the factions.
I think that's something that also could have been done better, sort of could have cleaned that up a little more.
I think in hindsight, 10 factions is probably sort of cluttering it up too much for the player.
I just liked all of them too much to, you know, scrap any one of them.
And then it sort of... I had, I don't know, I guess 300 something units and I had them in the first access and then did a balancing through a bunch of out that just didn't work and replaced them and sort of kept fine-tuning sort of...
what they were and where they belong to.
And I said there's a bunch of moments where I just shoveled stuff around to make the faction
identity stronger.
It's like, alright, this guy is nice but he needs to be over there, and then this guy
needs to go over here because I need to have equal numbers on the factions because they
have chances to roll, and that kind of thing.
Right on.
Alyssa, I need to pay attention to this text.
I think you're going to throw the questions all your way.
So I think I ask this, like, some variation of this question every time we do a stream with someone who has roguelike elements in their game,
but the thing that's persistently interesting to me with roguelike games is that you take failure or losing a unit or something and you make it into kind of like a positive learning moment.
So I guess, how did you balance with the roguelike elements in this game? How did you balance...
Kind of that fail, like quote-unquote fail state, like punishing the player, they're losing something forever,
with encouraging them to try new things and learning from their mistakes.
Oh god, so many good and hard questions.
I mean, you don't lose everything, there's some progress you can make in the game, like
you can unlock new stuff and you can sort of unlock new stuff, like new perks for the
convoys you have.
So even if you lose something, you still sort of make some progress somewhere, which I feel
even though each convoy has three perks and they're sort of...
There's small bonuses in the travel gameplay.
Like, you heal a little better, you sell stuff for a little bit more batteries,
that kind of thing.
Nothing that has a big impact, but stuff that feels nice,
and that you sort of have fun unlocking.
So I think that's a good sort of start to make that fail state not just feel super bad,
but again, sort of, you don't want to overdo it,
because then you can just grind your way through the roguelike
by just getting really good by having high stats.
So it's just like small bonuses.
And I think sort of the...
The audience that likes to play card games likes to have interesting puzzles.
You start to turn, there's a situation on the board, there's a situation in your hand,
and a lot of the stuff you can do is very predictable.
There's some random effects, but for example Hearthstone has a lot of unpredictability
to it.
Which makes it really good for new players because they can just win by sheer luck and they have a lot of fuck yeah moment
But for me, it's just it's too much like that's one of the things I really don't like about a hearthstone
There's just too much randomness. I can just make or break a game
so sort of
You start you have this sort of interesting puzzle. These are my cards
this is the situation and then you sort of look for what's the
The optimal play for this turn and maybe for the next turn and maybe the turn after that
And that's sort of always an interesting puzzle
I'm not sure what the game is about, but I think that's what the people play for.
They don't play to sort of win the game, they play to have interesting puzzles and sort of have
them transmute over time.
Right on.
I am going to quickly get myself more armor.
And then checking my question pile...
Uh, you just sort of talked about puzzles and like stringing together combos and I noticed that like, you know, when I'm trying to set up, you know, when I'm picking moves, I'm sort of saying,
Okay, what's the unit that can match my energy now versus what's the unit that when I play it now and then next turn I can play something else?
Um, in your head, like, I guess, like, what was your idea? What do you think makes a fun combo?
In a game like this. Like how do you...
That's sort of a generic strange question.
And I apologize for that.
But I sort of think it's worth noting.
Because you can sort of say, oh like...
When I put this card down, this next card will...
Do 3 damage to everything.
And then you go, actually no one uses it.
Because it's not even fun.
Because for some reason.
I guess that's where my head is right now.
I mean sort of a good combo I think...
Needs to feel like the player discovered it.
Like it needs to be like, oh, oh, if I do this and then this, this makes a lot of sense.
Like you see this one piece that we're like, all right, this is okay, but I'm not sure.
And you see this other piece and you go like, oh, wait, wait, there's these two together,
you know? And if the piece says A, says A, use B for me, and B says A, I work well with A,
then it just, you know, it's boring. But it's interesting if there's like,
sort of, if you can find them and if they're in a lot of sort of axes.
One thing I sort of found out in the design process of the cards, and specifically again when I redid the equipment system a couple...
...throughout the entire equipment system and redid it, because it just didn't combo well enough.
And I did try to come up with better effects that had more combo potential.
Kind of always err on the side of, alright, this thing needs to work in a way that a lot of other things can work off of it.
If that makes sense. I struggle to come up with an actual example right now, but...
I get what you mean. I play a lot of Hitman.
And there's this really cool phenomenon in that game where you have these moments where you do something really cool.
And you're like, I thought of this. This is great. I solved this big murder puzzle. I executed this really cool thing.
And then the developers are back. They're like, no, we actually meant for you to do that.
But crafting those moments where it feels like you did something really creative and substantial is a difficult beast to tame and explain, I'd imagine.
Yeah, I mean there's one example is there's robust units that when they get killed they
heal up so they get reset to 1 health and they get pushed back and if they cannot be
pushed back anymore they die, which actually is pretty strong, I'm thinking about nerfing
that a little bit.
But like, they get reset to 1 health and this reset to 1 health could be just reset, but
it's a heal, which means everything that triggers a heal triggers really well, works really
well with robust units.
And I think that's just making a lot of pieces that interact with a lot of pieces
allows people to find enough of them to make an interesting deck out of it.
Right on. Just a heads up for chat, we got about 15 minutes left in our conversation with Martin.
We would love it if you would ask some questions. That sounded a little more desperate.
Please, please.
Oh dear, my wifi is acting up.
I hope that doesn't cause problems for the stream, which is on a wired connection.
Okay, cool. Looking good, looking good.
But yeah, we'd love to hear your questions. That wasn't...
I mean, you know, there's only a little less written that, like, you know, questions...
Questions and gameplay can be hard.
Martin, I guess we were the GDC Twitch channel. We can talk about GDC. You have a GDC 2011 shirt.
Let's move a little bit outside the world of making nowhere profit, I guess.
You said this year you were skipping GDC because you were taking an off-conference here, and I imagine you had to actually ship your game.
That's important.
How, you know, as a game designer, I guess we haven't gotten to talk about your background at all.
So, like, what was your foundation as a game designer and what made you want to make games like Nowhere Profit?
And say, like, I can make a cool world that's expressed through cards and numbers and have it feel as real as a book or as other things, I guess.
Forgive the cross-medium comparison, if you will.
No, it's all good.
So, I don't know, my background sort of...
I always...
Like...
So...
It took me a while to understand that not everybody knows what they want to do with their life.
Because I always knew.
Like I was six years old and I was making terrible games that didn't work on a CD64 Commodore in BASIC.
I was making sort of, I have a sort of box with trashy, terrible roller dice to move card board games and built as like an eight year old.
I don't know, I always made games. I spent a lot of time in my high school years sort of modding Quake, which sort of dates me, I guess.
Quake 1, Quake 2, Quake 3, did a bunch of mods.
So, games were always something I was really interested in and spent a lot of time on.
I learned a lot.
I learned 3D modeling from making Quake II weapon mods, kind of.
And then, I actually studied architecture, because when I was done with school I wanted
to study and there was no real game options.
And I didn't want to do coding either, because that seemed too dry.
I wanted to do something more creative.
So I started architecture, was done with that, and was like, ah, fuck it, I want to do games instead, and went on doing games.
I don't know, what do you, I don't know, like, uh, do you, what do you still think about your architecture?
Like, like, do you still, like, does any of that still influence your work as a designer?
I mean, it, it, the architecture degree has, has, uh, in...
Irrevocably, man damn English is hard, irrevocably, irrevocably, whatever, I'm not gonna repeat it a fourth time,
changed and sort of bent my aesthetic sense, like people hate naked concrete walls and I love them.
It's just, that's just what happens to you I guess.
So I think it sort of influenced my aesthetic sensibilities a lot and it's also sort of given me a sharper sort of...
focus of a designer in general, because even though it sort of feels like it's very different,
architecture and game design are actually sort of close, because in both cases you're not the guy
necessarily making everything, but you need to be the guy that sort of keeps craft and arts
sort of in balance, and make sure the thing gets built, functions, and is sort of aesthetically
pleasing. Is that sort of an answer, I guess? It is. Yeah, that makes sense.
Sorry, I'm sitting here looking trying to figure out how the heck I'm gonna win this fight.
Yeah, you're actually fighting one of the bosses that I tweaked down a bit.
I hope you updated your game on Steam.
Nope.
Um...
He's, uh, his, his, like, he was actually the one that I got the most complaints about,
which is funny because in, in the beta test, I don't, not a lot of people complained about him.
He, his effect is whenever one of his guys gets killed, he gets them back on his hands for cheaper
and can play him again, which basically just means he never runs out of guys.
In the early release version, the effect would trigger for every guy you kill.
So it doesn't matter how many you killed, as long as he had room in his hand, he would get them back.
And now it's been changed to it only triggers on the first guy you kill.
So it's sort of the question is, which one do you want to pick off?
In this case, which one will he run against you to get back?
So it becomes a more active player choice.
It's not like, alright, whatever I do, he's going to get them back.
Which one can I...
Take off is the least bad for me to give them back to him.
So that's interesting.
I find.
Look what I got past him.
When we were talking before the stream, you mentioned like another
similar tweak you've had to make where there there is some system
that you change so that it became more involved on the player
side. So became a more strategic thing too, but you have another
boss, which was always whenever you dealt damage to him with
a follower the following you would.
So now it's always the first one each turn, so the question is which one of mine am I
going to sacrifice to make room for the other people, which makes them a lot more interesting.
I need to do a bunch of other tweaks, like for example the Glory Seeker you just fought.
He always gets his people back, and his deck has a lot of synergy with stuff that does
effects when they enter battle.
So he puts them out, gets an incisional effect, he loses them, gets them back, puts them out
again.
And I sort of had to lower the synergy of the enemy decks in the early levels a little bit.
Because if he just pumps out stuff all the time, he just gets too strong when your deck is still trying to find its footing.
Like in the first map, it's currently still sort of the hardest because your deck is sort of unoptimized.
You're sort of trying to get stuff together to build up a strategy, find some equipment that synergizes with something you can build.
And then sort of find people to put in there to make it stronger and stronger.
And early on, if the enemies are just really well sort of synergized,
you'll have trouble sort of keeping pace.
Nice.
Brent, I'm going to do a two-parter question where I post something and then you polish it, okay?
Sure.
So you talked earlier about wanting to kind of create a world.
So I'm just going to kind of segue into narrative stuff a little bit.
And then you had mentioned that fight in Mass Effect with Saren,
it's like one of like...
My favorite moments in games ever.
I love Mass Effect 1.
Oh god, it's so good.
Do the other games ever quite capture that narrative side?
I still sometimes watch the YouTube video of the conversation with Sovereign,
the first one you have, because it's just such an awesome...
God, I get goosebumps.
Oh yeah, like playing through that was like this moment.
I loved it.
But I kind of want to ask, I haven't played the game, Brian has, so I want to kind of segue into more about like the narrative side of things and how that kind of, that initial thought may have carried throughout the game, or if it didn't, or kind of go from there.
So I don't know, Brian, if you can elaborate as someone who's played the game more on that.
I think it does. I mean, I'd say my only comment is that the convoy still feels a little introversional, like even though there's a whole crowd of people down here. I love this graphic representation of...
All my units have gotten a little attached to some of them as they get kills, but if I'm being frankly honest, it's still...
It's missing a little bit of that Oregon Trail, you know, X person you cared about has died of dysentery.
Um, uh, where that bandit...
Oh, it's called dysentery.
I would've said dysentery.
Our language stinks.
Look, we're not here to debate the English language, guys.
I was like 10 when I discovered that one. It was a horrible word.
I was like 9.
I think the...
But I think the underlying theme is very obvious and clear.
What is it?
How would you describe it?
Um...
This is not a quiz. There's no wrong answer.
Oh, there's a wrong answer, alright.
There's always a wrong answer when you're hosting a stream.
So I got the sense when I'm playing this game, like, I am searching for an unattainable...
For almost an unattainable goal, you know.
Like, we're looking for...
We're on a journey to the Holy Land, if you will.
Like, that kind of...
That's very instinctual as I'm going.
I'm going somewhere that no one believes I can go.
Like, being on a sacred mission like that.
Um, and having this crew of followers with me, um, uh, my, my sense for them is like occasionally,
like when they show up in the chats, like I can see when their name is highlighted in
green and I get the, you know, that they've done something that helps me out.
Um, and I know that these are the people who will get me there.
What's interesting to me is that I get way more sense of character from the people I
meet in this game, from the shamans, from the guides who I couldn't afford to hire.
And so it got some of my people killed.
Um, the- sort of the- the thing we're pushing against, the other people in this world, the people we encounter,
give me way more of a sense of the world and the sense of how people are.
And it's interesting, cause like, you sort of get from the idea of an apocalypse that everything's dying.
What I love about my sense of this game is that,
every- everything actually feels pretty alive, like everyone's got a way of living, um,
the slave stuff is- is a li-
the slave stuff is sadly not cool, and by- that's a very light way to put it.
No, no, no, no, like slav-
Jesus Christ.
The slavery thing is the only thing where I'm like, wow, this is like the biggest sense I have that the world is not right.
But there is also a sense that people are alive.
So those are the things that have stuck with me as a player so far.
These militaristic factions that have popped up.
I thought it was interesting.
I was paying attention to, you know, I think I have in here some units in my convoy.
Uh, that's not the right deck, that's not the right button over here.
Uh, there's a couple units who have kind of a more of a colonial outlook about them, like they're wearing sort of...
Yeah, the Rajguard.
The Rajguard, yeah. And I have one of the Scion guys.
The Strategist's down there, I think, too.
Yeah, I have a strategist right here.
No.
If the YouTuber is the ultimate colonist, I don't know.
Um, there's- there are some sort of a...
Like- like, I like that sense of it.
I like the sense that there are ways that people, you know, who seek power have dressed themselves like other people who are just sort of trying to get by who have dressed themselves.
Um, it gives me a sense of place in being.
I- I know this is a question for you, but I guess I am the interviewed right now.
But yeah, that's- that's my- that's my sense-
Here we go, the Scion Instigator. Like, look at this.
Like, the guy's got a suit, uh, he's got a-
Not just a suit, he's wearing like a, you know, high-necked-
Fancy, fancy shirt.
Yeah, um, Harris licked back.
Man, it looks like he has a gut stone and a comb.
But yeah, that's where I'm at with the game, I guess.
Yeah.
I mean, that's sort of what I was aiming for.
I sort of agree with your assessment that the people in the convoy don't get enough character.
In hindsight, I feel like the event system is the one thing that would have...
I'm not, it isn't quite where it should be.
I did it by myself, most of it.
I didn't write all the events, because that's way too much anyway.
But I had to sort of, at some point, just sort of get it done.
But I think, especially the event system, would have benefited,
like there's a bunch of events, there's a whole bunch of events,
that are just like, hey, you meet some people, let's fight.
If I would have just scrapped those, put markers on the map, alright this is a fight, start
the fight and then have the guy on the other side give you like a one line bark, like I'm
gonna make you my slaves, that's enough.
Like we don't need all this text, it's great for world building but it's a lot of cruft.
I would have rather sort of boiled down to fewer events and have them be more complex
and have more events sort of involve your people on sort of like strings where they,
One of your guys is the
I don't know.
He's a war criminal.
This is a story, and it's randomly, you pick one of your guys every time, or like, every
fifth match you get a war criminal.
We pick one of them, he's a war criminal, and if you don't kill him, you can have the
story that sort of sometimes, like, and then you get to a milestone, and it sort of interacts
with a milestone in different ways based on which of these people you have.
That'd be super cool!
But...
Yeah, I think that was the...
The gist of the question I was trying to figure out words for before was with all the fights
where you mentioned tweaking them so there's more strategic player choice.
I was wondering if there's a similar thread in the narrative elements of the game or the
conversations you have with the events.
I mean, the one thing that I think really helps the event system is that there's moments
where the event pops up and there's a picture of one of you guys on the left and he goes
like, hey, I can do something.
There's some extra text.
Basically what the game does is it looks for a specific faction or specific rarity.
Like, do you have a beast that's at least a rare?
And then that unlocks options where you go like,
alright, let the beast snarl at these people to intimidate them.
Or send that guy to run a distraction because he's a bandit and he's good at distracting.
Or make that guy blow something up because he's from the Union, and the Unioners, they blow things up.
And that's where people get a little bit more fleshed out,
but it still doesn't give them a lot of character, because there's not a lot of personality behind these.
Because there's very little moments.
But that's really interesting things, I think.
No, I do like the composition of your party can kind of play into these random encounters,
or give you additional things you wouldn't have without that specific party member.
So that's great, I like that.
We only have a few minutes left here. I really want to finish this fight.
We're just going to wrap up today. Thank you all for watching.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah. Well I'm going to...
Oh. Well, I'm going to...
First I'm going to make sure that guy's out of the way.
And then steadily wear this guy down.
Thank you all for joining us on the GDC Twitch channel today.
We are thrilled to be joined by Martin.
The game is No More Profit, published by No More Robots.
We forgot to disclose up front that No More Profot...
No more...
No where profit, which is published by No More Robots, is advised by Simon Carles, who
is bossman, GDC bossman, vice president of GDC, blah blah blah.
There's a connection.
We forgot to mention out top.
Sorry about that.
He helped out on this game, so we would like to both give him credit and acknowledge.
A, you know, disclosure. Disclosures are important.
Um, uh...
You spend a lot of time making sure my English isn't terrible in the event.
Yeah, right on. Um, uh, we, uh...
Um, excuse me, I'm just gonna...
Um, from there, we would also like to invite folks who are following us to, uh...
Officially follow us to click on the follow button here on the GDC Twitch channel,
because if you'd like other cool games that are coming out this year,
there's a chance we might have an interview with the developers.
We are working to talk to the folks behind Elsinore right now. I've reached out to talk to some folks behind
hopefully games like Church in the Darkness and
Oh God, there's another one that I'm actually trying to line up. Oh, yeah creature in the well creature in the well
We're hopefully gonna have a stream with them
and with that
I'm
Sweet good timing
I'm going to actively wrap things up. Thank you everyone for watching. Thank for you for the question that we got from chat Alyssa
Thank you for helping out and Martin as always. Thank you for joining us
Thank you for having me.
Thank you.
Have a good day.
Bye.
Bye bye.