I'm here, well I'm Richard, I'm here from the UK, I'm going to talk about my game Kitty
Power's Matchmaker, which you may have seen. Let me start my slideshow. Oops, shouldn't
be there. That's better. So I'm going to try and come in a little bit early so people can
ask questions at the end.
I'll try not to waffle too much.
So I've been making games since 1996.
And all that time, it's been my personal holy grail
to make a game that was an expression of everything
I love as possible, just like every other game designer
I know.
A game that I could direct and not
have to answer to anybody else.
A game that my audience could play and get a real clear
insight into what I have to say as a designer.
and something unique that might add a new color to the rainbow of video games.
A couple of years ago I finally found myself with the chance to make that dream happen.
I left a well-paid job in AAA games after 10 years with enough cash to start something up.
And a friend and now ex-colleague had recommended a graduate programmer to me
who was very keen to get into the games industry.
I've seen success and failures, so I was conservative in my approach to this new venture.
So I got a contract job at Media Molecule, working on the fabulous Tearaway.
The contract really allowed me the freedom to work on my own projects
without the fear of the dreaded conflict of interest clause.
Working during the day gave me enough income to pay a full-time
legislating programmer and myself.
Enough to save for other contractors later on, like audio designers and artists and those kind of people.
And enough security to not have to worry about anything other than making a good game, which is kind of what you want really.
So I challenged myself to go against the grain of death,
destruction, and zombies that you tend to find in most games.
I had, after all, spent decades making driving and
shooting games about destroying people, cars, and
buildings. I wanted to see if I could create a game about
love, social interactions, and relationships, but with my own
stupid sense of humor.
And there is no better way to represent my stupid sense of humor
than my alter ego, Kitty Powers.
You can see there.
I'd been doing drag in my spare time for about five years
and I wanted an opportunity to take it to the next level.
So I decided to put her in the game, but
I wanted to make her presence meaningful.
Um...
What kind of game did I think Kitty would fit well into?
What I needed was a brief. No, not that kind of brief, Kitty.
A kind of checklist of all the things I wanted it to be.
So I didn't want any violence or destruction, but love and baby-making.
Procedural systems, because I love them.
Procedural characters with real humanity that would feel like they'd been designed,
rather than randomly generated.
People that you'd want to help and not shoot in the face.
I wanted a very English sense of humor because that's what I know best. Despite the pressure to
Americanize it, my argument against that being that the best British comedy such as Monty
Python and Ab Fab, etc. didn't need to be Americanized for people to get it. And I wanted it
to be a premium product with no in-app purchases like The Room, which is also made in
Guilford. So after all that, it seemed pretty clear to me that I was going to be
We'd make a dating agency simulator with Kitty Powers as your host. It would be so easy. We'd
just make a game similar to Guess Who, but without the demonic children. But where you're
matching procedural clients with potential dates and then seeing how it all panned out in
excruciating detail. And Kitty Powers would be your boss. On hand to be sarcastic and
saucy at every opportunity. It would be easy and sell millions, or so we thought.
So before we get into some detail, here's the launch trailer of the game to give you a taste of the flavour.
OMG, put your hands together for Miss Kitty Powers!
Ooh, hello kittens. I'm Kitty Powers, matchmaker extraordinaire.
As we all know, the path to true love is long and hard, which is why I created my new dating simulator, Kitty Powers Matchmaker.
I've got a little black book full of lonely hearts.
This is your job to find them love.
Help them through delicate dating dilemmas.
Guide their passage through the turbulent tunnel of love.
Outrageous!
Hello Kitty Powers Dating Agency.
You can even match-mate your mates and send them on dates.
Will they end up in the penthouse of passion, or the dustbin of broken dreams?
Sounds scary, doesn't it? But don't despair, kittens, because I, Kitty Powers, will be there for you every step of the way.
Every client deserves their happy ending, and it's your job to give them one.
Coming soon, kittens.
There she is.
So yeah, I was quite happy with that, actually.
Being a game about relationships,
it was important to me to be inclusive, accessible,
and respectful to all types of people.
This, of course, sounds sweet and lovely,
but it brought with it its own set of issues and challenges
that we had to meet sensitively and thoughtfully.
We were here to bring our players laughter and fun,
not offend them or make them feel left out.
We really wanted to make a game about how people really are and how dating really is.
Not a soft focus romance fest, but you know, the kind of gritty details about the way real
people think and act when they're dating.
At the heart of this are the characters and the procedural system we use to generate and
represent them.
So we wanted to create characters with depth and humanity, not just boring archetypes but
real people with flaws and foibles. We wanted the player to be able to think about themselves
in the terms of the game and identify with these characters. We started with personality,
the more scientific and psychological side of things. We wanted to create a system simple
enough to be easy to communicate but complex enough to represent everyone, at least
approximately.
So each character has five personality categories and each of them can be one extreme or its
opposite. Which ones do you think you would be? In spite of not wanting to generalize, we had
to put people into boxes in order to create game mechanics. So we were very conscious to make
sure that no box was treated as the wrong or right box. We love all the boxes the same. We
created ten boxes or types that characters could be. So we were very conscious to make sure that
to be an affectionate parody of a stereotypical section of society, mostly with a British
skew, but keeping other cultures in mind. These types are used to drive the character's
style and interests, and also the opinions of other people's style and interests. It
took a lot of tweaking and refining to design the system, but we felt that it does a pretty
good job of creating characters that the player can look at.
and take a reasonable guess at what type each character is, but also simulating the edge
cases and unusual randomness of humanity.
Which one are you?
Hipster?
So let's take a look at an example. Here's Tara, who Kitty reliably informs is a hippie type.
Tara is bisexual and we have two candidates for her, Danny and Sky. Danny's job as a festival
organizer should be popular with hippie Tara. Although Sky's horoscope is an air sign like
Tara's, so if they both believe in horoscopes, that could help.
As for what they're into, Danny is probably also a hippie based on his outfit and his
interests. Sky is probably a glam type based on her interests, which probably won't appeal
to Tara. Maybe the fishnet stockings. However, Sky is rather partial to Tara's hair and eye
color, so that's definitely a bonus. Personality-wise, we can see that all three of them are carefree,
so they have that in common.
But that's as far as it goes for Danny, whereas Sky is almost a perfect match for Tara in the
personality department. And finally, if you advance to matchmakers, we've got guilty pleasures
and bad habits. These are the bit that I like the best because they make people the most
human. Guilty pleasures are interests that go against the character's type because everyone
has their peculiar foibles that they don't tell their friends about.
Tara's guilty pleasure, smartphones, will probably go down well with Glam Sky. And Sky's
guilty pleasure, paganism, is likely to be popular with Hippie Tara. However, Danny's not
likely to be a match in that department because his guilty pleasure is casual video games. So
it looks like Danny or Sky could be a match for Tara if he chose to talk about the right
things on the date.
But remember not to ask about guilty pleasures or bad habits on a first date, because they're a bit
personal and might upset them. Which brings us to the dating part of the game. In addition to the
characters being somewhat realistic, the dates had to feel authentic too. We were keen to evoke
the feelings and thoughts that people have when going on a date with someone new. So we mined
all the usual dilemmas that people have to face when they're on a date.
What should I wear? What should I talk about? Can I tell a white lie? Can I let a fart go? Can I
remember their name? And how forward should I be if I like them at the end of the date? Here's
the gameplay trailer so you can see some of those dilemmas in action.
Uh
Boom
Bye.
I just spotted a bug.
I think it's been fixed actually already.
So, trying to do comedy in a replayable game also presented us with some unique challenges. We
had to create a significant amount of imagery to do Kitty justice so that she could have
enough presence in the game. We ended up doing two photo shoots and a video shoot in order to
generate all of the assets. We bought a green screen backdrop from eBay and shot the first lot
of images in my brother's garage.
Later we did reshoots because we decided Kitty's look needed an upgrade.
She wasn't very happy when I told her.
And we also needed to shoot the trailer so that the two would be consistent.
Both of these later shoots took place in Media Molecule's kitchen because it was the only place big enough.
Oh, that's funny.
We also had to be careful about our age rating.
Most drag comedy could be considered adult.
So we sailed as close to the wind as we could for a 12 plus rating.
Some of the restaurant names were among our saucier moments.
I think the King's Helmet is my favorite.
Repetition is the killer of comedy, so wherever possible we used procedural systems to create variety.
One source of inspiration was those random name generators you see on Facebook.
We took a similar approach with our customer and town names.
We mined the internet for lots of popular and unpopular first names.
For the surnames and town names, we analyzed hundreds of typically British names
and then chopped them into first and second halves,
which could be mixed and matched randomly.
Just, um, doing the...
Just...
Sorry, I can't read the bloody text. It's too small.
Just doing this creates some amusing combinations. Some of them we actually had to change because
they were filthy and borderline offensive to be removed. I won't tell you what they
were. We also wrote the entire conversation script five times to give the customers dialogue
as much variety as possible. So each customer is randomly assigned a voice type when they're
created, which the probability of which one they get is based on their type.
The scripts are all interchangeable so that each type can be used with every other type in
conversation as you can see here. This is just a little exchange when one of the characters
kills, when he decides to kill the spider and it turns out that they like spiders. The
ickle spidery orphans left behind. So Kitty appears pretty regularly as well to make smart
ass remarks. This helps to break up the conversation.
and add kitty-sorty humor. Certain lines in the conversation script are tagged to pull
specific kitty quips. Each quip has six variants, again to avoid repetitiveness, for a total
of over 900 quips in the whole game. And that's just her appearing and making stupid comments.
The entire game script has the same number of words as the novel Lord of the Flies. Our
Japanese localizer wasn't very happy with us.
All of our systems, dialogue and character generation, were driven by Google Sheets and
Google Drive. So we hooked up a special scene in Unity to download the latest spreadsheets
when we just had to press a button and it would rewrite all the text files that drove
the game, which was really useful because we were working remotely because we don't
have an office. It worked wonderfully as it meant we could both, we could work collaboratively
at the same time on the same documents.
Another issue was that we couldn't record that much dialogue, so we were struggling to find a way to evoke Kitty's uniquely sarcastic tone, just using text and stupid noises.
Then a friend of mine posted these amusing speech mark gaffes on Facebook and I had a bit of an epiphany.
So we went back through Kitty's entire script and judiciously added speech marks, which really helped make her the sarcastic bitch she is.
We also had one or two other unique challenges. So managing two identities is actually harder
than it sounds. So doing interviews is easier than me, because I can kind of talk about
serious stuff. Kitty swears a lot and likes to piss about. But obviously the crowds love
Kitty's fabulosity. And it's not like I can just spin around like Linda Carter in the
box.
transform magically, um, their logistics and duct tape to take into
consideration. Um, a customer emailed us and asked us if we could add a switch to
turn off the gaze. We chose to ignore that one. Um, we also got a little bit of
flack for how pink the game was. A vocal minority accused us of gender
stereotyping and targeting women and girls. I thought, well they were the one
doing the stereotyping then really.
But we weren't doing that. The game is for everyone, and pink is Kitty's favorite color.
So that's why we did it.
There were also some lovely surprises, too.
So EGX was a great opportunity to see how people took to Kitty.
She made quite an impression.
Everybody loved her.
She judged the cosplay competition, which was fun.
Also, when Game Informer published an article about me and Kitty,
it was lovely to receive messages from other drag queens who love video games,
telling me how great it was to see one of their drag sisters flying the flag in the games industry.
So, in conclusion, you may not make a lot of money, you probably won't,
but being an independent developer is a unique and unparalleled opportunity
to express yourself creatively.
in a deeply personal and rewarding way. You can bring a kind of joy to diverse audiences that
perhaps never expected to get that from a video game. And of course, broaden the scope of
gaming to exciting new horizons. And dress up as a bizarre freak if that's how you get your
kicks. Um, this is, I've got time for some questions I think, maybe, have I got time for
questions?
Anybody? Yes? Good. If we run out of time, we can go to the breakout room. I think it's room
3000 in this building, if you want to ask me something afterwards as well. And please don't
forget to fill out the feedback thing afterwards. So, does anyone have any questions? Go on,
don't be shy.
There you go.
So you made a fantastic game.
You created your own IP.
It's this wonderfully branded product.
Brand is all you.
It's absolutely fantastic.
It went over my conservative Southern Baptist mother.
She loves it.
It's great.
This is actually one of the talks that I've been most excited to come to at GDC.
So my question is, what's next?
Are you guys working on anything else?
We're doing a Steam version of the game, which should be out in the summer.
And we've actually, interestingly, done a Japanese version, which is free to play.
And actually, the character's artwork has been redone by Hatomoa, who created Hateful Boyfriend, the pigeon dating game.
So, if that goes well, we may well bring that back over.
So, I don't know, maybe we have two versions of the game or something.
characters. They are cool. It's weird, it was really weird getting used to seeing the characters
having different faces. I don't know about what we're going to work on next. I think we'll
probably try and make something more quickly and less expensively this time, just to prove
that we can do it. Because this was, I mean I love Kitty Powers Matchmaker, but it wasn't,
it was very self-indulgent and I allowed myself loads of time to make it.
But it's not really very practical from a business sense.
So we're going to try and make something smaller, but equally
amusing.
What was the development time?
Took about two years to make.
Oh, OK.
Thanks.
Anybody else?
Go on, you know you want to.
OK, well, we should wrap.
Oh, there we go.
Joe, come on.
Make me feel popular.
You mentioned the Japanese version. I'm interested in culturally how you think it's going to go down and what differences, apart from the artwork, you had to make or changes you had to make to the game to appeal to that market.
The Japanese publisher, Corus, who are publishing it, they've organized the translation.
They were the ones who said it would be better to make the characters a bit more kawaii,
as they call it, sort of cute, an anime style, just to make it more appealing to that audience.
But I think dating sims are popular in Japan anyway, so it seemed logical to take it over there.
Um...
I don't know if...
I mean, for example, there's a game, one of the dating dilemmas in the game is you have
to tip the waiter. You have to figure out what the percentage is. But in Japan you don't
tip. It's very rude. So, I mean, my thought on that is the game is set in England, so,
and that's why they all have these sort of Englishisms. So I guess we can get away with
that kind of thing.
Because I was keen not to change it too much.
And luckily, what I did was, when I was designing the game,
I wanted to make the decision about free-to-play quite late.
Because I didn't really know what the game was going to be,
what final form it was going to take when I started it.
We built like three versions of it before it was any good.
So it was quite easy to do free-to-play,
just to switch it over.
Because the mechanics were kind of built
to be able to do either kind of thing.
Is that right?
Anybody else?
I was going to ask, usually when you make a game like other games, you can kind of draw from other games in the genre.
I noticed with this, it doesn't look like a lot of other dating sims, that sort of thing.
Were there any...
What did you draw from when you go this far out in kind of a new territory?
I really wanted to design the game around the situation rather than...
We drew...
It's a tough one, that one, actually.
Because we really did design the game from scratch,
without really any reference at all.
Because we really wanted the mechanics to support
the feeling that we wanted to conjure up
in the player, kind of thing.
But I think we actually drew from things like game shows
and a little bit of...
Casino-y style stuff.
Because we wanted it to be exciting, but we didn't want to put any timers in it as well, because
I don't, I think
sticking a timer on gameplay is kind of annoying.
Most people don't like it.
And also when you're playing a game, quite a casual game like this,
you want to be able to play it with one eye, and sort of
while you're doing something else, almost, kind of thing, like if you're on the bus or something.
And you want to be able to just put it down and go and make a cup of tea,
come back in.
and not find that your game has buggered up because you've run out of time or something.
There is a pause button. But you know what I mean. We wanted to make it super accessible.
So, yeah. I hope that answered your question properly.
I think we've got to wrap up now, but I'm going to go down to room 3000 if you want to ask me something there.
Thank you very much for listening.