Hey. So, I'll apologize in advance if I look very tired.
I just landed at 3am this morning after 50 hours of non-stop traveling.
So, thanks for joining this presentation about what you can accomplish
and get using a community platform directly embedded in your game.
My name is Nicolas Notin. I'm the Senior Community Development Specialist at Flare Games.
We are a free-to-play mobile game publisher based in Germany,
mostly known for World War II.
Last year we released Zombie Gunship Survival.
Which is the game I'm going to be talking about in this presentation.
Like many other studios and publishers, for years we used external platforms
to develop and engage with our communities.
And most of those have very unfriendly registration process.
Players have to leave the game, they have to give up personal information,
activate their accounts before joining the community platform.
And usually that leads to very poor conversion.
And so you will end up with a very small community of usually hardcore players
compared to the amount of players you have in the game.
And those players tend to dominate discussions,
which tends to lead to a lot of toxicity,
and make it very hard for community managers and studios
to get large samples of feedback and quantify that feedback as well.
And so for Zombie Gunship Survival, we knew we wanted to do something different.
We knew we wanted to have something that was easy to access,
so we can have high conversion, a lot of engagement,
so that we could build very ambitious community strategies,
and something that would let players to share the content,
and ideally something that is really easy for developers to implement in the game.
So quite a lot of things.
So for ZGS we used the NSDK from a company called KTPlay.
So that's what ticked all the boxes for us.
There are plenty of other solutions out there, but it's not so much about what you use, it's
also how you use it.
So this is the landing screen in ZGS.
So when players are not doing anything or crafting items.
And as you can see on the right side of the screen, there is this little icon, community.
So players could access the community hub directly from the landing screen.
And the community hub will appear as an overlay.
So they will never leave the game when they want to access it.
But more importantly, there is no registration process.
So as soon as the players join on the Community Hub,
the account on the Hub is created based on the in-game accounts.
Which means that every player we had on the Community Platform,
they were players in the game as well.
And having such an easy access to the platform,
usually we had 40 to 60% of our players who completed the tutorial,
who accessed the Community Hub within the first five hours.
So how does that constrain conversion?
So if we look at the first five months post-release,
the conversion of our monthly new players
were between 45% to 50% after completing the tutorial.
And if we compare this to Royal River 2, which is a very successful game of our portfolio,
the conversion between the game to our old external form was in between 0.1 to 0.3 percent.
Although the form is also somewhat surfaced in the game, and the amount of monthly downloads
between the two games were quite similar.
More importantly, using an embedded community platform gives you more information about your audience.
As a community manager, we were able to confirm that we are engaging with our most important audience,
which are payers in the case of a free-to-play game on mobile.
But if you look at box products, you have more and more games with obviously DLCs, but also in-game shops and crates.
And so we were able to confirm as committee managers that we were engaging with 70 to
almost 90% of our payers.
And the amount of payers not engaging on the committee hub got lower and lower over a month.
And so having those information, we were also able to confirm that 60 to 80% of the monthly
revenue came from the payers who were engaging on the committee hub, which means that as
a committee manager.
I am able to adapt my communication strategy better to actually retain those most important
players and also see that their feedback came from players.
So if they complain about something such as in-game shop, it actually came from actual
players.
If we look at the overall population on the community hub we had in ZGS, obviously we
had more non-payers, but the amount of payers joining the community hub over months increased.
So having a...
properly surfaced community hub in your game, and if you ensure that it's really easy to
access it, you can have, like we did in ZGS, 1.5 million community members, so not players,
community members, on the hub after just one week post-release.
It's a lot of traffic.
So what about engagements?
So before looking at the metrics, again, it's not so much, it's not just about what you use,
it's also how you use it, how you implement it in the game.
So this is the community hub, when you put it in the game, it opens as an overlay,
and resources where...
put into branding the Community Hub so that the immersion wasn't broken.
So we always have, you know, those players complaining about us breaking their immersion.
But at the end of the day, if you brand the Community Hub, it's an easy win to encourage them
to participate, to stay in the game, and to stay in the Community Hub.
They have the most important information at the top, and then easy access to the different
discussion categories, introduction, general discussions, and feedback.
And players were able to share screenshots and gameplay videos,
so written content like game guides and fan fiction.
So we monitored the gameplay videos before players could publish them,
just to make sure there was no inappropriate content or issues with copyrights.
For the screenshots, players could post them directly,
but it actually took quite a while before seeing the very first inappropriate content,
despite the huge traffic we had on the Community Hub.
And like I said, we had a lot of written content.
So you have this really easy-to-access Community Hub directly in your game,
where everyone has an equal opportunity to feel like they can be an evangelist
and be part of the community.
And not just those who do Let's Plays and streaming, but also those who write fanfiction.
So if we look at the time spent on the community hub,
in between D1 and D7, we had an average of 14,
sorry, 15 to 30 minutes per day.
These were usually players who just discovered the platform
for the very first time and had a look around,
maybe created the thread to introduce themselves,
and then went back to the game to enjoy the content.
Between D8 and D30, the time is doubled.
So it's 30 to 70 minutes on the community hub.
And those are usually the players who come back to the platform, consume the content
created by the community.
experienced players, but also kind of look for information how to get better at the game.
And then again, between D30 to D45, that time is doubled.
So 60 to 80 minutes on average per day.
And this is usually players who have a little more experience playing the game.
And so they will go back to the community hub and feel quite confident sharing feedback,
constructive feedback with the team, which is, as a community manager, the most important
thing for a studio and publisher.
So if we look at just the content, so post only, if we compare the amount of content
created on the Community Hub versus the forum we had, again there is a massive gap.
If we look at May for instance, May was only one week.
The game was released around the 23rd of May.
And then...
We already had almost 30,000 posts created.
They were not all feedback, but a lot of people were just very happy to have easy access to
the developers, essentially, super early.
But how does that perform compared to, let's say, a social media channel like Facebook?
So we also had a ZGS Facebook page.
And here we are looking at the engagements, so only replies and likes on the threads
we created to announce in-game events.
And the engagements in between the Community Hub and our Facebook page, it was two to five
times higher on the Community Hub, because it's so easy to find information and so easy
to access it that it's really easy to come back there and then maybe just leave a like
or a reply or feedback.
So talking about feedback, that's a lot of engagement.
Do we get what we need the most as a studio, as a developer,
which is, again, feedback?
So if we look at the week of the 4th of July,
we did an event on the 4th, which ended on the 7th,
and then another event on the 7th, which ended on the 10th.
And the amount of content created
in the general discussion section,
so where we post the official announcements,
and the feedback section of the community hub,
You usually have more content created on the two last days of the event.
And those usually come from players who finished the event, maybe earlier than others, went
back to the official announcement or the feedback section, and then share feedback about their
experience playing the in-game event.
So, you know, most of the companies who run live ops and in-game events, they already
have data showing the completion rate of an event.
You might just assume if the metrics are very high and positive that everything is fine,
everyone likes the event.
Written feedback can tell you if the players actually completed the event, but they are
seriously getting bored of it.
If they like the reward or not, if they like the delivery system of the reward, or the
description of the event, or maybe the marketing campaign around the event was misleading.
So data can tell you that, but written content, written post feedback can, especially if you
have them in very large quantity, you can combine the two and then actually make a decision
on how to better improve your live ops so that players don't get too much fatigue.
So what about community strategies?
So everything that has retention, engagement, education.
So having so much details about our audience on the community hub, the community team was
able to suggest new ideas, such as cultural and lore events on top of the seasonal events
that everyone does, so like Christmas and Halloween.
And so...
We knew that if we did an event to celebrate the 4th of July,
or maybe the very first time the AC-130 gunship used in a game
was assigned to its very first military mission 50 years ago,
we knew that players would like it.
And those activities, driven by the community team,
are very surprising and unexpected.
But it also helps to establish diversity at a very low cost.
Because the only thing that we did is essentially just
change the picture.
The rewards were the same.
The conditions to finish the events were the same.
But they had different context.
And everything becomes just more than a game,
where players can actually maybe learn history.
But what about retention?
So this is a graph showing the traffic to the Community Hub and some of the different
community activities we did.
I'm not going to get into too much detail here about community strategies, but in September
we had an update that implemented the law of changes to the in-game shop and the loot
boxes based on the feedback we had received from players on the Community Hub.
And at the beginning of September we did two vlogs to announce those changes.
And so the revenue coming from engaging payers on the community hub who had seen the activities
and the vlogs was the highest in those five months.
Now the vlogs were not the only reasons why the revenue was the highest, but they helped
to establish trust so that when the update actually went live, those engaging payers
and players knew what to expect and didn't have to question their purchases basically.
But knowing, having so much information again helps the community team to justify investing
more resources into new ambitious ideas.
So we had this kind of teasing campaign where we kind of created the character that posted
encrypted messages on the community hub and then players had to use their skills.
to crack the codes and then get clues to what was coming to the next update.
And so they had to use their video editing skills and we even had players creating C++
based apps to automatically crack the code.
And seeing this in the mobile game is quite insane.
It's amazing.
And so all of that helps the community to feel connected and to share unique memories.
But it also helps the studio to focus on the next update,
and then have an activity just driven by the community team
to tease what's coming next in a very safe way, but also a very entertaining way.
So it's like a game within a game,
almost no cost, or at least no cost coming from the development team.
So talking about players creating videos and content, if we look at the first five months
again, the amount of feedback was quite a lot.
So these are unique threads.
So in June, after the first month, it was about a thousand unique threads just about
feedback about features.
Then we also had a lot of gameplay videos, but like I said, a lot of written content
as well, like game guides and fan fiction.
So all of that, it was a lot of content that we could use in committee spotlights featuring
those potential evangelists.
and kind of help educate the players that everyone has an equal opportunity to become
someone in that community.
And all of that helps to create a positive vibe and get rid of a lot of toxicity.
So obviously this was the very first time we actually implemented this platform in our
games, Flare Games, so there are quite a few learnings and best practices to share with
you.
So one, ensure an easy access.
So, and I just not mean the surfacing,
but also the way to access the platform.
So if you can have it on a landing screen as an icon,
or let's say a building or something like this,
it's a lot easier than actually adding the link
in the sub menu.
So if you play, if you work on the box product,
the best way to do it could be maybe in the pause menu.
And rather than having it in a separated tab that says social, you have it just right there, it says form.
Two, branding is key.
Again, there are a lot of players always complaining about us breaking their immersion,
but at the end of the day it could be a very easy win to encourage your players to really participate on the platform.
But it also helps to keep everything consistent and keep the branding of your game intact.
Three, proper introduction.
So if you have a tutorial, it's definitely a good idea to introduce this community platform to your players.
Even if it's just to say, hey, if you click here, you can join our community.
The monthly conversion we had in ZGS, so this average of 50% every month, we didn't have that.
So I'll let you imagine the potential if you actually introduced your players to the community platform as part of your tutorial.
It could be quite high.
For prepare deep links and redirect, so it's good to educate your players to know the kind
of the core platform where they can get information and participate with the rest of the community.
But if you are able to redirect your players to somewhere specific, it's even better so
that you can make sure that the most important information are surfaced properly.
And then you can also track if the players come back to the community hub.
allow external access.
So you can have the choice to allow access in read-only for people who don't play your
game yet, so that they can discover the potential of the community.
But it's also good to have a way for players to visit the community platform, especially
when you have several maintenance or downtime.
so that you can keep them posted on the core community platform during those phases where
they cannot access the platform from within the game.
And then six, think long term.
So if you have a, what I call a global portfolio account, like something similar to bottleneck
essentially, imagine the potential.
Those players, if they knew that they could kind of transfer their reputation from a game
to another on the platform that works in the same way, and then they would feel part of
your portfolio.
And that's great for the players, but also great for community managers.
Because when you actually start a new game,
you don't have to start from scratch.
You already have your well-established evangelists
that you can trust that understand the rules.
And they will be there from day one.
And they will help you to then educate other new players,
and so on.
So that's pretty much all from my side
on using a community platform embedded in the game.
So if you have any questions, please.
Hi, thanks for being here.
I was going to ask, what kind of information are you getting from your communities?
Is there any kind of like backdoor access that shows you kind of things, information about them,
that maybe they're not aware that you're getting?
Or is it all just like based on what they directly communicate to you?
So it's all about tracking essentially, so we don't get information about,
like personal information, like age and gender, we don't get that.
because we don't want to have it surface in the first place.
But I think there is activities such as looking at the threads,
coming back to the community hub,
or engaging on specific threads that we created and so on.
So it's purely about tracking activities in between the game and then what happens in the community.
So like engagement?
Sorry again?
Like engagement, like what they're engaging with?
Yeah, absolutely.
So it's a good way for us to actually determine if...
The campaign was successful, like a community activities essentially.
Well, first, thank you for mentioning LiveOps, because that's been brought up in my job.
But I'm wondering, I noticed that you said that the platform that you're using, it brings
players in by their player ID.
And I'm just wondering, how does that cross over with like your...
customer support team because in the game that I'm working for,
I need that player ID to do almost anything
in a support ticket, which is distinct from community management.
But, you know.
So we don't do customer support on the platform,
but the name used on the community hub
will be the same as the one used in the game.
So if you have a game that is a multiplayer focused game,
We will usually have a lot of conversations prior to launching the game
to ensure that everything that is unique usernames and so on are there.
So that as a community manager, if I see someone complaining about something,
I know I can use the username rather than ask the player,
can I have your user ID and so on.
That being said...
We do have access to their unique user ID, which then we can reuse on our platforms.
So there is a way to get that as well.
But in the case of ZGS, I can just use the username.
Any more questions?
Okay.
That is one.
Just to preface, I work with him, so this is somewhat a biased question.
That's mean.
It's a tricky question.
She's testing me.
Spike is very high.
Yeah, so your conversion rates were really good for this game, obviously.
What would you do to actually boost those in a future title?
So, like I said, I think having the community platform introduced to players as part of
the tutorial is definitely a good thing to boost that.
So we are kind of about to test this in a new game, but I'm fairly confident that as
long as your players finish the tutorial and you have made the FTE quite good and quite
optimized, there is a chance that you can almost get a 100% conversion.
So that's definitely the core idea to ensure that the conversion is boosted.
Aside from that, everything that is in that message with reminders is also a great thing,
but also think about rewards as well.
So everything that is...
Joining the community and getting these tiny rewards or currencies is also a good way to
encourage players maybe to join for the very first time, but also join, sorry, return the
community platform later. I have a couple questions, so I'll ask them one at a time.
First, how did you decide on the different sections you had in the community? You had
feedback, you had weapons, you had those ones. How did you decide on those? What was the process?
So, obviously, you can customize those.
So, at the beginning, we only had general discussions
and feedback and others based on the audience we had in the game.
And then we quickly realized that it might be good to have introduction
because there was so much traffic
that we didn't want players to introduce themselves
in sections that were not meant for it.
So, we put introduction at the very top
so that new players who join,
they see that, okay, this is the place where I can create that.
General discussion is mainly for announcements and general feedback.
But then we put feedback in third because that's the most important thing for us.
Did you see that once you introduced sections like that, did engagement improve from that?
Engagement...
Yes, obviously, because they know, so there are more sections, obviously, so they tend
to have less traffic.
It's mainly for those that are really looking for specific places to share specific content.
But yeah, if we had put introduction at the very last of the list, then I don't think
it would have impacted the engagement, but I think it would have put more resources into
moderation.
So we would have spent a lot more time to actually move through it around.
Since the last question I'll have is sort of the relationship between the community
that you've built within the game to communities that exist outside of the game, like on Facebook
and other platforms, what happens in those communities?
Since you've built your own, what need is being served, do you think, by those other
Facebook communities?
Yeah.
At the time we were quite happy with the algorithm on the Facebook page and so on,
and so we would usually have different content as well.
So the core activities could be on the same platforms,
so on the Facebook page and the Community Hub, such as Community Spotlights.
But there are specific activities that would work better on Facebook
and maybe less on the Community Hub.
And sometimes some of them could actually be seen as spam or...
Raffles is a good example.
So on the community hub, we run maybe a competition or a contest, like a creative contest.
On the Facebook page, we would just do a kind of comment here and have a chance to win something.
So it's mainly about, you know, thinking about your...
communication strategies and kind of find what's best for the different platforms.
The advantage of using a community platform directly in your game is that you actually
kind of you're in total control. It's yours. You're not dependent to an algorithm that is made by a
third party and if one day it changes then and you don't reach people that's yeah there's nothing
you can do about it.
Actually, sorry, one more.
Did, before you introduced the communities
that were within the game,
did you find that there was a lot more activity
on the Facebook communities?
And that obviously as soon as you introduce it
within the game, there's gonna be a lot more people
doing it there than on Facebook, but.
So, in between phase, I can make a comparison
in between not having the community hub
and having an external platform like a forum.
So we had the forum before.
for a very short time during the beta phase.
And obviously, we definitely saw the most hardcore players made the effort to go to
the forum, but it stopped there.
So again, if we had kept the forum and not used a community platform like this one directly
in the game, I think we would have ended up with a very small cluster of hardcore games
dominating that platform.
and a lot less potential.
I never imagined seeing so many players writing fanfiction about a game set in a post-apocalyptic context
and using real weapons from the army.
For us, it was kind of a shock.
And a good one.
Nice cap, by the way.
With the success of building a larger community, did you see a largely increased need for moderation?
Also, especially considering that this is, you know, very tied to your brand at this point?
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
I'll be totally honest with you, we didn't expect so much traffic.
You know, it's a good thing, but at the same time, we were prepared internally, so we had
maybe agencies and so on, and it was okay to actually, you know, we had the proper moderation
tools to share the task and so on.
But the good thing using this platform is that you can easily spot
and you have more chances to actually find evangelists
who are OK during moderation as well.
So, you know, like maybe a month after release,
I was able to actually find players who were good players.
And then I could I had a good feeling I could trust them to.
take on new responsibilities and moderate,
which also helps because it comes from a different perspective, right?
It's not official moderation. It's community moderation.
There is also a lot of features, like built-in features,
like if a post is reported multiple times,
it's going to be put in quarantine and so on.
So you already have, like, this SDK already has a lot of pre-built tools
to actually do this.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
OK, thank you.