On GDC Podcast Episode 8, we have Celia Hoden, a user experience consultant, psychology PhD, and author who will get us learned about cognitive science, UX, and how our brains process something as complex as a video game.
Back in a few.
And we're back. Hey, this is Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra, and I'm here with Alyssa.
Yeah, this is Alyssa, and I am already trying to interrupt you like a minute into this thing.
We're a little out of practice, huh? I think it's like we have to relearn every time.
I don't, I haven't talked, well I have roommates, but I haven't like talked to people
as much as usual, so it's just a little, a little rusty.
And your last name is Alyssa McAloon, not your last name is Alyssa McAloon.
Yeah, one of those is correct. One of those names might be the one that belongs there.
Yeah, the gears are just starting to spin in my head. Getting, you know, greased up and ready
to go for this. So, yeah, Alyssa McAloon. Anything new happen since the last podcast?
Animal Crossing. It's just Animal Crossing. That's it.
How'd your GDC go?
Oh, GDC, yeah, that was Animal Crossing 2.
Oh man, oh geez.
I did watch some of the streams that were going all week on the GDC Twitch channel,
which were pretty interesting.
Popped in every now and then, but you can probably talk a little bit more about those than I can.
Oh, no, I don't know if I can.
No, the virtual talks turned out really great, actually.
And there is something to be said
about hanging out in your living room,
absorbing content from the comfort of your own home.
So we actually streamed the GDC awards, the Game Developers
Choice awards, through Twitch, as well as the IGF awards.
And it was a, you know, it.
it was a big effort on the part of people who are like our hosts and you know the GDC events team
and it turned out it turned out really nice and just kind of it kind of made me feel it made me
feel good you know there's a lot of adversity right now it's tumultuous times right? Yeah yeah
no it was a I don't know it was difficult for them to bring together I imagine and it came
together in this really like
heartwarming online way. I think being on Twitter and in the Twitch chat throughout
like the entire week and for the awards, it was like the most wholesome gathering of minds that
I've seen online in a long time, which is like, wow. It was shockingly wholesome for Twitch chat,
considering how many people were watching.
So thanks for everyone who showed up for that.
And also there are a bunch of virtual talks that are on the GDC YouTube channel.
And they're up for free on the vault too, right?
Yes.
Yeah, the entire listing from that week is viewable.
Yeah, yeah.
And if they're not free now, they will be.
I'm pretty sure they're all free right now.
It's a good number of them scrolling through them right now.
So there's a lot of content.
Content.
A lot of free content.
is my middle name.
Chris Content Graph.
Uh, so yeah, other than that, you mentioned, uh, Animal Crossing. I think that we should just hit
on that real quick because I know that our listeners want to really listen, uh, listen to
us talk about that.
30 minutes later. Um, no, Animal Crossing's real good and what was that? Sorry.
You're like some kind of professional, like, uh, animal crossing player.
I go to your Island.
You're like, you know, you're kind of like when you have rich friends or
friends who are like really well off.
And when your gates open for Island, I go there.
You're like, the streets are, are paved with bells.
Yeah.
Like my real life.
That's me.
It's well organized.
No, I had a lot of anxiety that can be channeled into organizing, and Animal Crossing is a
wonderful conduit for that.
I'm pretty sure we talked about the Gamasutra editorial team had at talking about all of
that over yesterday in a lead on gamasutra.com, so you can read that for my long-form opinions
where I talk too much about it.
No, I don't think you could ever talk too much about it.
You do.
You have, you have very enthralling opinions.
You like live on a different, uh, tier of animal crossing-ness than I do.
It's everything I aspire to be.
Thank you.
I think.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Anytime.
Okay.
So I think that we should, uh, get on with our, uh, with our guest.
Yeah, game development time.
I'm excited.
Hello.
I don't know what you say.
You folks are hilarious.
I was muted most of the time to better sound.
But you're hilarious.
It feels like we're starting to relearn
how to interact with people.
Oh my god, how we do that?
We don't know anymore.
Yeah, I know.
It's a totally new.
See, I haven't even introduced you properly yet.
I'm going to give you the warmest introduction here.
And now you have to listen to it unmuted.
Then you can react.
and correct me as I'm doing it.
So, all right, here we go.
And if any of this is wrong, I blame your personal webpage.
Thank you.
All right, Celia Odent has worked on,
she has worked as a UX, okay.
Yay, that starts well.
Okay, our next guest has worked as a UX consultant
in the game industry for over a decade.
No, that's false.
Over, okay.
This is a bad start then.
No, I've only been a consultant for the past two and a half years,
but before that, I was working in the studios directly.
Okay.
But it was close.
Okay, this is good.
This is live editing.
All right.
Holds a PhD in psychology.
Yay, that's good.
Okay.
Has worked on Ubisoft franchises,
like Rainbow Six, Driver, Assassin's Creed, Watch Dogs.
Mm-hmm.
Okay. LucasArts sadly canceled Star Wars 1313.
That was sad.
Yeah. Or is it 1313?
Maybe it was 131.3, who knows?
The Kingdom Hearts approach.
And also worked on a little game called Fortnite at Epic Games.
Yeah, I don't know if you've heard of it. It's a nice game.
It's a nice little app.
Yeah, it's pretty cool.
And all right, there's more.
You're too accomplished.
Oh, stop.
Prolific speaker, including multiple times at GDC,
where she is chair and advisor of the GDC UX Summit.
Yes.
That's a cool summit.
All right, we're almost through here.
Author of The Gamer's Brain, How Neuroscience and UX
Can Impact Video Game Design, and the upcoming The Psychology
of Video Games.
Yes.
Is that all?
Is that the big stuff?
Yeah, I think that's good.
All right, everyone, help me welcome Celia Hoden.
Hey, Celia.
Hey, thanks for having me.
Yeah, of course.
We're super excited.
Should we call you Dr. Celia?
No, you can if you want.
If you have a tendency of yours.
How about just doc?
Doc, yeah, doc, it's cool.
Okay, all right, doc.
So...
Only if I can say Greg Scott.
Okay.
That's a requirement, I think.
Yeah, we will allow it.
So, first, we kind of went over your professional background,
but like, what, how did you get into this?
This is like, I'm excited to have you on because it's a unique thing.
It's not that unique but yeah, it's...
Ish.
Yeah, unique-ish.
Yeah, a lot of people ask me that question.
It's really funny because it really happened.
It just happened, serendipity.
So 12 years ago, I was working in the toy industry and doing educational games and stuff
like that.
But I was a gamer, I've always been a gamer my whole life, like light gamer, like I play a lot of games, not just video games.
And so back then, I was already seeing a lot of parents freaking out about video games and...
fearing that it would turn their kids into dumb people.
I don't know why, but it's been around for a while.
So back then I started to look into the science behind it and the psychology.
Is there any research behind the impact of video games?
Back then I found some research,
mostly about the positive impact on cognitive skills,
but also the worries around.
you know, violence and pathological gaming and stuff like that.
And so this is how I started to write articles about it back in France and to start going
into festivals.
There were a few festivals back in the day about video games and this is how I met with
Ubisoft.
And so it happened that way.
Got it that way.
How, why was that attractive to you or appealing to you?
It was, was it, you know, to validate your hobby or like?
It's just...
It was just the conver...
Everything was really converging
and all the things that I love.
So I love art.
In a previous life I was a musician,
I was playing music.
And so I love the fact that in video games
there's a lot of artists and there's a lot of ways to be creative.
I love science. More specifically, psychology, science, but I love all science.
And so there's that in my background. And I love playing games.
And so getting in the game industry was where everything is kind of converging.
So to me that was kind of, this is where, I don't know, where all the pieces came together.
And I thought, yeah, this is, I guess, this is where I belong, I think, I hope.
Yeah, was Ubisoft just looking for, was it kind of a new area for them as far as getting
you know, somebody with a psychology background?
Yes, it was, well that was back in 2008.
And that was new and there were a couple studios that were interested into that.
Ubisoft was interested in enriching people's lives and back then they had some educational,
not really educational, but games that you want to enrich people's lives.
all the coach games, you know, my word coach or my SAT coach.
And so I was hired to help them understand how people learn
and to work on different projects.
I was on the think tank, the strategic innovation lab
as reporting to the CEO, Yves Guillemot.
So I was working there, but I was also working with the Games for Everyone team,
and I was also working with the editorial team.
So I was right at HQ, so it was really cool for me to enter the game industry
at a place where I...
I could look at a lot of different relevant things in games and all the different topics
and things that people were doing in Ubisoft.
So yeah, they were interested in that aspect and I think they're still interested into
that.
So yeah, to me it was great.
It was really serendipity.
I was at the right moment, at the right place.
And I was interested in it.
Yeah, we've been kind of dropping the term UX and saying user experience, but we can't
assume that everybody who's listening understands what that is or what that means.
So can you explain what that is exactly and how it relates to games?
First of all, it's new in the game industry.
When I started at Ubisoft,
that was not a term that we were using.
We started to use it maybe when I was at LucasArts,
so more in 2012, 2011.
User experience is.
see it as a mindset. When we design things, and whether it is a video game or
an object or an aircraft, whatever it is, we can design it the way we find it the
easiest for engineers or for designers, but we can also shift from that
perspective and try to adopt the perspective of the user who doesn't know
what's going on in the back-end, who doesn't necessarily...
know how the thing works and try to adopt that perspective so that we can design the
object, the system or the game taking into account the limitations of the human who's
going to use the thing.
So it started back in World War II when there were a lot of pilots that were super highly
trained who still made some mistakes because when you're...
and the war, you're stressed out, of course.
And they were pressing a button instead of the other
because the dashboards in the aircraft
were not consistent, one aircraft from the other.
And so you have to always relearn for each aircraft.
And of course that was making.
human mistakes easier and so people would die or would crash planes and so this is where they really
People really start to shift from all right instead of designing the aircraft in the way
It's it's going to be the easiest for the engineer
How about we design it in the way it's going to be easier for humans considering humans flaws because we are we are flawed
And so we can make it better for the military.
And then it spread from the military, started there.
And then it started to gain traction in product design,
in health care, and video games.
So video games is pretty new.
It's been less than 10 years.
but it's gaining traction here too and the idea is to ensure that you're gonna offer the experience
that you want to offer to your players by considering their perspective first.
Yeah, and that whole idea of considering people's perspective is what seems that would make this
extremely difficult to figure out because people see things in in different ways, right?
Yeah, perception is subjective. We're all different, so we're all floating the same way,
but our perception is different. There's a little game that I often do and I show a picture and I
ask people...
What do you perceive in this picture?
And depending on where people are coming from, they see different things.
And this is just to illustrate that our perception is subjective, and it really highly depends
on what we care about, our culture, it depends on the games that we play, the conventions
that we're used to.
And so even if you're a gamer, there's not one gamer, we have gamers and depending on
what type of game you're playing, you're going to be used.
you know certain conventions, like if you play a lot of RPGs or playing a lot of FPS,
there are specific conventions that you don't find necessarily in puzzle games.
And so it's really important to understand different perspectives and we cannot do that
by ourselves because we cannot, it's just something we can't do, adopt someone else's
perspective, we're very bad at that.
So we need a methodology so we can...
So that's why we playtest, so that we can verify
that the game that you're designing
is going to be understood and perceived in the way you want it by the people
who are going to play it. And they might have a very different
perspective than you have. So that's the basic principle.
Can you talk a little bit about basic methodology
for something like this or give an example?
Sure.
So first of all, it's very broad.
When we talk about UX, a lot of people think UI.
Of course, UI is part of the experience and the icons that we're using and the menus and
organization and the HUD.
Of course, that's going to be very impactful, but it's not just the UI.
It's everything.
Let's take an example of what we call affordance.
Affordance is when you see something, you see an object and you know how you're going
to be able to use it and that the object is designed to help you interact with it.
So in product design, for example, if you think about, I have a mug just right in front
of me.
That mug has a handle.
That handle is an affordance for me to be able to just grab it with three or four fingers
and lift it.
That's helping me using that object without burning my fingers if there's something warm
in it.
In video games, most of the time we don't manipulate physical objects, so the affordances
are what we call cognitive affordances or just signifiers.
But the idea is just by looking at something in the game, can I understand what it's for
and how I can use it?
So for example, if you look at the enemies in Mario,
let's say Bowser, everybody knows Bowser,
he has spikes on his back.
That's telling you that if you're gonna jump on it,
it's probably gonna hurt you, so you should not do that.
This is a cognitive performance explaining to you
how this enemy is working.
So we need to help out players
because we want the game to be,
first of all fun and also easy to understand and to understand the rules of the world and
what we need to do in an intuitive way.
It's through affordance that we can do that a lot because games we don't want to read
a manual before playing a game, we just want to experiment it.
And if we can understand this by looking at something, so it's character design, it's
environment design, and yes, it's the UI, but it's not just that.
Even the music, sound effect, all of that is going to be important because all of that
is part of the experience and the idea is to ensure that we're going to give the experience
that we want to give.
So in video games, what's complicated is we are putting some challenges.
in front of players. Unlike other areas like military or product design, we don't want to
challenge people using something. But in games, we do want to challenge people in the games.
So what's going to be really important is to start by defining what experience do you want to offer?
Where do you want to challenge players? Let's say, for example, Fortnite.
is a game where you're going to challenge players with their twitch skills and combat and building
and coordinating with others. It's not a game where we want to challenge people into perception.
A game like Monument Valley is a game when you challenge people on their perception because you
play around with perspective. So it's really important to first define where you want to
put a challenge, what experience you want to offer and who are your users, who are the people going
to play your game. Because like I said, depending on what they're used to.
they might see things differently.
And so once you nail that, then you can start.
This is where the methodology starts.
And this is where you can try to anticipate problems
that your appliers are gonna have,
and you're gonna have to make trade-offs
and make the right choices so you can offer
the experience that you wanna offer to your appliers.
Sorry, it's a bit broad, but it's...
What?
sitting here intently listening. It's fascinating. Yeah, I can talk about that forever. So don't feel
free to interrupt me. I'm jumping back into like my college shorthand when I'm taking notes. You're
being like, oh yes, yes, this is like sitting in on a really interesting psychology course.
Yeah, the professor is in.
We're frantically taking notes here.
I'm like flashing back, it's weird, it's weird.
I did want to ask, so like, when you define your challenge or your users and stuff like
that, is there like moments throughout the process where you have to go back and reevaluate
after like having some hands-on like playtesting or like looking at how players are actually
reacting to your game and be like, okay, we need to change our definitions and adapt to
it?
how players are receiving it or do you adapt, like how do you adapt to that on the fly with
UX design or like UX anything?
Yeah, absolutely. So we use what we call design thinking, so it's an iteration cycle.
So you design something, you test it, and depending on how people are using it,
is it validating or not, what you're trying to accomplish. If not, you go back to design,
and you iterate, and then you retest. So of course we're going to adjust a lot of stuff,
but typically we don't tend to adjust what we thought the game should be about.
Because if your game is about combat and building and cooperation,
and you see that this is not what we're trying to accomplish,
it's rarer than we're going to say,
oh yeah, it's bad that our game is bad at doing that,
but it's great at doing something else.
Let's shift entirely and do that.
I mean, it's possible, why not?
But it's typically not what we do,
because making games is very, extremely expensive.
So we do have a, we're focusing on accomplishing certain goals that are broad goals.
But then to get there, yes, we're going to iterate on systems, we're going to iterate
on the art, we're going to iterate on the UI, we're going to iterate on all these things
and maybe going to adjust.
We're making some assumptions.
that might be wrong. And so we might have to remove, for example, a feature that we thought
would reinforce such a strange feeling that we want to give, but at the end of the day,
this is not what's happening. It's actually removing more than adding anything. So yes,
we adjust the features and systems, but typically we don't adjust the vision that we had for the
game. At least not in my experience.
In one of your GDC talks a few years back, you really focused on these concepts of perception,
memory, and attention, which was totally fascinating. We talked a little bit about
perception, but can you talk about how why those three things are important to consider
and how they relate to each other?
Absolutely. So when we talk about, I'm just gonna take one step back before, when we talk about UX,
so we want to offer the experience we want to offer to our players, there are two main things that we need to look into to offer great user experience.
The first one is usability and the second one is what I call engageability.
Usability is making sure that the game can be used.
People understand the objectives, they can manipulate all the things they need to manipulate, understand the systems.
If there's crafting in your game,
players understand how to interact with the crafting system
and they are able to craft something.
That's usability.
A game can be usable,
like meaning that people can understand
what they have to do and manipulate
all the features in a game,
but it could still be boring.
And so a game is more than just usability,
it needs to be engaging.
But back onto usability, to make a game usable,
we need to take into account the limitations
of the human brain.
So we look into mental processes,
and so this is where cognitive science kicks in,
because cognitive science is the study of mental processes.
And the main mental processes that we know well
and that are really important to make a game usable
are perception, attention, and memory.
So we look at the main limitations of these things.
The brain is performing for a lot of stuff.
We have great capabilities, but we also have great limitations.
So the one we talked about, perception, is subjective.
And we have a hard time remembering that.
Because for us, what we see, what we hear,
everybody should have the same perception of the reality.
But it's not what happens.
There's one reality, and there's multiple perceptions.
This is why it's so hard to communicate sometimes.
And then attention and memory are also very important.
Memory is critical because if you learn something, it means that you memorized something new.
If you don't memorize it, you don't learn it.
And so playing a video game is a learning experience.
There's a lot of things that your player is going to have to learn,
from the controls, to the objective, to the story.
And so we need to understand how we can make sure that players are going to memorize
the most important things in your game.
And the problem with memory is that memory is pretty flawed.
I'm sure you've experienced that.
You forget about stuff.
Not me. Perfect memory. Perfect memory.
So we have to deal with that.
And so memory is pretty flawed and we have what we call the forgetting curve.
And even if you learn something by heart and that's, you know, let's say today you've learned
something entirely by heart, like a series of numbers or words, but then tomorrow maybe
you're only going to remember half of them or even less than that if what you're trying to.
learn was meaningless.
And so we are forgetting stuff as time passes.
And that's really important for video games because a video game, we experience that across several days or weeks or hopefully months and years.
And if you play every day, you're less likely to forget about stuff.
But a lot of players, they're going to play a lot, let's say, a game that's complicated.
Let's take the example of Red Dead Redemption 2.
You play it, there's a lot of systems to learn and maybe you're going to play every day.
for a couple of weeks and then you go on vacation or you're going on crunch because we're making video games and we crunch.
And so you leave the game for a week or two and when you come back, it feels like you're downgraded
because now you don't remember how to do things and it's taking a long time to get back to it.
Oh, not to get hung up on this or interrupt through this,
but like, this is just so striking to me.
Like I forget like where I slotted my fishing rod
and my tool wheel in Animal Crossing.
And I like, like minute to minute.
And like, that's one of the things
that's frustrating to me too about RPGs, for example,
because you'll return to it.
And there's like, for most of them,
some of them are trying to do this now,
but these are like epically long.
you know, stories and then, you know, I'm not playing every single day and then I'll come back and like months later and I
just give up because I was like, what the heck am I even doing?
You might as well start all the way over again.
Yeah.
So there was like a moment with what you were describing with kind of forgetting like small elements of something where like I
previously played a lot of Hitman 2. Now I only play some Hitman 2.
And I took a break from that game to play Horizon Zero Dawn. That was Hitman 1, I think.
and then I came back to it and I'm like all right I'm gonna go to this level I know really well and
I'm gonna go through this way and I go behind this butler and I gotta sneak and open the door
and instead of hitting the open the door button I hit what in Horizon would be the action button
and I punched this butler directly in the face because like my memory of the buttons had been
overlapped with what I was playing at a different time and it just it went weird it all went bad.
Yeah, that's a great example.
And so as a gamer, we typically play a lot of different games,
and what you're describing is what we call muscle memory.
So in psychology, we call that procedural memories,
the memory of actions, which is a bit different from the memory
of facts and knowledge, such as what's
the storyline in that game.
That's more facts and knowledge.
The buttons that you press is more procedure.
And these are two different, completely separate memories,
and they work differently.
muscle memory is very strong.
And so once you're trained on a game
and you have certain buttons laid out,
if you go back to another game, it's a nightmare
because you have to relearn.
It's just like if you go from the U.S., you go to London,
and you have to look right before crossing,
and you're not used to that,
and it's going to take you a while to get used to that.
It's the same principle and there's a lot of games now that they care more about the
onboarding, they onboard players better, but not many games think about re-onboarding players
after they left the game for a little while.
And that can be okay if you're a paid up front game.
If you're a free to play game, that could mean that players when they get back to it,
they forgot about everything and they feel like it's going to be too hard to...
get bad at it and they might just quit and play another game.
So it's harsh. Yeah, like seriously, like I need a
like a re- you know, adjustment or like re-intro every time I turn a
game on or something. I should probably get a brain scan.
No, I can assure you your brain is perfectly normal.
We all have this problem. Humans are just flawed.
And then memory, so it's perception, how people see things,
and then memory, and then that goes into attention.
How does that go into UX?
So these elements are not really separated.
We talk about them separately.
But memory is the process of encoding, retaining,
and then recalling information.
So it's all of that.
And to encode information, you need attention.
So if you don't pay attention to something, you're not gonna remember it well.
So to pay attention to something, it also needs to stand out.
I'm sorry, what was that?
Which part?
I'm just kidding.
I was pretending like you lost my attention.
Oh my god.
I'm sorry.
That's terrible.
Wow.
Worm, worm.
Good try, good try.
Thank you.
It's difficult times, so we need to laugh.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So now I lost my...
Memory!
Remember me please!
So yeah, you need, so first of all, to pay attention to something, sometimes you need
to perceive it.
And so that's why we need stuff to stand out.
This is the reason why we have, you know, big flashes in games, or giant exclamation
marks to draw attention, but through perception.
So we draw attention, and once you pay attention to something, then you're going to process
things better.
So the better you process something and the more,
the deeper you process something,
the more likely you are to remember it.
So this is the reason why in most cases,
learning by doing is more efficient
than learning by reading instructions, for example.
So during the onboarding phase, it's going to be way more efficient if you want people
to remember it, to put your players in a situation where they have to do something, they have
to experience the thing you're trying to teach them.
And this is the way we really put Fortnite together, the save the world part.
So the more the story, the more the part.
For example, the first time you learn how to build.
The pliers are in a situation where they're in a cave and they need to exit the cave.
but there's nothing there to exit the cave.
And this is where we teach them,
hey, if you want to exit, you need to build stairs.
And so the idea is if you place players in a situation
where they have context,
it means that they can do the things that you teach them,
there's learning by doing,
and on top of that, it's meaningful.
They care about it right now
because they need to get out.
This is when people are more likely
to pay attention to what they're doing.
and they're more motivated to do it and they're more likely to remember it later on.
So that's the reason why perception, attention and memory all goes together and that's going
to be really critical for your onboarding and for your game usability and the best,
you know, the more you craft it carefully, the better it's going to be for your game
and this is the reason why you have to.
determine what are the most important things in your game, what is the most important thing for the experience of the players, because you can't do that for every single feature in your game.
You can't teach everything in your game through that, because otherwise you never ship.
And so you have to determine what are the most important things for your game, and also what are the most difficult things to learn.
Like in Fortnite, building is quite difficult. It's new and there's not a lot of games.
We'll have buildings, I mean at least back then, and even it's different from building in Minecraft.
So we know that's already going to be a feature in the system, it's going to be hard for players to learn.
So we need to pay more attention to that.
system more specifically and maybe the rest, if it's not as crafted carefully, never mind
because we can't do everything perfectly.
So if you do that, you determine what is the, this is what I call doing the onboarding plan,
defining what are the most important features in your game, things that if players don't
understand how to do that, they're never going to have fun.
And so you can place a lot of effort in that.
And if you do that, then you are more likely to make sure that player is going to remember it.
The other trick is also, so that players don't forget, is to have better affordances.
Also, give away information at all times.
That's why HUDs are so important.
Because if on the HUD, like on Assassin's Creed, the first...
the first of the series, you always have on the HUD all the actions they can do in context.
You don't have to learn about these.
So even if you come back two weeks later, you're not under the forgetting curve because
the information is still on your HUD.
And that's why caring about your HUD and making sure you have the right information for players
and that it's intuitive.
It's a great thing because then when players come back,
they can re-onboard more easily.
Alyssa, now that you have taken all these notes,
you've scribbled them all down,
how do you grade the UX in Animal Crossing, the New Horizons?
Scale of 1-10.
Good luck, Alyssa.
I don't, for me it's difficult because it's hard to separate it from what I had as a kid
and like what's like baked into my mind from so long because like I there's just so much
that game that's automatic for me because earlier on I learned these systems and then
carried that forward so like it's hard for me personally to kind of like grade that one.
But it's always hard and it's hard for everyone because we care about certain games more than others,
certain games have an extra-nostalgia.
And so this is the reason why it's really hard as game developers or gamers to grade and to rate any of these games.
This is why we need a methodology so we can detach from our own perspective and use very precise methodology.
to look at elements.
So that's why my framework is using the usability elements,
like signs and feedback, are they clear?
Do we have good form follows function,
meaning do we have good affordance?
Do we minimize the workload for players
when they have to play for things
that they're gonna have to do very often?
So we look at very precise things
and same thing for engagement.
Is it motivating?
It's more complicated for engagement
because we don't have a...
enough research on that and it's more fuzzy. But we do have elements like motivation, emotion,
you know, game feel and we're looking to game flow and onboarding and all that.
And so this is what we do. We don't... it's hard to...
evaluate a game just based on our feelings, even if we're professional.
This is why I highly recommend to try to detach ourselves from our own gut feeling and common
sense because common sense is flawed, because the brain is flawed.
Especially mine, yeah.
Well, again, it's not just you.
I can assure you that.
I'm just putting out the self-deprecating stuff.
So validate me and yeah.
So like, uh, when you're talking about getting other people's perspectives, I
mean, like you're, you're talking about, you know, different kinds of playtesting.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's a bunch of things that we can anticipate because we have principles that
we use from human-computer interaction.
But yeah, we always need to playtest because at the end of the day, we can't anticipate
everything.
We have blind spots and we need to playtest with a lot of different people.
That's why inclusion and diversity is very important so that we can ensure to uncover
our blind spots.
And this is typically the moment, it's both exhilarating and atrocious because you bring
over players from your audience and you watch them play and sometimes the things you were
expecting to work are working and it's exhilarating and sometimes something that you thought would
be obvious is actually not obvious to someone who doesn't know anything about the system
even though they're gamers.
And this is when it can be really depressing.
Because sometimes, like on Fortnite, there are some elements like,
you know, playdesk after playdesk after playdesk,
that we were iterating on something and it was still not working.
We're like, ah!
And that's why these rooms are soundproofed.
Because sometimes you're really like, why is this not working?
Like whenever I play something in front of a developer
and they're watching me play,
like I know, you know, if you're at a show or something,
like I am super self-conscious too
because I'm just thinking like,
I should know where to go and what to do.
And I know that that's what they're thinking,
like, what are you doing?
But that's typically why we don't have developers in the rooms when we play test.
Because first of all it's intimidating and second of all you want to be nice to the developer
because you know that that person put their heart and soul and sweat and blood in there
and you try to figure out things way more carefully than if you were at home.
especially or if you were on the commuting to work and trying a free-to-play game on your phone.
This is where really we don't care a lot about any of that thing and so we don't have a lot of time
to ensure that players first of all they understand what they have to do and it's compelling.
And then you're, it's done.
So.
And there's, there's like an amazing amount of like these tiny little details.
You were talking about menus and gestalt principle.
Yeah.
And you know, which it, you know, it's about grouping things together.
Right.
And how your brain.
Yeah, so it's more than that. It's about seeing patterns.
And across all humans we have the same way
of seeing patterns. But the problem is that we have different laws and
principles from Gestalt that can help us anticipate how people are
going to see things. But the problem is that in real life
there's all of these laws and principles that are interacting with
one another. But when we take them separately we can clearly anticipate.
So for example if you just see a
a block of dots that are equidistant,
you're just going to see a big,
I don't know, like square of dots.
Now, if you remove the center column of these dots,
then you're going to see two blocks of rectangles
because we group things that are close to one another together.
So, that's one of the main principle of Geisha,
we call that the law of proximity.
Yeah, and the way that you were applying it was fascinating.
And it had to do with, I think it was a menu in Far Cry
that you used to level up skills and stuff.
And sometimes those things,
like I know that's difficult to design at all.
But the way that you're explaining it's like,
see how these are close together.
This looks like it's vertical and it's
actually a horizontal progression system.
Yeah.
That and that, I don't know.
It just seems mind-bending to me.
I know. For us, it seems so obvious.
Sometimes we just do things and we're like,
oh, we're going to iterate on that later,
and that later never happens.
That's the reason why we need to anticipate
things and need to use these principles.
to design so that from the beginning it's at least it's following some principles
because we're going to have to iterate anyway.
But there's some principles we can easily apply but we just forget.
And there's a lot of things that are shipped that are violating these basic principles just because
to us it's so obvious because we know that the system is working horizontally
and so it's again, the perception is flawed.
So that knowledge is changing the way we perceive the system.
We're kind of running short on time.
Oh, god, already?
I feel like I could keep on going forever.
But we still have time for a few things.
Yeah, I'm going to cut in here.
Yeah, go ahead.
I was going to ask, obviously, having a UX researcher or UX
designer on your team has a huge payoff,
as the last 40 minutes of conversation can attest.
But what concepts from considering
UX should developers in other disciplines
keep in mind to their day-to-day if they don't have someone
like that on their team?
Yeah, well that's basically the information I want to give away in my book.
So this is where I summarized everything.
What's really important is to have the correct mindset.
And always think about players first and place them at the center of whatever you're doing.
So of course if you can't play this it's going to be difficult because you do need to have that check
because there are many things you can't anticipate.
But at least if you have a better understanding of how the brain works,
the main flaws in terms of perception, attention, memory,
and if you understand better how motivation works,
what's going to be important to make it engaging for players,
so things like motivation, emotion, and game flow.
This is just like the...
The basic information that at least if you have that is going to change a bit your mindset
and it's going to help you anticipate problems and iterate and find solutions faster.
But of course it's never going to replace a UX designer.
These people are really specialized into interaction design and information architecture
so they can help you define systems.
So that's going to be really critical if you have a game with a lot of systems and a heavy UI.
and play testing is always going to be important to help you out. So if you can't play test,
there's a lot of people who can offer these services. I assure you it is worth it.
So I know it's hard to
to invest money in there, but it's a new investment that you will not regret.
But the basic information is on my website, because I know the book is quite extensive.
But this is really the information you need to understand so that you can start shifting
your mindset from, I'm going to design what I want to do, to I want to offer that experience
to that sort of players, and I want to make sure this is really what I'm achieving.
Having that mindset is really key.
So like speaking of consulting on these games, can you, I'm interested in hearing
uh
What you know, are there what are the common mistakes or if there are or is it just like everything? Uh, you know
all the things
um
Well, the common mistakes, yeah, it's often times the same thing.
We have that hope that things are going to be okay and I mean it really depends on the games.
But when I work with AAA studios and they are making a game for hardcore gamers,
the typical...
caveat here is they always hope that, oh, because it's hardcore gamers, they will understand it.
But this is not true. And hardcore gamers, it's not only your game coming out,
or there's a lot of games that come out, and they're not going to blame it on their skills
if they don't understand something, and as well they should. They're just going to say,
well, I don't get it, or if they die and they don't understand why.
depending on how motivated they are to play your game,
they might not try to figure out your game.
And you can't count on that.
It's really rare that the game has so much hype
that even if it's confusing,
players are gonna really work around it
and try to be motivated to figure it out.
Or if they do, it's just a very small proportion
of your audience.
So that's one of the main...
flaw that I see from players, from studios that are developing a Harker, a game for Harker gamers.
Yeah, that's interesting too because the way that you, you know, are taking into consideration there
are other games that are coming out that, you know, but do you say that because it could like,
you know, they're understanding how one game works that's kind of similar and then...
The UX doesn't apply crossways or?
It's not just that.
So you need to be motivated.
And so for motivation, there's three principles
for intrinsic motivation.
So the motivation of playing your game just
for the pleasure of playing it, not because other people are
playing it so you want to be part of their gig.
But it's about competence, autonomy and relatedness.
Competence is about feeling in control and feeling that you're progressing in the game.
If the game is not making players feel competent in playing the game, they're going to quit.
And competence is not... I'm not saying that the game should... you should never lose and everything is always great.
You do need challenge. But competence is about if I die, I understand why I died and next time I can come back to it and get better at it.
And this is not happening because the signs and feedback in the game are not clear, because you don't have that good affordances.
Players are just gonna quit. And especially because there are other games out there.
So that's the thing we need to focus on.
It's really important to make sure, this is what the onboarding is all about,
is make sure players are going to feel competent into playing the game
and they feel they can get better and progress.
If they don't feel that, this is when trouble starts.
When you're describing that stuff, I'm thinking of like, you know, these really difficult,
like, Souls-like games that they're popular, they're really popular, you know, especially
considering how difficult they are.
It's kind of like, they're popular because you know that you're the one who messed up.
Yeah, but the Souls game, I mean, it's in the contract.
You know that you're getting in to suffer and this is typically the type of players
that they're targeting.
And so this is usually what I...
It's funny because typically Souls games are the ones that come up saying, oh, you know,
with UX, every game is going to be easy and we can lose Souls games, like, ah.
And no, if the experience of the game you want to offer is one for people who like to suffer,
we're absolutely going to help you accomplish your sadistic goals.
But you have to know that your audience is going to be much smaller.
And so to make it work, everything else has to be really well done in terms of UX.
Everything is UX.
Exactly. Everything in life is UX.
Do you have a difficult time turning your UX brain off?
You're just looking at stuff and you're like,
oh, every time you go up to a door
and then it looks like you push it,
but it's an actual pull, you're like...
I can't tell you how many times I get mad at things around me, like everything.
I'm like, oh, do they expect me to remember that shit?
Or if I see something like elevators or every time I go to a new place.
Well, sometimes it's fun because when I go to a new country, I try to see, can I operate this machine?
Can I figure out how to buy a metro ticket?
Oh, yeah, I know.
Oh, yeah. I've gotten lost in a fair share of foreign subways.
But it's fun, it's interesting.
But there's also, just to finish about the idea of difficulty, it's also really important
to make your game inclusive, which means also it has to be accessible.
And it's not because you define it.
Difficulty is really arbitrary.
It depends on how the designers, they
want the game to be difficult. But I
don't see why you should make your game not accessible
to a lot of people just because you can't have
many different options that can alleviate barriers
to enjoy your game.
So that's really important.
And there's a lot of debate around that.
And I really, I just really don't understand
why are we still having the debate today?
Yeah, yeah, I have a difficult time understanding it too.
You just brought up another topic
we could talk another hour about.
I'm sorry.
Oh yeah, I forgot about accessibility.
No, yeah, we didn't need to wrap it up,
but let's talk a little bit more about your book.
Gamer's Brain is already out.
Like it's, you know, people are reading it.
You have another one that you said
you just finished up recently.
Yeah, so the new book is called The Psychology of Video Games.
It's really more for a broad audience.
And it's about explaining how video games are made
and what is the impact of video games.
So it's the psychology of making games, also
the psychology of playing games.
And the idea is to go through, so first of all, UX,
so where is it coming from, and how psychology
is used to make games, because you have a lot of people.
and the public they don't understand and they feel,
oh, they have psychologists,
they must be trying to manipulate my brain.
And so there's a lot of fear around that.
So I really wanted to explain what this is all about.
And then also explaining a bit better the.
the research around the impact of video games because there's also a lot of great claims
around that.
So you have one side saying, oh, video games are going to save the world and they make
everything better.
Most of the time, these are great claims that are not necessarily backed up by science.
And on the other side, you have, oh my God, video games are killing everybody and everything
is dark and everybody is getting violent and hooked up in games.
And this also...
our great claims are not backed up by science.
So the idea was to look into these things,
look into the positive impact of games.
When is this happening?
What conditions and what can be the negative impact of games?
It's mainly regarding if you're over-consuming games,
of course, that can lead to problems.
But the main issues that we talk about video games as if it was
a big bucket of the same thing.
And we need to stop talking about the great or bad impact of games and start to talk about more specifically
what is bringing something interesting in terms of health or education or cognitive skills
and what are the limitations that we need to be careful about.
And it's mostly about mechanics and it's mostly about specific things and not just video games as a broad.
topics. So this is what I was trying to accomplish in this book and I also
finish by talking about ethics and what we need to look into because the game
industry also need to talk about ethics a bit more I think. How do you mean ethics?
So thinking, making sure that we are aware that there's no design is neutral.
So everything we design is going to influence people to use the design in a way or another.
So when we design games to encourage people to come back.
It's a fair game, especially for free-to-play, we need to have that to make money, so I totally
understand.
But sometimes, for example, we design games that punish disengagement.
And this is where it can be a little bit unethical because then it's not that you're encouraging
people to come back and they're going to be rewarded if they come back, you're going to
be punished if you're not coming back, which is a little bit different.
And I think it's important for the game industry to look into these mechanics and define where
we should draw the line.
before, because it's already, you know, policymakers and the public is talking about these things,
whether it is loot boxes or retention mechanics, and we need to own that discussion, and we
need to start looking into where's the line, and so that we can address the issue, because
there are some issues, and we should not shy away from addressing them.
And when is the new book coming out?
Ah, it's gonna be in October, so it's not anytime soon, I'm sorry.
That's alright.
But it will be available on newsstands everywhere.
I hope so, yes!
Yeah, if we still have, well, yeah, in October, hopefully, we're gonna be able to be out.
Yeah, it's frustrating, but it is the way it is.
That's a whole nother thing.
Yeah!
But we're all in there together.
Yeah, we are.
And well, thanks so much for joining us.
This was absolutely fascinating.
I'm glad you find that fascinating.
As you can see, I can talk about it forever.
Yeah, well, we need to have you on again sometime.
Anytime!
Alright, well, thanks, Doc.
And since I have permission to comment...
Thanks, Chris and Lisa.
Yeah, and take care and stay safe.
Yeah, everybody stay safe please.
And just like that, Celia was gone.
Is that how, I guess that's how we'll start the third bit like that?
No, she was, she was excellent.
Uh, like I, uh, I'm still absorbing, uh, all of the information and my
practical and applicable information.
It's the best kind.
Yeah, that's been the nice thing about our GDC podcast guests so far is they can just talk
about their subject matter forever. And it is incredible to listen to.
Yeah, I know. We like don't have to do anything.
Oh my god, just mm hmm. Every now and then and just podcast podcast itself.
Podcast podcast.
Podcast. No tongue twisting. Okay.
Yeah. This segment's gone really well.
Yep, back on track. I was looking forward to this one in particular, this conversation in particular,
because getting into more of like the behind the scenes writing about like the game industry and
stuff like that, UX was one of those like early question marks, you know, where like, I'm like,
yeah, I know what game design is, I know how programming and art like they just do the typing
and the drawing and then like, but UX is this like mystery one where I'm like, I don't actually know
what that is.
So like getting to kind of validate everything I've learned about that over the years of
picking things up here and there and just hearing an expert talk about it was a really enlightening
way of like all the ways it touches the different aspects of game design and how it goes unnoticed
when it's done so well and yeah and there's you know
a rising interest in it, it seems like, like, you know, like we mentioned earlier, she runs the GDC
UX summit. She's the chair of that. And I remember the first time that we did the summit,
I think it was the first time, pretty sure. But it was just a huge, huge turnout.
So this is something that, you know, is, you know, a newer field, you know, it's not like brand new,
but it's something that, you know, people are taking more interest in, and especially if you
are a small studio, you know, you might not be able to, you know, hire somebody like Celia,
which by the way, hire Celia.
And you want to try to, you know, obtain that information for yourself if you can.
And it's
I think it'll just make for better video games,
an overall better experience.
Because like I said, you start realizing everything
is user experience.
Yeah.
There is like the, I think it's in the Matrix,
where everything feels back, and it's just
like the numbers and the data.
It's like that, but everything's UX.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Yeah, and also, you know.
There was, I wish there was more time to talk to her about this stuff,
but there's the learning aspect of it.
And when I say learning aspect, it's like, it seems like
90% of it is about learning.
She was talking about onboarding and, you know, that's a way of talking
about, you know, the initial learning of, you know, this new system that
you're going to be interacting with.
So that's.
you know, that's fascinating. There's that great analogy with the first stage of Super Mario
Brothers and I don't know if you saw it but it or I can't even remember like where it was. It's
somewhere. If someone can find that who's listening. Somewhere online.
Yeah, but it, you know, that those very first blocks in Super Mario Brothers taught you so many things
about how the rest of the game works and then it's just like okay. Well, that's you know, that's why
Nintendo is
Number one in the biz right there. Yeah
That's the kind of stuff that I'll poke designers about when we talk to designers,
is intuitively teaching people things.
And I didn't realize that was such a big part of the UX side of game development,
was just kind of the more data-driven looks at creating things in a readable way.
Um, we, we brought out ethics, uh, also talked about that for a little bit.
And if you're interested in looking more on that, um, Celia actually, I think if
you just Googled, uh, Celia Hodent and, um, ethics, you'll turn up her Gama Sutra
blog, which is like thousands of words, a couple of, like a couple thousand words.
It's an expanded GDC talk, actually.
And she talks about the kinds of ethics and, you know, approaching these ethical issues in a scientific way.
And it, you know, talks about loot boxes also, all of these controversial things and, you know, a game addiction,
which we weren't able to talk about too much, but these are things that...
It's really interesting that it's at the top of her mind.
Um, and of course they should be because they're, they're UX based, aren't they?
Yeah, I was kind of married with earlier on in the conversation, it was mentioned that
like research, doing like a heavy research into how people think in game development,
like, outside, it kind of looks like shady, like, oh, they're trying to figure out how to
best extract money from the free to play. Yeah. But like her article on ethics talks about a lot
more of that, but in like a good multi layer and multifaceted way.
Yeah, her entire Gamma Sutra blog is very readable and
knowledgeable and I recommend checking it out. Please don't judge the UX of our website.
It's uh, what's the word, vintage? Yeah, it's vintage. It's uh, you know, it's the aesthetic
that counts. Comfortable throwback to uh, yeah, anyway. Simpler time. That was a great
chat. She's so enthusiastic and I love it. Yes. I'm enthusiastic about Celia's enthusiasm.
All right, so that's all for this week.
You know, check us out on iTunes, Google Play, Spotify,
and should we keep saying YouTube?
I haven't, we haven't uploaded one there
in a little while.
You can check something out on YouTube.
We'll do it at some point.
There's other content.
There is a couple things out on YouTube.
Yeah, there's plenty of GDC content on YouTube besides us.
Yeah, you can go to GDC YouTube for other stuff, I guess.
So if you liked what you heard, uh, like and subscribe, please.
We would love that.
All right.
For now I'm well, not for, for now I will continue to be Chris graft.
I will do my best to continue to be Alyssa McAloon and, uh, have a, uh,
shit, have an excellent outro.
Yeah.
So close.
All right.
you