All right.
Everyone was like, all right, we're behind schedule.
Let's just get to this quickly.
And I was like, no.
OK, so I'm not going to show you a video, apparently.
Instead, I'm just going to show you these screenshots.
And so, the mortician's tale.
In the game, you are tasked with the daily tasks actual morticians have in actual real life.
So preparing the bodies of the deceased for burials and cremations.
This is a contrast from the comedy that was just happening right now.
But you're also attending the respective funerals for each member of the deceased
and overhearing conversations with their loved ones.
And there's a bit of business elements to it too, so going through the protagonist's emails
and interacting with her bosses and co-workers and clients, etc.
And we launched a Mortician's Tale for PC, Mac, via Steam,
Humble, and HIO last October.
So this is the agenda for the talk.
I'm going to do a very, very brief history of death
in video games.
I'm going to talk about my personal history with death
in video games and how that influenced Mortician's Tale.
Most of this talk is going to be about developing a Mortician's
Tale.
And then at the very end, I'm going
to talk about other indie game devs doing cool things
with death and also close the talk with strategies
on how you can also do cool things with death
in video games.
So a very, very brief history on death in video games.
So death has existed in video games
as long as the medium has existed
as a way to punish the player and challenge them to do better.
And since then, we've seen some innovations
on how we use death in video games,
from things like life systems to respawning to regenerating
health or shields.
We've seen innovations on how damage is displayed,
from health bars to damage vignettes
and everything in between.
And we've seen different death mechanics
that innovate on game design altogether
that challenge the player to take death seriously.
So this can be things like permadeath,
really, really difficult combat, or the loss of items
and progress permanently.
We've also seen a lot of innovation
on how we use death narratively.
And I kind of want to focus on this a little bit
because Mortician's Tale is a narrative game.
It is a thing that's really important to us and our team.
And in my opinion, it's the area of game design in which players take death the most seriously.
So most often in games, the way that we see death used narratively is as a way to motivate the
player to play the game. So usually it's the very beginning of the game and it is your character's
spouse or partner or child being killed off, usually in a cutscene, usually off screen.
But there's been a lot of better ways to kind of use death narratively.
So a good example of this is the Mass Effect series,
which encourages players to build up relationships
with characters before they get killed off.
And most of the time, the deaths of these characters
are because of choices that you've made as the player.
So you're directly responsible for those deaths
and need to kind of deal with that impact
over multiple games.
And so when I do my podcast, every guest I have,
I like to ask them if they have a memorable video game death.
And I will say like 80% of the time,
they always bring up Aerith slash Aerith from Final Fantasy 7.
And this makes a lot of sense if this is a game that you kind
of grew up with, because they do a really, really good job
at handling death, both narratively and mechanically.
So in Final Fantasy 7, you have multiple characters
that you can add to your party, but the game
is designed so that Aerith is the dedicated healer.
So most likely you're going to be using her in your party.
And so when they kill her off,
spoiler alert, that game's like 20 years old.
When they kill her off, it's not just like, oh, this character that I liked is gone. It's also,
you have to rethink how you've been playing the game. Because up until now, you've been using her
and from here forward, you have to now rethink about how you're going to play the game. It is
a really, really good mechanical way to represent grief and something being taken away from you and
how you can move forward without them. And Final Fantasy VII and Mass Effect are both really,
really strong examples because they marry.
narrative and mechanics together.
And there's a reason why these games are always brought up.
Lots of games feature death, but very few
ask players to actually deal with it.
And so I want to talk about my most memorable video game,
Death.
And this is a game that got me interested in game development
on the whole, but also how it got
me interested in the subject matter to begin with.
So this is me.
When I was about 9 or 10 years old.
a girl in my class and her mom died in a very, very horrific way.
And it messed me up.
I developed some really, really serious death anxiety.
I couldn't stop thinking about death.
I couldn't stop thinking about how I was going to die,
how my mom was going to die.
I developed some separation anxiety.
I couldn't go to school.
It was just hell for a little while.
And the thing that helped me overcome this was
my mom kind of saw this behavior and was like,
oh, we've got to stop this.
So she encouraged me to...
kind of ask her lots of questions and talk about my feelings.
And she would always answer them honestly,
which is really, really important
when we talk to children about death.
But a really big thing is that she encouraged me
to kind of explore these feelings creatively.
So whether it was through drawing or writing or whatever.
And the thing that helped me overcome my death anxiety,
at least partly, was a Majora's Mask.
And so.
I remember renting it from Blockbuster,
and I became obsessed with this game.
I loved it so much.
And I liked it because it was Majora's Mask, on the whole,
is very, very, very death-centric.
There's a lot of death going on.
You interact with it a lot.
But very explicitly, I remember the villagers in Clock Town,
so the main hub area of this game.
They don't know that the moon's crashing into the Earth.
They need to stop it by rewinding time.
They don't know that you can do that.
They don't know that you can rewind time
and that you're actively trying to save them.
So all they know that they are going,
all they know is that they are gonna die.
And people deal with this in different ways.
So some deny it completely, like the carpenters.
Some people, like the soldiers are like,
we gotta evacuate the town.
We'll be safe from the moon crashing into the earth.
But some people just continue on with their lives.
And that was the thing that stuck with me the most.
is that the mailman's like, well, I'm still
going to deliver the mail, even if I'm going to die tomorrow.
And I remember just being like, whoa.
This is amazing.
And I remember that helping me so much with dealing
with my own mortality.
And I played that game so much, specifically just that town.
I just wanted to talk to people and see how
they were all dealing with it.
So not only did it help me get over some of my death anxiety,
but it also aided my professional curiosity
about this intersection.
So fast forward to 2015.
a book is recommended to me called Smoke Gets in Your Eyes,
which was written by this person here called Caitlin Doughty.
And she is a LA-based mortician slash YouTuber slash author.
And her book is a semi-autographical tale
about her job and how she got into the industry
and how she went from being an intern to going to school
and kind of seeing some weird, shady stuff with the industry
and then starting her own business.
And it's really, really good.
It's really well written and very funny.
But it also introduced me to the idea of death acceptance
or death positivity.
The death positive movement, kind of similar to sex
positivity, is the idea that the more we
talk about taboo subjects, the less scary they are.
And the better equipped we are to make decisions
for ourselves and our loved ones about these scary topics.
So in Western culture, America, Canada specifically,
we're really, really bad about talking about death.
We're really, really bad about pretending it doesn't exist and dealing with it really
poorly when it does happen.
And so the idea of death positivity is not to remove these feelings of grief or sadness.
It isn't like, Grandma, Dad, and I'm fine with it.
It's just the idea that death and grief are sad.
They're always going to be sad.
But if we're okay with confronting these things and lifting the veil on the death industry,
we are better equipped to make decisions for ourselves and our loved ones when we inevitably
die.
And I resonated with this idea a lot,
especially as a person who overcame my own death anxiety
through interacting with it directly.
And this is also what inspired a mortician's tale.
So Caitlin's story was really, really fascinating.
But I was also really into the idea
of creating a video game about the Western death industry
specifically, where players could directly
interact with those themes.
And my goals were to maybe encourage the players
to learn something about certain processes
behind cremation and burial, but also
learn about the Western death industry as a whole.
And one of our sub-goals, too, was
that maybe we could encourage people who have death anxiety
to maybe comfortably overcome it the way
that I did with Majora's Mask.
So in order to support our goals,
like these goals I just mentioned,
we needed to be as accurate as possible.
Right? We did our research, we talked to a lot of death professionals, specifically myself. A lot
of the things I did was look at certain procedures, so doing a lot of research on procedures, talking
to a lot of death professionals about things like embalming and cremation. Our writer, Caitlin
Tremblay, she did a lot of research about grief and kind of the spectrum of grief. So grief isn't
just sadness. It can sometimes be...
anger, it can be denial, it can be happy, it can be you talking about Netflix at a funeral, like it's
it's so broad and Caitlin did a really, really good job at exploring this and doing her research
on it. A big thing that we did too that was really important is that we drew upon our own
experiences with death and grief and we made sure to explore our personal experiences with it in
the game. So A Mortician's Tale started out as my personal game that I was planning on making by
myself. I was very lucky and I got some funding and I was able to hire a team and that was great because
Mortician's Tale grew to be a collection of all of our experiences with death, not just mine,
but our whole team. And I think it's a lot better of a game because of that.
Adding personal bits of our experiences with the subject matter is very important.
One of our goals was to get players hands-on with the processes behind cremation and burials,
and to learn these processes in a hands-on way.
So in video games it's pretty typical that when there's a lot of bodies or zombies or whatever,
when they're killed off, their bodies just kind of disappear.
The mechanic exists for a reason, but in A Mortician's Tale we're asking players to deal with that body directly.
And players take care of bodies in the game the way that funeral directors take care of our bodies in real life, when we die.
And so in the game, you don't know any of the people
that you're taking care of.
It isn't like, oh, surprise, it's your sister.
It's you're all strangers.
And again, I think pretty typically in game,
when people die, like narratively,
it's always someone that you know that you're connected to.
But in this game, we've asked players
to take care of someone that they don't know or love.
And something that we learned when we were doing a lot of research on the game and talking to a lot of
like Katelyn Doughty and a lot of death professionals was that it's really really important that you
spend time with the body after they've died.
It's a really really important part of the grieving process.
And if you're from any other part of the world, this is probably a normal thing for you, but for
again, America and Canada, this is not a thing we do. We're very much like, okay, grandma's gone. Bye!
See you at the funeral.
And so we wanted to make sure that we put the camera
first person during these medical procedures,
and that we made sure that players spent a lot of time
with each respective body.
In getting players to directly interact with subject matters,
it was important for us to be comfortable in finding
the balance of accuracy and comfort.
And we know this because the subject matter
can be really uncomfortable for people.
So finding that balance is really important to us.
And one way we do this is.
the color palette. So I prototyped this game a couple of years ago using Pico 8, which
has very, very few colors, and I kind of used a couple of purple colors. And when we moved
this over to Unity and made it a 3D game, I was like, I still like this palette. I'm
going to kind of keep going with this. One, because I think it...
really works with like the melancholy but hopeful vibe, but I think it also really does a good job
at masking some of the grosser things in the game. So again, there's no like bodily fluids,
there's no jaundiced skin, there's nothing gross like that. The purple kind of hides a lot of the
stuff and allows us to again like explore these things accurately without being too realistic
about it.
Another thing that we do, too, is kind of humanoid figures.
All of the bodies, all the people in the game,
yourself included, kind of have larger heads and larger eyes.
And this is just to avoid uncanny valley.
We also, in order for us to be comfortable,
we had to sacrifice some accuracy.
We didn't include a lot of things
that are part of the procedures behind embalming, for example.
The game is not a one-to-one simulation,
but it's just very, very accurate still.
So, mechanics-wise, Mortician's Tale is a narrative-first game.
Narrative is the pillar of a Mortician's Tale.
And it was really, really important for us
that everything else in the game supported this narrative.
So, the sounds, the music, the mechanics as well.
And so, for the medical parts of Mortician's Tale,
we were really inspired by Trauma Center,
which is a game series that you play as a surgeon.
But in Trauma Center, because you're playing as a surgeon,
they do this cool thing where the game has a timer and a score
and fail states.
So it's very, very, very stressful.
And it's trying to recreate the feeling of being a surgeon
and having some urgency in trying
to save this person's life.
So in contrast, A Mortician's Tale is very much the opposite.
There is no urgency to it.
We don't let you have fail states.
If we have, that was one of the biggest critiques about the game
was people were like.
I wish it could fail, I wish it could accidentally cut somebody.
But if we let you fail, that is, you're disrespecting the body.
We're allowing you to disrespect people.
And so we took that out of the game.
So yeah, the game's a little bit on the rails, but it was designed intentionally to support
the narrative of the game.
One decision we made as well is that the game has no dialogue options.
You are a silent protagonist.
And we did this for a few reasons.
One is because every single person deals with grief differently and death differently.
And so it felt really weird for us to have a fully fleshed out character,
like a Nathan Drake character, and that the player has to kind of take control of.
So it was better for us to create a silent protagonist that could act as a vessel
for the player to kind of insert themselves and their own feelings and own experiences in.
But it also, we did this because it also places the importance of listening rather than talking.
You're not worried about what you are or are not supposed to say, you're just worried about,
not worried, but the goal is to just listen to people and listen to what they're saying
to you.
And that is a big part of being a mortician in real life.
A lot of your job is not to tell someone how to grieve, it's to listen to them when they
are grieving.
So that was really important for us to be accurate in that way.
Regarding the goal of being accurate, we wanted to be accurate not just with technical and medical stuff, but also with the emotional parts of the job.
So one of the things that I asked all of our Martician friends that we were making the game is if there was ever a point where
they couldn't do their job, where they had to say,
I can't do this.
Someone else has to deal with this guy, or whatever.
And in my mind, I think it's like a gore thing or a body
thing.
But every single one of them responded
with the exact same answer, which was yes.
And it was always based off of the story behind the person.
So it was never like the procedure
is the exact same as what they've always
done in their life.
But because they knew the story behind the person,
it made it too hard for them to deal with.
And so we wanted to make sure we were being accurate with that.
So.
in the game, when you start out, depending on who you are, maybe it's a bit shocking to you that
there's a body on the screen. But then we kind of, you know, it's very ritualistic, everything is
kind of the same, the procedures are the same, maybe you get a little bit used to it. And towards
the end of the game we have a couple bodies that, again, same procedures but their stories are a
little bit sadder.
And this was really cool to see because when the game came out,
we saw a lot of streamers and YouTubers play the game.
And they got to those parts of the game.
And even though, again, the procedures are the exact same,
we didn't change a single thing mechanically,
every single person spent way more time on those bodies
than they did the beginning bodies.
So that was pretty neat.
All right, I want to talk about the reaction.
So we released this game in October,
and we were met with lots of critical success, which
is very nice, but also really cool
was that we received a lot of messages and emails and DMs
from people sharing personal stories about how
the game really, really resonated with them,
how the game helped them grieve.
There's a lot.
how the game helped them make decisions after they played the game and then someone died,
and the game helped them make decisions regarding those processes, or how to support someone who
was grieving. And a lot of people messaged us saying how they deal with death anxiety and
how the game has helped them kind of overcome it a little bit, which is really cool. Also,
a lot of fan art and cosplay, which I'm a big fan of, so that's pretty neat.
When we made the game, we expected no one to like it. It's super niche, we understand,
but it's really cool that players are interested in the subject matter.
that they're interested in exploring their own feelings
about it, and that the design decisions we made
are having a positive impact on people.
And we are not the only ones who are innovating
on how death is used in games.
So I think indie developers in particular
are doing some really, really cool things with death.
Thinking outside how we traditionally
use death in games, bringing their own experiences
to the table.
sharing stories from a variety of cultural backgrounds.
Here's some recent examples.
We've seen lots of really cool innovations
on the narrative side, whether it's thematically
via Night in the Woods or Speed Dating for Ghosts,
or very explicitly like The Graveyard and The Walking Dead.
There's a lot of games that combine narrative
with interesting mechanics to create immersive experiences
with death and grief.
There are games that are exploring new mechanics,
and in the case of E-Valkyrie, new mediums like VR.
And we're seeing lots of games
that are using existing mechanics
to tell stories about death and grief,
genocide, family legacy, or even horror.
These are just a few examples.
There's lots more games that I could have included in here.
All of these games deal with death in their own unique ways,
and they're very popular with players,
and they're really, really good and powerful
because they each use death mechanics that best
suit their respective games.
So how can you do the same?
If you're interested in using death in your games,
what is the best way that you can use it for your game?
So like I mentioned, it's important to talk about
and think about what death best fits your personal game.
If your game is mechanics first.
like a roguelike or FPS, everything else in your game should support it and should include narrative.
So Guacamelee is a fantastic example of this, right?
And one of the big mechanics in Guacamelee is you're shifting between two worlds,
and there's a lot of combat mechanics that are really interesting about that.
So the narrative, which is, you know, flipping between the world of the living and world of the dead,
fits very nicely with that, and the aesthetic looks very cool too.
The sound design changes when you flip over. Everything supports that mechanic really well.
If your game is narrative first, if the pillar of your game
is narrative, like a mortician's tale,
whether it's a visual novel or a first person narrative game,
everything else in your game should support that.
So Edith Finch, fantastic example of this, right?
Edith Finch mechanics do a really, really good job
at getting the player to directly interact
with different deaths.
They do a really good job with that.
And make sure that you're not just relying on traditional death mechanics.
They're fine, you know, respawning exists for a reason,
life systems exist for a reason, but it's really important
that you figure out what best suits your game's design.
And as much as I'm like, death is great, how are you guys using it in your games?
It's also important to think about, is death even necessary in your game?
If you're making a game like Animal Crossing, do you need to have death in it?
Does it support what Animal Crossing's doing?
Just think about that.
Specifically, if you are working with death the way that we kind of did, it's really,
really important for you to do your research and consult.
Do interviews, do consultations.
The internet can be a really good resource.
There was a lot of really gross stuff that we found when I was doing research for Martician's
Tale, so just be careful if you're squeamish.
But really, really importantly is to be.
respectful. That is the most important thing, not just with dealing with dead bodies,
but also with how other cultures are treating death. If you're interested in exploring that,
make sure that you are consulting and paying your consultants.
And if you're again exploring death kind of explicitly, make sure that you're understanding with, being understanding with your players,
especially like for very, very personal games like A Mortician's Tale.
Death and grief is a very hard for a lot of people, and so it's really important to kind of think about and make adjustments as necessary.
A really good also,
understanding, understanding play testing is not indicative of final play session.
I talked to Ian Dallas, who's the creative director of Edith Finch,
on one of my podcast episodes, and he told me a story about how
during playtesting, people would be like, this game's great, this is cool.
And the same people would go home and then message him and be like, I bawled my eyes out.
And he was like, why didn't you cry here?
So if you're playtesting your games, understand...
I don't think he actually said that, but my brain...
If you're playtesting your game and you're not getting the response you want, you're not like,
is this game sad enough? Understand that playing games by yourself is very different than playing
games when someone's standing over your shoulder watching you. Death is really personal. And it's
really important that, again, if you're dealing with death, that you assess your own feelings,
because it can be really hard as a developer to work on these games for two or three years.
it's really, really important to be comfortable when you're having discussions or doing research,
etc., and making sure that not just you, but your team is also comfortable with the subject matter.
Our sound designer, Jen Costa, did a lot of research to make sure the sounds were accurate,
and she had to listen to hours and hours of embalming music. If she was not comfortable
with that, the game would have been very, very different. So it's really, really important that
if you want to explore this topic as deeply as we did, that you're just somewhat comfortable with it.
And self-care is important.
Whether you're making a game about death
or just a very, very gory game or whatever,
it's really important to kind of take a step back sometimes
and just be away from it.
And self-care can be things like having a bath
or going for a run, or if you're me,
it's watching Riverdale.
It's a terrible show.
I love it so much, it's so good.
And if you're, very importantly,
if you're not a person who is comfortable with death.
maybe consider exploring those feelings about it. If you're not comfortable with it, you know,
consider making a game about those feelings because it can be very therapeutic. Ultimately,
developing Mortician's Tale has changed me for the better. I've learned so much from it and
I've taken those experiences with me when people I know have died. And so I hope if you decide to
explore this topic that it can be as therapeutic for you as it was for me. Thank you so much.
Hmm