Hi, I'm Lauralyn, and this is the Side Project Ritual.
So I'm not gonna do a lot of bio
because I have a lot to go over during the talk,
but I'll just say briefly that I've worked in games
for about 26 years now,
across a whole bunch of different platforms,
game styles, audiences for a lot of different companies.
And over the years,
I've almost always had a side project going.
In fact, most of my friends kind of consider
my side projects to be my ever-present companion
as I go through game development.
And that's largely what I'm gonna be talking about today,
what I've learned about that process
and how it's helped me stay in the industry
for as many years as I have.
I've also spoken quite a bit at conferences
and initially it was about design topics,
but recently I found myself at a niche
between
wellness and game development.
And so this talk today is also squarely
in between those two subjects.
So a little bit of an overview
about what I'm gonna be talking about
just to help us stay oriented.
I'm gonna spend a little bit of time
talking about burnout and its toll.
Not a lot of time, but a little bit
just to make sure we're operating
from the same assumptions about burnout.
Then I'm gonna be talking about the power of ritual
and other mental tools that you can use to succeed.
and then I'll actually be giving you the eight steps
in the side project ritual.
So let's get started by talking about burnout.
So everyone's familiar with the topic of burnout
if you've worked in game development at any time,
for any time length at all, you've probably encountered it,
if not in yourself, then in others.
The World Health Organization actually considers it
a disorder or syndrome, and they describe it as being
a syndrome resulting from chronic workplace stress.
that has not been successfully managed.
I'm not a big fan of that passive language.
I would almost call it passive aggressive language there,
because it implies that the person on the receiving
end of burnout has to be the one to manage it.
I don't necessarily think that's the case.
But I do agree with the dimensions.
I'm going to mention a couple more,
but the dimensions that they say here
that it's really characterized by a feeling of
exhaustion and feeling negative or cynical about your job,
and then reduced efficiency and effectiveness at your job.
We actually live in a time and work in
an industry with inevitable stress.
I don't know what possibly could be happening right now in
the world that would cause any of us to have any stress.
But on top of that, our industry is its own source of stress.
It's a creative work environment.
And what that means is that people are always
critiquing your work, and you're always
putting yourself and your skills and your talent
and what you believe out there for other people to critique.
And that inherently creates stress.
Where it's also an industry of constant change.
So whether it's moving on to a new game,
whether it's new people on the team, people leaving the team,
We're always, even when we make sequels,
we're always having to create new features
and new elements that have never been seen before in games.
It's just the constant flood of change can be overwhelming.
There's also a lot of loss and grief
we don't really discuss.
Even shipping a game that you're proud of
has a certain amount of loss and grief associated with it
because you spent a lot of time with that game.
and having it suddenly out of your life can be something that's hard to deal with. But even more
so, having games canceled and companies close and people leave the team or the industry altogether,
it's definitely cycles of loss and grief mixed in between the joy and creation.
And then most important, I think, in terms of adding stress, we have a silence
endurance culture. And what I mean by that is,
you're expected to endure. You're expected to find ways to cope by yourself. And you're expected
not to complain about it and not to try to make changes. And in fact, trying to make changes is
often seen as complaining. It's seen as a lack of passion. It's seen as you just not being strong
enough for this industry. And that is unfortunate because what that means is we don't fix the
problems that are causing people to feel so much stress. So
The stress that creates burnout and burnout itself often go unrecognized.
So here's some of the ways that you can recognize it in yourself and in others.
There's what everybody looks for, which is that intense anger.
I can't take this anymore.
But there are also other signs like the thousand mile pain stare
that you see from someone who's been crunching for six months now.
There's a frustration and an inability to focus,
and the two really are a self-feeding cycle.
between those two factors.
And there are feelings of worthless and incompetence.
And I want to make sure to separate this out
from imposter syndrome.
Imposter syndrome is when you feel
like you're not good at something you're actually
good at, a specific task or activity or thing
that you're actually good at.
This is feeling worthless and incompetent at everything.
You feel like you just are not worth anything as a person,
not just about the task.
It causes us to disconnect from friends and family and things that we enjoy.
And it also causes physical illness, heart illness, heart disease.
And stress itself can just cause a variety of effects,
including autoimmune disorders on your body.
And that's not to mention, of course, heartburn and ulcer.
So there are a ton of ways to recognize
when burnout is happening,
but usually we discover it way too late.
We figure it out at the point where you
or the person involved just wants to leave the team
or leave the company,
or maybe even leave the whole industry.
And this comes at a really high cost.
In a Deloitte survey, 91%...
of the people they surveyed. This is just about people in general, not about game development.
91% said that they have an unmanageable amount of stress. When they do, it negatively impacts
the quality of their work. 83% said burnout from work negatively impacts their personal
relationships. And here's the important point.
87% say they're passionate about their current job,
but 64% say they're still frequently stressed.
Passion does not exclude or make impossible getting burned out
and getting stressed.
So that is a fiction in game development
that if you're passionate about it, you'll never burn out.
And in fact, in game development,
there's also a very high cost.
So game development as a career, as a way to make a living,
has been around for at least 30 years.
I know because when I started.
people had already been in it for five or ten years.
And yet, when you look at the stats, there's this huge cliff
where 82% of game developers have been in the industry less than 15 years. It's
the 15-year cliff, which means, of course, the flip side,
only 16% of game developers have been in the industry for 15 or more years.
So that includes me. I'm in that category,
and I've actually watched a lot of the people that I knew and were friends with
who had as many years as I have.
get frustrated and burned out and leave.
So what can we do to start to take control over this
and to really battle burnout?
There's some standard things that are always suggested
when this topic comes up.
Mindfulness, which you'll see as a part of my presentation
as well.
They always recommend, of course,
that you take your breaks and schedule your vacations
and use up your PTO every year.
Although in most jobs, it's really difficult
to do that in many game jobs because you're always
a critical person.
and often told that you can't take your vacation this year,
you need to save it for next year.
Take advantage of mental health resources.
TakeThis is a great organization.
I encourage you to check it out
and avail yourself of their resources.
Cultural change, lots of movements
about changing our culture to be less abrasive
and to be less demanding in terms of crunch.
and in terms of expected ordinary overtime.
So those are all good ways to see the signs
and interrupt the process and try
to improve overall our industry so that there's less burnout.
But what would really be better is
to avoid that in the first place and to focus
on the kind of growth and resilience
that helps us not get burned out.
And I'm not saying that companies don't need to improve
because they definitely do.
But you as a person also can become more resilient.
The process, though, of becoming more resilient
requires an intent to do that.
It requires a sense of purpose.
And it also requires some plans and consistency.
It's not something that happens by accident.
But when you can manage to do that, you can really heal.
So this is a plan, the side project ritual,
is eight science back steps.
And I'll use the power of ritual for mental and emotional reset.
So when I say that I'm going to recommend you recover from the burnout of game development
with more game development, I anticipate the reaction is probably going to be,
really? You know, and I understand why this guy and you might be skeptical.
So let's just get into it and I'll talk about.
why I think this is valuable and why you shouldn't be skeptical about it.
The side project ritual is a purpose-driven plan to battle burnout,
and it does use the power of ritual.
And when I say the power of ritual, a lot of people get this image in their head.
And I understand that it has certain connotations,
but I do want to make the point upfront that that's not the case here.
If you're into crystals and incense, cool, good for you, you can totally use that.
But ritual does not have to be about.
those sorts of things. It doesn't have to be tied to any religion or even any spirituality.
In fact, this is going to be very pragmatic and very practical, and it includes a lot of
scientific data and studies and tips. So don't go into this expecting that it's going to be
kind of a new religion or anything like that. It's really a set of mental tools and tricks.
We're going to use cognitive science and reboot and build resilience in your brain.
So,
What do I mean when I say ritual?
This is my definition of ritual for the purpose of this talk.
A ritual involves words, signs, and actions
that take you away from the mundane,
crafting an intentional space for creative work
and free thought.
Some of the mental techniques involved around ritual
can vary depending on what the ritual is.
But there's a reason that it's so successful in human culture
across the world.
Almost every human society has elements of ritual.
embedded in various aspects of their life.
And they all have certain things in common.
One of them is visualization,
where you're picturing an outcome
of the work that you're doing.
Studies have shown that thoughts produce
the same mental instructions and effects as actions do.
And in fact, visualization, visualizing success,
visualizing things being better,
visualizing completing something.
is actually, can actually enhance motivation,
increase confidence and increase your efficiency.
It improves your motor performance.
It can increase the flow state.
Visualization is actually a profound way
to improve your success.
And some studies, for example,
showed that basketball players, this is the classic study,
basketball players were split into two groups.
One group practiced free throws
and the other group visualized making free throws
and didn't practice at all.
And when they actually played the next day,
those who visualized saw a slightly greater
performance increase over those that practiced.
It's that effective.
Superstition is another element of ritual.
And most people have a negative connotation to superstition,
but I'd like to invite you to change your mind about that.
An example of superstition is there was an experiment,
actually two experiments around golf.
In one experiment, people before they made a shot in golf
were told that they had a lucky ball
or that they had an ordinary ball.
In the other experiment, before someone took their shot,
either the moderator said nothing
or said, I'm crossing my fingers for you.
In both cases involving luck, performance increased.
And in fact, we as human beings and all animals, really,
are wired for superstition.
The probably most famous behavioral researcher,
B.F. Skinner, started researching pigeons.
And he set up something to feed the birds at regular intervals.
And what happened was the birds didn't
develop a sense of time and all cluster
around the feeding mechanism at a certain time.
they started acting in a particular way
and started believing that the way they were acting
influenced the arrival of food.
So by the end of the study, 3 quarters of the pigeons
became superstitious.
And for example, one pigeon believed
that turning around in a circle two or three times
was what brought the food.
And most interestingly, it wasn't
turning in any direction.
It was always counterclockwise, that he
would turn counterclockwise two or three times,
and then the food would come.
So if birds can become superstitious without any prompting from us, any really teaching that
behavior, that tells you how effective it is and how well it works. And in fact, many successful
creators have used lucky rituals. For example, Mary Shelley had a boa constrictor around her
neck while she wrote, and she would interpret how the boa constrictor was acting and moving
to determine whether she was done writing for the day.
Charles Dickens actually had a compass with him
that he carried all the time.
And he always slept with him and facing north.
So there's tremendous use of superstition as a tool,
as a mental tool.
And we want to use it to leverage
those internal mechanisms to build self-confidence
and self-esteem.
And then finally, creative therapy actually works too.
Creative exercises have been shown to reduce pain, anxiety,
and depression and stress while increasing self-esteem
and improving the quality of life.
Creativity itself has that effect.
It doesn't matter how good you are at it
or what you produce at the end of it.
It's the act of creativity that has the therapeutic effects.
And so I say all of these things knowing that inherently,
most people in game development are skeptics of science
when it comes to things like this.
We're absolutely believers in science and everything else,
but we tend to dismiss things like superstition
and visualization and even ritual itself
because it's sometimes easier to dismiss those
than to see them as tools.
And so I understand that sense.
I understand that sentiment.
but somehow ritual and visualization and superstition
and creativity and game dev just don't belong
in the same process together.
But I can tell you they do.
And I can tell you that game development
is the answer for burnout in game development.
And that's not just because it's the hair
of the dog that bit you.
So here's some reasons that you can use a solo game project
to battle your burnout.
First is that one thing that causes a lot of workplace stress
and game development is that you are constantly in,
for most people, under deadline, under stress,
trying to get things done,
trying to make sure those things coordinate
with what the rest of the team is doing.
And you have somebody who's telling you what to create.
And that's true for almost everybody.
Even if you're an executive at a game company,
I can say from experience,
I still had a boss who was telling me what to do.
So in my side projects though, no one could tell me what to do.
And that was when I especially was under stress during a project at any given time.
Or if I felt like I didn't agree with the decisions that were being made,
it was tremendously helpful for me to come home and work on something where no one could tell me
what to do. It also means you can focus on variety, make something new and exciting,
learn new skills, do things you haven't done before.
it gives you tremendous freedom to express yourself.
Most of us don't get to actually express everything
in who we are as a part of the games that we're making,
usually because we're making those in collaboration
with other people.
But it also lets you express yourself in other ways.
It doesn't mean every game you make has to be a message
game with a capital M.
It can let you express yourself in terms of making that game you voice that sounded fun,
but maybe three other people besides you would want to play. That's expressing yourself too.
But the bottom line and the thing that I found ultimately most helpful about having a game dev
side project is I can make whatever the hell I want and nobody could tell me any differently.
And that freedom of just being my own boss really made a difference to me.
So here's how all of these puzzle pieces fit together into the side project ritual.
It is eight steps and we're going to start with step one which is the opening.
So the opening of any ritual has a purpose. Every step has a purpose,
but the opening is particularly important. It triggers our superstitions.
And it tells your brain that you're switching modes,
that this thing that's about to come up,
you understand what it is, and you know what you're
going to be doing, and that it's important.
So before you start envisioning wind chimes and whale song,
it's about what's important to you.
So you want to collect inspirational items, images,
music, practices, because again, you're
triggering your brain that you're
getting ready to do the work.
You definitely want to give some thought to superstition.
And look, if you don't have things that you will consider lucky now,
start to try to build those superstitions. Think about, you know, if I have
green tea while I'm working, it's going to help me work faster or it's
going to help me work better. Try to build those links for yourself.
And again, so you don't think it has to be a whale song.
Let's look at an example.
Dad! Dad!
It's important!
Then wait, count to twenty.
No, Dad! Do you listen?
Junior!
One, two, three, four...
In Greek.
Ena...
...dio...
...dia.
Tessera...
...dente...
So did you catch it?
Henry Jones Jr. has a focusing phrase
that he would use in his opening when he gets distracted.
May he who illuminated this illuminate me.
And that's a good example of the kind of thing
that you would use as a focus during your opening.
A couple other examples.
I'll refer to Steven Pressfield in his book, The War of Art,
a little bit later again in this presentation.
It's an awesome book, though.
And he opens it or has in it what he does every day
as a part of his work.
He says, I put on my lucky work boots
and stitch them up with the lucky laces
that my niece Meredith gave me.
I head back to my office, crank up the computer.
My lucky hooded sweatshirt is draped over the chair with the lucky charm I got in St. Marie de la Mer
for only eight bucks. With my lucky Largo name tag that came from a dream I once had, I put it on.
On my thesaurus is my lucky cannon that my friend Bob Forsandy gave me. I point it toward my chair
so it can fire inspiration into me. I say my prayer which is the invocation of the muse from
Homer's Odyssey. And it sits next to my shelf.
with the cufflinks that belong to my father and my lucky acorn from the battlefield at Thermopylae.
It's about 10 30 now. I sit down and plunge in. And similarly from Stephen King.
I have a glass of water or a cup of tea. There's a certain time I sit down from 8 to 8 30 somewhere
within a half hour every morning. I have my vitamin pill and my music. I sit in the same seat
and the papers are all arranged in the same places.
The cumulative purpose of doing these things
the same way every day seems to be a way of saying to the mind,
you're going to be dreaming soon.
And that's really what the opening does.
It sets a space in your mind.
It creates that space.
It frames your work, and it gives it purpose.
But you need to figure out what matters to you.
You need to choose something that reflects you
as a unique person.
It can be things that inspired you in the past
or something that's inspiring you to create a new future.
So some examples.
If I were going to create, if my side project was an action
game or a stealth game or had a certain tone to it,
I might choose for my opening focus this quote from Thief.
wisdom and balance lay in knowing your own nature over time.
If during the process, if I wanted to be instead inspired
while working on my side project from the fact that
I've survived an immense amount of time
with incurable lung cancer,
I might quote, I feel fantastic and I'm still alive
from the ending theme song to Portal
and have a screenshot from Portal 2 along with it.
But my focus right now is actually built upon the fact that
I'm making an interactive narrative game.
It's a paranormal romance for Choice of Games
and their new Hearts Choice label.
So because it's writing, this is my opening focus.
I've been to another world and come back, listen to me.
That's from Mark Halprin's Winter's Tale,
which is a book that always inspired me
to write better than I do.
And I chose that focus intentionally
because I feel like as,
the writer and creator of this game,
I am seeing and experiencing this different world.
And now I have to come back and relay it
to people playing the game in a way that makes them
feel like they're experiencing it too.
So that's my opening focus.
But whatever you come up with,
it should be and will be as unique as you are.
So step two.
and the side ritual is the sacred space and time.
Now, when I say sacred, I don't mean religious.
I mean, for example, sacrosanct or regarded with great respect
and reverence.
So when you set up your space, you
want to have a dedicated space.
You're in the same spot every day if you can be.
And it can be really small.
It can be the corner of a kitchen.
You just want to have room to display some objects that
are inspirational to you.
And they don't have to be, again, religious or mystical.
They can be whatever.
It has meaning to you.
You do need to be left alone, though.
So noise-canceling headphones can
help when you're in a shared space,
but also just letting the people that you share your home with
know that when at a certain time of day or night,
you need to be left alone for a certain period of time,
like an hour or two hours, because that's
your focus time.
You also want to gather your tools together into this space.
Most people, of course, think of hardware and software
because we're talking about game development,
but it can also be things like timers.
If you are a big fan of things like the Pomodoro technique,
it can be timers to plan different work sessions.
It can include music themed
for whatever it is that you're working on,
but it can also include things like scent or light.
So it could be,
a candle that smells like evergreens if you're working on something that takes place in a forest,
or light that imitates sunlight to help you feel better during that time, or dim lighting that
makes you feel like it's an escape from the rest of your day, whatever works for you.
And the time is sacred too, so you want to decide how much time you're going to spend
and then you're going to commit to that time.
Committing means you're going to block out distractions.
You're not going to spend that time surfing the web, answering emails.
You're not going to do things that are unrelated to what you're working on.
You're also going to persist even when it's frustrating.
What I mean by that is,
you're going to use that time for something creative,
even if it means switching tasks.
If you are working on your game and you're working on code,
and you feel completely stuck and you just can't do it today,
switch to drawing, switch to making music,
switch to working on audio.
It can even be not related to the project if you have to, like adult coloring books,
things like that. Just do something creative for that space of time.
And always remind yourself that this is your time. It's not an obligation. It's a gift that
you're making to yourself. And over time, as you do the ritual more and more, you'll start
to look forward to it and actually really jealously guard your ritual time.
So step three is mindfulness.
Now, everybody thinks of meditation first when you mention mindfulness.
And yes, meditation is good.
A couple of different things that you can try,
because we're only going to meditate for two to three minutes.
It's a very short session.
You can do three minutes of breathing where you spend those three minutes
being aware of each breath you take.
You try to breathe in a certain rhythm and you try to be aware
of how the breath feels going in and out of your body.
There's something else called visualize the river.
And this is what I used when I was trying
to cope with cancer diagnosis.
So I would envision myself laying on my back,
floating in a river.
And for about 30 seconds, I'll just float in the river
and really even play sound effects
and really immerse myself in that sense
of floating in the river.
And then whatever it is that is distracting me or bothering me,
I'll picture myself actually bundling it up in my head,
like reaching into my head and taking it out.
And I feel it in my hand for a second.
And then I set it in the river beside me.
And now I watch it float along with me.
And after about a minute of that,
I make the decision to let it go.
It's going to be floating in the river with me.
When the time comes, it will still be there.
I just don't need to carry it along with me right now.
You can also repeat a mantra and it doesn't have to be OM or anything like official.
It can be things like I'm here, I'm present or my favorite mantra from a guided meditation that
I used to love. In this moment, everything is okay. But mindfulness doesn't have to be meditation.
There are other ways that you can be mindful. So attentive listening is one way and that is
finding a sound that you find interesting or intriguing.
like a sound of a forest and spending three minutes actually paying attention to it,
really listening to it, trying to pick apart all of the different sounds in it and how often do
you hear them and what do you think they mean. Then there is the raisin exercise which is as
fun as it sounds. You take a small piece of food and you act like you're from another planet and
you've never seen it before.
and you spend the three minutes just looking at it and marveling at it and feeling the texture of it
and smelling it and tasting a little bit of it. Really paying attention to that thing as if you've
never seen it before.
And then mindful seeing.
So mindful seeing is similar to attentive listening.
It's just visual instead.
So you take, you know, you can look out your own window
or for example, on Netflix, there are videos of,
for example, a train going through Sweden for an hour.
So you can take those videos
and just spend three minutes watching it carefully
and just being very mindful about everything
that you're seeing happening, every dust moat,
the wind moving leaves of grass, right?
Very specifically looking at that carefully.
And there are also sound effects and other gadgets
that you can use to help you focus during these sessions,
like singing bowls.
Bonsai.
Taking three to four to five minutes
and trimming and really lovingly caring for a bonsai tree
is one of the most meditative things that you can do.
There are various applications that can help you.
It's Buddhify over there on the left.
Buddhify is super great with short session,
especially for short session meditations that
happen while you're doing something else,
like walking to work or taking a break at work
or about to go to sleep.
I use Headspace myself and very much like it,
but I've also heard really good things about Calm.
And there are actually gadgets that
help with meditation, specifically with coherence,
most of them.
I haven't used the Muse, but I've used the technology in Unite,
which that company used to be called Wild Divine.
I've also used HeartMath,
that's what I have right now.
Coherence is when your breathing and heart rate are in coherence, they're aligned.
In that state, that's the state that naturally occurs with meditation.
In that state, you have enhanced.
senses and enhanced sense of well-being as well.
What the gadgets can do is they can help you
understand the feeling of when you're in that state.
You can achieve that state without the gadgets as well.
Then after the mindfulness, you're going to spend
a few minutes on your focused goals.
You're going to review the work you did in
the last session for about five minutes
and make note of any revisions you have,
but that's getting your head back in
the space of what you were working on.
And taking dedicated time to do that means you're not spending your actual work time,
getting a little bit of the ways down the road and then saying, wait, what was I doing again?
So you're going to take the time to review and get that all in your head first.
And then you're going to look at the focus goals that you had at the end of your last session.
So since those are created at the end of the last session, I'm going to talk about those a little
bit later. And then it's time to do the work. And I use the phrase do the work intentionally.
because that's the phrase that Stephen Pressfield uses in The War of Art.
He also talks about something called resistance. Resistance is the invisible force that stops you
from doing your work. And I think we've all experienced it in one form or another.
And he always says it's the if
It's the thing that stops you from actually working out because working out is good for you.
It's the thing that stops you from eating the healthy stuff instead of the unhealthy stuff
because the healthy stuff is good for you. So he says there's a secret that real writers know
that wannabe writers don't and the secret is this. It's not the writing part that's hard.
What's hard is sitting down to write. What keeps us from sitting down is resistance.
And he goes on to say, most of us have two lives, the life we live and the unlived life within us.
Between the two stands resistance.
Resistance cannot be seen, touched, heard or smelled, but it can be felt.
We all experience it as an energy field radiating from a work in potential.
It's a repelling force.
It's negative.
Its aim is to shove us away, distract us, to prevent us from doing our work.
And I say all of that because you need to focus on doing the work and you need to end resistance and understand when it's happening.
So of course first you'll need to choose a project.
Whatever you choose, it doesn't have to be your final answer. It just needs to be something that you plan to ship.
It can be really small, but you need to plan to ship it.
The act of knowing you're going to complete something changes the tone of your work.
And I think that's an important part of this process is belief that you're going to ship it
when you're done. Then, of course, you need to choose your weapon as well, which is, you know,
kind of for game development, hand in hand with the project that you want to undertake.
So it can be physical games. If you want to get away from working in the digital, which you do
all day.
There's some great narrative game tools out there.
This is actually a screenshot from my narrative game,
which I'm building in ChoiceScript for choice of games.
But there are things like Twine and Inform
that are great too.
There's some really simple game tools
that focus just on the act of creation
and not on the tool itself.
Things like Game Maker, RPG Maker, and Pico 8.
And of course, Unity and Unreal are always available.
So a little bit of a practical note,
a lot of people in game development
work under IP agreements and or restrictions
from mood lighting or commercial side projects.
Those suck and are often, and I'm not saying,
this is not legal advice,
but they're often unenforceable anyway.
But even if they're unenforceable,
it's got a chilling effect because no one wants to
be the person that sounds like you're distracted from your main game that you're working on for
work by this side game. I know personally I was never distracted by my side project,
but it still I felt odd even bringing it up when I had permission when I had to get permission for
a side project. So if you're in that situation and I'm not saying to be a secret squirrel
and work on it secretly, it's a terrible idea. What I am saying is you can do things like game mods.
Game mods are things that avoid the IP issues
because they're always owned by the company
that released the original game.
So things like Skyrim or Fallout, for example,
have creator kits and so do other games.
You can participate in game jams
that starts with your spark,
and then you can finish that small project
and release it for free as a part of the game jam.
Or if you feel completely blocked by your IP agreements,
there are always things like woodworking and papercraft
and knitting.
And often some of those can become games,
can become releasable games.
It's interesting to think about physical games
from glassmaking, for example.
But it's just another way to express yourself.
You want to think about your key skills
and make sure whatever you're working on,
you have at least one key skill that's
going to contribute to it.
You don't want to try something that's all new for you
because you'll feel like you're constantly failing.
But you do want a little bit of new,
a little bit of something you don't do in
your day job because you want this to feel like
an opportunity to do something different.
Ultimately, of course, you'll find
yourself staring at this blank page.
Blank page is my nemesis.
I'm actually terrible at dealing with the blank page.
So one of the things that I've learned to do is in whatever form I'm documenting or writing down
ideas for this game, whether it's a physical notebook or Google Docs or whatever, I make a
page called Scratch. And on the Scratch page, I can type in any idea I have, any thought I have,
any link I have, anything that I think is useful. And the fact that it's not
intended to be final, it's just intended to be a space to collect things, means I feel safe
typing in there. And a lot of times when I'm stuck on the blank page, I'll go to my scratch page and
just start typing stream of consciousness. And over time, I'll end up in a place where I feel
like, okay, I can work now. And also a lot of good ideas will come from it. You also need to
teach yourself to let go. We work in an industry where it's important that all of us know what
we're building and what to do now and how it all.
ladders up to the same goal and how it all works together. And that can feel really inhibiting
when you're working on a solo project. I know personally, it was one of the hardest things that
I had to get over was feeling like I can't work because I don't know everything that I need to
build. But in this, you don't have to plan for everything. That's a part of the joy with a side
project is that you actually can let go. But you absolutely do need to commit.
even if that means you're going to whittle until you uncover the shape of your game.
You're going to commit to spending that time. Something else that you should do as a part of
doing the work is to find a way to talk about it. You want a direct connection between people
and your personal work. And the reason that you want that is because it's going to keep
you accountable and engaged and purposeful. Being under contract for my side project right now
means I'm going to finish it because people are expecting it.
So you can stream your development on Twitch or Facebook, for example, but find a way to
build some anticipation, even if it's just with friends, because that will keep you accountable.
So then we're going to have a moment of purposeful goals.
You're going to save your work. Super important, obviously.
Didn't want to not mention that and have that not be a part of the process.
We all do it routinely, but certainly do it at the end of your session.
you're going to make your to-dos.
And what you're going to do in the process of making
those to-dos is you're going to add a context.
So this is something that I learned
as a part of the getting things done approach to productivity.
A context means the place where you can actually
do the thing in question.
And the reason I set different contexts
is because I learned that there are different mental spaces
where I can do different things.
Like, if it's complex code that I need to write, I need to be at my desk 100%.
Can't do it anywhere else. If it's something I need to think through,
a problem I need to solve, like, how can you find out about this thing before this other
thing has happened in this story? A lot of times I can do that while I'm walking,
while I'm using an exercise bike. I will find a time that is sort of action-oriented
where I'm not trying to write or do anything else at the same time.
So I'll make it to do walking task for that.
On my phone, there are certain things I can do from a narrative perspective. There's certain
writing things I can do on my phone. Lots of things I can't, but some I can. So the ones
that can't be done on my phone, I will make a note of that. So when I'm waiting at the doctor's
office or killing 15 minutes in bed before I try to fall asleep, I will actually pull up my phone
and start working on those.
And then we're going to have a moment of gratitude.
And this may seem like it's out of place,
but it's actually really important.
It's just one minute to press pause and reflect.
It's important to think of something
that you're sincerely grateful for.
It doesn't have to be anything that happened in your session.
It could be anything in your day, anything in your life.
And when you have that and you've thought about it for a minute,
you want to write it at the top of your notes section for your next session.
So the next time you start a session,
you're going to read that thing that you're grateful for again.
And here's why it's important.
Gratitude has been shown in studies, many studies, actually,
to improve physical and psychological health,
your ability to sleep, your self-esteem, your mental strength.
It enhances your empathy,
reduces your aggression, it reduces stress.
It can be one of the best burnout busters
around is having that moment of gratitude.
It's a part of your daily ritual.
Then finally, the closing.
Of course, the closing is the bookend to
the opening that you had
at the beginning of your ritual.
You're going to remind yourself of what you
accomplished and clean and prep your sacred space.
Blow out any candles and have this sense of finishing.
And then you're going to have your ending focus.
You want to choose something that emphasizes why you just
did the work that you did.
So for me, again, because this is primarily
a writing task or writing-driven game that I'm working on,
mine is also, again, from Winter's Tale, Mark Halperin.
All great discoveries are products
as much of doubt as of certainty.
And the two in opposition clear the air
from marvelous accidents.
So that those are the eight steps in the side project ritual.
And the beginning steps only take about seven, eight minutes.
The closing steps take about two, three minutes, maybe five,
if you have a lot of goals that you want to write down.
The bulk of it isn't doing the work, but in having it in this ritual format,
you're doing all of the things that will trigger your brain to
work in that space of time in a way that is creative and freeing and healing for yourself.
And this can actually become an evergreen process that gives you a sense of purpose and growth.
And again, it's true that most of my friends are aware of my constant side projects the entire
time I was in game development. I honestly believe it's what helped keep me whole and sane.
And over the course of
doing this ritual over days and then months and then years, you'll find that you're creating a
series of guiding lights for yourself. So you always have your way back to mental clarity
and you always have a way to keep burnout at bay. So that's the side project ritual. Thanks for
taking time to watch this today. If you have any feedback or questions, you can always find me on
Twitter at laralyn and I've also got a website laralynmcwilliams.com that has contact information
there as well.
So, thank you.