My name is Mike Rose.
I am from publishing label No More Robots.
Thank you very much for coming.
I appreciate the Google keynote is on right now.
So I'm very happy.
I was like, no one's gonna turn up to this,
but you have, that's really nice of you.
Thank you very much.
So yeah, today as part of the game discoverability day,
I'm going to be talking about how I do community stuff,
because a lot of the stuff that I do at No More Robots
is very community-based now.
And I'm gonna be talking a whole bunch
about Discord as well, and you're gonna think that.
I'm some kind of Discord shill, and I basically kind of am at this point, but it's very useful all the same.
So, at any one time, there is always this big thing that helps sell video games, right?
So years ago, it used to be people were saying,
you've got to get press, you've got to get all the press to talk about your games.
and then people were saying,
no, no, get the YouTubers, the YouTubers,
get PewDiePie to play your game,
and you'll make a bunch of money.
And then it was Twitch streamers.
And at this point,
all of these things are still pretty useful.
You know, you still want to be getting press
and YouTubers and Twitch streamers playing your game.
But really, at the moment,
the thing, at least from my perspective,
and it seems like from a lot of other people
are realizing this as well,
is that community building,
is the thing that's really driving players to buy your game right now.
Community building always has been.
You know, over the years, there's always been forums and,
I guess, IRC before then.
There's always been a lot of games that have had massive buzz around them.
A lot of the time, they have had a nice community presence.
Right now, I believe that community building
has sort of become the number one thing
that you want to be pushing for with your game
when you're trying to sell it.
So I'm going to talk a bunch about that.
Yeah, so I'm Mike Rose.
I was originally a writer.
I used to write about video games.
And then I sort of jumped the fence.
And I worked for a publisher called TinyBuild for a while.
We did a bunch of games, and then because I'm an egotistical maniac, I was like,
I can do this myself.
So a couple years ago, I started No More Robots.
It's gone all right.
We've had some pretty nice releases.
We had a mountain biking game called Descenders, which did quite well for us.
Last year, I put out a Brexit management game called Not Tonight.
That went down really well on the internet.
No, and weirdly, that one did really well.
And then last week, we just put out Hypnospace Outlaw,
which is a 90s internet simulator.
And that's done quite well as well.
We've got a game called Family Man coming up.
We've got a few other games in the pipeline as well.
But yeah, that has been the stress of my life
for the last couple of years, and will continue to be so.
So, the thing I should say is that there's loads of talks about community building and
stuff like that, right?
You can find a load of them even just on the GDC vault.
I specifically today want to talk about how you actually start it in the first place.
Because I think a lot of people struggle with that bit.
There's loads of stuff online where it's like, here's what you do with your community.
You've got this community.
But no one seems to ever talk about...
I've got zero people interested right now,
how do I make that number be bigger than zero?
And it's actually...
from my perspective, when you know what you're doing,
it actually is kind of simple.
There's some steps that I follow to make this happen.
So what I'm going to do is, instead of just being vague
and dancing around the subject, I'm
just going to straight tell you the step-by-step thing
that I do with every game.
I'm announcing a new game in about three weeks.
And this checklist, this step-by-step guide,
is literally what I am going to follow just
before we announce this game.
So if you follow this, then you can essentially
just do the stuff I do, and you don't need
a publisher anymore.
I won't be talking about stuff like
moderating communities, et cetera,
because again, I think there's already a ton of talks
on this kind of thing, you know, toxicity, et cetera.
But yeah, there's already plenty of people
who have talked about this, who quite frankly
can probably talk about it better than me as well.
So yeah, like I say, this is gonna be
just a straightforward.
here's what I do and you can do it too.
These are the things that I use when I am building communities.
So Discord, I'll talk about that in a second.
It's all there.
I mean, you can see here there's nothing where it's like,
that's crazy, he's using that.
Google Forms, MailChimp, Steamworks,
it's all stuff that I imagine if you've at least even worked in games a little bit,
you've probably used these things.
There's no like crazy...
magic program that I'm using.
I use all the obvious things.
So, Discord, the reason that I do all my community building
through Discord is because what has happened with Discord
is it kind of came out of nowhere, right?
It just started building a building.
I think in, I think between like 2017 and 2018,
they had something crazy like 120 million extra people sign up to it.
And I think they say right now that they have like 10 million active people who are using Discord on a daily basis.
The reason why that is amazing compared to other possible platforms that you might think of using
is that if somebody has signed up to Discord, there is a high chance that they like video games.
It's a video game platform.
So you already know that anybody who is on Discord is...
probably a potential person who might want to
buy and play your games.
The other thing with Discord as well is that
if somebody signs up for your server in the first place,
so, you know, for anybody who's not aware of how it works,
there's, you can get a link essentially,
and someone clicks this link, and they join your server.
If somebody has clicked the link for your server,
then already they've shown
that they are interested in following your game,
just by joining your server in the first place.
So, it's like...
you'll have this server that you're filling up with people,
and they are all people who have already specifically,
by clicking that link, told you,
I am interested in your game.
So they all become like potential customers, you know,
and if you get thousands and thousands of people
to join your server, then obviously that's pretty nice.
The other thing with Discord as well is that there's just loads of cool stuff you can do
with it that I think a lot of people aren't aware of.
There's all of these sort of, like, you can just run bots and scripts in there.
You don't even need to know any coding whatsoever, quite frankly.
There's thousands of people who have already made bots that you just install in your server
that will just do cool stuff for you and will automate whole systems for you.
I'll be talking about what I use some of the bots for later,
but the overall is that Discord is just a really, really good place
to be collecting people who are interested in your game right now.
So yeah, let's just do this step by step.
Discord, one thing to do if you're looking at this
and you're thinking, I don't even understand
what Discord is.
I mean, it's, I guess if you're sort of under 35,
it's Skype, except it works.
If you're over 35, it's just a glorified IRC.
It's literally just chat rooms where people can hang out.
You can create a server, so you can see,
this here is the server for Descenders,
and you can see all down the left
is just all the different channels people can join.
In the middle is just where they can chat to each other.
On the right is all the users.
It's very simple.
If you don't, if you're still a bit like,
I don't completely understand Discord,
go and read about it.
Honestly, it's an incredibly simple platform,
and you'll get it in no time.
So here is how I set up servers.
So first off, make a server, give it a name.
Once you've done that, you go get it verified by Discord.
Discord will verify any server.
from a developer or publisher who is making a game.
So you go to this link, you enter all the details of the server,
explain to them what the game is.
Getting the server verified is incredibly useful,
not just because it makes it look more legit to players
and makes it so that they're possibly more likely to join.
But you also get a bunch of other benefits as well.
You can get a custom URL for it, so, you know,
discord.gg slash descenders, discord.gg slash hypnospace.
It's a lot easier to link that than, you know,
discord.gg slash invite slash a bunch of letters.
It's just easier for people to remember it,
and they're just far more likely to click it.
And they just actually added this new feature,
which is rather nice, where they now have
just a public catalog of all of the verified servers
on Discord, so people, users can now actually
just look through all the verified servers.
I think there's only like a few hundred of them right now
that are actually verified.
So if you have a verified server right now,
obviously you, you know, you.
you get a nice little bit of visibility from that,
from people who might actually be interested in your game.
So the first thing is just setting up
the bog standard channels that I think
should be in every single Discord server.
So I see some people have a Welcome and a Rules channel.
I mix them into one, literally just a channel that it.
it kind of throws people into in the first place,
where they can see all information about the game,
they know how to behave.
An announcements channel,
this is where only you are gonna be talking in that one,
and that's the one where you're going to be
notifying people.
This is gonna be incredibly important later.
There's a thing in Discord called At Everyone,
where if the admin, if the person who owns the server
types At Everyone,
it pings every single person who is in your server,
it throws a notification onto their phone,
straight onto the home screen of their phone,
telling them you've been pinged.
Again, imagine how useful that is
if you've got 5,000, 10,000 people in your Discord server
who are interested in your game,
and you can now directly just throw a notification
onto their phone about a thing.
And then I usually have a channel,
so you see there's one called Descendants here,
I usually, that's the place where people just talk,
it's just the base place where everyone's talking,
just named after your own game.
You'll have like a mod channel as well,
because when you first open the floodgates
of your Discord server, then it'll get kind of crazy.
But the first time with the Descendants Discord,
the first time I did it,
I did not completely understand Discord at this point.
And I remember the day I opened it,
and thousands of people started flooding in.
And it was chaos.
And that will happen to you as well,
and you will be so scared.
Because the first time you do it,
you just have no idea what it's going to be like.
There's just people,
people will find ways to abuse your server
in ways that you couldn't think was possible,
using commands that you didn't know existed.
There was, on the day that I launched
the Descenders Discord.
I'd accidentally made it so that people could use a command to make
just sort of like a Microsoft voice read everything in the server
to everybody who was in the server.
So all of a sudden there was just hundreds of people
just screaming because there was a voice on their computer talking to them.
That was horrible.
And it will happen to you.
Everybody who first uses Discord will be like...
I don't understand the permissions or anything.
I think it's good to learn by failing a little bit on this.
But there's plenty of documentation you can read as well
on Discord to make sure it doesn't happen.
But yeah, from my perspective,
these are the kind of bog standard channels
I will always put into every server that I run.
What I will then have is what I call entry point channels.
And these are interesting because what they do is,
I believe, they force people who are joining your Discord
server to engage a little bit more.
They add an extra level of, I'm forcing you to do a thing
to be able to use my Discord server.
So right now you can see all the channels there,
but that's because I'm an admin,
so I get to see all the channels.
What will normally happen is when someone joins
the Descenders server, all they will be able to see
is the pick a side channel, and that's it.
Well, the welcome channel as well,
but just below it, pick a side.
They go into the pick a side channel.
And it says, it tells them that they need to enter a command to pick a team.
We've got three teams in the game, Enemy, Arboreal, and Kinetic.
And the idea is that we give them information in the welcome channel about these three teams
and say to them, you can't access the server until you've picked a team.
And once they enter a command, that pick a side channel
disappears, and the rest of the server opens up,
including special channels that are just for that team.
Also, if you look on the screen, you
can see that people have different colors.
It colors their name with the team they picked.
So the whole point of this is that they already the moment they join the server feel like they're part of something
They have no idea what you know they've not that we did this before the game had come out
they had no idea what it even meant to pick a team, but the level of
We essentially had people just
trash-talking each other, and bigging up their teams,
and banding together, all because their name
was a different color.
And it's this kind of thing.
If you don't have something like this,
I think it can cause people to just join a Discord server,
and then just sort of be like,
oh, well, I don't see anything to do here,
so I'm gonna leave again.
It forces people to actually do an action,
which then can lead them to do more actions.
Now, this stuff is really simple.
So, there's a bot called Dino,
and honestly, it's just the best Discord bot.
It does a whole bunch of permissions stuff.
This is the code, as if this is code.
This is the code I had to write just to make this work.
You can see all that happens is they type in
one of these teams, it gives them that role,
and then it just, in the specific channel for that team,
will kind of welcome them, so that then it pings them
in that channel to show them, look what you have now.
And it also then causes other people to say hi to them,
because someone else has joined the channel.
It's honestly, this is as difficult as it gets
in terms of the sort of coding you need to do.
It's all very simple.
And just these things here,
and then this is just the permission side of it.
So essentially all you're saying is that
in the pick a side channel,
if somebody is on team arboreal, enemy, or kinetic,
then make it so that they can't read
or send messages anymore.
So before they could, when they were in the channel.
they were able to see messages.
Once they've picked a team,
their permissions are removed from that channel
and they can't see it anymore.
And then imagine with all the other channels, you flip it.
So originally they had no permissions
in all the other channels.
Then once they pick a team,
it gives them permissions in all the channels.
It's that straightforward, quite frankly.
It really doesn't take any more than that.
You can go a little bit crazier, which I'll kind of mention a little bit later with some of the idiotic things we've done,
but realistically, just doing this is enough, quite frankly.
So once you've set up what I think,
that's sort of the basics of setting up the Discord server,
you then want to think about what it is
that is keeping people in your Discord server.
I talk a lot about thinking of the hook for your game,
and it's kind of the same thing.
Why do people want to not only join your Discord server,
but stick around?
When I did Descenders, we went for a very simple thing.
They've picked a team.
And so they're all different colors now.
And then at this point, we started doing weekly challenges for them.
We'd say to them at the start of the week on a Monday,
we want you to battle it out doing this thing this week.
And it was always extremely silly things.
You know, one week it would be, we want you to do fan art for your team.
The next week, we want you to do trash art for the other teams.
We want you to write haikus this week.
It's nothing crazy, it's just silly little things they can do,
which just keep them engaged.
And you can see that all of these channels at the bottom,
like I was saying, you know, for example,
team Arboreal people would only see the team Arboreal channel
using permissions.
This just... it worked really well for the Descenders
when we first announced the Descenders server,
because as well, this approach...
is quite hands off.
You know, there's not a ton that you have to do here.
It was essentially on a Monday I'd post a challenge,
and on a Friday I'd post the results of the challenge,
and whichever team had won the challenge,
they would get things like they would get,
we'd tell them they were gonna get a special kit
when the game came out.
You can also, you can have custom emotes in Discord,
so we'd tell them each week.
will give your team a custom emote for your team.
And so then they would start using those emotes
to then essentially trash the other teams.
Most of the teams just basically tried
to collect the letters of their names
so that they could then just spell them all out.
But yeah, this worked really well.
When we came to do the Discord for Not Tonight,
Because I'm crazy, I just always want to take it a step too far.
Or at least a step further than we did last time.
So I tried to do some weird permission stuff
that also kind of worked out.
So the whole point in our game Not Tonight
is that you're a bouncer,
and you're deciding whether to let people in or out.
I wanted to make it so that people in the Not Tonight discord could essentially go to work and earn money.
So the idea would be that they would be able to see home, they'd be able to see their home channel but nothing else.
and then they type a command,
and it would open up places for them to work
and remove their home,
and then after they decided they'd done a day's work,
they could then type a command to go back home.
Again, it was very, very simple to set this up.
It was just Dino again,
so I'm literally just making it
so that I add a role called Bouncer.
to them so that they can then see the channels
which have the permissions for Bouncer.
Then when they type in end job, it removes Bouncer
so all of those channels disappear.
I coupled this with a bot called Unbelievable Pizza,
which is a great name, and this is just essentially,
it's the currency bot that I now use for all my servers
because it's extremely useful.
It's very, there's just so much customization
you can do to it.
pick the type of currency I could pick,
how fast people would get the money.
I could give them things to buy using the money.
And this came in useful later when I would tell them,
right, if you earn this much money,
you can then buy a character in the full game,
or you can name a pub in the game.
Or there was like the grand prize,
which was a free copy of the game
that people were rushing to try and win.
But again,
Incredibly simple.
I just installed two bots and wrote those tiny bits of code there.
And that sort of set up an entire server,
which then, the great thing about the Not Tonight server
was that it just worked by itself.
I didn't really have to do much to it.
This whole currency thing was just running itself.
And so I could just walk away for weeks,
and people would have fun playing this game that I'd set up.
When it came to hypnospace, I went too far.
Don't do this.
I set up an entire 90s internet within a Discord server.
I actually got a guy, yeah, it's not right.
I actually got a guy, I found a guy
who had written a Discord bot,
which nearly did the thing I wanted to do.
I messaged him and I said,
here's the insane thing I'm trying to do,
and he said, I can write that for you.
So what happens here is that someone can go
to the search engine channel.
and they can see all the pages that people have made
and they can type a command to join the service.
So normally what would happen is,
again, because I'm admin, I can see all the channels.
People wouldn't be able to see all these channels
and they'd have to search in the search engine for a page
and join it to add it to the Discord server.
They can then type a sort of like a exclamation mark create
to make a web page that only they would be able to edit
and other people could join.
It was too much, quite frankly.
It was fun and people were joining and being like,
this is the craziest thing I've ever seen.
I don't think you need to do this.
I don't think this server benefited more
than the Not Tonight one did and it was way more work.
But you know, if you're crazy like me,
then maybe this is something you wanna try and do.
Okay, so at this point you've now got your Discord server all set up with all the right channels
and you've got some kind of hook for why people are going to join and then not immediately leave.
Everything at this point is now incredibly simple.
You make a channel that is just beta sign up.
We're doing a multiplayer beta for Descenders right now,
so this is a channel that I have live right now.
It just links to a Google form where people are just kind of signing up.
as simple as that, just a Google form asking them
for their name and email address.
The idea is that they're just going to be going
through your Discord server,
finding the link to the Google form,
and signing up there.
So you've now got them in two places.
You've now got them directly,
so you can talk to them within the Discord,
and you've now got them on a mailing list,
so you can keep them up to speed
with what is happening to the game.
both incredibly useful in their own way.
And at this point, so what I normally do is,
I normally now link this up
with the announcement of a game.
So if your game is already announced,
then obviously you can change this up.
But what I would normally do,
everything I've done up to now, I've done in secret,
kind of behind the scenes, not told anyone.
And then when it comes to the announcement of the game day,
then this is when I start spamming the link.
for the Discord to everybody that I possibly can,
along with telling them, if you go here,
you can sign up to play in the upcoming closed beta
for the game.
And that's the hook for why they are coming in
in the first place.
I see people sort of, they announce a game
or they just make a Discord for their game.
and they just sort of say,
hey, people, join my Discord
so you can keep up to speed with my game.
And unfortunately, the vast majority of players
aren't going to do that.
They won't just join a Discord server to hang out
because they're already probably in.
a dozen other Discord servers.
The whole point of timing the come here to sign up
to be able to play an early version of the game,
that's the reason why they come in.
And they do come in.
If you do this right and you sort of get the link out
to as many places as possible,
you can get thousands and thousands of people
to sign up to your server.
It's genuinely...
really not that hard to do.
You know, when, before I'd done it
and before we were gonna do Descenders,
I was wondering, I wonder how many people
are gonna sign up to this?
You know, it might not be that many,
and I think in like two days,
we got like 7,000 people join the server
because they were so desperate
to play an early build of the game.
So.
There's loads of places I've kind of listed here,
which are great ways to get people.
One of the interesting ones is there's loads of sites
on the internet that are sort of like freesteamkeys.com
and all that, where people who just want free games
are just going.
It seems like it's pointless to put them on there,
because...
You know if those people are just gonna grab your game for free
Why would they pay for it?
But the thing that I found is that actually is real useful because on the one hand you get a ton of people playing the
game early and whether or not they're gonna buy it in the end the feedback is useful and
it just
means that it looks like there's even more buzz
around the playing of your game
and all of these different people playing it early.
I've also found as well that a lot of the time,
these people who may not really buy games
and are just looking for free games,
they'll join your Discord,
they'll see there's some cool people around.
They'll be fascinated by the idea
that they've just joined a server
and now they can talk directly to the developer.
Because that doesn't happen very often, right?
Like, we launch a Discord server,
and there's people who are just like,
this is so cool that I can just,
right directly now, talk to people who are making this game.
And that, a lot of the time, I've found converts
a lot of people who have told me,
I just joined this just to play some free stuff,
but I've now got so much into this
that I'm more than happy to buy it at launch.
So, yeah, these are all the places I do.
Another thing you can do as well is you can talk to some of the big press sites.
People like PC Gamer, PC Games N, and people like that
will do beta giveaways with their viewership, I guess.
And that can be very useful as well.
You throw 5,000 Steam keys at them, and they will bring on extra people.
Of course, those people aren't coming into your Discord as well,
so you're kind of missing that angle.
But again, it's pretty useful to just have more people
playing your game, quite frankly.
And then, again, incredibly simple.
This is just the checklist of stuff that I then do
when I'm then running the beta.
What I normally do is I normally have it so that...
We announce a game on a Discord and have people joining.
We leave it a few weeks.
And then a few weeks later, we then
run the beta for the game.
What this normally makes happen is
that we get the boost of people joining when we announce.
And then three weeks later, we get a second boost of people
as we say that week, this is happening this week,
and more people start talking about it that week.
So you kind of get a second burst.
But again, it's very simple.
I normally set up a separate product on Steam,
literally just buy a second product for,
I don't know how much it is now, 80, $100,
something like that.
And yeah, just pick a weekend and go for it.
If you've not used MailChimp before,
it's very simple to use.
It's literally just assign Steam keys
for each of the email addresses
you've been collecting through the Google form
and email them all on the date that your beta starts.
You want to, I've seen people when they do this,
say like, oh, we'll just let it run.
Just let the beta run
or we'll do it for a month or something.
I think it's a good idea to have it for a very set period of time.
And I've actually done both,
and I've found that the very concentrated one works so much better,
because people know when they see that it's only going to happen
between these three to five dates, they make sure to play it.
And so you get far more, again, it's the concentrated,
lots of people all talking about it at the same time.
So yeah, I always stick to that.
And then again, Discord can be really useful at this point
for collecting bugs, essentially.
And you could set up a channel that's just bug reporting,
and you can have a form in there where you tell them,
this is how we want you to provide the bugs for us.
Because if you don't say that,
then you can imagine what happens,
just a million people all shouting,
this doesn't work, that doesn't work,
and it's just not useful whatsoever, it's just noise.
So yeah, it's good to get that kind of thing sorted.
And just another channel for, you know, suggesting features.
Again, it's probably the case, as bad as it sounds,
that 90% of the things people are suggesting
are not gonna be useful.
But then again, if a lot of people
keep suggesting the same thing,
then it's probably a sign that
that might actually be a cool thing.
And this whole time as well, of course, you can be asking people to wishlist your game on Steam.
Steam wishlists, if you're not aware, are incredibly useful.
If you can get to a certain level of wishlists, it means that around the launch of your game,
you're going to get sort of, you know, in the Steam front page lists.
It seems right now that if you can get to about 8,000 to 10,000 Steam wishlists at launch,
then that will cause your game to get featured in more lists.
So that's maybe a number you want to be aiming for.
But when you do this beta stuff through Discord,
this is a time when you will see tons of people wishlisting the game,
and you really want to be pushing hard for it at this point.
So this should be where you're up to at this point.
You've now run the beta, it's the end of the beta,
it's now the period between you've done this public test,
you've now got a server full of thousands of people
who are interested in your game,
and you now gotta just make the dang thing.
And it can be tricky at this point,
because now you've just got a ton of people
who are every day saying,
is the game out yet?
Is the game out yet?
And it just, you know,
well, we all know how long it takes to make games.
And so it can be tricky
to keep people happy at that period.
And you might find people leaving
because they feel like they're just sort of
sat in a stagnant server at that point.
So.
This point is where I sort of do the next step of what I do,
which is that I run silly meta games for each of the games.
The idea here is that running up to the launch of the game,
you want to keep people in your Discord happy
by just running silly games that by the time
that the launch of your actual game comes,
they have to buy your game at that point
because they are already so invested
in what has just happened to them
for the few months before then.
It's.
It really is.
I didn't really do a metagame for Descenders as much.
It was more we were just sort of trying to build hype
in the server up to the launch.
And I kind of wish I had done a metagame for it
because then I did one for Not Tonight and Hypnospace.
And you could really see by the time the game came out.
People that the stuff that we had done
In in the discord had made it so that they were already hardcore
You know hypnospace fans before hypnospace had even come out
So I should probably explain better what I mean by this whole metagame thing.
Essentially, at the very core of it, it's just doing a bunch of storytelling at people
and getting them to be involved in that storytelling.
So when we did the Not Tonight meta after we'd done the beta...
I essentially set it up so that everybody in the server,
they'd all picked a region when they first joined the server.
So they had to pick whether they were in the North, the South,
or the Midlands in the UK.
And then we had general elections
where everybody could vote on who
they wanted to be the Prime Minister and the MPs.
Once we had done that, then I started giving them,
I started giving the Prime Minister and his MPs
decisions to make each day. They started off all right at first, you know, just like who should be
taxed and all this kind of stuff, and by the end it had got really horrible where I'd, you know,
I was essentially doing things like I'd tell somebody, I'd tell one of the MPs that they were a spy.
and that they can't tell anyone,
and they have to try and stay undetected for a week,
and then midway through the week,
I tell everybody else that there was a spy,
and just let, just sit back and just watch what happened,
and you can imagine what happened.
A lot of the meta stuff that I do, actually,
is very inspired by just a lot of,
you know, sort of like the,
a lot of board games and card games really,
and hidden role games.
A lot of this really works in text form,
because you tell some people,
you tell like thousands of people some information
that maybe is worrying information
about the situation they're in,
and all of a sudden they scramble together,
they form little,
there was people in the Not Tonight server
who were making other servers
that they were only inviting people
who they knew wasn't the spy into.
so that they could try and work together to work out who the spy was.
This whole thing ended, we had a,
we had a, you know I said earlier that we had a prize that was
to win a copy of the game, but it didn't just do that. Whoever got
that prize, whoever managed to earn enough money to get that prize would become
king or queen of the server. And I didn't tell them this
until someone won it. So then we had to have a king's coronation
where hundreds of people all sat in voice chat
listening to, you know, just sort of random songs of YouTube, sort of UK royalty songs,
while people like, while the Prime Minister and other people just like role-played a coronation.
They decided I was the queen, so I had to sing the national anthem.
And then I essentially made a bomb go off,
because it ties in with the game, in Not Tonight,
it starts with a bomb going off and the whole point is that it jumps back in time,
you have to work out how we got to this point.
And then we had it where we locked the server down,
it was martial law until we could work out who the bomber was.
it got weird.
But imagine, by the time we got to the launch of the game,
all of these people needed to buy the game at this point
because they were already invested.
They were already so invested.
One of them was a king of the game.
We put him in the game as you could get posters
for the king and there was a picture of him on a coin
and stuff like that.
People had to get the game at this point
because they just had to.
So then when I came to do the Hypnospace one,
I essentially took what I'd done
and just tried to take it a step further.
So there's a character in Hypnospace
called Dylan Merchant who runs the operating system
that you are playing in the game.
And so I started, I made a discord account called Dylan Merchant with his face
and I started talking to people like doing announcements like,
hey everybody the new Hypno S update is coming out soon
and it all started off very nice and everyone was like, oh there's Dylan
and guys, great!" And I keep saying to them,
oh, what would you guys like?
Would you like this? Would you like that?
And then I said, would you like some monetization?
And I started giving them HypnoCoins,
which is the currency in the game which just means nothing,
which you can only spend in the game and not in real life.
So they all started earning HypnoCoins.
And then it started just getting really dark.
And we kept talking about how there was an update coming out,
but there was...
Some people in the press were saying there was something wrong with it.
And so maybe, so we made a Y2K enforcement team,
who were this team of about 20 users in the server,
who were only allowed to say nice things about Merchantsoft.
If they saw anybody saying bad things about Merchantsoft,
these people had to come along and crack down on it,
make sure no one was saying bad things.
it ended up with someone, again, winning a prize in the server which made them become
a cyborg called the Packard who ran around with his bell.
And then there was whistleblowers who knew that the new update on Hypno-S was going to
sort of overheat and destroy the...
basically the entire internet.
We had them running around a map
where I made up rules for a small board game
that they were all playing together.
Yeah, again, it got really weird.
And again, it just got to the point
where when the game came out.
there was no way these people who had been involved
weren't playing because they needed to see
how Dylan was in the game.
They needed to see if this Dylan
who they'd been talking to,
they needed to see what that bastard was up to next.
You know, like they had to play the game.
And everything that I do in the meta
then ties into the game in some way.
So this map here is actually like a mini recreation
of a part in the game where you're moving around a map.
So when people got up to this bit in the game,
they were all like,
oh man, look, it's this bit that we did in the meta,
this is amazing.
Yeah, the whole point, the bottom line of this
is that by running these things,
it really builds hype in your servers
to the point where on launch day,
you actually know your game's gonna probably do
pretty decently because all of these people
are going to go crazy over it, which is...
Again, obviously a massively useful thing.
If you already know on launch day
that you've got thousands of people
who are quite frankly going to definitely
buy your game on launch week,
what more can you ask for right now?
That's the dream, knowing your game is going to sell.
And that's kind of the point when we get
to the launch of one of our games,
we know it's going to sell at least
this sort of base level of well,
because we already can see all of these people
are gonna buy it.
And there's loads of other benefits as well to doing this.
So the day your game comes out,
what we've found with our last few games
is that we get a flurry of positive reviews
on our Steam page,
because all of these people want to buy the game
and they want to be one of the first
to leave a review on Steam of it.
They want to be able to...
leave a review and then link their review in the Discord saying,
guys I've just reviewed it and then other people will say, I've reviewed it as well.
We all know that Steam reviews are pretty useful, you know,
the more and the faster you're getting Steam reviews,
the more potential people are going to see that and are going to,
are going to decide, yeah go on then, I'll buy the game, it seems like people are enjoying this.
And of course, then that just kind of rolls along.
The more reviews you're getting and the more people who are playing it
in a very small space of time.
You know, if you're funneling all of these people directly on launch day,
that shoots you up the Steam charts.
It's just a flurry of action that all happens on launch day.
Thanks to this Discord.
I mean, obviously there's outside sources as well.
You know, you're obviously still doing all the trying
to get press and YouTubers and streamers, et cetera,
to play your game.
But you at least know that this chunk of people
are going to be hardcore supporting your game
on launch day.
So yeah, I said a bunch of words,
so this is just kind of a little roundup,
just to really show how simple everything I've just said is.
Nothing I've just said in the last, what, like 45 minutes
was really that hard in any way.
The vast majority of what I do is incredibly simple.
It can be a lot of work, is the one thing I would say.
Especially, you know, when I was talking about the meta stuff.
That would be me every day doing announcement in the afternoon
and then pretty much just sitting back and watching it happen
or maybe nudging it in different directions
for the next couple of hours afterwards.
There's, yeah, it can be a lot of work,
and so I guess something I would say is that
if you're in a situation where you're looking at this and thinking,
yeah, but I need to make my game, I don't have time for any of this,
what is quite frankly stupid crap.
I would find someone to do it for you,
whether that's a partner or just bringing an extra person on
because it genuinely is, I think we all know at this point,
this stuff is important now, it always kind of was,
but it's just so important that you are actually getting,
you can make the best game ever,
but if you haven't done any of this kind of stuff
and it gets to launch day and no one knows it exists,
that's obviously a terrible thing to happen for your game.
But yeah, I would very much suggest starting off simple,
not doing some of the stuff, for example,
that I did with Hypnospace.
Maybe start off less crazy than I have.
And as well, you know, the stuff I talked about,
there's other stuff you could be doing.
There's this website, discordbots.org,
where I found these bots that I use,
and where there are thousands of bots
that people have made
that all do very specific functionality.
And it's literally a case of.
you click the one you want and click the install button
and it installs into your server.
And then you can tinker around with it.
It's worth going there and just looking for weird stuff
that you can do.
Because there's bound to be loads of ideas
that I haven't thought of that would work very well,
specifically for what the theme of your game is.
Right, I'm done.
Thank you very much for listening.
There is time for questions.
About 15 minutes.
So there's a microphone there.
I think if you basically just exactly what you're doing
line up, then that's great.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Garrett.
Hello.
Is this on?
It should be.
Maybe try talking louder into it.
Hello?
Yeah, I can hear you.
At any time, did you feel like you were running a Stanford
prison experiment?
It is interesting.
When I started doing this stuff, it doesn't...
It's very hard. When I was just describing stuff to you then,
I actually don't think I really got across how crazy it gets.
There was stuff... I went on holiday for one week in the summer last year,
and...
I was basically just on my phone for the entire time because people, there was those people
in the server who, in the Not Tonight server, who had all convinced themselves that there
was another spy in the server.
I hadn't done anything, like I just, I purposely tried to leave it for a week because I was
trying to, I was trying to relax.
And I did not really relax much because these people kept messaging me over and over again.
And yeah, you don't know what it's going to be like until you do one of these community things.
But you at least at the time know it's probably a good thing.
Uh, so...
Well, is there any, like, a point where you're like,
oh my gosh, these guys are going too crazy,
I need to, like, do something to, like,
put people down?
Yeah, with Not Tonight, especially,
because it's about Brexit,
it's a little bit of a political game,
and that was a tricky one.
It's the kind of stuff I didn't really touch
on the moderation stuff.
That one in particular got difficult at times because there were people who were talking
politics as the meta and they would have heated debates and then someone would say,
guys calm down, and they'd say, oh it's just meta, it's just the meta, we're just playing the meta.
And at that point you're like, well, okay.
Maybe, yeah, it was a difficult one.
Hypnospace was easier because there was less politics about it.
But yeah, people definitely go too far at times
and you need to sometimes just like take them to the side,
just like go into a direct message and say,
I'm really happy that you're getting so involved with this
and you're so infused,
but maybe use half the words you're using
and don't use caps anymore.
That would be really nice.
Yeah.
Cheers.
Hi there.
Hello.
So you said, or in your talk you discussed
doing this for various titles.
How do you get buy in and trust from the developers
to handle their IP properly and take it
in all these new directions to build up the game?
Yeah, a lot of the time what I do,
especially before I start the meta stuff for a game,
is I will...
I will have chats with the developer where,
I mean, by the time I do a meta, I normally,
I would hope that I know the game pretty well at that point,
but I like to sit with a developer and say,
I'm planning to do this for the meta
and use these characters.
Does this fit into what you're doing?
There's a game, the game that I'm announcing
in a few weeks is a game about taking a journey
from one place to another.
And so for the meta for that one,
Right now my plan is to make the meta be starting from somewhere else,
going to the start point of the game.
So the idea is all of these people will play this Discord game.
and they will get to this place and when they get to this place we'll tell them when you
get here we're launching the game and then they will get to the place, obviously, you
know, behind the scenes I'm going to be controlling it, making sure they actually get there and
the game isn't delayed inevitably.
But yeah, we're going to make it so they go there and then the idea is the game will launch
and they will carry on their journey then.
You know, like it's, for them it's...
the obvious kind of story arc,
they're playing the next chapter
of what they've already played.
So yeah, it's definitely talking to a developer
and working out, does this storyline make sense?
Does this Discord setup make sense for your game?
Essentially.
Hi, so if the Discord is kind of like your endpoint where you're gathering everybody to build up for the eventual game launch, how do you build the entry points like Twitter, for example, or spamming Reddit if there's other ways of doing that?
Yeah, I mean, I guess that stuff is a whole other talk, right?
Like about how you're actually sort of building up presences in other places.
I mean, a lot of it is doing very similar stuff, you know?
When it comes to things like Twitter...
It can be a slow build up, but you can do things like running...
Like I was saying, I was pushing people into the Discord
by giving them something that makes them want to.
You need to ask yourself that question about other platforms as well.
Why are people going to follow you on Twitter?
Why are they going to follow the account for your game?
Is there anything that you can offer them?
Is there a reason why they should join you?
you tell people if you follow this game account on Twitter,
then I'm going to pick some random people who are followed
and they are going to be able to pick a character
that's in your game or something like that.
There's lots of different ways that you can,
with all social platforms really,
that you can incentivize people
to want to actually follow you.
A lot of the time just saying, follow me because my game's great, is not really enough because
everybody's saying that.
No one's saying, you can follow me if you want, my game's crap, whatever.
It's all about incentivizing people essentially.
Hello.
So you mentioned that one of the hooks to your Discord server
is telling, hey, come play a bit of the game,
or an early version.
And you keep the community going all the way until lunch.
So I was wondering, in what stage of the game development
should you start building community?
Because I think you can't do that.
too long or people will get tired.
That's a good question.
So what I normally do is
I normally
tell people that I like
to announce games
that are under my publishing
label somewhere
between
four to six months before the game is going to actually be ready.
It's going to be released.
The reason I say this is because I think it works time-wise.
It's like you're saying, you know, if you announce it a year before,
you can't run a crazy meta game for an entire year.
That would destroy you.
And also people would probably just lose interest.
I think that the four to six months...
time frame works because it's you know sort of you announce in that first
Month or two you do the beta for the game that you can then sort of have a month to be
One thing I'll sometimes do is deliver feedback that happened from the beta
two people. So for example, with this game Family Man we've got right now, we ran a beta,
we were tracking a bunch of stats from the beta, and now every few days we're putting
up these images in the Discord that are like, you know, like a thousand people did this
thing in the game, and here was a decision you all had to make, 40% of people made this
decision.
Like writing analytics or something like that?
Say again?
like analytics in the game?
Exactly, exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so, right, that's the stage we're at with Family Man right now,
where we're doing this, the meta hasn't started for that game yet.
Right now, we're delivering these cool ideas to them.
We've also, in that one, just started doing it
so that each week we're giving them the opportunity
to name characters and dogs, things like that in the game.
And then, when we then know...
Because the game is nearly ready, essentially.
It's on the cusp of us saying, OK, this is ready to go.
At that point, then, when we know that, we can then start
running this intense meta thing for a couple of months,
to the point where we've built people into a fever by the
time the game comes out.
But yeah, I think sometimes if you do longer than that.
it can drag, it can really drag.
Descenders, we did it, we announced the game
and launched the Discord server eight months
before the game came out,
and that felt like it dragged a little bit.
There was times when we were just sort of,
you know, people were coming to the Discord saying like,
what can we even do in here, why am I even in here?
You don't want that to happen, is the thing,
because then people just start leaving.
So yeah, it's definitely worth tightening it up, essentially.
Thank you.
Cool, cheers.
I'd be curious to hear a little bit more about the demographics of these people.
I'm curious about the age ranges and the gender balance.
And I'm also curious if this was a subset of your total audience for the game,
what are some...
Are there any unique characteristics to the Discord audience as compared to other segments?
Say that last bit again, sorry.
So, if this is just like one segment of your total audience,
like some people came to you through other marketing...
Are there any unique characteristics to the Discord audiences that you could observe as
compared to other people?
And I'm curious about the demographics.
Yeah.
Well, an interesting thing about this is that...
One thing that you really want to be doing is trying to mold your Discord community to be what you would like it to be.
And again, I didn't really touch on moderation stuff so much because I think there are quite a lot of other talks about it,
but in general, I want it such that when I get to the launch of the game,
the people who I have fostered, and especially the mods and the regulars in there,
as simple as it sounds, just nice people.
You don't want it so that when you launch the game,
you've got this toxic group of people who,
when someone comes into the Discord
asking for help about the game,
they're just shut down, you know?
And people are just.
you know, being sarcastic at them and stuff like that.
You want it so that you are fostering these people.
And I don't think it's that hard to do, quite frankly.
It's...
I personally have this...
I don't think a lot of people do this,
but I have this, like, sort of scorched-earth mentality to it, where...
If I see someone in a server being any form of bad,
I just get rid of them immediately.
I don't do like a three strikes and you're out
or anything like that.
I know a lot of places do do that.
For me, if I see one person just saying a word,
you know, that is a word that is not okay with me,
they are gone immediately.
And I find that works quite well for me
because by the time I get to the launch.
people just know.
If someone comes in and starts talking weirdly,
other people are like, yeah,
you might not want to talk like that
because Mike is going to see it in a second.
Which, you know, is, I don't know.
It works, I think, because I think when people
don't do that and they do the three strikes or whatever,
I think a lot of the time that's when, you know,
like a YouTuber is trying to build a community
for their streams and their videos and stuff.
We make games and we don't want.
I don't want idiots talking about or playing my games.
I just want nice people.
I mean, you know, it's a bit,
I mean, we've seen the Steam forum,
so that's never gonna happen,
but yeah, that's kind of what I try to aim for.
The actual demographic of people in the server,
to be honest, is not a thing I think much about
because
Because quite frankly, when the game comes out,
the important thing is that this group of people
are just ready to go as your sort of hype train for the game.
I think a lot of the time it is younger people, you know?
And we've had some servers, like the Family Man server,
we've had a lot of what you can tell is very young people coming in,
who, you know, you can, you realize are probably...
not going to buy the game when it comes out
and are just looking for a free game.
But honestly, with each game I've done,
it's just kind of works itself out in the end.
You find, you slowly but surely,
you find the people who are right for your community
and you just start to mold it around them, really.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi there.
Hi.
How do you manage the process of funnelling people into the one community access point
that you want people to be in, like the Discord, because that's where your energy is going?
If people are starting their own community, like a Facebook group or Facebook community
external to that, how do you manage the process?
stopping the fragmentation of that community.
For me, it's just a whole lot of spamming that link everywhere, you know?
I wish it was...
I wish it was more professional than that, quite frankly, but really, when I announce a game,
I just make sure that Discord link is everywhere.
You know, I'm putting it in the press release for the game,
I'm putting it at the end of the video, I'm putting it in the trailer's description,
I'm spreading it on Facebook and Twitter, I'm, like I say, I'm emailing.
I will directly email all of these free Steam keyplaces, saying,
here's a game I've got coming up.
please, do you want to post this link on your site?
It's just a whole lot of just putting it absolutely,
subreddits are another good one.
Reddit, there's loads of people who want to play
a free early copy of a game.
You know, there's the games one, indie games one,
game dev one, there's loads of different subreddits
where there's tens of thousands of people in those
who are pretty happy to click a link and sign up to a thing.
So yeah, the...
The horrible answer is to spam as many people as you can.
I would say there's nowhere not to put it, you know?
Because if people have joined a Facebook group or something,
they're interested in the game in the first place,
so you might as well try and funnel them into that place.
And if someone does create their own community group that you don't have control over, do
you try to create your own version of that and just drive people back to the Discord
or just let that exist?
I usually, I mean if you're in that situation where people are creating their own group
then that's pretty nice for you, right?
That shows that there's a decent amount of interest in your game.
So I don't think I would ever try and take control of that or close it down.
It's more like, I guess I'd see if there were ways I could support that group.
You know if it made sense to be telling people hey, there's this other group with these other people in it as well
I might do that
But I don't think I don't think I'd ever be in a position where I'd want to sort of take control
I guess there might be a situation where maybe the group is not nice
You and you kind of want to shut that down, but I I personally haven't been in that situation yet, so thank you
Hello.
So coming to the part that you mentioned
that some of the developers, like me or someone,
we would think that we don't have time for all this stuff.
We have to make a game, right?
So we might have to go and find some partner or someone else
who would do this for us.
But I feel like in the earlier stages of the game,
that
The amount of involvement and the amount of knowledge that we have about the game some other person wouldn't be able to do that
Good in the game. Yeah, I was sharing and all so I would still feel that I would need to get involved and I would still
Have to spend a lot of time doing all of this stuff and get away from the development
Yeah, because because you're like me you're a control freak right like you you need sir
Yeah, you you you hate the idea that somebody else will be running exactly
Yeah, unfortunately I've been having to learn that I have to let go at some points and just, you know, I have to
try and let other people
take charge of other things, I would imagine that would be,
if you just do not have the time to be doing this stuff,
if you can admit to yourself, there's no way I can do this,
it's important, it's still important,
and you can't, it's better to try and find someone
who can do it for you than to just not do it.
So I would probably say, you need to find someone
who is passionate to do it, essentially.
So like there are two parts, maybe.
I'm not able to find the good person, so I'll have to invest some more time finding the right person.
Or should I take some time out of my schedule to do all of this stuff myself?
It's different with each case.
Like, you know, it depends on the game you're making and the time you have and
whether if you're doing this, it will delay your game by a long time.
And you know, it's...
There will be situations where people,
most people making games, it's quite intense, right?
Especially as you're getting up to the launch of your game.
So it might be that you can't be doing this stuff at launch
because having the intensity of making a game
and the intensity of running a Discord server
might make you explode.
So yeah, it sounds like from your situation,
you probably maybe need to find someone
and just sort of grit your teeth and see what they can do.
Okay, thank you
Hey Mike.
Hello.
Do you see any value in doing company discords where you're putting your games?
Do you know, other people do, I know there's other publishers who do.
I was talking to one of them from Rofiori yesterday, they have just a singular discord
server and then channels for each of the things.
I don't like to do that.
It's less work doing that, obviously.
I don't like to do that because I think there's benefits.
don't give a crap about me.
You know, they don't care who No More Robots are.
They care what the game is.
That's why they joined the server in the first place.
So why would they want to join a Discord server
that's filled with other games they don't care about?
And they care about the singular one channel.
I imagine for you it might make sense
because all of your games, you know,
so you've got the games and the sequels
and they're all sort of quite similar.
So maybe it would make sense for.
for someone like you, but there's other benefits as well.
You know, when you're getting a verified server,
if you put your game on the Discord store,
they then put the store link,
it automatically appears at the top of your Discord server.
So people can now buy Descenders
through the Descenders Discord server.
So I think there's benefits to each way,
but I just like my way better.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mike. I really appreciate this great information about pre-launch prep now.
No worries.
Is there anything in here that can help a product that has gone to a less than stellar launch already?
Yeah, it's a tricky one. The whole, you know, is there something you can do after launch of a game?
It's not just for Discord stuff, just, you know, for everything.
I imagine if I was in a situation where I'd sort of had a launch that wasn't great,
I would start to wonder how I can sort of take what I've already got
and maybe even spin it off into a separate product that can then be, you know, sort of
announced and have a beta for it, etc. as a separate entity. But it depends on, it just depends on...
what it is, I guess, really.
But yeah, it's a tricky one.
I don't think anything I talked about today
can probably help after a launch, to be honest.
It's probably pre-launch stuff, this, really.
So, sorry, that's probably not the answer you want to hear,
is it?
Cool, all right.
Thank you again.
Cheers, everyone.