Good afternoon, welcome.
My name is Henke, and I'm a freelance composer for mobile
and VR games and films.
In the past, I also had co-composing credits
as an additional composer for some of these nice games.
And I wanted to share with you the findings
of the annual Game Audio Survey for 2017,
sponsored by the Game Audio Network Guild
and Game Sound Con.
We're very grateful to Brian Schmidt
for doing these amazing surveys.
72% of the game composers also create sound effects.
50% of all game composers also provide audio integration.
So this is my message to all emerging composers
in the audience, and I mean this from my heart.
Learn sound design to expand your job possibilities.
Also, learn sound design to improve your own skills
and craft as a composer for games.
Having sound design skills makes you a more valuable collaborator
to game developers.
You could get in-house jobs and build the career more organically,
starting out as a sound designer for a game company
and then gradually composing as well.
Many sound designers have full-time staff positions.
On another hand, most composers are freelancers,
unless they're also sound designers.
So, I started out as a composer, so I learned all of this.
Each game has many people working on the sound.
Some may work on weapons, vehicles, combat, or foley.
Others may work on ambiences, dialogue, editing, implementation.
It's common for a game company to have a few staff audio specialists
and also farm out other audio tasks to freelancers.
Most indie games use only one composer.
The composer is brought in for a few months at the end
or the last few months of the development cycle.
I wanted to tell you a joke from the old world.
A son asks his son, what are you going
to become when you grow up?
And the son answers, I'm going to become a doctor.
And the father says, become a dentist.
People have 32 teeth and only one heart.
Most opportunities for emerging composers are in a mobile and casual field,
where having all audio skills, music, sound design, voiceover, editing,
audio middleware in implementation could help you land a great job.
This is why I encourage all of you to consider this path.
Another crucial reason to learn sound design is this.
Learning sound design improves your own craft and skills as a composer.
So this is, I'm speaking from my personal experience,
as a composer working on fantasy content where music, sound design,
and voiceover always dovetail and always mesh together,
it makes you a better game composer.
to really know how to create diegetic and ambient sound design,
because it's all frequencies and it all comes through the ears.
By learning sound design, you learn how to compose around the frequencies
of diegetic sound and tonal ambiences.
You practice scoring hits and jump scares in horror or genre titles
without the music smearing what the sound design is already doing.
On the other hand, the music is going to soar in the theme, the menu, the boss battles,
obviously, and action cinematics without dialogue.
It was a real epiphany for me.
I learned this from my developer friends.
Game developers approach the hierarchy of audio like this.
The voiceover is primary because it tells the story.
Diegetic sound effects.
or sound effects directly related to what's visible on the screen are secondary.
Emotional sound design, this is kind of a loose term, is the non-diegetic such as drones,
ambiences, which is anything that makes you feel something, is also secondary.
And music, the diegetic music, the non-diegetic music is tertiary.
So, in summary, I wanted...
You'll get staff jobs in game audio,
in game studio as a sound designer and implementer first,
and later as a composer.
And also, deep understanding of the sound in games
makes you definitely a greater game composer.
I wanted to briefly discuss one of my composing assignments.
I scored this Mummy VR game that is an arcade game.
And it's a shooter with zombies.
Genre projects always have a very elaborate...
By genre projects I mean horror, science fiction, fantasy, which I love and adore.
So these projects always have a very elaborate soundscape.
You have monster roars, you have fantasy creatures, voices, death,
sound of imaginary lands, interiors, dungeons, and so on.
So when scoring horror, I learned the hard way
to very carefully select the frequencies, timbres, instruments, and density of my music.
The Mummy VR is an eight minute experience.
It had helicopter diegetic sound
for the first four minutes throughout,
then a continued barrage of machine gun sound effects
for the next four minutes.
The game had a continuous voiceover for all eight minutes,
and my job as a composer was to figure out
a musical solution that would dovetail
with all sound design and the voiceover,
and I rescored the game twice
because my first approach failed.
It was too busy and too noisy and too orchestral.
So, my second approach was iconic sound for the characters, which were special forces and zombies,
and iconic sound for the genre.
And by iconic I mean a basic, like a basic signifier that instantly will telegraph to you who the characters are.
So the second big challenge in VR is that all the sound comes directly from headphones,
and usually they're crappy headphones in your brain.
In arcades, these are conventional headphones.
So the music needs to convey the emotions in a simple arrangement
that's not too busy, not too complicated, and won't burn your ears.
So this is how I approached the special forces without melody,
and with minimal chord changes.
with electronic arrangement that we associate
with like the special forces.
So I'm going to play the first half,
well, there's no video, you'll see the still image,
and you'll hear the music also dubbed
with the sound design and voiceover.
All strike team personnel report to your fields.
Target has been spotted.
Briefed on the target.
And the second half of the game was shooting at zombies and a lot of
creatures, a lot of noise. This is just a still image and I'll play just a little
bit of the second half of the game with the zombie shooting.
Because of the machine gun, I took out all percussion and really only had the pads and the brass,
because otherwise it would compete and it won't be good.
I wish you much success in your careers. Good luck and enjoy the rest of the panel. Thanks.
Hi, folks.
So I'm next, Bonnie Brogovich.
My talk, I have titled, I Have a Particular Set of Skills,
also known as How to Be Yourself
and Embrace Your Background.
And first off, I wanted to say that I was inspired
to take this twist on my micro talk
based on the results of being part of a panel
that was in 2016 titled,
Everyone at this Conference is a Fraud.
It was me, Stefan Schuetz, Laura Cartman,
Verun Nair, Austin Wintory, and D.B. Cooper.
And it was really inspiring to be on a panel of so many experts in the field who I personally admire,
and to hear that they also had fears about not being prepared for the industry that they're currently working in,
and the things that they encountered getting into the industry, and how to conquer them.
So I wanted to put a particular twist on it.
And first off, I kind of want to just quickly get a raise of hands.
Who here in the audience came from a non-direct-to-game path, or...
had a completely different career before going into the industry, something not game related.
Awesome, that's what I was hoping for.
So either if you're coming from a different industry
and hopping in or you're completely new to games
and you're trying to figure out how you can fit
into this wacky world, you know,
we'll enter a normal scenario that many of us have gone to.
You go to LinkedIn or you hear about a job posting
from someone and they're told,
oh yeah, you'd be perfect for this game opening.
Please go to it, check it out.
And you're like, sure, how bad could this be?
and you click on the apply now or the web link
and you start to read all of these descriptions
for crazy job titles and departmental needs
and must have 14 AAA products and must know why's
and all these other words are flashing at you
and suddenly you're like, oh my god,
I have no idea what I'm doing.
I don't have 14 titles under my belt.
I didn't go to a school for a degree in game audio
for most of us.
Like in my age group or older,
there weren't game audio degrees.
Heck, there sometimes weren't even music tech degrees
when we went to school.
So, it's like, what do you do when you're told, like,
yes, this is the field you wanna go to,
but you don't have a direct path?
And I wanna just assure a lot of you that,
especially those of you who have succeeded
in hopping into the industry,
not straight from a game path in the beginning,
just first, keep calm, take a deep breath,
know you're not alone, and...
I feel like many of us like to say that everything we learn,
especially bizarro quotes, we all learn from the movies of things to live by.
And I find Liam Neeson is a really good example.
Because we've all heard this quote, like, I have a very particular set of skills,
right, from Taken, and it's my bad impression.
And I want to remind all of us that we all have very unique sets of skills,
and we gather these skills through life and through all of the different experiences we have.
And often we forget that those skills can apply to dream jobs that we have,
or jobs that we don't even know exist yet.
So whenever you look at these giant lists of skills that are demanded for jobs,
especially wacky new careers in the game industry,
it's like, how do I gather all of these?
techniques, how do I gather this experience?
And you may be gathering it right now and you don't even know it.
You just need to start to learn to rethink your brain process and
know that you learn something every day if you pay attention.
And
You learn by doing, and often I think we forget this,
especially when we're not kids anymore.
We forget that we're all constantly learning.
And we learn it from every aspect of the day,
every job we've ever had, every mentor,
every experience, personally, before I worked in games.
I had many different jobs.
I came from, I was a fall spot operator,
boom operator for a while, I'm a chorus junkie,
I know a lot of people around GDC actually are.
Sing-along musician, stage manager, teaching assistant,
I've done multimedia, I do puppetry.
And I can assure you that I use skills
from every single one of these jobs every day
in my current career in game audio.
And you may think, oh God, that is crazy.
Do any of these relate to games?
Those of you in the audience who may have come from stage,
you're like, well, this is obvious.
For those of you who are not,
I'm gonna analyze one of my biggest career patterns
before I worked in games, which was a 10-year sprint
working as a touring stage manager in Pittsburgh
for opera companies, ballet,
and a bunch of modern art installations.
And while working as a stage manager, I acquired many different types of skills
that I realized later, when I eventually got in the game industry, were actually valid.
So I'm going to analyze two different sets of skills.
For those unfamiliar, there are hard skills and soft skills that you acquire.
Hard skills are practical knowledge you learn hands-on.
Software, handling rigging, things that actually
were hard skills that I worked on in theater
that I use in games, where I learned a ton about software,
spreadsheet management, organization.
Whenever you're working as a touring stage manager,
you have to manage actors' calendars and rehearsal
calendars.
Anyone who works in freelance is a game audio person.
Sometimes you have, oh, what, 700 color-coded calendars going
at the same time with different deadlines.
You learn about play testing when you work in theater because you do rehearsals and you try out stuff in front of audiences.
And in games you do that a lot too.
I learned a lot about working in different departments in software because I worked with some theater companies that had multimedia projection systems.
And my knowledge of things that I learned through them prepared me for working side by side as an audio person with graphic people in the game industry.
So those are some examples of actual software-based technical things.
But one of the most important types of skills you can get
that people often forget whenever they're trying to look at a career in games
is soft skills.
And whenever I say soft, I mean personal skills,
ways to deal with people, emotions.
A big word that floats around this conference is stress.
burning out, learning how to say no whenever a task is impossible,
or not being afraid to admit whenever you need help.
Theatre can be really stressful for anyone who's been on the tech or acting side,
and sometimes when you're on a game project and there's crunch,
one of your teammates might start exploding,
or maybe they're just low on sugar,
and you need to have that sense in your brain in a meeting
to be nice and offer them a cookie, and suddenly that saves the game.
But these are skills that...
You know, you can read about, you can see online, but the only way to really learn a soft skill is to work a job.
Work as a barista, work in theater, work as an educator.
Teachers deal with stress often. I mean, my God, they're saints.
But again, stage management taught me all these things and I carried them through whenever I was in-house.
Now you may think to yourself, OK, so you get into this mindset,
you analyze every type of job you've ever had.
I had, what, 14 jobs, right, because freelance is insane.
It's like, oh my god, so I have 7 million skills.
I can do all the things.
What can possibly go wrong if you say yes to every possible opportunity that
comes up, no matter how little it pays?
And obviously, burnout is a problem.
So you should learn that even though you are now able to analyze your life
and that you have these skills and you can take on stuff,
like maybe you're really good at handling.
people and making them not fight with each other and stress and balancing calendars and schedules.
And you become that person that everybody wants to balance their calendars and schedules.
It's good to not take on everything.
And after you've analyzed all the skills you have,
learn how to narrow it down and actually admit
what you don't want to do anymore.
So even though I praise, when I talk to kids
or I go and speak in front of crowds
and I say stage management I still feel
gave me the most skills I use in games,
I never want to be a stage manager again.
Because it burned me out too many times.
If you're lucky, especially on tour, you sleep.
Some people are nodding. They've been in stage tech.
You sleep three hours a night.
You're the last person to leave the theater.
You're the first person in. Everything's always your fault.
So, you know, that's life.
And I know I'm really good at my job.
I worked a long time because people knew I could handle it.
But I knew that health-wise, it wasn't for me.
But hey.
It's okay to acknowledge that I don't like burning out
and sleeping three hours a night isn't my thing.
And maybe someone else is really good
at not ever getting a good night's sleep.
So I'm happy now that I know how that job works
to pass on stuff to other people,
but keep the parts that I really learn from
and apply them in other places.
Again, please always remember, especially in game jobs,
if you're looking at different companies you wanna work at
and you learn that through working these other experiences,
you don't like working 80 hours a week
or you do like having a family life,
it's okay to say no to jobs where you know
that that industry or that lifestyle of the community
that works there, they like to burn people out.
Just don't apply there.
Look for companies that actually value
taking care of their employees.
And long story short, never forget where you came from.
Every job is valid.
Every experience is valid.
You never know what you're going to learn from something
until you do it.
And you don't have to stick with it if you don't like it.
But always cherish where you came from and find some way to
use that towards a future job.
Never stop learning.
Life never stops teaching you.
And always remember Liam Neeson in your brain.
Whenever you're looking at any job post and it lists all
those crazy skills, and a lot of them are really crazy
words that you don't know what the heck's going on.
Remind yourself that you have your own secret skills, and it's up to you how you apply them.
So, always be yourself guys.
Unless you can be Batman.
And then be Batman.
Thank you.
Hello, my name is John-Amber Matts, I'm going to talk about music and sound, a match made
in Slack.
Not endorsed by Slack.
So, here's a thesis statement for you.
Sound design and music are two parts of a whole,
and as such, we need to approach them holistically.
Now, for some projects, the audio team's eyes is one.
Now, if that's you, congratulations,
you control everything.
Good luck with that.
On the other hand, if you're working as part of an audio team, you can specialize, right?
As a composer, a sound designer, etc.
You don't have to worry about what anyone else is doing, you only have your one little
world to worry about, and it's just great.
I don't know, wait, no, heck, that's not how it works at all.
Because everything you do has an effect on someone else's work.
So how do we communicate?
If you're like me.
You're wincing right now, but that was the goal.
Anyway, so how do we communicate, right?
First, a word about remote work versus in-house work.
There's a bit of difference.
If you're in-house, you're very lucky.
You get to be in the same area as your team,
but you need to make sure you do everything, as Burr put it,
to be in the room where it happens.
All right.
So proximity and visibility are key.
Put your workstation in the midst of the development team.
Invest in good monitor headphones.
Make sure you find opportunities to share your works in progress
out loud when you reach milestones.
You want to make audio feel like it's part of the larger picture.
rather than something that's siloed off in a back room somewhere, an isolated element.
Go to the meetings, even if they don't have specifically things to do with audio.
And even if they're outside your normal area of expertise, be part of the team.
Now, if you're not fortunate enough to be in the same building as the rest of your team,
you need to find a way to...
communicate. Something, a solution that works to clearly show where you are on a project,
that show where everyone's working on, and allows you to easily share works in progress,
questions, insights, et cetera, and allows for quick and clear feedback on those works
in progress. And something, ideally, that fosters a sense of community within the team.
Now, I've used everything from Slack to Discord
to Skype to Facebook Messenger to communicate with my teams
and find that being able to pose a question
and share something I'm working on
and get feedback right away without having to worry
about a broken email chain or something like that
is super, super valuable.
It helps make you feel like you are
in the same room with the people.
No matter what your technical solution is
for communication, though,
it needs to be able to accomplish those goals.
So.
Communications techniques aside, what do you actually say?
Every discipline in game development has unique language.
Most of my experience comes from indie teams
where you are.
one person or two people on an audio team,
working with like four or five other people.
Now, you don't need to know everything about a language
to communicate with them.
There are hundreds of terms
unique to every language and discipline.
But understanding the basics can help you
and help form a effective bridge
from one discipline to another.
Knowing basic terminology or.
the structural logic behind a discipline
will help make you more valuable to the team
and help make your own ideas come across much more clearly.
So, a couple examples.
These are gross generalizations,
but programmers tend to really like logical arguments
and or randomization sequences, if this, then that.
If it's a complicated idea,
but you can express it in a flow chart,
they're gonna love you.
Maybe not this flow chart, but still.
Now artists on the other hand, again, gross generalization,
but they tend to understand color and emotion and intent.
Same with writers, all right?
A plethora of things that can be ample fodder
for your creative mind,
either in music or sound effects fields.
All right, these are things that can inspire you
and give you an idea of where things are gonna go
even before there's something in the game.
They're also the only people you can legitimately ask
to make something more purple.
sound and music share a common language. So if you're a sound
designer or a composer, that's great. You can pretty much talk
with them naturally, but sometimes you have to decipher
the accent. So things like frequencies, compression, EQ,
audio mix, ducking, dissonance, etc, etc, etc.
These are things that you're going to have in common
with your sound designer or your composer, all right?
And you can use them to describe things pretty effectively.
If you don't understand a term or a term in this context,
ask, learn.
Remember that everyone on the team
wants to produce the best possible work of art.
So it's always better to clarify and add to your knowledge
rather than assume and smile and nod your way
through a conversation.
I know that may seem obvious, but you'd be surprised.
So sound and music, working in concert.
Music and sound both come out of the same speakers
and go into the same receiver, human ear, right?
So picture this.
You need to make sure you communicate your intents clearly,
leave room for each other's work as appropriate.
Here's an example.
You're writing a vital cue for a key moment in a game.
As the hero looks up at their goal so very far away,
we hear this plaintive horn theme.
It's quoting the theme of her quest,
the theme you painstakingly stitched
into the prophecy cut scene at the start of the game.
She's come so far and through so many trials
to reach this point, and she's never been more alone
or more determined.
Now your sound designer looks at this scene
and says, oh, this is super lonely.
You're on the top of this hill, there's a lot of wind.
I want to just make you feel isolated.
We'll do this.
Now, remember, everything you do has an effect
on someone else's work.
Both approaches are valid, but some communication
would have saved us from this.
I won't subject you to that anymore.
There's only so much space in the audio spectrum at any given point, as was mentioned earlier.
Sound effects and music need to be especially considerate of each other's requirements.
Gameplay in the end is king, and sound effects frequently provides vital player feedback.
So you always want to take into consideration the likely sound design of a scene before you score it.
Now, Penka touched on this earlier with Mummy, alright?
But also, last year, Will Roger was talking about stripping out percussion elements for his Call of Duty World War II score,
leaving it with just, like, brass and strings and woodwinds,
so that that left space for explosions and gunfire and other stuff.
You want to make sure, in addition, that the sounds you're using don't clash with the music, they'll be heard alongside.
Just like you want to make sure the music isn't going to get in with the sounds, vice versa.
The sound, you know, so say your sound has a pitched element to it.
You want to make sure that it's in a compatible key with the music it's going to be heard alongside.
It would take up huge swaths of the audio spectrum with it,
unless the score's not doing anything so that it won't interfere.
Compliment. Don't compete.
That's a little cue from a game I worked on called Fossil Echo.
In Fossil Echo, we had two possible ways
your character could die.
You could be shot, or you could fall to your death.
When you fell and didn't die, we got a good body thump kind
of impact, but he brushes and gets up, brushes himself off,
and goes on.
When you die in another way, you get this hit.
Early on, we had a body impact sound and this hit,
and that was a bad move.
But the musical hit proves much more effective
to tell you that, like, hey, that's the end for you.
Sorry, kid.
Anyway, what about musical sound design?
Good communication can help you find and capitalize
on these opportunities.
Even as a composer working with a sound designer,
sometimes musical sound design elements
can be a vital aspect of a game's overall sound design
and help tie the score and sound together in a holistic way.
Here are a few examples here.
So in For the King, when enemies pop up on the map,
we get these little horn stings.
Now, our sound designer was struggling to find,
well, he basically immediately realized
that there really was no good sound effect for these things.
It should be a musical element.
And so I used some of the instruments and timbres
that I'd used in the score to kind of cue these things in.
Same thing with rolling dice in this game.
Rather than actual dice sounds, we used
little drum and percussion sounds, all right, to further kind of cement the idea that this
was a sort of a collaborative musical thing.
In addition, we had a whole class of characters that were minstrels and bards, and they played
lutes and other things to cast magic spells.
And so we wanted to make sure that when we were in a battle, you were using these instruments
and the sounds that we would have coming out of there.
various accoutrements would mesh with the key of the combat music.
All right? Most of the time. Anyway, so in conclusion, ask questions.
Stay in the room where it happens, either physically or digitally. Find a way to do
that. Stay connected to the rest of the team's
development progress and process, and let them know that you are, what you are
doing as well.
Hopefully, I've impressed upon you the importance of good communication with your audio team
and within the larger development ecosystem.
Asking questions, knowing what everyone else is creating, and being able to get and give
feedback are vital to a unified project.
I hope you all have protective, communicative teams going forward.
Thank you very much.
Hello, everybody.
Hope you guys are having a great GDC.
I want to start this presentation
by apologizing in advance, because I am not
the best presenter.
Emmanuel, I don't know what you were thinking.
But here I am.
So never again.
I'm kidding.
So my name is Erika Escamez, and I am from Monterey, Mexico.
I live here in the city, though, and I'm the audio director
and lead sound designer for Ektra Games.
We work on a project called Torchlight Frontiers.
Like many of you here, I'm assuming,
how many of you are composers?
Raise a hand.
All right, all right, cool, cool.
And how many of you have done sound design
with your composing before?
All right, pretty much the same.
Cool, awesome.
So like many of you, I have a music background.
I went to Berklee College of Music,
the music one, not the impressive one from California.
And when I graduated I had no idea that sound design was even an option for me.
I didn't even know what it meant.
But believe me when I say that being a composer can only make you a better sound designer.
Almost everything will be covered by the amazing speakers and the amazing presentations they
have.
But I'm just going to jump in and go through this and let you know what I think.
you need to do to think like a sound designer
if this is your first time trying it out.
Where's the mouse?
Oh, there it is, okay.
First thing, the strategy.
It is not enough to just be able to create something cool.
How can you take it to the next level?
To have like a dynamic mix,
then showcase what's really important
and what really means something to the player.
And for that,
we need to think outside of the box.
Second, coming up with the questions and not the answers
on how to make a simple composition that loops,
for example, into something dynamic
that conveys information to the player
is what will set you apart.
Having the ability and thought process
to use your composition to do this
is what differentiates a composer from a sound designer.
Also, I'm sorry for my accent.
Not just composing the cue is enough.
but saying, hey, so you need a two minute piece of music
for the gloomy dark pond.
Well, how about I can give you a six minute piece
without actually going through over two minutes of content
and all the programmers will love you
because you'll save a bunch of memory
from streaming and all that.
So those are the kinds of things that you wanna be,
or the kind of way that you wanna be thinking about.
In our game, specifically,
everything's changing all the time.
And Matt Ullman, our composer, basically delivered me a four minute song.
And after 20 minutes of playing, I've heard the same motif five times.
And I already know it by heart.
So I said, how can we fix it so it's every time the timeline is going through,
changes a little bit?
It changes.
It's different every time.
How can we use this to our musical advantage
to convey the information that we need, and vice versa?
How can we use the information that we want to convey in a musical way?
I have a note that says next slide.
So come up with the questions and not the answers.
Here are some examples of questions you can ask yourself
while you are composing.
How many enemies are on screen?
How far are they from my player?
How many other players are around?
How difficult is the enemy?
What's the environment like?
Just is there a monster skill happening?
Am I using a special skill?
Is there a UI?
Is there a hazard monster doing skill status?
And you can go on and on and on, man,
like with so many questions.
Why did I put so many?
So yeah, final questions.
Questions, not answers.
How does the music change based on all these factors
in a non-linear environment?
Next slide.
Using music as a sound skill
in your.
Using music is a sound design skill in your game.
Thought process.
I need to communicate all of the above questions,
all of the above questions.
And what better way to do that than using music
to communicate how much danger the player,
you the player, or me the player are in.
So the first thing we did is I sat down with Matt Ullman
and I came up with a way to write up music in a,
well we came up with a way to write the music
in a different way, not in a linear way.
And instead of creating music in one big loop,
we decided that we were gonna create the music
in four bar variations.
Imagine thousands upon thousands of four bar motifs
and hits coming together in a puzzle-like way
to make a song.
And then once we put those songs together,
two minutes long or four minutes long,
however the piece is,
we wanted these instruments to change the intensity
and drama as a game of,
drama increases or decreases.
So the result is the mix within our two minute piece would change dynamically and it will
never be the same.
I will show you how we did this in a second after I explain the next part.
So then I said, I couldn't do this by myself, obviously.
We came up with the idea, and we sat down with Guy,
who's right here, who is an amazing,
our lead programmer, audio programmer,
programmer extraordinaire.
He says he does not restructure the universe when he codes,
but I swear he does.
And we told them what we wanted to do
with this new music system.
And the way we came up with this is
how do we communicate how much drama is happening at once
by assigning things within the world a drama value
which then drives the code to set the instance
as low intensity, medium intensity, and high intensity.
Next slide.
The result, flexible music.
flexible dynamic music.
The music should change if the tension increases,
if the drama increases.
For example, the drums should rise
if the enemy is particularly difficult
by assigning a higher drama value to that enemy.
And if you're just cruising,
then the intensity of the music should be low,
it should be calm, it should just fill your space.
And the most important thing,
it should not interfere with the sound effects
or skills of the player.
which is something they've already talked about.
It should be cohesive.
So instead of having a sound effect that would say,
hey, here comes a big enemy,
the music is the one that triggers you.
The music is the one that says,
oh, I am in this amount of danger.
Hit escape.
And then tab.
Oh, there it is.
Cool.
So this is one of our music sessions.
We have a couple beds here, just to make it easier.
But to give you an example of
toms, here we go.
These toms, there is one, two, three, four variations.
This is fmod, by the way.
For those of you who do not know, it's a great tool.
Each tom is different, one from another.
You get the idea, right?
And if we solo this, every time the timeline goes through here,
it will pick a new one.
Well, I'll show you in a second.
Oh, yeah, yeah, cool.
I got to turn this up, and this mouse not, there we go.
and it just picked on a different one, and so on.
So every time the timeline goes there,
it randomly picks one, or we can choose
if we want a priority on a certain one.
So that's the way the variations were working,
and if you can see here, we have it with the toms,
we have it with the hi-hat,
we have it with Fuzz 16th bass notes,
the crash cymbals, the crash high only,
a kit, et cetera, et cetera, shakers, blah, blah, blah.
Okay, cool.
And so.
Then we had the system where basically it grabs all the drama values, so say 0 to 10.
If the game says it's 0 to 10 intensity, then play low intensity.
If it's 10 to 20, play medium.
If it's 20 to 30, play high.
So I'm just going to show you a little bit how that would work, basically what the engine
would be doing if that was the case.
We're on low intensity.
This is for a creepy bug world, by the way.
And here come a couple monsters.
And then here comes a champion.
And it just stays there until you're done killing it.
We'll go back to medium.
Because you still have a couple other enemies.
You're done with them, you go back down.
And that is it.
Now to congratulate myself for getting through this
without having a heart attack,
I'm gonna have a milkshake.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Matthew Martinson. I don't have a very great title. So this is me. If you don't
know, I'm Matthew Martinson, like I just said.
I think I always repeat that twice, I don't know why.
I'm a sound designer at Clay Entertainment.
I've been doing game audio for 16 years.
I also do the Beards, Cats, and Needy game audio podcast
that some of you might know of, I'm not sure.
I'm a sound designer, not a composer,
so I'm coming from that end of things.
Bear with me.
Usually, I'm overly verbose about just about everything,
so seven minutes is a challenge,
but we're gonna try and speed run this.
So, you want to get into sound effects.
Right away, lots of people are going to tell you
that you need to spend a lot of money.
I've always had a problem with that,
and in the long run, doing sound design
is going to take a lot of investment on your part.
But when you're starting out,
when you're just trying to see
if you even enjoy doing this part of it,
now you don't need to do that.
I'm going to make a few assumptions here.
That you're a composer, you have a computer, a DAW,
an interface, some sort of monitoring,
your usual suite of plugins that comes with that.
And if that's what you've got, you don't need much more than
that to start out.
I think to note that the fanciest tools that you see a
lot of sound designers talk about and throw around that
they use all the time.
are really about speeding up workflows.
When you're starting out, you don't know
how you're going to work yet.
So don't worry about the special stuff
until you actually know what your workflows might be like,
and then you know which ones you want to speed up.
So what do you need to make sound effects?
You need a DAW, you already got that.
You need some sounds to layer with
and a way to record things.
Don't feel that you need to change the DAW
you're using to make music
because you're now doing sound effects and it's different.
Some might be better in certain ways once you know what you're doing, but you're better off sticking with something you already know
Because you're not don't want to learn two skills at once you can use Pro Tools Reaper or Cubase logic live
Fruity loops, whatever
Whatever you use now keep doing that for sound effects
Sounds can come from libraries in your own recordings that
As long as you do this, it always comes from those.
Lots of sound effects providers will give small free
packages of sound effects that basically are the cost of an
email, so you can start to build a library for free or
next to nothing.
There's also freesound.org, but be careful.
Lots of sounds there need proper credit, and then you
need to keep track of that, which can add a workload that
you might not want to do.
I never want to do that.
And you also have to sift through a lot of garbage to find the good stuff, so you can
spend a lot of time trying to find something usable.
And there's also always rumors of copyright infringing sounds have been uploaded there
and you could get nailed for that infringement without even knowing it.
A portable recorder will be a really useful tool that you might not have that could be cool.
Even the really cheap ones from any of the reputable manufacturers will do just awesome, great job.
Don't worry about you got to spend thousands of dollars on that kind of stuff.
And if you don't have that and don't want to spend that,
your phone is a perfectly good recorder.
There's YouTube channels devoted to making sound effects
just from phone recordings.
They will show you just, you can do great results.
It doesn't really matter.
If you wanted to record at home,
you've already got a setup, you've got a DAW,
that means you have an interface.
Maybe all you need is a microphone then.
I found there's a $20 Chinese microphone
that is like way better than it should be.
buy that. There's lots of slightly higher priced ones from
reputable manufacturers that you can get into too. Anything on
the low end really is quite good these days. But the great thing
about cheap microphones is you can put them in really dangerous
places. You get some really interesting sounds until you get
no sound at all. I totally haven't melted any microphones
when recording things. Never happens. So, that said.
Always be recording.
Nothing is what it seems when you're building sound effects.
So it's all about reinterpreting sounds
from libraries and from recordings.
This is great for starting out
because you don't need to actually own
any of the things you're making sounds for.
You don't need to own a tank to make tank sounds.
Everything within arm's reach can become a source
of new and interesting sounds to make things from.
Think about bone breaking, it's always celery.
We don't break bones for those sounds.
So start taking things from around your house and putting
in front of a microphone.
Shake the thing, hit the thing, rub it, hit it with
something else.
Do these things softly, do these things hard.
Record them in all the different ways you possibly
can, listen how the sound changes when you do different
actions, listen for the elements of the sound that you
can then use for something else.
Recording sound effects is then like any other
instrument, you need to practice at it.
So approach it with that mindset.
It's a performance.
You can get totally different things out of items
when you use them in different ways.
And just like any instrument with practice,
you gotta do a lot of it before you get good at it.
So, you actually wanna make some sense.
It's all about layers.
You layer lots of different things together
to make a new cohesive whole.
This is the same way you would approach orchestrating a song.
So you've already got that skill set.
Just think about making a sound effects
like putting a band together.
You layer all these different bits
and you come up with something new.
You build up the lows, the mids, and the highs
and you balance all these elements into this new thing.
It's just the things are the body and the punch
and the mechanics of a gunshot.
instead of the bass guitar drums of a rock band
or the different sections of an orchestra.
It's all the same concept underlying it.
So your direct compositional orchestration skills
will translate into making these sound effects.
Middleware, that's the other big part
of making sound effects.
You might already do some of that as a composer.
If you don't, the implementation will definitely work
into how your sound effects work into the game.
You will need to skill up on this middleware and game engines at some point, but worry about that second.
Don't take on too many things at once to embark on this new endeavor.
You can do it one step at a time.
So learn to be an effective sound designer first, then become an implementer.
Your implementation will become way better if you already have an understanding of sound design to go into it with.
And once you are ready to tackle that,
just about all the major middleware programs
are available out there for free.
There's game engines that you can download for free.
Well, so that's a like no cost thing
to invest some time in and learn.
So there you go.
You don't need to spend a lot of money
if you wanna get into this.
Remember, you already know what you're doing.
Your skills are transferable.
You wanna record as much as you possibly can
and don't worry about learning everything at once.
Next.
Hi, I'm Emmanuel Lagoon-Bai, a freelance audio designer,
and I'm here to tell you how you can haz job.
Is this you?
I'm a composer, all I do is music, I love music, I love my sub-life, it's great.
Hey, do you need a composer for your game?
I know, I'll take my cards, I've got like plenty.
I'm like, it's actually like this musical, it's kind of like Star Wars, you know, it's awesome, it's a lot of fun.
I like machine games, I was wondering if you needed a composer.
Thank you, it's pretty awesome, I'm doing it with it.
Keep me in mind, dude, like here, let me give you my business card, let me just like...
Yeah, totally.
Yeah, I'll definitely keep you in mind.
Thank you.
If it is you, can you not?
So anyway, who am I?
I'm a composer gone rogue.
Sound effects are now my best friend.
I worked on Ventureverse,
or I worked on a game called Ventureverse.
It's currently in early access.
I've contracted for Torchlight Frontiers,
though I think I might be fired
after putting Erica through that.
So, I've also done sound effects for the VR experience,
Wonderfall, A Tale of Two Realms.
And we're just gonna get started with some basic numbers
here before getting to the other details
of how you can start getting your jobs,
your first gigs as a sound designer.
So according to that same survey that Pinka referenced
in the beginning of the chat,
50.8% of 464 audio professionals said that they actually
got work from referrals or networking.
In other words, 50.8% of people are working
because they showed up and said hi.
So congratulations, half of you will all have jobs
somewhere down the road.
Ventureverse, Wonderfall, Miracle Mia,
those were all games I actually got the sound design for
because I actually knew the composers
that were working on it, or I was friends
with a few people that didn't want to take on that work.
There's another one I got to do
where I had a friend who's actually sitting here, Andrew,
who was out of the country, and he called me.
He said, hey, one of my deadlines got pushed back
to like two days from now.
Can you do the sound effects for me?
And I'm like, sure, man, yeah, I got you.
I'll get you covered.
So are you ready to be that person as part of the gig?
And I would much rather have six great relationships
than $60,000 of sound libraries.
While the libraries and friends can both comfort me
as I cry myself to sleep,
the sound libraries won't directly buy me alcohol
outside of the office.
And.
Yeah, sure, not everyone here gets jobs from other people.
I get that.
Some people have to talk to real people.
Some tips regarding that,
do not do what you saw in that video there.
Leading with, do you need a composer?
Makes us all look like really desperate and just kind of bad.
You will have plenty of time to talk about you
and your craft in the future
if the relationship is there to begin with.
Also, please remember that people are hiring a person
and not just a role.
You can be an excellent designer, but you can be a complete ass that no one wants to work with.
So people will remember that.
Surprise! In the end, it's a numbers game.
And like Penka said, 72% of composers also do sound design.
This means that everyone here is probably out to get you.
Which also probably means everyone out here is sometimes here to get you a job.
We're all competing at different tiers at all times.
People may work on student projects when they're starting out,
they may move to indie, then they move to mid-tier,
and then eventually AAA.
But there's always backwards compatibility between the two,
so if you're a AAA composer,
don't just consider yourself shoehorned into AAA.
You could be doing other work for other things too.
Believe it or not, people in the industry
often get too much work, so if they don't want to take it,
are you ready to be that person they can go to as a referral?
But how do you prepare for that moment?
I'm assuming here that not everybody here
has fully gone into sound design.
Can I see people that have never sound designed before?
Yeah, there's a handful of people here.
Wow, I'm actually kind of impressed
that there's a handful of people
that a lot of you are doing sound design already.
Nice.
But if you aren't, you have to start
by putting together a demo reel.
what do you actually do?
So putting together a demo reel is kind of like
picking clothes for GDC.
Are you gonna be wearing something fancy?
Are you gonna be wearing something nerdy?
The point at the end is just really
to be comfortable in your own skin.
Wear what you want, show what it is
that you want yourself to show,
and identify the niche you resonate with most.
For instance, if you wanna work on shooters,
you probably wanna be showing gun sounds,
explosions, vehicles, and not necessarily swords and shields.
But E-man, I have no credits.
I can't make a demo reel.
That's a lie.
No credits, no problem.
So a lot of stuff comes from footage
that you can actually just overlay sounds on.
Like when you're starting out,
if you have a student project,
you're often asked to do that kind of work.
Find the footage which you can create opportunity with,
and you feel that you can add to.
Always try to be better than the original in your own way,
because it's a lot easier to work on pieces
that have room for growth,
rather than those that have already
a lot of established sound.
For instance, I'm gonna later show you a demo
of something I felt I could add to,
rather than something I felt I couldn't elevate
with my current skill in design.
So you may be wondering though,
why is there a delicious pineapple pizza on the screen?
Thank you, thank you.
Exactly this, this is exactly it.
You need to know your audience.
If you buy a pizza for a group of friends,
and you're the only person there that likes pineapple pizza,
you've just disappointed a ton of people.
But you made yourself very, very happy.
You're going to be the happiest guest at that table.
My best friend, who actually isn't in audio,
stated it best for me while I was mentally freaking out
about a lot of stuff.
He said, it's a lot about, it's like cards against humanity.
You have to know your audience.
You have to appeal to the people that are voting for you.
And if you think your work will benefit from something
you add, then go for it.
Get that pineapple on that pizza.
If not, better to play it safe.
Well, E-man, now I know what to do,
but I don't know how to do it.
That's okay.
Ask for help.
Contrary to popular belief, it's actually okay
to ask other people their opinion
before you submit their work,
or before you submit your work,
your work, before you submit your work.
I made this.
You don't know any sound designers?
Well, there's plenty of composers out there
that are actually pretty capable
of providing some fantastic feedback.
And look around you now and start making friends.
Everyone here is able to help each other grow.
Some of these friends may even see your work down the line
and may be the ones you work with in the future.
I'm gonna go ahead and plug Reel Talk by Power Up Audio.
That's a podcast slash stream in which people can
submit their reels for review and it's fantastic.
A lot of people can get a lot of great feedback from that.
So I'm gonna go ahead and share
my first ever sound design attempt.
In 2017, this is when I decided
to just jump into sound design.
So as you can imagine, guys, I immediately got hired after that.
The truth, though, is after many iterations and sending it to colleagues for some feedback,
and then presenting that version to a panel of people at the demo derby, and then getting
more feedback from them, I was able to present and create this.
Thanks for watching!
Far from perfect, but after two weeks of work really on it
and just jumping in and diving in
and getting as much critique as I could,
I was able to add an additional 30 or 40 seconds to it
and secure the attention of some of my colleagues,
which is really where it all began.
After being super humbled and inspired
to post it on Facebook
and share my first sound design project,
I actually turned the heads
of my mostly audio employees friends list,
which led to some of my first sound design gigs.
So, I'd like to leave you with a few thoughts
and things to remember.
It takes time and effort to get better.
It takes time and effort to build great relationships.
It takes time and effort to be a good person.
Don't just surrender after your first KO.
Press continue, try again, see what happens,
because everyone's path is different in the end.
You may have noticed that this presentation
was in Comic Sans, with some occasional inconsistencies
and bullet points and spellings and dash marks here and there
But the reality is that's kind of life.
Not everyone likes Comic Sans, but someone out there may.
While one person may hate and not like your reel,
another might want to hire you for something that just might change your life.
Because you picked Comic Sans.
So, if anyone out here is currently hiring and likes Comic Sans,
I have a full stack of business cards for you.
Thank you.
We've got a few minutes left.
I'd like to go ahead and share with you everybody here.
Thanks to the panelists that decided to jump in on this and
dive in with me.
Pankaj, please stand up as well.
If you haven't already, you'll probably be receiving a survey, so please like, comment,
subscribe, smash that like button. So that way we can actually get some great feedback and
just understand how to make this process better. We have a couple minutes for questions, so
I'll take like maybe one or two. Run! Fight, fight, fight!
Hi everyone, thank you for your presentations.
They were all great.
One of the first slides that was shown had percentages of,
and one of those percentages said C-sharp in scripting.
I was wondering how much of that falls on your role,
or do you typically just send your content to a programmer
and then it's their responsibility to implement?
Thank you.
Erica, do you wanna take that one?
That was Pankaj.
Oh, gotcha.
It was Pankaj, it's like with the game video.
So my perspective is of a freelance composer who only writes the music.
I talk very closely with all my bosses, my collaborators.
I don't write the first note of music until I understand fully
how the music is going to be implemented in gameplay, the different levels.
So there are a lot of conversations and a lot of planning how to compose.
I transitioned into game scoring from film, from linear media, and it was a learning curve.
This is what I would encourage you to do.
Read the game audio survey from 2017, which is just Google it, it's going to pop up.
Brian Schmidt is providing this service to the community.
It's an incredible learning tool.
I myself have made the choice to be only a composer.
This means I'm always hustling to get work.
This is why I'm encouraging.
the young composers, the emerging composers to also consider sound design because it's a very viable career path.
But as far as programming, I put the slide there, and I'm not a programmer.
Thank you.
We're just about six sound designers now.
And I don't touch a lot of code, but one of our sound designers
is basically an audio programmer now.
So even within our, it's going to change studio to studio
how much code you might touch.
Even within my studio, sound designers
touch different amounts of code.
It will never hurt you to learn some of that.
Even if you never touch it, you can communicate more effectively
with your programmers.
And being able to talk on their level will always be a plus.
Rachel, do we have time for one more? All right, sounds good.
Thank you all for presenting. This is to you as well as to the
room. It is Thursday night, maybe night four or night five
of GDC for some people. Audio people, where the party at?
So the Game Audio Network Gold has their award show tonight.
It's going to be a second floor of Moscone 2016, 2018.
It's an award ceremony, and there's also going to be an after party for that too.
Thank you.
There's also another talk about audio at the same time.
Oh, so about VR, actually.
VR and audio at the same time.
So maybe that's why?
No, no, no, five and four.
Isn't what it does?
Oh, no, he's saying where the party at?
Like where is she at?
Oh, the party!
Yeah, where the party at?
Well, there's a lot of places around here
where you can party.
Yeah.
You don't need the audio people to party, man.
Cool.
We bring the party.
Brian.
All right, slam that next question in.
I'm a huge fan of Comic Sans, so.
Yay!
I'll talk to you after.
Sorry.
Let's go.
We'll be outside if you guys have any more questions.
Feel free to approach us at any time.