Greetings, fellow TDCers! I'm Ingvild and I run a small studio called Henchmen & Goon
out of Norway, the land of fjords, mountains, and picturesque cottages riddled with traditionally
rose-painted accessories.
Last year we launched our latest title, Pode, which is a cute, family-friendly, slow-paced
game all about exploring, solving puzzles, and experiencing the beauty of the world around
you.
I'll be giving a talk on how we approach the visual design for PODE, so if you're interested
in hearing how the Scandinavian political turmoil of the previous millennium has inspired
the colourful, friendly, cosy world of PODE, I hope you'll join me in San Francisco.
See you there!