Hello everybody. Oh, it's too loud. Hi. I'm so glad to be here. A bit nervous. It's my
first GDC, first talk. So, yeah. Thank you. It was definitely on my bucket list. It's
so glad to see so many nice and friendly faces. I'm talking to you, Jeremy. Yeah.
So this presentation will contain spoilers,
so if you haven't played Expansion Packs,
you can sometimes cover your ears and eyes.
But before we get down to the business,
I'd love to just introduce myself properly.
So my name is Sebastian Kalemba,
and I'm Animation Director at CD Projekt Red.
I worked there on Witcher 3 Wild Hunt and then both expansion packs.
Right now we are working on Cyberpunk 2077.
Before I worked at a company called Platige Images in Poland
in a cinematic department as a lead animator.
And even before I worked in England for the Real Time UK
on a few AAA titles like Kinect E-mails or Disneyland Adventures.
On a daily basis, I'm an animation tutor at iAnimate and I really love it.
And a fun fact is I used to be a vice champion of Brazilian Jiu-Jitsu in Poland,
so I love motion, not only in games.
But before we move forward, I'd love to introduce this great team
of animators, producers, cinematic designers and TDs.
So, pushing boundaries. Let's talk about that.
For the Wild Hunt, we had to deliver around 16,000 assets in three years.
The game is quite big, I don't know if you've played that,
but it's like 200 hours to finish it with side quests and minors.
For the expansion packs, we had to deliver just 50 hours,
but we did more animation content.
I will talk about that in a minute.
So...
we had in essence we had like half of that time because that was just a year and we had to deliver
even more more animations in less time. So I'm now going to show you the show reel.
It's just five minutes, hopefully you'll enjoy that. It's from expansions.
Stunt.
Fight.
well.
All right, thank you.
So here's the agenda.
Mind you, I won't talk about our daily work.
I will talk more about how we took our existing skill set
after main game and we just straight jump
into the expansion packs.
We had to upgrade our pipelines and workflow a little bit
because there was a little bit like too much content.
We'd be scared of that.
So we had to pimp this fundamental,
like basics in our workflow.
So I'm going to talk about improving communication and this helped with speeding up many processes,
focusing on character motivation which helped us on quality,
and reorganizing the animation department during this one year which helped us with both time and quality.
But starting with tech, there's a tiny background I want to tell you.
We worked all expansion packs and main game
using the MotionBuilder 2010, just MotionBuilder.
There was no time to make re-exporters,
jump into the new version of MotionBuilder.
So we sometimes really been like Geralt,
looking at the roach on the roof, getting some crazy bugs.
We had really stable tech and that was good.
So we felt like Geralt in armor and with two swords.
But at the same time we get the.
high like a high level like message from the production that we shouldn't bother so much the
programmers because they need to focus on
of course cyberpunk at the same time
I must say that animators as a mock-up specialist,
they've been like one man's band.
We've been like one man's band.
So we didn't have, even the motion capture department
that time wasn't like an independent team.
We had to, we have very small studio,
we have to, like mock-up studio, I mean,
we have to manage the mock-up by ourselves.
So we got idea, we got some story,
we had to mock-up by ourselves,
we had to clean it up by ourselves.
and then we had to animate by ourselves.
So it was really sometimes frustrating.
So first things first, communication.
And this relates to pushing the time boundary.
And it's not that we haven't communicated before.
Of course we did, a lot.
But still we could definitely optimize
some parts of the communication.
So as Lana mentioned at the beginning,
I need to start from the kiss rule. So, honestly, that was the most important thing. In expansion
packs I knew that we have a year, so I wake up every morning, went to the bathroom and
kiss myself in front of the mirror and I'm not a vain, I'm just, you know, I was telling
myself that keep it simple, stupid, there's no time for crazy iteration process. So that
was definitely the most important rule during the production of expansion packs.
Second, abundance of cool, but not unnecessary ideas.
It's like, yeah, you know that.
It's like having a lot of ideas is as bad as having no ideas at all.
So, this rule...
like a keep it simple rule and like having very very like a really clarity at the beginning of
each process of creating monsters or main main npcs in the game it was helping us a lot.
Yeah this is what I'm talking about. Lag of structure and formalizing the pipeline by templates.
So we incorporated templates into our production. We start communicating even more often.
with the design team and the story,
and it was a really infinity loop.
Because, you know, our games are heavily story-driven.
Everything comes from the story.
So we had to really make sure that if you really make,
the question always was, like at the beginning,
if you want to make your character
really grounded in the world,
you have to make sure that the story department
knows about that and agrees.
So before, as I said, we communicate,
but the process was a little bit messy,
and it looked like that.
So, for example, you see the toad here, yeah?
The first boss in the Hearts of Stone expansion pack.
So that was the process at the beginning.
Like, you know, we got the idea, you have to make a toad.
But it's like, what toad?
Prince toad.
So, oh, OK, another dandelion, beautiful, handsome guy.
But yeah, it's a dark fantasy game.
So dark prince?
Okay, but the design said, hey guys, we need to have a ranch attacks.
They have to have, the toad has to have tumors on his back,
his tongue has to be covered with spikes.
So I'm like, oh my God, don't tell us, yeah?
So we need to put some blisters on his face because of, you know,
that's exactly what I'm talking about.
Keep it simple, stupid.
We start narrowing down the basics, design and animation process
as soon as possible.
So that finally the guy.
in a game look like that.
Hey, mom.
Yeah.
And in the...
Let me show you.
Yeah but thought was rather simple. This guy was a nightmare. Because normally in a very small strike
teams we spend like three months on each monster, each boss fight I'm talking, each boss fight.
And that laugh was a little bit more difficult. You know vampires yeah? Vampires are supernatural.
They are transforming into mist. They can rip apart the human being so quickly.
So yeah, that was the Death Laugh first form.
But then we knew that this guy is the final boss of the whole game
in the end of expansion pack 2, Blood and Wine. And we got those concepts.
Yep, so, okay, this guy is transforming into that thing
and we have to make him fly, we have to make him walk, run,
and then, like, we didn't even know how to manage this guy
from the body mechanics perspective, you know?
We cannot transform the model
during the fight so many times.
So, that was his first monster stage.
As you see, we even changed a little bit the communication with the FX department.
You see those tiny helpers around him?
We, with the animator, the owner, Tizian, he actually animated those helpers
just to show FX artists how we want to make the FX supporting the whole animation.
And it definitely like speed up the process of creating FX a lot.
But yeah, that was the first stage.
And this is exactly where we iterate.
Ah, my God, like three months.
We had all together, we had like just six months.
We should have like, honestly, like nine months.
But we had just six months for that guy
with a very small team.
And what we had, we had this guy.
We knew that we, at some point, we need to get him down.
So we need to chop his wings off.
And what's then?
We've been iterating and talking to Story, what's then?
And they said, okay guys, let's fight with the construct of his blood in illusion of his heart.
I'm like, yeah, good.
But how to do that?
So here you have a few examples of this construct.
The construct, the idea of construct, he was brainless.
He was kind of magic monster, like very aggressive and quick.
And there's the scene when we are chopping his wings off.
So yeah, guys, this template saved our lives.
Honestly, we finished Dead Love in six months.
And that was a really big challenge for us.
So the second, the most important thing we did during
the expansion packs was pushing a little bit the
character motivation.
And
How we did that, I've already told you that
story is the king in our games.
Like no matter what, story has to drive everything.
And we constantly talk to story.
So we got this template, which really speed up
the iteration process.
The iteration process was really dynamic.
So we communicate a lot.
So we get this idea of
getting this template and communication
sorted out as soon as possible
and
we made out of
almost every animator
was like a supervisor of an NPC or a monster
so they've been not even just actors
they've been even co-directing
each monster on a mock-up session.
and that really helped us a lot because with that template,
on the first day of the mock-up shoot, we had a brief,
we knew everything about the character,
so directing the characters was really much easier.
Not easy, but way more easier.
So we had these dedicated teams for every monster.
Every department had his own artist specialist
in every single monster department.
So, let's say, always like 68 people in one strike team.
And as I said,
Because of that, because of having those people around the one monster,
the process of iteration was really dynamic.
They've been communicating all the time on a daily basis.
So this is a good example of Olgierd.
It's the first boss fight in the first expansion pack, Hearth of Stone.
So what's cool about Olgierd?
Olgierd is a human being and we've been like,
okay, Geralt is killing monsters every day,
so how to make a human being a demanding enemy to Geralt?
But yeah, we got this message from the story
that this guy's actually immortal.
So yeah, so if he's immortal, how to show it through the gameplay animation, through the combat?
I mean like, it would be cool to show that he's, because he's a noble guy,
he signed a pact with the devil, and he doesn't care.
He has everything he wants.
So we wanted to show that he's really cocky,
that even his idle position in a fight is really open.
He's like even inviting you to kill him.
Because he doesn't care, he even doesn't check where you are, he's just constantly very cocky and aggressive guy.
But we've been like thinking about what kind of combat style we should develop, we should work on.
And finally, we found that in 17th century, in Poland actually, the combat like the cross sabers masters, the saber masters,
they developed this combat style, very deadly style, called...
cross saber. They called him like the Polish samurai, let's say. The stance was very open.
That's the, let's say, idle position for them. The position was very open. The sabers were very
light, so they could deliver so many attacks in seconds. They've been like twirling around the
enemy.
really, and the style was very cheaty and dirty.
So they really been killing enemies very quickly.
The sword masters didn't have like any chance
to even fight with them.
So really we've been studying that.
And finally, this is a part of the mock-up session.
It's one of the first days of the training sessions
with Maciej Kwiatkowski.
I love the stuntman.
He's amazing.
I call him, his nickname is Washing Machine.
Because you can program him,
and next day you just press the button and it works.
It's crazy.
Muscle memory is just unbelievable.
So this is how the Olga looked like in Maya.
uh... in in motion builder
as a final polished
game loops
as you see
very open position
no, he didn't even use the hard blocks
the cross saber masters
they just parry it
they parry it just to kill you
very offensive style
so it fit
perfectly into his character
We did the same thing with cinematics and dialogues.
We have our own, like, a dialogue system.
And let's talk about Regis and Henrietta now.
So Henrietta, she was a queen of blood and wine.
Yeah, of the Buclair in blood and wine.
So we developed, like...
just custom poses to her, just to make her more queen look like.
Yeah?
And, but she's not a typical queen.
Of course, we made a lot of custom acting choices,
and just to make her more queen-like and feminine.
But at the same time, she had a really high temper.
So...
we need to somehow connect those two worlds,
this high temper and being very noble and queen-like regal.
So here's the part of the cut scene when she is like,
I know probably this advert from Mentos.
So as you see here, she just got angry and she even doesn't want to wait for Geralt.
She gets on the horse and she needs to help her people.
poor guy. And Regis, yeah, he's a vampire so you might think that we could copy Dead
Labs moveset or whatever but he's a completely different guy. And we could even tell that if
they knew physics there he could be a physics teacher.
like check this guy, he's very like static pose, he's a scientist slash biologist vampire,
even his facial expression is very calm and of course there is still his first most important
nature so until he smells blood and you piss him off he is like this but still...
hours. Sent one. Yeah. And the third thing, they're organizing the animation department. So
there's a quality at time boundary.
What we used during the main game
and the first expansion packs,
we used the old OptiTrack system.
And as I said before, the animator was one month banned.
So in the middle of creating expansion packs,
we bought new icons, we extend our area of shoots,
and...
we made Mocap as an independent team.
We've hired a motion capture specialist who helped us a lot
because animators could really focus only on animation then.
So we've been at least getting the clean data from shoots,
from shootings.
So to sum it up,
we did like 50% of the main game animation-wise
in a better quality in half the time.
with deeper and more story-focused characters,
more refined monster designs,
and better overall animation quality.
And like...
Oh, shit.
And I would like to just say one more thing that...
It's, in my opinion, just to really sum it up,
I must say that the most important thing
is always to just try to at least once per week
take a step back and no matter what,
if you are in the middle even of the production,
it's good to try at least,
check the, like a big picture where you are.
Because people, like at least me,
I tend to really skip the basics sometimes and in my opinion like stepping back before
creating the expansion packs and really improving the most important, the crucial, the
fundamental steps at the beginning help us a lot in creating the expansion packs. And
that's it. Thank you.
Thank you, guys.