Hello folks and welcome to GDC 2020 Summer Conference.
This talk is part of the Skill Building Series
and is Pixel Art and Animation in the High Bit Age.
Our host is Tyreek,
noted pixel artist with some sharp looking titles
under his belt.
I am Joel Couture and I will be moderator for this session.
Now Tyreek, here's the floor.
Hello, I am Tyreek Plummer.
I make games.
I have a few goals for this session
because I have a lot of thoughts and feelings
about pixel art and animation in the hybrid age, which
is why I named the talk that.
The first goal is to kind of lay out the role of pixel art in modern games
and define what it means to be in the hybrid age.
The second goal is to provide some examples of contemporary pixel art
that I think are pushing the medium and its aesthetic potential forward.
And the final goal is to give specific technical insight and advice
into how to actually make pixel art with a live demonstration.
But first...
Who am I? I'm a game designer and artist who's been making pixel art since I was a wee lad.
I've done pixel art for a number of games, including Thor DS, Epic Mickey, Power of Illusion, Adventure Time, Explore the Dungeon because I don't know.
Most recently, I've done work on Cadence of Hyrule and UFO 50,
and I've also spent a not insignificant portion of my soul working for an unhealthy number of years on my platformer roguelike, Catacomb Kids.
All of this is to say, I really like pixel art, and I think I'm not terrible at it,
which is about the highest praise I'm willing to afford myself, so that's pretty good.
All that being said, what is high-bit art?
Um, oops, I forget to go forward.
This is Cadence of Hyrule, a game I worked on.
This is Catacomb Kids, my game, my beloved, precious baby.
Um, what is hybrid art?
The term was coined by Simon Anderson, also known as Snake, who is an incredibly skilled
pixel artist and the creator of Owlboy. He coined the term to describe modern pixel art that has
quote pushed beyond the limitations of the old formats and quote operates beyond the limitations
of the old 8, 16, and 30 bit...
32-bit consoles.
When I tell people I do pixel art,
even people within the games industry,
a lot of times they're like,
oh, you mean like 16-bit stuff or like
SNES-type stuff? And increasingly,
these comparisons just don't make
sense anymore because we as pixel
artists aren't confined by the hardware
limitations of those old systems of
16- and 18-bit hardware.
So to say I do that kind of
art would kind of be a lie or a
misnomer.
There's a tendency to think that pixel art immediately equates to nostalgia.
And while that is kind of a large part of its appeal to a lot of people,
I think that to assume that nostalgia is the primary force behind pixel aesthetics
ignores all the work done by pixel artists in the meantime to push the medium forward
in the intervening stretch of time between nostalgia and now.
Like that whole time period existed and pixel artists did too.
And they've been making progress for a long time.
The first thing to understand is that pixel art isn't just a style of art, it's a medium.
And like any medium, it can contain and convey a multitude of styles and aesthetics.
And equally importantly, like any medium, pixel art has continued to evolve alongside
newer technologies and tools in the same way that photography didn't make painting obsolete
but shifted its context.
The computing power that has made high resolution
and complex 3D art in games possible
hasn't made pixel art obsolete,
but it has shifted its context.
So that's the end of the preamble.
With that out of the way,
let's look at some examples of high bit modern art.
And at this point, Joel,
if you have any questions about the particular games
that I'm bringing up, feel free to ask away.
Um, we'll do.
So this is Retro City Rampage.
A lot of so even though I know I just said that nostalgia
isn't the primary driving force behind pixel art, it is still a big part of of
what what people find appealing about it.
And some games, some modern games really play into that
that perception, this being one of them.
Retro City Rampage.
Yeah, it just looks looks old, kind of emulates the aesthetic of old NES games
to evoke those same feelings of the hardware limitations.
I think there's actually even a version of retro city rampage
that will run on an NES, but.
That's not to say that it hasn't taken the lessons that pixel artists have learned and the techniques that they've developed since the time of the NES and incorporated them into their aesthetic as well.
Always Awakening is another example of a modern retro looking game that uses pixel art.
Very much in the sort of Zelda 2 style looking.
Right. UFO 50, which is a game that I'm working on,
is another game that sort of leans into the the perception of pixel art
as having a retro association and aesthetic to it.
So for UFO 50, we're working with a.
Made up restrictions for an imaginary console, essentially,
but.
you know, sometimes we can bend and break those restrictions because we're not actually working
with the hardware, you know, so.
We can we give ourselves a little leeway when it comes to certain aspects of like,
oh, this will just make the game better or make make this more readable or make
this make more sense and that sort of thing.
So there aren't any like like we're roughly following some color color
restrictions and that sort of thing in terms of how many colors per tile we can
use. And we try to keep, you know, sprites.
to a relative minimum because old old hardware had limited sprites per scan
line and that sort of thing, which caused the flickering that that happened.
But we don't really have those limitations.
So they're really self enforced.
And if we don't enforce them, then the game just is what it is.
Another is another UFO 50 game.
So beyond the games that sort of lean into the retro aesthetic,
I think there are also a number of games that sort of display a virtuosic
nature to pixel art, where it's just really dang good.
Just normal pixel art.
Nothing super fancy going on.
This is Hartforth, Alicia, Alicia.
One of those currently in development.
Another sort of long running development game that makes me feel
more at home with Catacomb Kids, which I've been working on for a very long time.
But this is just a really good looking game that just has very good pixel art.
And I think that is another sort of trend of modern pixel art games
is that people have taken the lessons that have been learned over the past
decades of of techniques and
sort of introspection into the medium
and taking them to their natural heights.
More heart for Felicia.
I'm really looking forward to that game.
Iconoclasts would be another example that I would say falls under that category.
It's just it doesn't do a whole lot.
That's extremely fancy.
It's just very good.
And.
You can see that the screen size for this is like significantly larger
than a lot of other pixel art games and the real estate
to match modern displays, so.
That's another trend that's kind of happening to modern pixel art is that the
artists are having to adapt to more modern displays that aren't like, you know,
tiny CRTs or very small, like mobile phone screens and that sort of thing.
So we have a lot more real estate to work with.
And sometimes that can be a challenge because we have more real estate to work
with. You have to work harder to make it interesting and fill it up in ways that
are aesthetically pleasing.
Owlboy, as mentioned, created by the coiner of the term HiBit,
is another example of just virtuosic pixel art.
Very pretty game.
And then we have things that combine pixel art
with other sort of.
medium. So this is Octopath Traveler, which combines pixel art with,
um, 3d. And you can see it does something like combining pixel art with 3d
isn't super new. That's been a thing since, you know, PlayStation one era.
And I think breath of wild four, uh, had a really good look, look about it.
Uh, but you can see this as using a lot more modern techniques,
like using the depths of field to blur the background and a lot of like
really soft lighting effects and kind of a vignetting at the edge of the screen.
That gives it a really unique look and appearance.
The other textures you can see on the in the environment are still pixeled,
which keeps them,
which keeps everything feeling grounded in the same same sort of style.
This is another example, a game in development called Zealot,
which combines pixel art with 3D environments.
And this is a game called The Last Night,
which is also in development.
It looks kind of crazy, but you can definitely see there's there's
pixel pixels happening and.
This is kind of a combination of, I think, like virtuosic talent and,
and, and aesthetic with the extremely modern,
like combination combinations of 3d and depth of field and all the lighting
effects and all that sort of thing. I've never really seen anything like this.
So I'm curious to see how this actually turns out once it's finished.
Um, there's also a game developer named Chloe, uh, also super blizzard on Twitter,
who combines again,
sort of combining the two things of nostalgia and retro aesthetics with,
uh, 3d art. This picture is really tiny. I'm sorry. Hold on.
Let me see if I can make it bigger. There we go. There we go. Um,
Uh, so yeah, like combining 3D with these retro aesthetics and keeping everything
quite chunky.
And I think I think this is a really fun, good look.
More work by the same same developer.
Tyreek, if you don't mind me interrupting,
you've shown quite a bit of flexibility with this style for very different things.
What draws you to continually work in pixel art and to use it in some unique ways?
It's a great question.
I find the limitations
of working in low resolution
kind of conducive to creativity.
Working in lower resolutions
like sort of limits my decision space when it comes to certain things, but at the same time,
as you said, there is a lot of flexibility in it. And so I feel like a lot of times I have to come
up with creative solutions and creative ways to solve visual problems in pixel art that
in other media, there's a little more leeway. And so those restrictions are kind of
harder, not harder to come by. Like you can always make restrictions for yourself,
but I find that the, the particular restrictions of, of, of pixel art are,
are engaging to me in the way that they're forced you to think about the way you
use details and, uh, how to represent, uh,
things in such a small real estate. Um,
and as well, I think that as I'm showing,
like there's still a lot of exploration in the space to be done.
And I want to be a part of that process.
So this is a game still in development called Acid Knife
by the developers of Crawl.
And as you can see, it's got a lot going on
in terms of like, there's a lot of like shader effects
that are kind of melting and blending the world around
in the dark sections.
Like that's not video artifacting,
that's just how the game looks.
Which I find really fascinating is the idea of
taking pixel art and then manipulating it after the fact
with these post-processing effects that still
maintain the aesthetic and stay in the style and resolution of these games.
But while expanding what's what's possible and beyond what
what, you know, could be normally done by just human hands
working on it on single frames of game and that sort of thing.
Another is still shot of the game.
Radio universe.
Radio of the universe is another sort of game that has a lot of post
processing effects and glitchy sort of styling to it.
Also still in development,
a lot of these games are still in development, I guess, I just like games
that aren't out yet, but.
Yeah, I think this is a really good example of a game that just takes the pixel
aesthetic and sort of twists it and like leans really heavily into it
while still being its own completely unique thing.
You can see it looks like went through like a lot of like Photoshop filters and what have you.
There's some chromatic aberration on the numbers where the RGB channels are kind of slightly separated.
A megasphere is, I think, what I would say is another sort of combination of
virtuosic pixel art combined with a lot of like the shader effects and whatnot.
It uses like normal mapping to to use lighting on the actual environment
and characters.
And there's a lot of you can see like there's a lot of like glowing lights
that aren't strictly in.
in the resolution as the sprites and stuff.
And I think this is one of the few games I've seen that does like resolution
mixing in that way really well in a way that isn't detrimental.
So, yeah, I think it looks kind of kind of wild and really good.
More of it.
Carrion is another game that
uses the pixel aesthetic and pixel art,
but combines it with a highly procedurally animated
like main character protagonist.
Kind of hesitant to call it that.
Your big meat blob that goes around killing things and escaping labs
and what have you.
But yeah, you can see like this meat blob is very procedurally animated,
like all the tentacles and such are just kind of whipping and lashing out
in various ways, willy-nilly.
But it's all still within the same sort of lower resolution pixel aesthetic.
And you can also see that the the lighting coming through the windows is is sort of
something that wouldn't have necessarily existed in
older, older hardware and on pixel art games.
a pathway.
Yet another example, I think, of
virtuosic mixing with modern technology, technology.
The as far as I understand it, like the this game has like
a whole lighting engine where basically they combine pixel art with voxels.
So to to make the the tiles and and and elements in the game
have actual volume at volumetric lighting.
which is something I've never seen before and is really fascinating to,
so like all these walls and characters cast actual shadows because they're
technically voxel bodies that just aren't being drawn and instead are being
drawn as pixel art, uh,
which I think is a really clever solution to that. And, uh,
so that's the end of, that's kind of the end of, of that sort of.
uh, look over existing, existing, um,
games that are, they're doing things. There's a lot more out there. There's,
it's by no means a, uh, all encompassing extensive list.
Um,
And yeah, I just wanted to kind of run through a few of those things
before we started getting into the actual practical application
of of the pixels.
So any questions about any of that or what's what's up?
We've got some about, what's your favorite software to use for developing high bit modern art?
Ah, fantastic question and an excellent segue.
So, there are a number of programs that exist for pixel art.
My personal favorite is GraphicsGale.
which is free. It used to not be. It used to be 20 bucks.
And I got it when it was, when it wasn't free, but it's free now. Um,
I like it a lot. I've used it for like a decade over a decade,
which is kind of weird to say, um, that I've been doing this for that long.
Uh, but, um,
you can see it right now because this is, if you want to try to go back to my
screen,
Um, this is a character that I drew a while ago.
Uh, the giraffe Ian, cause he's a giraffe and a ruffian.
Ha ha ha.
I'm proud of that.
Um, and so I was like, ah, I need something to pixel for this thing stream.
So, uh, for this, this talk rather.
Um, so I chose this guy and I made a little tiny sprite of him and this
is what graphic scale looks like.
Um, there are a lot of other, uh, programs, uh, that exist.
Um,
A Sprite is one of them that I know a lot of people use.
It's a more recent one.
I really like the timeline in a Sprite
for like animating and that sort of thing, it's much more akin to,
I think, like a flash timeline, if you're familiar with that.
And it also lets you like separate multiple
different animations without having to have completely separate files for them.
So that's one.
Another one is pixel edit, which I've only used a very little bit of,
but seems really promising.
And I might actually consider transferring to that
if if I put enough work and effort into learning how it works.
It has some neat features like being able to move around
layers in an animated fashion so that you can like animate a face
and then like have it.
stick to the character.
And then if you want to make a change to the face, you'd only have to change one
frame and then it changes on every frame.
It has some really neat features like that.
So pixel edit spelled with a Y P Y X E L.
If you're looking for software that might be one to check out.
Another one.
ProMotion, I've heard, is one that people use.
I've never personally used it, but I've heard it's decent and good
and has been around for quite a while, similar to how GraphicsGale has.
So, yeah, there's a lot of software out there.
GraphicsGale is the one I use just because it's what I'm most familiar with.
Yeah. And I figured if I'm going to be doing this live,
I should use the one, use the program that I'm that I'm quickest in.
So let's do some animating and I can answer some questions if, if, if anybody has them.
Oh, so another more, actually, I have more to say about this.
So I made this, made this draft guy.
Uh, and I was like, Oh yeah, let me just animate this guy.
And then I was like, wait a second.
This is a lot of detail.
I don't know if I can do this in 45 minutes now, around 20.
So, um.
I like simplified the shading and I was like, ah, it's not actually going to help
that much. So we'll see how far I go with this.
But I think one of the one of the important things to understand about pixel
art is that like the lack
and and presence of certain details can really like
make and break a sprite like.
As an example, like.
If I had like a ball about like that big, let's say it.
Let's say like this is my entire sprite, right?
Like I just got like a little ball this big
and I want him to have buttons on his belly, you know, like let's say
let's say this is a little happy face right here.
Um, I think like about pixel art is is the, um,
the fact that you're working with such small resolutions means that the
units of size are like
significant relative to the to the scale of the entire piece.
So like these these buttons here, if I want him to have like a curved belly,
like these buttons, like a single pixel is all I need to get that impression
across. Right. Um.
And so the same applies for these larger sprites
and that sort of thing.
If I come back, if I come back here, you can see like I this is
supposed to be like a little pocket zipper thing that I just kind of
alternated darker and lighter pixels on to get the zipper effect across.
But if I'm going to have to be working on this and animating it, I don't want to
necessarily have to render that every frame.
So I just simplified it to a single line.
There's a lot of anti aliasing around his edges and that sort of thing that if I'm
going to be rendering is going to take time.
it's not going to actually affect the process of animating it
because animation is
like more focused on the actual like present details.
So like if I wanted to make animating him easier,
I would probably get rid of this zipper so that I wouldn't have to have
do the secondary animation on that sort of thing flopping around.
And like, I wouldn't give him shoelaces because that would be another thing to animate.
But I kind of think of animation and rendering as sort of separate processes.
So simplifying this made the rendering process easier,
but the animation process is still going to be roughly,
if I'd say equally as difficult or easy, whatever the case may be.
All right. We do have a couple more questions for someone who's just starting to get into making pixel art.
What courses or YouTube channels can you point us at for learning the basics?
So I know Derek, you had a pixel art tutorial for a long time and he just recently updated it.
I would recommend checking that out.
It's quite a good tutorial.
There are a lot of good tutorials that exist.
I would also recommend checking out or joining a community,
a Pixlr community.
Uh, pixel joint is, is a good one.
Um, it's quite friendly to, to beginners and it has like a whole like gallery,
gallery section to it that you can, um, check out other people's works on and
post your own work on and get critiques and feedback.
And, uh, pixelation is another one, which is, I think at way of the pixel.net,
or if you just Google pixelation forum, it'll pop up.
Um, I know it's not a YouTube channel.
Uh, I don't.
You don't not not super aware of like specific
YouTube channels and video series and that sort of thing that that tutorialize
pixel art as much.
But I found the most valuable thing to be
actually engaging with other pixel artists and.
and getting their feedback and giving them feedback because if you can learn how to critique
something then it'll help you improve yourself by leagues as well.
Um, personally, I also, uh, stream, uh, very often.
I have a Twitch stream that I, that I stream on, uh, it's at a four bit Friday,
um, on Twitch, um, and I usually do programming stuff, but I also
occasionally will, uh, just do pixel art.
And I'm, uh, quite happy to, if you have.
you know, questions, if you stop by there and I'll, you know,
answer them to the best of my ability.
Or if you have work that you want feedback on, I can do that as well.
Or just hit me up on Twitter at 4 Bit Friday.
I'm 4 Bit Friday everywhere.
Do you use a tablet when creating pixel art?
Yes, I do use a tablet.
I used a Wacom Intuos for a while and then it broke after like many years of abuse.
So now I'm currently using a he he he.
Yeah, I don't know how to pronounce it.
It's H-U-I-O-N.
It was way cheaper than Wacom and it works perfectly fine.
Uh, but yes, I do prefer using using tablets for my art in all forms, regardless of whether it's pixel or not.
Although sometimes I will switch to mouse if I'm doing like a really tiny sprite.
But even then, I'll usually sketch it out with a tablet before I like go into the nitty gritty details with a mouse.
And then sometimes I'll be working with a mouse and I'm like, Why am I using this mouse?
I hate using a mouse.
I'm just going to use a tablet.
Oh boy, this isn't I haven't made any progress.
This is going slowly.
All right.
Let's let's see.
Keep them coming.
Are there any types of techniques you find particularly effective or common in
making good high bit pixel wires?
I think.
So I think, um, there are a lot of things that, uh, like in graphics scale
specifically that I really liked that, that sort of, uh, streamline my workflow.
Um,
Uh, so for instance, uh, one thing that I really like to do, if I have something
to outline, uh, let me stop this animation again.
Um, if I have a blob that I need to need to outline, like, let's say this is, you
know, a thing of some sort, let's, yeah, let's make this, let's make this little
happy guy again.
Right.
Um, this guy, he's back.
with his buttons.
Let's say I have to like outline this entire shape.
One thing that I that I find really, really helpful about graphic sales,
it has the color replace tool, which lets me like draw.
Oh, I'm on the wrong layer.
Classic artist problem.
Um, the color replace tool lets me like draw freely without, without,
um, but only, only replacing the color that I have selected to, to replace.
And what that allows me to do in addition to just recoloring things, if I decide I
don't like the color of it is outline things very easily because I can choose
like a large sort of brush size and just go around the edges.
Um.
And that is much faster outlining than having
to place each individual single pixel and that sort of thing.
I'm not sure which other pixel art programs
have the color place tool, but it's probably
one of my most used tools.
Another thing to note might be that if you're
doing.
If you're doing pixel art and you're using it in a game
and it's going to be rotated a lot and that sort of thing,
it's good to note that straight lines,
that is to say lines in one of the four cardinal directions,
rotate much more cleanly than diagonal lines.
So if you're having to rotate any pixel art in a game
and you're keeping it in resolution
and not resolution mixing and that sort of thing,
you can see if I have like this diagonal line
and try to rotate it.
There we go.
It gets real nasty.
You see, it gets like if I even if I just rotate it to a cardinal direction,
it gets real, real, real grody and just kind of like all it breaks up
and that sort of thing.
But if you have straight lines,
they tend to keep keep their form a lot better.
Like you can see the the
the sides of them aren't like breaking up, even if I make this one one thick.
A single single line thick.
So yeah, I'd say like, keep, keep, keep your, uh,
if you have stuff to rotate, try and keep it cardinal by default, um,
as much as possible. Um,
yeah, that, that, that helps a lot to keep, to keep things looking,
looking much cleaner. Um,
Yeah, there's a lot like that.
That's those sorts of things are the kind of thing that you kind of like
have to pay attention to, especially when you're working in pixel art,
if you want it to look good throughout these like all these transformations
and things that are becoming more common in in modern games
that use pixel aesthetics and that sort of thing.
I'm sure I could probably think of more.
I will try to keep thinking of of those sorts of like little details
and mention them if I can remember whenever I can.
Alright, when creating a character for a pixel art game, do you normally go straight into
creating pixel sprites or do you create your concepts in a different medium and then translate
it into pixel art?
It depends on the game and the style
for larger sprites like and in higher resolutions,
I'll usually try to do a larger, higher resolution concept beforehand.
For smaller sprites, I will usually just jump straight into
straight into doing it as as pixel art.
Yeah, that's about it.
And also, usually, more often than not,
I will just jump straight into the pixel art aspect of it
before concepting anything else.
And if I'm struggling with it, then I
might go back to the concept phase and be like,
oh, this needs work and solving.
All right, another question.
What dartboard size do you use slash how do you
know how to scale properly?
What what board size?
It says dartboard dartboard.
Do they mean artboard?
Probably. OK.
Again, so this is something that comes down to,
is this going to be on a game by game basis?
I'm hesitant to like just make generalizations about like what's good
and what's bad and what's best and all that sort of thing,
because it's going to vary so much from game to game
and from from project to project.
I kind of.
oscillate between enjoying working in really large sizes,
like relative to pixel art, like 128 by 128, 96 by 96.
I really liked those sizes. Um, and, uh, really, uh,
really tiny, like 16 by 16, uh, eight by eight.
It's kind of annoying, but, but, uh, I, I,
I oscillate between enjoying like working in the various sizes cause they offer
different, uh, challenges and different, um,
opportunities and sort of just senses of finality
and of what the finished thing is going to be.
They're both fun.
Yeah.
Alright, here's one. I have a question not related to the games themselves.
What are your thoughts on pixel art content in the corporate slash commercial space through
brand activation combined with IP? Wow, that's a fun question.
repeat that. Sure alright. What are your thoughts on pixel art
content in the corporate slash commercial space through brand
activation combined with IP? I think I see what you're saying
so like like in terms of pixel art used outside of the context
of games as just like an aesthetic for advertising that
sort of thing. I assume that's what you're talking about.
I mean, it's fine.
It's like I said, pixel art isn't necessarily a style.
It's a medium and it's a valid medium
for advertising your stuff if you wanna.
I actually was hired a few years ago to...
This is kind of annoying, actually.
I was hired a few years ago to not work on a game, but to work on a credit card
like they wanted to design for their credit card that was pixel art.
And I made a piece that I thought was really good and fun and, you know, charming.
And they hated it and made me make some really just banal, boring.
nonsense that I absolutely hated working on.
So in that sense, I'm not a huge fan of those sorts of things,
but they did pay me eventually.
I had to hound them for a while, but
that's that's not a great story. I'm sorry. But.
So in that sense, like I didn't like working with that particular company,
but like if you want to advertise your stuff in whatever style like that's fine.
I don't I'm not going to tell you to stop or whatever.
But I wouldn't do it again.
I feel like that's I feel like the nature of that experience is probably more
indicative of just being an artist in corporate culture as opposed to
necessarily being a pixel artist in that particular, you know,
in, in, in any kind of corporate culture and that sort of thing.
All right. How does working at pixel art differ from other visual mediums?
Um,
Well, I think there's a
there's some misconceptions about pixel art that it's easier,
specifically from gamers, I think, not necessarily from other game developers.
But I see a lot of times like, you know,
sometimes like gamers will be like, Oh, this game is pixel art.
This cheap, they didn't have a budget for like real art or whatever.
And I'm like, I forget you.
That's not the case at all.
Like pixel art is not easier or cheaper necessarily than any other type of art.
It's can sometimes be quite a lot more time
consuming than just drawing something at high resolution.
But also a lot of times people ask me, like, like, oh, how do you do shading or
how do you do, how do you pick colors and pixel art and that sort of thing?
And that's always been kind of a strange question to me because it's like you
shade like you would anything like it's just shading, like light, the way light
works doesn't change when you move into pixel art suddenly.
and the way color theory and, and, and, you know,
composition and that sort of thing doesn't suddenly change, uh,
when you move into pixel art. So a lot of there's,
there are a lot of differences,
but there are also a lot of similarities and overlap. And I feel like a lot of,
what, uh,
what makes pixel art sort of special and specific is the fact that,
like I was showing with the buttons earlier and like, like on,
especially this is a bad example because this sprite is right.
It's so large, but especially on smaller sprites, um,
the, um,
a single pixel can make such a huge difference. Um,
And that's like just a single decision you can make.
And I feel like a lot of a lot of other art media
don't really have that kind of just strict binary of like,
here's a single decision I can make that changes one single pixel in this picture
and completely changes the meaning of the entire thing.
I feel like that's kind of what the core of pixel art comes down to
is just like having those sorts of moments where it's like, oh,
I'm going to put this pixel here, and it's
going to mean this whole slew of things
for the rest of the image.
And I think another sort of thing about pixel art
is that it can be used to abstract.
Um, so like a lot of if you think of like a lot of like the older games
that use pixel art and that sort of thing, like especially in NES
and those sorts of things, a lot of the character designs,
the iconic character designs are were like.
in sprite form, just like super abstract and like, is that a nose?
Is that a mustache? That sort of thing.
That's something that I feel like, you know, can still be leveraged
in art today and leaving things up to the player or viewer's mind
of just like, I don't know what I'm looking at, so I'm just going to fill in
the blanks and probably whatever I think of is maybe going to end up
being a lot cooler than.
whatever was intended, maybe not what was intended, but like what, what,
what the artists could have executed on their particular timeframe and
budget and that sort of thing. Uh,
which I think is a pretty,
pretty fun thing to play around with is mess like playing around with those
spaces of abstraction and, uh,
deliberately making certain details kind of obtuse so that people
don't really know what exactly they're looking at and can fill in the blanks
themselves.
All right, next question.
How do I make my pixel art look good
if I am not otherwise an artist?
Practice.
It's the same answer as any kind of art or endeavor
that you want to be good at.
I will say though,
and this goes for not just pixel art,
but for all art in general,
I feel like
How do I how do I phrase this?
I feel like you can get away with a lot as long as you're consistent.
And that's why that's.
Like. A game
with art that is bad
in all the same way,
I think is visually compelling.
as compared to a game with art that is sometimes bad and sometimes good,
because to me,
to me, it kind of comes down to like a sense of intentionality.
And I feel like if.
Art is, you know, mostly good, but then sometimes bad.
The bad art is going to feel really unintentional
and it's going to make the whole thing feel worse to me.
This is just my personal feelings.
But if everything is equally bad, then it's going to be like,
oh, they knew what they were doing.
You know, they meant to do all this stuff wrong.
Sorry, that didn't answer the question at all.
The answer to the question is practice and
Do it, do it, do it a lot, make, make a bunch of stuff, study,
study art that you like, pixel art that you like.
Looking examples of of of games that you that you like
would like to approach the style and quality of and see what they do
and how they do it.
It's the like I said, it's the same the same set of steps
for learning any kind of art or craft is.
Just practice and practice and study it.
Yeah.
Here's possibly a lighter one.
Do you ever dream in pixels?
I don't know that I dream in
pixels necessarily, but I've definitely dreamed
in games that were pixeled.
Um, like I've never, I've never had a dream that was like, uh, oh, I'm going
through like a real life situation now, but everything's pixel art.
It's always been like, oh, I'm dreaming.
I'm in this really cool game.
And I dreamt, I dreamt once that I made the best game in the world and it got put
in a museum and it was really amazing.
And then I woke up and couldn't remember what the game was.
And I was really sad about that one.
Uh,
Yeah. All right.
Another question.
When hiring a pixel artist, what should we expect to pay?
Personally, I tend to charge
between 40 and 50 dollars an hour
for. Pixel art stuff.
that's just sort of like my baseline and any like compensation
that I do that's below that.
I try to make sure it's of at least that value. Um,
it depends on the artists though. Uh, I know some, some,
some artists who will charge like 60 an hour. Uh,
I know a lot of artists who greatly undercharge, um,
and that's not cool. Uh, so yeah,
I would say like, just try and try and,
Compensate them fairly.
Like I said, I usually try and be around 40 to 50 an hour, which is honestly
probably a little low, lower than I should be, but it's, uh, it's, it's, it's,
it's where I'm at.
I, I'll probably ask for more eventually, but I'll, I'll get there.
Um, yeah.
All right.
I believe we have time for one more.
I didn't get anywhere with this guy, man.
I'm sorry about that.
I was I was I was having such high, high expectations of myself.
I was like, oh, yeah, I'm going to have like a whole
rough of this guy's swing and follow through and everything.
And it's just not happening.
He's still winding up.
All right, well, let's see, we can squeeze the last one in.
Yeah.
What kinds of games might benefit most from a pixel aesthetic?
Um, well, obviously there's, uh, as I mentioned, kind of a nostalgia factor.
So like, if you want to play into that, then you can definitely, uh, use that.
And.
And that sort of thing.
Um, but I feel like a lot of younger people never really experienced the era of
gaming when pixel art was a necessary hardware restriction.
Uh, so they have kind of a different context for, uh.
for the for their, you know, their.
Their experience of pixel art,
which is maybe more akin to like, you know, kids,
you know, liking really liking music from the 80s and that sort of thing
when they were like or like like synth wave and that sort of thing,
or it's like 80s aesthetic, but sort of completely disconnected
from from the experienced
time frame.
So like you can you can.
Play into that and that sort of thing.
But even even even aside from, you know, the whole historical aspect
of pixel art and its place in, you know, gaming, gaming aesthetic,
I think pixel art can be used to communicate things about the game itself,
like you might be able to use pixel art to communicate like, oh, some
this game is.
kind of a purity of design, I think,
can be communicated via pixel art,
where like you look at, you know, some 3D game
and you're like, oh, I don't really know how to play that.
It looks fun, but I don't know what's happening necessarily.
But I feel like sometimes you can look at like
a pixel art game and be like,
I can kind of tell what's going on here.
You know, it, it, it's, I think the,
the nature of pixel art and the way it sort of enforces a,
a simplification of design and, uh, and, and, uh,
visual elements also tends to lend itself well to, uh,
being quickly readable, uh, and, and, and, um,
And especially if you if you use the because Pixel has like the sort of built
in visual language of the entire history of video games in it.
Like, you know, like if you see like a photorealistic
3D game, then you're.
your comparisons might be closer to like, oh, this looks kind of like a movie.
But if you see a pixel art image of anything,
you're going to have the association with video games and you can leverage that to
communicate certain video game
tropes and language in terms of like, oh, this is a platformer.
This is, you know, shoot him up and that sort of thing.
So, yeah, I think that that's kind of a way to use the you that you can maybe use
pixel art if you're not explicitly tapping into the
like remembered history of of of the style
of the medium and that sort of thing.
Yeah, maybe that.
All right, take with that, we're out of time.
OK, I got I got two and a half frames done.
Nope, not even done.
Thanks.
All right.
Thank you all for coming out.
Again, this is Tyreek Plummer, and thanks again for attending.