I'm going to get really close to a grown man, talk about stickers for an hour.
My name is Rob Davio.
I've been a game designer for 18 years, board game designer professionally most of that
time with Hasbro.
I'll get into that a little bit as we go.
And out of all the games I've done,
and I don't have an exact count,
but I've done 70 or 80 games in various forms
over those 18 years, nothing has quite resonated
more than the three games that I put out,
Risk Legacy, Pandemic Legacy, and Seafall.
And I couldn't figure out why,
and I'm still not sure I figured out why,
but I'm gonna give an attempt today
to talk about why these games
have sort of caught on how they have,
why they are controversial.
where they might go from here.
I'm gonna talk for 35 to 45 minutes
and then we'll take questions from people here.
But before I begin, I just wanted to kind of get a sense
of what you're looking for in the talk.
So who has played a Legacy game here?
All right, so most of you.
I will keep it spoiler free for those of you who haven't.
It's just second nature now.
It's like some sort of deep training, if you want.
I'm an operative.
I just maintain cover the entire time.
Who is thinking of designing a Legacy game?
OK, a few brave souls out there.
So I'll give some tips on what I've learned and what I do now
when I approach new ones, because I have one that's
coming out later this year, and I'm working on three other
ones right now.
So just to give a little background of where I am
and what I'm doing and to kind of warm up
with some shameless plugs.
I do non-legacy stuff.
I know it's a big surprise to many people
and I have some games coming out later this year
or early next year.
I've got a game based on the Lock and Key comic book,
a game in the middle based on
Mountains of Madness by Lovecraft.
That one's a little different because I think
it's really boring when the characters get to go insane
but the players don't, so I tried to.
I tried to change that for this one.
And then a game for the Titans of Gaming,
which is about opposite from a legacy game
in my usual work, as you can do.
I'm also the chief restoration officer
in a new game company called Restoration Games,
where we take old, out-of-print games
and restore them and put them back in print.
And this is our first year's line
that we're just finishing up right now,
and they'll be out later this year.
So, Stop Thief from 1979.
uh... indulgence in down force a renamed from the game called dragon master and a
game called top race
uh... so that's fun so sometimes i'm just mining the ball for
old ideas
and bring them back but what i'm really gonna talk about
today is
covenants
and
i had a ton of really bad are for the covenant
jokes
uh... that i'm not going to get into
and you're welcome for that because when I woke up this morning I realized how awful
they were. They were so clever when I wrote them, like awful clever, but they're not clever
whatsoever. And by covenants I mean nothing legal, nothing binding, nothing biblical,
but almost every human interaction, especially when you're dealing with strangers, has some
sort of underlying covenant.
you don't expect the cook to poison your food at a restaurant, you don't expect to be punched in the face when you buy coffee or walk down the street, right?
Some things are illegal, and then there's some things that are just sort of culturally inappropriate and vary from culture to culture,
and it's no different as a game designer, I realize, that when you make a game as a game designer,
you have a covenant with the players and there are certain expectations that are sort of unspoken and perhaps even unknown to both parties
that you are agreeing to.
to deal with and basically be beholden to.
What I realize is that legacy games are disruptive in a way
and controversial because when I came up with the idea,
I accidentally broke a number of these covenants,
which makes it sort of exhilarating in one sense
and off-putting in another to some people
who don't want them broken.
This is the same thing.
and I'm not comparing myself to him or his success,
but that George R. R. Martin did with Game of Thrones,
which is there is a covenant that the main character
cannot be really killed, just set back.
And he made a pretty good point of saying
he could abuse that main notion,
and he did it so that the reader would always be nervous
and care more about every character
because no one was truly safe.
So I think sometimes, you know,
if you're designing something creative
and you're designing something new,
if at all possible, and I don't know how possible this is
because this is me looking back eight years later
and spending a lot of time thinking about it,
being able to identify covenants
between the person that you're designing something for
and yourself and figuring out if these are actual covenants
that are inviolate and need to be maintained
or if it's something that's just a cultural shorthand
that can be broken or otherwise manipulated.
That's about as heady as we're going to get in this.
After this, we're going to talk about games and stickers.
So what path led me to deciding one day that it was going to be
really fun to make a game that you write on and that you rip
up cards for?
So it all starts in the 70s.
That's not exactly me, but it might as well be me.
Everyone was blonde, and the world was orange from the
friction from the corduroy or something like that that was
going on.
So I grew up.
I grew up in the 70s.
And then when I got to about 1980, I discovered D&D, which
is storytelling.
One game leads to another.
And I got so good at it, I moved on to advanced D&D.
So that's why I get to be up here,
because I became advanced.
And so whole new things changed there.
D&D remains a through line through a lot of my designs
and a lot of my thinking.
And when I was 12 years old, I played a lot of it.
When people ask me now, what's your favorite game?
I say, it's very simple.
It's playing first edition D&D with my friends
and my brothers when I'm 12.
But I don't get to do that anymore.
But it's maintained and the idea of getting up one morning and then saying like,
where were we yesterday?
What was happening?
And then something happens and then a character dies or you lose something,
you get that bad die roll and you fudge it all the time in D&D.
But in general, you get this sense of things have just moved forward and
you're just picking up where you left off.
So that's always been in my mind.
And I discovered D&D when I was at camp at age 12.
And at the same time, because I didn't really want to go away to camp,
my parents let me bring my first comic books.
That was the exact one that I, well, not the exact one.
It's a picture of the exact one that I got to bring with me.
And again, this also, this episodic storytelling,
what happens in the next chapter.
And it's not uncommon.
It's television.
It's comic books.
It's serialized novels of the 19th century.
But the idea is.
pick up where you left off. And then, you know, I went through and I played a ton of
I played a ton of Infocom games. I still get nostalgia seeing that blue on cyan screen.
Like, that's like, why isn't this still the default user interface in the world? Nothing
has been improved upon since that. So I played a lot of those games. And then, let's see
if anyone, I did, had two deep nerd cuts I wanted to bring up. I was a member of the
Star Wars fan club and got Bantha Tracks magazine delivered to me.
which got me so hyped for Empire Strikes Back
because I was seven to 10 reading a quarterly, I think,
fan news magazine, they're sending pictures,
and I was out of my mind, like only a kid could be,
and then somehow the movie was better.
So I also will maintain that that is the best movie
ever made because it was for me.
And on the right is something called
Adventure Construction Kit.
Has anyone seen this or played with it?
Couple people?
Oh wow, of course, I'm at the GDC.
This was something put out 1985, 84, 86,
which basically let you create your own little world.
And you had characters and you could set different genres
and write dialogues and walk around
and open chess and do stuff.
And I played around and I sort of fell in love
with the theory of it.
I think in the reality, either I was using it wrong
or they were missing one vital point,
which is when you play tested it
and kind of move people around and did things,
when you wanted to reset it,
you had to go manually put everything back.
You couldn't just be like, let's reset.
And so you test them, like this is great.
Move this guy back, put that in the chest, lock this door.
So I never really moved on.
So these are some of the things that formulated my life
as a kid, and I never thought for a moment
it would lead to anything professional.
When I grew up at age 28,
I became a professional game designer,
which still seems, even though it is a ton of work,
it seems in some way like it can't actually be
what I've been doing for a living.
I mean, my career is old enough to vote and smoke,
so it should feel normal right now.
Along the line, a couple games that I worked on,
Risk 2210 AD, which started to talk about
making bigger games and factions
and working with an engine already,
in this case, the Risk engine to do more.
interesting things and you know that's part of the thread that would lead to
Risk Legacy.
I was one of the three people
who all claim 70 percent of the design work on Betrayal at House on the Hill
which is probably fair because it's a big game.
And then I think the math holds.
I was not the original inventor on that,
but I worked on it for about a year and a half at Hasbro,
some sort of either second designer or developer,
there's really no word for it.
But I kind of fell in love with the fact
that you start a game
and then it goes in an unexpected direction.
Like you're halfway and like, you got surprised by the game.
You literally don't know when you're starting the game,
what's going to happen or even how to win.
So the idea that a game can sort of come out
and surprise you while you're playing it
was something I inherited from the inventor of this
and get to spend a lot of time with
and sort of internalized.
I was one of the designers on HeroScape.
So then again, like narrative storytelling
and campaign development,
and I'm still really proud of this game.
The fact that we sold it as,
take your toy box and shake it out onto your Lego set
and then you've got a game.
Unfortunately, the price of plastic is tied into the price of petroleum, and from when
we conceived the idea until like five years later, it became sort of cost ineffective
to me.
But the one game that I think is the direct predecessor to the legacy idea is something
that most people don't even know of and would be very surprised to find out what it is,
which is Lord of the Rings Trivial Pursuit DVD.
I'm sorry, Trivial Pursuit Lord of the Rings DVD, the Trivial Pursuit brand comes first.
This was something I worked on.
I worked on a number of DVD games
in the middle of last decade.
If you think you have restrictions
in the code you have to work with,
DVDs were a whole other exciting world.
There was no real standard to them.
Different DVD players would make different calls
to different code at however they wanted to do it
because most of the time you put it in
and you played a movie.
But this was a fad and this was a thing
and Hasbro jumped on board
and I did a number of things with it.
And what I did with Lord of the Rings, I was doing a lot of work with Trivial Pursuit at the time,
is, Trivial Pursuit is a box of cards,
and you take out a card and you read it. I don't know why I'm telling you this, you kind of understand how that works.
But there's something interesting about themed trivia.
Themed trivia, the person buying this
probably knows Lord of the Rings.
You wouldn't buy it for them
or you wouldn't buy it for yourself
unless you had an interest in Lord of the Rings.
But that person playing a trivia game
is probably with people who don't know
as much as they do about Lord of the Rings.
So you have a dilemma as a designer,
which is do you write easy questions
or do you write hard questions?
Because either way, you're alienating
about half of your audience
who's likely to be playing this.
So what you usually end up doing is doing a mix of both,
and then you put it in a card box,
and you randomly draw it out.
And you get a question, and now again,
you've got a 50% chance of the person who's good at it
getting some really obvious question,
and the person who's not good at it
getting some ludicrous question,
and they both feel frustrated by the experience.
So I had what I thought was a clever idea.
of on the DVD, sort of turning the box of cards,
which is randomly shuffled into something,
and this is an analog version,
which is a more controlled experience.
So there are different pre-programmed games on the DVD,
and game one starts in the Shire
and contains very easy questions in game...
15 or 18 was on Mount Doom and contained all hard questions so you could, as a group, decide
how you were going to play and which level you were going to play in.
It essentially took the random box of cards and just sorted it from easy to hard.
People lost their shit because I made a consumable game that had an end.
Amazon reviews were difficult.
When you're done, you're done.
You can't go back and replay it.
The fact that a box of cards has the same number
of questions, but I just sort them in order,
was an argument that I couldn't make.
Because the box is perceived to be infinitely replayable,
and there's this weird psychological thing
where if you draw out a question you've had before,
you just go, I've had that before,
and you read another one,
because you just don't know.
Somewhere in that box is a magic new question
that you haven't found before.
So it was weird, because I'm thinking, Hasbro had researched this.
So it was an active game family plays like twice a year.
So that box can last a long time.
And this DVD can last a long time.
And I thought I had done something very interesting
to make a better user experience.
But what I realized is that perceived infinite replay is highly valued.
in the board game. So I'm going to talk about a lot of covenants and a lot of assumptions
right now and they all apply to board games. I realize that a lot of these don't apply
to digital games and I stole or I guess borrowed or was inspired by a lot of digital pieces
when I was porting them over to the analog world. So somehow infinite replay was highly
valued.
And what I had done is I had broken a covenant that I didn't even realize, and I don't think anyone realizes existed,
which is the player of the board game decides how much a game is played.
And that's always been the case.
When you buy a board game, it is up to you to decide how long
that game is played.
It is not up to me as a designer.
And what I had done is I had taken away sort of a
fundamental agreement from the players that said, no, no,
this is my decision.
This is my decision now.
I'm deciding how much you play.
And even though it was basically more than they would
ever play and gave them a better experience when they
played, I had accidentally violated this covenant of who
gets to make this decision.
And that is something that continues
with the Legacy game series.
Not really getting into what the legacy is,
but I guess I'll take a quick brief thing.
I assume if you're here, you know how they play,
but I guess for 30 seconds, I'll say some of the actions
you take place in one game,
carry forward into the next game.
That's wrapped up within a narrative
that has emergent content through packets and envelopes.
And then at the end of this campaign,
the game is either completely finished
in the case of a pandemic or sort of stabilizes
and you can play it in its final state
in the case of Risk Legacy and Seafall.
But some reason this covenant, I took it away.
Even yesterday on a different panel I did
on pandemic legacy, one of the questions at the end,
someone said, well, yeah,
given that you can only play it once.
And it was sort of like this lead thing,
and I don't think it meant to be confrontational,
but when you hear that for about eight years running,
it gets confrontational.
And I said, well, hold on,
you get to play it about 16 or 18 times,
and instead of being something
where you can only play it 16 or 18 times,
I've given you a reason to play it 16 or 18 times.
But that's a very interesting argument
because it's very emotional
because it's about this covenant.
If you took something away, that's my choice.
And you can do it at a restaurant, well,
you can do it at restaurants now,
like oh, just whatever the chef wants,
or give me the tasting menu and I'm not gonna pick,
but you can still see what's coming,
and you can opt out, or not go to the restaurant
or something like that.
So it's interesting of whether the creator
gets to decide how much they decide versus the end user.
And so I thought about it.
I realized that people really want games
to be like Groundhog Day.
They want to start in the same place
when they wake up in the morning,
and they want to make little different choices
in their day to see where it ends,
and they want to do it as much as possible.
Do they want to save the,
who is it, the kid who falls out of the tree?
Do they want to, you know, and,
but Groundhog's Day is this sort of analogy
in that the main character does mature and learn
and go on and know things different.
People really like the conception of a board game
being in their control and that there's these safe parameters
around what they can do, which led
me to think about different experiences,
different creative experiences if you're a consuming
narrative.
for the most part, or you're consuming something.
Some things are very repeatable,
and when you repeat them, they're exactly the same thing,
and some things are more experiential,
which is like when you do it, you're done,
and you can't do it again,
or you can't do it exactly the same way.
And sort of the traditional ones,
and this is deliberately off-center,
is there's a movie, and then you see the movie again,
and it's the movie, and then there's a book,
and there's music, and when you put on Sergeant Pepper,
you're going to get the same songs in the same order.
And no one's upset about this.
In games, people want them to be largely repeatable,
but I moved the letter E over the line to be like,
but I want to experience it in a different way.
I want to come in at different angles and play with it,
but I want it to be a repeatable experience.
But almost all of these things
which are traditionally repeatable
also have sort of an experiential equivalent.
So instead of going to a movie,
which granted, it's repeatable now
that you can just get it into your home
or you can own it 50 years ago, it's different.
But if you go to see a play,
which is a lot like a movie.
It's gonna be different every time.
You buy a ticket, depends like who the actors are,
an understudy or what choices they made
or what theater it in.
And even if you see the exact same people do it
three nights in a row,
it's going to have these little nuances.
And if you don't like the play in the middle,
you can leave, but you don't get your money back
from your ticket and no one else can come in
and take where you left off.
you know if you want to see it again you gotta buy a new ticket.
It's the same thing with a concert, which is a musical equivalent to theater.
And you know for books there are coloring books and there are crossword puzzles and
no one gets mad when they go back to their coloring book that they colored in and
they're like, God, you used up, like this.
This is ridiculous.
My other book isn't used up, but this one is.
These had these sort of alternate versions
where you could experience them one and manipulate them
and then be done.
But the board game world didn't really have this equivalent.
And I'd like to say that I really sat down
and thought this all through at the time.
But again, this is looking back over years
of sort of unconscious thinking made conscious.
Now, there's one flip side that I just sort of made an analogy to,
and I put this out as a design challenge to all of you
that I hope no one takes me up on it,
which is food is a consumable experience,
and no one has made a repeatable food experience yet.
So it can go the other way.
So that's an open space, free for you to design in,
however you like.
So some years pass and just circumstances,
and I've talked about this a lot in other talks and things,
so I'll kind of gloss over here
because I'm trying not to duplicate
from other things you can find me talking about online.
There was this brainstorm where we were talking about Clue,
and there was this big moment where I made a joke,
as I like to do in corporate meetings,
where I said, I don't know why they keep inviting
these people back to dinner every night.
They always kill someone.
And everyone's like, ha ha ha.
And I was like, oh, wait a minute, wait a minute.
And I said, well, what if the game didn't reset?
What if it really was Tuesday after Monday
and we knew that mustard killed someone?
And my boss, who's a big game designer and things,
kind of gave me this like, oh, like we had this look,
like, well, that might be something.
And then everyone else was like,
oh, that was a good joke about dinner.
So I kind of put it off to the side.
And then I, you know, I realized,
okay, I had found that thing.
I found a thing where you play a game and then the next day the game's kind of like,
it's the next day.
It's, we're used to that.
We go to bed and we wake up, it's the next day.
Like this is not a radical thought for any place except this gaming space.
And I got excited about that.
And I'm like, well...
what really makes it the next day,
like when, what actions and consequences and things,
and how does this work?
And started playing around,
and I came up with something,
I realized what everyone's gonna do is one of two things.
It's either they're going to start playing,
and they're gonna be playing Clue,
and I had this, it was called Clue, the usual suspects,
and you're getting grudges and enemies,
and you need a little rap sheet,
like in your world it's mustard,
in your world it's peacock,
and there's a couple of things that are gonna happen.
One, people are gonna get to the point
where they don't like a decision
they made a couple of games ago,
and they're going to rewind it.
they're going to be like, nope, revert to save.
Okay, here's before I got the merchant mad
and then I had the people chasing me in Skyrim,
so I'm gonna just back up to there.
Because that's what you wanna do.
You wanna control your experience
so that you're always the hero of the story
or the villain or whatever.
You wanna be able to choose that
and you wanna be able to manipulate that
and most games give you the ability to do that.
And that felt like cheating a bit to me.
And then I also realized, to be very selfish, is if...
How are you gonna track this?
How are you gonna get up and play a game?
I remember if you're playing twice a year or something,
even if it was a couple weeks,
and you're like, what happened?
And there was gonna be tokens and bags and markers,
and you would have to have this...
very elaborate craft project about how this all goes together.
I'm like, if you just kind of wrote on it and put a sticker on it,
then it's just done and you don't have to worry about it coming apart.
So part of this whole permanent was to prevent cheating,
but a large part of it was to make my job easier and to make the game,
which I thought at the time was going to be like 10-year-olds playing Clue,
easier to manage.
And so then you get this idea of permanent change.
Now, the game doesn't tell you to burn things,
but some people are very, very excited about
the fact that they can finally abuse a game component.
Cause we don't, don't touch that,
and don't eat your chips near it,
and sleeve that, and don't rifle shuffle this thing.
And it's just like, they're so precious
when they're really pieces of cardboard.
Which I recognize, and I don't like take a game
and step on it just to prove a point and things like that.
Like I take care of my games as well.
There was a nice release.
for doing this. And this comes back, remember I talked about comic books, that was one of
the things I collected. And I put them in backs and sleeves because this was going to
be my retirement fund in the 80s. Everyone's going to want, you know, the silver Wolverine
cover or whatever it is. And then I bought some, basically they were just fall off the
back of a van comic books off a scruffy guy in New York City right after I graduated from
college. It was literally like, hey man, you want some comics?
10 bucks. And I'm like, sure, here you go.
And they were already beat up.
And I brought them back to my little New York apartment
and I threw them everywhere and I stepped on them.
And it was this release of not having to take care of something.
And it was really freeing.
So that was in my mind when I thought of this.
So this has been probably,
especially the destruction of components,
the biggest sticking point on a lot of these legacy games.
A lot of people are very, very happy
to go along with everything except that.
And if you've only tangentially heard of it,
a lot of times it's like,
oh, that game where you rip up a card.
Cause it's just feels wrong.
So I realized that there's a second covenant
that comes to board games
and that they allow for consequence-free exploration.
The whole point of a board game is probably most of us
really don't want to fight a war,
or necessarily crush our enemies into the ground economically,
or be hunted by a serial killer, or a number of things
that games can explore.
Probably most of us also don't want to be bean farmers,
for different reasons.
So the theme of a game, it lets you basically
try things that are conservative or radical.
or just different, but the idea is that, you know,
at the end of the game, it all goes back in the box
and it didn't happen.
So there's this covenant that you can play on,
but this is kind of, there's a very, very other big,
big, very successful branch of gaming called casinos.
which play upon the exact opposite,
which is the thrill of making it matter.
So one of the thing I thought about is like,
well, poker's a very, very bad game
unless you have stakes in the game
that hurt just enough that you don't wanna lose them.
You know, it's a game about money played with people
that happens to have cards on the table.
And so I was like, can we kinda take some of this,
can we break this covenant?
Again, it wasn't this conscious.
And basically say, let's try it.
let's put some skin in the game.
Here's a card, rip it up.
Here's a decision you make.
You can't take that decision back.
Does that get the blood going or does it make people mad?
And I don't really have an answer,
but it was sort of exciting enough to give it a try.
So I present all this stuff to Hasbro for Clue
and they looked at me like I had lost my mind,
which is fair.
So it went away again for like another year or six months.
And then we're thinking about things doing for risk
and
And I was like, well, you know, that idea might work for risks.
And my boss and I talked, I was like, I think you should give it a try.
And it was one of many things we were going to do with risk and really kind of
dug into it and decided to start designing what became risk legacy.
Permanent change, putting stuff on the board, building factions, games,
carrying to the next.
And so without getting too much into the like the nitty gritty design,
you can ask about it after if you want more details.
Yeah, the tension was there.
People were really nervous about what's going to happen next and don't ruin this and oh
this happened in the game and it's going to be there and it was sort of like hitting all
these notes that I was hoping it would.
Then something magical happened which is cliffhangers.
Come back next week and see what happens.
It's like you get to the end of the game and people were like...
I wanna play this again
cause I wanna see what happens next.
And it was this, oh, there's a reason
that you wanna play the game again.
The game finally spoke up and said,
here's a reason not to put me back in the closet.
Total accident.
But I was like, let's mine this for where it's worth.
And then what happened with Risk Legacy is
I just decided I was gonna give up most rational thought
of what a game was supposed to do.
And just any crazy idea I had, I put in there
and we'll get to this craziest one in a little bit
that you probably know about.
So an interesting side effect is that games,
all games, almost all life experiences, you have the sense of
I don't know what I'm doing and then you have to gain mastery and there's this
thrill of learning how to play a game and Eric Lang mentioned this yesterday on a
different panel, he's
another game designer, that some of the most exciting parts of a game are
the end of the first game into like game three or four where you know what's
going on but you don't know how to do it well.
And then everyone reaches a point where you've gained mastery and now you're sort of getting
into like secondary and tertiary strategies and it's like comfort food.
But a lot of people, and part of the reason people don't go back to games again and again
and again, especially now in the board game world, is you want to get that sort of hit
of the new and learned mastery.
And this is Fischer random chess.
Bobby Fischer came up with, I'm not a chess expert,
I'm not an expert on this,
but he scrambles the pieces in the back row.
So there's certain rules.
The king is always between the rooks,
black mirrors white, and there's a black and white bishop.
Well, now you're in the mid-game from the first turn.
You've just taken away the mastery
of learning the opening moves to chess
because there is no more opening moves.
So it tests chess skill instead of chess knowledge.
And I thought, wow, if we just keep changing this game,
we can kind of duplicate some of this
and keep people in that first couple games,
the entire experience that they're playing.
So part of this is preventing people
from ever feeling like they know how to play
because whatever they did in the last game,
it's only 90% relevant to this game.
And so that was a kind of fun thing.
But then I made mistakes.
And the big mistake I made was everything was sort of random.
Now, risk, I'm assuming most people here have played risk,
and most people here don't play risk anymore.
Risk is, in some sense, sort of like this Skinner box
experience of how well people psychologically handle
the edge of the bell curve.
It's like there's no reason why you should have just lost all those troops, but you did.
And so one of the things I had was, you know, like you roll three sixes when you're attacking
and the area is destroyed in a giant nuclear devastation.
And that sounded really cool because every die roll was tense.
Well, as a designer, I'd given up way too much control.
That could happen the very first roll of the game.
It might never happen.
It might happen on the last roll or the same.
Like there was just not enough control
over when this happened.
And I realized if you're gonna ask people
to make permanent changes in a game,
they should be the ones doing it.
And that's one of the things
that I've put in all the legacy games,
which is you may not understand what you just did,
You may not understand why you just did it,
but in almost every single case,
you were responsible or it was preventable,
or you had some sort of general under,
you were an agent of that.
In Risk Legacy, you had full control.
So, which is right here, which is, you know,
you know, there was a sticker that's on a card
and you choose when to put a sticker on a board.
And later on, you might really regret it, but you did it.
So it's like actions have consequences.
And what I always wanted was when you look back at it,
it always makes sense in retrospect why that happened.
So that leads to another covenant, which is,
board games, the designer always controls the materials.
Here's the game, it's done, play with it.
They're never like, here's most of the game.
Here's a bunch of stickers, here's some plastic pieces.
Just kind of put them together however you like
and it'll all work out.
You have this trust as a player, which is,
okay, you've done your job and my job is now
to enjoy your job, and what the legacy games do
is they sort of stop 80% along the way
and say I've done or we've done, if we're a co-designer,
this much of the game, now together we're going
to do the last part of the game.
You are now become like an unwilling co-designer
who has very limited knowledge of what you're designing.
And I think that that's like, you know, it's exhilarating to some people in every gamer as a game designer.
So, you know, you get to sort of get in and put your fingerprint on things,
and it's just basically like permission to make house rules.
But the downside to the giving people all these cards
is because it was so new and because it was so powerful
and because it was so different,
it was like giving matches to a toddler
in the sense that I would give out 10 stickers
and they'd be gone within the first two turns of the game.
Like, well, I'm gonna do this,
well, I'm gonna do this, well, I'm gonna do that.
And then you get to the second game
and you have this incredible hangover of why'd we do that?
There's nothing fun left to do
and we've made a mess of our board.
So I was like, well, I can't give them
all the materials right now.
I need to wait and say like, here's a couple things,
learn how to use your tools.
play for a while, integrate those,
and now here's some new tools.
And I'm like, well, I gotta put them in a box or something
or lock them up.
And which led to the second big moment,
which is these secondary goals.
And the box lid was deliberately designed to be open
so you could see them.
And I'm like, well, this is cool.
There's a chance for some narrative here, right?
Instead of saying open this at the end of game three,
it's like open this, you know, one of them is when,
I'm trying to think what the exact thing is,
when one person, when a person wins for the second time.
And so I could do the math and be like, well, that's not going to be game one.
And in a five-player game, it might be like all the way to game nine or
something like that.
But most of the time, it would be like game three or four.
So it gave me enough control as a designer to figure out, here's when
stuff comes out.
And I was like, this is neat.
This is just like, if you play a game and people go like, here's the
beginner rules, the intermediate rules, and the advanced rules.
And you're like, OK.
I'm really cool, I'm gonna start with the advanced rules
and then you play it.
And you're like, this game's hard, I don't like it.
But you know, it's like, I just took that and sort of,
it was kind of the reverse thing.
Instead of saying, I'm gonna give you that choice,
I'm gonna say, I'm gonna leave it here.
I'm gonna make you play the beginner game
and then you earn your way to the intermediate game,
but you earn it in a thematic way.
And I have seen with these legacy games,
totally unexpected side effect is people are like,
open a pack and they're like, oh, new rules!
No one gets excited about rules.
That just doesn't happen, but I'm like, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Oh, wow, right?
Like you're drawn into this thing.
So it's just a matter of opening something.
So in my mind, I'm like, well, that kind of works,
because sometimes you're playing a game,
and the game doesn't work out, and you're not winning.
And you can look over there, like, well, I'm not winning,
but maybe I can do one of those things, and sort of feel like.
And so I'm like, OK, this is how I had it in my head.
This is how this works.
I'm like, that's cool.
I provided sort of secondary features to that.
Huge misunderstanding on my part,
because the rest of the world saw it as this.
What's in there?
How do I get to it?
How fast do I get to it?
When does this happen?
Why don't you and I work together?
I'll lose so you can win, just so we can open that thing.
And so that's when I learned the power
of anticipation and the unknown.
This was not until the game came out
that I really got a sense that, for me,
what had been, again, sort of like.
the permanence was a way to make the game trackable.
The locked up content was to make the game
that you didn't abuse the game
with the first part that I made permanent.
And it's only in retrospect and I'm like,
oh yeah, it was this total narrative thing
that I was doing and the power of foreshadowing
and everything like that.
So but once I kind of realized like this is the,
this is the sticker that closes the risk legacy box.
I'm like, well, like I said,
now I'm just gonna do whatever.
I'm gonna put a note on there and make it a ritual.
and you have to cut it and then you're breaking the seal
on something like that.
Then there's another covenant that kind of comes in here,
which is game's gonna tell you everything that's in the box.
Hasbro is a big corporation.
It's got a lot of layers of lawyers and safeties and checks.
So the meetings I had in where they're like,
well, we need to put the box contents on the outside.
I'm like, well, you can't.
Those were some interesting meetings.
There were two meetings that I had many times.
One is making sure they, I'm like, can we say and more?
Can we say at least?
we say and and and like old again they want to things that they rise had to be
in there did not have to be in there they were just customs they were lost
the other one was
least three times i'd be in a meeting in some production present like out
you would uh... you'd mark the stickers a permanent but i i switched it so you
could kill moffitt remove them because you know i know i was permanently
yet that means you you can't pick them up again a minute
but you don't want that.
Yes, I do.
Right?
And then three months later,
some other person would be like,
hey, we noticed you had put permanent stickers,
so we made them repeal.
I'm like, no, nope.
I want them to be where even if you accidentally
put the corner on something, like that's it.
Like it's gonna be there
or you're gonna rip off your board.
But so this is another covenant.
It's like when you buy a board game.
we're telling you what's in the box,
we're telling you here's the rules,
here's the factions, here's what you get.
You can look on the bottom,
and then when you open the rule book at the beginning,
you can just kind of go down,
and some people just do it as an accounting
to make sure that they got everything they were supposed to
and there wasn't a production error.
Some people like to get their head around the project,
and so I'm like, no, I'm not gonna tell you.
There's a whole bunch of stuff in sealed boxes,
and hopefully we produced it right.
Sometimes we don't.
CFAL's fun because I've seen people,
there's a battery warning,
which you are required to put on.
Nothing with batteries that you'll see for.
So then it led to very quickly to,
well, if I'm not telling you everything,
am I telling you the truth?
There's a certain amount of trust
that I as a game designer am being truthful with you,
and I break this covenant every Legacy game that I do.
It's just like an author, it's narrative surprise.
And I'm like, okay, well, how can we really use this?
And that's when I did this idea.
I don't know if all of you know about this.
It still continues to entertain me.
What I realized is.
people aren't gonna wanna rip up a card.
And the first thing that Risk Legacy asks you to do
is take out a card with two stickers on it,
apply one sticker to the faction you're playing
and then rip up the card that contains the other sticker.
Like the first thing is A or B,
and you can't go back and it's being torn up.
And what I wanted was the people go, nope,
and just quit right there.
Like don't torture them.
Like I just like, it's this little litmus test
of whether you're up for this.
But I also realized that everyone's gonna go,
I'm not gonna rip it up.
There's this big black plastic vacuum form tray in the box.
And you're like, eh, there's no real way to put this.
I know, I'll put it under the tray.
And when you pick up the tray, that is taped to the bottom.
Some people find it right away.
Some people don't find it until they played 15 games
because that tray's in there tight.
So basically it was a way to torture people
who were meticulous.
And I had joked around at first that I was going to put in an envelope that said,
do not open until instructed and then never instruct them.
So to be fair, I am nicer than I threatened to be.
And there's been a whole fascinating bits of psychology here around.
groups finding this and then spontaneously again,
I've given creative control over them,
house ruling how they're gonna,
we'll do it after everyone wins once,
we'll do it after eight games,
we'll do it after Bill finally wins
because he hasn't won, we won't open it all,
we'll open it right now.
And just to make sure that no one could find out
what it was, there are four random packets at the bottom.
Two are bad for everyone, just messes up your world.
One is bad only for the people
who were there when it's opened.
And one is only good if you're there when it's opened.
Because even if you wanted to Google it,
you wouldn't have an answer of whether you
wanted to be there or not.
So then people open it, and it's more often than not bad.
And then something very interesting
happens with the psychology.
They integrate these rules into the game
and play with this bad expansion.
because they opened something they shouldn't.
There is no reason why they have to, right?
If you're playing a game and you are like,
someone's like, do you want to play with this expansion?
Like, I don't like it, it's kind of a downbeat.
You're like, okay, cool, we'll leave it out.
I just gave you an expansion and you're like,
pah, well, we got to do it.
And then they do.
And then people get mad at me.
It's like, I opened this envelope that you told me not to
and it was bad and you're a jerk.
And I'm like.
Okay.
So I haven't done anything that crazy since then,
but that is one of the more enjoyable moments
of my professional career.
Actually, so I was at a game convention last year,
and someone was auctioning away one of these,
and the people doing the auction asked me to open the box
and change one component, so that when they found it,
they had a customized version.
And because it was a last-minute request,
and I panicked, I didn't know what to do,
so I opened up that envelope,
and then put my cell phone number,
and said, text this to this cell phone when you open it.
Figuring I'd have this wonderful plan when they texted me.
So nine months later, when someone texts me,
and I'm like, Unpub 27, what does that mean?
And I'm like, oh, I was supposed to think of something.
So I'm like, are you playing now?
They're like, yeah, we're playing.
We're in the middle.
We're waiting.
Okay.
One sec.
And luckily I just came up with an idea that I was running,
I was a secret scientific bunker running,
teleporting portals between places
and they could text this number for the next two hours
and I would open up two random portals.
But if they went through, something good might happen
or something bad might happen,
but they could get their jump on their enemy.
And they were so excited, like, we need a portal.
Actually, no, they would do it.
We need a portal between Brazil and France,
like coming online.
And then I would literally roll percentile dice.
Oh, sorry, you lost three troops on the way.
And we had a great time.
And then we shut the portal down.
Actually, it worked out really well.
At the end of that game, they opened up another envelope,
which opened up this like really big, dramatic point
with this like big new bad guy in this dramatic twist.
And I was like, they've tapped into our signal.
I'm sorry we helped cause this.
Signing off.
And then just didn't answer any more of their texts.
Thank you.
So these are some of the covenants and where there's a little bit more to talk
about but these are some of the covenants I broke with with risk legacy
and ultimately
it ended up here where the players were in the control of sort of these spokes
which were these different packets in the sandbox play
which is meant to be open in nearly any order.
I think it's possible to actually open them in
almost every order or every order.
And then you get to 15 games and then it's just the ending was like you're done.
It doesn't lead to any sort of climax like
15 games thank you for playing.
And so it sort of looks like this,
and it came out and I expected it to,
I had like no F's to give at this point
because Hasbro had moved my job
and I knew I was leaving Hasbro.
And I'm like, I don't think I can make it on my own.
I'm probably gonna have to find a different career.
It was a good run.
Let's just do something crazy on the way out the door
just to see what happens.
I don't get royalties from it.
I don't own a piece.
If it failed, I didn't make less money.
There was no business thought in it.
I'm like, I saw eight copies.
This will be fun.
So I was really thrilled when it was received very, very well.
So I set out and I'm on my own and I'm like,
okay, I'm gonna do another one.
And what became C-Fall.
And I had 14 years of doing kids games and I'm like,
I'm gonna make the biggest thing that's ever been made ever.
Yeah.
So I wanted to do like longer play time
and more narrative and more unknown.
I'm like, oh, you want Christmas presents?
I'm gonna give you an empty board.
How's that?
And you're gonna explore it and do stuff.
And then it took three years.
But we'll get back to it.
It's called foreshadowing.
So in the meantime, Matt Leacock comes up to me
and he's like, hey, let's take this idea for pandemic.
And I'm like, I don't think it's gonna work as a co-op, man.
Sorry, but let's give it a try.
So we sat down and we did a whole talk on this yesterday.
So I'm not gonna get into in detail here
because you can find it.
online after.
But one of the first things we did is like,
well, we want more of a story.
We want more of a movie feel.
So we came up with something completely radical.
Feel free to take pictures.
It's called a three act structure.
We created a timeline of months
and we did upbeats and downbeats.
And we ended up basically taking this sort of free form
sandbox thing that'd be done in risk.
And we turn it into a tightly scripted legacy deck
where you start with card one
and we go through and you get to card,
I think it's 60 or something in season one.
And along the way, like we are presenting
a fairly linear narrative that you get to sort of wobble
in different places.
But if you played Pandemic Legacy
and we had a little breakout session here,
most of you would have similar experiences,
but you might say like, oh no, we never use that character.
Or for us, Europe was more problematic.
For us, it was South America.
But so you're having your own experience,
but it's within the, it's starting.
But the big question we had to do, and this is for people who are interested in doing legacy games,
a little bit of a design sidebar now, we're getting away from Covenants and design things,
is, uh, is...
You as a designer have less and less control the longer the games go.
Like, people are like, why is it 15?
And for us, I'm like, well, because that's a pretty big commitment already.
And I've had two people ask me this weekend,
I'm like, can we have like a six pack legacy game experience,
just like a long weekend.
And I'm like, okay, two separate people asked me,
so I'll think about it.
But 15 felt like you got your money's worth,
but it's sort of capped because I felt like
people weren't gonna wanna play after a certain point.
And the design cone of where the game was gonna go
was gonna get so wide that as a designer,
I was gonna have no idea if the game broke.
Like it will break eventually
if you give people the ability to keep changing it.
But what happened in Risk and what happens in Seafall is it's a competitive game,
so I'm relying on the players, again, unwitting co-designers to keep the game balance
by beating up on the leader.
Well, you don't have that in a co-op game, right?
So in a co-op game, you're like...
Matt and I just had these fears of literally the game just
kicking the players in the fetal position,
like game after game after game, and losing leading to losing,
and winning leading to winning.
And we get into this in more detail in our talk.
But basically, you need to, if you're designing,
have some way where losing doesn't lead to more losing,
and winning doesn't lead to more winning,
but winning is always better.
And so there's a series of weird incentives.
And what we did was something called funding.
In Pandemic Legacy, most of you probably know this,
but there are event cards.
Event cards are good because they give you actions
and they pad a deck to give you more time.
So every time you win in Pandemic Legacy,
we took two cards away.
And every time you lost, we gave you two extra cards
so that you could stay in this zone.
Also, this is important in a co-op game.
There's a safety net.
When we were play testing and people would win, sorry, lose,
I had some friends lose first game in January,
second game in January, first game in February.
And they said, well, we're your friends,
and we'll keep playing, testing this if you ask,
but we're pretty sure that we would throw this away
because we broke the game.
I'm like, no, you didn't.
They're like, we just lost the first three.
There's no way we're coming back.
And we kept playing and they kept going.
and they had a good time and Matt and I were talking about it and we realized
we put this box in that says open if you lose four games in a row and all this
does is provide a psychological anchor of you are doing fine until you lose
four games in a row. Now if you lose four games in a row
there's stuff in there that will help you but basically if you're like we lost
the game like that happens you lost two games like
okay we lost three games this is horrible now at least we didn't lose
four
If four, we'd be in trouble, but if we lose four,
we get what's in that box.
And they're like, okay, let's keep going then.
And until we let them know when they should panic,
they would panic after two losses or after three losses.
So all this does is sort of say like,
I know I'm gonna lie to you.
I know I'm gonna trick you.
I know I'm gonna do unexpected things,
but really, honestly, we want you to have a good time
and we got your back if things get bad.
And so that became a pandemic legacy.
Some takeaways from there is a linear story can work.
Cooperative can work and in fact, maybe even better
because you all integrate and learn new rules together
and you can think through and as you open things,
it's not like one person is better at figuring out
how to use this new tool.
And timed unlocks can work, whereas Risk Legacy,
you sort of chose how things happen.
For the most part in pandemic, we're like,
here's your next bit of content.
Now we've heard criticisms that it's a little too railroady,
but people enjoyed it.
So in season two, there's a little more creative choice.
So let's go back to C fall and I realize I'm I'm talking too much I want to get
the questions it got big and it stayed shaggy and it got some mixed reviews,
although now I've seen later reviews and later people playing is I think the
people who I wanted to have play it are finding it I think a lot of people who
played earlier people would play pandemic legacy and expected this to be
like a season 2 but it's a much heavier game it was designed to be but it is
because it was a heavier game.
There's some things, longer play time discourages binge play.
I think with risk and pandemic, they're 45 minutes to an hour.
You get done and you say, let's play again.
Seafall can be two hours.
You don't say, let's play again.
And then mentally, when people are like,
do you want to play another game?
You might be like, I don't know if we have time tonight.
Right, so with this game where I'm giving you reasons
to play again and again and again,
one of the things I need to give you
is a quick, cleaner experience.
The rules start heavier and ramp up more,
which means the early games need to be more of a tutorial.
They need to be handled.
I had to take a lot of rules out,
which made some of the early games like,
ah, this is a little flat.
And then you open up some stuff and you're like,
oh, this is where the game gets good,
which is where I had started it,
but then people were confused.
So moving the whole complexity scale up
leads to a lot of issues in those early games,
which get compounded by a longer play time.
But I will tell you, there's some really cool stuff in there.
So if you're into like a big, sprawling, Lord of the Rings,
D&D campaign sort of longer thing,
I think there's a lot of fantastic stuff in there.
And I'm very happy with it.
It just didn't meet the expectations
that had been set with the first two games that had come out.
So other people have jumped into this pool.
So going downstream, right after Risk Legacy came out,
the Pathfinder Adventure card game,
sorry, I should say card game on there,
it came out and Mike Selinker, the designer,
said he had played Risk Legacy.
He's like, oh, that's cool, we're allowed to do that now?
All right, you can make things change
and continue and create campaigns, cool.
And then he went off and did this.
There's this game that just came out now called Gloomhaven.
That is not two boxes stacked together.
That is the Gloomhaven box, which I was going to bring out
and play with some friends out here
until I realized it was the suitcase.
Like, I mean, it's huge.
It's a big map.
It's a tactical dungeon crawling thing
with branching characters
and all these little boxes in there.
And Mechs vs. Minions is a board game
that came out from Riot last year.
which has like a box with a miniature in it and a campaign play.
And then even a card game called Fabled Fruit.
What most of the games I just went through
are doing though is they took that second moment, the aha moment where I said,
oh, there's going to be narrative contents locked up.
Fabled Fruit makes a point of saying this is not a legacy game, it's not a legacy game,
like on the back it's almost like, hey Rob, this is not one of your games.
Because they didn't do the permanent change, they didn't do that permanent change, they
just said, oh, we can lock up content or otherwise keep you from doing it or have a deck that
as you play the game you bring new stuff in.
So people are sort of taking the less controversial half of things.
and implementing games and I think it's fantastic that you know all of this is
happening because now again like giving you a reason to play the game again and
again again to ramp up in complexity to start you out simple to give you some
actions moving forward.
And then for me like I said I'm working on 3 other ones right now.
And then you just pitching whole boy myself just
right in there, my brother that told me.
He said, hey, I'm from Boston.
He's like, David Ortiz doesn't bunt.
He's like, just keep making these legacy games
until everyone tells you to stop making them.
So I have this coming out in the third quarter.
Matt and I have this coming out.
Excited, it's very different from the first one.
The box bottom just leaked so I can say things now
like it takes place 71 years in the future
and the world's already ruined.
Good luck.
So here are some of the covenants that we talked about.
I can leave those up if anyone want to ask about them.
But we've got about 10 minutes now to take questions.
There's two microphones there if you want to line up.
I can't really see you because of the lights on
either side of those.
Or you can shout from your seats if you like.
Also, I need to tell you to fill in your evaluations.
And we'll start over here.
Hello.
Yep. So one of the big differences between board games and video games is that the video game kind
of enforces the rules for you. Yep. Whereas in board games the players have to do that. Yep.
I've heard a bunch of stories of people who started a pandemic legacy campaign,
messed up the rules in their first game and then never went back to it. Okay. I was wondering when
you were designing whether you put much consideration into the fact that people
might just get the rules really wrong and maybe get a different experience than what was meant.
Well, that's the problem with any board game.
And I've made this analogy before in other talks, which
is learning a board game would be like if you're going to
learn a new TV show, and you have to spend 20 minutes doing
a reading comprehension test and answering questions.
And then when you watch the show, scenes are out of place
and one character speaks in Spanish for no reason.
And you get to the end and you're like,
I don't really like that.
I didn't like the Spanish speaking guy.
And they're like, what?
No, that's not supposed to be right.
And then you're like, oh, hold on.
And then you take the test again.
And then you get to watch it.
Like, it's a really unfair burden put on people
that gets compounded in the legacy games.
Now, what Matt and I put at the end of the book is like,
it's all cool.
You're not going to break it.
If you mess something up, just cut your funding
or add your funding and just keep rolling with it.
So of course, like, you know, it's discouraging.
Or, you know, tell me who they are.
I'll tell them it's OK.
And they can keep playing.
They can keep playing up after one game.
I would hate to have that happen, right?
There were some people who were playing a C fall game
and they found out in game nine
they were playing some rule horribly wrong
and they went on BGG and asked about it
and everyone's like, no, it's fine.
It's good, just keep rolling with it,
you're all playing under the same role.
So it's a necessary problem of board games,
it gets compounded in legacy games,
and Matt and I, to an extent in season one,
and religiously in season two,
tried to do forms and factors and numbers
and reminders and cards and putting things
in certain places to guide this experience even more.
Thank you.
Hi.
John Arnold from Handelabra Games.
I was curious, as you mentioned, video games
inspired a lot about what's going on in legacy games.
Do you have any thoughts about digital versions
of legacy tabletop games?
Any opportunities or challenges that you could think of?
Yeah, well, I mean, the challenge is what is it?
Because a digital game already has campaign modes,
and they already have branching narratives,
and unlockable content, and a lot of the stuff
that I cribbed and put back in here.
And so what I don't want to do is
end up having a photocopy of a photocopy going backwards.
I mean, the joke I always make is when you finish the game,
it uninstalls itself, and you have to buy it again for $5
or something.
But I don't think that anyone's going
to let us get away with that.
I don't know, I suspect it would be something like a series of board games in campaign mode
where actions have consequences.
But I don't know exactly what it is.
It's something that people have been asking me about lately and I don't have a clear answer
for it because it feels like, again, it's going back to a medium where a lot of stuff
came from.
But there's an answer.
Like potion explosion sort of.
What's that?
Sort of like potion explosion.
I haven't played that yet.
Oh, it's a physical bejeweled that's also gone back to a digital version.
Hi uh thanks for the talk. Also I'd say uh to that idea a
server side, lock everybody in, can't undo your save, pay
fifteen dollars for the legacy style expansion pass, I would do
that with co-op prints. Anyway my question is the play testing
process. Especially when you are
explicitly breaking covenants and you are trying to make a game that is essentially
fucking with some players' expectations but also want to playtest a long game.
Yep.
Like, I'd love to hear how you go after that and what you really look for in that feedback
that's actually valuable to you.
Yeah, so there's three different games that I've done, or four if you include season two,
which is done and with, you know, they finished that last year.
They all had a slightly different playtesting methodology,
and the one that worked the best
was the one from Pandemic Legacy,
which is qualitative over quantitative.
At Hasbro, it was just the usual playtest group.
CFAWL, Plaid Hat did a great job
of doing their usual thing that you would do
for something like a.
a deck-building game, which is to get a lot of data
from a lot of different groups.
But what Matt does with all his games
when we do a pandemic legacy is we gave it
to two to four groups at a time
and had them video their entire experience,
including before the game and then after the game.
And then we watched all of these
and made hundreds and hundreds of notes.
Because you can't get enough data,
meaningful data across the spectrum,
it's more important to get really good data focused in,
because they're more of an experiential game.
it's a little bit less important whether is this costed 2 or costed 3
because it's something you can make a different choice on later.
We still try to get it right.
What's more important is people got confused.
This text was too long.
This didn't fit on the board.
This rule is, they stopped play for 7 minutes figuring out this rule.
This rule shouldn't come out in the middle of the game.
It should come out at the end of the game because it's longer to integrate.
So with legacy games now going forward to me, it's a video.
It's a lot of work.
It's hundreds of hours of video watching and making notes,
but that's how you find all the things that aren't in the game
but above the game, like above the table.
I've got four minutes, so I can probably take these three questions.
Okay, I'm interested in the covenant that the players make with each other to continue
playing the game.
With like an RPG, you say, oh, we're going to play D&D once a month, whatever, and it's
effectively infinite.
But
Yeah.
And with regular board games, we're going to play board games every week.
It's going to be different.
It's whatever we sit down to play.
But here I'm finding it difficult to find a group
who's going to commit to pandemic legacy or see fall. Yep.
Basically, the campaign nature of D&D is I inherited a lot of things from D&D or took
a lot of things.
And one of the things I also took is the how do we get a group together problem.
It's like forming a band, right?
Like everyone has great ideas and then it just falls apart.
It's different. It lives in that space of, hey, we're going to do this thing and it's going to take,
we're going to play, you know, the first game we played our game group every week is going to be
Pandemic Legacy and that will take our time for the next three months. That's one of the reasons
people said they wanted a six-pack. They wanted like five games and I'm done or eight games and
I'm done because I was so concerned about adding the value.
that we put the number at like 12 or 15,
but I'm discovering now that maybe that's not as important
as doing something where you can get a group together
and committing and maybe a smaller number makes sense.
I don't have a magic answer other than
it's the same issues that come from D&D.
And we've made a point with Pandemic Legacy
to make it a two-player game because it's a good
couples game or parent and child game, right?
It doesn't need a large,
it's easier to get one person together than three.
Right. Okay?
Okay.
I don't have an answer, unfortunately.
Hi. What were some of the lessons you learned about tuning and balancing on a game like Betrayal at House on the Hill that you applied to the Legacy game?
Yeah, well that's probably the first time I've heard the phrase tune and balance associated with Betrayal at House on the Hill.
Yeah, it's surprising.
Yeah, my take is sometimes tuning and balance is not as vital as the experience.
What happens in Legacy is there's always a chance to fix it later, right?
You make a chance and like, oh, that was a bad idea.
It's like, well, at the end of this game, we now have to do this to correct for that
because it didn't work how we wanted to give enough people enough tools
that they can solve whatever problem they created.
That's when Matt and I will talk about what designing like, well,
if they really mess up this portion.
we'll give them these tools.
If they don't pay attention to that,
So I don't know what problems you're gonna have
in your world, but we should have found a solution
for all of it.
So you may say like, well, we never use these stickers.
And it's like, well, you didn't end up
with a problem there.
So for me, it's not about balancing it.
It's trying to think of every problem
and giving them the ability to balance it themselves.
Okay.
You showed some of the other games that are starting to do more sort of
continuing campaigns and stuff like that, but that none of them are doing the more
permanent changes that the legacy games are doing. Do you think more games will
start doing, you know, writing on the boards and stickers? Are you excited
about that and will they be called legacy games?
They can be called legacy games if they want. I mean, I'm associated with it but I
control or own nothing to it because I thought of the idea why I work for a
corporation so thank you Hasbro for not locking that down.
Some people are doing it.
Gloomhaven's doing it a little bit.
I was a little behind on time, so I didn't get into his detail.
But that is multiple groups can be exploring the same world
at the same time.
So group A might raid this tomb and shut it down
before B gets there on a different night.
One of the things about a legacy game
is you can't leave it at a library and everyone plays it.
But Gloomhaven, you could.
You could walk and be like, oh, that other group that
plays on Tuesday got that sword.
So there's some interesting things
that are going on with permanence now.
And I think when Risk came out, people
saw it as an interesting fad.
or an interesting idea.
A number of people tried it and said,
this is ridiculously difficult to do
and probably is never gonna be successful again.
And then pandemic came out and everyone now said,
okay, maybe there's something to this.
And I keep hearing through the grapevine
that there are more coming out.
I think we're starting to see other people doing it
based on it.
And they'll come up with all sorts of new ideas
that I couldn't possibly think of.
Cause I'm now at the point where I'm like,
this is how it's done.
Like it's gone from crazy idea to here are the rules
of how to do it really quickly.
So I'm looking forward to people shaking up my assumptions
of what.
what this can do. It's 10 31 so I'm afraid they're going to kick us out now
so I want to thank you all for taking the time this morning.