Hi, my name is Joseph and I'm Technical Designer at World Void, and I'll be giving a talk about how
to port a real-life castle into your game when you're broke. I needed to scan a castle to use
in my game and I was low on funding, so I decided to just go out and do it with whatever equipment
I can find. And it worked! So, in this talk I'll be going over how I managed to scan the castle
while reducing the cost as much as possible. Then I'll be going over the trade-offs in choosing
your equipment, your software, and your processing computer.
Then, I'll be going over the guidelines of capturing a high quality scan, and the tips and tricks you can use in order to fix errors that can generate from a mutation of your captured photos.
Finally, I'll be going over the different approaches of processing a huge scan into a game-ready asset, which can be quite a challenge when working with such a high-poly model.
So this talk should cover everything you need to know about scanning your own castle, so if you want to replicate this process, you'll find the external links in my site very useful.
Thank you for showing interest in my talk, I hope you like it, and I'll see you at GDC!