This is GDC Podcast Episode 4.
Hey everybody, this is your host Chris Graft.
I'm editor-in-chief of Gamasutra.
I'm here with my co-host Alyssa McAloon.
Hello, I'm Alyssa. I am news editor and associate publisher at Gamasutra.
Yeah, how you feeling today?
Sick. Great, thanks for asking.
You're feeling a little sick.
I learned a lesson about don't fly with a head gold.
Oh, yeah. You just came from South Dakota, right?
Yeah.
Yeah. The hotbed of the game industry, as they call it.
We have Dakota State, which is a game design college. So they're great. I graduated from there.
Oh, okay. All right. Well, good job
So, uh today we do have we do have a a guest he is kind of hanging out back right now, uh,
You know what? I'm, not even gonna
I'm, not even going to uh to you know, avoid spoiling it's brandon sheffield. Uh,
It's me
A lead writer, uh, the lead writer on, uh, on, uh, lab zeros indivisible,
but we're not going to acknowledge him yet.
We're going to put him, we're going to put Brandon in a corner for now.
Uh, but real quick, let's go over some, uh, GDC 2020 news, some,
uh, real quick announcements.
Uh, we got to mention that registration.
It's still open. It's still open. It hasn't closed yet. So if you would like to go, you should go to
the website gdconf.com. Sort that out. It's from March 16th through the 20th. There's something
else that is cool that happened. The GDC narrative wall is up. Alyssa, what exactly was that again?
It was a project they hosted at GDC 2019 where they solicited contributions from developers
in attendance and built that into three neat little twine projects that are now up and
playable.
Yeah, and that can be found at narrativewall.gdconf.com.
And lastly, this is freshly baked news,
fresh out of the oven, newly announced game funding and
investment summit at GDC 2020, and that'll be a place where you can
learn about how to partner with people and, you know, who have money
to give you.
And also people who want to give you money, they can go over there and find out how to be a wiser investor.
So if you're interested in, you know, supporting your studio or your project with cash money,
which I think that, you know, some people might be, check it out.
Game Funding and Investment Summit at GDC 2020.
All right, I think, what do you think, Alyssa?
Should we just cut to the chase?
I think so, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, the suspense, I don't think that I can take it
anymore.
So our next guest, former editor-in-chief of Game
Developer Magazine, sibling publication of Gamasutra
before its unfortunate demise.
Contributor on Gamasutra. Sorry, that was kind of bleak. Game Developer Magazine was, you know,
it was the best game development magazine that ever existed. And so, he's also a contributor
on Gamasutra, founder of the indie studio Necrosoft Games, which is responsible for
great games like Gun House and Oh Dear. That's D-E-E-R.
It is a racing game where you run over deer.
Or not.
You can choose not to.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
I always played running over.
He also worked on, uh, the highly successful releases, the, uh, Street
Fighter 30th anniversary collection.
SNK 40th anniversary and an upcoming Samurai showdown.
What is it like 50th anniversary?
You just gotta keep ramping it up.
Yeah, ramping it up.
The older the franchise of fighting games, the better for Brandon.
A frequent GDC speaker and a really great advocate for students who want to enter the
game industry and develop careers in the game industry.
And kind of the main reason he's here now is he was the lead writer on Lab Zero's Indivisible,
which came out in October this year.
Great game that we'll find out more about.
And here we go.
Let's welcome Brandon Sheffield.
Hey, Brandon.
It's me.
Yeah, it is you.
So you are the lead writer on Indivisible, or were.
It's out now.
So your work is mostly done, right?
Mostly done is what I should say.
Yeah, it's mostly done.
Can you tell us, uh, for listeners who, who aren't familiar, what is
indivisible and, uh, what exactly did you do on the game?
yeah indivisible is
a
it's a platforming
uh... action
metroidvania-ish game with
a
kind of fighting game inspired
battle system uh... we did kind of make the
mistake of calling it
an action rpg and
it
it sort of misses a lot of the core
elements of an rpg
uh... like
a lot of stats and leveling and equips and stuff.
But it does still have that kind of vibe, which is why
we said it, but it's more like a
weird Metroidvania action turn-based fighting game.
Yeah, that's a lot easier to remember. Yeah, it's much easier to remember that way.
Yeah, and it's got this, I really like, we can talk, I mean, I know you didn't work directly
on the battle system, but you know, it, I like how it's just so fast-paced and it does have that kind
of, that immediacy like a fighting game might, which makes sense because Lab Zero worked on
Skullgirls, right? That's right, they did Skullgirls before and the battle system was very much
Mike Z's baby, Mike Z being the, I guess, the
gameplay lead on Skullgirls, and he's also the creator of the engine that this whole
game is made in.
Yeah, I'm terrible at the indivisible battle system, but other people are good at it.
Yeah, well that's good.
But it's made by Mike Zedd, as he's known in the rest of the world.
Yeah, Mike said.
Yeah.
So the lead character is Ajna.
Am I pronouncing that correctly?
Yeah.
And you did the dialogue, which, you know, also would mean that you did a lot of the
character creation and development.
And this, Ajna is such a strong character.
You can tell like what, that she has had a strong vision behind her.
Can you talk about how you began to lay the foundation for her as a character?
It's an interesting one. It's kind of a long, meandering story, and she was less established
than you might think. I guess I should... I forgot to mention exactly what I did on the game.
Oh yeah, let's do that.
I basically did all the writing that, aside from the backer NPCs, because it was the highest
ever game on Indiegogo, and so it had a lot of backers that put their own NPC dialogue
in there.
So I did basically the dialogue, but the story beats were already established when I came
in.
There was a big outline.
and it was all tied to specific gameplay stuff, so it was an interesting challenge that we can talk about later
to have to essentially write around existing story beats to try to get the results that we wanted.
And that's kind of, in a way, the story of Ajna's development as well, because she was originally...
created by the team, and they had a vision for her.
She went through a lot of visual iterations, but by the time I came on,
I knew what she looked like. So I had that, and also when I came on,
there was an existing script.
which i re-wrote
uh... well actually
re-wrote is not exactly the right word
put that in there, which i re-wrote
i just started over, is what i did
and one of the challenges that the team had with Ajna was that
Because as she goes along, she has to undergo some things that aren't fantastic,
and she has to make some choices that are not great and the player might not make.
So it was really important that she be likable.
And that was the big issue before I came on, was that she wasn't a likable character.
Yeah, let's talk about that because I read a blog post that you wrote that focused a lot on the importance of making this particular character likable.
So what was the difference between the unlikeable version versus the honestly completely likable version that ended up in the final game?
I would say what started out as angsty teen, which was a little more of a coming of age kind of thing,
I opted to go toward...
a couple things. One is humor, which I have a kind of complicated view of, you know, maybe
it's not complicated, but I have a specific view of. We're going to talk about that. Okay.
And then the other thing was like...
So, Meryl Cartwright, who's the creative director and was also the story lead,
she was like, Ajna can be dumb, she can be stupid, and that's okay.
And so I really took that forward and made her, not stupid, but like, incredibly straightforward.
Just like, she sees a goal and she goes toward it regardless of whether she knows what that goal is or how to get there or whatever.
She's just like, here we go!
And I think that doing that allowed me to have a lot of fun with her without making fun of her.
Because she's just like... she's got that kind of tenacity of character that lets you build a lot of things around her.
I guess. Yeah, it's also, uh, she has a certain kindness to her, even if she is,
you know, her, her, like, like she, she, she is kind of naive, but she's also
optimistic and, and she is kind.
Yeah.
There's, there's a, uh.
There were kind of a couple of anime that I actually took cues from.
One is
Azumanga Daioh, where
there's a...
a character called Tomo who
is very energetic and always smacking people and
there's a particular scene in that
anime that
was kind of an inspiration for
Ajna. There's a bit where
everybody, all the, it's a bunch of schoolgirls and they're going on a
class trip
uh... well not a class trip, they're going on a trip to someone's summer home
and uh...
Tomo, when they arrive after this long, arduous journey, grabs the keys and throws them into the grass.
Because she's like, wouldn't it be funny if someone grabbed the keys and threw them into the grass, and everyone's like,
no! And then she said, yes, it would, and she throws it.
And then everybody has to spend the next 30 minutes looking for the keys so that they can get into the house.
When they finally get them again, she's like,
wouldn't it be funny if someone did it again?
And so that scene was kind of partially an inspiration for Ajna.
And another is one called The Promised Neverland.
I'm familiar with that.
Alyssa, I was waiting for Alyssa to pop in here.
But yeah, go ahead.
I love the premise of Neverland, sorry.
No, I do. It's really good, but also...
yet well it's it's not a that no that's the key bits that are inspiring here
it's just the
the main female character in that
uh...
she
no matter what
wants to save everybody all the time
She's like, everyone around her is like, let's compromise, we gotta do what makes the most
sense to save as many people as possible, and she's like, no, we're saving everyone.
Even if it kills me, we're saving everyone. And that's another part that I got,
and kind of slotted into Ajna's character.
Yeah.
So not only is this lead character a young woman, but also
the whole game is inspired by the mythology of Southeast Asia.
So, you know, of course, you have to be mindful of, you know,
you know, writing for a young woman, but, you know, also for a different,
you know, something inspired by a different culture that you want to make sure
that you still are accurate and respectful towards.
How did you go about doing that?
Well, a lot of the work was done already in terms of that stuff, because the mythology was set up by a very multicultural team, so there was already a lot of thought and concern put into that.
And then, for myself, to make sure that I didn't kind of mess anything up too bad,
I did a lot of research.
Like, in the early part of the game, you have to find this thing called the Campfaria Galanga,
which is also known as Resurrection Lily.
in order to recruit this character.
And so I did a bunch of searching to see what plants
were used in kind of traditional medicine
in any of the regions that we were covering
that also vaguely looks like the plant that we had.
And that was the one that I found
that pretty much fit all those things.
And so anytime there was something where we needed
to have a...
or an opportunity to have a cultural touch point,
I would try to do some research and find something
that would meet that.
Yeah.
Hey, Alyssa.
How's your cold?
I'm just spacing out over here a little bit.
But no, it's really good conversation.
I'm having that interviewer's dilemma
where when the person you're talking to
is saying really interesting things,
I forget to turn my question brain on.
I'm just like, yeah, no, that is really interesting.
Yeah, the anime stuff, it sounded like you wanted to say something about that.
Oh no, it's just that Promised Neverland is an emotional journey.
And Emma's fantastic, the character he was talking about, and I could see a lot of that reflected
in the very little I've seen of Indivisible. I haven't got to play it yet, I'm so behind on games.
That's okay.
I've played every single game.
True gamer, Chris Kraft.
Promise Neverland is an interesting one for me as a story exercise.
I'm actually trying to... not exactly emulate, but I'm trying to draw from it for the next
game that I'm writing too, because it has a great cat and mouse tension between the various
parties that are involved in the mystery that's unfolding.
And one really cool thing that I learned from it is that a great way to do mystery in a
visual medium like this is to show...
You show all these various sides that are competing.
You show their individual internal dialogues and their stories within themselves.
So like they...
you know, one faction is discussing their plans and then another faction is discussing their plans,
so you as a viewer know more than either one of those factions knows, but at the same time,
both of those factions are hiding something both from you and from each other.
So...
you know, as a viewer you have more, you feel like you have more information than everybody
in the show does, and that allows you to kind of speculate about what's going to happen
and try to think about how these threads could interweave. But since the characters are also
hiding from something from you, there's a lot of potential for mystery and setups of complicated
scenarios and things.
I think it's really cool, so I like that anime.
Yeah, and Indivisible, you know, if people haven't played it,
like, there is, I mean, all of these things,
there's so many things that are internalized inside of Vajna.
The whole, like, the premise of the game is that
she recruits people and they live in her brain, right?
Yeah.
That's, yeah, I guess I just wanted to clarify.
Yeah, she absorbs everybody that she meets into her brain.
And a lot of the dumb jokes that I make in it are like...
I don't really like direct fourth wall breaking, because I think that's kind of weird and silly,
but I like having the characters be aware of how ridiculous the situation is within
the framing of their universe.
So having one particular character, Razmi, often commenting on how Ajna is just essentially
abducting people into her brain.
felt appropriate to me because I would think that it was weird, so surely somebody else would as well.
Yeah, and that avoids the winking into the camera type thing.
Yeah, which you don't want.
What's your process for writing humorous dialogue?
Because it's so easy to write a line and be like, oh, this is the funniest thing in the world,
and then it just falls flat.
So how do you go from idea, inception, to actually what ends up in the game?
uh...
so
what i tend to do is
look at what i've got
uh... be it
images of characters or
various
scenarios that have to happen
and then
i'd just start writing something and see if something interesting happens
it's
my kind of
i had a background in writing
kind of uh... web comics for a while
and that actually really helped me find my
comedic voice, I guess
and how to write
dialogue between characters that
sounded like
humans were involved with it
and
so it's kind of a similar process where I'll
I'll start from an image or an idea and then build it out from there.
And sometimes, you know, I wind up writing myself into a corner and the whole thing is
just terrible and I hate it, and so then I'll scrap it and rewrite it from scratch.
But you know, once you've got a few decent jokes in there, you can...
recycle them with restraint as the game moves along.
And that's really...
That actually, like, people love callbacks and stuff,
so for the people that pay attention, that's really handy.
But you can also sometimes...
Some of the blocks of text that I will scrap are ones where I'm recycling too much and I wind up feeling like I'm trying to make everything a joke.
And those wind up being just terrible.
That's my life, I try to make everything a joke.
I just did it now. So, like, I think we really established that you and I have known each
other for a pretty long time. Yeah. We're good friends. So I'm playing, oh, by the way,
this is total, what is it, collusion and, you know, yeah, it's happening right now.
Be aware, everybody.
No, but I'm playing Indivisible and within the first, you know, five minutes of gameplay
and I'm encountering NPCs, the dialogue, I mean, they read like text from you as far
as like the personality, you know, is there.
I mean, I'm pretty sure that if I was playing Indivisible...
I'd be able to be like, wait, and I didn't know, you know, that you were working on the
game.
I'd be like, wait, did Brandon?
Yeah.
Well, yeah, go ahead.
My, uh, I did a, a short talk at GDC.
like i don't know how many years ago eight years ago or something like that
uh... which was
about how you should make games for yourself
because
i think i believe that if you make something that really resonates with you
then
and showing a perspective, then people will actually like that much more
and find it more interesting and more engaging than if you do something that's generic and for everybody.
So, you know, obviously this game is made by a lot of people, and all the gorgeous art and music and everything is by a whole group of folks,
but the writing was something that...
was kind of my part that I got to own, and so I was able to just be like,
this is my joke. This is my style of joke that has been in my brain for some time,
and so now, here, you may have it. And so it really was kind of like I was writing.
jokes to my friends. And I think the important part of that is, say I'm making a dumb joke to
you or any other person that I've known for a long time, I assume that you will get it. I don't feel
like I need to explain it to you or whatever. And I think that having a trust in the audience
to get your joke is a big part of it.
Yeah, yeah, it's almost like you know we're referring to these as jokes, but they're not things
You know they're not like jokes there. It's just humorous
So for example really early on in the game you run into a guy with a bunch of sticks
And then he's just like I like to carry a bunch of sticks. I like to build stuff with it
I like to sit on fire, and I like to slap people with them and something like that. That's not the exact
I'm not looking at the game right now. It's not a direct quote but
It's just kind of, there's that kind of like,
oh, that's like, you know, that's silly, you know,
type thing and it's just, and that kind of humor
plays out through, you know, so much of the game
that it really, it makes it feel like wilty.
You know, there's still some heavy things
that happen in the game.
But there are these, like really,
micro scenario instances where you get to meet one of the very many NPCs in this game and
You just you know their personality right away
which
let's let's talk about that because this there's a whole lot of characters in this game and
How do you write for all those keep track of them give them their own unique personalities
well i can't say that it did the greatest job of that
uh...
but
i did sort of track
the with with like that
sticks guy
i think
the
like this
one one way to
get people on board with your character is to just
kind of
have their first sentence almost describe who they are completely and
and that guy that guy the first thing he says when you
click on him is
ah yes, bale of sticks
uh... and uh... and of course the reason that came about is
they just showed to me
and pcs
that i needed to write for
and i was like
was guys carrying sticks when he looked with the loves it with that this whole
deal
and
you know it makes it all out
How much of that, how much, sorry to interrupt, but how much of that is just you as somebody who's on deadline writing on a project just like, I can't think of anything else. He's got sticks. Let's do something with sticks.
Well, yeah, I mean, there's, there's definitely some of that. There's a, there's a character in one of the other, other regions, Connell, that has,
they they sent me this character and he's looking down into this white bowl
and i was like it just looks like he's staring at milk
and so i made him a uh... a milk fortune teller who reads the milk to tell you
what
is gonna happen and it's just like
so stupid
but it is
the very first thing that i thought of
i like that though
Yeah, and I find that when I'm under pressure and I have to think of the absolute
simplest or first thing that I think of and do it, a lot of my better work comes from that.
Just like a gut reaction, gotta do something, uh, this.
and then it'd be funny if it was actual.
Alyssa, you probably can't...
I've never done that in my entire life.
Yeah, it's like...
That's just how writers and reporters and, you know,
just in general operate, I feel like.
Yeah, we love pressure.
I mean, we must.
So, in terms of writing all these various characters...
It was tough because there are something like, I should really know the real answer, but there's something like 34 voiced characters in this video game.
We'll fact check that, yeah.
And you don't have...
this is only a minor spoiler, but you don't have access to all of them all the time.
And so, that made it a real challenge because there's a lot of...
Up until the very end, we were still deciding with some characters, like, when you could even get them.
and so
they couldn't
be part of the main scenario so I had to
essentially pare the main scenario down to only the characters I knew you could
get
and
even then
there's still like eight of them
which is too many to put
into
any one conversation so I had to limit conversations
to four at the absolute max, three would be a better number
and obviously two is much easier but
since we had so many characters I had to keep inserting them
into conversations so you'd remember that they existed or
so that they could have some sort of an arc and all that kind of stuff
and we wound up having to relegate some of the side characters. Their
whole arc only takes place during their recruit
and loyalty quests that they have because there just wasn't a lot of space
to put them otherwise which
I would imagine.
Is regrettable.
I'd say working with a voice acting deadline, too, it just added a whole bunch more pressure
on top of what's already a very time-sensitive process.
Oh yes.
Because of voice acting, I actually had to be, creative-wise, I had to be finished first.
Because we had to...
you know, record everything
and implement it in the game and all of that takes a lot of time and so
I had to...
maybe I wasn't the very first but I had to finish up
uh... while other folks were still
working away on
designing stuff and
implementing cut scenes and all that sort of thing so...
it made me really nervous because there's no going back from voice acting.
There's no return point because unless you can get people back in the studio,
which is expensive and thus not going to happen, you're stuck with the dialogue that you've got.
And so if anything changes, then you have to find creative ways to work around that.
Yeah, that sounds scary.
Yeah, it's a little spooky.
Earlier you mentioned you were basically handed, you know,
all the story beats.
And on top of that, also we didn't mention,
like this is an Indiegogo funded game.
It's a $2 million Indiegogo funded game.
So it was big.
So a lot of the backers on there, what did they offer?
It was like their own.
dialogue or...
They had their own dialogue and their own character.
The rule that I made, because I actually didn't edit the NPC dialogue for the backer characters
— someone else did that — but the rule that I set was that backers could not write
dialogue.
the main characters or any of the
any of the core characters, any of the playable characters or even our NPCs.
They had to, they could only do monologues for themselves.
Yeah, and then
somebody added those all together and had to deal with all that stuff and
then they just got put
all over the place and so if you want to see a
chubby merman or a
furry cat girl or whatever, they're in there.
And as far as the story beats go, what was that like where it's like, okay, this is what's
going to happen. Now you finish it up. Yeah, it was interesting because
there were definitely things that I would have liked to change but was unable to. And it's
been interesting to see the results of those.
changes, or not the changes, the results, how people react to those scenes.
Like, for example, we had a huge...
huge is the wrong word, long is the correct word... long argument about...
this is not really a spoiler either because it happens in the first ten, fifteen
minutes, but...
there's a character called Dar who kills Ajna's father
and he winds up being the first person that you recruit into your brain
and i was against that i was like can we at least have him
not be the direct killer of the father maybe it's
it's under his orders or
something like that, but not have him be the one who actively killed him because it makes
it so difficult for him and Ajna to be together in the same space.
Everyone was very adamant that he should, in fact, do this.
You wind up with this tension of...
Ajna carrying around her father's killer in her brain and being her only
companion for the first portion of the game.
And so, everyone thought that it was important for later events for that to be true.
And so I tried to write around it as best I could.
And so, reading reactions to that part have been very interesting because some people
are like...
Ajna took no time to grieve, this makes no sense, and they didn't like it.
And then other people are like, this throws the traditional RPG narrative on its head
and is a good example of how this story seems like it's going to go down one lane of tropes
but in fact goes another way.
So, it's been interesting to read that both of us were kind of correct.
Yeah, I mean, how does that make you... I mean, it doesn't like...
What were your thoughts when you're reading all these?
Oh, reading the comments?
Yeah, the comments.
I would say that the majority of people's complaints, I was like, yeah, I get that.
There were only a few where I was like, that's not quite right. But
I think the ones where I didn't agree totally were the ones where they were...
where they didn't
decouple writing and story,
which I wouldn't really expect people to, but a lot of people actually did.
They were like,
I love
the characters,
but I don't love this aspect of the story, or something like that.
But ultimately, I was really happy with the results because most people did love the whole
story it seems and we made a bunch of people cry, which is good.
It's always good.
That's what you want.
That's proof now.
You know, this is the answer.
Can video games make you cry?
And here we are.
yep we did it
and
it's it's definitely nice to
read that
the game
made people laugh a lot
and then also made them cry
and they got to feel several ranges of emotion going on
in the one game so overall i'm pretty
pretty happy with reading
the reviews. I didn't really like hearing Zero Punctuation's review, that one was
kind of not so cool, but otherwise... I somehow missed it. Yeah, good. He's very snarky about a lot of things that are, like, fair enough, but kind of out of any one individual person's control and thus difficult to...
feel like this is those comments should be as bad as they were
on that note uh... how does like reading reviews for something you put your heart
and soul in your time and just to be like
horrifying i would be my personal word for it but uh... there's some value
like how you're explaining it and reading what other people have to think
in my criticism of the thing that you made
how do you kind of like
go about getting the useful information from reviews are kind of knowing when to
be like no i can't let this get to me that that takes completely wrong
Yeah, I think I've found that somehow, perhaps due to a long time of being a journalist and
just being very online and such, I seem to have a slightly thicker skin when it comes
to reading these kinds of things.
if i feel like i did a pretty good job
that's that's my defense
against everything else
and there'll be people that say that they hate it
and
you know that won't stop me reading the review or the
commentary because i'll be curious to see
what they have to say about
like if they say they hate the writing i'll keep reading the rest to see if they
really liked something else and
you know, I'll often find that someone
didn't like the writing but they
were kept playing through the game because they liked the battle system, or
they compared the platforming to Celeste, or they thought that the game was too pretty to
stop playing, or something like that.
And then I can share that back with...
the team and
have them, I don't know, feel a little nice about it. So that's valuable in itself.
Another thing is
it's worth sifting through a lot of
these just general comments because, for example,
I found someone on the internet, on Twitter, who was making fanart of Ajna and Torani,
who's kind of like her mentor character that shows up later.
And Torani is... she's sort of modeled after a Thai deity.
So I found a word that an older Thai woman could give affectionately to a younger Thai woman,
and found this word, Luk Sao, which is basically like, my child.
And this person that I found on Twitter that was doing this fan art...
was a Thai person and was really focusing on the use of that word and writing it in Thai along with
the images that they were drawing, and it was great because it felt like
that person... I mean, I wonder how many times that person had gotten to see a Thai term of
endearment in an English-language video game before, and they were...
also validating for me
that the term was used correctly because I'm always nervous when I
look up something from
any culture that's not my own and then try to put it
into
a video game in correct context and so
you know it was worth sifting through tons of
good, bad, mediocre tweets to find something like that where it's like
this totally resonated with somebody and that's fantastic.
Yeah, you get that connection.
And it's good that the word didn't end up being like jerk face or something.
Yeah.
I mean, I, I got it from, uh, from Thai friends, so I had a reasonable amount
of confidence that it was fine, but yeah, you never know.
And of course, like there's like, there is the underlying.
you know, a concept here of all the benefits of having an inclusive team when you're when you're
writing a story, not just like this, but you know, any kind of story, just get more interesting
characters and like more viewpoints on, on, you know, different ways that people, you know, live.
Yeah, and I was a little... I had some trepidation around being a Caucasian dude who's writing the
story. I mean, writing all the dialogue, you know, for this very diverse cast, but...
you know I realized that having
a diverse team
behind you, all of, I mean not behind me, but um...
with me
uh...
Good save.
Mike Z thinks I'm too arrogant, so...
Anyway.
Having this group of people that not only were responsible for crafting the story and the characters visually and story beat-wise in the first place,
but having them look at everything I wrote and veto stuff if it seems like it's wrong or just add a bit of themselves if they can or need to or want to somewhere,
I didn't do as much of adding of themselves as I could have because of time pressure, but there was some of that.
And that all just kind of made it so much easier to make a game that has a lot of inclusivity, a lot of different kinds of people,
without making it a big deal or a big point.
I read an article that someone wrote recently about...
how they were happy that all these characters were hanging out together and allowed to just be there.
They didn't have to be like,
you're this race and I'm this race.
We gotta figure out how to work together.
Everybody was just like,
hey, it's a new friend, or I don't like that person.
And it didn't...
that didn't follow down any particular lines and it's unfortunate that that's
rare but I guess it is rare and I'm happy we were able to get somewhere with that.
Yeah I mean to be fair when you and I first met we were like you're white, I'm half Filipino.
Right.
That's how it went down.
My personal reaction already failed that test, I'm sorry.
Yeah, so, well, we need to wrap up here.
Brandon was only supposed to be on for five minutes,
but this got really interesting.
One thing, as I mentioned earlier,
you really do a lot to give young people the information
that they need to.
uh, you know, get into the game industry or navigate through the game industry.
Um, you do that, you know, through, uh, projects at, at GDC and, and just in
general, uh, but, uh, for, for writers who are trying to, uh, get into the industry.
Uh, you know, what's, what's Brandon Sheffield's, uh, tip for that.
Yeah, so I actually recently did a little talk at a group called Gameheads in Oakland,
which is all about kind of youth of color breaking into the game industry and stuff.
I mean, number one tip is, of course, do writing.
Do a bunch of writing.
And get critiques.
And try to do better.
And realize that you can always do better.
And, like, this isn't exactly game-specific either, but I also think it's super important
for people to figure out what their own taste is and write things based on that.
I remember in high school I got, um...
invited some
writer's forum or something like that
and i decided this was going to be a good time to challenge myself and
write
like a sci-fi story that was out of my comfort zone
and uh... it totally
fell flat
what i learned from that experience was
not that i shouldn't have
written a sci-fi story or something but that i shouldn't have tried to
right so far beyond my feelings and my experience and whenever you can.
Not that people shouldn't branch out, because they obviously should, but if you are going
to branch out, you need to ground it in stuff that you know super well first.
So you can take the germ of something mundane and very familiar to you, and which might
be familiar to other people, like the particular ritual that you have for getting cereal in
the morning or something like that.
and then we pan out from this serial thing to we're in a hellscape or whatever.
It just helps to ground the experience and helps people to identify with it.
And I find that that's a mistake that a lot of young writers make,
is they try to go straight for the fantasy bit without doing the,
here's how this.
relates to my life and this is why it came from me as a person rather than anyone else.
Then in terms of game stuff, people should make Twine games, I think. That's good,
because Twine's free and it's really easy to use and you can make
visual novels with choices and things. Another tip that I have is...
If you write dialogue, try to read it out loud and see if it sounds extra stupid, because
that happens to me a lot.
I'll write something and I'll be like, is this fine?
And then I'll try to read it out loud or read it in my head and I'll be like, yeah, this
is not something a human being would say.
How loudly do you recommend reading it out loud?
Just the top of your lungs is probably...
Okay, good, I'm doing it right.
yeah just uh... get on public transit and uh... just just scream it out
but yeah also
just write
write for any game
that you can
my first video game that i
did any writing for was
oddly enough a capcom collection with digital eclipse back in two thousand five
uh... in digital eclipse's first iteration
And I was just writing some dumb quiz questions for a...
They had like a... there's this Capcom game called Quiz and Dragons, which had a bunch of quiz questions in it that were about Capcom.
And they wanted to re... renew those, and so I wrote some new Capcom trivia.
And, you know, that of course didn't do very much for me career-wise, because I was definitely
a footnote in that video game, and very little of it had to do with me.
But when I next then went to someone...
who needed a writer, I knew they needed a writer,
I was like, hire me because I can write things
and also I have one game credit and then you can see it.
And so having just-
For a little company called Capcom.
That's right.
So having any game credit can really help.
It is fun that, you know, now, I guess I've been doing writing in games for...
almost 15 years now and I can finally claim to have a million seller and that's Street Fighter
30th anniversary and it is like there's absolutely no way that that sold a million copies because of
me but I can still put it on my resume. You don't have to tell people that though. And that's what matters.
Yeah, oh that's so good. So we'll wrap it up here then. Indivisible, Lab Zero, it's Brandon Sheffield,
lead writer on the game. Highly recommend it, not just because he's my friend,
but it really is good. It does convey so many emotions. The battle system is so much fun
and check it out and thanks a lot for joining us, Brandon.
Thank you.
It was enjoyable.
That's what we came for.
What a weird way to say that.
What do human beings say that?
I didn't think they would.
Alright, we're back for a little bit.
This is where we reflect on our guests.
Reflect about them.
Talk about them behind their back.
Yeah, this is where, yeah, Brandon's gone now.
Yeah, this is where we talk crap.
So, uh, I got some juicy information on Brandon Sheffield, now that he's gone.
The man has 20 game consoles connected to his television set.
I'm trying to imagine, like, all at once? Like, that's...
Yeah, it's all at once.
I don't know.
I'm like staring at my TV in the background right now and just like, you can see the
cords hanging from behind the shelves and just this nightmare that if like a cat got
back there, they'd be stuck forever.
Like I can't imagine.
Yeah.
I'm looking, I'm looking at my, uh, entertainment system that has one
PlayStation 4 connected to it and one Apple TV and it just looks like a rat's nest.
So he, he must have some kind of system that makes that possible.
On the podcast, just to talk about cord management.
Yeah, yeah, we'll get him back on for that for the GDC podcast.
We need to have... GDC should have a Chord Management Summit.
I think that that would be well attended. No, but Brandon, we didn't even get to
talk about it. He's a multifaceted person, but he collects games and
he collects old hardware and things like that.
So it's there.
Yeah, he knows that stuff.
That is an area of interest and expertise.
And intrigue.
Yeah.
Well, what did you think about the conversation we had with Brandon?
Like I said, I kept kind of like it's mostly the cold brain
But I kept kind of like just zoning out and listening like I was just listening to a very good podcast
Conversation and forgetting to contribute but it's a really good
This wasn't just a live stream like for yeah, I know I just come in to these are my own exclusive little interviews
I can listen to and not contribute to but
I always like when we end up either on here the couple times I've been on the GDC
Twitch channel
And we're talking to like writers and stuff like that because I try to poke in I'm like, okay
But how do you how do you write good? How do you make words? Great?
and
Every time it's just like oh, yeah
I'm, just I just do and it just kind of works out like that
but
The that was kind of the case here too where I tried to like dig in like how does how does humor work?
How do you make jokes funny and just he explained his process but like the thing that's not being said there is
These are people with
20, 15 years in like experience and that it's just like a practice skill over and over and over again like he was saying with um
Just getting your first like game credits
but like all that kind of builds into experience that gives you the ability to just kind of like
Not overthink your jokes and just look at like the art you're given and be like, oh, this is a stick guy
This is the milk guy and just kind of like make that a funny productive thought
And that's kind of like a secret expertise that I would pick up. Yeah, just
Yeah, just get a time. I mean, you know, writers and journalists, not just those professions,
but anyone, I don't know, there's a certain kind of person that can only do anything on a deadline.
Yeah.
You know, and I'm kind of that way too.
Yep, same.
And yeah.
I'm sure that every single person that you know, I have worked with in uh in in journalism or writing or whatever
uh
They're the same way. I don't want to say when we're recording this podcast, but
Oh man
Yeah, this case in point
My other takeaway that I want to sneak in is anime is good and everyone should watch it
Yeah, and apparently you watch enough anime, then you'll get a video game credit somewhere.
Yeah, no, it was interesting for people should go watch The Promised Neverland.
It's on Crunchyroll, which is an anime viewing subscription.
It's like Netflix of anime.
But the things he was saying about characters in there kind of changed.
Like, I hadn't thought that deeply into it because I was just consuming my media.
But the way he was describing how certain characters are very driven and each the
conflict for the entire series is set up at the beginning and then it's these smaller
micro internal conflicts that create the suspense and like I
Don't know
I'm really interested to see what game that manifests into because just how he was describing it was like really great. So
Yeah, that's that's something that you know, where this just sounds like an
interesting I haven't seen it, but I haven't seen a lot of anime, those
Transformers, you know, count. Yeah. But, you know, that's such an interesting way
to create suspense without hiding everything. It's like, we're going to show you everything.
and you know we'll be able to draw the suspense from there is what it sounds like.
Yeah just like very like character driven turns where everything feels it's there's like mystery
novels you'll read where you'll get to the end you'll guess who the killer is and it's like
actually it's this guy because of this thing you that was kind of obscured for you and you don't
feel justified in it but uh the kind of turns he was talking about are those where you don't see
it coming but it still feels justified and like it fits into the overall narrative. Yeah.
Thank you, everybody, for joining me.
Chris and Alyssa, Anime Hour.
I will review anime on this podcast if you let me.
Do not.
Please do not.
Yeah, we can do that.
We'll add a segment.
Anime with Alyssa, sponsored by Subway.
OK.
No, we have no sponsorship with Subway.
A little game awards joke for you.
Yeah, we're very timely.
What were your big takeaways from the conversation
now that I've blabbed on?
Oh, no, no. Oh, you're not blabbing? Um, it's, uh...
I don't know, a lot of the stuff that Brandon, you know, talks about are conversations that I've had with him about writing.
And I think with him, I love the advice that he had at the end about, you know, finding your voice and, you know, not, you know,
I could tell that he was trying to walk a line between, you know, write what you know and also, you know,
Writing like branching out, you know into into new topics and just to be to be careful about that
but it is
It's just an interesting thing that I think that you can only
Figure out I mean you can watch YouTube videos. You can watch it
You know that that talk about process you can watch Brandon's, you know talk
you know on GDC vault or GDC YouTube, but
the only way that you're going to be able to figure that out is like writing and I know that
probably is really annoying whenever any you know young writer asks for advice and the advice
suggests well just write more but that that really is what it
It is what it is. I mean, you just have to keep on trying. And I do think that there is a point where it, you know, clicks or becomes more clear to you about the style, like your writing style.
Like, you know, if I'm sitting around and, you know, trying to write like Philip K. Dick or Ray Bradbury.
It's not gonna go so well for me and and in fact hasn't gone well for me
But that's kind of the thing I really like that idea of just kind of like figuring out you know
What you like and I also liked when talking about writing the dialogue for
invisible
Indivisible, it's kind of
that same idea
Excuse me, like
You know writing
Don't write necessarily for other people. I mean obviously you're writing for other people
But do something that you know write something that you
Enjoy, you know something that you enjoy, you know, there's gonna be somebody else out there that
That it connects with so
Yeah, there's a lot of stuff there, and it's kind of nice to talk to somebody that you
know about their craft, because usually we're just making dumb jokes.
But yeah, it was great.
So I think that about does it for this one.
You need to get loaded up on NyQuil or something.
Day quill?
It's ear pressure, so Benadryl is what I have to do, but I can't function as a human being
after taking that, so it's gotta be like, suffer through the work day and then just
go to sleep.
All right, yeah, or you could just take it off. Take it off. Take the afternoon off.
I don't know about that.
All right, well, we'll figure that out later on and thanks everybody for listening.
You can subscribe to us, you can follow us on Spotify, you know, rate us if you love us.
And you can also find us on GDC YouTube, Spotify, the Apple podcast thing,
and then what's the Android one? It's just Google Play, right?
Yeah, Google Play Music, even though it's not music.
But yeah, you'll find us.
I trust all of you. All right.
All right. This is Chris and Graf.
All right. Thanks, everyone. Bye.
you