All right, hey everybody.
Thanks for coming to our talk.
We make ARC.
A lot of us in this room also make ARC.
Got some of our team here.
We're gonna be talking to you a little bit
about our journey through early access,
and so let's go ahead and kick it off.
I'm Jesse Rapsack, art director, technical art director,
co-creative director with Jeremy on ARC.
I'm Jeremy Stiglitz, the lead designer,
lead programmer and co-creative director of ARC.
So we'll just start out real quick and get right into it and why we chose to ship our game in early access.
You know, Ark is a very large game in terms of scope, gameplay mechanics, and breadth of content,
and we're a small team, only about 25 people or so on the core team,
and it would be very difficult, maybe impossible, for us to really develop such a game
without large-scale testing and iteration.
And one of the concepts we've really tried to take farther in Ark than...
in other games we've created in the past
is the concept of emergent development.
And kind of maybe a similar concept to emergent gameplay,
where emergent gameplay would be gameplay mechanics
you don't necessarily plan for or predict as a designer.
Emergent development is kind of the concept
that we don't know every direction
the arc development process is going to take us.
And those things are kind of determined on the fly
based on community feedback and metrics.
throughout the early access process.
So one example of this is really like the
creative game play ideas.
We really iterate very heavily with the community on this.
If you've ever paid attention to our game,
we've got a very two-way dialogue.
We've got a great body of testers and people that
give us early feedback when we're working on stuff.
And we really implement those community suggestions
to make the game better.
And that's really a big part we think of being successful
in early access is establishing that relationship
with your game's community.
And so we'll be talking about that a little bit
during this presentation as well.
To say how we do it and maybe provide some ideas
on how you might do the same thing in your title
if you're gonna go the same route.
The concept of emergent development essentially
in our case means that we have a set of guiding first principles that really define whether
something is ARC, but we don't have a specific rigid master design document or master plan
that defines all of the gameplay.
features or content that we intend to have from start to finish.
And we essentially leave that to the iterative process of early access to guide the game development
as long as it fits within this first principles framework
and then of course a slightly more refined scorecard metric that we're going to go over later.
But I wanted to give you a sense of really what those first principles are.
in Ark's case.
What we're gonna do is walk through the original pitch
document for Ark, and this is effectively all that we have
as a design document for the game, master design document.
And essentially, we don't do anything in Ark
that would contradict this principles design document.
But this document is not necessarily a blueprint
for everything that goes in the game.
So don't contradict, but otherwise anything
that doesn't contradict is fair game.
That's pretty much what I just described.
So this is the original design document that we generated
prior to commencing development arc.
And I'm not gonna actually go into each detailed slide of it.
I'm gonna kind of step through it real fast.
But you'll get a sense of how high level it is.
And this is as close to a design document
as we have got on the title.
What's interesting is while it is very basic and high level,
it's all actually still accurate
to what the game's current state is.
We've never explicitly contradicted it.
And of course, if you go through and scrub through
the video recording of this,
you'll be able to look at the documents details
in more detail.
Probably worth noting too that the design spec
we put together here informed a lot of things.
It didn't just keep the team on the same page.
It also let us tell our partners, hardware partners,
platform partners, what the game was about
in a very succinct, easy to digest way.
And it just made it less complex to understand
the scope of the game we were trying to make
without getting into all the little nitty gritty details.
And effectively this mapped out a set of axioms
that defined what is ARK as a game.
And it gave us kind of some guardrails
when we had some ideas that maybe seemed like good ideas.
If they fit strongly outside of this framework,
then they would kind of be rejected out of hand.
But it gave us enough freedom to iterate
and kind of creatively brainstorm within this framework.
And as you can see, it's really more set of goals than a specific list of content. And that was
the whole thing. That's all of ARC's design document.
But out of that, we've added so many features
with the help of the community.
These are all actually features that explicitly came
out of community suggestions and community iteration.
And we're gonna go over shortly with how we kind of distill
when we get a bunch of suggestions on our forum or on Steam,
how do we actually distill that into what we decide
to implement in the game, since we obviously can't put
in everything that's suggested.
But as you can see, many things that run the gamut from
gameplay to UI to meta game mechanics.
So I'll talk a little bit about the community.
As Jeremy mentioned, we get lots of good feedback,
gameplay ideas directly from our community.
And we treat the community feedback in the same way we
treat our own feedback internally when we were first
making the game before we launched.
It's kind of a bottoms up approach, very playing the game.
We already know what the high level goals are,
so when we're playing the game and thinking about features
and listening to the way the community is playing the game,
we're thinking about all those things
Jeremy just mentioned with,
does it fit into our original plan?
Is it something that we feel makes the game better?
And we've got a bunch of metrics around that as well.
But the first thing is really to have that community
in the first place.
And if you're going to do an early access title,
it's really one of the most important things.
When you go to launch your game, you better be ready with community management and take it
very seriously. Our community managers are very good at what they do. They have a pulse on the
community and they reinforce the relationship we have with the community on a daily basis. I
don't want to make them blush. Some of them are in the room here.
So one of the first things we feel is really to get the community excited and to keep them excited
Because hype can be really good. We do this through a combination of patch notes
We're always writing up what's coming so people know what to look forward to
might not always be exactly when it's coming,
but we kind of leave that stuff up there
so that people kind of know down the road,
like a mini road map a little bit
of what they can look forward to
in the coming months of development.
Teasers we do all the time.
When we first launched ARC,
we started putting out dossiers
for all the dinosaurs that would be in the game.
Even though some of them weren't coming
for months or even years,
players still got to see the dinosaurs
and the creatures that would be in the game,
hear a little bit about their abilities
and the things that they might do.
and also give them an idea of kind of the scope
that was like ahead of development.
You know, it's one thing to read about words on a page,
the Steam page about what we're going to put in the game,
but when you start seeing visuals
and start seeing stuff early, it's real.
you start to feel a little bit more attached to it
and excited about it.
Announcements, too, to go right along with those teasers.
Whenever we have something new that's going into the game,
we really spend a lot of time
putting together those announcements,
working to get out media alerts and press releases
about the content that we're going into the game.
And it's not just for content, it's for things that we do
around the community that we'll see here
in a couple more slides.
So touching on that, spreading the word is really important.
How do you get the word out about, you know,
all this hype that you're generating?
I mentioned media alerts and press releases.
It's really good to, if you don't have a PR company
or a media company to...
partner with one that can help you get into voicing your stuff that way. Because we all spend a lot of time making games.
We're not PR experts. We don't have the relationships with the media and all that stuff to do that.
So it's really beneficial to not spend a lot of time on that,
but partner with somebody that can help you maximize your time around those alerts.
We always do trailers, like I mentioned,
the visuals are very good.
Trailers, screenshots, presentations for everything we do.
We really want players to get super excited
about the stuff that we're putting out,
whether it's coming right now,
which is usually the way we do things.
It's like, here's the trailer, it's available today,
which is very useful for getting the word out
because everybody's so excited about it
that they want to play it right now.
So we try to pair those announcements and the media
with gameplay stuff available right now as well,
and it's probably a good practice.
So we post stuff on our website, survivethearc.com.
We mirror that on Steam and Reddit.
We try to foster communities where players congregate.
You know, we love our website.
It evolved in a similar way to development
where it kind of emerged out of a need for.
a place for players of all platforms to go.
But a lot of people like to chat on Reddit.
They like to chat on Steam.
So we try to mirror our messaging there
and spend most of our time moderating our own site.
But we go out on social media
and the various console platforms,
PlayStation and Xbox have their own ways
to talk to the communities.
Again, everything I'm talking about here is community management.
So going back to the first thing I said, it's very important that you have somebody or multiple
somebody, they're going to focus on this so you can spend time developing your game and
all the great work you do gets out to the community and they get very excited about
it.
So we want to keep the conversation flowing with our community.
We've got a variety of ways to do this that we came up with with our community team.
One is one we call community crunch and
this is something that Jatt runs all the time and Jen and it's
just the latest cool stuff from the community.
I mean, Ark is a game with emerging gameplay
about creating stuff.
You see all sorts of things from music videos
to funny cartoons to screenshots
and media that people are taking.
And we encourage that because people have a lot of fun
with their creativity.
We want to highlight it when it's.
awesome and amazing. Sometimes even if it's questionable, but it's still awesome. We put
that out there, we put it in our spotlights. Anything anybody sends us, we've got fan made
dossiers, screenshots. It really makes the community feel like we're listening to them,
which we are, and we're valuing the work that they're doing inside of our game that's so
important to them. And it really creates that kind of like two-way communication pipeline we
talked about. And we also do some content sneak peeks within the community crunch.
Occasionally we'll put out a little teaser or something that's outside of our normal
template for doing that sort of thing, like a little mysterious graphic of something that's
hinted that might be, you know, we did that when we were launching new creatures that
hadn't been in the scope of the game before.
We put mysterious dossiers in the community crunch and stuff like that.
So hiding little Easter eggs in our community stuff.
And then we do smaller announcements with Community Crunch,
like things about sales, merchandising, gameplay tweaks.
Again, this is all community stuff.
Very important to have somebody that's on top of this.
Arc Digest is really great too.
Usually this is Jeremy answering direct questions
from community members, players.
They submit them all, we call them,
we answer their questions, listen to their feedback.
And again, it's that two-way communication
with the community.
So we're not just telling them stuff.
We're listening to them and responding to it.
Another thing we do is rewarding our community for all of this great two-way relationship we have.
We really try to give back to them.
We call them out in all of the weekly spotlights with Community Crunch.
We run contests and prizes.
We reward people for building beautiful things in the game.
We give them things like Steam gift cards, you know, a couple bucks here, call-outs there, free keys here.
We run mod contests.
We partner with...
partners like NVIDIA with new platforms like Ansel,
and we integrated that, we run some contests for that.
And we just now launched a sponsored mods program,
which is kind of a middle ground
between being a professional game developer
and being a hobbyist.
There's not really a way for people
to reliably sell their mods right now.
out there, but ARK is a game that has a lot of mods,
a lot of high quality mods.
This video here is our first sponsored mods
that we're starting this month,
and we're literally funding these people
to keep making their great mods,
because we don't want them to stop or give up
because the pressures of life or their job or whatever
are too much and they have to stop working on it.
We really want to reinforce the work that they're doing
and the best mods...
will rise to the top and month over month we'll continue to find those that the players are
playing and that they're really loving. A couple serious stuff, too, when it comes to
rewarding people. We've in the past done exploit bounties, making sure that anything that's
kind of a hack or some sort of thing that's detrimental to the game, we can try to reward
people for finding those things instead of exploiting them for their own personal gain.
It just goes along with this whole two-way street
we're talking about.
So the result of all this is that you have a community
that's passionate, which we do.
They're entitled, they know that they're part
of development and they want to continue to contribute.
they've got kind of an expectation from you
and you've got an expectation from them.
They've got a voice and they've got all these ideas,
these great ideas sometimes,
sometimes not the greatest ideas
to contribute back to development.
So that's the big question.
How do you know?
and you shouldn't always listen to your community
and what they are saying, and you have to decide.
All these emergent features we talked about earlier
kind of went down a path, and throughout development
we thought about how do we call these
and how do we take these and find the best ones
and actually implement them, and that's what we're gonna
talk a little bit about now.
Get through this one.
I mean, ultimately, the community really does have a bigger, more creative brain than any of us could possibly have by ourselves.
But it also can pull the game in a thousand different directions.
And, you know, the loudest voice in the room isn't necessarily representative of the larger player base.
And to the extent that it's the loudest voice in the room, it might also be an impossible idea.
And for...
various reasons it's important to have some kind of metric or scorecard we
found to kind of weight ideas against gameplay ideas whether they're coming
from us or even coming from the community we need a way to gauge their
viability and desirability that was
Beyond just how vocal people or even ourselves were about doing a specific idea
This was particularly important because the game was live. So any misstep, you know, ultimately would cost us in terms of
players
experiencing
the better or worse that we might put into the game.
So ultimately we came around to implement
a feature scorecard into our internal design process
that would allow us to grade potential ideas
against a variety of criteria.
And I'm gonna go over how the scorecard works.
Okay, so it's a series of points,
and ultimately there's a threshold
over which a specific idea must reach
for it to be like automatically included in the game
that we should totally do it.
And the first kind of question is, do we want to do it?
Is it, doesn't necessarily mean that we came up
with the idea, that's irrelevant.
But is it something that we, internally at Wildcard,
are really passionate about?
Easy enough for us to determine.
Just ask the team.
Then...
do we think the community wants it?
And again, it's not necessarily as simple as saying
we should do everything the community wants
and nothing the community doesn't want.
As we're gonna see, some things the community wants
turn out not to be so great,
and something the community doesn't want,
at least initially before it comes out,
say they don't want, actually turn out to be quite useful
to the long-term health of the game.
But we try and gauge whether the community wants it.
community is going to want something. That's usually by putting it in patch notes, by
telegraphing it on social media, and having our very talented community team
gauge the response through a variety of metrics. However, this does tend to boil
down to the loudest voice in the room, so that's why it's not the only criteria
or it's not necessarily weighted any higher than our own voice in the matter.
The other question is, is it good for new players?
If you just have downloaded Arc Today,
you're a new noob on the island starting out,
is this going to help you get into the game?
Is it gonna be neutral?
Some things we add that are actually very useful
can actually be negative towards a new player in the game.
You'll see one of those later that's actually a good feature overall for the game,
but it's not necessarily helpful for new players.
But generally that's a criteria we want to bias towards,
is things that are good or at the very least neutral for the new player experience.
Is the idea beneficial to development?
What that means is, it's shipping the game, specifically.
I'm not talking about whether it's good for marketing purposes or anything else.
I'm talking about is this feature in line with the ideas of what ARK needs to have to ship
or does this idea kind of sit outside that rubric, maybe make the game take longer to ship,
make it more complicated to ship, add a lot more work to what would be the total content set of the game.
Does it lack controversy? Obviously we're not afraid of controversy at wild card as you've
probably seen, so it's not weighted as highly as the other points. But nevertheless, it's
still something we try to factor in. Is this going to be controversial or is it not?
And we gauge this, by the way, again, by reading the community posts and taking polls.
It's worth noting that this is a little different than whether the community wants it.
What we look for in terms of gauging whether the community wants it is whether there's any
sizable group of players out there saying, this is really cool, this is a good idea.
Conversely, is whether there's also a sizable group saying no.
is easy to implement.
You know, like any human beings
are sometimes afraid of challenges,
so we don't like to necessarily take on things
that we think are gonna be very, very difficult for us.
But it's not the most overriding determining factor,
and usually the producers will give us
a pretty good estimate of what it's gonna take
to make it happen.
Final criteria is can we do a good job with it?
We don't necessarily love to jump into tasks
that we think inherently are going to break our team,
technically or creatively,
that we think we're going to do a poor job at,
and sometimes that's inevitable,
and we just have to give it a shot anyway.
the greater good, but other times that can be a factor in deciding whether or not to
go into doing a feature if we think it's just beyond our capability to do what we would
be proud of with it.
But then what we do is we take the results of all of these
criteria and sometimes it can be a neutral, a slash,
zero points, or a check mark would be the positive points
or a X would be negative points and we add it up.
And we consider our threshold to be two.
If it's two or above,
we should do it. Less than two, we probably shouldn't do it. And it's really just that
simple. And we kind of run this through every new feature now that comes through the
pipeline. And there we go.
Now we're gonna talk a little bit,
before we get into how this scorecard actually applies
to some of the features in the game,
let's talk about a subject which many PC developers
will probably be familiar with, which is Steam reviews
and how we think that actually relates
to looking at the feedback we get
from some of these features.
We don't consider it to be the overall metric
that is most meaningful and here's why.
Yeah, it's worth noting that Steam actually does encourage users to provide any type of feedback that feels relevant to a game's development, not just based on a game's merits.
So, you'll find that this kind of biases the recent reviews portion of Steam to...
what's been going on with the game in the last 30 days or so in a lot of cases. And we've
noticed we've gotten some review bombs and they can be very informative as kind of a
response to your actions. And this has been not just for things in the game but for things
that have nothing to do with the game development itself. And because of that, it's kind of
a little bit to be taken in consideration with the other factors you use to judge the
health of the game.
And one thing is with the reviews themselves,
it's really just generally another metric for temperature.
You know, Jeremy, you've got probably
some thoughts on that, but.
Steam reviews, in our opinion, are very, very helpful
for gauging the...
Feeling of your community and it is important to take that into consideration
But they're not necessarily as useful for gauging the overall health of your game in my opinion the most important metric for that in
terms of steam at least is
Concurrent user count players who's actually playing your game, and how many of them are there?
We've hit some of our highest CCUs ever six digits
We've had some of our lowest steam reviews ever
And take from that what you will, but our goal is that people are playing the game,
and they are staying in the game.
And that ultimately, hopefully means a fun game, but we are not as obsessed over our
Steam reviews as we are about player engagement in the title.
And now we're going to look at some historical examples about how the scorecard was used or not used
relative to features in the game, and ultimately what happened.
What did the data post-launch of a feature actually show, if we could gauge it,
in terms of the impact, and does it match up with what the scorecard would predict?
First we're gonna talk about survival of the fittest,
which I more or less said, this will be a great idea.
We have a quote associated with each feature.
In fact, the scorecard itself was designed
in response to the failure that was survival of the fittest
and a subsequent feature.
We eventually came to the viewpoint that we needed
a system to actually make such decisions.
We couldn't go solely based on our gut.
So this one's on me.
In terms of the scorecard,
I'm gonna briefly walk you through
how it kind of sort of stacks up.
We wanted to do it.
It's fun.
We really like the game mode.
We thought it was a worthy shot
at trying to do some e-sports type gameplay.
Frankly, what we were getting from the community was they wanted it too.
We had a lot of fun running tournaments, we got a lot of great feedback that this was something players were really enjoying.
It was Sotif, by the way, Survival of the Fittest, originally began as a mod for ARK that we created as a test,
and the feedback there was, I mean, it was a super popular mod.
you know, hundreds and hundreds of thousands of downloads,
lots of people viewing these play sessions.
We still, to this day, have people who are really,
really hardcore into it.
We thought, you know, very much based on what we could tell,
the community was enthused about it, and I think they were.
It's neutral for new players.
I mean, obviously it's not what a new player
is really caring about when they buy Ark Survival Evolved,
and that probably should have been the first warning sign.
It's not beneficial to development
in the sense of shipping Ark Survival Evolved.
also another warning sign, it didn't lack controversy because even though the community
wanted it, it was still controversial. Remember what I was saying about in terms of engaging
with the community who wants something, we're just looking for a core of really positive feedback.
But it certainly was controversial to the extent that should we be utilizing development time and
development resources for making a mode that is...
not really considered to be a core feature of the game,
should that really be our priority?
And that was the controversy justified from that standpoint.
It certainly wasn't easy to implement.
We ultimately did spin it off as an entirely separate,
free product related to the ARK Survival Evolved game, but...
That's a lot of work to launch in a completely separate application and manage that and QA
that.
Very significant time investment there.
And as far as doing a great job, neutral at best.
I mean, while the game mode certainly was very fun, even in its final form.
Wildcard is not an esports company and ultimately could not build the systems fast enough to support esports level gameplay
with the full tournament and matchmaking systems that people expect of that genre at this point in time.
So, you know, best case scenario, we couldn't do a great job relative to player expectations.
So, you know, ultimately where this gets us is, we, you know, perceived that there was a demand for it.
There was obviously a great majority of players who at best didn't care.
And it was costly to develop.
The CCUs were not impressive to say the least.
That's the CCUs chart right there on the bottom, by the way.
Yeah. Ultimately a failure.
And at the time, we did not have the scorecard.
So how do we, you know, quantitatively looked at this?
We hopefully would have made a different decision about whether to go forward with it.
Ah yes, my favorite quote.
The fact that Studio Money Grab's still in business
is a shame.
Scorched Earth, as you may know, is a paid DLC,
launched in early access.
Don't recommend that anybody really does this,
but for us, it was a success for a lot of reasons,
and we'll go through that right now.
So we wanted to do it because it was important
to our development.
It was part of our pipeline for creating new content,
new maps that players could go to,
and it allowed us to really develop portions of the game
that we needed to do for launch.
We had kind of a huge controversial thing happen
when we launched it where of course people were upset
that any early access game could do such a thing.
So we did get a lot of that sort of pushback
and there was a big review bomb as a result of this.
You can see that's our reviews chart on the top there.
That's when we launched Scorched Earth.
Those are the reviews for ARK
and it was pretty bad for a couple weeks
of negative reviews.
But it was still number one on Steam for over a week.
The expansion pack was.
The game, the base game was number two on Steam
at the same time.
The expansion pack was highly rated,
higher than ARK had ever been, 82%.
And there was also a large increase
in the daily user counts.
I mean, people were loving the content,
they were playing it,
and the user counts were just going up.
So for all of these reasons,
Scorce Earth for us was a success.
Players loved it.
It was a financial success.
It helped us get closer to the game's development.
And even kind of knowing what we do now about launching,
we'd probably still do it because it
was such an important part of our road to launch.
The next thing we would apply to the scorecard
is the dino rebalance.
And this ultimately had us going through and,
I like that quote.
This ultimately had us going through
and fixing some serious magic numbers
associated with how powerful,
I mean, what has that dinosaur been doing?
It's killing like humongous giganosauruses
all over the place.
So we needed to rescale how powerful players' dinosaurs were.
And this is always a tough challenge in a live game
because players like candy.
And when you take the candy away,
they can be pretty vocal about it.
But sometimes that's necessary
because too much candy can make someone sick,
to take that metaphor all the way through.
So, we wanted to do it.
We knew the numbers and how they were scaled
in terms of these tame dinosaurs
becoming God-killing machines was unsustainable.
The general consensus from the community prior to releasing this was they did not want their dinosaurs to become weaker.
It is good for new players because ultimately people's super tame dinos were unkillable for new players.
So it gave new players more of a slightly more level power ramp relative to people who had...
already gotten Tamed Dinosaurs.
It was beneficial to development in the sense that
we were trying to shape the game a little closer
to its final balance and so doing this.
It certainly was not without controversy.
Prior and post its launch, there were many people
who said that they would never play Ark again
and then they played Ark again.
But it was easy to implement.
Ultimately we're just talking about changing some numbers
behind the scenes and because it was easy to implement,
we could do a good job.
It was not the most technically difficult thing.
But there we go.
I mean, certainly, you know,
there was a bit of a review hit for that,
like many things we do,
but the ultimate data, as you can see in that graph there,
it was very clear when it came out,
the player counts went up and they never went back down.
So, you know, sometimes this is one of those cases
where the community, prior to its release,
and in the immediate post of its release
was telling us no, no, no, but ultimately
was helpful for the health, the long-term health
of the meta game.
And I would say that many players,
probably most players by this point,
have seen that I think rescaling those numbers
has given the game a longer tail
and have probably appreciated that in the long term.
And I guess the general rule I would draw from that is
sometimes you have to do what's necessary for the long-term health of the game
in spite of maybe some short-term negative consequences.
Swamp fever is the worst thing I have ever experienced.
That's a good one too.
So this one was the other thing Jeremy mentioned
that kind of made us realize we need
this sort of scoring system.
We really wanted it.
It was kind of part of our original plan
to add communicable diseases to the game
and to really kind of make that survival aspect
a little bit more hardcore,
make you have to deal with a little bit more stuff.
The community, some people liked it,
some people didn't like it.
They probably didn't know what they were in for
before they had that feeling though.
What ended up happening was we implemented this feature
and it turned out to be very bad for new players.
It was the requirements to construct an antidote
were very high in the game.
It was very easy to catch swamp fever.
And so the new players were just getting like wrecked.
by this feature.
And the players that are already good at the game
were just super annoyed by it,
because they're like, well, great,
now I have to make more antidote.
And so it was kind of like something
that we felt was beneficial to development,
because it was getting us closer to our goals,
but it ended up being super controversial.
Even though it was easy to implement, there is like...
we really didn't do the best job doing it in the end,
retrospectively.
And the interesting thing about Swamp Fever
was that there wasn't really a huge outcry
of like, this is terrible,
even though that quote literally says that.
But the community did hate it,
but they weren't responding in some of the other ways.
Like we weren't getting like hammered with negative reviews.
You know, there were threads popping up
and like, oh, this is bad.
This is, I can't believe Wildcard's doing this, whatever.
But it wasn't like,
Crazy, I mean we always see that.
Anytime you do something, it's the worst thing ever.
But we did notice there was a steady downward CCU trend.
And for us, that's very strange.
And so the only thing that we could conclude
was that Swamp Fever was pushing players from the game.
New players were coming into the game,
getting Swamp Fever and just quitting
because they would just die over and over.
Players that were more advanced were just like,
well, I'm gonna sit this out until
this whole thing gets figured out
because I don't wanna like ruin my character
and all of my equipment.
Wait out the apocalypse.
Exactly.
So we really miscalculated the effect
this would have on everybody, especially new players,
but it just made the game very difficult to play
and this is definitely a failure.
And this, because it was kind of a sneaker failure,
we're like, how do we?
How do we tell in the future if something like this comes up?
And it really helped us kind of design this scorecard
around the things that are most important in decision making.
And in our scorecard, it's something we shouldn't have done
if we had used the scorecard on this feature.
This one is a feature that allows people in ARC to transfer their progress between servers.
Science based.
Yes. Like most things in ARC.
And it definitely is a...
not conversion was a bold move on our part if I don't say so myself. So when we look at the
scorecard though, it's actually quite directly and dramatically indicative of we should do it.
And we wanted to do it because we thought this would make the Meta game much more
interesting. We like.
dynamic mega games. We noticed a lot of these, prior to this a lot of the servers were
becoming ossified, static, the alpha tribes, the big dogs were just sitting on a server and
nobody could touch them because any time someone would join that server they would squash
them like a bug. And what cross arc lets you do is if you're a big tribe on another server you
can warp in all of your powerful stuff and you can really have alpha tribes from multiple
servers going at it.
in a dynamic way, so you don't get this static, frozen balance of power on a single server.
You can also have multiple tribes from different servers team up to take down a super tribe.
So we wanted to do it. We thought it would have some great long-term benefits to the game.
The community was...
apathetic at best. There were a few people who thought it was a good idea, but no one was
really like, yeah, tie all the servers together. It's not really good for new players, let's be
honest about this. Because if you're a new player just trying to start out in the arc, you
don't really need, and you're just getting your little thatch hut set up, you don't really need
some gods from above just swarming down and deciding that they don't like you on their beach
and wiping you out. So it's not really a new player thing, it's more of an advanced player
mechanic.
Not really helpful for that, but this is one of those cases maybe where the long-term health of the game isn't explicitly
oriented towards just the new player. It is beneficial to development in multiple, for multiple reasons. One,
we're interested in having a long-term tail for the game, but two, we also needed this technology to better support
DLC in the future. We wanted to allow players to progress their characters
from one server to another to enter DLC servers without losing or having to
losing the progress or having to start over from scratch and so this
technology was necessary to support that. Therefore in line with our long-term
technical goals. Certainly didn't lack controversy though when this rolled out
there are many threads on all of our channels.
popping up, there was a lot of people on both sides of the fence, so we certainly think the
community was and is split over it. It was fairly easy for us to implement given we actually
had already built the technology for this for DLC. We just had to kind of widen it and
change a few back end things to allow it to operate between all servers and not just from a
non-DLC server to a DLC server. We figured we could do a pretty good job at it given that
we had already kind of experimented with the technology for DLC transfer.
An interesting thing happened when we released this feature.
the meta game did improve.
The people who thought Ark had just become a frozen static,
you know, wasteland of alpha tribes
sitting on their unassailable fortresses
found that they actually had to compete to survive again,
no matter how powerful they thought they were.
And over time, to this day,
our CCUs have continued to trend upwards as a result
of this feature, probably primarily.
So by the metric we consider most important,
people playing our game,
we consider it a success and the scorecard bears that out.
All right. This is a little embarrassing. Sorry we have to talk about this. I would
like to apologize for our sheep gate scenario. In case you missed it, this was a little controversy
that arose while we were all on vacation and during the holiday time frame, of course.
But basically, ARK was nominated for a Steam Award,
and it was best use of a farm animal.
We thought, hey, we don't really have any farm animals,
so maybe it'd be cool to add one if we won.
That would be cool, right?
Like maybe people would like that,
and they might wanna vote for the game.
Yeah, guess what?
People felt pretty bribed, apparently, by that.
And news articles, left and right.
Wildcards, gummy developer,
bribing players for a Steam Award.
Mind you, the Steam Awards are very silly.
Like, if you don't know about the Steam Awards,
they're very silly.
And we had a really quick onset of negative press for us,
you know, wanting to give back
and put something in the game.
And we got kind of a mild review bomb from this,
but...
you know, we just thought it wasn't really worth it.
Like if you go through our scorecard,
like we wanted to do this
because we thought it was a cool idea.
The community didn't want it
because like they didn't even know about it.
And once they heard about it,
you know, they definitely were upset about it.
We kind of like
didn't matter to new players at all.
It didn't really help us get closer to launch.
Pretty much, there was no reason to do this,
except we thought we could do a good job at it,
and we thought it was kind of fun.
Unfortunately, there was no real direct positive effect
from this whole idea of putting a sheep in the game,
and it was not really doing anything to help us
in a time when the game was already doing really well.
Like the CCUs were going up.
crazy because of the holidays and the sales and everybody is getting into new games and
this didn't really add anything to the community or the game.
So we kind of quickly realized this and adjusted our messaging and decided, look, regardless
of what happens with the Steam Wars, we're going to put the sheep in the game anyway
because we really thought it was fun and why not have farm animals in ARK.
It was a failure the way we tried to approach it,
but we quickly fixed it and I think we turned it into a win
because now we have cool sheep shearing and growable hair
and all sorts of stuff spawned off from this sheep thing.
But we probably would have handled it slightly differently
if we were to kind of rewind
and rethink things a little bit.
you know, applying the scorecard isn't always about looking at cases that are, you know,
historical. We also, as we indicated now, use it going forward.
We did just launch a feature so I guess this is technically a historical case as well but we'll go
through it anyway. We want to apply the scorecard to one of our most recently launched features
which is called Tech Tier. And Tech Tier is basically a set of sci-fi items for the game
that pretty much dramatically change how the game is played in the long term.
You know, we really wanted to do tech tier, the sci-fi stuff, because it was always in line with our vision for Ark.
I don't remember if it's in the pitch document, but I'm pretty sure we imply there's a real serious sci-fi aspect of the game.
We viewed Ark from the beginning as starting with cavemen and ending at Halo.
and so very much completing our vision
of the player's power progression to the end game.
The community is for this.
I mean, they think it's pretty cool.
New players, eh, it's really an end game type of mechanic.
Look, we could ship without it
and still have what we consider to be a complete game,
so it's not really beneficial to development.
It is controversial, though.
It's a feature which, if you're just interested
in this primitive kind of survival.
maybe actually diminishes the feeling of
being in a primitive lost world.
Of course, we already had guns made out of raw materials,
so it's kind of debatable how realistic ARK was
prior to the introduction of laser pistols,
but I think that players did feel that maybe it diminishes
the realism of the title.
And it's not easy to implement.
It's a lot of content that is actually fairly orthogonal
to the...
mechanics of the main game. We're talking about laser guns and force fields and cloning
chambers and teleporters. These are all very distinct pieces of functionality that don't
really overlap with the rest of the title. So from that standpoint, there's some overhead.
Not easy to implement. However, the team's really engaged with it artistically and
creatively, so we're not considering an afterthought. We do think we can do a good job at
it. So it ultimately hit the
you know, criteria of we should do it.
And sorry, here's all the things I just said.
But here's the interesting thing.
So it's a should do it on a scorecard,
and about a week after we launched this feature,
we hit our highest CCUs ever.
Six figures, over 100K players playing the title
on Steam simultaneously.
So, you know,
Is there a direct cause and effect relationship there? I think, likely.
The addition of this feature provides content for the hardest of the hardcore players,
the endgame players, who otherwise might not have anything to do in the game anymore.
And, you know, targeting them with some long-term content and mechanics,
it was part of our goal with this and probably brought a lot of those players back into the title.
So we consider that a success. So far, so good.
So underwater bases is a feature we haven't launched yet,
but everybody knows about.
And it's something people are really excited about.
As you can see, this person's been waiting for years
for underwater bases.
Note that Ark has not shipped years ago,
but just small minor points.
So we say we don't really want it
because it kind of adds a lot of work to our plate
and it kind of changes a lot of dynamics
about the game in a way we'll have to deal with.
for development.
We definitely know the community wants it.
There's no doubt about that.
There's a lot of underwater ocean space in ARK
and players want to make use of that space for sure.
There's kind of like, nah, neutral on new players
because a lot of the underwater content
and especially the tech tier is geared towards the end game.
But new players are in tribes and they can team up
with players that have underwater bases
and there's nothing preventing them
from engaging in that content.
And beneficial to development,
honestly we could ship the game without it.
So it doesn't really help us get closer to launch in that.
regard. We really feel like it straight up lacks controversy.
Like, nobody's like, they better not put underwater bases in this
game or I am quitting ARK. ARK is dead to me. That is not what
anybody is saying. But it is really hard to implement. I mean,
it's a totally new system. You know, we have to deal with, like,
physics changing and there's oxygen and then there's not
oxygen and then, you know, there's all sorts of collision
problems we're going to probably have to deal with. And again,
it's another place where people can build bases that might get
modified if we update maps and things like that later,
introducing more bug cases.
And, you know, it's like, honestly,
something we're like a little hesitant
because of all those complexities.
How good of a job can we do with this?
We're gonna do our best at it, as we always do.
But just going into it, we're a little like,
man, this is gonna be a lot of work.
And, you know, like.
it's hard. To be honest, it's going to be a hard feature. And it's not because we don't think it
will be good for people that we're hesitant to do it. We really think it will be awesome. But
you know, it's just we're human and stuff's hard and it's getting close to launch. But we're
already publicly committed to this. No way around that. Community really wants it. And
there's kind of this whole risk reward thing. It's not like survival of the fittest where, you
know, it's high risk and if it fails, it's like really.
not the best thing.
But this is, you know what,
if it doesn't work out perfectly,
if it's got its issues,
it's a little bit of a less impact
on the game in a negative way.
And it's another feature that we can add.
And it's not something that we're overly scared about
being really bad in any way.
So we think that we're gonna take a leap of faith,
even though the...
Scorecard says we should not do underwater bases.
We're kind of going to ignore that.
And that's a good point about this whole system
is that sometimes you just have to go
with your gut on something.
And even though this feature is something
that we probably shouldn't do based on our own scoring
system, we're just going to do it anyway.
And the risk is not great enough that it's
going to kill us if it ends up being a failure.
We'll see where we end up in a month.
Yeah, I may be saying something different
after like 100 hour weeks of no sleep
for the next four weeks.
So anyway, yeah, just to recap.
So we have an interesting.
kind of overall process for making decisions in ARC
about what we do.
We, first off, keep the community really healthy
and engaged through weekly updates,
daily social engagement,
and a two-way communication process.
We essentially don't stick with a rigid,
static, top-down roadmap.
We go with more of a bottom-up approach.
to designing features in terms of soliciting community ideas.
But we don't just say, hey, if the community wants it,
it's something we should do.
We run it through a process now that
includes a grading system.
But we also don't religiously adhere to that either.
We still leave for an element of serendipity,
of inspiration, and of faith to get ultimately
to the bottom line of what should go in the game
and what shouldn't.
And if there's an element of risk in that,
then there's also an element of reward.
You know, overall, ARK certainly is a successful early access game.
The numbers kind of speak for themselves.
But it's definitely some things you have to keep in mind by going this route.
You are best off, in my opinion, not...
committing yourself to a static mindset of,
here's the game you're going to make,
and darn if anybody's going to tell you otherwise.
You realistically need to be prepared to swerve left
and swerve right based on how the community is perceiving
the direction of your game.
Essentially, keep an open mind and be very reactive.
It's really important to prioritize content in early access.
You'll see some games come out with a decent amount of content
and then really right away focus on bug fixes and performance stuff.
And that's all great. It's an important part of development.
But we really feel like the optimization and non-critical bug stuff
is less important than adding the content to the game that keeps people coming back.
It keeps new players coming to the game because there's new stuff.
It keeps old players still playing the game
because there's always new stuff to come back to.
And the way we've chosen to do early access
is throughout the rest of development,
we kind of front loaded all the content features
and planning to do the final optimization
and non-critical bug fixes towards the end of development.
A lot of people take issue with that in the player community.
Everybody has a bug that is the most important bug.
But in the broader player base, that may not be the case.
And we really try to prioritize which bugs actually get fixed
and which optimizations we do, because all that work
takes away from adding the new content to the game
that we want to add.
And it's important to note that nobody buys what they can't see.
So it's really important to keep the game visible.
Anytime you can take advantage of a sale, do it.
Combine it with a content update.
It's kind of the way we roll.
If there's a sale happening, whether it's on Xbox or PSN or
Steam, we think, OK, what content update can we combine
with that sale?
Let's put the game on sale.
Let's get it out there promoted, visible,
and in front of people so they can dive
into that new content.
It's not just a sale for sales sake,
it's a sale because there's something new.
And that's really important.
We really try to reinforce all of our updates,
as we mentioned earlier, through more media.
working with influencers and social channels
so people have an actionable item.
When it comes to what's happening with ARK,
they can go see something, watch something,
buy the latest content if they don't own the game yet.
And then really, it's doing all of that
throughout all of development.
And so, that's pretty much our spiel.
So, thank you.
Thank you everybody.
And I want to say thank you to everybody who's played ARK and enjoyed it.
We really wouldn't be here without you.
Exactly, yes.
We are hiring, by the way, so notice.
We've got a booth, so if you are one of these people with these talents,
please come talk to us.
And we have time for questions if anyone has questions
about anything related to ARK development or design or anything we talked about.
Hey, I'm working on a fighting game called Fantasy Strike for Steam Early Access.
And I had actually two questions for you.
First about PlayStation 4.
You don't have the Early Access label there because there's no such thing,
but you do have it on Xbox and Steam.
So how do you handle that?
Do you frame the exact same game as finished on one platform and not the other?
And the second question is that your slide at the very end
showed sales from 1 million to 7 million.
And most of your terrific talk was about kind of that journey from 1 million to 7 million.
But can you say something about how you were so incredibly successful?
with your first launch on early access.
Sure.
I'll give you a repeat question.
Okay, so the first question was about early access in PS4
and Ark's placement on PS4.
So Ark is technically not a early access title on PS4.
It's that moniker or program doesn't explicitly exist
at the present time on PS4.
It is noted on the store as an unfinished game, however,
or the game will be receiving lots of updates.
Oh, really?
I didn't realize that.
Yes.
Specifically, we just asked Sony,
can we put an unfinished game on the platform
as long as we're committing to finishing it
and rapidly updating it, and they said yes.
Well, it's also worth noting,
we had to actually pass full game cert,
which is not a requirement for Game Preview
or Steam, as you know.
But for Sony's platform, you have to go through cert to even put your game on there.
Technically certified as a retail title, but planning, you know, updated on a weekly basis.
And Sony has really good back-end systems to update the game rapidly,
so it's made it very effective to operate in that way on that platform.
The second question was about how are we successful early on at launch.
And I mean, I think two things really play into that.
Number one is, you know, having a...
a good idea that a large number of people are going to be interested in in the first place.
The, obviously, survival in dinosaurs was effective for us.
But secondly, it's the things we did around launch that really worked to our benefit.
Namely, right after launch, we were just updating the game five times a day.
I don't think anybody has updated the game, their title on early access as much as we did with
Arc for not just a day or a week or a month, but really the first six months. Now we've
obviously more lately not slowed but focused on larger patches released less frequently. That's
in order to stabilize the technical state of the game.
But very early on, our goal was to be there 24-7 to react to whatever issues were arising in the
online game day or night. And that was difficult, very, very difficult. But I think it really made
an impact because the launch of any online game is going to be very rocky and faced with a lot of
issues. And to the extent that we could, we tried to stay on top of them. And I think that helped
us continue the acceleration beyond the first few hours of launch.
And all the stuff we talked about with the community team. That's a very challenging time for the
community team as well. They have to stay on top of the launch, talk to people, let them know
what's going on, get stuff back to us. So that's why everything we talked about, even though it
was about all of the success up until now, it was really forged in the fire of those early
launch days, how we dealt with updates, how we dealt with the community, and we just kept
doing it the rest of the time until now. So. Thanks a lot, guys.
Hi. First of all, my favorite GDC talks are ones where developers talk frankly about their
failures as well as successes. So thank you for addressing sheep gate. That was really
awesome. The question that I have is about you guys talked a lot about, you know,
getting community feedback being a part of your scorecard system for whether or not you want to
implement a new feature. So if you are doing all this visible effort to get community
feedback on a potential new feature and then you decide not to do it, how do you break that to
the community? How do you go, you know, that can be a tricky point of communication. So
what's your strategy?
You know, that's a really good question.
The question was, when we inevitably are faced
with a feature that the community really wants,
maybe we've even solicited feedback from them
and then have to not do it
because it doesn't meet our overall criteria afterwards
for inclusion into the game, how do we break that?
to the community and not get skinned alive.
And the answer is unfortunately no good answer.
We have had to do that in the past.
And usually it just involves a very mea culpa sorry post.
And what we usually try to do is time it
with some sweetener.
So we have good news, bad news type situation.
news, you're getting something really cool that may be unrelated. Bad news, we had to cancel
this feature that you were looking forward to. And you'll get a set of players who will want
your head on a spike anyway, but at least there will be something to look forward to as well.
And that's the only thing you really can do at that point.
Hi, hello. I was wondering if after the early access you will wipe the servers?
That might be privileged information.
We are still considering what the best options are there,
whether it's to add new servers or keep the existing ones.
We're leaning towards, at the present time,
adding new servers.
We certainly have resources, financial resources.
So while having a lot of servers is costly,
when you look at the grand scope of player investment
and new players,
We're leaning towards adding new servers,
but honestly, we're gonna continue to kind of evaluate
the situation as we get closer to launch.
But that is, with any online game,
that goes through early access,
a challenge about how often you wipe, if you wipe at all,
and what do you do when you have a bunch of new players
coming in during the inevitable retail influx.
And so, we don't have a perfect solution,
but we're gonna be keeping an eye on that
and figuring it out as we get closer to the launch date.
Thank you. And also, please, if you can add a queue system. We would greatly appreciate it.
are thinking about it.
It's really technically complicated, but yeah, it's just.
How much is the scorecard?
On the technical complication side,
that would definitely be an X,
but definitely, I understand your pain
if you're on console especially.
Yes.
Thank you.
I spent Christmas, around Christmas.
and cleaning dishes, pressing X every 30 seconds. We saw somebody made a mechanical device to
press A button over and over again to try and join a server. That was the arc cue system.
That was a YouTube video. Sounds like there's a solution. Why do we need to implement
anything? Okay, thank you. Thanks. So I had a question. You touched on the end about using
influencers to sort of disseminate information. And I know from the beginning of the early
access, you had a very robust influencer program.
So how did you go about spinning that up, getting streamers and other influencers into the fold
and putting out regular content about the game and sort of building that community?
So the question was about influencers and how we kind of build up that sort of community, I guess, around it.
One thing I would say, I wasn't just talking about influencers in the terms of, you know, voicing the game and, you know, we're trying to get them to get the word out.
Influencers in the sense of content creators, like on YouTube, Twitch, people that are creating content for the game or they have their own fan bases.
And we really try to reinforce their popularity,
give them cool stuff to work with,
report on from the game's development.
Occasionally, we've done like an early look at something,
but we tend not to work that way
because we're always so close to launch.
But it's important with the influencers, I think,
to reinforce the good work they are doing.
If we have a video that we think is good from a content creator, we'll retweet it.
We'll give props to people that are creating content for the game.
If it's, you know, a music video or it's a funny comic that somebody's made,
those type of influencers are not like direct,
oh, I'm playing the game, watch me on Twitch.
Those are influencers that are spreading the word about the game.
And I think that's kind of the answer for us,
is reinforcing that relationship by...
being an amplifier to the stuff people are doing about our game
outside of us. I think we're almost done. Was that the no
more questions signal? We'll hang around a little bit.