OK, so welcome, everybody, and thank you for joining me
for my talk, Virtual Insanity, Lessons Learned
from Creating Virtual Reality Engine.
So let's get started.
So the agenda for today, I'm going
to take you through the horror engine, which is the technology
that this talk's based on.
So I'm going to be talking about what it is and what it does.
And then the inspirations behind it,
so the developers and the existing applications
that informed its development.
And then I'm gonna give a technical overview
of the minimum viable product.
So just underpinning the key functionality of what it does.
So then that should give a great background
to the lessons learned.
So I'm hoping that if you're here
because you need to know more
about creating your own technology,
that you should at the very least,
by the end of this talk,
have the confidence to go away and get started.
So, hello, yes.
I'm Liz McCurrey.
I love dinosaurs, first and foremost.
And I'm an educational evangelist for Unity.
But I'm.
But I'm actually a super recent graduate too.
So I graduated from a master's last year
in computer game software development.
So all the lessons that I'm sharing with you today
are super fresh.
And I'm also a Prince William Scholar,
so that's a partnership between BAFTA and Warner Brothers.
So if you are wanting to continue into higher education
in the entertainment industry,
I'd definitely look at the initiatives they offer
because for new talent,
because it was a game changer for me.
So the horror engine, what is it?
So it was the focus on my research project of my master's.
And it's...
An overall concept, so it's a set of ideals for what would be a fully formed engine that we may all be familiar with
and it was informed by my research into
virtual reality and horror and how the mechanics of virtual reality can really lend themselves to the horror genre.
I like to define it as
a prototype which shows the potential of social virtual reality
through the use of an interactive social screen.
So to add a little bit more color to that,
I'll go through what inspired it, who and what inspired it.
Unsurprisingly, virtual reality inspired it.
So last year was the consumer release of virtual reality.
We finally welcomed it into our homes and it has us now.
So we saw the commercial release of the PSVR for example, and the Vive, and we've also got mobile VR at our fingertips.
So as this all became more commercially available, it also became more available to developers and educational institutions.
And so with me starting my masters at the crest of this massive new wave of VR,
There were so many amazing experiences being made,
and not just in the games industry, but from TV,
and also educational and financial sectors.
So there was a massive wealth of inspiration
there being created for me to get to get grips with.
As I did my research though, it was often said that virtual reality was a very isolating experience.
So you're there in your headset and you're goofing around and doing whatever you're doing,
and your friends can only kind of watch you and guess.
But we've seen with the commercial release of VR that this idea has been addressed.
So, there's like the rec room for the Vive
and the playroom VR for the PlayStation VR,
which has addressed this more inclusive
and social idea of virtual reality.
So when I was doing my research,
the biggest area of inspiration
was a company called Triangular Pixels,
that I don't know if you've heard of.
They did a talk last year too.
And they used this idea of a social screen,
which I think was a term coined by Sony.
And so what this social screen does, as you can see here,
if you have a player in virtual reality,
the social screen gives you a window
into that virtual reality world.
So you can have access to information
about what's going on.
So this game here is called Smash Hit Blunder.
a plunder, and so you're sort of in a dungeon
and you're going around collecting treasure
and smashing things up in the process,
and they found that by using this social screen
and by giving information to the players outside of VR,
that the players in VR
may not be privy to, such as a timer or a leaderboard for example, it just really organically
created a more inclusive virtual reality experience and I just found that concept super interesting.
And then finally, horror.
So I could talk about horror forever,
so I'm gonna stop myself right there.
But I went around asking friends and other developers
what scared them, because horror's super subjective
and a lot of different things
scare a lot of different people.
But I spoke to Lizzie Atwood.
And she told me that her company, Furious Bee,
had created this little tech demo of what scared her.
And so you were in a house,
and you had an object in the house.
And every time you went looking at the object,
and it was outside your field of view,
its position updated,
so it was kind of like you were being followed,
like those creepy angels from Doctor Who.
And I just absolutely loved that.
And I thought, this is scaring her,
and it would be so cool if I could be the one
that's placing that creepy angel and scaring her.
And so that's really where the idea for the horror engine came to life.
So going back to the original definition then.
So it's a prototype, it's proof of concept
for social and more inclusive virtual reality.
through the use of an interactive social screen.
So the idea that while one of you is in VR,
another one of you on a separate machine
can manipulate that world and place objects
as an aim to scare your friends.
Because I'm terrible at that.
So why did I create it, other than the obvious?
Well,
As I said earlier, I started university at this peak of this amazing new wave.
So virtual reality in itself isn't a new technology, but this new wave, this new iteration of it
is.
It was just the perfect time to get involved.
And as a developer, this newness of it really fascinated me.
Which meant that I naturally wanted to get a better understanding of it.
I was one of those kids that couldn't just have a radio,
I had to take it apart and put it back together
to understand why the radio was a radio.
So, I could have...
used existing plugins and an existing engine
to create this experience.
But as a programming student,
I really wanted to create that code myself.
I wanted to write it myself, get an understanding of it,
and not just take for granted and at face value
what this plugin was telling me it did.
And I think as developers, it's super important
to understand more the technologies we're using every day
so we're able to leverage it
and just make better experiences.
And finally, giving back.
So, yes, virtual reality is ever-evolving
and we're finding out a lot of new developments,
but actually our industry is like that as a whole.
And I think it's really great
that anybody can contribute to that.
And it's important to do so,
to sort of keep the potential of what we're all making.
So now, onto the technical overview
of the minimum viable product, the MVP.
So I set out with this big goal that by the end of my master's I'd have made this engine.
But actually that doesn't just happen overnight or in a very short space of time.
So what I did was I started off with the minimum viable product for what I wanted to create.
So this is like the minimum functionality that you need in order to validate what you're creating.
So I split this into three areas,
which was the virtual reality integration,
the networking, and the rendering.
So this is what it built up to be.
So everything was built from the ground up
in C++ libraries using the Visual Studio's
integrated development environment, the IDE.
For the rendering, I used DirectX 11.
For virtuality integration, I use the C++ SDK from Oculus.
I use Windows Sockets libraries for networking, so
the communication between two machines.
And I use direct input for player movement.
So let's just take a little moment.
to consider what this minimum viable product is compared to what I overall wanted to create.
So you'll see straight away that it's missing quite a bit.
There's nothing, for example, for collision or audio.
And you'll also see that everything is set in stone.
So there's no abstraction, for example, to allow for the integration of another virtual
reality headset or rendering API.
And also setting in stone like this
really limits the release platform.
So there's all these considerations
that you would take for granted having used an engine.
So the MVP then, the minimum viable product,
is the minimum functionality before concerning itself
with all the outer intricacies
that you're going to have to consider
when you make your final project.
And just a word of advice that I learned from doing it this way
rather than using plugins is that when you use a plugin,
more often than not, the person who's created it
has an appreciation of the pipelines of the engine
that you're going to integrate it into.
So sometimes you don't have to alter too much
what you already have to be able to accommodate it
or get it to work how you would expect or you want it to.
Whereas if you build up a product in this way,
you really have to have a deep understanding
of what you're using.
So just because the Oculus SDK supports DirectX 11,
just by integrating and referencing that
in your existing DirectX 11 project
means it's gonna work as expected or at all.
There's a process of identifying the code that you need
and integrating that together appropriately.
And so the minimum variable product as a concept
looked like this.
So on one machine, the product would load
as a virtual reality experience.
So this is where the SDK was used, Oculus SDK.
And then on the mother machine,
you would have this interactive social screen.
So the player on this machine could use the grid system
to be able to place the objects.
and the network libraries were used to facilitate this data transfer between the two machines.
So while the player with the interactive social screen
could place the object and it would send the geometry type
and position to the VR machine,
which would manifest it in the VR world,
the VR world was always sending back
the position of the player in VR
so that the player with the social screen
could more strategically place those scares.
And you'll see there's a Twin Peaks
kind of aesthetic going on, that's my doing.
So in reality, it looked like this.
So this was the first time that I showed it to anybody,
actually.
So you can see the two-way machine communication
that I've talked about, the DK2 there.
And then the picture on the left was some concept art
done by my friend whose concept art is called Bradley.
and he mocked up a number of scenarios for what the MVP could be
the mechanics of it could be used for
so he came up with the idea of a detective game where
you could place clues and move the clues and that kind of thing
so it was really cool
so
this is the reason you're all here
so the lessons learned
I learned a lot doing this, some good, some bad.
And so what I've done is I've taken all that
and I've tried to condense them down
into what I think were the key important parts.
that I'm hoping will be useful to some of you.
So I've split them into three areas.
So one is pre-development,
so things to consider before you even get started.
Then development is early on in development
and iteratively throughout.
And then finally, just more personal lessons learned
about just being a developer and looking after yourself.
And all these are going to sound really obvious as well,
but actually when you get into that development headspace,
they quickly go out the window.
So it's worth remembering them.
So clear goals.
Yes, they sound obvious.
What do you want what you're creating to do?
But actually it goes beyond that,
and it's about what you want to achieve from it too.
So is there something that you want to collaborate to,
or something that you want to learn?
So for me, yes, it was an academic project.
And I wanted to create this multiplayer virtuality
experience.
That's what I wanted the technology to do.
But what I wanted personally was the ability
to learn more fundamentally how virtual reality code worked.
So then that leads quite naturally onto resource.
So you've identified what you want to do,
but now you need to think about how you're going to do it.
And there'll often be things that you forget.
So if you're not at university,
you need to sort of think about the software
and also the licenses,
and not just the development software.
Is there anything that you need outside of that?
There's also the consideration that if you're using virtual reality,
you're going to have to think about what headsets you have available,
but also the hardware to be able to run those headsets.
So for me, my machine at home didn't suffice,
and I had to make sure I was in the computer labs at university
all the time to be able to support the Oculus.
And this also extends to any research journals or articles.
Because if you're working in something fairly new,
there might not be the resource that you are used to having
if you use an established engine, for example.
And what do you already know?
Because I think it's really important to, at this point,
to address your strengths and play to them.
So for example, I'd already had experience
with networking and rendering,
so that allowed me to more fully apply myself
to learning those virtual reality elements.
So if you have a project that you already have
that you're wanting to build on,
or a strength that you really want to play to,
it's a good idea to get started that way.
Oh, have I gone backwards?
How do I go forwards?
Oh no, am I spoiling it?
Don't worry, roll with it, roll with it.
So, research.
So this is gonna start very early on in your project,
but it's gonna carry on iteratively throughout.
And so, this is adding color to what you're creating.
So the inspirations part of this talk was my research.
It was existing products, existing processes,
and developers that inspired what I was creating.
And this also went into research journals
and articles as well.
And then starting small again seems obvious,
but this is why I took this overall concept
and started off with the minimum viable product.
What I did then when I had the minimum viable product
is I broke each concept down further.
So for each of those elements, I broke it down
until I couldn't break it down any further.
And this sounds mental, because I would
have a million tasks to do.
But actually having tasks that took two minutes or two days or two hours
was a great way to keep having that constant positive reinforcement that I was going in the right direction.
And I think that's really important for momentum and morale when you have a big project ahead of you.
So how can you do this?
This is really dependent on developer or team or individual.
I know some people who've used burndown charts in Excel
or just kept a diary or written on a whiteboard every day
and cleared it down and started again the next day.
But for me I used Trello because I thought it was a really great visual representation of what I was creating.
I could color code each of the areas of that MVP.
And as you can see with this tiny articulus,
this is what I mean about that constant positive reinforcement.
I could break each task down even further,
so I always had that visual representation that it was going in the right way.
Code design.
So when I start out on this and I establish
the minimum viable products, I was like, this is fine.
I've been prototyping those bits in separate applications,
separate projects.
I'll just throw them all together
because that's the sensible thing to do.
And spoiler alert, it very quickly crashed and burned
and was a nightmare.
So don't do that.
What I ended up doing was having to go back and think more about,
think more smartly about my development process.
And some advice I was given, which I used and I recommend,
is to have a visual flowchart of what you're creating.
So what I did was I took each object, each element of my project,
and I popped it down on a piece of paper.
And so I very quickly built up a roadmap of the areas that I needed for my project.
And once I had all these pieces of paper and I could move them around,
I could very quickly identify the data flow between them I may need,
what objects needed to be aware of each other, any commonalities in the relationships,
and I moved them around until it made sense.
And only then did I transfer that into code.
So to illustrate that a bit further,
I'll just give a really high-level overview
of the networking element of the project.
Sorry, I keep doing that.
So I needed a way to be able to control the application
if it was launched in virtual reality,
but also if it wasn't.
So my first piece of paper was virtual reality integration.
So let's say that translated into code,
I called this VR application.
So then I needed to think about what that class would need
in order to work.
So then I started thinking,
well it's gonna need the virtual reality integration,
that's another piece of paper.
There's gonna have to be some sort of player class,
The geometry, that'd be a selection, more pieces of paper.
And so it's starting to build up.
And then I'd think about the other side,
the non-virtual reality side,
and I'd repeat the process.
And so I could clearly see quite early on
that there's gonna be commonalities
between these two applications,
even though, these two classes,
even though they were fundamentally
going to be doing the same thing,
rendering geometry and taking note of the player.
So when I had these classes defined,
I started to think about how they could be aware
of each other, when they needed to be aware of each other,
and how to facilitate that.
So what you may find, again, if you use engines,
is that it's usually a good, well, in code constructs,
it's a good idea to have an overall class
that has an appreciation, a visibility
for everything that you're creating.
So in this example, we could call it the manager.
So the manager could have an instance of or a reference
to every other class within your application.
So it instantly is able to access the state of it
and facilitate that communication
between all the other classes.
It could, for example, detect when a headset
is attached to the machine,
therefore trigger the virtual reality classes implementation
to get started.
So then if I look a little bit more at this area of code reuse,
so like I said, both these applications share attributes.
And usually when that happens, it
means that we're rewriting the same or similar code.
And so to reduce that, we usually have a base class
which holds that generic functionality,
but which still allows the derived classes
to be able to utilize or override that,
and also maintain their individual elements and behavior.
And this is likely to change,
even when you've got all your pieces of paper laid out
and you've translated it to code.
As you find new elements that you want to add to it,
or areas that you, sticking points you come across
that you didn't consider, it will start to change.
But having that roadmap, that visual representation
already mapped out, just makes it a lot easier
to be able to identify where you're gonna be putting in
these new resources or changing it.
So then testing.
I found from very early on that it was important to have testing from very early on in the
project and iteratively throughout.
Especially with virtual reality, it was really important to have as wide a test base as I
could because virtual reality was affecting a lot of different people in different ways.
And I also found, because I had my head in virtual reality all the time, I was more forgiving
of it.
So it's really important to keep testing on that wider audience
so you don't get caught in that trap of sort of getting used to it and just going with it.
Usability was a big one for me because I remember when I first showed my project to people
and I was like, hey look at this, it does this and it does that and it's super shiny
and they just went, yeah but how do I use it?
And I was like, I've been sat in my little cave,
really hammering on those technical elements
with no consideration for how the wider world would use it.
Like maybe I just assumed they were psychic.
And so it very quickly became apparent to me
that if what you're creating isn't intuitive to use,
then people just really aren't gonna take the time
to get to figure out how to use it.
So these more personal points.
I actually heard a talk with an engine programmer,
Tamir Tabori, who did a talk last year.
And I don't often hear these iterated.
And again, they're obvious,
but I think they're really important to point out.
So the first is to pace yourself.
So I'd find I'd start developing mid-morning, like 11 a.m.,
and then I'd look up and I'd look at the clock
and it'd be 4 a.m. the next day.
And like, I hadn't gone out, I hadn't eaten anything,
I hadn't had a cup of tea,
I hadn't spoken to another human being.
And this was usually when I was trying to figure out
how to solve a bug or implement something
before I went to bed.
But what I found is that if I took a step back and had a break,
I went and got something to drink and I ate properly,
I went for a walk or I spoke to someone,
that I'd had the headspace to be able to go back to that problem
and approach it in a lot more open-minded and different angle.
And it just was great for productivity.
Again, when you're on any sort of project, you learn what you're good at and what you enjoy,
but you also learn what you're not very good at and what you hate.
And I found that really tough to take.
It took me a long time to be able to turn that into a positive
and identify it as areas for improvements,
but also as a way of identifying what I really enjoyed.
And I think it's really important that if there's something you enjoy,
to take that passion and run with it.
and celebrate too.
So like I said about taking off those many achievements,
share and ask your friends and your peers
and share it on social media too.
Like social media is a great way to get
that immediate response and feedback and feelings
for the response to what you're creating
from the active development community.
and ask.
There's no such thing as a stupid question,
and even if you think the person is the smartest person
in the world, they don't know everything.
Asking is all part of the learning process,
and nobody ever stops learning, so don't be afraid to ask.
And also, this is important, so believe in yourself.
If you're doing something that you're emotionally
investing yourself in and putting a lot of your time in,
you can often get to sticking points where you think,
do you know what, I can't do this anymore.
I'm not smart enough for this,
I'm not good enough for this, I can't do it.
But if you talk to the development community,
you'll find that everybody feels that way.
It's supernatural.
So you can do it, and you just have to keep at it.
So, in summary.
Set your goals clear.
Please do code design.
Just please remember you're a human being,
and collaborate, share, and celebrate.
And thank you for joining me today.
And I hope that there's been something
useful for you to take away.
I'm going to be in the wrap-up rooms
if you have any questions.
I have a summary PDF of all the lessons learned part.
Or you can just throw a tweet at me.
But thank you for spending your time with me today.
I really appreciate it.