All right, let's get started.
Hey, everybody.
My name is Ethan Levy, and I'm here to present Legendary Game
of Heroes, five lessons from 12 months of LiveOps growth.
And actually, between the time I put this presentation
together and now, we've had an additional four
months being live.
So it's actually the top five lessons from 16 months.
A little bit about me. I've spent 14 years working game development, worked on over 50
shit titles across console, PC, mobile, mostly in the free-to-play space, mostly some interaction
of design and monetization. For the past two years, I've had the pleasure of working on
this game as part of Network, a legendary game of heroes. If you haven't played Legendary,
I think it could be quickly summed up as Puzzle & Dragons westernized.
So today I'm going to talk about, over the past 16 months as we've been in players' hands,
I think I personally and the team have learned a lot, and we've grown a lot, and I want to
kind of summarize some of the top things I've learned over this period of time.
Just to give you a feeling for what we're talking about, this chart shows ARPDAU growth
over the course of 2016.
This is, each data point is a 30 day proceeding average.
So I didn't just want to talk about peaks and valleys,
but actually numbers that represent really sustained
ARPDAU or player engagement metrics.
So this is our growth over the course of 2016
in terms of ARPDAU.
And you can see in the middle,
a big kind of baseline resetting
as we hit a worldwide launch.
And similarly, it's not just about how much each player spends,
but it's about how much time each player spends in the game,
and our engagement time per day for your average player has also grown.
Looking just at that 2016 period, we have increased 652% in terms of our ARPDAU and
136% in terms of minutes per day spent, and that's if you're looking at a 30-day average.
So that's, I'm not just giving you like our worst technical issues to our peak sale day.
That's a 30-day average for each one of those.
This growth has really enabled remarkable results on the iOS.
store. We've been top 100 in 63 countries, 49 countries on Android. We've gone top 10
in 18 countries on iOS. And we've done this all with a team of 15 people.
Today, I'm going to be talking primarily about feature development and the lessons learned
from feature development.
And the reason I'm focusing on that is because that's where I spend the vast majority of
my time.
But it's really important to note that features alone don't produce results like these, right?
As I said, we've got about 15 or 16 full-time people on the team,
a bunch of shared studio resources,
and just world-class people in every one of these pillars.
And it's taken a blend of live operations, UA and business intelligence,
feature development, player support.
All held up by a strong studio operations staff,
and all held up by a world-class studio culture.
And so I'm here talking about features
and the impact of features on growth,
but this game is a complex ecosystem,
and all mobile games like this are a complex ecosystem.
And it's not just one thing.
It's the full team and the full studio's effort
that I'm talking about today.
So as I said, it's really world class execution
across all these pillars that have empowered our LiveOps
growth.
So with that, let's talk about the top five lessons
I've taken away when reflecting on this period.
Number one, focus on inflection.
So if you look at this, this is a list of all of our major updates over the course of
the year.
I left out some small point releases that are just bug fixes.
And they range from, you know, you can see our soft launch in early November of 2015,
up to Commander Skill, which we're actually releasing this week.
And by about 6 or 7 on Tuesday, we'll be able to know how well players are receiving our
new Commander Skill with the Crusade event.
So, I've taken the ARPDAU chart and I've broken it up, each color, by kind of the period of
the major feature release.
And so this is why I used those 30-day preceding averages so that you could see on each day
for the next 30 days what the average are.
Because I was really interested in the trends and in spotting where things change.
And as you can see, there's a giant baseline reset
when we go worldwide.
And that's because we're looking at per player metrics.
And when we went worldwide, we got an influx of feature player
thanks to features from our friends at Apple and Google.
We were very lucky to have that.
And we also started scaling our user acquisition.
And so once we started scaling up our players,
there was a baseline reset.
So for right now, I'm going to zoom in on that soft launch
period.
And that first month in January is pulling in a lot of days
where there was not a lot of people.
So really starting on February through worldwide launches
where I feel like these numbers are really
valuable to look at.
So I said my number one, my top lesson was to focus on inflection.
What am I talking about?
So you can see with our 1.2 release, we built the support for events.
But we didn't yet have leaderboards on those events.
And so we were missing the competition angle of it.
And we didn't actually start running events.
We kind of laid the baseline with our 1.2.
And you can see.
That first trend line is showing where ARPDAU was heading on 1.2.
And then as soon as we turned on leaderboards, turned on competition,
and started running events on a weekly basis,
you can see the inflection in our ARPDAU that that caused.
So when I look at this 16 months worth of updates,
I look at four releases.
And I think these really had immediate, measurable
inflections.
Leaderboards and turning on weekly events,
our Raid Boss event harness, which
was a new type of event we released in May of last year,
optimization on the Android platform.
and
each one had a positive impact, but it wasn't that really satisfying level up.
So, you know, why am I making the differentiation?
Well, obviously, if I focus on feature development,
I feel like each time you release a new update,
it's kind of your turn at the bat,
and really, I'd love to hit a home run every time I'm up there.
And where our home runs came from was adapting and innovating
on best practices from the marketplace.
But we hit plenty of base hits along the way.
And those base hits, I would say,
were either bundles of smaller features
that didn't tie together into a cohesive whole immediately,
or something I've started calling bank shots.
So what do I mean by a bank shot?
I mean, when you're trying to inflect a specific metric,
or you're trying to motivate a specific behavior,
but the way your feature gets there isn't a direct line.
It's more like, oh, if I hit off this wall and off this wall,
then this is what the player will do.
So to give you a really tangible example, late last year we released a Guild Wars feature
and it had a couple different motivations and one of the motivations was to increase
the appetite for heroes.
In our game, you bring five heroes with you into each round of combat.
And you really, during the course of the week, probably only need five great heroes for that event
until you go to the next event when you need another five heroes.
And most of those heroes might be the same, or now that we're running different event types,
the same as you did two weeks ago.
And so...
We released this Guild War feature where it was the first chance that one player has to attack another in the game.
And we released skills and counter skills.
So there was interplay between one player's attacking deck and one player's defending deck.
And that was five attackers and five defenders.
And part of the idea was that we would increase the appetite for rare...
a
wish that if we had won to increase our appetite for heroes we had done it by delivering a game
mode that required more heroes.
If we want to make it that you need more than five six-star heroes,
then we should make a game mode that requires 36 star heroes at the highest
levels of competition, something like that.
That, to me, is a much more direct attempt at it.
Anyways, so the lesson here, as I said, is before committing to an update, ask yourself,
is this going to directly inflect our business?
And I think it's kind of a tough question to ask.
We had what I think was a very successful moment late last year when we started going
down the path for a feature that was called World Boss.
And in the room, when we decided to pursue World Boss,
part of its appeal was it seemed like a low-effort feature
that we could get out fairly quickly that
would have a nice inflection.
And so we started designing this feature.
We got it to what I would call about 60% resolution.
We started reviewing it.
And it seemed like, in order to really make
it a feature that was up to our standards of greatness,
it would be much better.
More meaningfully effortful than we initially anticipated.
And when we looked at the amount of effort it would take to get World Boss out,
and the amount of effort some of the other things we thought would be more impactful out, we said,
well, let's stop developing World Boss and choose one of those things and work on that instead.
And even though that meant throwing out a significant amount of design work
and potentially even causing some inefficiencies in the development and release of new features,
I think it was worth it.
I think we made the right...
choice by choosing to focus on something that we believed in could be inflective relative
to the amount of effort we were putting in.
Second lesson, build for your bandwidth.
So all teams have bottlenecks, and when I look at kind of the middle period of 2016,
one of ours was building game data.
As I said, there are a couple features that I look at, and I feel like we made immediate measurable inflections in our software.
And then there are a lot of things that I look at and I say, well, we put great tools in the toolbox.
And some of those we're still pulling out and using today, right?
Nothing, everything that we have done has been useful over a period of time and helped us
increase how much fun events are for players, make the software better, make more revenue
per player.
But, I think there's a period where it felt like we were building more tools than we could
use at their full potential.
And that was because we had a really turbo-charged, world-class engineering team.
Not enough manpower on the PM front for the amount of tools that we were building to use them effectively.
Let me give you two examples. One example is an early feature that was ally missions.
The design intention was it was a really low effort feature where we wanted to increase session frequency by giving a snackable timer-based mission.
The inspiration point was missions that you'd be familiar with from Mobile Strike or Game of War.
At the time, this failing I can take ownership of.
This is my failing.
When I set it up, I set it up with no loss aversion.
And when I look at what works well in those missions
in Mobile Strike is if you don't come back every six hours
and collect all your timers, you've lost resources.
But the way I set these up was that there
was no loss aversion.
Once you get past a certain rank,
there are always four ally missions available for you.
And so there's no part of you that says,
I have to come back to the game.
to set one of my allies on this ally mission and when that 15 minute timer's up I better
come back to set the next one.
Instead, they're always available, the rewards are fairly consistent and not that great and
you can look at it and go, once you're a high level player and just sort of forget about
this whole section of the game.
And so this feature hasn't had a retune, I think, since it's launched.
We use allies and other ally missions as part of our weekly events, so as I said, they're
a valuable tool in the toolbox.
But at no point have we put the effort towards going back and raising up the level of what
these do, and it's not really clear to me that that effort would be paid off relative
to putting that same amount of effort in another area of the game.
Another example would be the enemy skill system that we first released, I think, in 1.2 or 1.3, kind of early on.
Our design intention was to increase intention by adding progression novelty to the campaign.
And, you know, our game is like a Candy Crush match game below with an RPG mechanic on top.
with a bunch of heroes with stats and skills.
And part of the intention here was that your enemies would drop gems on the board below
that would add a little bit of skill play in and change things up and make levels more exciting.
We could use it to make the campaign more exciting, events more exciting, etc.
When we first implemented enemy skills, we put it in one section of the game,
which was the daily dungeons.
And it really took a long time until...
Those enemy skills and the skill system in general start to bubble up and play a meaningful
role outside of that initial use.
And again, I look at that as our bottleneck on design and data creation, right?
We had to be very tactical every day about what the PMs are doing to level up the software.
And so...
We have things where I feel like we just didn't use the tools to the full potential.
But now, I mean, we made those investments
and in the past two weeks, one of our new and very talented team members
has been pumping out unique battle skills and enemy skills for our event characters
that I think like finally...
I'm going to make this part of the game shine and where I've had some of the most fun in
our events recently with our characters because they're starting to feel unique.
So over time that investment has paid off.
But when I look at that period of time, what I think the
lesson is, is to adjust your output to
match your capabilities.
Given the mismatch we had in terms of how much could be
accomplished between this world-class engineering team
and not quite enough PMs, I wish we had done more better.
I think we could have made even more inflection than we
made by investing in fewer features and bringing them out
either at higher quality or bringing them out at a faster
cadence.
And again, that's one of those great lessons you can see with a lot of clarity in hindsight.
Lesson number three, live ops events are the heart of your game.
I joined the legendary team, I think it would be kind of on the tail end of pre-production,
at the beginning of production.
We didn't have clearly defined milestones,
but I think getting to version 0.9 was like, we're building the base game,
and then that year of growth was like, we're building the events on top of the base game.
We're building the event structure on top of it.
And I think that the key lesson I've really taken away
is that live ops, live op events,
are the core of your game when you're
focused on this sort of game.
And there is no separate other base game.
And I wish we had just started there.
So this is a slide I already showed.
This is showing the inflection point
when we just started releasing, started and released
our first event that was driven by leaderboards.
We saw an immediate inflection.
And ever since that point, we've run one event every week
up till we have an event ending tomorrow at 5.
Our weekly events pull on a core LiveOps suite.
As I said, everything contributes to our events.
But kind of the core of it are our two harnesses,
which are our special dungeon and our raid boss harness.
And actually next week, we're leaning into an older part of the software,
the activity map, and combining it with the raid boss harness
to make even a new event type.
But you've got your event harnesses,
the leaderboards that drive competition.
Initially it was just solo competition.
Now it's solo competition,
an additional global leaderboard for top players,
and a guild leaderboard.
all within an event.
We've got a pop-up system that plays a critical role
in the game.
And we've got guilds and localization.
Every event, we time it, the execution of it,
so that all the text is localized in the key countries
that we localize in, which was a fun moment of LiveOps growth,
getting things together early enough
to get everything localized.
But that's kind of the core of our LiveOps suite.
So what does that mean when I say we run an event each week?
Well.
We have some form of limited time content, which
is a special dungeon, an area where you fight special raid
bosses, which have unique rules relative to the base campaign
game.
And now with these Crusader events,
we're experimenting with using the campaign map
to be part of that limited time content.
So those levels are there, those bosses are there,
and when the event turns off, they're gone.
Every week, there's at least one new event boss.
I snapped screenshots from our Phantom of the Opera event,
because I think it was.
One of my favorite examples of giving the art team something that's not immediately obvious in a puzzle RPG,
and I think they really executed it at an amazing level. I really enjoy these characters.
Limited time content, brand new boss, competition on a leaderboard.
As I said, we've grown over time from having, you know, even out of the gate we had segmented
league-based leaderboards, but now we have a solo leaderboard, a separate global leaderboard
that if you're in one of the top positions in the game you get both solo and global leaderboard
results, and guild leaderboards.
Each leaderboard gives rewards and that boss character is the exclusive, exciting reward
that you can get only from that event.
We also sell at least one new hero in a new card pack with each event and we use our pop-up
system, our event-driven pop-up system to run in-game marketing and in-game messaging
about what's new, what's exciting, what's valuable, decks you should build, etc.
That's kind of the core suite.
A slight addendum to rule three is that left unchanged, event performance will decay over
time.
Now what do I mean by that?
When we launched out of the gate, we just had dungeon events, and as I said, we were
in the road to soft launch.
We had a lot we needed to do.
From soft launch to worldwide launch, we had a lot we needed to do.
And so for a period of time, we were pretty much running the same dungeon event week after week after week.
That's all we had.
And over time, we saw players' interest naturally leveling off.
Until we released our second event harness,
our Raid Boss Harness, which really turned around the trend
there and allowed us to run two different events,
Dungeon Raid Boss, Dungeon Raid Boss, back to back,
and so to keep things fresh.
On top of it, not only do we have two major categories
of events, but as I've been saying,
all these tools we put in the toolbox
we use to change up events, to improve their performance,
to make it clear for the player what's important.
So.
You know, in my first point I hit on immediate inflection
and trying to hit a home run every time.
If I look in that 1.2 and I look at pop-ups,
pop-ups at the time, just driving in-game marketing,
on its own might not have seemed like one of the most inflective things we've done in the game,
but over the time as we've leaned into that
and learned to use it better and really focused on our marketing messaging,
that has probably become one of the most impactful features we've added to the game.
And it was easy to look at it and go like, oh, we added
marketing pop-ups.
We can put images in front of players and text, hooray.
But it's actually like, over time, learning to use all of
those tools in the toolbox has driven this incredible growth
in terms of ARPDAU, or has been one of the main things
driving growth in terms of ARPDAU and player
engagement over time.
What I put up there, and this kind of hits to the point that,
you know, I'm focusing mainly on the impact of features,
but these changes in ARPDAU and player engagement
are not just about features.
It's a complex ecosystem.
And so you're getting a combination
of feature inflections, population, veterancy,
and event optimization.
So new things that change the way players behave in the game.
The metrics naturally changing as your player population grows over time, right?
If you have a successful free-to-play game, that means your veteran players are sticking around for a long period of time.
And so as the mix of new players or early game players to veteran players changes,
your ARPDAU and daily engagement are naturally going to grow over time because your veteran players
are naturally the most engaged and tend to spend the most.
And so part of that's just the shift between those that's natural over the growth of the
game and part of it's intentional through feature growth and part of it is through event
optimization.
But as I said at the beginning, events with leaderboard competition and exclusive content
to buy and win are really at the heart of what I think a modern free-to-play mobile
game is.
And really, if this was day one of a new mobile game, a new free-to-play mobile game, this
would be one of the primary design considerations.
Lesson number four was to believe in the power of guilds.
I think if you look at the top 150 grossing games...
And you look in the mid-course section, you can see that there are a lot of games with
guilds where it's been really successful.
There are games with guilds where maybe it hasn't paid off, but I think going into this
game I had never operated a game with true guilds, and releasing it has, I think, been
one of the major inflections that the team has made during the course of this game's
live operations.
At its heart, guilds are a player can join a group of people.
They have a shared chat room where they can strategize.
They have a guild emblem now, which they didn't have it
launched, but they have a guild emblem
to symbolize who they are.
The leadership has some tools around setting
different ranks of players in the software in their guild.
So you can promote some people to the council
or give them the title of dukes and duchesses to just.
show how they're doing in the guild.
So it's a chat room.
The ability for the guild to compete as a unit
on a guild leaderboard during each event
and the ability for players in the guild to earn special gifts.
We made this item gifts that when you earn it,
you can only send it to a guild member.
So for instance, I may earn a gift
Due to my placement on the solo leaderboard at the end of an event, I may purchase a $100
IAP pack and get 10 gem gifts to spread the wealth with other players in my guild.
And I can't use them in myself, I can only send them around.
Now, Guild did not have an incredibly long period in soft launch.
It was the last thing we launched right before Worldwide.
So...
The reason you're looking at inflection downward is because this graph ends at the point where
it crosses over and the inflection happens.
So this is just the soft launch graph.
So let's zoom out to the worldwide launch graph.
And as you can see, there's that, as I said, that natural resetting when we went from soft
launch to worldwide launch and we scaled up meaningfully.
But when you look here on this ARPDAU chart, you can see that inflection that the guild system was a part of.
When I look at it, I think introducing guilds was a major inflection point for the game.
So let's go back to that previous chart I was showing, where I'm showing ARPDAU on top and player engagement on bottom.
And as I said, this growth isn't feature-centric.
It's an ecosystem.
So part of that growth was due to our user acquisition
strategy.
Part of it was feature inflection
from the guilds and subsequent features we launched.
Part of it was event optimization.
And part of it is that population veterancy.
So what do I think that Guild's major contributor
to the software was?
People who are in social groups and are
in an engaged social group are going
to stick around for longer.
And so guilds, by creating more veterans,
helps improve the stacking of veteran players in our software
and increase the portion of our player base that are veterans.
And that lifts all of our metrics on a per-player basis
and has a meaningful change in our absolute numbers.
Let me go back to my lesson.
Guilds belong at the heart of a modern free-to-play game.
So if I take those two and combine it, and if today was
day one on a new mobile free-to-play product, the
first question is, how is this game built for guild events?
That's the primary design consideration in my mind.
Number five, this one's a real short one.
Complexity of feature design increases over time.
So I'm just going to talk about two features.
One we launched early on, leaderboards.
One we're building right now, relics and scrolls.
And if I just, at a high level, segmented league-based
leaderboards that drive competition and a set of
relics that you can equip to a team to boost their stats are
not wildly different in a vacuum in terms of effort.
But at the point where we released Leaderboards, the
game was much less complicated.
So this is the overview page from Leaderboards.
These are the six main screens that Leaderboards had to touch
from a user-facing perspective.
This is the overview page of our currently in development
Relics and Scrolls PDF.
And I think it's like 32 or 33 screens.
And as I said, in a vacuum, these two features aren't
crazily different.
What's different is that the size of the game has increased
and the number of points each one of these new features has
to integrate with increases.
So as feature richness increases, so does the complexity of adding new features to the core loop.
And I think if you've heard any of my previous talks, I've hit on this a lot,
that building features into the core loop in a way where they market themselves
is critical to players discovering them and them having the impact that you want on the game.
So my counterpart, Hide, who I think was really the architect of the game economy,
he came to this game with an incredible view on the needs of growing the game economy over time,
and he knew and planned for that growth.
On the UX side, I don't think we did enough to plan for the growth and anticipate years
of growth of features being added to our game and needing to add them to the core loop.
And each feature we just have to do more like UX refactoring to make sure it really works
and that it's surfaced to the player.
And I think this is natural.
There's just like, you know...
There was no way to not have stat inflation in our game over time and power creep over time,
and it's a challenge just to plan for it and make sure to provide a great user experience.
I don't think it's possible to grow your game's feature depth over three years
and not need this sort of refactoring over time,
but I think better planning for it at the outset
would have made our lives easier in presenting great features to players over time.
So, wrapping up real quick, these are my top five lessons.
Focus on inflection, build for your bandwidth, live ops and guilds, and live ops events that
guilds compete in are at the heart of your game.
Build tools that allow you to combat the natural decay of events, and plan for the fact that
your feature design complexity will increase over time.
And really, the most important thing to take away from this presentation is great results are possible over time.
You can do incredible things during the LiveOps period of your game, during the soft launch and worldwide launch, to change how players interact with your game.
But it's not just one of these pillars, it's all of them.
It's world-class people working together across LiveOps, UA, feature development, player support.
Supported by a great studio, built on a great culture.
This is what it takes.
It takes all of these things to achieve greatness
with a modern mobile free-to-play game.
So thank you very much.
When a little bit long, I probably
have time for one, maybe two questions.
Then I can take questions for anybody
who has them who'd like to stick around.
All right.
Well, thank you all very much.
We've got one.
Hi, very good speech, thanks.
And what's about impact on revenue of sales, of pop-ups,
like Game of World, Mobile Strike?
So the question was, what is the impact on revenue of sales?
And I think there are two types of sales, and it's very
important to think about them differently.
One is a sale where you're selling currency.
So I used to go into, I used to play Mobile Strike six times a day every day for months.
Now I pop in once a month.
And each month that sale, the amount of bonus gold is inflated, right?
They've inflated that over time.
And so what that means is that they're selling currency.
And a key lesson I've learned is that selling currency
can be a really effective way to boost
your revenue in the short term.
But generally, the more currency you sell,
there's a hangover on new currency purchases
after that happens, unless you've designed the game so
that there are new things to always be soaking up
that currency.
So selling currency is really effective,
but you have to plan for the after effects.
The other thing, you know, a thing I think we focus on selling a lot more is new things that are really limited time.
And that's worked really well for us, and there you're just dealing with a different sort of inflation.
You're dealing with the power inflation over time.
Another part of your question was about the pop-ups and how important are the pop-ups.
Pop-ups are key to promoting and explaining the value of new things that we're putting on sale in our game.
Neil's in the back row, and I think within at least the last week, if not the last two,
there have been times where he goes,
What's wrong with the pop-ups?
And it's because he looks at the hourly revenue,
and he can tell instantly that something's wrong with how
we're messaging to our players.
So as I said before, the power of messaging to your players,
what you're selling to them, and what the value of those things
are to their play experience, it can't be overstated.
Thanks.
I'll just take one more.
Hello, this is Victor from Gameloft. You said that you had kind of problem with kind of content fatigue with weekly events.
What is for you the best way to counteract that? So with through gameplay or through the metagame, let's say?
Ah, so the question was early on I said we had a problem with fatigue during events and
it's just kind of a natural part of the game.
I really think, I think that the best way to combat that, you know, you're not going
to be able to release a completely new event harness every week.
It takes a long time to build each one of those.
And so really focusing as a LiveOps team on novelty.
having the tools to introduce new things
and releasing new client updates that make minor improvements,
such as, as I mentioned, the global leaderboards
or launching this week commander skills,
like just introducing new things over time
and using the tools you have to make things
feel as new as possible.
Because you're going to need new skills, this is pure gameplay, you're going to need a new
leaderboard system, this is a meta game.
So what do you think?
It's both things at the same time?
You can change just one, change the other, it's one that works better?
I think it's both.
I mean, I think it's you have to each week basically look at the tools you have and say
like what's the best thing we can deliver, or do we need to deliver absolutely new things?
No easy answer.
Sorry.
No magical formula there.
No.
Okay.
Alright, thank you all very much for listening and please fill out your review, let me know
how I can improve, and hopefully I'll be back next year to tell you about another 12 months
ago.