I'm Kim Swift, and I was a level designer and the team lead on Portal.
And I'm Eric Wolpaw, and I was a writer on Portal.
So we're here to talk to you today a little bit about our techniques for integrating narrative
and design, sort of phrased as a Portal postmortem, giving examples of what we particularly did.
So in case you were wondering, postmortem means we will be talking about stuff that's
in the game.
So if you haven't played the game and you're one of those people that gets all squealy
and upset whenever someone tells you something that you hadn't heard about a game, then you
might want to leave the room.
Or not.
That's fine too.
So here's what we're going to try and cover today.
First of all, I'm going to make a real brief case of why you should care about anything
we're going to tell you.
Secondly, I'm going to go real quickly into our narrative philosophy, which is sort of
our crackpot theory of how gameplay and narrative should be combined.
And third of all, we're going to talk about how we took the crackpot theory and tried
to apply it to our development process.
So in particular, why should you care about how we did this on Portal?
Well, first of all, we had a really small team with about only ten people at once working
on the game.
Usually it was anywhere between five and seven.
And it's been pretty popular, and we're surprised, despite the game being kind of unorthodox.
So after all is said and done, we actually don't really have any regrets.
Unlike this poor guy.
So now, why would you care about how we put together our narrative and design?
So by itself, our story wouldn't really make a whole great novel.
Don't get me wrong, the dialogue is just really, really funny.
He's probably about the funniest man you'll ever meet, just in case you were wondering.
Set the bar pretty high for the talk.
Sorry about that.
Nothing funny in this.
There's no ad-libbing now from this point on.
And on its own, the gameplay, it'd be all right.
But honestly, a little on the dry side.
Honestly, it would be a race to see which one would fail the fastest on its own.
But because we had a really tight integration of both our story and our gameplay, it seemed
to really resonate with people, and it worked.
And like Kim said, our team size kind of imposed a lot of constraints on our design choices.
So our design methods from the beginning had to be low impact on both our time and energy
budgets.
But this kind of helped us creatively sidestep a lot of our constraints.
For instance, Gladys being a disembodied voice might not have actually occurred to us if
we'd had a ton of animators and a ton of resources to make her a little robot buddy that followed
you around or something.
And yet it kind of turned out to be just the perfect solution to the narrative in Portal.
So here's a crackpot theory.
The idea is that games tell two stories.
There's a story story, which is sort of the sum total of the game's dialogue and cutscenes.
And then there's the gameplay story, which is the story described by the actions the
player takes in the game world.
And if you lower the delta between those two stories, the closer you put them together,
the more satisfying your game will be.
Or at least that was our theory.
There's a lot of games that I think suffer from a high story delta, but since it's a
game developers conference, if I run down a lot of them, it's going to be like super
dick moves.
So I'm not going to do that.
I'm going to mention one game that I actually like a lot, so it should be non-controversial
and it's also kind of old, is Clive Barker's Undying, which is a first-person shooter that
was released like six years ago.
And it's a good shooter.
And regardless of what you may think about his style, Clive Barker, and that's him wearing
super scary pair of pants, he's a talented writer who actually, in interviews, I think
seems to care a lot about the story in his games.
So Clive Barker's Undying, you play this World War I war hero who goes to Scotland
to visit the castle of one of your war buddies.
And the castle is sort of infested with ghouls.
And you're shooting a lot of monsters and there's a lot of death and destruction all
around.
But pretty frequently, as you're going through the mansion, the game all of a sudden stops
to play one of these cut scenes where you sort of calmly interrogate one of the members
of the staff.
You know, you're sort of, what do you do?
How are you doing?
How are you feeling?
Stuff like that.
Meanwhile, at no point does your character just grab the help by the label and say, you
know, like, there are monsters five feet around that corner killing everyone they come across.
You need to run now.
The two stories make absolutely no sense when you smoosh them together.
And Undying is one of the first times that I remember a good game sort of being undermined
by a disconnect between the story the gameplay was telling and the story the story itself
was telling.
So, with all that in mind, our fundamental Portal narrative design goal was that the
story story would never ever intrude or contradict the gameplay story.
For us, less was always more.
And we were ruthless about it.
We were ruthless about trimming the narrative fat, tightening our belts, and then trimming
it even more.
So, Portal was going to be a lean storytelling machine if it killed us.
And usually it meant killing you.
Killing me.
Because it was a lot of good lines that had to get cut.
And we're really sorry about that.
But it was, yeah, it was worth it.
So enough about how we feel about games.
Like, let's talk about how we practically applied these feelings.
First of all, we're going to talk a little bit about our playtesting process, which,
by the way, in case you were wondering, it's really important.
Second, reflecting story in your environment.
Next, evolving narrative out of gameplay.
And then again, vice versa, evolving gameplay out of narrative.
So playtesting is probably the most important thing we ever did on Portal.
You know, actually sit down and watch people play your game.
Don't just have some other company playtest the game and then send you a report afterwards.
It's just not going to be as valuable to you as just sitting down, having someone play
your game, and you watch them and see how they react to it.
You can find out what your players actually want by watching them.
In the case of Portal, we adjusted our gameplay to what players looked like they needed.
Did they need more training?
Because clearly they were really confused here.
Maybe they needed some more reinforcement of what we trained them on.
Because they wanted to use those new skills.
And in addition to that, we also adjusted our story to enhance, essentially, what our
players were feeling at that time.
Yeah, and frequent playtests helped keep us objective about our design decisions.
Watching playtests is a great way to expose pretty quickly what isn't working.
One rule we had, narrative-wise, was at the end of a playtest, we would ask playtesters
to just tell us the Portal story back, beat by beat.
And if they couldn't tell it to us, we took that as a real clear sign that they just weren't
interested, that we were failing.
And the fix for it, almost always, was just to cut more story, cut more exposition.
It usually meant cutting something that initially seemed essential to the story.
And as it turned out, it just made it stronger every time we cut something.
It says something about the writing.
Yeah.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Another thing is playtest early and often.
On the far side there, you can see what the first room in the game actually looked like,
you know, maybe a couple weeks into development.
And then on the other side, you can see what it finally shipped, you know, as.
And we literally started playtesting this room the first week that we got to Valve and
started working on the game.
We, you know, hacked portals together in some horrible way that, you know, we're glad doesn't
exist anymore.
And we were already making better decisions about what our levels were like.
So I don't know, it's kind of hard to make out, but in the first picture, there's kind
of like this shimmery force field, which was, you know, the original cage for the player.
And we got rid of this pretty quickly because our playtesters, you know, just didn't understand
what it was.
They would, you know, walk up to the force field and they, you know, were wondering why
they couldn't walk through it.
So they would just kind of like trace the edge of the cage like five times and get really
confused.
So we changed it to glass just to fix that problem.
So, you know, not only did our playtesting help us get a better narrative and get better
gameplay, it also helped us refine our art direction.
You know, as you can notice in the later picture, it's a lot cleaner, it's a lot simpler.
We extracted any of the elements that, you know, didn't really have any relevance to
the player.
And it really helped us teach the players what they needed to know.
So as just kind of a digression, yeah, I labeled this slide advice because this is
the only one I'm fully behind as advice of anything we're going to say today.
This is actually good advice.
If you're writing a funny game, first of all, God help you because it's unpleasant.
Because tough guy dialogue is just about as macho the 50th time you hear it as the first
time.
Whereas funny dialogue is funny once maybe.
About three years ago, I worked on a game called Psychonauts.
Yay!
There's more people clapping than bought it.
Now I lost my train of thought.
Working on Psychonauts.
Double Fine.
Oh, so Double Fine is kind of structured.
Everybody sits in one big room.
It's 40 people maybe.
Sitting in one big room.
And it's, you know, the two and a half years that I was there, no game development, it's
12 hours a day, six, seven days a week.
And so I had to sit there in the middle of this pit of people working on Psychonauts
hearing my supposedly funny dialogue blaring out of 40 monitors to just grim, stony silence.
And it was just, it was torture.
It was psychological torture for me because Tim wisely had his own office somewhere where
you didn't have to hear the grim, stony silence.
So yeah, this is you writing a funny game.
You are going to exist in a black cloud of despair for however long it takes you to make
the game.
But so here's the advice.
Trust your instincts.
Try and remember your initial reaction, people's initial reactions to seeing it.
And you know, do whatever you can do to not despair.
But the fourth part, the part that helped us a lot, again on Portal, is playtest.
More often you playtest, the more often you actually get to see someone, hearing your
dialogue, seeing the game for the first time.
And it, honest to God, whatever the benefits of playtesting are for the design team, for
a writer, it is the only way really to maintain your sanity during the two or three years
it's going to take you to make the game.
Or Prozac.
Yeah, and I'll, yeah, medication.
So another thing we tried to do when we had to cut exposition was to, if we didn't want
to cut it all together, was to try and embed exposition in the environment.
When we were initially talking about it, we had some email, ideas for embedding it in
email, and we were actually using email to talk about putting it in email, and at some
point we discovered that reading email wasn't actually that fun.
He's like, did you enjoy reading that last email?
I was like, no, it wasn't that exciting, we probably shouldn't put it in the game.
So that was one of our rules.
And the idea was, try and be creative about reflecting the story in the environment.
And again, easy to say, be creative, but if you apply a rule set and then you're ruthless
about the rules, it's amazing how creative you can get in a big hurry if it's a choice
between coming up with some novel way to embed your exposition in the environment and simply
cutting it all together.
So what we did in Portal, at least one of the things we did, was to have these little
wall scribblings in the behind the scenes areas of the game.
And honestly, these are really quick and easy to do, like they really only took like one
or two days tops.
And they were pretty effective at telling a story.
So here's an example of the room.
And you know, put yourself in the position of your characters.
What would they do in the situation of the game?
So in this case, we had this idea for a character that we called the Ratman.
And he was supposed to be a fellow escaped test subject, just like you, and he's a little
loopy.
And we originally wanted you to actually meet this NPC at some point in the game, but we
had two artists.
So it wasn't really feasible.
So rather than just sort of cut our backstory on this guy, we decided to manifest him here
in these rooms.
So you know, I asked myself, if I was trapped inside an insidious facility, bent on my destruction,
run by a homicidal AI, what would I do to pass the time?
So another big tool we used was to try and evolve our narrative out of gameplay.
Like Kim said, we tried to write to enhance what playtesters were feeling, which required
me to try and keep the story as wet as possible.
It was a big, big hurdle to overcome to just not get attached to any piece of writing.
And yeah, because it was just going to disappear at any given time, and we'd have to think
up something else.
And the same goes for gameplay too.
Don't get too attached to anything.
Like you know, you might need to cut it, and it's probably for the best.
So here's an example of that.
The Way to Companion Cube.
So we're going to talk about this first from a game design standpoint of one day, we sat
down and decided we wanted to make what we called the box marathon level.
So where essentially you've got your cube at the beginning of the map, and then you
take it all the way through to the end of the map and put it on a button.
It's supposed to be a big, long obstacle course.
So the first thing that we tried was having sort of this moving platform, you know, over
a goo pit where you'd have to stand on it with your box and avoid stuff.
Kind of similar actually to the last test chamber that we shipped.
And you know what?
It pissed players off, like to no end.
They would end up destroying the box by dropping it in the goo, and they'd get really annoyed
because they had to go back to the beginning of the map, and you know, they didn't really
want to carry this stupid thing with them everywhere.
So we went back to the drawing board.
The first thing we did was remove the moving platforms over the goo, you know, so you couldn't
destroy the box.
And we added more gameplay events where having the box is necessary for you to solve a puzzle.
So here's a couple examples.
On one side there you can see that we used the cube to, you know, kind of make a dynamic
set of stairs there to get up those platforms.
And then on the other side, it's a puzzle where you have to, you know, put the box on
one of these buttons and then, you know, go stand on another button and get this energy
ball through those doors into a, you know, catcher thing.
And these worked pretty well in terms of making players at least somewhat take the box with
them and not hate it.
And but, you know, players were still kind of forgetting it.
They'd leave it at one puzzle and then, you know, go to the next puzzle and go, oh crap,
and then have to go back to the beginning and grab their box.
So we said, okay, maybe if we redesign this room so that way you're always kind of facing
this button and taking a look at it.
So that worked pretty well, at least to remind players, by the way, you need this at the
end of the map.
But, you know, we needed something else.
Like players really weren't getting that attached to the box and there were still a few people
that would kind of forget it behind.
And so, Eric to the rescue over here.
Though as much as possible we tried to, you know, put hints for our players, you know,
in the environment, whether it be through lighting or geometry, you know, when all else
fails, great dialogue really was a great tool for us to give a hint to the player.
Yeah, I'd been reading, luckily, these declassified government interrogation manuals.
And one of the things, they're awesome.
I recommend them.
They're really cool.
But one of the things they talked about was that isolation leads interrogation subjects
to start becoming attached to inanimate objects.
And kind of just something clicked.
It was like, well, you're sort of alone this whole time.
Maybe if Clatus psychologically needles you a little bit, you know, it would work.
And crazily, I mean, they know what they're doing.
They're government interrogation specialists.
They were right.
Yeah, it totally worked.
It's super duper worked.
No one ever forgot their box after we put in that dialogue, that's for sure.
And sort of as an afterthought, you know, we put these pink hearts, they're so pretty,
on the cube just to kind of cue back to the dialogue that there's something special about
this box and you should take it with you and take care of it.
Yeah, that worked.
And honestly, this was a really great thing for us just because it had a dual function
as far as the ending of this map went.
And the first thing is, well, at the time that we were finishing up this map, we were
also working on our ending boss battle.
And we had settled at the time on just disintegrating these little parts of Clatus.
And we had an incinerator in the map and we didn't train our players.
So obviously, they had no idea what they were doing.
And you know, they'd have to press the switch to open up the incinerator and they just,
they completely ignored it.
And then they would wander around the room and then get really angry at us.
So we obviously had to train this somewhere and we had a great idea of where to put the
training.
Yeah, originally, up until almost the last minute at the end of the companion cube level,
you just had to just leave the companion cube.
You had to abandon it because you couldn't bring it with you into the elevator.
And Clatus made some reference to it being euthanized.
And it was sort of sad, but it wasn't really a good ending to the level.
So putting the incinerator there and having you be forced to euthanize it was just an
awesome way to end it.
And in addition to that, it was also a great place to train the player because there was
no stress.
There was no pressure for...
Well, the stress of killing it.
Well, yeah, it was a little stressful.
But more like, you know, there was nothing shooting at you or, you know, they didn't
have a clock ticking down.
Like, oh my God, I've got to do this in 10 seconds.
And we did that because, well, players do not learn anything when they're completely
stressed out.
Like, they just won't absorb anything.
So putting the training there was pretty good.
Also it provided a really great point to our narrative as well because, you know, you
get to incinerate Clatus the same way, you know, she made you incinerate your best friend.
Yeah, the whole companion cube saga was just a really great example of how the gameplay
kind of influenced the story, which then turned around and influenced the gameplay.
Okay, so having said all that about how it's gameplay, gameplay, gameplay, no narrative,
we did reach a point where we discovered that gameplay wasn't really working by itself.
And this was the original ending of Portal.
Honestly, the biggest obstacle to us when making Portal was our ending boss battle.
You know, we look at other games, okay, we know what a boss battle will look like in
a first person shooter or an RPG, but what in the world is a boss battle going to look
like in a weird environmental puzzle game?
Yeah, the first thing you'd think, or at least the first thing we thought, was that the boss
monster for a puzzle game should be a deviously complex puzzle.
And that sort of innocuous sounding conclusion really just gave us a lot of headaches and
pain.
So we're going to show you a few examples of some things that we tried as boss battles
and eventually abandoned for one reason or another.
So the first one that we tried was James Bond lasers.
So literally, they were big giant lasers that would follow the player around trying to zap
them, and obviously we cut this.
Here's, I know, aren't they pretty?
Isn't that nice?
These are training maps that we had for the James Bond style lasers, where essentially
you'd have to place your portal in front of the laser and then place one on a wall
and then redirect the laser at that weird orange thing sitting in that glass wall and
break through and be able to get to the other side, where you would meet GLaDOS.
That's GLaDOS there in her giant shimmery cube phase.
Don't you love temp art?
It's great stuff.
And once again, you'd have to redirect those lasers at those, which you find out are orange
plugs supplying GLaDOS with power.
And you know, the end.
But yeah, it was not good.
The lasers were extremely boring to dodge and kind of difficult to tune, because we
would make them follow the player kind of fast and then it would be unfair, and if we
slowed them down, then they're boring.
They were also really difficult to aim, believe it or not, through a portal.
It was kind of a pain.
And it was also hard to tell if you were hit by the lasers too, so we abandoned this idea
and instead chose to use a rocket launcher.
So the second attempt that we had was Portal Combat.
Sorry, I had fun with Photoshop one day.
So, you know, we had a lot of players test our game that were hardcore first-person shooter
players.
We were like, you need more action, and you need to jump around and be a crazy portal
ninja, and so we were like, yeah, okay, sure, we'll give it a shot.
And, you know, it didn't really work out very well.
Here's a picture of a level that we actually shipped in the game.
And this is what it originally looked like.
So, this was supposed to be the first time that you would meet GLaDOS, and you can see
that there's a rocket launcher there.
We had put it in at that point.
And you would have to redirect the rockets and use your portals to shoot GLaDOS in the
face.
And that's GLaDOS, yeah, she's a bunch of roller minds.
So, you know, this was, you know, it was okay.
But we then made it a little bit more complex.
So she would rise to the top of this room, and then all of these little pillboxes would
pop open with turrets in them.
And the rocket launcher was still on, and you would have to try and, you know, redirect
the laser and hit her again.
And all the meanwhile, the turrets are firing at you, the rocket launcher is firing at you,
and it's just not fun.
So, yeah, the high-intensity gameplay sucked.
In fact, it sucked so bad that I'm talking when you're supposed to be reading.
Is that true?
No, no, it's all right.
Anyway, I'll finish it.
It sucked.
It was bad.
It sucked so much, I'm not going to let Kim talk about it.
It sucked because I hated it so much.
No one paid attention to GLaDOS, any of her dialogue, because there was just way too much
stuff going on.
And we had playtesters who'd come in who were sort of hardcore Counter-Strike or shooter
fans, and they were able to bring a little bit of enjoyment out of it.
But the vast majority of our playtesters, who had sort of gotten used to the slower
paced, cerebral nature of Portal, were just frustrated and confused and dissatisfied,
which was absolutely not the way we kind of wanted to send them out the door.
So, the final attempt was to have a chase sequence.
And that's GLaDOS there as the kitten.
Isn't she cute?
So, here's kind of what that looked like.
This is actually a continuation of the previous section, where GLaDOS would rise up to the
top of the ceiling.
Well, after you hit her with the second rocket, she'd rise up even more and would zoom down
this hallway.
And you would actually have to follow her by flinging a couple times and getting up
into this hallway.
And honestly, the pacing was just horrible, because players wouldn't necessarily see where
she would go, and so they didn't know where they were going.
So, they would wander around for a while, and they'd eventually realize, oh, I don't
think I've been there before, and kind of get up there.
But if it's a chase sequence, it's supposed to be action-packed.
You're supposed to be going, going, going.
And instead, players are just wandering around confused.
And then, once you actually got up into this hallway, we wanted to make it seem like, oh,
GLaDOS had sprung some sort of trap to kill you.
So, we had all these pistons kind of break out of the walls and try and crush you or
block you from getting further.
And we also had these turrets and stuff pop down from the ceiling.
And if you actually played the game, you can see that these hallways are kind of similar
to what we shipped.
And we took a lot of stuff out.
Because...
Yeah.
This, I'm not even going to bother reading down.
This failed in every way that's possible for a level like that to fail.
It had bad pacing.
Players didn't really know what was going on with GLaDOS making the pistons come out
at you.
And every solution we came up with to try and fix those were either too expensive for
us to do or just made the gameplay even worse.
So, a complex boss battle?
Yeah, it didn't work.
And the thing that we actually learned from all this was that the more complex that we
made our puzzles, the slower the pacing actually got.
Because players would have to stop and think about what they were going to do next.
And, you know, if you watch an action movie and you get to the climactic sequence, there's
something happening all the time.
And in our game, when we wanted it to be climactic, because we made everything more complex, it
did the opposite thing than what we expected.
So, it's funny to us now, but we were desperately screwed at this point.
Because Episode 2 was winding up and TF, after 10 years, was going to beat us out.
And, you know, the Episode 2 guys are running around, they're like, our final battle is
going to be 100 Striders and you're going to be driving a car and running into little
mini Striders.
What are you guys doing?
It's a secret.
So, but again, once again, our old friend playtesting helped us.
There was a point, and I don't know why we didn't realize it earlier on, but there was
one piece of feedback that we were getting, that there was a point in the game that playtesters
felt, excuse me, was both climactic and satisfying.
And it's the fire pit.
It happened about two-thirds of the way through the game.
The testing, proper, the regular testing, hold on, I'm going to take a drink of water,
is almost over and GLaDOS is kind of talking you out, you're riding this platform into
a fire pit, and you eventually, you escape out of here.
But playtesters were just consistently telling us, not only was this dramatic and exciting,
they kept telling us that it was actually like, it was a really tough puzzle that I
felt super satisfied to solve, which absolutely made no sense to us.
Because...
That's a good picture.
Yeah, I know, it's a good picture.
Portal 2 is just going to be this picture over and over again.
When it comes right down to it, at that point in the game, that's about the easiest puzzle
in Portal.
You place a portal on the wall next to the fire pit, and then you place one in a safe
area, and you just hop through it.
That's it.
So, we then had to sit down and reflect, like, what in the world made this so climactic?
And one of the things that we learned was that, well, it had time pressure.
You know, there was only a limited amount of time while you were on that platform before
you were going to get burned alive to place your portals and escape.
And, you know, as I think I've said before, time pressure makes people think something
that is a lot more complicated than it actually is.
Another thing was it had a really high visual impact.
I mean, you can't really go wrong with a platform heading straight into a giant pit of fire
for visual impact.
But, you know, it's something that our players had never seen before in the game, and so
it was, you know, something new.
There's also a dramatic high point, because for the first time, GLaDOS is pretty openly
trying to kill you, and also for the first time, you're able to assert a little bit of
control over your environment and escape from her.
And, like Kim was saying, all of those three things combined made it so that an easy puzzle
was sort of feeling like a much more complicated puzzle, which allowed us, led us to the realization
that we'd been holding onto this idea that we needed a complex puzzle at the end, and
it simply just wasn't true.
So here's what we actually shipped in the game as boss battle.
You can see GLaDOS there with her little personality spheres, and then next to her was a hatch
where a rocket launcher would pop up, and you'd have to reorient the rockets and hit
GLaDOS, take one of those spheres, and then put it in the incinerator by, you know, getting
to the activation switch with your portals, and then getting back to the incinerator and
tossing it in.
The end.
Done.
So, taking the four lessons we learned, this is how we applied them to the final GLaDOS
battle.
First of all was time pressure.
We were ourselves under some time pressure, so instead of getting fancy, we actually just
had a timer counting down to something that would kill you.
And we decided that thing that would kill you would be some neurotoxin, because it was
also really cheap just to make a green particle system.
You laugh, but it's seriously true.
Yeah, that's 100% true.
So, you know, visual impact.
Well, on one side of the screen, you know, on the far side over there, you can see a
piece of concept art that an artist at Valve, Jason Braschel, did for us.
Thanks, Jason.
And on the other side there, you can see what we actually shipped.
So everything in this room, visually, is pointing at GLaDOS.
You know, got the geometry of the stairs leading up to her, got all the lights pointing at
her.
You know, after all this time of hearing GLaDOS heckle you and harass you, you know, we wanted
to make this room have some serious impact.
And, you know, I think it did its job pretty well.
And, you know, it's not like any other room in the game, and so I think it really gave
players a sense of satisfaction.
And then in terms of a high dramatic moment, putting some time pressure to the puzzle made
it so that I only had to write like six minutes of decent dialogue, which is in stark contrast
to all our previous attempts, which required me to write infinity minutes of excellent
dialogue.
Which makes Eric crack.
That was a bad time for me, writing infinity minutes of dialogue.
And finally, the easy puzzle.
You know, when all is said and done, Portal is a puzzle game.
But all the things that we learned led us back towards, you know, we need to simplify
this puzzle.
So adding time pressure and then, you know, having it be a very dramatic room and have
a lot of really interesting points made by GLaDOS.
Scaling back the puzzle allowed players to really absorb this moment and have a good
time.
And, you know, honestly, at least for me, there's nothing more frustrating than getting
to the finale of a game and not being able to beat that stupid boss battle and see the
ending of the game, which in our case, we really wanted people to see, or rather hear.
So we wanted to leave players, you know, with a real sense of satisfaction.
You know, you scratch that.
We wanted players to feel genuinely happy and leave the game with a smile on their face.
So, yeah, we sat down and we kind of made a list of what makes people happy.
And then we kind of made a list of what we could put in a game and then put it into Excel
and pivot table.
And the catchy song kind of floated to the top.
And this is Jonathan Colton, who we got to write our catchy song.
Who is wearing his best hat, by the way.
And so, you know, when all is said and done, a lot of this actually came out of our constraints.
You know, we had a small team.
We had a limited amount of time.
And, you know, frankly, we just couldn't make a giant FMV epic finale of Doom.
And, you know, the cost to happiness ratio of putting a song over some scrolling text
was really high.
So, the moral of the whole thing for us was just try to fully embrace your constraints
as fuel for creativity.
Honestly, without the constraints that we had, I truly believe Portal would not be as
good a game as it turned out to be.
And in addition to that, you know, have faith in yourself.
Have faith in your writing.
And in the skills of your team, because, you know, they're your best resources.
And, once again, playtest, playtest, playtest.
And when you're done with that, playtest some more.
Because, honestly, you will get the most valuable information for your game out of watching
your playtest.
And it'll make for a better player experience in the end.
So...
Thank you.
So we deliberately kind of kept our talk short because, you know, we kind of assumed people
had questions because we keep getting asked questions.
And so, you know, we wanted to just kind of make our point and then leave the floor open
to you guys to, you know, ask us whatever you want.
So, questions?
You...
Is there a microphone?
I'm pointing at that guy.
Oh, okay.
Okay, fine.
Can you hear me okay?
Yeah.
Okay, so my question is, you touched earlier on not using emails or voice recording for,
like, story segments in your environment.
And, you know, most of my experience, however, a lot of successful games use this a lot.
Most notably Resident Evil and most recently BioShock.
And they're all bad games.
Next question.
Oh, yeah, I have no idea.
None of these were actually prescriptive.
You know, go for it if you want.
It was just a personal choice we made.
I think it can work.
I just personally, I don't like...
I don't...
I mean, for me, I don't like to read that much.
I don't like to read in-games.
I mean, I like to read books.
But when I'm in a game, I just want it to kind of happen and not have to read that much.
And Eric, you know, we were talking about this before, and Eric made a really good point,
which was, you know, how often do you use a voice recorder to leave secret messages
for your friends and family?
Well, I mean, yeah, that's the thing.
These futuristic games, there's always, like, oh, we're in the future, and everybody's leaving
messages on PDAs.
I can go buy a PDA for $8 at Best Buy now, and nobody's using it to deliver messages
to me ever.
So, yeah, we just...
So that's our own personal hang-up with those two things, but I think they're fine in games.
Guys standing with mics?
Oh, there's people with mics.
This isn't plugged in, so if I start to stand here anyway, it'd look like a good place to stand.
Yeah, it's a great place to stand.
Yeah.
I wanted to ask this question because I thought it was exactly the type of thing that I think
of Eric normally railing against.
Why does GLaDOS have an incinerator in her room, other than just...
It's actually kind of a funny story.
So the question was, why does GLaDOS have an incinerator sitting in her room?
And the answer is actually kind of fun.
Like, we were talking sort of like a back story, and they wanted to, like...
So they created this giant AI, and they weren't really sure at Aperture Science if she was
going to go out of control.
So they made this room so that way, you know, if she did completely lose her mind, they
could, you know, incinerate her and get rid of her.
Right.
There's a red phone in there that is supposed to be...
There was a guy who...
That was his job, to sit there and call somebody if it looked like the AI was going rogue,
and then they'd come and throw it in the thing, and it sadly didn't work.
Nope.
It was bad by Aperture Science.
They're sort of half geniuses, half morons.
Thanks.
So you mentioned playtesting as a really critical step, but also not outsourcing it to another group.
How do you go about selecting and acquiring a steady supply of new players throughout
your process?
How did you guys go about doing that?
So the question was, how did we go about getting new playtesters all the time to playtest our
game?
Do you know how easy it is to go walk out to the nearest GameStop and say, hey, we've
got this game, do you want to come play it?
I mean, you know, the answer is like, yeah, of course.
And also we had, you know, friends and family come in and playtest.
Gabe's kids actually playtested for us.
You were going to say something?
Oh, just in Valve, there's a lot of people working at Valve who are kind of heads down
on their own projects.
So we had a lot of people who could just come in, you know, from other parts of the company
as well.
And did you ever have people come back for, like, additional tests?
Or was it sort of a, you test once, and that's all the useful information?
So the question was, do we have people come back and playtest again?
Usually we would have people playtest once, but we had a few playtesters, mainly at Valve,
who seemed to really like Portal and were stubborn.
So, you know, they wouldn't really get frustrated easily.
So when we would have a puzzle that we wanted to try out that was really, really rough and
we just wanted to see if the concept was good, we would usually grab one of those guys and
have them sit down and chug through it.
Thank you.
Hi.
In the developer commentary, you said there will be more Portal games, and obviously,
you know, your first couple sides show, you know, you're having a lot of success.
And when that happens, you get a lot of resources, you will be a little tiny team.
So what kind of, are you, you know, afraid, or how will you overcome the challenge of
not having as many constraints?
And next.
You have to say the question.
Oh, so how will we make a next Portal if there is one?
How can we keep some of our design philosophies if we have a lot more resources?
And it's a good question.
I don't know.
I'm scared to tell you the truth.
I don't know how it's going to work.
I'm trying to just bask in the moment now about people bugging me about the next one.
Just let me enjoy it for one minute.
No, but seriously, I don't know.
Yeah, I don't know.
A little bit of a personal flashback for me.
But as I remember, toward the end of Narbacular Drop, there is a puzzle where you're required
to aim through one of the doorways and put, you know, a Portal on the wall on the other side.
In essence, to shoot through, which was very elegant as a way of pushing the mechanics of the game
to its limit, I suppose.
And I noticed, of course, that in Portal, you chose for one reason or another not to allow
the player to fire the Portal gun through one portal.
And I can think of a couple of reasons why you might have done that, but I was just wondering
if it was, I guess, for technical purposes or as part of a larger idea of some sort.
So the question was, did we...
So in Narbacular Drop, we gave players the ability of being able to shoot one portal
through another portal.
And we decided to, you know, not do that for Portal because...
Not because it was, you know, technically impossible, technology-wise, you know, impossible.
But more for a design purpose.
Like, you know, we wanted players to learn something in particular in a certain level.
And so giving the players suddenly the ability to bypass all the training that we had tried so hard
to construct and, you know, just seemed like shooting ourselves in the foot, essentially.
Thank you.
In the first trailer for Portal, the portals seemed to have sort of an almost liquid quality to them.
Now they're more like holes in the wall.
Also, they were a blue and a red portal.
And now it's a blue and an orange one.
What triggered this change?
So the question was, why did we change the look and color of our portals?
Yeah.
Well, honestly, we went through just a bunch of just iterations.
And as far as blue and orange goes, you know, we liked orange better than red.
I mean, it really just boils down to that.
Like, we liked the color choice better in the end.
And, you know, we left it sort of up to our artists.
Like, you know, what do you want the portals to look like?
And the liquid quality?
It was kind of like they were rippling at the edges.
Yeah, so I think what you're referring to as far as the liquid quality of how the portals were looking was
that was an opening shader for it.
And we just decided to change it.
Like, honestly, it just sort of, we decided one day.
I just wanted to leave a comment.
I just wanted to thank you guys for the end of the turret level.
The most satisfying thing that I felt in that game was picking up that last turret
and walking into the elevator through the field and watching it just turn into a ball of ash.
Thank you guys for that.
Yeah, no problem.
We also really like the way they screen, too.
So I have a question.
I'm a student, and you guys started out as an indie developer.
So I'm just wondering if you have any suggestions for students and whatnot
who are hoping to get into the game industry and break in like you guys did.
So the question is, do we have any advice for student developers on how to break into the industry?
Make games. Make as many as you can.
And fail, because honestly, failing, you'll learn a lot of stuff.
I can't tell you how many times we failed on our game designs working at DigiPen.
Like, yeah, one of them worked out, but we had three others that were not the best games ever.
And honestly, practice makes perfect, right?
So the more things that you have on your resume and in your portfolio
to show to game developers that, look, I did all these projects.
I worked on them from start to finish.
It obviously shows that I have commitment to the project, right?
So make games.
Whether it be a mod or a student project,
just make as many as you possibly can and have fun with them.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So when I spoke to people that also played Portal about the fire pit puzzle,
one of the things that we talked about a lot was the fact that
we felt like we had broken the game somehow by escaping this final ending.
And that there was this moment of sort of shock and confusion about what to do next
when you suddenly had gotten past what you imagined was the game's end.
And that was a very powerful moment in the way that it defied conventional game narrative.
So I'm wondering if that defying of conventional game narrative
was something that was intentional in the design of the level
or whether that was just something that was an accidental occurrence from what you set up.
Honestly, that was one of the very first things...
Repeat the question.
Oh, sorry. Well, I forgot the question.
I was just going to talk about it.
No, was it intentional the sort of way that you feel maybe like you've broken the game after the fire pit?
And I guess there was some unintentionality there
because that's one thing that virtually never changed.
The beats as far as you start in the relaxation vault at some point during the game,
although I think maybe it was earlier in the game at one point,
you escape the fire pit and then you would eventually meet GLaDOS.
It was in there before anything.
I mean, the test levels with no dialogue basically had that structure
just because we had this intuitive feeling that it would work
and it just ended up working better than we thought.
So we can take some credit for it, but not total credit.
It just worked really well.
Thank you.
Thanks.
So when I first heard about Portal, I went and played Nervecular, dropped really thoroughly.
And when I played Portal, I noticed there were a lot of similarities.
The one big difference was that Portal had all this humor, a profound amount of humor in it.
And I was wondering what the decision was and how you decided to throw in the comedy.
So the question is, why did we decide to throw in comedy for Portal?
Nervecular dropped really wasn't that funny.
And there's something inherently funny about Portals.
Especially, you put both of them on the floor and you drop a box in
and you see it popping out back and forth.
There's something kind of funny and visceral about it.
And well, honestly, Eric's really damn funny.
Yeah, well, I mean, given a choice, that was kind of in my comfort zone.
Like, if my task at Valve was to write stuff for Portal,
if nobody was going to object, I would just make it funny.
I mean, that would be something I was more likely to succeed at.
Because you like despairing.
Yeah.
Hi, I have no problems harvesting Adam from Little Sisters.
I love kicking innocent bystanders through bloody pulp and lots of games.
But why, why, why, why did you have me kill off the companion cube?
So, why did we kill off the companion cube?
Well, I think we explained that in the speech, didn't we?
You can thank the United States Secret Service.
Actually, I don't think it was the Secret Service.
Secreter than the Secret Service.
I have two questions and the second one's quick.
The first one is, it sounds like there's a lot of trial and error
and rework that went into Portal.
Did you have to do anything to smooth that over with management?
Set their expectations or anything like that?
So, the question is, there's a lot of trial and error with the game, obviously.
And did we have to, you know, convince our management that that was perhaps a good idea?
And honestly, the way management works at Valve is a lot different than it does at other game companies.
We don't really have producers there.
You know, we have team leads that basically, you know,
maybe do like the administrivious stuff every once in a while and do some PR.
But, you know, honestly, the people working on the game get to make the decisions about the game
and have direct impact on what they're working on.
And, you know, we found that it just makes for a much more, you know,
satisfied group of people making games.
Fantastic.
Also, like the playtesting, the commitment to playtesting wasn't our insight.
That's the Valve philosophy.
I mean, that's how they make games.
If we hadn't done that, then we would have been in deep trouble.
Okay, fantastic.
Second question, is GLaDOS still alive and when will we see her again?
Who's still alive?
So, the question is, is GLaDOS still alive and when will we see her again?
Well, did you not listen to the last song?
The song is called Still Alive.
That's kind of a failure of writing if you don't know if she's still alive.
100% still alive. Thank you.
And as far as when you'll see her again, who knows?
Alright, hi.
I had a question about your development background
and how you guys scored yourself an awesome seat by working with Valve.
So, were you still making a question?
Well, no, go ahead.
How did you score yourself a position to work with Valve?
So, the question was, how did we end up hooking up with Valve to make Portal?
So, as far as the team goes, with the exception of Eric,
we were all students at DigiPen Institute of Technology
and we created a game called Nervacular Drop,
which was our student project for our senior year.
And it was the predecessor to Portal.
You had two portals on the wall and it was an environmental puzzle game.
And every year DigiPen has an expo for graduating seniors.
And Valve came by, took a look at our project,
and thought it was interesting enough to drag us over to Valve
and have us present the game to Gabe Newell.
And after about 15 minutes through our presentation,
Gabe told us to be quiet and then asked us
what we were planning on doing after we graduated.
And we were like, well, hopefully paying our loans, getting a job, eating food.
And he offered us a job on the spot, essentially,
to come in and create Portal using a source engine.
And, you know, that's how we ended up there.
And Eric's got a different story.
Yeah, I'd been just doing a lot of writing,
and then I went and I worked at Double Fine for a couple of years.
And then I left Double Fine and I was just back to freelance writing.
For me, it was just, I got a mail one day from Gabe Newell
and said, do you want to come work at Valve?
I have another quick question.
Yeah, go ahead.
Why didn't you guys submit this to IGF?
It seems like a perfect candidate.
Was it the reason because you guys got picked up by Valve?
So, the question was, why didn't we submit the game to IGF?
So, Narbacular Drop actually was in the IGF Student Showcase,
I think, three years ago.
DigiPen submits the games that they find to be
interesting to Student Showcase and the IGF.
We didn't make the, you know, indie professional,
I guess, section, but we made it to the Student Showcase.
Thank you.
Hi, how did the element of cake come into fruition?
So, the question is, how did the element of cake come to fruition?
It kind of started off as like an inside joke, sort of.
I mean, really, it just was one of those things.
Originally, when we sat down, you guys were showing me the game,
there was something about cake in there, and it just seemed
like it's a comedy tool, obsess over one thing
that maybe you wouldn't expect to obsess over.
And we just, it really didn't have any deeper meaning than that.
Yeah, we were just kind of having fun.
Fun work, work fun.
Yes, yes, yes. We were working very hard.
And having fun.
Yeah, no, no, it was hard work.
Geez.
Conference is turning ugly.
Hey, guys, two quick questions.
First, was there any reasoning behind making, like,
all the characters and the references and GLaDOS quotes and such female?
So, the question is, why did we decide to make our characters female,
GLaDOS and, you know, the main character?
So, as far as the main character goes,
Gabe actually made a suggestion one day.
We were, at the time, looking to find what we wanted, you know,
to be the main character, protagonist of Portal.
And you can see, like, some of our, you know, earlier shots of the game,
there's, like, a balding dude as the main character.
And that was just hemp art.
Like, it was something that we, you know, used a citizen model
from Half-Life 2 and just kind of fixed him up a little bit
and put him in just for our testing purposes.
And then, Gabe came up to us while we were looking to figure out
what we wanted our main character to be and said,
well, why don't you make it a girl?
And we're like, all right, sure.
I mean, it really didn't stretch beyond that.
We sort of, well, what if?
Okay, why not?
It's like post-feminist.
It didn't even occur to us not to make it a girl.
It was no big deal.
And as far as GLaDOS, well, there was the awesome GLaDOS pun,
which kind of made it seem like we had to, it had to be female.
But really, we knew an actress.
It's hard because we knew this person was going to have to carry the game.
So, we needed an actress.
Or actor.
Or actor, actor or actress, who A, was good,
and B, wouldn't be offended when, you know, the first third
of our recording sessions were just us playing her text-to-speech
and saying, say this exactly like that back to us.
Because actors hate that sort of thing.
But she was super nice about it.
And so, that kind of informed that.
Okay.
And the other one is just to officially shut my friend up.
Is Chell a cyborg?
No.
Another failure of writing.
Chell is not a cyborg.
There's no, she's not a cyborg.
Those ridiculous shoes.
Cyber shoes?
Yeah, her future shoes.
Hey, this might have already been addressed at some point,
but I got in late, so I have to ask anyways.
Obviously, Portal was a very short game
that met a lot of very popular demand.
And it was a very popular success.
Do you think this might start making a movement
back towards the idea of shorter games being on the market?
I mean, right now, the huge pressure is, you know,
everybody wants 20 plus, 30 plus, 40 plus hour games
because everyone wants to get as much out of the game
as they possibly can for, you know, what they're paying out of their wallet.
Yeah, I mean, I, oh, sorry.
Do you think Portal would influence more developers
to make shorter games because of the,
well, according to the questioner,
people want longer and longer games.
Although I'm not 100% sure about that.
You know, everybody at Valve,
all the people I know who play games who are adults now,
the common complaint is they never finish a game.
You know, nobody ever finishes a game that I know who isn't 14.
They just, they don't have time.
And also, they have 40 hours a week to play World of Warcraft, too.
Cuts in their gaming time.
But, so, you know, there are some practical constraints
on how long we're going to make it.
But, you know, if we could have done anything,
I really wanted to make a game that
everybody who played it would be able to finish.
You know, you'd be able to,
it's weird to be playing these games
or trying to tell a story in a game where
almost everybody, it just sort of peters out.
You know, you just stop playing at some point
and never finish it.
Thank you very much.
Alright. Okay.
Hello. Two-part question.
The first part is,
you mentioned that a lot of dialogue
had been cut from the game.
I was wondering if any of it had gotten recorded
and or put through the process
of being somewhat final for GLaDOS.
And, if so,
is there any chance you could release it
on one of your websites?
Because as a member of the portal mapping community,
we would give our eye teeth to have extra GLaDOS dialogue.
So, I think,
so, the question was
how much of final dialogue got cut
and could we release it?
So, a lot,
it wasn't a lot of final dialogue.
Virtually everything went through the text-to-speech
as temp audio.
And a lot of it got cut at that point.
And some of the stuff that got cut,
you know, a lot of it I'm just not super proud of.
So, I wouldn't want to give it to anybody.
And some of it is good.
And if it is good,
I'll put it somewhere else.
Fair enough.
Not to be mean.
Yeah, not to be mean,
but probably the chances are somewhat slim.
I had to try.
Thank you.
My question is,
were there any considerations for making
a multiplayer or cooperative experience?
So, the question was,
were there any considerations for making
Portal a co-op or a multiplayer game?
Yeah, we thought about it.
Actually, the,
I'm not sure if it's possible or not,
but we played around for a little while
actually having multiple sets of portals.
And it is technically possible.
We just, you know,
didn't really have the time to think through
what would the gameplay be that was fun.
You know, sort of the immediate conclusion
that we actually kind of tried a little bit
was, oh my gosh, Portal's in Deathmatch
and it's less fun than you think it is.
Honestly.
It's actually kind of frustrating.
So.
Hi.
I had a lot of really good advice
about keeping it wet,
keeping the project wet,
not getting too attached to ideas
and being willing to cut things
or make changes later.
I'm just wondering how,
what your experience was for balancing that
with the need to get a project done
and the kind of tendency of a project
to kind of gain momentum
the further it goes along
and be harder to make changes later than earlier.
So, the question was,
how do we temper
a game,
you know, the longer you work on it
the harder it is to, you know,
sort of cut things and
is that kind of what you were saying?
Yeah, okay.
You said it better than I do.
And play testing.
You will know right away
if your idea is good or bad.
You know, if you watch your players
and they are just totally frustrated
out of your mind
and you can't really, you know,
necessarily pinpoint ways to fix it,
because,
so, you know, one of the things that we do
making our levels at least
is we try and get them up and running
once we come up with an idea,
okay, we want, you know,
such and such objectives
as we try and get it up and running
within like two to five days,
like really, really fast.
And then we start running play tests through it.
And if we play test it like maybe,
you know, three or four times
and we find that it's just really not working out,
then it's going to the cutting floor
and we're going to have to cut it.
So, we never really got to a point where,
you know, it was really, really difficult
to cut something because,
you know, we were always play testing
and getting reinforcement
for whether or not our ideas were good or bad
directly from, you know,
people we consider our customers.
Thank you.
Yep.
If your development team were,
or your development process
were a style of painting,
what would it be?
Wow.
So, if our development process
were a style of painting,
what would it be?
Uh,
uh,
maybe,
maybe a,
gosh, I don't know.
Yeah, that's a good,
cubist painting.
Uh, you know,
you have a good one?
Yeah, I'm out of material.
Sorry.
So, um, Chell obviously has
a very good set of DNA
and you mentioned that it was
Gabe's idea to make her female
and Gordon Freeman has good DNA.
Is there any?
So, the question is,
are Chell and Gordon going to hook up?
Uh, essentially.
Uh, I don't know.
I mean, you guys, you know,
have access to Gary's mod, right?
You can do what you want.
Yeah, I was wondering,
um,
you kept on talking about
how you cut off a lot of things
in the narrative and, like,
cut off a lot of exposition
and stuff like that
and just really streamlined the process
and I was just wondering,
do you think that it's possible,
I mean, do you think
there's a way to make exposition
and narrative, like, interesting
and fun for the play testers?
Do you see where we're going to get at?
Oh, so the question is,
do I think there's a way to,
I think you're saying,
is there a way to include a lot more exposition
and still make it entertaining?
I mean, for me personally,
I'm sure there's somebody
who's a genius who could do it,
but I personally don't,
I mean, I like it when there is less.
Uh, you know,
my own personal taste is less.
Uh, so for me, probably,
probably not.
I try and do as little as possible.
So you believe that games aren't good at telling,
like, long expository stories, then?
Uh, yeah, I guess I'm not good at it,
but I'm also not good at sitting through it.
I mean, I just don't like it that much in games.
When I play a game,
I like it to be as concise as possible
because, honestly,
I'm a game writer,
but I'm not even 100% convinced
that games are the best medium
for, like, telling epic, long stories.
I kind of think of what I do
as more of, like,
guiding a film score.
You know, movies aren't about the music,
but the music is definitely an important part
that enhances the experience of watching the movie.
So the writing is something
that enhances the experience of why you're there,
which is playing the game.
And honestly, for me,
there's something to be said
for leaving things to people's imagination.
You don't have to have someone
sitting there next to you dictating to you
exactly what's going on at all times.
Like, you know, people are smart.
Give them credit.
But for me, personally,
it's kind of fun just sort of imagining up,
you know, what I think some of the storyline is.
Thank you.
Playing through portals,
one of the biggest surprises that I had
was finding references to Black Mesa
inside of it,
and then references to Aperture
and the Borealis inside the Half-Life 2 Episode 2.
Around what point in development
did you make the decision
to drop portals into the Half-Life universe?
So the question is,
when did we decide
to, you know, sort of cross-reference
between the two games of Episode 2 and Portal?
Kind of like, you know,
maybe in the middle of development or so?
Well, middle of development for you,
but I think when I came on,
that was in the earlier meetings.
That was just one of the constraints
on the game,
initially because I think they weren't sure
exactly where they were going to position it,
and also because we were still using
a lot of Half-Life art.
So it sort of made sense to tie them together
as Portal kind of got its own identity
and we worried less and less about it.
Like, you know, we're not going to
have to have the G-Man appear or something.
We can kind of make it a little bit more subtle
and not have to dwell on it too much.
Thanks.
Two questions.
I have a friend who says
that the best games teach us something.
What do we have to learn from Portal?
So the question is,
what do we have to learn from Portal
because the best games teach people something?
You want to take this one?
That's a tough one.
If anybody has an idea,
just shout it out.
Don't trust anyone with something.
Don't trust anyone.
The cake is a lie.
There's your cake.
No, I mean, we definitely wanted to
explore the idea of manipulating space
and thinking about, you know,
a 3D space in a different way.
And so, you know, throughout Portal,
we're kind of teaching you to look at
a situation in a way that you haven't before.
So I don't know if that kind of answers
your question.
It'll do.
Also, I noticed that the companion cube
was kind of silent.
Does it have any dialogue in the sequel?
So the question is,
will the companion cube have dialogue
in the sequel to Portal?
I don't know about this sequel
that you're talking about.
This might be a little bit proprietary,
but I'm curious.
How did you guys and Orval
figure out, or when did you figure out,
or was it an evolutionary process,
when you were going to sell the game?
So the question is,
when did we figure out
how we were going to market and sell Portal?
So when we initially started Portal,
it was supposed to be
just a seriously short game,
maybe like, I don't know,
15 minutes, just like a quick tech demo.
And then the further we got on the game,
our constraints would change.
And I guess about
a year or so after we started,
we were like,
we're going to sell it.
And I guess about
the middle of Portal's development,
we had started talking about
doing the Orange Box,
and it just sort of
seemed like a really
reasonable conclusion that
it should be packaged with
other games that
have a lot of clout
and are awesome games.
And from our standpoint,
that's great.
We were seriously honored
to do an episode two
because we think they're
truly awesome games.
You said that you used
the playtesting as kind of
a method by which you tested
whether or not the players
got the storyline.
And I wondered,
as the game length grew,
how, when you compartmentalized
the testing, because grabbing
people for 8-hour or 10-hour
play sessions isn't always
possible, did you get them
through?
Oh, sorry.
How did we get people
to experience the entire story
if they didn't playtest
the whole game?
Luckily, because Portal
was a pretty short game
throughout most of its value,
at no point was it so long
that it would take people
8 hours to get through it.
Please don't hit me in the face.
Sorry.
What was I going to say?
So, if somebody didn't finish
the game, we didn't take it
through, but most of them,
we sat and watched them
for the entire time
and they made it through.
I know that this question
has kind of been beaten
to death a bit, but it
was about storyline.
You're saying less is more.
Would you say that that
policy applies to other
genres besides just Portal,
or is it just mostly for
that type of niche?
I don't know.
I don't have a surefire
solution for every genre.
In terms of my enjoyment
of a game, less is more.
But again, if you're
making a giant RPG,
you probably need to say
who begat whom
and where the hammer came from.
So, Portal and Half-Life 2
have a very different tone
in terms of the writing
and the sort of themes,
the thematic elements.
If you ever do try and tie
the universes together
and do something with
the cross-referencing you've done,
do you have any ideas
for how you might resolve that?
Well, so how do we resolve
the differences in tone
between Half-Life universe
and the sort of Aperture universe?
And actually, it was
something I thought about
and I honestly don't think
you're seeing GLaDOS, right?
You're seeing things,
even though you're playing a character,
you're actually kind of
experiencing the world
through GLaDOS's eyes.
And so if Chell is out
in the Half-Life universe,
no action that you took
as a player is really
in direct contradiction
to anything that would
happen in the Half-Life universe.
Inside the sort of
Aperture science funhouse,
it's a little bit different
in terms of the
art style-wise.
So I'm not super-duper
worried about it.
Is that Paul?
Yeah, it is.
Is there any chance
of an art book?
Say that again, please?
Is there any chance
of an art book?
I don't know,
I haven't seen the
GLaDOS battle,
which there's some
awesome artwork.
There's actually a print
I think that you can buy of it.
Or look at it on the website.
But a lot of the other stuff,
compared to TF or Half-Life,
there isn't a lot of
really awesome concept art.
I mean, we've got a lot
of thumbnails and stuff,
but there aren't a whole lot
of really great pictures
that are ratcheted
maybe six or so.
But essentially,
we've just got a lot
of thumbnails of the
turrets and the gun
and a bunch of other stuff.
Also, why are the portals
ovoid?
So the question is,
why are the portals ovals?
Well, ovals look better
than rectangles.
We wanted something
to kind of fit the
where you can pass
through the portal to be.
So we kind of just
filled an oval
through the rectangle
where the portal
technically is.
The game alludes to
a lot of backstory
that isn't really
fully explained,
like the fact that
you're a test subject
for no explained reason.
How much of that backstory
is actually written
in the game?
So the question is,
how much backstory
is there that isn't
in the game?
And there's a fair amount.
There's a lot.
There's a lot of,
I don't know,
there's probably
a 15-page document
about Aperture Science.
There's actually a little
bit of it is on
the Aperture Science
website kind of hidden
in there somewhere.
And I'd written up
a bunch of stuff
in the beginning
just to kind of help me.
And I sent it to Jonathan
too that kind of
helped him get into
the sort of mindset
of the whole thing.
But yeah,
there is a bunch.
Hi.
I think
I speak for a lot
of people on this
that Portal
really was a huge
triumph because
it was so creative
and it won
so many awards
and it's got so much
acclaim
and it's so different.
I was wondering
if you could talk a little
bit on how you think
that's affecting
the community of games
as a whole.
So the question,
so it's like how
Portal impacts
the community of games
as a whole?
Yeah,
and the approach
to making games
as a creative medium.
I don't really know.
Yeah, I mean it's
kind of too early
to tell.
I hope it,
I mean,
because since we made Portal
we made a game
that we sort of like.
So if I make a game
that I think is
really cool,
I would probably,
I will probably
like them.
So that's good.
But I mean,
you just look at it
this year,
it seems like
the independent games
are
Getting really
awesome.
Awesome, yeah.
They're higher
production quality
and also higher
profile.
So maybe it'll mean
people take risks
on, you know,
more oddball games.
Good evening.
Hello.
So I had a question
about in terms of,
like,
the game industry
and that sort of media.
So my question to you
as writers and developers
of this game is
what are your influences?
What did you look,
like,
what did you think of
as inspiration
for Portal
or inspiration
to get into the game industry?
And, you know,
how does that influence
how you attack this game,
this project?
So the question was,
do we have any influences
that kind of inspired us
to make Portal
or get into the gaming industry?
So,
I think that's
a really good question.
So,
for me personally,
like every other person
on the planet,
you know,
Miyamoto is definitely
an inspiration.
You know,
I grew up with
Nintendo games
and I was kind of
raised on them.
So,
you know,
from an early age,
like,
you know,
I wanted to be
a game designer.
And, you know,
as far as
just kind of
interesting games
that actually
get published,
you know,
Katamari Damacy
was a really great one.
Do you have
any other
inspirations?
Do you have inspiration?
Oh, well,
direct inspiration
for Portal
was,
there's a book
by,
who's the Dune guy?
Frank Herbert.
Frank Herbert
called Destination Void
that was,
it's about people
that,
clones that go into space
and they're
tasked with
building an AI
and there's always,
like,
this fail-safe mechanism
because the AIs
always go crazy
and kill everyone
and they,
the crew doesn't really
know that that's
what happens
and then they blow up the ship
and it just fails
and fails and fails
because the AI goes rogue
and they blow up the ship.
There's,
there's like one mole
guy in there
who knows that he's supposed
to blow up the ship.
So that was an inspiration
for that.
The game industry,
I just,
I don't know.
Okay.
No Isaac Asimov
or anything like that?
Or,
no,
you know,
I'm honestly not,
when I was a kid
I read a lot of science fiction
but I don't read a lot
of science fiction now.
Interesting.
So,
I'm going to go with
Robert Sheckley
after Robert Sheckley
just because he writes
kind of funny science fiction.
Yeah.
When I was a kid
I loved his stuff.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Oh,
you know what,
just because we have to
catch a plane at some point
so these,
if we can just do these
three and then,
and there's nobody else
so that's easy.
Hey,
I have a question
specifically for Eric.
If the portal design process
was an animal,
what would it be?
That's Anna
who used to sit
right next to me
at Double Fine.
So,
that was her joke question
I'm not going to answer.
Okay,
so my question
pertains to the current slides.
Yeah,
we were actually waiting
for someone to actually
ask us what in the world
did we put on the slide.
What's the significance
of the two shots?
And if you were
each one of the characters
in each of the pictures,
which would you be?
Eric's the one crying.
I don't know,
it's just,
it's friendship
and,
and fire.
Over two pictures
we just had,
we couldn't quite fit
into the talk
in any meaningful way.
So,
and we thought
they were pretty funny.
I think one of those
is my,
the crying guy's
is my Steam community ID too.
And that's Rudy Ray Moore.
That's awesome.
Hi,
so I was actually
wondering about
the development team.
Because you're female
and that's kind of unusual,
how many girls
are on the team?
So,
the question was
how many girls
were on the Portal team?
There were two,
myself
and one of the artists,
Realm Lovejoy.
Right on.
Do you think that
that helps in the creativity process
in making like a unique game,
having that different perspective